<document id="004606b82f7609592a76c2108e56e0fb-3.1" name="Katyn_massacre" cat="14">
<text>
When, in September 1943, Goebbels was informed that the German army had to withdraw from the Katyn area, he entered a prediction in his diary. His entry for 29 September, 1943 reads: ''"Unfortunately we have had to give up Katyn. The Bolsheviks undoubtedly will soon 'find' that we shot 12,000 Polish officers. That episode is one that is going to cause us quite a little trouble in the future. The Soviets are undoubtedly going to make it their business to discover as many mass graves as possible and then blame it on us."''


Indeed, having retaken the Katyn area almost immediately after the Red Army had recaptured Smolensk, NKVD forces began a cover-up. A cemetery the Germans had permitted the Polish Red Cross to build was destroyed and other evidence removed. In January 1944, the Soviet Union sent the ''"Special Commission for Determination and Investigation of the Shooting of Polish Prisoners of War by German-Fascist Invaders in Katyn Forest,"'' (''Spetsial'naya Kommissiya po ustanovleniyu i rassledovaniyu obstoyatel'stv rasstrela nemetsko-fashistskimi zakhvatchikami v Katynskom lesu voyennoplennyh polskih ofitserov'') led (at least nominally) by Alexey Tolstoy to investigate the incidents again. The so-called "Burdenko Commission", headed by Nikolai Burdenko, the President of the Academy of Medical Sciences of the USSR, exhumed the bodies again and reached the conclusion that the shooting was done in 1941, when the Katyn area was under German occupation. No foreign personnel were allowed to join the ''Burdenko Commission'', whereas the Nazi German investigation had allowed wider access to both international press and organizations (like the Red Cross, with experts from Finland, Denmark, Slovakia etc) and even used Polish workers, like Józef Mackiewicz and Allied POWs., last accessed on 19 December, 2005, English translation of a Polish document The Soviet commission declared that all the shootings were done by German occupation forces in autumn 1941. The final report of the commission lists a number of items, from gold watches to letters and icons, allegedly found on the bodies. These items were said to have dates from November 1940 to June 1941, thus 'rebutting' the German claim of the Poles being shot by the Soviets. The report can be found in pro-Soviet publication ''Supplement to Russia at war weekly'' (1944); it is also printed in Dr.Joachim Hoffmann's book ''Stalin's Annihilation War 1941–1945'' (original: ''Stalins Vernichtungskrieg 1941–1945'').Full text of the original report as printed in "''Pravda''" on January 26, 1944 is available at the Russian Wikisource.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="accaddb6a24c29b189258e8b7b5a4fec" name="Katyn_partout" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/accaddb6a24c29b189258e8b7b5a4fec.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>