<document id="01393b6e451f650fdf67abdbc8247ced-1" name="Finnish_Civil_War" cat="29">
<text>
The main factor behind the Finnish Civil War was World War I. The conflict caused a collapse of the Russian Empire, mainly in the February Revolution and the October Revolution during 1917. This led to a formation of a large power vacuum and struggle for power. The Finnish Grand Duchy, "Finland", as a part of the Russian Empire, between 17 September 1809 and 6 December 1917, became a part of the struggle and the vacuum. The war between Germany and Russia had a major impact on the Finns since the year 1914. Both empires had political, economic, and military interests in the Finnish area. The military significance of the Grand Duchy of Finland for the Russians had been increasing since the half of the 19th century as the tension and competition between the major European powers constantly rose. The northwestern territory was a part of the  gateway and buffer zone (with Estonia) to and out of the Imperial capital St. Petersburg, both via Gulf of Finland towards the Kronstadt naval base, and via the Finnish land area, the Karelian Isthmus. The Grand Duchy had also become a vital source of raw materials, industrial products, and food and labour supply for the growing capital of Russia. Since the beginning of World War I the German Empire had seen Eastern Europe, mainly Russia, as a major source of vital products and raw materials for sustaining the capacity of the nation during the war, and after the final victory. A part of the German leaders were most concerned of the  two-front war, which Germany had engaged in, and a policy of breaking up the enemy from inside by supporting revolutionary groups, such as Bolseviks in Russia, financially was issued (in total 25 million German marks was spent to Russia). For the German army the Finnish area was a way for both controlling and/or penetrating to St. Petersburg, and reaching northeast, towards Kola Peninsula, an area rich of raw materials for mining industry., , , , ,    

During 1809-1898, a period called ''Pax Russica'', the Finno-Russian relations had been exceptionally peaceful and stable, compared to other parts of the Russian Empire. The crisis of the Crimean war of 1850's in Russia led to attemps to speed up the modernization of Russia, which caused over a 50 year-period of positive economical, industrial, cultural (especially concerning the Finnish language) and educational development in the Grand Duchy. This enhanced also Finnish nationalism and cultural unity, e.g. via birth of fennomania, bound the Finns to the domestic governmental system and led to the idea that the Finnish Grand Duchy was an increasingly separate part of the Russian Empire., , , , , , 

Since the year 1899 the Russian Empire initiated the policy of integration-russification in the Finnish Grand Duchy. As the  international strategic status of Russia had become more difficult e.g. via the rise of Germany and Japan, the Russian central administration and  ''panslavism''  had strengthened in Saint Petersburg, the Russian Tsar and the military leaders attempted to unite the large, heterogeneous empire. Russification of Finland had the aim of increasing military and administrative control over the Grand Duchy. The Finns called the integration policy "the first period of oppression 1899–1905". After 1899 the Finno-Russian relations became worse, and plans for disengagement from Russia or even achieving sovereignty for Finland were drawn up for the first time. Several political and economical groups with different policies in respect to Russia arose. The most radical one, the activist movement, including anarchistic  groups both from the working class and the Swedish speaking intelligentsia, arranged terrorist attacks. During World War I and via rise of ''germanism'' the latter (svecomans) began a covert collaboration with Imperial Germany, and during 1915-1917 a Jäger bataljon of 2 000 voluntary Finnish men was trained in Germany, by the support of the same German source of financing, which aided the Bolseviks in Russia. Contrary, a few thousand Finns with a positive attitude towards Russia, joined the Tsar's army in 1914. , , , , , ,
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="88f465242faaf782744f32877fd84ed5" name="Peasants_in_finland" sectnum="1#1">../img/88f465242faaf782744f32877fd84ed5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>