<document id="016bb5f8a0f78e3e51fafe4fd880e7fc-4.3" name="Komodo_dragon" cat="3">
<text>
Auffenberg described the Komodo dragon as having septic pathogens in its saliva, specifically the bacteria: ''Escherichia coli'', ''Staphylococcus sp.'', ''Providencia sp.'', ''Proteus morgani'' and ''P. mirabilis''.  He noted that while these pathogens can be found in the mouths of wild Komodo dragons, they disappear from the mouths of captive animals, due to a cleaner diet.Balsai,Michael Joseph (2001). ''The phylogenetic position of Palaeosaniwa and the early evolution of the Platynotan (Varanoid) anguimorphs'' (January 1, 2001). Univ. of Pennsylvania - Electronic Dissertations. Paper AAI3031637. This was verified by taking mucous samples from the external gum surface of the upper jaw of two freshly captured individuals.  Saliva samples were analyzed by researchers at the University of Texas who found 57 different strains of bacteria growing in the mouths of three wild Komodo dragons including ''Pasteurella multocida''. The rapid growth of this bacteria was noted by Fredeking: "Normally it takes about three days for a sample of ''P. multocida'' to cover a petri dish; ours took eight hours. We were very taken aback by how virulent these strains were".  This study supported the observation that wounds inflicted by the Komodo dragon are often associated with sepsis and subsequent infections in prey animals.

In late 2005, researchers at the University of Melbourne speculated that the perentie (''Varanus giganteus''), other species of monitor, and agamids may be somewhat venomous. The team believes that the immediate effects of bites from these lizards were caused by mild envenomation. Bites on human digits by a lace monitor (''V. varius''), a Komodo dragon, and a spotted tree monitor (''V. scalaris'') all produced similar effects: rapid swelling, localized disruption of blood clotting, and shooting pain up to the elbow, with some symptoms lasting for several hours.

In 2009, the same researchers published further evidence demonstrating that Komodo dragons possess a venomous bite. MRI scans of a preserved skull showed the presence of two venom glands in the lower jaw. They extracted one of these glands from the head of a terminally ill specimen in the Singapore Zoological Gardens, and found that it secreted a venom containing several different toxic proteins. The known functions of these proteins include inhibition of blood clotting, lowering of blood pressure, muscle paralysis, and the induction of hypothermia, leading to shock and loss of consciousness in envenomated prey., Yahoo news from May 18th 2009Bryan G. Fry, Stephen Wroec, Wouter Teeuwissed, et al., (University of Melbourne): PNAS, publisched online, , ''A central role for venom in predation by ''Varanus komodoensis'' (Komodo Dragon) and the extinct giant ''Varanus'' (''Megalania'') ''priscus'''' As a result of the discovery, the previous theory that bacteria were responsible for the deaths of komodo victims was disputed.Staff. "." ''CNN''. May 20, 2009. Retrieved on May 25, 2009. 

Kurt Schwenk, an evolutionary biologist at the University of Connecticut finds the discovery of these glands intriguing, but considers most of the evidence for venom in the study to be "meaningless, irrelevant, incorrect or falsely misleading". Even if the lizards have venomlike proteins in their mouths, Schwenk argues, they may be using them for a different function, and he doubts that venom is necessary to explain the effect of a Komodo dragon bite, arguing that shock and blood loss are the primary factors.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5f9e5d52fd2b9b89098f17ef1e0ceb9f" name="KomodoDragon" sectnum="4.3#1">../img/5f9e5d52fd2b9b89098f17ef1e0ceb9f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>