<document id="0174e628c0d9a007c78819c9eb1029b2-4" name="Pontiac's_Rebellion" cat="29">
<text>
The violence and terror of Pontiac's War convinced many western Pennsylvanians that their government was not doing enough to protect them. This discontent was manifest most seriously in an uprising led by a vigilante group that came to be known as the Paxton Boys, so-called because they were primarily from the area around the Pennsylvania village of Paxton (or Paxtang). The Paxtonians turned their anger towards Native Americans—many of them Christians—who lived peacefully in small enclaves in the midst of white Pennsylvania settlements. Prompted by rumors that a Native war party had been seen at the Native village of Conestoga, on December 14, 1763, a group of more than 50 Paxton Boys marched on the village and murdered the six Susquehannocks they found there. Pennsylvania officials placed the remaining 14 Susquehannocks in protective custody in Lancaster, but on December 27 the Paxton Boys broke into the jail and slaughtered them. Governor John Penn issued bounties for the arrest of the murderers, but no one came forward to identify them.Nester, ''"Haughty Conquerors"'', 173.

The Paxton Boys then set their sights on other Natives living within eastern Pennsylvania, many of whom fled to Philadelphia for protection. Several hundred Paxtonians marched on Philadelphia in January 1764, where the presence of British troops and Philadelphia militia prevented them from doing more violence. Benjamin Franklin, who had helped organize the local militia, negotiated with the Paxton leaders and brought an end to the immediate crisis. Franklin published a scathing indictment of the Paxton Boys. "If an ''Indian'' injures me," he asked, "does it follow that I may revenge that Injury on all ''Indians''?"Franklin quoted in Nester, ''"Haughty Conquerors"'', 176.One leader of the Paxton Boys was Lazarus Stewart who would be killed in the Wyoming Massacre of 1778.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8d1ec77ad9662bf81abd76217e82a366" name="Paxton_massacre" sectnum="4#1">../img/8d1ec77ad9662bf81abd76217e82a366.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>