<document id="0174e628c0d9a007c78819c9eb1029b2-2.2" name="Pontiac's_Rebellion" cat="29">
<text>
General Amherst, the British commander-in-chief in North America, was in overall charge of administering policy towards Native Americans, which involved both military matters and regulation of the fur trade. Amherst believed that with France out of the picture, the Natives would have no other choice than to accept British rule. He also believed that they were incapable of offering any serious resistance to the British Army; therefore, of the 8,000 troops under his command in North America, only about 500 were stationed in the region where the war erupted.Dixon, ''Never Come to Peace'', 157–58. Amherst and officers such as Major Henry Gladwin, commander at Fort Detroit, made little effort to conceal their contempt for the natives. Natives involved in the uprising frequently complained that the British treated them no better than slaves or dogs.Dowd, ''War under Heaven'', 63–69.

Additional Native resentment resulted from Amherst's decision in February 1761 to cut back on the gifts given to the Natives. Gift giving had been an integral part of the relationship between the French and the tribes of the ''pays d'en haut''. Following an Native American custom which carried important symbolic meaning, the French gave presents (such as guns, knives, tobacco, and clothing) to village chiefs, who in turn redistributed these gifts to their people. By this process, the village chiefs gained stature among their people, and were thus able to maintain the alliance with the French.White, ''Middle Ground'', 36, 113, 179–83. Amherst, however, considered this process to be a form of bribery that was no longer necessary, especially since he was under pressure to cut expenses after the war with France. Many Natives regarded this change in policy as an insult and an indication that the British looked upon them as conquered people rather than as allies.White, ''Middle Ground'', 256–58; McConnell, ''A Country Between'', 163–64; Dowd, ''War under Heaven'', 70–75.

Amherst also began to restrict the amount of ammunition and gunpowder that traders could sell to Natives. While the French had always made these supplies available, Amherst did not trust the natives, particularly after the "Cherokee Rebellion" of 1761, in which Cherokee warriors took up arms against their former British allies. The Cherokee war effort had collapsed because of a shortage of gunpowder, and so Amherst hoped that future uprisings could be prevented by limiting the distribution of gunpowder. This created resentment and hardship because gunpowder and ammunition were wanted by native men because it made providing food for their families and skins for the fur trade much easier. Many Natives began to believe that the British were disarming them as a prelude to making war upon them. Sir William Johnson, the Superintendent of the Indian Department, tried to warn Amherst of the dangers of cutting back on presents and gunpowder, to no avail.For effect of the Cherokee gunpowder shortage on Amherst, see Anderson, ''Crucible of War'', 468–71; Dixon, ''Never Come to Peace'', 78. For Native resentment of gunpowder restrictions, see Dowd, ''War under Heaven'', 76–77; Dixon, ''Never Come to Peace'', 83.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="501a7b9c0580aed6eb455c56f7fc0f15" name="Amherst" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/501a7b9c0580aed6eb455c56f7fc0f15.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>