<document id="0179a2e06258056b0f9c23583da1c66c-6" name="The_Catlins" cat="11">
<text>
The early European economy of the Catlins during the 1830s and 1840s centred on whaling and sealing. The exploitation of the forests for timber started in the 1860s with the rapid growth of the city of Dunedin as a result of the goldrush of 1861–62. In the early 1870s more timber cargo was loaded at Owaka than at any other New Zealand port.Buckingham and Hall-Jones (1985), p. 11. Forestry and sawmilling declined in the late 1880s once the easily accessible timber had been removed. The extension of the railway beyond Owaka breathed new life into these industries, however, with activity peaking during the 1920s., p. 7. Retrieved 28 March 2006.

The land cleared of trees largely became pasture. From the 1880s, clearing of land for dairy farming increased, especially in the areas around Tahakopa and the Owaka River valley. Considerable sheep and dairy farming continues on the cleared hills on the periphery of the region, and this accounts for much of the Catlins' income. A rural polytechnic specialising in agricultural science (Telford Polytechnic) is located south of Balclutha close to the northeastern edge of the Catlins.

Fishing and tourism account for much of the area's economy. The rugged natural scenery, sense of isolation, and natural attractions such as Cathedral Caves makes the Catlins a popular destination for weekend trips by people from Dunedin and Invercargill, the two nearest cities. A large number of cribs (holiday cottages) occur at places such as Jack's Bay and Pounawea. Ecotourism is becoming increasingly important to the area's economy, with many of the visitors coming from overseas. Tourism resources grew from three motels and four camping grounds in 1990 to eight motels, four camping grounds and 12 backpackers hostels a decade later, along with at least ten regular guided tour operations.A  gives, on pp. 17–18, a case study of "Catlins Wildlife Trackers", a local tourist concern. This study indicates that only 20% of this company's visitors are from New Zealand, and that tourist numbers are steadily increasing, and are also moving from back-packers to more up-market tourists. Retrieved 4 April 2006. Tourism added an estimated $2.4 million to the region's economy in 2003., Department of Tourism, University of Otago, p. 19. Retrieved 4 April 2006.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7030b690dd759d385b78b4cd670f79fe" name="In_Cathedral_Caves_3" sectnum="6#1">../img/7030b690dd759d385b78b4cd670f79fe.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>