<document id="01f6736d00cc0893ac90b55ccc989a34-5" name="Thomas_C._Hindman" cat="14">
<text>
By 1854, Hindman realized that he had little room to maneuver in the crowded Mississippi political arena. Looking across the Mississippi River, Hindman observed that the young and turbulent State of Arkansas was wide open for a well educated and ambitious politician. Hindman left Mississippi politics when he moved to Helena, Arkansas on March 18, 1854.Sons of Temperance, Minutes, Term Ending March 31, 1854, Item 64.

Hindman threw himself into the political and social scenes in his new home state. In June 1854, he formed a law partnership with John Palmer, a young Kentucky native who was known as a "distinguished member" of the Helena bar. Hindman became active in civic affairs and plans for Helena's economic development. At an Independence Day festival in 1854, he gave a speech about the importance of railroad development in Arkansas.Helena ''Democratic Star'', July 5, 1854. Hindman catapulted himself into the fray by taking a stand against the anti-immigrant and anti-Catholic Know-Nothings, whom he considered "pestilent fanatics."Little Rock ''True Democrat'', June 12, 1855. Hindman and Palmer established a Democratic association designed to stamp out the Know-Nothing threat. During this time, Hindman became close friends with Patrick Cleburne, who would later parallel his course as a Confederate Major General. The two men also formed a business partnership with William Weatherly to buy a newspaper, the ''Democratic Star'', in December 1855.Helena ''Southern Shield'', December 29, 1855. 

Cleburne and Hindman were both wounded by gunshots during a street fight in Helena with Know-Nothing members. After the men recovered, they appeared before a grand jury to respond to any charges brought against them. They were exonerated and, afterwards, went to Hindman's parents' house in Mississippi.Nash (1895), pp66–69. Hindman received praise for his actions and became a force in Democratic politics after the Know-Nothings were defeated.

In 1856, Hindman ran for the Congressional seat in his First District, but was defeated by the incumbent, Alfred B. Greenwood, at the Democratic state convention.''True Democrat'', May 20, 1856. His gracious withdrawal at the convention to avoid Democratic infighting earned him more notice from the party hierarchy. During this time, Hindman met and courted Mary "Mollie" Watkins Biscoe. Despite her parents' reluctance, the two were married on November 11, 1856, with Patrick Cleburne serving as best man.Neal (1997), p39.

In the summer of 1857, Hindman became editor of the ''Helena States-Rights Democrat''Nash (1895), p75.''Southern Shield'', July 30, 1857. and was the unchallenged leader of the Democratic Party in eastern Arkansas.Neal (1997), p42. From this platform, he launched his 1858 Congressional bid. He did not face a serious challenge for the Democratic nomination and he had the backing of newspapers through the state. Editor Richard H. Johnson of the Little Rock ''True Democrat'' reminded voters of Hindman's previous run for the nomination in 1856 and praised him for being a "thorough going Democrat" of "marked abilities."''True Democrat'', February 16, 1858. At the state Democratic convention in Batesville, Hindman easily defeated A. M. Wilson and Dandridge McRae.''True Democrat'', May 18, 1858.Van Buren ''Intelligencer'', May 21, 1858. In the general election, Hindman defeated the Republican challenger, William M. Crosby, by a vote of 18,255 to 2,853.''True Democrat'', August 18, 1858.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c00798c00eee84de9ec90cd6e800e226" name="Hindman" sectnum="5#1">../img/c00798c00eee84de9ec90cd6e800e226.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>