<document id="022b721531b70a95477f6ac1a9c17343-4" name="Hoysala_architecture" cat="1">
<text>
Surveys in modern times have indicated that 1000&ndash;1500 structures were built by the Hoysalas, of which about a hundred temples have survived to date.Kamath (2001), p1321,500 temples in 958 centres were built, according to historical records, between 1000–1346 CE.  The Hoysala style is an offshoot of the Western Chalukya style, which was popular in the 10th and 11th centuries.Kamath (2001), p134 — James Fergusson and Henry Cousens opine that the Hoysala style has features in common with the Western Chalukya style It is distinctively Dravidian, and owing to its unique features, Hoysala architecture qualifies as an independent style.Hoysala architecture and sculpture have been called a phenomenal effort of human concentration, skill and religious consciousness (Percy Brown in Kamath 2001, p134) While the Hoysalas introduced innovative features into their architecture, they also borrowed features from the earlier great builders of ''Karnata'' like the Kadambas, Western Chalukyas. These features were the use of chloritic schist or soapstone as a basic building material,Kamath (2001) p136 — The Western Chalukya carvings were done in green schist (soapstone), a technique adopted by the Hoysalas pierced stone window screens which were very popular in Hoysala temples,This is very commonly found in earlier Western Chalukya temples (Kamath 2001, p116) and the ''vimana'' which follows a stellate pattern. — The Western Chalukya architecture has a stellate plan for the ''vimana'' All these features were popular with their early overlords, the Western Chalukyas. Other features were the stepped style of ''vimana'' tower called the ''Kadamba shikhara'', which was inherited from the Kadambas.The most prominent feature of Kadamba architecture is their ''shikhara'', called "Kadamba shikhara". The ''shikhara'' is pyramid-shaped and rises in steps without any decoration and has a ''stupika'' or ''kalasha'' on the top (Kamath 2001, p38) Engrained in the craftsmanship of Hoysala sculptors was their knowledge of the effect of light and shade on carved walls, which they used to maximum effect in their sculptures in the numerous projections and recesses. The Hoysala sculpture in all its richness is said to be a challenge to photography. The artistry of the Hoysalas in stone has been compared to the finesse of an ivory worker or a goldsmith. The abundance of jewelry worn by the sculpted figures and the variety of hairstyles and headdresses depicted give a fair idea of the lifestyles of the Hoysala times.Sastri (1955), p429
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f55e8e62156df8aebf49410d720ee866" name="Chikkamagalur_Amruthapura_kirthimukha_retouched" sectnum="4#1">../img/f55e8e62156df8aebf49410d720ee866.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>