<document id="02b0e855355864af75ebbe39c93af357-2" name="Matthew_Brettingham" cat="1">
<text>
During the early eighteenth century, a building contractor had far more responsibilities than the title suggests today. A contractor often designed, built, and oversaw all details of construction to completion. Architects, often called surveyors, were employed only for the grandest and largest of buildings. By 1730, Brettingham is referred to as a surveyor, working on more important structures than cottages and agricultural buildings. In 1731, it is recorded that he was paid £112 for his work on Norwich Gaol.Howell James, p.346 From then, he appears to have worked regularly as the surveyor to the Justices (the contemporary local authority) on public buildings and bridges throughout the 1740s. Projects of his dating from this time include the remodelling of the Shirehouse in Norwich, the construction of Lenwade Bridge over the river Wensum, repairs to Norwich Castle and Norwich Cathedral, as well as the rebuilding of much of St. Margaret's Church, King's Lynn, which had been severely damaged by the collapse of its spire in 1742. His work on the Shirehouse, which was in the gothic style and showed a versatility of design rare for Brettingham, was to result in a protracted court case that was to rumble on through a large part of his life, with allegations of financial discrepancies.Howell James, p.348 onwards In 1755, the case was eventually closed, and Brettingham was left several hundred pounds out of pocket, and with a stain—if only a local one—on his character. Transcripts of the case suggest that it was Brettingham's brother Robert, to whom he had subcontracted and who was responsible for the flint stonework of the Shirehouse, who may have been the cause of the allegations.Howell James, p.349 and Colvin, p.155 Brettingham's brief flirtation with the Gothic style, in the words of Robin Lucas, indicates "the approach of an engineer rather than an antiquary" and is "now seen as outlandish". The Shirehouse was demolished in 1822.Colvin, p.157
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="deee24a0544dbdb02998aa1f9faa4574" name="Norwich_castle" sectnum="2#1">../img/deee24a0544dbdb02998aa1f9faa4574.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>