<document id="02c30178376298fedaf02044d8f1ca74-5" name="Gyromitra_esculenta" cat="3">
<text>
Despite its recognized toxicity, ''Gyromitra esculenta'' is marketed and consumed in several countries or states in Europe and North America. It was previously consumed in Germany, with fungi picked in and exported from Poland; more recently, however, Germany and Switzerland discouraged consumption by prohibiting its sale.  Similarly in Sweden, the Swedish National Food Administration warns it is not fit for human consumption, and restricts purchase of mushrooms to restaurants alone. The mushroom is still highly regarded and consumed in Bulgaria, being sold in markets and picked for export there. In some countries such as Spain, especially in the eastern Pyrenees, they are traditionally considered a delicacy, and many people report consuming them for many years with no ill effects. Despite this, the false morel is listed as hazardous in official mushroom lists published by the Catalan Government and sale to the public is prohibited throughout Spain.  Selling and purchasing fresh false morels is legal in Finland, where it is highly regarded. However, the mushrooms are required by law to be accompanied with a warning that they are poisonous and legally prescribed preparation instructions. False morels are also sold prepared and canned, in which case they are ready to be used. Official figures from the Finnish Ministry of Agriculture and Forestry report a total amount of false morels sold in Finland of 21.9 tonnes in 2006 and 32.7 tonnes, noted as being above average, in 2007. In 2002, the Finnish Food Safety Authority estimated annual consumption of false morels to be hundreds of tonnes in plentiful years. Outside of Europe, ''Gyromitra esculenta'' is consumed in the Great Lakes region and some western states in the United States.

In Finnish cuisine, false morels may be cooked in an omelette, or gently sautéed in butter in a saucepan, flour and milk added to make a bechamel sauce, or pie filling. Alternately, more fluid can be added for a false morel soup. Typical condiments added for flavour include parsley, chives, dill and black pepper.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a82a651ecd2ac28c85ddc2d449b9a974" name="False_morels_for_sale_in_Helsinki_2" sectnum="5#1">../img/a82a651ecd2ac28c85ddc2d449b9a974.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>