<document id="02de319d059dfa89da3b23b9a62af166-3" name="Fin_Whale" cat="3">
<text>
Like many of the large rorquals, the Fin Whale is a cosmopolitan species. It is found in all the world's major oceans, and in waters ranging from the polar to the tropical. It is absent only from waters close to the ice pack at both the north and south extremities and relatively small areas of water away from the large oceans, such as the Red Sea, the Persian Gulf, the eastern part of the Mediterranean, and the Baltic Sea. The highest population density occurs in temperate and cool waters. It is less densely populated in the hottest, equatorial regions. It prefers deep waters beyond the continental shelf to shallow waters.

The North Atlantic Fin Whale has an extensive distribution, occurring from the Gulf of Mexico and Mediterranean Sea, northward to the edges of the Arctic ice pack. In general, Fin Whales are more common north of approximately 30째N latitude, but considerable confusion arises about their occurrence south of 30째N latitude because of the difficulty in distinguishing Fin Whales from Bryde's Whales. Extensive ship surveys have led researchers to conclude that the summer feeding range of Fin Whales in the western North Atlantic was mainly between 41째20'N and 51째00'N, from shore seaward to the 1,000 fathom (1,800 m) contour.

Summer distribution of Fin Whales in the North Pacific is the immediate offshore waters from central Baja California to Japan, and as far north as the Chukchi Sea bordering the Arctic Ocean. They occur in high densities in the northern Gulf of Alaska and southeastern Bering Sea between May and October, with some movement through the Aleutian passes into and out of the Bering Sea. Several whales tagged between November and January off southern California were killed in the summer off central California, Oregon, British Columbia, and in the Gulf of Alaska. Fin Whales have been observed feeding in Hawaiian waters in mid-May, and several winter sightings have been made there. Some researchers have suggested that the whales migrate into Hawaiian waters primarily in the autumn and winter.

Although Fin Whales are certainly migratory, moving seasonally in and out of high-latitude feeding areas, the overall migration pattern is not well understood. Acoustic readings from passive-listening hydrophone arrays indicate a southward migration of the North Atlantic Fin Whale occurs in the autumn from the Labrador-Newfoundland region, south past Bermuda, and into the West Indies. One or more populations of Fin Whales are thought to remain year-round in high latitudes, moving offshore, but not southward in late autumn. In the Pacific, migration patterns are difficult to understand. Although some Fin Whales are apparently present in the Gulf of California year-round, there is a significant increase in their numbers in the winter and spring. Antarctic Fin Whales migrate seasonally from relatively high-latitude Antarctic feeding grounds in the summer to low-latitude breeding and calving areas in the winter. The location of winter breeding areas is still unknown, since these whales tend to migrate in the open ocean and thus exact locations have been difficult to determine.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="843992656f7f7caa61203f7f3394e17d" name="Fin_whale_from_air" sectnum="3#1">../img/843992656f7f7caa61203f7f3394e17d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>