<document id="02de319d059dfa89da3b23b9a62af166-5" name="Fin_Whale" cat="3">
<text>
In the 19th century, the Fin Whale was occasionally hunted by the open-boat whalers, but it was relatively safe because of its quick speed and the fact that it often sank when killed. However, the introduction of steam-powered boats in the second half of that century and harpoons that exploded on impact made it possible to kill and secure Blue Whales, Fin Whales, and Sei Whales on an industrial scale. As other whale species became over-hunted, the whaling industry turned to the still-abundant Fin Whale as a substitute. It was primarily hunted for its blubber, oil, and baleen. Approximately 704,000 Fin Whales were caught in Antarctic whaling operations alone between 1904 and 1975. After the introduction of factory ships with stern slipways in 1925, the number of whales taken per year increased substantially. In 1937 alone, over 28,000 Fin Whales were taken. From 1953 to 1961, whaling of the species averaged around 25,000 per year. By 1962, Sei Whale catches began to increase as Fin Whales became scarce. By 1974, fewer than 1,000 Fin Whales were being caught each year. The IWC prohibited the taking of Fin Whales from the southern hemisphere in 1976. In the North Pacific, a reported total of approximately 46,000 Fin Whales were killed by commercial whalers between 1947 and 1987. Acknowledgement that the Soviet Union engaged in the illegal killing of protected whale species in the North Pacific means that the reported catch data is incomplete. The Fin Whale was given full protection from commercial whaling by the IWC in the North Pacific in 1976, and in the North Atlantic in 1987, with the exception of small aboriginal catches and catches for research purposes. All populations worldwide remain listed as endangered species by the US National Marine Fisheries Service and the International Conservation Union Red List, and the Fin Whale is on Appendix 1 of CITES.

The Fin Whale is hunted in the Northern Hemisphere in Greenland, under the International Whaling Commission's procedure for aboriginal subsistence whaling. Meat and other products from whales killed in these hunts are widely marketed within the Greenland economy, but export is illegal. The IWC has set a quota of 19 Fin Whales per year for Greenland despite concern about uncertainty of current population levels. Iceland and Norway are not bound by the IWC's moratorium on commercial whaling because both countries filed objections to the moratorium. In October 2006, Iceland's fisheries ministry authorized the hunting of nine Fin Whales through August 2007. In the southern hemisphere, Japan has targeted Fin Whales in its Antarctic Special Permit whaling program for the 2005–2006 and 2006–2007 seasons at 10 whales killed per year. The proposal for 2007–2008 and the subsequent 12 seasons includes 50 Fin Whales per year, but by the close of the 2007-2008 season in April 2008, no fin whales had been caught.

Collisions with ships are an additional major cause of Fin Whale mortality. In some areas, they represent a substantial portion of the strandings of large whales. Most lethal and serious injuries are caused by large, fast-moving ships over or near the continental shelf.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1caca91d05b929c1f152b9c434dc22c9" name="Captured_fin_whale" sectnum="5#1">../img/1caca91d05b929c1f152b9c434dc22c9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>