<document id="02e5ff428166789934a75274fccd3472-3" name="Oregon_State_Capitol" cat="1">
<text>
The capitol grounds cover three city blocks and include Willson and Capitol parks. Near the west entrance of the capitol is a replica of Philadelphia's Liberty Bell. This bell is one of 53 full-sized replicas made in France and donated by the United States government to each state. Oregon received its copy on July 4, 1950.A Walking Tour: State of Oregon Capitol Grounds. Published by the Oregon Department of General Services. Throughout the grounds are native trees and shrubs, including blue spruce, Oregon-grape (the state flower), giant sequoia, coast redwood, Japanese maple, dogwood species, Bradford pear, cherry tree species, English holly, rhododendron, and magnolia tree species. One Douglas-fir tree was grown using a seed that rode aboard Apollo 14 to the Moon in 1971 and was transplanted to the capitol in 1976 from Oregon State University.

On the east side of the building is Capitol Park, which includes the Circuit Rider statue by A. Phimister Proctor, statues of John McLoughlin and Jason Lee by Gifford Proctor, and portions of the Corinthian columns of the second capitol building.  Lee established the Methodist Mission and what would become Willamette University. McLoughlin, of the Hudson's Bay Company, was proclaimed the Father of Oregon.  The Circuit Rider was added in 1924 as a monument to early preachers. During the Columbus Day Storm in 1962, this statue was knocked over and damaged but restored in 1963.  There is also a memorial to Oregon's recipients of the Congressional Medal of Honor. This memorial, dedicated on September 18, 2004, has 13 pillars of granite and includes bronze plaques with images and medal citations for each recipient. 

To the west of the building is Willson Park, named for Salem founder William H. Willson and sited roughly at the center of his former landholdings.  From 1853 to 1965 it was a Salem city park. After the park was turned over to the state, Lloyd Bond and Associates were asked to redesign the park. Willson Park has the Waite Fountain, a gazebo built in 1982, and a Parade of Animals sculpture, designed as a play structure and added in 1991.  Waite Fountain was donated in honor of Oregon businessperson E. M. Waite in 1907 by his wife. The Breyman Brothers Fountain, added in 1904 as a memorial to Werner and Eugene Breyman,  is at the far west end of the park.  It was originally decorated with a statue of a soldier from the Spanish-American War and also served as a lamp post and horse trough. Today the statue holds no water and is sometimes planted with flowers.  In 2005, a Walk of Flags feature was added that displays the flags of every state in the Union. In 2009, the nine flags of Oregon's federally recognized Native American tribes were added to the Walk of Flags.

Other features on the capitol grounds include Sprague Fountain and the Wall of Water. The Wall of Water is located across Court Street from the main entrance. It was added in 1990 and has 22 nozzles shooting water  into the air in a plaza that also has slabs of stone with  information about Oregon's history. Added in 1985, the Capitol Beaver family represents the state animal. Additional features of the grounds include a peace pole donated by the Society of Prayer for World Peace, a large boulder that once lay along the Oregon Trail, a planter that spells out "Oregon" using shrubs, and a rose garden maintained by the Salem Rose Society.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b752c280e6928debce7701bac836a940" name="WalkofTheFlagsORCapitol" sectnum="3#1">../img/b752c280e6928debce7701bac836a940.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>