<document id="0326a61f1522b13bde5c4cab2507430c-1" name="Chromatophore" cat="3">
<text>
Invertebrate pigment-bearing cells were first described as ''chromoforo'' in an Italian science journal in 1819. Sangiovanni G. Descrizione di un particolare sistema di organi cromoforo espansivo-dermoideo e dei fenomeni che esso produce, scoperto nei molluschi cefaloso. ''G. Enciclopedico Napoli''. 1819; 9:1–13. The term ''chromatophore'' was adopted later as the name for pigment bearing cells derived from the neural crest of cold-blooded vertebrates and cephalopods. The word itself comes from the Greek words ''khrōma'' (χρωμα) meaning "colour," and ''phoros'' (φορος) meaning "bearing". In contrast, the word ''chromatocyte'' (''cyte'' or κυτε being Greek for "cell") was adopted for the cells responsible for colour found in birds and mammals. Only one such cell type, the melanocyte, has been identified in these animals.

It wasn't until the 1960s that the structure and colouration of chromatophores were understood well enough to allow the development of a system of sub-classification based on their appearance. This classification system persists to this day even though more recent studies have revealed that certain biochemical aspects of the pigments may be more useful to a scientific understanding of how the cells function. Bagnara JT. Cytology and cytophysiology of non-melanophore pigment cells. ''Int Rev Cytol''. 1966; 20:173–205. PMID 5337298

Colour-production falls into distinct classes: biochromes, schemochromes.Fox, DL. ''Animal Biochromes and Structural Colors: Physical, Chemical, Distributional & Physiological Features of Colored Bodies in the Animal World.'' University of California Press, Berkeley, 1976. ISBN 0520023471 The biochromes include true pigments, such as carotenoids and pteridines. These pigments selectively absorb parts of the visible light spectrum that makes up white light while permitting other wavelengths to reach  the eye of the observer. Schemochromes, also known as "structural colours", produce colouration by reflecting some wavelengths (colours) of light and transmitting others, by causing light waves to interfere within the structure or by scattering light which falls upon them.

While all chromatophores contain pigments or reflecting structures (except when there has been a genetic mutation resulting in a disorder like albinism), not all pigment containing cells are chromatophores. Haem, for example, is a biochrome responsible for the red appearance of blood. It is primarily found in red blood cells (erythrocytes), which are generated in bone marrow throughout the life of an organism, rather than being formed during embryological development. Therefore erythrocytes are not classified as chromatophores.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e68f7db774589fbf126f23d312a68296" name="C_Calyptratus_female" sectnum="1#1">../img/e68f7db774589fbf126f23d312a68296.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>