<document id="0326a61f1522b13bde5c4cab2507430c-1.3" name="Chromatophore" cat="3">
<text>
Melanophores contain eumelanin, a type of melanin, that appears black or dark brown because of its light absorbing qualities. It is packaged in vesicles called melanosomes and distributed throughout the cell. Eumelanin is generated from tyrosine in a series of catalysed chemical reactions. It is a complex chemical containing units of dihydroxyindole and dihydroxyindole-2-carboxylic acid with some pyrrole rings. Ito S & Wakamatsu K. Quantitative analysis of eumelanin and pheomelanin in humans, mice, and other animals: a comparative review. ''Pigment Cell Res''. 2003; 16:523-31. PMID 12950732 The key enzyme in melanin synthesis is tyrosinase. When this protein is defective, no melanin can be generated resulting in certain types of albinism. In some amphibian species there are other pigments packaged alongside eumelanin. For example, a novel deep red coloured pigment was identified in the melanophores of phyllomedusine frogs. Bagnara JT ''et al.'' Color changes, unusual melanosomes, and a new pigment from leaf frogs. ''Science''. 1973; 182:1034–5. PMID 4748673 This was subsequently identified as pterorhodin, a pteridine dimer that accumulates around eumelanin. While it is likely that other lesser studied species have complex melanophore pigments, it is nevertheless true that the majority of melanophores studied to date do contain eumelanin exclusively.

Humans have only one class of pigment cell, the mammalian equivalent of melanophores, to generate skin, hair and eye colour. For this reason, and because the large number and contrasting colour of the cells usually make them very easy to visualise, melanophores are by far the most widely studied chromatophore. However, there are differences between the biology of melanophores and melanocytes. In addition to eumelanin, melanocytes can generate a yellow/red pigment called phaeomelanin.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fb916cb5e6bb8a2a92e1d1847a615598" name="Dendrobates_pumilio" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/fb916cb5e6bb8a2a92e1d1847a615598.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>