<document id="038574999a443cd4acf16e40a9ab1b9e-1" name="Maiden_Castle,_Dorset" cat="1">
<text>
There was activity on the site of Maiden Castle before the hill fort was built; a Neolithic causewayed enclosure was constructed around 4000 BC. This was an oval area, enclosed by two ditches,Sharples (1991a), p. 34. and it is termed a causewayed enclosure because the way the ditches were dug meant that there would originally have been gaps in the ditches.Sharples (1991a), pp. 38&ndash;39. These gaps, and the bank being only  high, indicate the site would not have been defensive, but the ditches may have been symbolic, separating the interior of the enclosure and its activities from the outside.Sharples (1991a), p. 39. Archaeologist Niall Sharples, who was involved in excavating the hill fort in the 1980s, has identified the hilltop views of the surrounding landscape as a likely factor for the enclosure's position. Situated on the side of the hill, it would have been visible from several miles away, and when first cut the ditches would have exposed the underlying white chalk and stood out against the green hillside. The interior of the enclosure has been disturbed by later habitation and farming. The site does not appear to have been inhabited, although a grave containing the remains of two children, aged 6&ndash;7, has been discovered.Sharples (1991a), pp. 35&ndash;37. The enclosure is the earliest evidence of human activity on the site. 

The purpose of Neolithic causewayed enclosures is unclear, and they probably had a variety of functions. As well as burials, indicating the site at Maiden Castle was important for rituals related to death, pottery from the coast and areas to the east and west indicate it was used as a meeting place which attracted people over long distances.Sharples (1991a), p. 53. Radiocarbon dating indicates that the enclosure was abandoned around 3,400 BC. Arrowheads discovered in the ditches may indicate that activity at the enclosure met a violent end.Sharples (1991a), pp. 54&ndash;56. 

Within a period of about 50 years, a bank barrow was built over the enclosure. It was a -long mound of earth with a ditch on either side; the parallel ditches were  apart.Sharples (1991a), p. 56. Many barrows lie over graves and are monuments to the deceased, but as the barrow at Maiden Castle did not cover any burials, it has been suggested that it was a boundary marker, which would explain the limited human activity on the hilltop for the 500 years after the bank barrow's construction.Sharples (1991a), pp. 59&ndash;60. Around 1,800 BC, during the early Bronze Age, the hill was cleared and used to grow crops, but the soil was quickly exhausted and the site abandoned. This period of abandonment lasted until the Iron Age, when the hill fort was built.Sharples (1991a), pp. 65&ndash;67. The bank barrow survived into the Iron Age as a low mound, and throughout this period construction over it was avoided.Sharples (1991a), pp. 94&ndash;96.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="cd8efee69c49d0f2e52f15134dcc7fe6" name="Maiden_castle_dorset" sectnum="1#1">../img/cd8efee69c49d0f2e52f15134dcc7fe6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>