<document id="038a69f549d1470199e92700231bb34b-3.5" name="Derfflinger_class_battlecruiser" cat="29">
<text>
Named after Georg von Derfflinger, a German field marshal during the Thirty Years War,  was commissioned on 1 September 1914. A dockyard crew transferred the ship from Hamburg to Kiel, via the Skagen. The ship was assigned to the I Scouting Group at the end of October. Damage to the ship's turbines sustained during trials prevented the ship from seeing active service until 16 November. On 15 December, the ship took part in the raid on Scarborough, Hartlepool and Whitby. She was also present during the battle of Dogger Bank on 24 January 1915. The ship was hit once by a 13.5-inch shell from one of the British battlecruisers; in response, she heavily damaged . Repair work was completed by 16 February, but ''Derfflinger''s starboard turbine was accidentally damaged on 28 June, and the ship was again in the dockyard until August. On 24 April 1916, ''Derfflinger'' took part in the bombardment of Yarmouth.Staff, p. 39


On 31 May, ''Derfflinger'' was heavily engaged during the battle of Jutland, as the second ship in the German battlecruiser line. She sustained 21 major hits during the battle, but dealt considerable damage to the British battlecruiser force as well. At 16:26,  sank after a magazine explosion that tore the ship apart; she had been targeted with a hail of heavy-caliber gunfire from ''Derfflinger'' and ''Seydlitz''. Two hours later, at 18:30,  suffered a similar fate, though ''Derfflinger'' was assisted by her sister ''Lützow''. During the engagement, ''Derfflinger'' had both of her rear turrets knocked out by British gunfire. Her crew suffered 157 men killed and 26 wounded, which was the highest casualty figure for any ship not sunk. The resilience of the vessel earned her the nickname "Iron Dog" from her British adversaries. Repair work lasted until 15 October, during which the ship had her pole mast removed and replaced with a tripod mast. The ship conducted training operations until November, at which point she returned to active duty with the fleet.Staff, pp. 39&ndash;40

Following the German capitulation in November 1918, ''Derfflinger'' was interned with a significant portion of the High Seas Fleet in Scapa Flow. On 21 June 1919, with the guard ships of the Royal Navy out on maneuvers, Rear Admiral Ludwig von Reuter ordered that the fleet be scuttled.The Armistice was scheduled to expire at noon on 21 June 1919; however, by the 20th, it had been extended to 23 June. There is some contention as to whether von Reuter was aware of this. Admiral Fremantle, the commander of the British fleet based in Scapa, stated that he informed von Reuter on the evening of the 20th, though von Reuter claims he was unaware of the development. For Fremantle's claim, see Bennett, p. 307. For von Reuter's statement, see Herwig, p. 256 The resulting scuttling of the German fleet saw some 66 vessels of various types sunk.Herwig, p. 256 Among those was ''Derfflinger'', which sank at 14:45. The ship was raised in 1939 to be broken up for scrap metal, but the outbreak of World War II intervened. The ship, which remained capsized, was anchored off the island of Risa until 1946, at which point she was sent to Faslane Port, where she was broken up. The ship's bell was delivered to the German Federal Navy on 30 August 1965.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="89880b232781783c7b1adeb4b14168f3" name="HMS_Queen_Mary_Jutland" sectnum="3.5#1">../img/89880b232781783c7b1adeb4b14168f3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>