<document id="038a69f549d1470199e92700231bb34b-3.6" name="Derfflinger_class_battlecruiser" cat="29">
<text>
was named after Ludwig Adolf Wilhelm von Lützow, a Prussian lieutenant-general who fought during the Napoleonic Wars. The ship was commissioned on 8 August 1915, and then underwent trials. On 25 October, while still running sea trials, ''Lützow''s port low pressure turbine were severely damaged. She was sent to Kiel for repairs, which lasted until late January 1916. The ship went on additional trials that lasted until 19 February. ''Lützow'' was by then fully operational, and assigned to the I Scouting Group on 20 March 1916. She took part in two fleet advances, on 25 March and 21&ndash;22 April, without any major incidents. The following day, on 23 April, ''Lützow'', along with her sister ''Derfflinger'' and the battlecruisers ''Seydlitz'', , and , bombarded Yarmouth. While en route to the target,  Vice Admiral Franz von Hipper's flagship ''Seydlitz'' was heavily damaged by mines. As a result, ''Lützow'' was transferred to the role of squadron flagship. During the operation, the German battlecruisers encountered British light forces, and a running battle ensued. ''Lützow'' engaged the light cruiser  and hit her several times.Staff, p. 40


At the Battle of Jutland, she was the first ship in the German line, and Hipper's flagship. Shortly after the start of the battlecruiser action, ''Lützow'' hit her opponent  several times; one hit knocked out ''Lion''s "Q" turret, and the resulting magazine fire nearly destroyed the ship.Only the quick action of Major Francis Harvey, who despite being mortally wounded ordered the magazine be flooded, prevented a flash fire. Shortly after 19:00, the armored cruisers  and  inadvertently ran into the German line; ''Lützow'' opened fire immediately, followed by several German dreadnoughts. In a hail of shells, ''Defence''s ammunition magazines detonated and the ship was sunk.Tarrant, pp. 138&ndash;140 At around the same time, the fresh battlecruisers of the III Battlecruiser Squadron engaged their German opposites. Between 19:26 and 19:34, ''Lützow'' sustained four 12-inch shell hits in her bow from the British battlecruisers; these eventually proved to be fatal. Despite this, at 19:30, ''Lützow'', along with her sister ''Derfflinger'', destroyed the battlecruiser ''Invincible''. By 20:15, ''Lützow'' had been hit five more times, including hits on her two forward turrets.Staff, p. 41

By 22:15, ''Lützow'' had shipped nearly 2,400 tons of water, and the ship was dangerously down by the bows. After midnight, attempts were made to steer the ship in reverse. This however failed when the bow became submerged enough to bring the stern out of the water; by 02:20, the screws and both rudders were coming out of the water and the ship was no longer able to steer. The order to abandon ship was given, and at 02:47, ''Lützow'' was sunk by the torpedo boat . The ship was lost because the flooding in the bow could not be controlled; the forward pump system failed and the central system could not keep up with the rising water. The crew was picked up by four torpedo boats that had been escorting the crippled battlecruiser; during the battle the ship suffered 116 men killed.Staff, p. 42
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7ec7bef91a89402ea4a2ccedf7a8df84" name="InvincibleBlowingUpJutland1916" sectnum="3.6#1">../img/7ec7bef91a89402ea4a2ccedf7a8df84.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>