<document id="040d81bab2d70218daac18a0e7bd61b2-5.5" name="Metacomet_Ridge" cat="11">
<text>
Although the Metacomet Ridge has abutted significant urban areas for nearly two hundred years, because of its rugged, steep, and rocky terrain, the ridge was long considered an undesirable place to build a home except for those wealthy enough to afford such a luxury. However, suburbanization through urban exodus and automobile culture, and modern construction techniques and equipment have created a demand for homes on and around the once undeveloped Metacomet Ridge and its surrounding exurban communities. As of 2007, the metropolitan areas bordering the range—New Haven, Meriden, New Britain, Hartford, Springfield and Greenfield—had a combined population of more than 2.5 million people. Populations in exurban towns around the range in Connecticut have increased 7.6 percent between the mid-1990s to 2000, and building permits increased 26 percent in the same period. Considered an attractive place to build homes because of its views and proximity to urban centers and highways, the Metacomet Ridge has become a target for both developers and advocates of land conservation. Quarrying, supported by the increased need for stone in local and regional construction projects, has been especially damaging to the ecosystem, public access, and visual landscape of the ridge. At the same time, the boom in interest in outdoor recreation in the latter 20th century has made the Metacomet Ridge an attractive "active leisure" resource. In response to public interest in the ridge and its surrounding landscapes, more than twenty local non-profit organizations have become involved in conservation efforts on and around the ridge and surrounding region. Most of these organizations came into being between 1970 and 2000, and nearly all of them have evidenced a marked increase in conservation activity since 1990.Regional examples include: , , , , , ,    
, and the . Organization websites. Retrieved December 21, 2007. Other examples provided in Wikipedia articles about specific summits in the range. Several international and national organizations have also become interested in the Metacomet Ridge, including The Nature Conservancy, the Sierra Club, and the Trust for Public Land. The Trust for Public Land. Retrieved December 23, 2007. The Nature Conservancy. Retrieved December 24, 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="99cd3b3424542620b3b98a7cd3ff68be" name="Suffield_Mountain_forsale" sectnum="5.5#1">../img/99cd3b3424542620b3b98a7cd3ff68be.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>