<document id="040d81bab2d70218daac18a0e7bd61b2-7" name="Metacomet_Ridge" cat="11">
<text>
Because of its narrowness, proximity to urban areas, and fragile ecosystems, the Metacomet Ridge is most endangered by encroaching suburban sprawl. Quarry operations, also a threat, have obliterated several square miles of traprock ridgeline in both Massachusetts and Connecticut. Ridges and mountains affected include Trimountain, Bradley Mountain, Totoket Mountain, Chauncey Peak, Rattlesnake Mountain, East Mountain, Pocumtuck Ridge, and the former Round Mountain of the Holyoke Range.''Google Earth.'' Satellite images of specified mountains. Google, inc. Retrieved December 7, 2007. The gigantic man-like profile of the Sleeping Giant, a traprock massif visible for more than  in south central Connecticut, bears quarrying scars on its "head". Mining there was halted by the efforts of local citizens and the Sleeping Giant Park Association.    

Development and quarrying threats to the Metacomet Ridge have resulted in public open space acquisition efforts through collective purchasing and fundraising, active solicitation of land donations, securing of conservation easements, protective and restrictive legislation agreements limiting development, and, in a few cases, land taking by eminent domain. The Trustees of Reservations. Retrieved November 28, 2007.  Recent conservation milestones include the acquisition of a defunct ski area on Mount Tom, the purchase of the ledges and summits of Ragged Mountain through the efforts of a local rock climbing club and the Nature Conservancy,. Retrieved December 7, 2007. and the inclusion of the ridgeline from North Branford, Connecticut to Belchertown, Massachusetts in a study by the National Park Service for a new National Scenic Trail now tentatively called the New England National Scenic Trail.. United States National Park Service. Retrieved November 4, 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ce124652274de7ba0e575e3e7565fe83" name="Round_Mountain_Quarry" sectnum="7#1">../img/ce124652274de7ba0e575e3e7565fe83.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>