<document id="040d81bab2d70218daac18a0e7bd61b2-4" name="Metacomet_Ridge" cat="11">
<text>
The Metacomet Ridge hosts a combination of microclimates unusual to the region. Dry, hot upper ridges support oak savannas, often dominated by chestnut oak and a variety of understory grasses and ferns. Eastern red cedar, a dry-loving species, clings to the barren edges of cliffs. Backslope plant communities tend to be similar to the adjacent upland plateaus and nearby Appalachians, containing species common to the northern hardwood and oak-hickory forest ecosystem types. Eastern hemlock crowds narrow ravines, blocking sunlight and creating damp, cooler growing conditions with associated cooler climate plant species. Talus slopes are especially rich in nutrients and support a number of calcium-loving plants uncommon in the region. Miles of high cliffs make ideal raptor habitat, and the Metacomet Ridge is a seasonal raptor migration corridor. Because the topography of the ridge offers such varied terrain, many species reach the northern or southern limit of their range on the Metacomet Ridge; others are considered rare nationally or globally. Examples of rare species that live on the ridge include the prickly pear cactus, peregrine falcon, northern copperhead, showy lady's slipper, yellow corydalis, ram’s–head lady's slipper, basil mountain mint, and devil's bit lilly. (Undated) The Mount Toby Partnership. Amherst, Massachusetts: University of Massachusetts Amherst. Retrieved November 30, 2007.

The Metacomet Ridge is also an important aquifer. It provides municipalities and towns with public drinking water; reservoirs are located on Talcott Mountain, Totoket Mountain, Saltonstall Mountain, Bradley Mountain, Ragged Mountain, and the Hanging Hills in Connecticut. Reservoirs that supply metropolitan Springfield, Massachusetts are located on Provin Mountain and East Mountain.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c9b89bb83aaa153a9ea522127aa8fa1a" name="Ram's-Head_Lady's-Slipper_(Cypripedium_arietinum)" sectnum="4#1">../img/c9b89bb83aaa153a9ea522127aa8fa1a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>