<document id="042bf8fe953f342bb97cbd5f25825c46-5.11" name="Sea_otter" cat="3">
<text>
Sea otters consume over 100 different prey species. In most of its range, the sea otter's diet consists almost exclusively of marine invertebrates, including sea urchins, a variety of bivalves such as clams and mussels, abalone, other mollusks, crustaceans, and snails. Its prey ranges in size from tiny limpets    crabs to giant octopuses.VanBlaricom pp. 18–29 Where prey such as sea urchins, clams, and abalone are present in a range of sizes, sea otters tend to select larger items over smaller ones of similar type. In California, it has been noted that sea otters ignore Pismo clams smaller than 3 inches (7 cm) across.Love, p. 96

In a few northern areas, fish are also eaten. In studies performed at Amchitka Island in the 1960s, where the sea otter population was at carrying capacity, 50% of food found in sea otter stomachs was fish.Kenyon, p. 121 The fish species were usually bottom-dwelling and sedentary or sluggish forms, such as ''Hemilepidotus hemilepidotus'' and family Tetraodontidae. However, south of Alaska on the North American coast, fish are a negligible or extremely minor part of the sea otter's diet.Love, p. 76 Contrary to popular depictions, sea otters rarely eat starfish, and any kelp that is consumed apparently passes through the sea otter's system undigested.Kenyon, p. 119

The individuals within a particular area often differ in their foraging methods and their prey types, and tend to follow the same patterns as their mothers.VanBlaricom, p. 29 The diet of local populations also changes over time, as sea otters can significantly deplete populations of highly preferred prey such as large sea urchins, and prey availability is also affected by other factors such as fishing by humans. Sea otters can thoroughly remove abalone from an area except for specimens in deep rock crevices,VanBlaricom, p. 30 however, they never completely wipe out a prey species from an area.Nickerson, p. 57 A 2007 California study demonstrated that in areas where food was relatively scarce, a wider variety of prey was consumed. However, surprisingly, the diets of individuals were more specialized in these areas than in areas where food was plentiful.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f4316cadfc055c7ecc22687b5bb34785" name="Kelp-forest-Monterey" sectnum="5.11#1">../img/f4316cadfc055c7ecc22687b5bb34785.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>