<document id="042bf8fe953f342bb97cbd5f25825c46-6.14" name="Sea_otter" cat="3">
<text>
Archaeological evidence indicates that for thousands of years, indigenous peoples have hunted sea otters for food and fur. Large-scale hunting, which would eventually kill approximately one million sea otters, began in the 1700s when hunters and traders began to arrive from all over the world to meet foreign demand for otter pelts, which were one of the world's most valuable types of fur.

In the early 1700s, Russians began to hunt sea otters in the Kuril Islands and sold them to China.Silverstein, p. 34 Russia was also exploring the far northern Pacific at this time, and sent Vitus Bering to map the Arctic coast and find routes from Siberia to North America. In 1741, on his second North Pacific voyage, Bering was shipwrecked off Bering Island in the Commander Islands, where Bering and many of his crew died. The surviving crew members, which included naturalist Georg Steller, discovered sea otters on the beaches of the island and spent the winter hunting sea otters and gambling with otter pelts. They returned to Siberia having killed nearly 1000 sea otters, and were able to command high prices for the pelts.Silverstein, p. 35 Thus began what is sometimes called the "Great Hunt", which would continue for another hundred years.

Russian fur-hunting expeditions soon depleted the sea otter populations in the Commander Islands, and by 1745 they began to move on to the Aleutian Islands. The Russians initially traded with the Aleuts inhabitants of these islands for otter pelts, but later enslaved the Aleuts, taking women and children hostage and torturing and killing Aleut men to force them to hunt. Many Aleuts were either murdered by the Russians or died from diseases that the hunters had introduced. The Aleut population was reduced, by the Russians' own estimate, from 20,000 to 2,000. By the 1760s, the Russians had reached Alaska. In 1799, Emperor Paul I consolidated the rival fur hunting companies into the Russian-American Company, granting it an Imperial charter and protection, and a monopoly over trade rights and territorial acquisition.
Under Aleksandr I the administration of the merchant-controlled Company was transferred to the Imperial Navy, largely due to the alarming reports by naval officers of native abuse, and in 1818 the indigenous peoples of Alaska were granted civil rights equivalent to a townsman status in the Russian Empire.Middleton, pg.8, 
Other nations joined in the hunt in the south. Along the coasts of what is now Mexico and California, Spanish explorers bought sea otter pelts from Native Americans and sold them in Asia.Silverstein, p. 37 In 1778, British explorer Captain James Cook reached Vancouver Island and bought sea otter furs from the First Nations people.Silverstein, p. 38 When Cook's ship later stopped at a Chinese port, the  pelts rapidly sold at high prices, and were soon known as "soft gold". As word spread, people from all over Europe and North America  began to arrive in the Pacific Northwest to trade for sea otter furs.

Russian hunting expanded to the south, initiated by American ship captains, who sub-contracted Russian supervisors and Aleut hunters Farris, pg.21, in what is now Washington, Oregon, and California. Between 1803-1846 72 American ships were involved in the otter hunt in California,harvesting an estimated 40,000 skins and tails, compared to only 13 ships of the Russian-American Company, which reported 5,696 otter skins taken between 1806-1846Mathes, pg.326,. In 1812 the Russians founded an agricultural settlement at what is now Fort Ross  in northern California  as their southern headquarters.  
Eventually, sea otter populations became so depleted that commercial hunting was no longer viable. In the Aleutian Islands, commercial hunting had stopped by 1808, as a conservation measure imposed by the Russian-American Company.Middleton, pg.4 Further restrictions were ordered by the Company in 1834.Middleton, pg.4 When Russia sold Alaska to the United States in 1867, the Alaska population had recovered to over 100,000, but Americans resumed hunting and quickly extirpated the sea otter again.Silverstein, p. 40 Prices rose as the species became rare: During the 1880s, a pelt brought $105 to $165 in the London market, however by 1903 a pelt could be worth as much as $1,125. In 1911, Russia, Japan, Great Britain (for Canada) and the United States signed the Treaty for the Preservation and Protection of Fur Seals, imposing a moratorium on the harvesting of sea otters.VanBlaricom, p. 50 So few remained, perhaps only 1,000–2,000 individuals in the wild, that many believed the species would become extinct.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="91021ccc188dd9a3644a3ea08ffb923f" name="Sea_otter_hunters_1896" sectnum="6.14#1">../img/91021ccc188dd9a3644a3ea08ffb923f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>