<document id="048a135264054d9c6829f8e4157397aa-10" name="Anna_May_Wong" cat="19">
<text>
Wong's image and career have left a lasting legacy. Through her films, public appearances, and prominent magazine features, she helped to "humanize" Asian-Americans to white audiences during a period of overt racism and discrimination. Asian-Americans, especially the Chinese, had been viewed as perpetually foreign in U.S. society, but Wong's films and public image established her firmly as an Asian-American citizen at a time when laws specifically discriminated against Asian immigration and citizenship. Wong's hybrid image dispelled contemporary notions that the East and West were inherently different.Lim 2005, pp. 49–51.

Among Wong's films, only ''Shanghai Express'' retained critical attention in the U.S. in the decades after her death. In Europe, and especially England, her films appeared occasionally at festivals. Wong remained popular with the gay community who often claimed her as one of their own, and for whom her marginalization by the mainstream became a symbol.Hodges 2004, p. 232. Although the Chinese Nationalist criticism of her portrayals of the "Dragon Lady" and "Butterfly" stereotypes lingered, Wong herself was forgotten in China.Hodges 2004, pp. 231–232. Nevertheless, the importance of Wong's legacy within the Asian-American film community can be seen in the Anna May Wong Award of Excellence which is given out yearly at the Asian-American Arts Awards;Chan 2003, p. 276. the annual award given out by the Asian Fashion Designers was also named after Wong in 1973.

For decades following her death, Wong's image remained as a symbol in literature, as well as in film. In the 1971 poem "The Death of Anna May Wong", Jessica Hagedorn saw Wong's career as one of "tragic glamour", and portrayed the actress as a "fragile maternal presence, an Asian-American woman who managed to 'birth,' however ambivalently, Asian-American screen women in the jazz age".Liu 2000, p. 35.  Wong's character in ''Shanghai Express'' was the subject of John Yau's 1989 poem "No One Ever Tried to Kiss Anna May Wong", which interprets the actress' career as a series of tragic romances.Liu 2000, pp. 31–33. In David Cronenberg's 1993 film version of David Henry Hwang's 1986 play, ''M. Butterfly'', Wong's image was used briefly as a symbol of a "tragic diva".Liu 2000, pp. 34–35. Her life was the subject of ''China Doll, The Imagined Life of an American Actress'', an award-winning fictional play written by Elizabeth Wong in 2005.Wong 2005.

As the centennial of Wong's birth approached, a re-examination of her life and career took shape; three major works on the actress appeared, and comprehensive retrospectives of her films were held at both the Museum of Modern Art and the American Museum of the Moving Image in New York City.''Performing Race on Screen''. Anthony Chan's 2003 biography, ''Perpetually Cool: The Many Lives of Anna May Wong (1905–1961)'', was the first major work on Wong, and was written, Chan says, "from a uniquely Asian-American perspective and sensibility".Chan 2003, p. xvii. In 2004, Philip Leibfried and Chei Mi Lane's exhaustive examination of Wong's career, ''Anna May Wong: A Complete Guide to Her Film, Stage, Radio and Television Work'' was published, as well as a second full-length biography, ''Anna May Wong: From Laundryman's Daughter to Hollywood Legend'' by Graham Russell Hodges. Though Anna May Wong's life, career, and legacy reflect many complex issues which remain decades after her death, Anthony Chan points out that her place in Asian-American cinematic history, as its first female star, is permanent.Chan 2003, p. 275.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c6146bfbb015b65ea2e69cc879e79ea2" name="AnnaMayWong" sectnum="10#1">../img/c6146bfbb015b65ea2e69cc879e79ea2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>