<document id="048a135264054d9c6829f8e4157397aa-2" name="Anna_May_Wong" cat="19">
<text>
Wong was working at Hollywood's Ville de Paris department store when Metro Pictures needed 300 girl extras to appear in Alla Nazimova's film ''The Red Lantern'' (1919). Without her father's knowledge, a friend of his with movie connections helped Anna May land an uncredited role as an extra carrying a lantern.Chan 2003, p. 31.

She worked steadily for the next two years as an extra in various movies, including Priscilla Dean and Colleen Moore pictures. While still a student, Wong came down with an illness identified as St. Vitus's Dance which caused her to miss months of school. She was on the verge of emotional collapse when her father took her to a practitioner of traditional Chinese medicine. The treatments proved successful, though Wong later claimed this had more to do with her dislike of the methods.Hodges 2004, pp. 26–27. Other Chinese thought such as Confucianism and particularly Taoism and the teachings of Laozi had a strong influence on Wong's personal philosophy throughout her life.Chan 2003, pp. 145–146. The family's religious life also included Christian thought, in the form of Presbyterianism, and as an adult she was a Christian Scientist for some time.Hodges 2004, p. 225.

Finding it difficult to keep up with both her schoolwork and her passion, she dropped out of Los Angeles High School in 1921 to pursue a full-time acting career.Lim 2005, p. 51.Hodges 2004, p. 41. Reflecting on her decision, Wong told ''Motion Picture Magazine'' in 1931: "I was so young when I began that I knew I still had youth if I failed, so I determined to give myself 10 years to succeed as an actress."Wollstein 1999, p. 249.

In 1921, Wong received her first screen credit for ''Bits of Life'', the first anthology film, in which she played the wife of Lon Chaney's character, Toy Ling, in a segment entitled "Hop".Gan 1995, p. 84. She later recalled it fondly as the only time she played the role of a mother;Hodges 2004, p. 35. her appearance earned her a cover photo in the British magazine ''Picture Show''.

At the age of 17 she played her first leading role, in the early Metro two-strip Technicolor movie ''The Toll of the Sea''. Written by Frances Marion, the story was based loosely on ''Madama Butterfly''. ''Variety'' magazine singled Wong out for praise, noting her "extraordinarily fine" acting.''The Toll of the Sea'' (film review) December 1, 1922. ''The New York Times''  commented, "Miss Wong stirs in the spectator all the sympathy her part calls for, and she never repels one by an excess of theatrical 'feeling'. She has a difficult role, a role that is botched nine times out of ten, but hers is the tenth performance. Completely unconscious of the camera, with a fine sense of proportion and remarkable pantomimic accuracy ... She should be seen again and often on the screen."''The Toll of the Sea'' (film review) November 27, 1922.

Despite such reviews, Hollywood proved reluctant to create starring roles for Wong; her ethnicity prevented U.S. filmmakers from seeing her as a leading lady. David Schwartz, the chief curator of the Museum of the Moving Image, notes, "She built up a level of stardom in Hollywood, but Hollywood didn’t know what to do with her."Anderson, Melissa.  ''Time Out: New York'', Issue 544: March 2–8, 2006, TimeOut. Retrieved: March 24, 2008. She spent the next few years in supporting roles providing "exotic atmosphere",Parish 1976, pp. 532–533. for instance playing a concubine in Tod Browning's ''Drifting'' (1923). Film producers capitalized on Wong's growing fame by using her brief appearances in these supporting roles to promote their films.Hodges 2004, p. 58. Still optimistic about a film career, in 1923 Wong said: "Pictures are fine, and I'm getting along all right, but it's not so bad to have the laundry back of you, so you can wait and take good parts and be independent when you're climbing."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1459323a2e1451119bab460d8dfbcf67" name="Anna_May_Wong_as_Lotus_Flower_calling_out_in_The_Toll_of_the_Sea" sectnum="2#1">../img/1459323a2e1451119bab460d8dfbcf67.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>