<document id="048a135264054d9c6829f8e4157397aa-8" name="Anna_May_Wong" cat="19">
<text>
To complete her contract with Paramount Pictures, Wong made a string of B movies in the late 1930s. Often dismissed by critics, the films gave Wong non-stereotypical roles which were publicized in the Chinese-American press for their positive images. These smaller-budgeted films could be bolder than the higher-profile releases, and Wong used this to her advantage to portray successful, professional, Chinese-American characters. Competent and proud of their Chinese heritage, these roles worked against the prevailing U.S. film portrayals of Chinese-Americans.Lim 2005, pp. 47, 63, 67. In contrast to the usual official Chinese condemnation of Wong's film roles, the Chinese consul to Los Angeles gave his approval to the final scripts of two of these films, ''Daughter of Shanghai'' (1937) and ''King of Chinatown'' (1939).Leong 2005, p. 94.


In ''Daughter of Shanghai'', Wong played the Asian-American female lead in a role that was rewritten for her as the heroine of the story, actively setting the plot into motion rather than the more passive character originally planned.Lim 2005, p. 66. The script was so carefully tailored for Wong that at one point it was titled, ''Anna May Wong Story''. Of this film, Wong told ''Hollywood Magazine'', "I like my part in this picture better than any I've had before ... because this picture gives Chinese a break – we have sympathetic parts for a change! To me that means a great deal."Leung, Louise. "East Meets West", ''Hollywood Magazine'', June 1938, pp. 40, 55. Quoted in Leong 2005, p. 94. ''The New York Times'' gave the film a generally positive review, commenting of its B-movie origins, "An unusually competent cast saves the film from the worst consequences of certain inevitable banalities.  ... combine with effective sets to reduce the natural odds against any pictures in the ''Daughter of Shanghai'' tradition."Crisler 1937. In October 1937, the press carried rumors that Wong had plans to marry her male co-star in this film, childhood friend  and Korean-American actor Philip Ahn. Wong replied, "It would be like marrying my brother."Wollstein 1999, p. 256.

Bosley Crowther was not so kind to ''Dangerous to Know'' (1938), which he called a "second-rate melodrama, hardly worthy of the talents of its generally capable cast".Crowther 1938. In ''King of Chinatown'' Wong played a surgeon who sacrifices a high-paying promotion in order to devote her energies to helping the Chinese fight the Japanese invasion.Lim 2005, p. 47. ''The New York Times''' Frank Nugent gave the film a negative review. Though he commented positively on its advocacy of the Chinese in their fight against Japan, he wrote, "... Paramount should have spared us and its cast ... the necessity of being bothered with such folderol".Nugent 1939.

Paramount also employed Wong as a tutor to other actors, such as Dorothy Lamour in her role as a Eurasian in ''Disputed Passage''. Wong performed on radio several times, including a 1939 role as "Peony" in Pearl Buck's ''The Patriot'' on Orson Welles' ''The Campbell Playhouse''.Hodges 2004, p. 191. Wong's cabaret act, which included songs in Cantonese, French, English, German, Danish, Swedish, and other languages, took her from the U.S. to Europe and Australia through the 1930s and 1940s.Corliss January 29, 2005, p. 1.

In 1938, having auctioned off her movie costumes and donated the money to Chinese aid, the Chinese Benevolent Association of California honored Wong for her work in support of Chinese refugees.Leong 2005, p. 95. The proceeds from the preface that she wrote in 1942 to a cookbook titled ''New Chinese Recipes'', one of the first Chinese cookbooks, were also dedicated to United China Relief.Hodges 2004, p. 203. Between 1939 and 1942, she made few films, instead engaging in events and appearances in support of the Chinese struggle against Japan.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="048a135264054d9c6829f8e4157397aa" name="Anna_May_Wong" sectnum="8#1">../img/048a135264054d9c6829f8e4157397aa.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>