<document id="048a135264054d9c6829f8e4157397aa-5" name="Anna_May_Wong" cat="19">
<text>
During the 1930s, American studios were looking for fresh European talent. Ironically, Wong caught their eye and she was offered a contract with Paramount Studios in 1930. Enticed by the promise of lead roles and top billing, she returned to the United States.  The prestige and training she had gained during her years in Europe led to a starring role on Broadway in ''On the Spot'',Lim 2005, p. 56. a drama that ran for 167 performances and which she would later film as ''Dangerous to Know''.Hodges 2004, p. 187. When the play's director wanted Wong to use stereotypical Japanese mannerisms, derived from ''Madame Butterfly'', in her performance of a Chinese character, Wong refused. She instead used her knowledge of Chinese style and gestures to imbue the character with a greater degree of authenticity.Lim 2005, p. 57. Following her return to Hollywood in 1930, Wong repeatedly turned to the stage and cabaret for a creative outlet.

In November 1930, Anna May's mother was run over and killed by an automobile in front of the Figueroa Street house.Hodges 2004, p. 112. The family remained at the house until 1934, when Wong's father returned to his hometown in China with Anna May's younger brothers and sister.Chan 2003, p. 90. Anna May had been paying for the education of her younger siblings, who put their education to work after they relocated to China.Hodges 2004, p. 155. Before the family left, Wong's father wrote a brief article for ''Xinning'', a magazine for overseas Taishanese, in which he expressed his pride in his famous daughter.Hodges 2004, p. 148.

With the promise of appearing in a Josef von Sternberg film, Wong accepted another stereotypical role – the title character of Fu Manchu's vengeful daughter in ''Daughter of the Dragon'' (1931).Wollstein 1999, p. 253. This was the last stereotypically "evil Chinese" role Wong played,Lim 2005, p. 59. and also her one starring appearance alongside the only other well-known Asian actor of the era, Sessue Hayakawa. Though she was given the starring role, this status was not reflected in her paycheck: she was paid $6,000, while Hayakawa received $10,000 and Warner Oland, who is only in the film for 23 minutes, was paid $12,000.Corliss February 3, 2005, p. 4.

Wong began using her newfound celebrity to make political statements: late in 1931, for example, she wrote a harsh criticism of the Mukden Incident and Japan's subsequent invasion of Manchuria.Hodges 2004, p. 118.Chan 2003, pp. 95–96. She also became more outspoken in her advocacy for Chinese-American causes and for better film roles. In a 1933 interview for ''Film Weekly'' entitled "I Protest", Wong criticized the negative stereotyping in ''Daughter of the Dragon'', saying, "Why is it that the screen Chinese is always the villain? And so crude a villain – murderous, treacherous, a snake in the grass! We are not like that. How could we be, with a civilization that is so many times older than the West?"Lim 2005, p. 58.


Wong appeared alongside Marlene Dietrich as a self-sacrificing courtesan in Sternberg's ''Shanghai Express''. Her sexually charged scenes with Dietrich have been noted by many commentators, and fed rumors about the relationship between the two stars.Chan 2003, p. 232. Though contemporary reviews focused on Dietrich's acting and Sternberg's direction, film historians today judge that Wong's performance upstaged that of Dietrich.Lim 2005, p. 60.

The Chinese press had long given Wong's career very mixed reviews, and were less than favorable to her performance in ''Shanghai Express''. A Chinese newspaper ran the headline: "Paramount Utilizes Anna May Wong to Produce Picture to Disgrace China", and continued, "Although she is deficient in artistic portrayal, she has done more than enough to disgrace the Chinese race."Leong 2005, p. 74. Critics in China believed that Wong's on-screen sexuality spread negative stereotypes of Chinese women.Leong 2005, p. 75. The most virulent criticism came from the Nationalist government, but China's intellectuals and liberals were not always so opposed to Wong, as demonstrated when Peking University awarded the actress an honorary doctorate in 1932. Contemporary sources reported that this was probably the only time that an actor had been so honored.''Mein Film'' 1932, p. 333. Cited in Hodges 2004, p. 125.

In both America and Europe, Wong had been seen as a fashion icon for over a decade. In 1934, the Mayfair Mannequin Society of New York voted her "The World's best-dressed woman", and in 1938 ''Look'' magazine named her "The World's most beautiful Chinese girl".Chan 2003, p. 33.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1b17b01220f43e440d015fe78ceff5d6" name="Anna_May_Wong_Shanghai_Express" sectnum="5#1">../img/1b17b01220f43e440d015fe78ceff5d6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>