<document id="048a135264054d9c6829f8e4157397aa-6" name="Anna_May_Wong" cat="19">
<text>
After her success in Europe and prominent role in ''Shanghai Express'', Wong's Hollywood career returned to its old pattern. Because of the Hays Office's anti-miscegenation rules, she was passed over for the leading female role in ''The Son-Daughter'' in favor of Helen Hayes in yellowface. Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer deemed her "too Chinese to play a Chinese" in the film,Hodges 2004, p. 128. and the Hays Office would not have allowed her to perform romantic scenes with the film's male lead, Ramon Navarro in yellowface. Wong was scheduled to play the role of a mistress to a corrupt Chinese general in Frank Capra's ''The Bitter Tea of General Yen'' (1933), but the role went instead to Toshia Mori.Hodges 2004, pp. 127–128.


Again disappointed with Hollywood, Wong returned to Britain, where she stayed for nearly three years. In addition to appearing in four films she toured Scotland, Ireland, and outlying British provinces as part of a vaudeville show. She also appeared in the King George Silver Jubilee program in 1935.Gan 1995, p. 89. Her film ''Java Head'' (1934), though generally considered a minor effort, was the only film in which Wong kissed the lead male character, her white husband in the film. Wong's biographer, Graham Russell Hodges, commented that this may be why the film remained one of Wong's personal favorites.Hodges 2004, pp. 144, 217. While in London, Wong met Mei Lanfang, one of the most famous stars of the Beijing Opera. She had long been interested in Chinese opera and Mei offered to instruct Wong if she ever visited China.Hodges 2004, pp. 150, 155.

In the 1930s, the popularity of Pearl Buck's novels, especially ''The Good Earth'', as well as growing American sympathy for China in its struggles with Japanese Imperialism, opened up opportunities for more positive Chinese roles in U.S. films.Leong 2005, pp. 75, 94. Wong returned to the U.S. in June 1935 with the goal of obtaining the role of O-lan, the lead female character in MGM's film version of ''The Good Earth''. Since its publication in 1931, Wong had made known her desire to play O-lan in a film version of the book;Hodges 2004, pp. 150–151. and as early as 1933, Los Angeles newspapers were touting Wong as the best choice for the part.Hodges 2004, p. 152. Nevertheless, the studio apparently never seriously considered Wong for the role because Paul Muni, an actor of European descent, was to employ yellowface to play O-lan's husband, Wang Lung. The Chinese government also advised the studio against casting Wong in the role. The Chinese advisor to MGM commented: "whenever she appears in a movie, the newspapers print her picture with the caption 'Anna May again loses face for China' ".Hodges 2004, p. 151.

According to Wong, she was instead offered the part of Lotus, a deceitful song girl who helps to destroy the family and seduces the family's oldest son.Leong 2005, p. 76. Wong refused the role, telling MGM head of production Irving Thalberg, "If you let me play O-lan, I will be very glad. But you're asking me – with Chinese blood – to do the only unsympathetic role in the picture featuring an all-American cast portraying Chinese characters." The role Wong hoped for went to Luise Rainer, who won the Best Actress Oscar for her performance. Wong's sister, Mary Liu Heung Wong, appeared in the film in the role of the Little Bride.Chan 2003, p. 261. MGM's refusal to consider Wong for this most high-profile of Chinese characters in U.S. film is remembered today as "one of the most notorious cases of casting discrimination in the 1930s".Berry 2000, p. 111.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="59db8464788212ccbc2ee9d6d7e85886" name="AnnaMayWong2" sectnum="6#1">../img/59db8464788212ccbc2ee9d6d7e85886.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>