<document id="04bf7084ba862f29153267e920830d92-3.1" name="Fred_Moosally" cat="29">
<text>
On May 23, 1988, Moosally took command of ''Iowa'' at Norfolk, Virginia. Reportedly, Moosally favored ''Iowa's'' missile and engineering systems and deemphasized 16-inch gunnery. A week after taking command, Moosally and his executive officer, Mike Fahey, canceled a planned one million dollar repair package for ''Iowa's'' main gun batteries, including repairs to the main gun turrets' lighting, electrical, powder hoists, and hydraulic systems; seventy-five detailed deficiencies in all. Instead, the funds were spent on overhauling the ship's powerplant.Schwoebel p. 259, Thompson pp. 46–47. One of the deficiencies needing repairs was the sprinkler system in Turret 2, including the ones in the powder magazines, intended to help put out any propellant fires, were inoperable.

After completion of the overhaul, according to Thompson, Moosally took ''Iowa'' on a shakedown cruise around Chesapeake Bay on August 25, 1988. Encountering difficulty in conning the ship through shallow water, ''Iowa'', with Moosally at the helm, narrowly missed colliding with the frigates USS ''Moinster'' and ''Farragut'' and the cruiser ''South Carolina'' before, Thompson claims, running aground in soft mud outside the bay's main ship channel near the Thimble Shoals. After one hour, ''Iowa'' was able to extricate herself without damage and return to port. Although other US Navy vessels observed ''Iowa'' grounded in the mud, the incident apparently was not acted upon by Moosally's superiors.Thompson, pp. 58–60. According to Thompson, the near-misses with the other navy ships were recorded in ''Iowa's'' log as attempts to "render honors" to them. Mike Fahey, the ship's executive officer, warned the other officers on ''Iowa'' to never mention the grounding to anyone, including superior Navy officers. Throughout August and September, ''Iowa'' continued with sea trials, then began refresher training in the waters around Florida and Puerto Rico in October.Thompson, pp. 65–67.

Thompson states that between September 1988 and January 1989, ''Iowa's'' crew did not conduct much training with the 16-inch guns, in part because of ongoing, serious maintenance issues with the main gun turrets. According to Ensign Dan Meyer, officer in charge of the ship's Turret One, morale and operational readiness among the gun turret crews suffered greatly. In spite of the problems with the main gun turrets, the ship passed its Operation Propulsion Program Evaluation in October 1989.Thompson, pp. 67–69.Vistica p. 289
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5fc145bf8ddad89f63aecae0944c4eba" name="BB61_USS_Iowa_BB61_broadside_USN" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/5fc145bf8ddad89f63aecae0944c4eba.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>