<document id="058a209eb073b5ee7c24a5c99d3efb9d-3.4" name="Operation_Cobra" cat="29">
<text>
By 28 July the German defenses across the US front had largely collapsed under the full weight of VII and VIII Corps' advance, and resistance was disorganised and patchy. VIII Corps' 4th Armored Division, entering combat for the first time, captured Coutances but met stiff opposition east of the town, and US units penetrating into the depth of the German positions were variously counterattacked by elements of the 2nd SS Panzer (Das Reich), 17th SS Panzergrenadier, and 353rd Infantry Divisions, all seeking to escape entrapment.Hastings, p. 260 A desperate counterattack was mounted against the 2nd Armored Division by German remnants, but this was a disaster and the Germans abandoned their vehicles and fled on foot. An exhausted and demoralized Bayerlein reported that his Panzer Lehr Division was "finally annihilated", with its armor wiped out, its personnel either casualties or missing, and all headquarters records lost. 

Meanwhile Marshal von Kluge, commanding all German forces on the Western Front (''Oberbefehlshaber West''), was mustering reinforcements, and elements of the 2nd and 116th Panzer Divisions were approaching the battlefield. The US XIX Corps, led by Major General Charles H. Corlett, entered the battle on 28 July on the left of VII Corps, and between 28 and 31 July became embroiled with these reinforcements in what would be the fiercest fighting since Cobra began.Hastings, p. 261 When ordered to concentrate his division, Colonel Heinz Günther Guderian, 116th Division's senior staff officer, was frustrated by the high level of Allied fighter-bomber activity. Without receiving direct support from 2nd Panzer as promised, Guderian stated that his panzergrenadiers could not successfully counterattack the Americans.Hastings, p. 263

During the night of 29 July near Saint-Denis-le-Gast, in the afore-mentioned action to the east of Coutances, elements of the US 2nd Armored Division found themselves fighting for their lives against a German column from the 2nd SS Panzer and 17th SS Panzergrenadier Divisions, which passed through the American lines in the darkness. Other elements of 2nd Armored were attacked near Cambry and fought for six hours; however, Bradley and his commanders knew that they were currently dominating the battlefield, and such desperate assaults were not a genuine threat to the American position. On 30 July, to protect Cobra's flank and prevent the disengagement and relocation of further German forces, the British VIII Corps launched Operation Bluecoat south from Caumont towards Vire and Mont Pinçon.Hastings, p. 265 Advancing southwards along the coast, later that day the US VIII Corps seized the town of Avranches&mdash;described by historian Andrew Williams as "the gateway to Brittany and southern Normandy"Williams, p. 185&mdash;and by 31 July XIX Corps had thrown back the last German counterattacks after fierce fighting, inflicting heavy losses in men and tanks.Hastings, p. 262 The American advance was now relentless, and the First Army was finally free of the bocage.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8de51354328fdc34d20e4f3bc49b6493" name="Coutances" sectnum="3.4#1">../img/8de51354328fdc34d20e4f3bc49b6493.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>