<document id="058a209eb073b5ee7c24a5c99d3efb9d-4" name="Operation_Cobra" cat="29">
<text>
At noon on 1 August, the US Third Army was activated under the command of Lieutenant General George S. Patton. Lieutenant General Courtney Hodges assumed command of the First Army, and Bradley was promoted to overall command of both armies, designated 12th Army Group.Hastings, p. 266 Patton wrote a poem containing the words:


The US advance following Cobra was rapid. By 8 August the city of Le Mans, the former headquarters of the German 7th Army, had fallen to the Americans,Williams, p. 194 and Patton's VIII Corps had swept through Avranches and over the bridge at Pontaubault into Brittany.Hastings, p. 280 The German army in Normandy had been reduced to such a poor state by the Allied offensives that, with no prospect of reinforcement in the wake of the Soviet summer offensive against Army Group Centre, very few Germans believed they could now avoid defeat.Hastings, p. 277 However, rather than order his remaining forces to withdraw to the Seine, Adolf Hitler sent a directive to von Kluge demanding "an immediate counterattack between Mortain and Avranches"D'Este, p. 414 to "annihilate" the enemy and make contact with the west coast of the Cotentin peninsula.Williams, p. 196 Eight of the nine Panzer divisions in Normandy were to be used in the attack, but only four (one of them incomplete) could be relieved from their defensive tasks and assembled in time.Wilmot, p.401 German commanders immediately protested that such an operation was impossible given their remaining resources, but these objections were over-ridden and the counter-offensive, codenamed Operation Lüttich, commenced on 7 August around Mortain.Hastings, p. 283 The 2nd, 1st SS and 2nd SS Panzer Divisions led the assault, although with only 75 Mk IV and 70 Panther tanks, and 32 self-propelled guns, between them.Hastings, p. 285 Hopelessly optimistic, the offensive was essentially over within 24 hours, although fighting continued until 13 August.Hastings, p. 286

With von Kluge's few remaining battleworthy formations destroyed by the First Army, Allied command realised that the entire German position in Normandy was collapsing. Bradley declared: "This is an opportunity that comes to a commander not more than once in a century. We're about to destroy an entire hostile army and go all the way from here to the German border".Williams, p. 197 On 14 August, in conjunction with American movements northwards to Chambois, Canadian forces launched Operation Tractable&mdash;the Allied intention was to trap and destroy the entire German Seventh and Fifth Panzer Armies near the town of Falaise.Hastings, p. 301 Five days later the two arms of the encirclement were almost complete; the advancing US 90th Infantry Division had made contact with the Polish 1st Armoured Division, and the first Allied units crossed the Seine at Mantes Gassicourt while German units were fleeing eastwards by any means they could find.Williams, p. 203 By 22 August the Falaise Pocket, which the Germans had been fighting desperately to keep open to allow their trapped forces to escape, was finally sealed, effectively ending the Battle of Normandy with a decisive Allied victory.Bercuson, p. 232 All German forces west of the Allied lines were now dead or in captivity,Hastings, p. 306 and although perhaps 100,000 German troops succeeded in escaping they left behind 40,000–50,000 prisoners and over 10,000 dead. A total of 344 tanks and self-propelled guns, 2,447 soft-skinned vehicles and 252 artillery pieces were found abandoned or destroyed in the northern sector of the pocket alone.Hastings, p. 313 The Allies were now able to advance freely through undefended territory, and by 25 August all four Allied armies (1st Canadian, 2nd British, 1st US, and 3rd US) involved in the Normandy campaign were on the river Seine.Williams, p. 204
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6b462e56e64f8dc1bbe51f56de379c30" name="Normandybreakout" sectnum="4#1">../img/6b462e56e64f8dc1bbe51f56de379c30.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>