<document id="058a209eb073b5ee7c24a5c99d3efb9d-2" name="Operation_Cobra" cat="29">
<text>
According to Montgomery's official biographer, the foundation of Operation Cobra was laid on 13 June.Williams, p. 126 Montgomery's plan at that time called for Bradley's First Army to take Saint-L么 and Coutances and then make two southward thrusts; one from Caumont towards Vire and Mortain, and the other from Saint-L么 towards Villedieu and Avranches. Although pressure was to be kept up along the Cotentin Peninsula towards La Haye-du-Puits and Valognes, the capture of Cherbourg was not an immediate priority. However, with Cherbourg's seizure by Collins' VII Corps on 27 June Montgomery's initial timetable was soon outdated and the thrust from Caumont was never adopted.Esposito, p.78-80

Following the conclusion of Operation Charnwood and the cancellation of First Army's offensive towards Saint-L么,Wilmot, p. 351Greiss, p. 311 Montgomery met with Bradley and Dempsey on 10 July to discuss 21st Army Group's next move.Trew, p. 49 During the meeting Bradley admitted that progress on the western flank was very slow. However, he had been working on plans for a breakout attempt, codenamed Operation Cobra, to be launched by the First Army on 18 July.Blumenson, p. 187Zaloga, p.32D'Este, p.338Weigley, p.136Pogue, p.197Williams, p. 175 He presented his ideas to Montgomery,Bradley, p. 272 who approved, and the directive that emerged from the meeting made it clear that the overall strategy over the coming days would be to draw enemy attention away from the First Army to the British and Canadian sector; Dempsey was instructed to "go on hitting: drawing the German strength, especially the armour, onto yourself - so as to ease the way for Brad". To accomplish this, Operation Goodwood was planned,Trew, p. 64 and Eisenhower ensured that both operations would have the support of the Allied air forces with their strategic bombers.


On 12 July, Bradley briefed his subordinate commanders on the Cobra plan, which consisted of three phases. The main effort would be under the control of Collins' VII Corps. In the first phase, the breakthrough attack would be conducted by Major General Eddy's 9th and Major General Hobbs' 30th infantry divisions, which would punch a hole in the German tactical zone and then hold the flanks of the penetration while Major General Huebner's 1st Infantry and Major General Brooks' 2nd Armored divisions pushed into the depth of the position until resistance collapsed. During the second phase, an exploitation force of 5&ndash;6 divisions would pass through the opening created in the German defenses and swing west.Hastings, p. 250 If these two phases were successful the western German position would become untenable, and the third phase would permit a relatively easy advance to the southwest end of the bocage to cut off and seize the Brittany peninsula.Esposito, pp. 76&ndash;77 First Army's intelligence estimated that no German counterattack would occur in the first few days after Cobra's launch, and that if attacks materialized after that date, they would consist of no more than battalion-sized operations.

Cobra was to be a concentrated attack on a  front, unlike previous American 'broad front' offensives, and would have heavy air support.Hastings, pp. 249&ndash;250 Fighter-bombers would concentrate on hitting forward German defenses in a  belt immediately south of the Saint-L么&ndash;Periers road, while General Spaatz's heavy bombers would bomb to a depth of  behind the German main line of resistance.Williams, p. 181  It was anticipated that the physical destruction and shock value of a short, intense preliminary bombardment would greatly weaken the German defense, so in addition to divisional artillery, Army- and Corps-level units would provide support, including nine heavy, five medium, and seven light artillery battalions. Over one thousand tubes of divisional and corps artillery were committed to the offensive,Weigley, p. 151 and approximately 140,000 artillery rounds were allocated to the operation in VII Corps alone, with another 27,000 for VIII Corps.Griess, p. 324 Blumenson, p. 219

In an attempt to overcome the mobility constraints of the bocage that had made offensive operations so difficult and costly for both sides, "Rhino" modifications were made to some M4 Sherman and M5A1 Stuart tanks, and M10 tank destroyers, by fitting them with hedge-breaching 'tusks' that were capable of forcing a path through the Norman hedgerows.Hastings, p. 252 While German tanks remained restricted to the roads, US armor would now be able to maneuver more freely, although in practice these devices were not as effective as often believed.Zaloga, p.3 However, by the eve of Cobra sixty percent of First Army's tanks were so equipped.Weigley, p.149 To preserve operational security, Bradley forbade their use until Cobra was launched. Blumenson, p.207 In all 1,269 M4 medium tanks, 694 M5A1 light tanks, and 288 M10 tank destroyers were available.Zaloga, p.30
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9334d94451aa9990cd808a42e79d2f4e" name="Saint_Lo_and_Vicinity" sectnum="2#1">../img/9334d94451aa9990cd808a42e79d2f4e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>