<document id="058a209eb073b5ee7c24a5c99d3efb9d-2.1" name="Operation_Cobra" cat="29">
<text>
On 18 July the British VIII and I Corps, to the east of Caen, launched Operation Goodwood. The offensive began with the largest air bombardment in support of ground forces yet, with more than a thousand aircraft dropping 6,000 tons of high explosive and fragmentation bombs from low altitude.Williams, p. 161 German positions to the east of Caen were shelled by 400 artillery pieces, and many villages were reduced to rubble, but German artillery further to the south, on the Bourguébus Ridge, was outside the range of the British artillery,Williams, p. 165 and the defenders of Cagny and Emieville were largely unscathed by the bombardment.Williams, p. 167 This contributed to the losses suffered by Second Army, which sustained over 4,800 casualties. Principally an armored offensive, between 250 and 400 British tanks were put out of action, although recent examination suggests that only 140 were completely destroyed with an additional 174 damaged.Trew, pp. 97&ndash;98 The operation remains the largest tank battle ever fought by the British Army,Van-Der-Vat, p. 158 and resulted in the expansion of the Orne bridgehead and the final capture of Caen.

Simultaneously, II Canadian Corps on Goodwood's western flank launched Operation Atlantic. Intended to strengthen the Allied foothold along the banks of the Orne River, and take Verrières Ridge to the south of Caen,Copp, Approach to Verrières Ridge Atlantic made initial gains but ran out of steam as casualties mounted. A counterstroke by two SS Panzer Divisions pushed the Canadians back past their start lines, and II Canadian Corps's commander, Lieutenant-General Guy Simonds, had to commit reinforcements to stabilize the front. Atlantic cost the Canadians 1,349Zuehlke, p. 166 casualties and failed to take Verrières Ridge, but in conjunction with Goodwood caused the Germans to commit most of their armor and additional reinforcements to the British and Canadian sector. Only two Panzer Divisions with 190 tanks now faced Bradley's First Army,Jackson, p. 113 while seven Panzer divisions with 750 tanks were positioned in the Caen area, far away from where Operation Cobra would be launched.Hastings, p. 236
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2e56c0a14e2805e939412155618b0529" name="Fightinggoodwood" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/2e56c0a14e2805e939412155618b0529.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>