<document id="058a209eb073b5ee7c24a5c99d3efb9d-3.3" name="Operation_Cobra" cat="29">
<text>
Cobra got underway on 25 July at 09:38, when around 600 Allied fighter-bombers attacked strongpoints and enemy artillery along a  wide strip of ground located in the St. L么 area.Williams, p. 180 During the next hour, 1,800 heavy bombers of the US Eighth Air Force saturated an area  wide and  deep on the Saint-L么&ndash;Periers road, succeeded by a third and final wave of medium bombers.Hastings, p. 254 Approximately 3,000 US aircraft had carpet-bombed a narrow section of the front, with the Panzer-Lehr Division taking the brunt of the attack.Williams, p. 181 However, once again not all the casualties were German; Bradley had specifically requested that the bombers approach the target from the east, out of the sun and parallel to the Saint-L么&ndash;Periers road, in order to minimize the risk of friendly losses, but most of the airmen instead came in from the north, perpendicular to the front line. Despite efforts by US units to identify their positions, inaccurate bombing by the Eighth Air Force killed 111 men, including Lieutenant-General Lesley McNair&mdash;the highest-ranking US soldier to be killed in action in the European Theater of Operations&mdash;and wounded 490.Williams, p. 182

By 11:00 the infantry began to move forward, advancing from crater to crater beyond what had been the German outpost line. Although no serious opposition was forecast, the remnants of Bayerlein's Panzer Lehr consisting of roughly 2,200 men and 45 armoured vehicles, had regrouped and were prepared to meet the advancing US troops, and to the west of Panzer Lehr, the German 5th Parachute Division had escaped the bombing almost intact.Williams, p. 183 Collins' VII Corps were quite disheartened to meet fierce enemy artillery fire, which they expected to have been suppressed by the bombing.Hastings, p. 255 Several US units found themselves entangled in fights against strongpoints held by a handful of German tanks, supporting infantry and 88 mm guns&mdash;VII Corps gained only  during the rest of the day. However, if the first day's results had been disappointing, General Collins found cause for encouragement; although the Germans were fiercely holding their positions, these did not seem to form a continuous line and were susceptible to being outflanked or bypassed. Even with prior warning of the American offensive, the British and Canadian actions around Caen had convinced the Germans that the real threat lay there, and tied down their available forces to such an extent that a succession of meticulously prepared defensive positions in depth, as encountered during Goodwood and Atlantic, were not created to meet Cobra. Further unbalancing the German position, Operation Spring, a follow-up to Atlantic conducted by II Canadian Corps, had drawn the 9th SS Panzer Division away from the US sector on the eve of Cobra's launch.Hastings, p. 256

The St. L么 breakthrough, 25&ndash;31 July.
On the morning of 26 July, the US 2nd Armored Division and the veteran 1st Infantry Division joined the attack as planned, reaching one of Cobra's first objectives&mdash;a road junction north of Le Mesnil-Herman&mdash;the following day.Hastings, p. 257 Also on the 26th, Major General Troy H. Middleton's VIII Corps entered the battle, led by the 8th and 90th Infantry Divisions. Despite clear paths of advance through the floods and swamps across their front, both divisions initially disappointed the First Army by failing to gain significant ground,Hastings, p. 258 but first light the next morning revealed that the Germans had been compelled to retreat by their crumbling left flank, leaving only immense minefields to delay VIII Corps' advance. By noon on 27 July, 9th Division of VII Corps was also clear of any organized German resistance, and advancing rapidly.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="470fb756d389ca278968dda2f839ff6c" name="Saint_Lo_and_Vicinity_-_Operation_Cobra" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/470fb756d389ca278968dda2f839ff6c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>