<document id="05b58b67166d2e5dd34e0b811df3454a-10" name="Somerset" cat="11">
<text>
Somerset has 6,531 km (4,058 mi) of roads. The main arterial routes, which include the M5 motorway, A303, A37, A38 and A39, give good access across the county, but many areas can only be accessed via narrow lanes.
Rail services are provided by the West of England Main Line through Yeovil, the Bristol to Taunton Line, Heart of Wessex Line which runs from Bristol to Weymouth and the Reading to Plymouth Line. Bristol International Airport provides national and international air services.

The Somerset Coal Canal was built in the early 19th century to reduce the cost of transportation of coal and other ''heavy'' produce. The first , running from a junction with the Kennet and Avon Canal, along the Cam valley, to a terminal basin at Paulton, were in use by 1805, together with several tramways. A planned 11.7 km (7.25 mi) branch to Midford was never built, but in 1815 a tramway was laid along its towing path. In 1871 the tramway was purchased by the Somerset and Dorset Joint Railway (S&DJR),Athill, Robin (1967). ''The Somerset & Dorset Railway''. Newton Abbot, Devon: David & Charles. ISBN 0-7153-4164-2. and operated until the 1950s.

The 19th century saw improvements to Somerset's roads with the introduction of turnpikes, and the building of canals and railways. Nineteenth-century canals included the Bridgwater and Taunton Canal, Westport Canal, Glastonbury Canal and Chard Canal. The Dorset and Somerset Canal was proposed, but little of it was ever constructed.

 

The usefulness of the canals was short-lived, though some have now been restored for recreation. The 19th century also saw the construction of railways to and through Somerset. The county was served by five pre-1923 Grouping railway companies: the Great Western Railway (GWR);  St. John Thomas, David (1960). ''A Regional history of the railways of Great Britain: Volume 1 - The West Country''. London: Phoenix House. a branch of the Midland Railway (MR) to Bath Green Park (and another one to Bristol);Smith, Martin (1992). ''The Railways of Bristol and Somerset''. Shepperton: Ian Allan Ltd. ISBN 0-7110-2063-9. the Somerset and Dorset Joint Railway,Awdry, Christopher (1990). ''Encyclopaedia of British Railway Companies''. Patrick Stephens Ltd. p. 237.Casserley, H.C. (1968). ''Britain's Joint Lines''. London: Ian Allan. ISBN 0-7110-0024-7. and the London and South Western Railway (L&SWR).Williams, R. A. (1968) ''The London & South Western Railway'', v. 1: The formative years, and v. 2: Growth and consolidation. Newton Abbot, Devon: David & Charles, ISBN 0-7153-4188-X; ISBN 0-7153-5940-1 The former main lines of the GWR are still in use today, although many of its branch lines were scrapped. The former lines of the Somerset and Dorset Joint Railway closed completely,Atthill, Robin and Nock, O. S. (1967). ''The Somerset & Dorset Railway''. Newton Abbot, Devon: David & Charles. ISBN 0-7153-4164-2. as has the branch of the Midland Railway to Bath Green Park (and to Bristol St Philips); however, the L&SWR survived as a part of the present West of England Main Line. None of these lines, in Somerset, are electrified. Two branch lines, the West and East Somerset Railways, were rescued and transferred back to private ownership as "heritage" lines. The fifth railway was a short-lived light railway, the Weston, Clevedon and Portishead Railway. The West Somerset Mineral Railway carried the iron ore from the Brendon Hills to Watchet.

Until the 1960s the piers at Weston-super-mare, Clevedon, Portishead and Minehead were served by the paddle steamers of P and A Campbell who ran regular services to Barry and Cardiff as well as Ilfracombe and Lundy Island. The pier at Burnham-on-Sea was used for commercial goods, one of the reasons for the Somerset and Dorset Railway was to provide a link between the Bristol Channel and the English Channel. The pier at Burnham-on-Sea is the shortest pier in the UK.Handley, Chris (2001). ''Maritime Activities of the Somerset & Dorset Railway''. Cleckheaton: Millstream Books. ISBN 0-9488975-63-6. In the 1970s the Royal Portbury Dock was constructed to provide extra capacity for the Port of Bristol.

For long-distance holiday traffic travelling through the county to and from Devon and Cornwall, Somerset is often regarded as a marker on the journey. North&ndash;south traffic moves though the county via the M5 Motorway.Charlesworth, George (1984). ''A History of British Motorways''. London: Thomas Telford Limited. ISBN 0-7277-0159-2. Traffic to and from the east travels either via the A303 road, or the M4 Motorway, which runs east&ndash;west, crossing the M5 just beyond the northern limits of the county.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7c2b36ac45fdc0ac43b95d6dfa5585c3" name="West_Somerset_Railway" sectnum="10#1">../img/7c2b36ac45fdc0ac43b95d6dfa5585c3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>