<document id="05b58b67166d2e5dd34e0b811df3454a-4.3" name="Somerset" cat="11">
<text>
The Somerset Levels (or Somerset Levels and Moors as they are less commonly but more correctly known) are a sparsely populated wetland area of central Somerset, between the Quantock and Mendip hills. They consist of marine clay levels along the coast, and the inland (often peat based) moors. The Levels are divided into two by the Polden Hills; land to the south is drained by the River Parrett while land to the north is drained by the River Axe and the River Brue. The total area of the Levels amounts to about 
and broadly corresponds to the administrative district of Sedgemoor but also includes the south west of Mendip district. Approximately 70% of the area is grassland and 30% is arable.
Stretching about  inland, this expanse of flat land barely rises above sea level. Before it was drained, much of the land was under a shallow brackish sea in winter and was marsh land in summer. Drainage began with the Romans, and was restarted at various times: by the Anglo-Saxons; in the Middle Ages by the Glastonbury Abbey, from 1400&ndash;1770; and during the Second World War, with the construction of the Huntspill River. Pumping and management of water levels still continues.Williams, Michael (1970). ''The Draining of the Somerset Levels''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. ISBN 0-521-07486-X.

The North Somerset Levels basin, north of the Mendips, covers a smaller geographical area than the Somerset Levels; and forms a coastal area around Avonmouth. It too was reclaimed by draining.Rippon, Stephen (1997). ''The Severn Estuary: Landscape Evolution and Wetland Reclamation''. London: Leicester University. ISBN 0-7185-0069-5 It is mirrored, across the Severn Estuary, in Wales, by a similar low-lying area: the Caldicot and Wentloog Levels.

In the far west of the county, running into Devon, is Exmoor, a high Devonian sandstone moor, which was designated as a national park in 1954, under the 1949 National Parks and Access to the Countryside Act.
The highest point in Somerset is Dunkery Beacon on Exmoor, with an altitude of 519 metres (1703 ft). http://www.mountaindays.net/mountains/peak.php?defn=0&area=37&peak=2889 Over 100 sites in Somerset have been designated as Sites of Special Scientific Interest.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c418571f73fa6da367adc5963d8c5840" name="Brean_Down" sectnum="4.3#1">../img/c418571f73fa6da367adc5963d8c5840.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>