<document id="05fd98c2c26765853d32977f0a493713-5" name="Battle_of_Svolder" cat="29">
<text>
The Norse sources agree that Olaf Tryggvason fought against overwhelming odds in the battle. ''Fagrskinna'', for example, says that he had "only a small force", and that the sea around him was "carpeted with warships"Finlay 2004:121. The sources which specify the number of warships all agree that Olaf Tryggvason had 11 vessels but they give various numbers for the allied fleets.



Though the sagas agree that Olaf Tryggvason had only 11 ships in the battle, some of them quote a verse by Halldórr the Unchristian saying that Olaf had 71 ships when he sailed from the south. The sagas explain the discrepancy by saying that some of the 71 ships belonged to Jarl Sigvaldi, who deserted Olaf, and that others sailed past the trap at Svolder before it was sprung.

The sagas describe three of the ships in Olaf Tryggvason's fleet. According to ''Heimskringla'', the ''Crane'' was a large swift-sailing warship with thirty rowers' benches, high in stem and stern.Snorri Sturluson 1991:209. It was commissioned by King Olaf and used as his flagship for some time.

Olaf confiscated the second of his great ships from a pagan he had tortured to death for refusing to convert to Christianity. King Olaf "steered it himself, because it was a much larger and finer ship than the Crane. Its stem had a dragon's head on it, and on its stern, a crook shaped like a tail; and both sides of the neck and all the stern were gilded. That ship the king called the Serpent, because when the sail was hoisted it was to look like the wing of
a dragon. That was the finest ship in all Norway."Snorri Sturluson
1991:214.

Olaf's third flagship, the ''Long Serpent'', was a legendary vessel mentioned in several anecdotes in the sagas.



The only allied ship described is Jarl Eirik's ''Iron Ram''. According to ''Fagrskinna'' it was "the biggest of all ships".Finlay 2004:123. ''Heimskringla'' gives more detail:
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="560d9332f99b0c94bbbb999051750e2f" name="Olav_Trygvasons_saga_-_Ormen_lange_-_Halfdan_Egedius" sectnum="5#1">../img/560d9332f99b0c94bbbb999051750e2f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>