<document id="05fd98c2c26765853d32977f0a493713-11" name="Battle_of_Svolder" cat="29">
<text>
Several factors combined to make the Battle of Svolder one of the most famous battles of the Viking Age. In Norwegian-Icelandic historiography, King Olaf Tryggvason was held in high regard as the man who brought Christianity to the North. His colourful end in a battle against overwhelming odds therefore makes a fitting narrative. Jarl Eirik’s court poets also ensured their lord a fair share of the glory. ''Mesta'' says:




In Iceland, where the kings' sagas continued to be copied and studied, the battle exercised the imagination of several poets. A 15th century ''rímur'' cycle, ''Svöldrar rímur'', chronicles the battle in verse, largely following the account of Oddr Snorrason.Printed in Finnur Jónsson (1912). ''Rímnasafn''. Two more ''rímur'' cycles on the same topic were composed in the 18th century, one of which is preserved.Finnur Sigmundsson 1966:459–60. In the 19th century, the popular poet Sigurður Breiðfjörð composed yet another ''rímur'' cycle on the battle, based on the account in ''Mesta''.First printed 1833, republished numerous times.  See: 
 Retrieved 30 January 2007. 

With the 19th century rise of nationalism and romanticism and the growing number of translations of the sagas, interest in the battle of Svolder increased outside of Iceland. Around 1830, the Faroese poet Jens Christian Djurhuus composed a ballad on the battle titled ''Ormurin langi'', following Snorri's account.See:  for an online version of the 1925 edition. Retrieved 30 January 2007. The ballad was well received and remains among the most popular and well-known Faroese ballads. In 2002, an abridged rock version by the band Týr gained some following abroad.

In Norway, Johan Nordahl Brun's rousing patriotic play ''Einar Tambarskjelve'', written in 1772, is considered a milestone in Norwegian literature.Naess 1993:77. Later Bjørnstjerne Bjørnson wrote a well-known short poem, ''Olav Trygvason'', on the fall of the king.English translation at Gutenberg . Retrieved 30 January 2007. Bjørnson also collaborated with Edward Grieg on an opera about Olaf Tryggvason, but the two fell out before the work was finished. Ragnar Søderlind has now completed the opera, which premiered in September 2000, 1000 years after the Battle of Svolder. Søderlind introduced fate motifs from Wagner, Beethoven and Liszt in the battle scene.Levin 2002.

The battle has also inspired art outside of Scandinavia, including a manga volume by the Japanese artist Ryō Azumi.See   and  Retrieved 30 January 2007. The best known English-language work is probably Henry Wadsworth Longfellow’s cycle ''The Saga of King Olaf'' (from his 1863 collection of poems ''Tales of a Wayside Inn''), much of which is dedicated to the Battle of Svolder, and which includes the verse:

:Louder the war-horns growl and snarl,
:Sharper the dragons bite and sting!
:Eric the son of Hakon Jarl
:A death-drink salt as the sea
::Pledges to thee,
:Olaf the King!See  Retrieved 30 January 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b488075b65f0c05ec81585e0201ef9fd" name="Faroese_stamp_562_Ormurin_langi" sectnum="11#1">../img/b488075b65f0c05ec81585e0201ef9fd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>