<document id="05fd98c2c26765853d32977f0a493713-1" name="Battle_of_Svolder" cat="29">
<text>
In earliest recorded history, Norway was divided into a number of small and sometimes warring petty kingdoms with weak central authority. In traditional historiography the rise of Harald Fairhair in the 9th century started the process of unification of the country and the consolidation of royal power.More recently it has been argued that Harald Fairhair should be regarded primarily as a mythic character. See Sverrir Jakobsson 2002:230. Harald's descendants, and other claimants to the throne, had to contend with strong regional leaders such as the Jarls of Lade in the north and the rulers of Vingulmark in the east, while the kings of Denmark claimed regions in the south and were eager to acquire Norwegian vassals to increase their influence. The spread of Christianity also became an increasingly important political issue in the late 10th century.Midgaard 1963:23.

In the 970s, Haakon Sigurdsson, Jarl of Lade, became the most powerful man in Norway, at first supported by Harald Bluetooth of Denmark and paying tribute to him — though the two later fell out over religious matters. Harald had converted to Christianity and was eager to Christianise Norway, while Haakon remained a staunch pagan. In 995 Haakon was deposed and the young Christian leader Olaf Tryggvason came to the throne.

While rejecting Danish authority, Olaf made it his mission to convert Norway and the Norse colonies in the west as quickly and as completely as possible. Proceeding with threats, torture and executions, Olaf broke down pagan resistance and within a few years Norway was, at least nominally, a Christian country. But King Olaf had acquired several enemies during his meteoric rise to power. The most prominent were Jarl Eirik, son of Jarl Haakon, and Svein Forkbeard, king of Denmark, both of whom felt that Olaf had deprived them of their share of Norway.Midgaard 1963:25–6.

The same interests which clashed in the Battle of Svolder were to divide Norway for decades to come, leading to further major engagements, including the Battle of Nesjar and the Battle of Stiklestad. The resolution came in 1035 with the accession of the Norwegian Magnus the Good to the throne of an independent and Christian Norway.Sawyer 1993:54–8.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c841c748f4fdb95744311e7171836581" name="Peter_nicolai_arbo,_olaf_tryggvasson_king" sectnum="1#1">../img/c841c748f4fdb95744311e7171836581.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>