<document id="05fd98c2c26765853d32977f0a493713-6" name="Battle_of_Svolder" cat="29">
<text>
It is unlikely that the saga writers had accurate information on details of the battle beyond the sparse accounts in the surviving poems. Nevertheless, starting with Oddr Snorrason, they present an elaborate literary account, depicting the main participants through their words and deeds.

Olaf Tryggvason's ships pass the anchorage of his allied enemies in a long column without order, as no attack is expected. Conveniently placed to observe the fleet, Jarl Eirik and the two kings remark upon the passing vessels. Svein and Olaf are eager to join battle, but Eirik is portrayed as more cautious and familiar with the Norwegian forces. 

As progressively larger vessels appear, the Danes and Swedes think each one is the Long Serpent and want to attack straight away, but Eirik holds them off with informed comments:Oddr modelled his narrative on an episode from ''Gesta Caroli Magni'' by Monachus Sangallensis where Desiderius of the Lombards surveys the approaching armies of Charlemagne. Bjarni Aðalbjarnarson 1941:cxxx.



As Eirik finally consents to attack, King Svein boasts that he will command the Long Serpent "before the sun sets". Eirik makes a remark "so that few men heard him" saying that "with only the Danish army at his disposal, King Sveinn would never command this ship". As the allies set out to attack Olaf Tryggvason, the point of view shifts to the Norwegian fleet. 

After spotting the enemy, Olaf might have used sail and oar to outrun the ambush and escape, but he refuses to flee and turns to give battle with the eleven ships immediately about him. Seeing the Danish fleet arrayed against him, he comments: "The forest goats will not overcome us, for the Danes have the courage of goats. We will not fear that force because the Danes have never carried off the victory if they fought on ships."Oddr Snorrason 2003:123. Similarly, Olaf writes off the Swedes with a reference to their pagan customs:



It is only when Olaf Tryggvason sights Eirik Hákonarson's contingent that he realises he is in for a hard battle, because "they are Norwegians like us".Oddr Snorrason 2003:126. The sagas' emphasis of Eirik's contribution stands in marked contrast to the Danish accounts of Adam of Bremen and Saxo Grammaticus, who portray the battle as a Danish victory over Norwegians, with no mention of Jarl Eirik or his men.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="18d046acac02a61ea5eb0090aa293d40" name="Olav_Tryggvasons_saga_-_Olavs_skip_seiler_forbi_-_H._Egedius" sectnum="6#1">../img/18d046acac02a61ea5eb0090aa293d40.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>