<document id="0649339e3c133f746da0cc055013466d-2.1" name="1926_World_Series" cat="26">
<text>
Yankee Stadium was filled with 61,658 fans on October 2, there to watch the inaugural game of the 1926 World Series. Those who could not get tickets for the game gathered at City Hall to watch the game's progress being charted on two large scoreboards.Eig (2005), p. 75. Before the start of the game, United States Senator Robert F. Wagner, who represented New York, threw out the ceremonial first pitch and seated himself in the box seat next to New York City mayor Jimmy Walker. Baseball Commissioner Kenesaw Mountain Landis and former heavyweight champion of the world Jack Dempsey were also present. The Cardinals selected left-handed pitcher Bill Sherdel to start Game One. During the regular season, Sherdel pitched nearly 235 innings, attaining 16 wins and 12 losses. The Yankees' pitcher was Herb Pennock, the team's only 20-game winner that season. The future Hall of Fame pitcher, nicknamed "''The Knight Of Kennett Square''", had a 3.62 ERA in 266.3 innings and had finished third in the American League Most Valuable Player Award voting, behind winner George Burns and runner-up Johnny Mostil.

Cardinals leadoff hitter Taylor Douthit started the offense in the first inning by hitting a double into left field. Douthit advanced to third base after Billy Southworth hit a slow-moving ground ball to Yankee second baseman Tony Lazzeri. Rogers Hornsby followed by hitting another ground ball right to Pennock, who threw it to first baseman Lou Gehrig for an out. Cardinals first baseman "Sunny Jim" Bottomley hit a bloop single, which allowed Douthit to score. In the bottom of the inning, Sherdel walked Earle Combs, Babe Ruth and Bob Meusel, putting runners on each base. At his first batting attempt, Lou Gehrig grounded the ball to shortstop Tommy Thevenow, who tossed the ball to Hornsby. Hornsby threw to first base, but the Yankees slugger reached the base before Bottomley could get him out. Combs scored on the play, giving Gehrig his first World Series run batted in (RBI). In the bottom of the third inning, Babe Ruth singled. On a Bob Meusel bunt, Ruth slid into second base and split his pants. Radio announcer Graham McNamee exclaimed, "Babe is the color of a red brick house". Doc Woods, the team's trainer, sewed up Ruth's pants on the ballfield, much to the amusement of the audience.

The score remained tied at one apiece until the sixth inning, just as it began to rain. Ruth lined a single past third baseman Les Bell. Meusel hit a sacrifice bunt, advancing Ruth to second base. Gehrig followed with a single, scoring Ruth and giving the Yankees the lead. Lazzeri lined a shot into left field, and Gehrig dove into third base headfirst, but was tagged out by Bell.Eig (2005), p. 76. Lazzeri advanced to second base, on the play. Bell committed an error while trying to field Joe Dugan's ground ball, resulting in runners at first and third base. Hank Severeid hit a grounder to shortstop Thevenow, who threw the ball to Hornsby. Hornsby then made a force play to end the inning. In the ninth inning, Bottomley singled off Pennock. However, the Cardinals could not advance Bottomley, and the game ended as a 2–1 win for the Yankees. Gehrig was the Yankees' offensive leader for the game, batting in both of the team's runs. Pennock pitched a complete game, striking out four batters and giving up three hits. Pennock had also held the Cardinals to hits in only two of the nine innings. Cardinals losing pitcher Sherdel threw for seven innings, giving up two runs and six hits, while striking out one batter.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e5eb2d800cbe640bf9771c8c802b9756" name="Bob-meusel_cleaned" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/e5eb2d800cbe640bf9771c8c802b9756.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>