<document id="0649339e3c133f746da0cc055013466d-1" name="1926_World_Series" cat="26">
<text>
The Cardinals won the 1926 National League pennant after finishing with a league-best record of 89 wins and 65 losses, two games ahead of the runner-up Cincinnati Reds. The previous season, the Cardinals ended the regular season fourth in the National League after posting a record of 77 wins and 76 losses. During the first half of the 1926 season, they traded outfielder Heinie Mueller to the New York Giants in exchange for outfielder Billy Southworth. They also picked up future Hall of Fame pitcher Grover Cleveland Alexander, after the Chicago Cubs had placed him on waivers. The Cardinals' pitching staff was led by Flint Rhem, who pitched 20 wins and had a 3.21 earned run average (ERA), far surpassing his eight wins and 4.92 ERA of the previous season. Offensively, the Cardinals were led by Jim Bottomley, Rogers Hornsby—who had a batting average of over .400 the season before—and catcher Bob O'Farrell, the winner of the season's National League Most Valuable Player Award. This was the first World Series appearance in Cardinals team history.

The contest for first place in the National League was heated. During the second and third weeks of September, both the Cardinals and the Reds had multi-game winning streaks and swapped positions in the league standings for win–loss record on a daily basis. On September 17, the Cardinals went one game ahead of the Reds and continued building their lead in the standings in the coming days as the Reds lost several games in a row. The Cardinals concluded the season with a loss to the Reds on September 26, but still finished two games ahead in the final league standings.

The Yankees had the best record in the American League with 91 wins and 63 losses, finishing three games ahead of the Cleveland Indians. They improved on their 69-win season in 1925 by making Lou Gehrig their permanent starting first baseman and trading for rookie second baseman Tony Lazzeri in the offseason. Gehrig, Lazzeri, Babe Ruth and Earle Combs led the offense. Yankee pitchers Herb Pennock and Urban Shocker combined for 42 wins in the season. The Yankees were making their fourth World Series appearance in six years; they had previously won the World Series in 1923.

In early September 1926, thousands of Cleveland Indians fans, confident that their team would win the American League pennant despite being six games behind the Yankees, filed requests to reserve World Series tickets. By September 2, the Indians were two games behind the Yankees, but then lost three of their final four games to finish the season three games behind them.

On September 11, Commissioner of Baseball Kenesaw Mountain Landis met with representatives from four of the top teams in the American and National Leagues. The group decided that the first two games of the World Series—scheduled for October 2 and October 3—would be played in the stadium of the American League pennant winner. The third, fourth and fifth games would be played in the National League pennant winner's stadium, followed by the final two games at the American League stadium. Landis and the representatives also agreed that each game was to start at 13:30 local time.

Some bookmakers named the Yankees a 15-to-1 favorite to win the World Series over the Cardinals, while others, like New York's top betting commissioners, thought the teams were evenly matched. One writer from ''The New York Times'' claimed that "there is little justification for installing either team as favorite". Regardless of the odds, players from both teams expressed confidence regarding their team's chances of winning the championship. Hornsby said, "We're going to come through winners. We have the better pitching staff, the better hitters and the greater experience. That's what it takes to win. ... We're going to beat the Yankees. Any of my ball players will tell you that, and we expect to do it." Yankees manager Miller Huggins stated:
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="318caae6703d35056a45bd939b1f3a70" name="Miller_Huggins_baseball_card" sectnum="1#1">../img/318caae6703d35056a45bd939b1f3a70.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>