<document id="06d986db00025cc339a14d62d85bbc79-2.1" name="Angkor_Wat" cat="1">
<text>
Angkor Wat, located at , is a unique combination of the temple mountain, the standard design for the empire's state temples, the later plan of concentric galleries, and influences from Orissa and the Chola of Tamil Nadu, India. The temple is a representation of Mount Meru, the home of the gods: the central quincunx of towers symbolises the five peaks of the mountain, and the walls and moat the surrounding mountain ranges and ocean.Freeman and Jacques p. 48. Access to the upper areas of the temple was progressively more exclusive, with the laity being admitted only to the lowest level.Glaize p. 62.

Unlike most Khmer temples, Angkor Wat is oriented to the west rather than the east. This has led many (including Glaize and George Coedès) to conclude that Suryavarman intended it to serve as his funerary temple.The diplomatic envoy Zhou Da Guan sent by Emperor Temur Khan to Angkor in 1295 reported that the head of state was buried in tower after death, and he referred to Angkor Wat as a mausoleum Further evidence for this view is provided by the bas-reliefs, which proceed in a counter-clockwise direction—''prasavya'' in Hindu terminology—as this is the reverse of the normal order. Rituals take place in reverse order during Brahminic funeral services. The archaeologist Charles Higham also describes a container which may have been a funerary jar which was recovered from the central tower.Higham, ''The Civilization of Angkor'' p. 118. It has been nominated by some as the greatest expenditure of energy on the disposal of a corpse.  Scarre, Chris editor "The Seventy Wonders of the Ancient World", p. 81-85 (1999) Thames & Hudson, London   Freeman and Jacques, however, note that several other temples of Angkor depart from the typical eastern orientation, and suggest that Angkor Wat's alignment was due to its dedication to Vishnu, who was associated with the west.

A further interpretation of Angkor Wat has been proposed by Eleanor Mannikka. Drawing on the temple's alignment and dimensions, and on the content and arrangement of the bas-reliefs, she argues that these indicate a claimed new era of peace under king Suryavarman II: "as the measurements of solar and lunar time cycles were built into the sacred space of Angkor Wat, this divine mandate to rule was anchored to consecrated chambers and corridors meant to perpetuate the king's power and to honor and placate the deities manifest in the heavens above."Mannikka,  Stencel, Robert, Fred Gifford, and Eleanor Moron. "Astronomy and Cosmology at Angkor Wat." Science 193 (1976): 281-287.(Mannikka, nee Moron) Mannikka's suggestions have been received with a mixture of interest and scepticism in academic circles. She distances herself from the speculations of others, such as Graham Hancock, that Angkor Wat is part of a representation of the constellation Draco.Transcript of , broadcast BBC2 November 4, 1999.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4a88e151f4bf942582570cd7ff10e49f" name="Awatcornertower01" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/4a88e151f4bf942582570cd7ff10e49f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>