<document id="07209a8c34755d8280856c7d2856fed5-2" name="BP_Pedestrian_Bridge" cat="1">
<text>
The bridge was built using 22-gauge stainless steel type 316 plates ( thick), with an angel hair finish and a flat interlocking panel process.  Stainless steel type 316 is known for its excellent welding characteristics, as well as for its resistance to pitting. According to the ''Chicago Tribune'', the bridge materials used in construction include 2,000 rot-resistant Brazilian hardwood boards for the deck, 115,000 stainless steel screws and 9,800 stainless steel shingle plates.Gilfoyle, p. 243. According to Architecture Metal Expertise, the bridge has "10,400 stainless steel trapezoidal panels in 17 different shop fabricated configurations  involved 1,000 shop hours". The sheet metal work totaled 5,900 field hours over a six-month period.  During construction, about 200 shingles were installed per day.Sharoff, p. 105  The bridge includes two types of structural steel: steel that is  thick and  in diameter for the approaches and box girders for the span.Sharoff, p. 100

CATIA software was used to handle the complex geometric layout.Sharoff, p. 103 To ensure accurate fitting and alignment to the sloping, curving sides of the bridge, 4,400 custom-made convex, concave and radiused cladding panels were fabricated on site by sheet metal contractor Custom Metal Fabricators (CMF). CMF used  of stainless steel sheet to cover the sides, which have a combined perimeter length of . CMF built special heated enclosures so that work could continue on site through the winter. They designed, fabricated and installed custom type 4 brushed stainless steel parapets serving in the place of handrails on the bridge.  CMF earned the 2005 Tom Guilfoy Memorial Architectural Sheet Metal Award, by the California chapter of the Sheet Metal and Air Conditioning Contractors' National Association for the project. In 2005 it received a Merit Award from the National Steel Bridge Alliance, and an Excellence in Structural Engineering award from the Structural Engineers Association of Illinois. 

On the day that the two halves of the bridge were joined, each side of Columbus Drive was closed for a 12-hour period and a  crane was used to install the girders.  Before bringing the jack to the location, screw jacks were used to shore up the underground garage roof to hold the crane's weight.Sharoff, p. 109
 
The landscaping surrounding the bridge was redesigned by landscape architect Terry Guen.  Honey locusts, ash and maple trees were removed and replaced with three varieties of magnolia and more than two dozen ornamental and canopy trees along the eastern foot of the bridge in Daley Bicentennial Plaza. Other preliminary construction work included setting reinforcing rods for the bridge in the concrete roof deck of the parking garage located under the park.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9fc2ee6439ac509414906ccd851421b5" name="BP_Bridge_entry" sectnum="2#1">../img/9fc2ee6439ac509414906ccd851421b5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>