<document id="074de933dbcd9a2cf35d528a5bed5dda-5" name="Elfin-woods_Warbler" cat="3">
<text>
The survival of the Elfin-woods Warbler faces two main threats, predation and the destruction or alteration of suitable habitat. Confirmed native predators are the Pearly-eyed Thrasher (''Margarops fuscatus''), the Sharp-shinned Hawk (''Accipiter striatus'') and the extirpated White-necked Crow (''Corvus leucognaphalus'') while unconfirmed native predators include two endemic snakes and several carnivores (from fossil records). Introduced species, such as cats (''Felis domesticus''), dogs (''Canis lupus familiaris''), Black Rats (''Rattus rattus'') and Small Asian Mongooses (''Herpestes javanicus'') are also potential nest predators. These species have proliferated due to the presence of human-developed facilities, mainly for communication purposes, in the Maricao State Forest and the Caribbean National Forest. Two factors contribute to the destruction of the Elfin-woods Warbler's habitat, humans and nature. Human-related habitat destruction includes the construction of communication towers, acquisition of timber, and expansion of roads and trails. Nature's contribution comes from natural disasters such as forest fires and hurricanes.

The Elfin-woods Warbler was placed on the United States federal candidate list for Endangered Species Act in 1982. In 2005, a group of scientists, scholars, artists and environmentalists petitioned the Bush administration to admit 225 species, among these the Elfin-woods Warbler, to the Endangered Species Act. Of these 225 species, more than one third have been on the candidate list for 20 or more years and half for 10 or more years. Recent studies also show that since the creation of the Endangered Species Act in 1973, 114 United States species have become extinct, many because of lack of habitat protection by the federal government.

The IUCN first evaluated the status of the Elfin-woods Warbler in 1988. At the time it was given a classification of lower Risk/least concern. In 1994, its status was changed to Lower Risk/near threatened and in 2000, its status was changed to vulnerable, where it remains. The justification for maintaining the species' status as vulnerable is that "There are no direct or immediate threats, but the combination of a very small range and population may have important implications for its chances of long-term survival, and this species consequently qualifies as Vulnerable".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c6f85936cbc5fd7c48bfa33e8476be35" name="SharpshinnedHawk23" sectnum="5#1">../img/c6f85936cbc5fd7c48bfa33e8476be35.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>