<document id="0766665dbb750d978e903755f3e98c46-2.4" name="Pinguicula_moranensis" cat="3">
<text>
Prior to Alexander von Humboldt and Aimé Bonpland's Latin American expedition in 1799–1804, only 8 ''Pinguicula'' species were known to science — 5 from Europe, 2 from North America and ''P. involuta'' from Peru. From 1803–1805, three additional species from Europe and North America were described, bringing the total of known species to 11.  In 1817 Humboldt, Bonpland and Carl Sigismund Kunth described 3 new species from their Latin American expedition: The Peruvian ''P. calyptrata'' and the first known Mexican species: ''P. macrophylla'' and ''P. moranensis''.From Ruiz, S.J. 2001, orig. Humboldt, A., A. Bonpland & C.S. Kunth. 1817   At this point no infrageneric classification had yet been suggested.

In 1844 a French-Swiss botanist by the name of Alphonse Pyrame de Candolle (who created the first Code of Botanical Nomenclature) proposed a division of the genus into three sections based on floral morphology. He placed in the section ''Orcheosanthus'' those species with purple, deeply bilabiate corollas with 5 sub-equal lobes, a short floral tube, and a large spur not protruding past this tube. He included four species in this section, all of them from Mexico: ''P. oblongiloba'', ''P. orchidioides'', '''''P. caudata''''' and ''P. moranensis''.  He excluded ''P. macrophylla'' H.B.K. on the grounds that it was a "dubious species".From Ruiz, S.J. 2001, orig. Candolle, A.P. De. 1844


The section ''Orcheosanthus'' grew as Charles Morren described '''''P. flos-mulionis''''' in 1872, Eugene Fournier added '''''P. sodalium''''' in 1873 and Sander proposed '''''P. bakeriana''''' in 1881.  In 1879–1888, however, a botanist by the name of William Hemsley, after studying multiple specimens in herbariums and in culture, came to the conclusion that all the taxa placed in the section ''Orcheosanthus'' up to that point belonged to the same single species. Due to doubts as to the identity of the original two species described by H.B.K., Hemsley decided to use the name ''P. caudata'' Schltdl. for his conglomerate species. This name has been "indiscriminately" applied to members of the complex ever since.Ruiz 2001, pg. 26
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a8698bfe373592c17b4e3a33b4dcecec" name="Pinguicula_caudata_print" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/a8698bfe373592c17b4e3a33b4dcecec.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>