<document id="0766665dbb750d978e903755f3e98c46-2.4.2" name="Pinguicula_moranensis" cat="3">
<text>
When Barnhart revised the family Lentibulariaceae in 1916, he recognized six species in the section Orcheosanthus, admitting however that this number was likely to change as others studied the section in the future.  Sprague in 1928 proposed that the species joined by Hemsley were probably distinct, but that they were likely so interrelated that distinguishing between them would require observing characteristics that were usually or always indistinct in dried specimens.The difficulty of basing taxonomical work in the genus ''Pinguicula'' solely on dried specimens has been noted by several frustrated botanists. McVaugh & Mickel in their 1963 notes on the section ''Orcheosanthus'' noted that "Herbarium study of these plants is difficult and frustrating because the leaves and other vegetative and reproductive structures are so fragile that dried specimens are seldom adequately preserved. Usually but a single flower is found on a plant, and the extraordinarily fragile pressed flowers often lose their original color and shape to a very large extent. Often neither vegetative nor reproductive structures can be studied without severe damage to the specimen" (McVaugh, 1963).  Barnhart (1916) had stated that "the range of variation is enormous, but how much is seasonal, how much individual, and how much of taxonomic importance, is (based on herbarium samples alone) at present mere guesswork" (Barnhart, 1916).  This conclusion was echoed by Sprague (1928), Ernst (1961), and McVaugh (1963). Sprague recognized eight species in the section: ''P. moranensis'' H.B.K, ''P. caudata'' Schltdl., ''P. oblongiloba'', ''P. flos-mulionis'', ''P. bakeriana'', a ''P. moranensis''-like '''''P. rosei''''' described by Watson in 1911, and the very distinct ''P. gypsicola''.

In 1966 Casper published the first ever monograph of the genus. He clearly defined his taxonomic organization according to a broad range of morphological and phenotypic characteristics. Casper considered ''P. caudata'', as well as various other taxa, to be a synonyms of ''P. moranensis''. He therefore recognized only 6 species for the section ''Orcheosanthus'': ''P. moranensis'', ''P. gypsicola'', ''P. macrophylla'' H.B.K., ''P. oblongiloba'', and the two recently discovered species ''P. colimensis'' and ''P. cyclosecta''.  Since that time 14 additional species have been discovered and assigned to the section.Ruiz 2001, pg. 29  When Zamudio redefined the section in 1999, however, he chose to include only 12 species, including all six of Casper's choices.  ''P. moranensis'', therefore, remains in the section ''Orcheosanthus'', along with over a dozen synonyms it has inherited in its 200-year taxonomic history.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="98295159aa6f2ebb4f13eb5bbe37d17a" name="Pinguicula_moranensis_flowering" sectnum="2.4.2#1">../img/98295159aa6f2ebb4f13eb5bbe37d17a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>