<document id="0789d77e27962a5ce5f7f5017816aa63-2" name="Colley_Cibber" cat="17">
<text>
Cibber's colourful autobiography, ''An Apology for the Life of Colley Cibber'' (1740), pioneered the truly personal autobiography, and inaugurated a distinctive British tradition of chatty, meandering, anecdotal memoirs. At the time of writing the word "apology" meant an ''apologia'', a statement in defence of one's actions rather than a statement of regret for having transgressed.

Cibber wrote in detail about his time in the theatre, especially his early years as a young actor at Drury Lane in the 1690s, giving a vivid account of the cutthroat theatre company rivalries and chicanery of the time, as well as providing pen portraits of the actors he knew. The ''Apology'' is notoriously vain and self-serving, as both contemporaries and posterity have enjoyed pointing out (see Barker). For the early part of Cibber's career, it is also unreliable in respect of chronology and other hard facts, understandably, since he was writing down his recollections fifty years after the events, apparently without the help of any journal or notes. Nevertheless, it is an invaluable source for the theatre history of the Restoration and early 18th-century period, for which documentation is otherwise scanty. Because he worked with many actors from the early days of Restoration theatre, such as Thomas Betterton and Elizabeth Barry (albeit at the end of their careers) and lived to see the ultra-modern David Garrick perform, he is a fascinating bridge between a mannered and a more naturalistic style of performance.

The self-complacency of Cibber's ''Apology'' infuriated some of his contemporaries, notably Pope. However, generations of readers have found it an amusing and engaging read, projecting an author always "happy in his own good opinion, the best of all others; teeming with animal spirits, and uniting the self-sufficiency of youth with the garrulity of age."Hazlitt, p. 201.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7416c6254186311feda9f0b6378ee5ea" name="Colley_Cibber_Apology_small" sectnum="2#1">../img/7416c6254186311feda9f0b6378ee5ea.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>