<document id="0789d77e27962a5ce5f7f5017816aa63-5" name="Colley_Cibber" cat="17">
<text>
Cibber's creation of the combined actor-manager role is important in the history of the British stage because he was the first in a long and illustrious line that would include such luminaries as Garrick, Henry Irving, and Herbert Beerbohm Tree. Rising from actor at Drury Lane to advisor and spy (see ''Dictionary of Actors'') on behalf of the manager Christopher Rich, Cibber worked himself by degrees into a position to take over the company. With two other actors, Thomas Doggett and Robert Wilks, he was able to buy the company outright around 1710. The events are well documented, but the three actors' maneuvering to squeeze out previous owners was so lengthy and complex that an approximate date must suffice here. After a few stormy years of power-struggle with Doggett and Wilks, Cibber became in practice sole manager of Drury Lane. He wrote no more original plays, though he continued producing adaptations and patchwork plays from "the frippery of crucified Molière" and "hapless Shakespeare"Pope, ''The Dunciad'', Book the First, in ''The Rape of the Locke and Other Poems,'' p. 214. for the company, and to act on the stage. He thus set a pattern for the line of more charismatic and successful actors that were to succeed him in this combination of roles. His near-contemporary Garrick, as well as the 19th century actor-managers Irving and Tree, would later structure their careers, writing, and manager identity around their own striking stage personalities. Cibber's ''forte'' as actor-manager was, by contrast, the manager side. He was a clever, innovative, and unscrupulous businessman who retained all his life a love of appearing on the stage. His triumph was that he rose to a position where, in consequence of his sole power over production and casting at Drury Lane, London audiences had to put up with him as an actor. 

Cibber had learned from the bad example of Rich to be a careful and approachable employer for his actors, and was not unpopular with them, but made enemies in the literary world by his obvious enjoyment of the power he wielded over authors. Many were outraged by his sharp business methods, which may be exemplified by the characteristic way he abdicated as manager in the mid-1730s. First selling his share for over 3,000 pounds, he immediately encouraged his scapegrace son Theophilus to lead the actors in a walkout to set up for themselves in the Haymarket, rendering worthless the commodity he had sold. Cibber's application on behalf of his son for a patent to perform at the Haymarket was, however, refused by the Lord Chamberlain,  who was "disgusted at Cibber's conduct."Lowe, II, 260.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="509d18f39d9a2bd7a5a5715a6cab2696" name="Drury_Lane_playbill_1718" sectnum="5#1">../img/509d18f39d9a2bd7a5a5715a6cab2696.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>