<document id="0789d77e27962a5ce5f7f5017816aa63-7.5" name="Colley_Cibber" cat="17">
<text>
From the very beginning of the 18th century, when Cibber first rose to being Rich's right-hand man and spy at Drury Lane, his opportunism and his brash, thick-skinned personality gave rise to many barbs in print, especially against his patchwork plays. The early attacks were mostly anonymous, but some have been ascribed to Daniel Defoe and Tom Brown (see Lowe). Later, Jonathan Swift, John Gay, James Thomson, Richard Blackmore, John Dennis and Henry Fielding all lambasted Cibber in print. The most famous conflict Cibber had was with Alexander Pope, the greatest poet of the age. In the first version of his landmark literary satire ''The Dunciad'' (1728), Pope referred contemptuously to Cibber's "past, vamp'd, future, old, reviv'd, new" plays, produced with "less human genius than God gives an ape", and Cibber's elevation to laureateship in 1730 further inflamed Pope against him. The selection of Cibber for this honor was widely seen as outlandish, at a time when Pope, John Gay, Thomson, Ambrose Philips, and Edward Young were all in their prime. As one epigram of the time put it:
:"In merry old England it once was a rule,
:The King had his Poet, and also his Fool:
:But now we're so frugal, I'd have you to know it,
:That Cibber can serve both for Fool and for Poet." (Recorded by Pope in the 1743 ''Dunciad'').
That he was selected immediately after a change in the government from Tory to Whig was also noticeable.  Further, Cibber associated himself with Robert Walpole, the highly divisive "first Prime Minister."  



Pope, mortified by the elevation of Cibber to laureatehood and incredulous at the vainglory of his ''Apology'' (1740), took every opportunity to attack him in his poetry, and easily got the laughers on his side. Mostly Cibber replied quite good-humoredly to Pope's aspersions ("some of which are in conspicuously bad taste", as Lowe points out), but in 1742 he snapped and hit below the belt in an angry and damaging pamphlet, ''A Letter from Mr. Cibber, to Mr. Pope, inquiring into the motives that might induce him in his Satyrical Works, to be so frequently fond of Mr. Cibber's name''. In this pamphlet, Cibber's most effective ammunition came from a reference in Pope's ''Epistle to Arbuthnot'' (1735) to Cibber's "whore", which gave Cibber a pretext for retorting in kind with a scandalous anecdote about Pope in a brothel. "I must own", wrote Cibber, "that I believe I know more of your whoring than you do of mine; because I don't recollect that ever I made you the least Confidence of my Amours, though I have been very near an Eye-Witness of Yours." Since Pope was around four and a half feet tall and hunchbacked due to a tubercular infection of the spine he contracted when young, Cibber regarded the prospect of Pope with a woman as something humorous, and he speaks mockingly of the "little-tiny manhood" of Pope. For once the laughers were on Cibber's side, and the story "raised a universal shout of merriment at Pope's expense."Lowe, II, 275. Pope made no direct reply, but took one of the most famous revenges in literary history. In the revised ''Dunciad'' that appeared in 1743, he changed his hero, the King of Dunces, from Lewis Theobald to Colley Cibber.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="dd673602e10c70912ef596be1cc25af8" name="Alexander_Pope_by_Michael_Dahl" sectnum="7.5#1">../img/dd673602e10c70912ef596be1cc25af8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>