<document id="078f3eb97ff6c365c2e645282a661bad-5.4" name="George_V_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
The German composer Paul Hindemith, who was in London preparing to perform the British premiere of his work ''Der Schwanendreher'', went to a BBC studio on the morning after the king's death and in six hours wrote ''Trauermusik'' (Mourning Music). It was performed that same evening in a live broadcast by the BBC, with Adrian Boult conducting the BBC Symphony Orchestra and the composer as soloist. The scheduled premiere was cancelled.

An equestrian statue of King George V was unveiled outside Brisbane City Hall in 1938 as a tribute to the King from the citizens of Brisbane, Australia. The square in which the statue stands was originally called Albert Square, but was later renamed King George Square in honour of the King. In London, a statue by William Reid Dick stands outside the east end of Westminster Abbey.

The King George's Fields in London were created as a memorial by a committee in 1936 chaired by the then Lord Mayor of the City of London. Today, they are each registered charities and are under the guidance of the National Playing Fields Association. The national stadium of Newfoundland in St. John's was named King George V Park in 1925. Jerusalem and Tel Aviv both have major thoroughfares named for King George V. Both date back to the period of the British Mandate for Palestine. In Paris, a large avenue from the top of the Champs-Elysées down to the Seine river and an underground station were named for George V; as are Avenue Georges, Shawinigan, Quebec, Canada; King George V Avenue, Sale, Victoria, Australia; King George V Secondary School, Malaysia; and King George V School and King George V Memorial Park in Hong Kong.

The World War I Royal Navy battleship HMS ''King George V'' and the World War II Royal Navy battleship HMS ''King George V'' were named in his honour. George V gave both his name and donations to many charities, including King George's Fund for Sailors (later known as Seafarers UK).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="418a619ea506735103d12f8419f3a5c7" name="KingGeorgeVSqBrisbane" sectnum="5.4#1">../img/418a619ea506735103d12f8419f3a5c7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>