<document id="078f3eb97ff6c365c2e645282a661bad-3" name="George_V_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
On 24 May 1892, Queen Victoria created George, Duke of York, Earl of Inverness and Baron Killarney. After George's marriage to May, she was styled ''Her Royal Highness The Duchess of York''.

The Duke and Duchess of York lived mainly at York Cottage,Renamed from ''Bachelor's Cottage'' a relatively small house in Sandringham, Norfolk where their way of life mirrored that of a comfortable middle-class family rather than royalty. George preferred the simple, almost quiet, life in marked contrast to his parents. Even his official biographer despaired of George's time as Duke of York, writing: "He may be all right as a young midshipman and a wise old king, but when he was Duke of York ... he did nothing at all but kill  animals and stick in stamps."Harold Nicolson's diary quoted in Sinclair, p. 107

George was a well-known stamp collector, and played a large role in building the Royal Philatelic Collection into the most comprehensive collection of United Kingdom and Commonwealth stamps in the world, in some cases setting record purchase prices for items. His enthusiasm for stamps was denigrated by the intelligentsia.Rose, p. 42

Randolph Churchill claimed that George was a strict father, to the extent that his children were terrified of him, and that George had remarked to Edward Stanley, 17th Earl of Derby: "My father was frightened of his mother, I was frightened of my father, and I am damned well going to see to it that my children are frightened of me." In reality there is no direct source for the quotation and it is likely that George's parenting style was little different from that adopted by most people at the time.See Sinclair, pp. 93 ff for a full discussion George and May had five sons and a daughter.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b94784cc5820b6f3f312a107d33705fb" name="York_Cottage" sectnum="3#1">../img/b94784cc5820b6f3f312a107d33705fb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>