<document id="078f3eb97ff6c365c2e645282a661bad-5.3" name="George_V_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
World War I took a toll on George's health, and his heavy smoking exacerbated recurring breathing problems. He long suffered from emphysema, bronchitis, chronic obstructive lung disease and pleurisy. In 1928, he fell seriously ill, and for the next two years his son Edward took over many of his duties.Ziegler, pp. 192–196 The King retired for a brief period to the seaside resort of Bognor Regis in Sussex.Pope-Hennessy, p. 546 A myth later grew that his last words, upon being told that he would soon be well enough to revisit the town, were "Bugger Bognor!"

George never fully recovered. In his final year, he was occasionally administered oxygen. On the evening of 15 January 1936, the King took to his bedroom at Sandringham House complaining of a cold; he would never again leave the room alive.Pope-Hennessy, p. 558 He became gradually weaker, drifting in and out of consciousness. By 20 January, he was already comatose and close to death. His physician, Lord Dawson of Penn, issued a bulletin with words that have become famous: "The King's life is drawing peacefully to a close." Dawson's diary reveals that the King's last words, a mumbled "God damn you!", were addressed to his nurse when she gave him a sedative on the night of 20 January. Dawson admits hastening the King's end by giving him a lethal injection of cocaine and morphine, both to prevent further strain on the family and so that the news of his death could be announced in the morning edition of ''The Times'' newspaper. He died at 11:55 p.m.

At the procession to George's Lying in State in Westminster Hall, as the cortège turned into New Palace Yard, part of the Imperial State Crown fell from on top of the coffin and landed in the gutter. The new king, Edward VIII, saw it fall and wondered whether this was a bad omen for his new reign.The Duke of Windsor, p. 267The cross surmounting the crown, composed of a sapphire and 200 diamonds, was retrieved by a military man following later in the procession. He would abdicate before the year was out, leaving Albert, Duke of York, to ascend to the throne.

As a mark of respect to their father, George's four surviving sons, Edward, Albert, Henry and George, mounted the guard, known as the Vigil of the Princes, at the catafalque on the night of 28 January, the day before the funeral.''The Times (London)'', Tuesday, 28 January 1936, p. 10 col. F He is buried at St George's Chapel, Windsor Castle.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="88f3d7743a61dd7f4e3a12f689059b33" name="Westminster_king_george_v_statue_1" sectnum="5.3#1">../img/88f3d7743a61dd7f4e3a12f689059b33.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>