<document id="0811abf5a5bc74534bececf59628f85a-2.3" name="Cell_nucleus" cat="3">
<text>
The cell nucleus contains the majority of the cell's genetic material, in the form of multiple linear DNA molecules organized into structures called chromosomes. During most of the cell cycle these are organized in a DNA-protein complex known as chromatin, and during cell division the chromatin can be seen to form the well defined chromosomes familiar from a karyotype. A small fraction of the cell's genes are located instead in the mitochondria.

There are two types of chromatin. Euchromatin is the less compact DNA form, and contains genes that are frequently expressed by the cell. The other type, heterochromatin, is the more compact form, and contains DNA that are infrequently transcribed. This structure is further categorized into ''facultative'' heterochromatin, consisting of genes that are organized as heterochromatin only in certain cell types or at certain stages of development, and ''constitutive'' heterochromatin that consists of chromosome structural components such as telomeres and centromeres. During interphase the chromatin organizes itself into discrete individual patches, called ''chromosome territories''. Active genes, which are generally found in the euchromatic region of the chromosome, tend to be located towards the chromosome's territory boundary.

Antibodies to certain types of chromatin organization, particularly nucleosomes, have been associated with a number of autoimmune diseases, such as systemic lupus erythematosus. These are known as anti-nuclear antibodies (ANA) and have also been observed in concert with multiple sclerosis as part of general immune system dysfunction. As in the case of progeria, the role played by the antibodies in inducing the symptoms of autoimmune diseases is not obvious.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="707213f6b4ee8d551c9487bf38bf62f0" name="MouseChromosomeTerritoriesBMC_Cell_Biol6-44Fig2e" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/707213f6b4ee8d551c9487bf38bf62f0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>