<document id="090cd4ad469e9af440f17e6e2a6a81e4-8" name="Blade_Runner" cat="19">
<text>
While it initially was not a success with North American audiences, the film was popular internationally and became a cult classic.Sammon, pp. 318–329 ''Blade Runner's'' dark style and futuristic design have served as a benchmark and its influence can be seen in many subsequent science fiction films, anime, videogames and television programs. For example, Ronald D. Moore and David Eick, the producers of the re-imagining of ''Battlestar Galactica'', have both openly cited ''Blade Runner'' as one of the major influences for the show. ''Blade Runner'' continues to reflect modern trends and concerns, and an increasing number consider it one of the greatest science fiction films of all time. The film was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry in 1993 and is frequently used in university courses. In 2007, it was named the 2nd most visually influential film of all time by the Visual Effects Society.

''Blade Runner'' is one of the most musically sampled films of the 20th century, and inspired the Grammy nominated song "More Human than Human" by White Zombie. ''Blade Runner'' has influenced adventure games, such as ''Rise of the Dragon'', ''Snatcher'', ''Beneath a Steel Sky'' and ''Flashback: The Quest for Identity'', the anime series ''Bubblegum Crisis'', the role-playing game ''Shadowrun'', the first-person shooter ''Perfect Dark'', and the ''Syndicate'' series of video games. The film is also cited as the a major influence on Warren Spector, designer of the computer-game ''Deus ex'', which both in its visual rendering and plot displays evidence of the film's influence. 
The look of the film (darkness, neon lights and opacity of vision) is easier to render than complicated backdrops, making it a popular choice for game designers.

''Blade Runner'' has also been the subject of parody, such as the comics ''Blade Bummer'' by Crazy comics, ''Bad Rubber'' by Steve Gallacci, and the ''Red Dwarf'' special episodes, "Back To Earth".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="77b038c04b720e2daf1a518247e34a20" name="BladeRunner_Spinner_Billboard" sectnum="8#1">../img/77b038c04b720e2daf1a518247e34a20.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>