<document id="09764e13abbe99ab79652cea0ec7816d-1.4" name="Cricket_World_Cup" cat="26">
<text>
In 1999 the event was hosted by England, with some matches also being held in Scotland, Ireland, Wales and the Netherlands.Browning (1999), p. 274 Australia qualified for the semi-finals after reaching their target in their Super 6 match against South Africa off the final over of the match.Browning (1999), pp. 229–231 They then proceeded to the final with a tied match in the semi-final (also against South Africa) where a mix-up between South African batsmen Lance Klusener and Allan Donald saw Donald drop his bat and stranded mid-pitch to be run out. In the final, Australia dismissed Pakistan for 132 and then reached the target in less than 20 overs, with eight wickets in hand.Browning (1999), pp. 232–238

South Africa, Zimbabwe and Kenya hosted the 2003 World Cup. The number of teams participating in the event increased from twelve to fourteen. Kenya's victories over Sri Lanka and Zimbabwe, among others &mdash; and a forfeit by the New Zealand team, which refused to play in Kenya because of security concerns &mdash; enabled Kenya to reach the semi-finals, the best result by an associate. In the final, Australia made 359 runs for the loss of two wickets, the largest ever total in a final, defeating India by 125 runs. 

In 2007 the tournament was hosted by the West Indies; the Cricket World Cup became the first such tournament to be hosted on all six populated continents. Bangladesh progressed to the second round for the first time, after defeating India, and they later went on to defeat South Africa in the second round. Ireland making their World Cup debut tied with Zimbabwe and defeated Pakistan to progress to the second round, where they went on to defeating Bangladesh to get promoted to the main ODI table. Following their defeat to Ireland, the Pakistani coach Bob Woolmer was found dead in his hotel room; it was later found out that he died of heart failure. Australia defeated Sri Lanka in the final by 53 runs (D/L), in farcical light conditions, extending their undefeated run in the World Cup to 29 matches and winning three straight World Cups.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5749d0fe899a89adc2d36ecc6c7d4424" name="Australian_World_Cup_treble" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/5749d0fe899a89adc2d36ecc6c7d4424.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>