<document id="09beb8dbb993465f6b3f826656e850a0-3.0.8" name="Battle_of_Blenheim" cat="29">
<text>
:'' … Prince Eugene and the Imperial troops had been repulsed three times – driven right back to the woods – and had taken a real drubbing.'' – Mérode-Westerloo.Spencer: ''Blenheim: Battle for Europe,'' p. 270


On the Allied right, Eugene's Prussian and Danish forces were desperately fighting the numerically superior forces of the Elector and Marsin. The Prince of Anhalt-Dessau led forward four brigades across the Nebel to assault the well-fortified position of Lutzingen. Here, the Nebel was less of an obstacle, but the great battery positioned on the edge of the village enjoyed a good field of fire across the open ground stretching to the hamlet of Schwennenbach. As soon as the infantry crossed the stream, they were struck by Maffei's infantry, and salvoes from the Bavarian guns positioned both in front of the village and in enfilade on the wood-line to the right. Despite heavy casualties the Prussians attempted to storm the great battery, whilst the Danes, under Count Scholten, attempted to drive the French infantry out of the copses beyond the village.Falkner: ''Blenheim 1704,'' p. 71

With the infantry heavily engaged, Eugene's cavalry picked its way across the Nebel. After an initial success, his first line of cavalry, under the Imperial General of Horse, Prince Maximilian of Hanover, were pressed by the second line of Marsin's cavalry, and were forced back across the Nebel in confusion. Nevertheless, the exhausted French were unable to follow up their advantage, and the two cavalry forces tried to regroup and reorder their ranks.Tincey: ''Blenheim 1704: The Duke of Marlborough's Masterpiece,'' p. 67 However, without cavalry support, and threatened with envelopment, the Prussian and Danish infantry were in turn forced to pull back across the Nebel. Panic gripped some of Eugene’s troops as they crossed the stream. Ten infantry colours were lost to the Bavarians, and hundreds of prisoners taken; it was only through the leadership of Eugene and the Prussian Prince that the Imperialist infantry were prevented from abandoning the field.Spencer: ''Blenheim: Battle for Europe,'' p. 268

After rallying his troops near Schwennenbach – well beyond their starting point – Eugene prepared to launch a second attack, led by the second-line squadrons under the Duke of Württemberg-Teck. Yet again they were caught in the murderous cross-fire from the artillery in Lutzingen and Oberglauheim, and were once again thrown back in disarray. The French and Bavarians, however, were almost as disordered as their opponents, and they too were in need of inspiration from their commander, the Elector, who was seen – " … riding up and down, and inspiring his men with fresh courage."Falkner: ''Blenheim 1704,'' p. 73 Anhalt-Dessau’s Danish and Prussian infantry attacked a second time but could not sustain the advance without proper support. Once again they fell back across the stream.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e6e06acaec54bb286e490aebe9e52e0e" name="Spanischer_Erbfolgekrieg_1704,_Lutzingen,_Germany" sectnum="3.0.8#1">../img/e6e06acaec54bb286e490aebe9e52e0e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>