<document id="09beb8dbb993465f6b3f826656e850a0-3.0.7" name="Battle_of_Blenheim" cat="29">
<text>
Cutts ordered Brigadier-General Archibald Rowe's brigade to attack. The British infantry rose from the edge of the Nebel, and silently marched towards Blenheim, a distance of some 150 yards (~130 metres). John Ferguson's British brigade supported Rowe’s left, and moved in perfect order towards the barricades between the village and the river, defended by Hautefeuille's dragoons. As the range closed to within , the French fired a deadly volley. Rowe had ordered that there should be no firing from his men until he struck his sword upon the palisades, but as he stepped forward to give the signal, he fell mortally wounded.Churchill: ''Marlborough: His Life and Times,'' p.  853. Two of Rowe’s staff officers were killed trying to carry him away: Lieutenant-Colonel Dalyell and Major Campbell. The survivors of the leading companies closed up the gaps in their torn ranks and rushed forward. Small parties penetrated the defences, but repeated French volleys forced the British back towards the Nebel, sustaining heavy casualties. As the attack faltered, eight squadrons of elite Gens d'Armes, commanded by the veteran Swiss officer, Beat-Jacques von Zurlauben, fell upon the British troops, cutting at the exposed flank of Rowe's own regiment.Churchill and Coxe states only three squadrons of Gens d'Armes. Rowe’s own regiment lost their colours, but they were soon retrieved by the Hessians. However, Wilkes’ Hessian brigade, lying nearby in the marshy grass at the water's edge, stood firm and repulsed the Gens d'Armes with steady fire, enabling the British and Hessians to re-order and launch another attack.Falkner: ''Blenheim 1704,'' p. 68

Although the Allies were again repulsed, these persistent attacks on Blenheim eventually bore fruit, panicking Clérambault into making the worst French error of the day.Chandler: ''A Guide to the Battlefields of Europe,'' p. 145 Without consulting Tallard, Clérambault ordered his reserve battalions into the village, upsetting the balance of the French position and nullifying the French numerical superiority. "The men were so crowded in upon one another", wrote Mérode-Westerloo, "that they couldn’t even fire – let alone receive or carry out any orders." Marlborough, spotting this error, now countermanded Cutts’ intention to launch a third attack, and ordered him simply to contain the enemy within Blenheim; no more than 5,000 Allied soldiers were able to pen in twice the number of French infantry and dragoons.Falkner: ''Blenheim 1704,'' p. 70
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="216f63e292a9ba93dd6ade8b575b942b" name="Battle_of_Blenheim_Tapestry" sectnum="3.0.7#1">../img/216f63e292a9ba93dd6ade8b575b942b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>