<document id="0aa90b35e8ef4289c54a8a4b75a92edb-1.1" name="Great_Fire_of_London" cat="14">
<text>
The City was essentially medieval in its street plan, an overcrowded warren of narrow, winding, cobbled alleys. It had experienced several major fires before 1666, the most recent in 1632. Building with wood and roofing with thatch had been prohibited for centuries, but these cheap materials continued to be used.Hanson (2001), 77&ndash;80. The section "Fire hazards in the City" is based on Hanson (2001), 77&ndash;101 unless otherwise indicated. The only major stone-built area was the wealthy centre of the City, where the mansions of the merchants and brokers stood on spacious lots, surrounded by an inner ring of overcrowded poorer parishes whose every inch of building space was used to accommodate the rapidly growing population. These parishes contained workplaces, many of which were fire hazards&mdash;foundries, smithies, glaziers'&mdash;which were theoretically illegal in the City, but tolerated in practice. The human habitations intermingled with these sources of heat, sparks, and pollution were crowded to bursting point and their construction increased the fire risk: the typical six- or seven-storey timbered London tenement houses had "jetties" (projecting upper floors): they had a narrow footprint at ground level, but would maximise their use land by "encroaching", as a contemporary observer put it, on the street with the gradually increasing size of their upper storeys. The fire hazard posed when the top jetties all but met across the narrow alleys was well perceived&mdash;"as it does facilitate a conflagration, so does it also hinder the remedy", wrote one observerRege Sincera (pseudonym), ''Observations both Historical and Moral upon the Burning of London, September 1666'', quoted by Hanson (2001), 80.&mdash;but "the covetousness of the citizens and connivancy  of Magistrates" worked in favour of jetties. In 1661, Charles II issued a proclamation forbidding overhanging windows and jetties, but this was largely ignored by the local government. Charles' next, sharper, message in 1665 warned of the risk of fire from the narrowness of the streets and authorised both imprisonment of recalcitrant builders and demolition of dangerous buildings. It too had little impact. 	 

The river front was important in the development of the Great Fire. The Thames offered water for firefighting and the chance of escape by boat, but the poorer districts along the riverfront had stores and cellars of combustibles which increased the fire risk. All along the wharves, the rickety wooden tenements and tar paper shacks of the poor were shoehorned amongst "old paper buildings and the most combustible matter of Tarr, Pitch, Hemp, Rosen, and Flax which was all layd up thereabouts."Letter from an unknown correspondent to Lord Conway, September 1666, quoted by Tinniswood, 45–46. London was also full of black powder, especially along the river front. Much of it was left in the homes of private citizens from the days of the English Civil War, as the former members of Cromwell's New Model Army still retained their muskets and the powder with which to load them. Five to six hundred tons of powder were stored in the Tower of London at the north end of London Bridge. The ship chandlers along the wharves also held large stocks, stored in wooden barrels.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="594e1d495af8430f661aba4d43380b93" name="Charles_II_of_England_cropped" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/594e1d495af8430f661aba4d43380b93.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>