<document id="0ab77ec86e8e769eec1a241d519560fd-2" name="Freedom_Monument" cat="1">
<text>
The monument is located in the center of Riga on Brīvības bulvāris ("Freedom Boulevard"), near the old town of Riga. In 1990 a section of the street around the monument, about  long, between Rainis and Aspazija boulevards, was pedestrianized, forming a plaza. Part of it includes a bridge over the city's canal, once a part of the city's fortification system, which was demolished in the 19th century to build the modern boulevard district. Rīga 1860–1917 Rīga 1978 Zinātne (No ISBN) The canal is  long and surrounded by parkland for half of its length., retrieved on 2007-05-30 The earth from the demolition of the fortifications was gathered in the park and now forms an artificial hill with a cascade of waterfalls to the north of the monument. The Boulevard district east of the park is the location of several embassies and institutions, of which the closest to the Freedom Monument are the German and French embassies, the University of Latvia and Riga State Gymnasium No.1. , retrieved on 2007-06-03

Situated in the park near the monument to the south is the National Opera House with a flower garden and a fountain in front of it. Enciklopēdija "Rīga" Rīga 1988 Galvenā enciklopēdiju redakcija (No ISBN) Opposite the opera house on the western part of plaza near the old town, is a small café and the Laima clock. The clock was set up in 1924, and in 1936 it was decorated with an advertisement for the Latvian confectionery brand "Laima", from which it took its name; it is a popular meeting spot. , retrieved on 2007-04-20

Originally it was planned that an elliptical plaza would be built around the foot of the monument, enclosed by a granite wall  high, with benches placed inside it, while a hedge of thujas was to be planted around the outside. This project was however not carried out in the 1930s. The idea was reconsidered in the 1980s but shelved again. "Latvijas Enciklopēdija" (I sējums) Rīga 2002 SIA "Valērija Belokoņa izdevniecība" ISBN 9984-9482-1-8
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="eee841f57ca758e977dfc71309e3f1ac" name="Laima_clock_Riga_150a" sectnum="2#1">../img/eee841f57ca758e977dfc71309e3f1ac.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>