<document id="0ab876cd182527b839573064c70a8223-8" name="Battle_of_Verrières_Ridge" cat="29">
<text>
The Battle of Verrières Ridge, although given no particular prominence in German military history, has earned the distinction of being one of the First Canadian Army's most scrutinised actions. Simonds's official report on Operation Spring, released after the war, blamed its failure on "11th hour reinforcement" of German lines and "strategically unsound execution on the part of Major Phillip Griffin and the Black Watch".Simonds, pp. 67&ndash;68. However, recently declassified wartime documents show that Simonds, along with several others in the Allied high command, had likely been notified on July 23 of a massive German buildup on the ridge.Copp (1992), p. 50. Some historians, including David O'Keefe and David Bercuson, consequently accuse Simonds of being too careless with the lives of his men. In contrast, others such as Terry Copp and John A. English argue that, given the amount of pressure that all Allied commanders were under to break out from Normandy, Simonds probably had little choice in the decision he made.Copp (1992), p. 61.

Operation Spring did succeed in its later-defined objective of a "holding attack",Simonds, p. 65. and aided the overwhelming success of Operation Cobra by tying down powerful German formations that might otherwise have been in the American sector, thus precluding any immediate inquiry into its failure. The German commander of the Normandy Sector, Günther von Kluge, was at the Canadian front on July 25 instead of the American front where the eventual breakout occurred.Bercuson, p. 227. However, the Battle of Verrières Ridge had little overall effect on British attempts to break out of Caen, as significant resources were transferred to the American Front in the aftermath of Cobra to exploit Bradley's success, and the ridge eventually fell to the general Allied advance.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7b8c76ff55c662bbf638579d9f5938bb" name="Monty_and_Simonds" sectnum="8#1">../img/7b8c76ff55c662bbf638579d9f5938bb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>