<document id="0ab876cd182527b839573064c70a8223-4" name="Battle_of_Verrières_Ridge" cat="29">
<text>
The next assault took place on July 20, under the aegis of Operation Atlantic. It was led by the South Saskatchewan Regiment, with supporting units from the Cameron Highlanders. In the early hours of July 20, the Highlanders secured a position in St André-sur-Orne, but were quickly pinned down by an effective German infantry and armoured response.Bercuson, Pg. 220 At the same time, the South Saskatchewan Regiment moved directly up the slopes of Verrières Ridge, supported by tanks and Hawker Typhoon ground attack aircraft. However, the Canadian attack faltered in torrential rain, which rendered air support useless and turned the ground into mud. Heavy German counterattacks by two Panzer divisions threw the South Saskatchewans back past their support lines,Zuehlke, p. 166. and their supporting battalion, the Essex Scottish, themselves came under attack. The Essex Scottish lost over 300 men as it tried to hold back the advance of the 12th SS Panzer Division,BBC: People's War while to the west the remainder of I SS Panzer Corps engaged British forces in the largest armoured battle of the campaign.Van Der Vat, p. 159. By the end of the day, the South Saskatchewans had taken 282 casualties, and the ridge was still in enemy hands. 

Despite these setbacks, Simonds was adamant that Verrières Ridge should be taken, and sent in the Black Watch and the Calgary Highlanders to stabilise the precarious Allied position. Minor counterattacks by both regiments on July 21 managed to contain Dietrich's armoured formations,  and by the time the operation was called off, Canadian forces held several footholds on the ridge,Bercuson, p. 224. including a now secure position on Point 67.Copp (1992), p. 47. However, four German divisions still held the ridge itself. In all, the actions around Verrières Ridge during Operation Atlantic accounted for over 1,100 Allied casualties.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a0c64794d2f53644795a90b0d5d218c4" name="Lieutenant-General_Guy_G._Simonds" sectnum="4#1">../img/a0c64794d2f53644795a90b0d5d218c4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>