<document id="0b4ebd99673d910a6747df881d000dc1-6" name="Uncle_Tom's_Cabin" cat="17">
<text>
''Uncle Tom's Cabin'' is dominated by a single theme: the evil and immorality of slavery.''Homelessness in American Literature: Romanticism, Realism, and Testimony'' by John Allen, Routledge, 2004, page 24, where it states in regards to ''Uncle Tom's Cabin'' that "Stowe held specific beliefs about the 'evils' of slavery and the role of Americans in resisting it." The book then quotes Ann Douglas describing how Stowe saw slavery as a sin. While Stowe weaves other subthemes throughout her text, such as the moral authority of motherhood and the redeeming possibilities offered by Christianity, she emphasizes the connections between these and the horrors of slavery. Stowe pushed home her theme of the immorality of slavery on almost every page of the novel, sometimes even changing the story's voice so she could give a "homily" on the destructive nature of slavery''Drawn With the Sword: Reflections on the American Civil War'' by James Munro McPherson,  Oxford University Press, 1997, page 30. (such as when a white woman on the steamboat carrying Tom further south states, "The most dreadful part of slavery, to my mind, is its outrages of feelings and affections—the separating of families, for example.").''Uncle Tom's Cabin'' by Harriet Beecher Stowe, Vintage Books, Modern Library Edition, 1991, page 150. One way Stowe showed the evil of slavery  was how this "peculiar institution" forcibly separated families from each other.''Drawn With the Sword: Reflections on the American Civil War'' by James Munro McPherson,  Oxford University Press, 1997, page 29.

Because Stowe saw motherhood as the "ethical and structural model for all of American life,""Stowe's Dream of the Mother-Savior: Uncle Tom's Cabin and American Women Writers Before the 1920s" by Elizabeth Ammons, ''New Essays on Uncle Tom's Cabin'', Eric J. Sundquist, editor, Cambridge University Press, 1986, page 159. and also believed that only women had the moral authority to save''Whitewashing Uncle Tom's Cabin: Nineteenth-Century Women Novelists Respond to Stowe'' by Joy Jordan-Lake, Vanderbilt University Press, 2005, page 61. the United States from the demon of slavery, another major theme of ''Uncle Tom's Cabin'' is the moral power and sanctity of women. Through characters like Eliza, who escapes from slavery to save her young son (and eventually reunites her entire family), or Little Eva, who is seen as the "ideal Christian",''Somatic Fictions: imagining illness in Victorian culture'' by Athena Vrettos, Stanford University Press, 1995, page 101. Stowe shows how she believed women could save those around them from even the worst injustices. While later critics have noted that Stowe's female characters are often domestic clichés instead of realistic women,''The Stowe Debate: Rhetorical Strategies in Uncle Tom's Cabin'' by Mason I. (jr.) Lowance, Ellen E. Westbrook, C. De Prospo, R., Univ of Massachusetts Press, 1994, page 132. Stowe's novel "reaffirmed the importance of women's influence" and helped pave the way for the women's rights movement in the following decades.''Historical Dictionary of Women's Education in the United States'' by Linda Eisenmann, Greenwood Press, 1998, page 3.

Stowe's puritanical religious beliefs show up in the novel's final, over-arching theme, which is the exploration of the nature of Christianity and how she feels Christian theology is fundamentally incompatible with slavery.''The Company of the Creative: A Christian Reader's Guide to Great Literature and Its Themes'' by David L. Larsen, Kregel Publications, 2000, pages 386–387. This theme is most evident when Tom urges St. Clare to "look away to Jesus" after the death of St. Clare's beloved daughter Eva. After Tom dies, George Shelby eulogizes Tom by saying, "What a thing it is to be a Christian."''The Company of the Creative: A Christian Reader's Guide to Great Literature and Its Themes'' by David L. Larsen, Kregel Publications, 2000, page 387. Because Christian themes play such a large role in ''Uncle Tom's Cabin''—and because of Stowe's frequent use of direct authorial interjections on religion and faith—the novel often takes the "form of a sermon."''The Cambridge History of American Literature'' by Sacvan Bercovitch and Cyrus R. K. Patell, Cambridge University Press, 1994, page 119.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bc66174862ac75397b44182afc4661a9" name="FugitivesSafe" sectnum="6#1">../img/bc66174862ac75397b44182afc4661a9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>