<document id="0b4ebd99673d910a6747df881d000dc1-10" name="Uncle_Tom's_Cabin" cat="17">
<text>
In response to ''Uncle Tom's Cabin'', writers in the Southern United States produced a number of books to rebut Stowe's novel. This so-called Anti-Tom literature generally took a pro-slavery viewpoint, arguing that the issues of slavery as depicted in Stowe's book were overblown and incorrect. The novels in this genre tended to feature a benign white patriarchal master and a pure wife, both of whom presided over child-like slaves in a benevolent extended-family-style plantation. The novels either implied or directly stated that African Americans were a child-like people''Playing the Race Card: Melodramas of Black and White from Uncle Tom to O. J. Simpson'' by Linda Williams, Princeton Univ. Press, 2001, page 113. unable to live their lives without being directly overseen by white people.''Whitewashing Uncle Tom's Cabin: nineteenth-century women novelists respond to Stowe'' by Joy Jordan-Lake, Vanderbilt University Press, 2005.

Among the most famous anti-Tom books are ''The Sword and the Distaff'' by William Gilmore Simms, ''Aunt Phillis's Cabin'' by Mary Henderson Eastman, and ''The Planter's Northern Bride'' by Caroline Lee Hentz,"" by Philip D. Beidler. Alabama Heritage Number 75, Winter 2005. with the last author having been a close personal friend of Stowe's when the two lived in Cincinnati. Simms' book was published a few months after Stowe's novel and it contains a number of sections and discussions disputing Stowe's book and her view of slavery. Hentz's 1854 novel, widely-read at the time, but now largely forgotten, offers a defense of slavery as seen through the eyes of a northern woman—the daughter of an abolitionist, no less—who marries a southern slave owner.

In the decade between the publication of ''Uncle Tom's Cabin'' and the start of the American Civil War, between twenty and thirty anti-Tom books were published. Among these novels are two books titled ''Uncle Tom's Cabin As It Is'' (one by W.L. Smith and the other by C.H. Wiley) and a book by John Pendleton Kennedy. More than half of these Anti-Tom books were written by white women, with Simms commenting at one point about the "Seemingly poetic justice of having the Northern woman (Stowe) answered by a Southern woman."''Figures in Black: words, signs, and the "racial" self'' by Henry Louis Gates, Oxford University Press, 1987, page 134.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b47213a9325e3193175e98e935383ba6" name="Auntphillis" sectnum="10#1">../img/b47213a9325e3193175e98e935383ba6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>