<document id="0b4ebd99673d910a6747df881d000dc1-7" name="Uncle_Tom's_Cabin" cat="17">
<text>
''Uncle Tom's Cabin'' is written in the sentimentalMarianne Noble, "The Ecstasies of Sentimental Wounding In Uncle Tom's Cabin," from ''A Routledge Literary Sourcebook on Harriet Beecher Stowe's Uncle Tom's Cabin'' Edited by Debra J. Rosenthal, Routledge, 2003, page 58. and melodramatic style common to 19th century sentimental novels and domestic fiction (also called women's fiction). These genres were the most popular novels of Stowe's time and tended to feature female main characters and a writing style which evoked a reader's sympathy and emotion. American Literature Sites, Washington State University. Retrieved April 26, 2007. Even though Stowe's novel differs from other sentimental novels by focusing on a large theme like slavery and by having a man as the main character, she still set out to elicit certain strong feelings from her readers (such as making them cry at the death of Little Eva). The Kansas Territorial Experience. Retrieved April 26, 2007. The power in this type of writing can be seen in the reaction of contemporary readers. Georgiana May, a friend of Stowe's, wrote a letter to the author stating that "I was up last night long after one o'clock, reading and finishing ''Uncle Tom's Cabin''. I could not leave it any more than I could have left a dying child."''Reading Women: Literary Figures and Cultural Icons from the Victorian Age to the Present'' by Janet Badia and Jennifer Phegley, University of Toronto Press, 2005, page 67. Another reader is described as obsessing on the book at all hours and having considered renaming her daughter Eva.''Reading Women: Literary Figures and Cultural Icons from the Victorian Age to the Present'' by Janet Badia and Jennifer Phegley, University of Toronto Press, 2005, page 66. Evidently the death of Little Eva affected a lot of people at that time, because in 1852 alone 300 baby girls in Boston were given that name.

Despite this positive reaction from readers, for decades literary critics dismissed the style found in ''Uncle Tom's Cabin'' and other sentimental novels because these books were written by women and so prominently featured "women's sloppy emotions."''A Routledge Literary Sourcebook on Harriet Beecher Stowe's Uncle Tom's Cabin'' by Debra J. Rosenthal, Routledge, 2003, page 42. One literary critic said that had the novel not been about slavery, "it would be just another sentimental novel,""Review of ''The Building of Uncle Tom's Cabin'' by E. Bruce Kirkham" by Thomas F. Gossett, ''American Literature'', Vol. 50, No. 1 (March, 1978), pp. 123–124. while another described the book as "primarily a derivative piece of hack work." by Charles Nichols, ''The Phylon Quarterly'', Vol. 19, No. 3 (3rd Qtr., 1958), page 328. In The Literary History of the United States, George F. Whicher called ''Uncle Tom's Cabin'' "Sunday-school fiction", full of "broadly conceived melodrama, humor, and pathos." by Jane Tompkins, from ''In Sensational Designs: The Cultural Work of American Fiction'', 1790–1860. New York: Oxford UP, 1985. Pp. 122–146. 

However, in 1985 Jane Tompkins changed this view of ''Uncle Tom's Cabin'' with her book ''In Sensational Designs: The Cultural Work of American Fiction.'' Tompkins praised the style so many other critics had dismissed, writing that sentimental novels showed how women's emotions had the power to change the world for the better. She also said that the popular domestic novels of the 19th century, including ''Uncle Tom's Cabin'', were remarkable for their "intellectual complexity, ambition, and resourcefulness"; and that ''Uncle Tom's Cabin'' offers a "critique of American society far more devastating than any delivered by better-known critics such as Hawthorne and Melville."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2a8d984cc0a2aaf85b02f7e5de4d3633" name="Eliza-Crossing-the-Ice-Morgan-1881" sectnum="7#1">../img/2a8d984cc0a2aaf85b02f7e5de4d3633.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>