<document id="0b4ebd99673d910a6747df881d000dc1-1" name="Uncle_Tom's_Cabin" cat="17">
<text>
Stowe, a Connecticut-born teacher at the Hartford Female Academy and an active abolitionist, wrote the novel as a response to the 1850 passage of the second Fugitive Slave Act (which punished those who aided runaway slaves and diminished the rights of fugitives as well as freed Blacks). Much of the book was composed in Brunswick, Maine, where her husband, Calvin Ellis Stowe, taught at his alma mater Bowdoin College. Harriet Beecher Stowe House and Library. Accessed February 17, 2007.

Stowe was partly inspired to create ''Uncle Tom's Cabin'' by the autobiography of Josiah Henson, a black man who lived and worked on a 3,700 acre (15 km²) tobacco plantation in North Bethesda, Maryland owned by Isaac Riley.Susan Logue,  VOA News, January 12, 2006. Retrieved May 16, 2006. Henson escaped slavery in 1830 by fleeing to the Province of Upper Canada (now Ontario), where he helped other fugitive slaves arrive and become self-sufficient, and where he wrote his memoirs. Stowe eventually acknowledged that Henson's writings inspired ''Uncle Tom's Cabin''.Harriet Beecher Stowe,  1853, page 42, in which Stowe states "A last instance parallel with that of Uncle Tom is to be found in the published memoirs of the venerable Josiah Henson…" An excerpt of this information and acknowledgement is also in ''A Routledge Literary Sourcebook on Harriet Beecher Stowe's Uncle Tom's Cabin'' by Debra J. Rosenthal, Routledge, 2003, pages 25–26. When Stowe's work became a best-seller, Henson republished his memoirs as ''The Memoirs of Uncle Tom'', and traveled extensively in the United States and Europe. Stowe's novel lent its name to Henson's home&mdash;Uncle Tom's Cabin Historic Site, near Dresden, Ontario&mdash;which since the 1940s has been a museum. The actual cabin Henson lived in while he was a slave, still exists in Montgomery County, Maryland.

''American Slavery As It Is: Testimony of a Thousand Witnesses'', a volume co-authored by Theodore Dwight Weld and the Grimké sisters, is also a source of some of the novel's content. The Columbia Encyclopedia, Sixth Edition, 2001–2005. Retrieved May 15, 2007. Stowe also said she based the novel on a number of interviews with escaped slaves during the time when Stowe was living in Cincinnati, Ohio, across the Ohio River from Kentucky, a slave state. In Cincinnati the Underground Railroad had local abolitionist sympathizers and was active in efforts to help runaway slaves on their escape route from the South.

Stowe mentioned a number of the inspirations and sources for her novel in ''A Key to Uncle Tom's Cabin'' (1853). This non-fiction book was intended to verify Stowe's claims about slavery., Uncle Tom's Cabin and American Culture, a Multi-Media Archive. Retrieved April 20, 2007. However, later research indicated that Stowe did not actually read many of the book's cited works until after the publication of her novel.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e2268e549515d478cb639a5a70656cf2" name="StowePainting" sectnum="1#1">../img/e2268e549515d478cb639a5a70656cf2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>