<document id="0b70416f7bbf38c21234300ba2ff90ae-1.4.1" name="Stanford_Memorial_Church" cat="1">
<text>
The Rev. Scotty McLennan has served as Dean for Religious Life at Stanford since 2001. He is joined by associate deans Rabbi Patricia Karlin-Neumann and The Rev. Joanne Sanders to form a multi-faith team.  The deans oversee educational programs and serve on administrative committees on campus.

McLennan, a Unitarian Universalist minister, was "an activist neighborhood lawyer" in Boston before becoming a university chaplain, first at Tufts University.  Garry Trudeau, who was McLennan's roommate when they were students at Yale University, based his Doonesbury character, the Rev. Scot Sloan, in part on McLennan.

Rabbi Karlin-Neumann is Stanford's first Jewish associate dean of religious life.  Before the university hired her in 1996, the chaplaincy position was called "Dean of Memorial Church"; in order to accommodate Karlin-Neumann, the position's name was changed to "Dean of Religious Life at Stanford".  Before coming to Stanford, Karlin-Neumann had been a Hillel director and chaplain at UCLA and Claremont College, a rabbi in Alameda, California, and was active in Reform Judaism.  She has taught courses in Jewish feminism, rabbinical ethics, education, and social justice.  She refers to her role at Stanford as "Mem Chu and a Jew, too".

Sanders, an Episcopal priest, has worked at Stanford since 2001.  She has degrees in theology, sports administration and physical education.  Her career has focused on the connection between body, mind, and spirit.  She serves as liturgical officer for Memorial Church, is responsible for coordinating and facilitating the religious services at the church, and is active in the athletic community on campus.  She is also a member of Stanford's Women's Community Center.

Robert Huw Morgan has been Stanford Memorial Church's organist since 1999.  He is a lecturer in organ at the Stanford University School of Music.  Morgan performs at up to thirty services, mostly weddings, each month at the church.  Mary Gallagher is the wedding coordinator at Stanford Memorial Church.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4d9cb045cbe04808c91db7a511b1f881" name="Scotty.McLennan" sectnum="1.4.1#1">../img/4d9cb045cbe04808c91db7a511b1f881.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>