<document id="0b70416f7bbf38c21234300ba2ff90ae-2.7.2" name="Stanford_Memorial_Church" cat="1">
<text>
According to architectural historian Willis L. Hall, the church's 20 large stained glass windows "are as much a feature of the church as the mosaics".Hall, p.   The windows, designed by Frederick Stymetz Lamb (1863–1928) and fabricated by J&R Lamb Studios, his father's firm in New York City, took three years to complete, and eight months to install at Stanford.Gregg, p. 60  Jane Stanford hired Lamb because she felt he was more interested in "the ecclesiastical rather than commercial aspect of the work".Gregg, p. 21  The installation of the windows at Stanford Memorial Church was the largest enterprise of its kind at the time, and the project is considered one of the best examples of Lamb's work.  Stanford chose the life of Christ for the windows' theme, inspired by the religious paintings by European master painters such as Shields and Doré.  Her personal touch is shown in one of the nave windows, which is based on a cartoon by Paoletti and depicts Christ welcoming the soul of a child into Heaven before the eyes of its grieving mother, an allusion to the death of Leland Stanford, Jr., the Stanfords' only child and the university's namesake, who died in 1884 of typhoid shortly before his 16th birthday.  

Oberhausen, who has studied the source of the mosaics and windows, states that at least four stained glass windows were inspired by the paintings of Pre-Raphaelite artists that were enjoying a resurgence in popularity at the time.  These windows are: "Christ in the Temple" in the east transept, based upon a painting by William Holman Hunt; "The Annunciation" in the east nave, inspired by a work by Frederic Shields; "The Nativity" in the chancel, based upon a painting by Edward Fellowes-Prynne; and "The Good Shepherd" in the west transept, inspired by a painting by Sibyl C. Parker, the only female artist represented in the artwork of the church.  None of the windows of Stanford Memorial Church required replacement after the 1906 quake, except for "the famous rose window of the original structure" in the organ loft which was replaced by the current large, central arch window.  This window, entitled "Lilies of the Field", is the only window in the church that cannot be viewed from the inside because it is blocked off by the central organ.Gregg, p. 37  There is a cross in the center of this window made of "faceted pieces of glass that are inset like gems", which sparkle when light strikes it.

The church's clerestory contains many smaller windows of individuals from the Bible or Christian history.  The windows in the nave above the east arcade depict the following Old Testament figures: Abraham, Hagar and her child Ishmael, Moses, Pharaoh's Daughter, Joshua, and Deborah.  The windows in the east transept depict David, Ruth, Solomon, The Queen of Sheba, Elijah, Esther, Isaiah, Judith, Daniel, and Hannah.  In the nave above the west arcade feature saints and virtues: Stephen, Agnes, Peter, Priscilla, John, and Hope.  In the west transept are Simeon, Anne, Matthew, Faith, Mark, Charity, Luke, Dorcas, Paul, and Martha.  The clerestory above the east and west doors are two windows of angels.  Unlike the other windows throughout the church, they do not receive natural light from outside and are artificially illuminated instead.




'''East Nave'''


'''West Nave'''




'''East transept'''The best time to view these windows is in the early morning.


'''West Transept'''



'''Chancel'''
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="133dd824d6d56007e0e02e0894853d87" name="Stanfordchurch-ascension" sectnum="2.7.2#1">../img/133dd824d6d56007e0e02e0894853d87.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>