<document id="0b70416f7bbf38c21234300ba2ff90ae-3" name="Stanford_Memorial_Church" cat="1">
<text>
Although the Stanfords were religious and viewed "spiritual and moral values as essential to a young person's education and future citizenship", they were not formally committed to any Christian denomination.  As a result, Jane Stanford decreed, from the beginning of Stanford Memorial Church's history, that the church be non-denominational.  She believed that adopting this philosophy would "serve the broadest spiritual needs of the university community".  The church's first chaplain, Charles Gardner, declared on the day of its dedication that the church's goal was to serve the spiritual needs of the university in a non-sectarian way.  The Stanfords' goal was that moral instruction would occur at the church, as demonstrated in the inscriptions carved into its walls, which was influenced by the late 19th-century liberal Protestantism they embraced.Gregg, p. 9  As former Stanford chaplain Robert C. Gregg states, "The Stanfords sought to protect free intellectual inquiry—in classroom, laboratory, and church—from any interference prompted by the caution or dogmatism of religious authorities".Gregg, p. 10

Stanford Memorial Church was the earliest interdenominational church on the west coast of the U.S. and has remained "among the most prominent".  Multi-faith services are held at Stanford Memorial Church, in addition to denominational and non-denominational Christian services.  As many as 150 weddings take place in the church each year as well as many memorial services for people affiliated with the university. Members of the university community use it for "quiet, for reflection, and for private devotions".  The church also hosts frequent musical performances from Stanford's own choirs and orchestra, as well as visiting groups such as the vocal ensemble Chanticleer.  Catholic masses are held in the church several times a week. Offertories at the principal Sunday services are donated to local charitable organizations.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e3653ab72aa0a76576a3278345c29ab2" name="Memchu_wedding" sectnum="3#1">../img/e3653ab72aa0a76576a3278345c29ab2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>