<document id="0b70416f7bbf38c21234300ba2ff90ae-2.7.3" name="Stanford_Memorial_Church" cat="1">
<text>
The mosaic project began in 1900 and took five years to complete.  Jane Stanford chose mosaics to decorate her church because of the similar weather in Italy and Northern California, where the moderate climates and rainy seasons in both settings protect the images from erosion and clear the pollution that accumulates on many buildings in large cities.  As Hall states, the "mosaics on the facade are always clear and brilliant."Hall, p. 19  Their "shimmering quality" was created by different tones of green and gold; the artists that installed the mosaics had over 20,000 shades of colors to choose from.  The images cost US$97,000,This figure is the equivalent of almost US$2 million in 2002. and were based upon original watercolors created by artist Antonio Paoletti.Salviati & Company also designed and built eight large mosaics in Stanford's museum and decorated the vestibuile of the university's mausoleum.  Jane Stanford worked closely with Paoletti, planning a combination of Old Testament and New Testament scenes that represented men and women equally.  

The mosaic adorning the church's chancel is a reproduction of Roselli's fresco of the Last Supper from the Sistine Chapel in the Vatican.  Camerino obtained permission from Pope Leo XIII to reproduce it at Stanford Memorial Church.  Unlike other works, which were reproduced frequently, it was the only reproduction of Roselli's fresco at the time.Hall, p.   Artisan Lorenzo Zampato was given the task of supervising the in-studio fabrication and final installation at Stanford.  There are 12 mosaics in each transept balcony that are split into two sets of six, creating an arc of six mosaics, ten windows, and six mosaics.  Most of the church's mosaics were made from 1/8-inch tiles; larger 3/4-inch tiles were used on the higher mosaics, and smaller 1/4-inch tiles were used in "The Last Supper" mosaic.Gregg, p. 52  Mosaics are "virtually everywhere" inside the church and have been described as "a perfect complement to Frederick Lamb's stained-glass windows".List taken from Hall, pp. 31–33
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="32882e28718c11fd147d79e53b2d15c0" name="Memchu_mosaics" sectnum="2.7.3#1">../img/32882e28718c11fd147d79e53b2d15c0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>