<document id="0b70416f7bbf38c21234300ba2ff90ae-1.3" name="Stanford_Memorial_Church" cat="1">
<text>
Before the 1950s, Stanford "had the reputation of being a completely secular university".Harvey, p. 3  Stanford professor Van Harvey refers to this as a "background of aggressive secularism and the almost complete neglect of the academic study of religion".  In 1946, Merrimon Cuninggim, a visiting chaplain at Stanford Memorial Church, criticized the "dearth" of religious and spiritual resources available at Stanford for its students and criticized the university's  lack of academic courses offered in the study of religions.  Cuninggim insisted that the university's administration and trustees were responsible because they had interpreted the non-sectarian clause in Stanford's charter in "a negative and restrictive fashion rather than as enabling the tolerance and the flourishing of many religious faiths on campus".  

Cuninggim also charged that Stanford's religious policies were inadequate compared to other prominent U.S. universities.  Harvey speculated that if Stanford had established a seminary like other prestigious universities, its religious studies department and the "ethos" of the entire institution would be different.  In 1966, however, the Board of Trustees got a court order that allowed them to change the non-sectarian clause in Stanford's charter so that they could expand the university's religious program, which included permitting sectarian worship services at Stanford Memorial Church.

Stanford did not employ a full-time professor in religion until 1951 and did not establish a religious studies department until 1973, later than most other universities in the U.S.  Earlier courses in religion were largely offered by the chaplains of Stanford Memorial Church.  David Charles Gardner offered a course in Biblical history and literature beginning in 1907, and by 1910, he was teaching New Testament Greek and Bible classes.  Gardner's successor, D. Elton Trueblood, taught classes about the philosophy of religion.  In 1941 Trueblood's efforts to expand the study of religion resulted in the creation of a minor in religion, as well as twenty-one courses offered by him and four faculty members.  By 1960, the chaplains of Stanford Memorial Church no longer had to run the program, which had expanded to allow students the option of majoring in the study of religion.Harvey, pp. 4–6  By the mid-1960s, the religious studies program at Stanford was enjoying "enormous success".Harvey, p. 6

In the 1960s, the study of religion at Stanford focused not on academics, but on social and ethical issues like race and the Vietnam War.  Leading this focus was Stanford Memorial Church chaplain David Napier, who was "a powerful critic of U.S. policy in Vietnam".  Napier, along with Stanford professors Michael Novak and Robert McAfee Brown, were the subject of a ''Time Magazine'' article in 1966, describing "the renaissance of faith and learning at Stanford".  Students crowded into the church to hear anti-war speeches by them, as well as by "notables" such as Linus Pauling and William Sloan Coffin.

In 1993, Stanford became the first major educational institution in the United States to give formal permission allowing same-sex commitment ceremonies at its chapel.  The first ceremony, called "vows of commitment", took place on Labor Day, September 6, 1993, and was performed by Associate Dean of the Chapel, Diana Akiyama.  Stanford's Memorial Church's dean at the time, Robert Gregg, obtained permission from the university administration and discussed it with his staff before the ceremony was performed.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6ff1e9da362874ef08190f722e3276cc" name="MichaelNovak" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/6ff1e9da362874ef08190f722e3276cc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>