<document id="0bea422cf6b12f623ca25749efc42c4e-3.2" name="Mary:_A_Fiction" cat="17">
<text>
One of the key differences between Wollstonecraft's novels and her philosophical treatises, as feminist critic Cora Kaplan has argued, is that her fiction celebrates female emotion and argues for its value while her treatises present emotion as "reactionary and regressive, almost counter-revolutionary".Kaplan, 35. Johnson has extended this argument and contends that Wollstonecraft is interested in presenting the benefits of romantic friendship over marriage: "whereas Wollstonecraft shrinks from homosocial 'familiarity' and advocates the ennobling properties of domestic heterosexuality in ''Rights of Woman'', her novels not only resist the heterosexual plot, but displace it with protolesbian narratives wrested from sentimentality itself."Johnson, ''Equivocal Beings'', 48; for a deeper discussion of this idea, see Tauchert's "Escaping Discussion". While many critics have argued that Mary "capitulates to" or "matures into" both sentimentality and heterosexuality, Johnson's interpretation has become the standard.


Mary's relationship with Ann challenges the definition of friendship; as Johnson explains, it "is no ordinary friendship". Mary looks to Ann, in Wollstonecraft's words, "to experience the pleasure of being beloved".Wollstonecraft, ''Mary'' (Kelly), 8. Mary is "coded as masculine (agentive, sublime) while Ann is stereotypically feminine in  'die-away' delicacy".Johnson, "Mary Wollstonecraft's novels", 194. This gendered divide is even reflected in Mary's choice of reading material; she reads books associated with the masculine sublime such as Edward Young's ''Night Thoughts'' (1742–45) and John Milton's ''Paradise Lost'' (1667). Although Ann does not feel the love for Mary that Mary does for her, Mary devotedly nurses Ann and is distraught by her death.Johnson, ''Equivocal Beings'', 54; Todd, ''A Revolutionary Life'', 113; Hoeveler, 35; Kelly, ''Revolutionary Feminism'', 50.  The unusual intensity of this relationship is revealed in Wollstonecraft's description of Mary's sorrow:

The ladies . . . began to administer some common–place comfort, as, that it was our duty to submit to the will of Heaven, and the like trite consolations, which Mary did not answer; but waving her hand, with an air of impatience, she exclaimed, "I cannot live without her! — I have no other friend; if I lose her, what a desart  will the world be to me." "No other friend," re–echoed they, "have you not a husband?"  Mary shrunk back, and was alternately pale and red. A delicate sense of propriety prevented her from replying; and recalled her bewildered reason.Wollstonecraft, ''Mary'' (Kelly), 26.

Johnson cautions against labelling Mary and Ann's relationship lesbian, since the identity-defining concepts of heterosexuality and homosexuality did not exist during the eighteenth century; she maintains, rather, that their relationship is a bond which cannot be articulated through language. This bond is perhaps best described as erotic rather than overtly sexual.Johnson, ''Equivocal Beings'', 54–55; for a discussion of Wollstonecraft's sexuality, see Kelly, "Female Philosopher in the Bedroom". Further evidence to support such an interpretation comes from Wollstonecraft's life. Wollstonecraft based her portrait of Ann on her close friend, Fanny Blood, and when her husband, William Godwin, came to write his ''Memoirs of the Author of A Vindication of the Rights of Woman'' (1798), he described Fanny and Wollstonecraft's first meeting as similar to the one between the tortured lovers Charlotte and Werther in Goethe's sentimental novel ''The Sorrows of Young Werther'' (1774).Johnson, ''Equivocal Beings'', 53. One biographer of Wollstonecraft notes that Hester Chapone's ''Letters on the Improvement of the Mind'', which influenced Wollstonecraft's earlier ''Thoughts on the Education of Daughters'' (1787), dedicates several chapters to these "friends of the heart"; such friendships would not have seemed unusual to eighteenth-century readers.Sunstein, 46.

After Ann's death, Mary replaces her with Henry; as Johnson writes, "this tale of forbidden and unnarratable passionate friendship becomes a tale of forbidden but narratable adulterous love".Johnson, ''Equivocal Beings'', 56; see also Todd, ''A Revolutionary Life'', 114. Like Ann, Henry is a feminine counterpart to Mary's masculine persona. Mary's relationship with Henry is both erotic and paternal:

he thought of him till she began to chide herself for defrauding the dead, and, determining to grieve for Ann, she dwelt on Henry's misfortune and ill health . . . she thought with rapture that there was one person in the world who had an affection for her, and that person she admired — had a friendship for. He had called her his dear girl . . . My child! His child, what an association of ideas! If I had a father, such a father! — She could not dwell on the thoughts, the wishes which obtruded themselves. Her mind was unhinged, and passion unperceived filled her whole soul.Wollstonecraft, ''Mary'' (Kelly), 36.

In Johnson's interpretation, Mary does not replace Ann with a masculine lover as one might expect in a sentimental novel but rather with a "feminine", yet still acceptably male, lover.Johnson, ''Equivocal Beings'', 56.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="768de4d7433b4067d923004a34fc8465" name="WertherTomb" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/768de4d7433b4067d923004a34fc8465.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>