<document id="0c5be5dc86307128f0d52ce983107ce7-2.1" name="Maynard_James_Keenan" cat="20">
<text>
After moving to Los Angeles, Keenan met Adam Jones, who had heard him singing on a demo in college, and Jones suggested that they form a band. Although reluctant at first, Keenan agreed and, in 1990, Tool was formed. Fronted by Keenan, the eventual lineup included guitarist Jones; his neighbor, drummer Danny Carey; and bassist Paul D'Amour, who would later be replaced by Justin Chancellor.

Keenan performing as a part of Tool at 2006's Roskilde Festival

Tool signed to Zoo Entertainment in November 1991 and released the ''Opiate'' EP the following year. To support this release, the band toured with Fishbone and Rage Against the Machine. During a 1993 show at the Church of Scientology’s Celebrity Centre in Los Angeles, Keenan (who would later write the lyrics "Fuck L. Ron Hubbard and fuck all his clones") baa-ed like a sheep for a good portion of the show. "Before our set this guy tries to intimidate me by showing me a gun in his jacket," Keenan recalled. "I explained to him that if he pissed me off I’d start a riot." Shortly thereafter, Tool released their 1993 debut album, ''Undertow'', in the United States, where it was certified gold after just eight months, and platinum less than a year later. In 1994, the band released their single "Prison Sex"—a song in which Keenan opted to deliver in a slight grunge-style—with a corresponding music video created and directed by Jones. The video was deemed "too graphic and offensive", and was withdrawn by MTV after a few airings due to "a symbolic dealing with the sensitive subject of child abuse".

In October 1996, the band released their second studio album, ''Ænima'', which was certified gold in ten weeks and achieved double platinum in ten months. In 1998, "Ænema" won the Grammy Award for Best Metal Performance. After the release of the album, Tool began a prolonged legal battle with their label Volcano Records (formerly Zoo Records) over alleged contract violations. Following this legal battle, which resulted in a new three-record deal, the members of Tool decided to take some time off. During the hiatus, the band members were outspokenly critical of filesharing networks, due to the negative financial impact on artists dependent on success in record sales. During an interview with ''NY Rock'' in 2000, Keenan stated, "I think there are a lot of other industries out there that might deserve being destroyed. The ones who get hurt by MP3s are not so much companies or the business, but the artists, people who are trying to write songs."



Five years after the release of ''Ænima'', Tool announced a new album, ''Systema Encéphale'', with a 12-song tracklist in January 2001. A month later, the band revealed that the new album was actually titled ''Lateralus'' and that the name ''Systema Encéphale'' and the tracklist had been a ruse. The album was released in May 2001 to positive reviews. Known for his "dark, intelligent, compelling, and unexpected lyrical twists", Keenan was acclaimed for his songwriting on the album, in which he "doesn’t cross the line from darkness to ugliness ... as often as he has in the past". In an interview with  ''NY Rock'', Keenan explained, "Everything we release with Tool is inspired by our music. It doesn't matter if it is a video or if its lyrics. The lyrics for "Schism" are nothing more than my interpretation of the music." The album became a worldwide success, reaching #1 on the U.S. ''Billboard'' 200 albums chart in its debut week, and Tool received their second Grammy Award for the best metal performance of 2001 for "Schism".

Fifteen years after the band's formation, Tool had acquired what Dan Epstein of ''Revolver'' described as a devoted "cult" following, and in May 2006, the band released ''10,000 Days'', an album in which Keenan sang about more personal issues, in contrast to previous attempts to inspire change. His mother is the inspiration for two tracks on the album; the two-part song "Wings for Marie" and "10,000 Days (Wings for Marie, Pt 2)", and "Jambi"McAlley, p. 88. which deals with her 2003 death after 27 years, or around 10,000 days, of suffering. The album sold 564,000 copies in its opening week in the U.S. and was #1 on the ''Billboard'' 200 charts. However, ''10,000 Days'' was received less favorably by critics than its predecessor ''Lateralus'' had been.Metacritic calculated an average score of 68 for ''10,000 Days'' compared to 75 for ''Lateralus''. 

Following ''10,000 Days'', Tool had one album remaining to fulfill the obligation of its record contract. Though there is no information available on any plans for this album, Tool has worked around Keenan and his side projects since 1999, starting with the creation of A Perfect Circle, which has led to several years between projects. Regarding the future of Tool, Keenan stated in a 2007 interview with ''Spin'', "We'll make music together until one of us is dead."

On March 24, 2009, it was announced on Tool's website that a summer tour was set with dates still to be confirmed; and periodic updates are made for confirmed dates. In a March 26 press release, Tool was confirmed as a headliner for the second annual Mile High Music Festival in Commerce City, Colorado, with Widespread Panic and The Fray on July 18&ndash;19. Tool has also been confirmed as a headliner in Lollapalooza on August 7&ndash;9 in Chicago, Illinois.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1382e031e80204895481af203ed0243b" name="Maynard_ruisrock2006" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/1382e031e80204895481af203ed0243b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>