<document id="0c8667ae0f48f6e6984ca47b005890de-2.12" name="War_of_the_Fifth_Coalition" cat="29">
<text>
In Italy, Archduke John went up against Napoleon's stepson Eugène. The Austrians beat back several bungled French assaults at the Battle of Sacile in April, causing Eugène to fall back on Verona and the Adige River, but Eugène regrouped and launched a more mature offensive that expelled the Austrians from Northern Italy again. By the time of Wagram, Eugène's forces had joined Napoleon's main army.Fisher & Fremont-Barnes p. 122 In Dalmatia, Marmont, under the nominal command of Eugène, was fighting against General Stoichewich. Marmont launched a mountain offensive on 30 April, but this was repulsed by the Grenzer troops.Fisher & Fremont-Barnes p. 123 Like Eugène, however, Marmont did not let an initial setback dictate the tempo of the conflict. He went back on the offensive and joined Napoleon at Wagram.

In the Duchy of Warsaw, Poniatowski defeated the Austrians  at Raszyn on 19 April, prevented Austrian forces from crossing the Vistula river, invaded Austria and forced the Austrians to retreat from occupied Warsaw (see Polish-Austrian War). In Tyrol, Andreas Hofer led a rebellion against Bavarian rule and French domination that resulted in early isolated victories, but the uprising was suppressed after the French won at Wagram. Hofer was executed in 1810 by firing squad.

In Saxony, a joint force of Austrians and Brunswickers under the command of General Kienmayer was far more successful, defeating a corps under the command of General Junot at the Battle of Gefrees. After taking the capital, Dresden, and pushing back an army under the command of Napoleon's brother, Jérôme Bonaparte, the Austrians were effectively in control of all of Saxony. But by this time, the main Austrian force had already been defeated at Wagram and the armistice of Znaim had been agreed.F. Loraine Petre, ''Napoleon and the Archduke Charles''. p. 318

In the Netherlands, the British launched the Walcheren Campaign to relieve the pressure on the Austrians. The British force of over 39,000, a larger army than that serving in the Iberian Peninsula, landed at Walcheren on 30 July. However, by this time the Austrians had already lost the war. The Walcheren Campaign was characterized by little fighting but many casualties nevertheless, thanks to the popularly dubbed "Walcheren Fever". Over 4,000 British troops were lost, and the rest withdrew in December 1809.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="eb27e33834c2d9779090f627500b2d8b" name="Death_of_Poniatowski" sectnum="2.12#1">../img/eb27e33834c2d9779090f627500b2d8b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>