<document id="0c9624e7f1fc9451e164183fcb453db0-6" name="Cool_(song)" cat="20">
<text>
The song's music video was directed by Sophie Muller and filmed in Lake Como, Italy.Collis, Clark. . ''Entertainment Weekly''. December 1, 2006: issue #909. Retrieved April 11, 2007. The video follows the song's theme very closely and depicts the relationship that Stefani has with a former boyfriend, who is played by Spanish actor Daniel González. González and his new girlfriend (played by Tony Kanal's girlfriend, Erin Lokitz) are shown walking to a house. Stefani answers the door, and the three of them are seen in each other's company, with intercut scenes of Stefani rolling around on a bed. There are brief flashbacks to the time when Stefani and her former boyfriend were dating, where she wears a brunette wig, representing her younger self (her natural brown hair has not been seen since she was in ninth grade).Toht, Betony.  .  ''In Style''.  Retrieved April 28, 2007. Flashbacks and modern day are linked with match cut cinematography. The lyrical theme of "Cool" is maintained in the video, frames are incorporated to portray Stefani feeling "cool". She is depicted as "cool" with her former boyfriend and his girlfriend throughout most of the video. 



The video showcases the scenery of Como's forests, lakes and restaurants and was the first from ''Love. Angel. Music. Baby.'' not to include Stefani's Harajuku Girls, who were present throughout the majority of the album's promotion. The complete version of "Cool" featured in the music video was released commercially on CD single and digital download formats and introduced an orchestral arrangement that differs from the original 1980s composition on ''Love. Angel. Music. Baby''.

"Cool" premiered on MTV's top-ten chart program ''Total Request Live'' on June 30, 2005,. PopFusion.  Retrieved January 30, 2007. where it reached number three. On VH1's ''Top 20 Video Countdown'', the video peaked at number two.. VH1.com. Information on Gwen Stefani. Retrieved January 30, 2007. After its July 8 debut on MuchMusic's ''Countdown'', it reached number one for the week of October 7.''#1s''. MuchMusic programming. Original airdate: October 2006. Retrieved January 30, 2007. "Cool" debuted and peaked at number nine on LAUNCHcast's top one-hundred most-watched videos for the week of July 23.LAUNCHcast. . Retrieved January 30, 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="67e9f77115c57c94cd3163044ec9e5ad" name="CoolCap1" sectnum="6#1">../img/67e9f77115c57c94cd3163044ec9e5ad.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>