<document id="0d379f070fbd5492f0363ed8c8400c26-2" name="Voyage_of_the_James_Caird" cat="14">
<text>
Elephant Island, on the easterly edges of the South Shetland Islands, was remote from anywhere that the expedition had planned to go, and far beyond normal shipping routes. No relief ship would search for them there, and the likelihood of rescue from any other outside agency was equally negligible. Shackleton, pp. 156&ndash;57

It was clear to Shackleton that he needed to act to secure the party's deliverance. The island was bleak and inhospitable, and its terrain devoid of vegetation, although it had fresh water, and a relative abundance of seals and penguins to provide food and fuel for immediate survival.Huntford, p. 523 The rigours of an Antarctic winter were fast approaching; the narrow shingle beach upon which they were camped was already being swept by almost continuous gales and blizzards, which rapidly destroyed one of the tents in their temporary camp, and knocked others flat.Alexander, pp. 130&ndash;32 The pressures and hardships of the previous months were beginning to tell on the men, many of whom were in a run-down state both mentally and physically.

Consequently, Shackleton determined to set out for help without delay in one of the boats. The nearest port where help could be obtained with certainty was Stanley in the Falkland Islands, 540 miles (1,000 km) away, but unreachable due to the prevailing westerly winds. Another possibility was to head for Deception Island, at the western end of the South Sandwich chain. Although uninhabited, Admiralty records indicated that this island held stores for shipwrecked mariners, and was also visited from time to time by whalers.Shackleton, p. 119 However, this would mean a journey against the prevailing winds, with no certainty of when rescue would arrive. After discussions with the expedition's second-in-command, Frank Wild, and ship's captain Frank Worsley, Shackleton decided to attempt to reach the whaling stations of South Georgia, to the north-east. This would mean a much longer boat journey, of 800 miles (1,500 km) across the Southern Ocean, in conditions of rapidly approaching winter. However, it offered the possibility of more rapid relief. As Shackleton later wrote, "a boat party might make the voyage and be back with relief within a month, provided that the sea was clear of ice, and the boat survive the great seas".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b7d3bbd639662c4fbacf5004ee4ed676" name="Elephantlanding" sectnum="2#1">../img/b7d3bbd639662c4fbacf5004ee4ed676.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>