<document id="0d379f070fbd5492f0363ed8c8400c26-1" name="Voyage_of_the_James_Caird" cat="14">
<text>
On 5 December 1914, Shackleton's expedition ship ''Endurance'' left South Georgia for the Weddell Sea, on the first stage of the Imperial Trans-Antarctic Expedition.Shackleton, p. 3 Its destination was Vahsel Bay, the southernmost explored point of the Weddell Sea at 77°49'S, where a shore party was to land and prepare for a trans-continental crossing.Huntford, p. 367 Before it could reach this spot the ship was trapped in pack ice, and by 14 February 1915 was firmly beset, despite prolonged efforts to free her.Shackleton, pp. 29&ndash;34 During the following eight months she drifted northward until, on 27 October, she was crushed by the pack's pressure, finally sinking on 21 November.Shackleton, p. 98 Shackleton was forced to abandon his plans for a trans-continental crossing, and his 27-man crew set up camp on the slowly-moving ice.Huntford, p. 460

It was now a question of deciding how the expedition could best save itself. Shackleton's initial plans, to march across the pack ice to the nearest land and then try to reach a point where ships were known to visit,Huntford, pp456&ndash;57 were thwarted by the nature of the ice's surface. It was later described by Shackleton as "soft, much broken up, open leads intersecting the floes at all angles", which made travel almost impossible.Shackleton, p. 102&ndash;06 After struggling to make headway over several days, the march was abandoned; the party established "Patience Camp" on a flat ice floe, and waited as the drift carried them further north, towards open water.Shackleton, pp. 107&ndash;116 They had with them three lifeboats, which Shackleton named after the principal backers of the expedition: ''Stancomb Wills'', ''Dudley Docker'' and ''James Caird''. Huntford, p. 469 They waited more than three months until, on 8 April 1916, the men took to the boats as the ice started to break up. Over a perilous period of seven days they rowed through stormy seas and dangerous loose ice, to reach the temporary haven of Elephant Island on 15 April.Shackleton, pp. 120&ndash;43. Shackleton (p. 143) claimed it as the first landing ever on the island.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4dfce6ad67993f6386580584d120574f" name="EnduranceEnd" sectnum="1#1">../img/4dfce6ad67993f6386580584d120574f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>