<document id="0d59d6f5c28ce2f7517136922f8783d4-1.2" name="The_Lucy_poems" cat="17">
<text>
Between October 1798 and February 1799, Wordsworth worked on the first draft of the "Lucy poems" together with a number of other verses, including the "Matthew poems", "Lucy Gray" and ''The Prelude''. Coleridge had yet to join the siblings in Germany, and Wordsworth's separation from his friend depressed him. In the three months following their parting, Wordsworth completed the first three of the "Lucy poems": "Strange fits", "She dwelt", and "A slumber".Matlak 1978, 46–47 They first appeared in a letter to Coleridge dated December 1798, in which Wordsworth wrote that "She dwelt" and "Strange fits" were "little Rhyme poems which I hope will amuse you".Wordsworth 1967, 236 Wordsworth characterised the two poems thus to mitigate any disappointment Coleridge might suffer in receiving these two poems instead of the promised three-part philosophical epic ''The Recluse''.Moorman 1968, 422 In the same letter, Wordsworth complained that:

Wordsworth partially blamed Dorothy for the abrupt loss of Coleridge's company. He felt that their finances&mdash;insufficient for supporting them both in Ratzeburg&mdash;would have easily supported him alone, allowing him to follow Coleridge. Wordsworth's anguish was compounded by the contrast between his life and that of his friend. Coleridge's financial means allowed him to entertain lavishly and to seek the company of nobles and intellectuals; Wordsworth's limited wealth constrained him to a quiet and modest life. Wordsworth's envy seeped into his letters when he described Coleridge and his new friends as "more favored sojourners" who may "be chattering and chatter'd to, through the whole day".Matlak 1978, 50; Wordsworth 1967, 254 Although Wordsworth sought emotional support from his sister, their relationship remained strained throughout their time in Germany. Separated from his friend and forced to live in the sole company of his sister, Wordsworth used the "Lucy poems" as an emotional outlet.Matlak 1978, 50–51
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9e951590a5263e498c67622c13c2a619" name="SamuelTaylorColeridge" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/9e951590a5263e498c67622c13c2a619.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>