<document id="0d59d6f5c28ce2f7517136922f8783d4-1.1" name="The_Lucy_poems" cat="17">
<text>
In 1798 Wordsworth and Samuel Taylor Coleridge jointly published ''Lyrical Ballads, with a Few Other Poems'', a collection of verses each had written separately. The book became hugely popular and was published widely; it is generally considered a herald of the Romantic movement in English literature.Wu 1999, 189–90Gilbert; Allen; and Clark 1962, 198 In it, Wordsworth aimed to use everyday language in his compositionsMurray 1967, qtd in 5 as set out in the preface to the 1802 edition: "The principal object, then, proposed in these Poems was to choose incidents and situations from common life, and to relate or describe them, throughout, as far as was possible in a selection of language really used by men, and at the same time, to throw over them a certain colouring of imagination, whereby ordinary things should be presented to the mind in an unusual aspect."  

The two poets had met three years earlier in either late August or September 1795 in Bristol.Sisman 2006, 111–112 The meeting laid the foundation for an intense and profoundly creative friendship, based in part on their shared disdain for the artificial diction of the poetry of the era. Beginning in 1797, the two lived within walking distance of each other in Somerset, which solidified their friendship. Wordsworth believed that his life before meeting Coleridge was sedentary and dull, and that his poetry amounted to little. Coleridge influenced Wordsworth, and his praise and encouragement inspired Wordsworth to write prolifically.Matlak 1978, 48 Dorothy, Wordsworth's sister, related the effect Coleridge had on her brother in a March 1798 letter: "His faculties seem to expand every day, he composes with much more facility than he did, as to the ''mechanism''  of poetry, and his ideas flow faster than he can express them."Wordsworth 1967, 200 With his new inspiration, Wordsworth came to believe he could write poetry rivaling that of John Milton.Alexander 1987, 62 He and Coleridge planned to collaborate, but never moved beyond suggestions and notes for each other.Gill 1989, 131 

The expiration of Wordsworth's Alfoxton House lease soon provided an opportunity for the two friends to live together. They conceived a plan to settle in Germany with Dorothy and Coleridge's wife, Sara, "to pass the two ensuing years in order to acquire the German language, and to furnish ourselves with a tolerable stock of information in natural science".In a letter to James Losh dated 11 March 1798. Wordsworth 1967, 212 In September 1798, Wordsworth, Coleridge, and Dorothy travelled to Germany to explore proximate living arrangements, but this proved difficult. Although they lived together in Hamburg for a short time, the city was too expensive for their budgets. Coleridge soon found accommodations in the town of Ratzeburg in Schleswig-Holstein, which was less expensive but still socially vibrant. The impoverished Wordsworth, however, could neither afford to follow Coleridge nor provide for himself and his sister in Hamburg; the siblings instead moved to moderately-priced accommodations in Goslar in Lower Saxony, Germany.Matlak 1978, 49–50
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fb6b488e781811cef2a291d1387ef33d" name="Lyrical_Ballads" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/fb6b488e781811cef2a291d1387ef33d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>