<document id="0e3b7ad51f5ff913c546cb88b198c525-7" name="Arthur_Morris" cat="26">
<text>
With the retirement of Hassett following the 1953 England tour, the Australian captaincy was open for competition.Cashman, pp. 119&ndash;120. No international cricket was scheduled until 1954&ndash;55, so there was a full domestic season in 1953&ndash;54 for players to stake their claims. Morris started strongly with consecutive centuries against Queensland and South Australia, but was unable to maintain his form, passing fifty only twice in his remaining eight innings. He ended with 487 runs at 54.11 as New South Wales won the Sheffield Shield under Miller's leadership.Perry (2005), pp. 348&ndash;349. Nevertheless, the Australian selectors indicated that they were considering Morris as a captaincy option by making him captain of Morris's XI, which played Hassett's XI in a testimonial match. Morris's XI won by 121 runs.

At the start of the next season, Morris was not made Australian captain despite being the incumbent vice-captain. Instead, he was remained as deputy as Victoria's Ian Johnson was recalled to the team and assumed the captaincy. There was speculation that the two Queensland board members voted for Morris, the three New South Wales delegates voted for Miller and, while the remainder voted Johnson.Perry (2005), pp. 350&ndash;350.Haigh and Frith, p. 113. When England returned to Australia in 1954&ndash;55, Morris made his first Test century in almost four years during the opening Test at Brisbane. After English skipper Len Hutton won the toss and controversially sent Australia in,Perry (2005), p. 353.Haigh, p. 87. Morris made 153 to lay the foundation for a score of 8/601 declared and an innings victory. This included a partnership of 202 runs with Neil Harvey. The pair scored at a rate of nearly four runs per over, despite both players being repeatedly struck by the bowling of Frank Tyson, who was regarded as the fastest bowler of his era.Perry (2001), pp. 93&ndash;94. Those were the only centuries made by Australian batsmen for the entire series, and Morris was covered in bruises; he deliberately used his body to fend off short-pitched balls rather than risk a catch.Robinson, pp. 215&ndash;216.

In the Second Test in Sydney, Johnson and Miller were both unavailable due to injury; Morris led the team for the second and final time in Tests.McHarg, p. 133. The Australian Board of Control made the surprising move of appointing the young and inexperienced Richie Benaud as Morris' vice-captain for the match. Benaud, selected as a batsman, had scored just 195 runs at 13.92 in ten Test matches and was not a regular member of the team. Benaud noted that the situation was embarrassing and that Morris had asked him not to be offended if he sought advice from veteran players Ray Lindwall and Harvey, who had been Test regulars for seven years.Cashman, pp. 118&ndash;119, 174&ndash;175. Morris won the toss and elected to bat on a green pitch, in  match marred by time-wasting. Although Australia took a first innings lead, they lost the low-scoring match by 38 runs after a batting collapse in the face of a Tyson pace barrage on the final day.Benaud, p. 92.Pollard, p. 84.Haigh, pp. 89&ndash;90. Aided by a powerful tailwind, Tyson bowled at extreme pace and the slips cordon stood 45 m away from the wicket.Piesse, p. 182. Morris added a poor personal performance, scores of 12 and 10, to the disappointment of his team's defeat. He failed to pass 25 in either of the following Tests as Australia fell 3&ndash;1 behind with a hat-trick of losses and he was dropped for the Fifth Test, ending the series with 223 runs at 31.86.McHarg, p. 210. Aside from the First Test century, Morris struggled throughout the entire season, passing fifty on only one other occasion and managing only 382 runs at 31.83. 

Morris' international farewell was the 1954&ndash;55 tour of the West Indies. Prior to the tour, Miller replaced him as Australian vice-captain.Perry (2005), p. 357. He struck 157 against Jamaica in his first tour match, earning a recall to the Test team.Perry (2001), pp. 94&ndash;95. He made 65 in the First Test victory in Kingston, Jamaica, before making his final Test century (111) in the drawn Second Test in Port of Spain, Trinidad. He made 44 and 38 in the Third Test win and then missed the Fourth Test with dysentery. He scored seven in his final Test innings in the Fifth Test, which Australia won by an innings to seal the series 3&ndash;0. Morris ended the Test series with 266 runs at 44.33. In his final tour in Australian colours, Morris totalled 577 runs at 57.45 in seven first-class matches.

Returning to Sydney after the West Indian tour, Morris learned that his new wife Valerie had been diagnosed with breast cancer in his absence. She had concealed her illness until his return, fearing that it would distract him from his cricket.Pollard, p. 96.Haigh, p. 251. With his wife's condition deteriorating over the following year despite the removal of a breast, Morris retired at the age of 33, as he realised that his wife's condition was terminal and that their marriage would soon be over. Morris scored centuries on his first first-class appearances in four countries: England, South Africa, the West Indies and Australia, a record not equalled as of 1997. In general, he was known for scoring centuries in his debut appearance at many grounds. His eight centuries against England was second only to Bradman. He was a popular player, highly lauded by Australian and English commentators for both his character, goodwill and ability. His childhood mentor O'Reilly said that he was a "man worth knowing", while Tyson called him "one of cricket's patricians...endowed with a genteel equanimity, without seeming aloof or less than cordial and friendly".McHarg, p. 192.McHarg, p. 173. The English commentator John Arlott, known for rarely praising an Australian, said that Morris "was one of the best-liked cricketers of all time &ndash; charming, philosophical and relaxed".McHarg, p. 17.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9e2813c27002990e62fecff5a46fb9aa" name="Morris_Hutton" sectnum="7#1">../img/9e2813c27002990e62fecff5a46fb9aa.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>