<document id="0ec5ef4ac923dcb81b1fe684bf59e90f-1.4" name="Zelda_Fitzgerald" cat="17">
<text>
After arriving in Paris, they soon relocated to the French Riviera. While Scott was absorbed writing ''The Great Gatsby''; Zelda became infatuated with a dashing young French pilot, Edouard Jozan. She spent afternoons swimming at the beach and evenings dancing at the casinos with Jozan. After six weeks, Zelda asked for a divorce. Scott at first demanded to confront Jozan, but instead dealt with Zelda's demand by locking her in their house, until she abandoned her request for divorce. Jozan did not know she'd asked for a divorce. He left the Riviera later that year, and the Fitzgeralds never saw him again. Later in life he told Zelda's biographer Milford that any infidelity was imaginary: "They both had a need of drama, they made it up and perhaps they were the victims of their own unsettled and a little unhealthy imagination".


After the fight, the Fitzgeralds kept up appearances with their friends, seemingly happy. But in September, Zelda overdosed on sleeping pills. The couple never spoke of the incident, and refused to discuss whether it was a suicide attempt or not. Scott returned to writing, finishing ''The Great Gatsby'' in October. They attempted to celebrate with travel to Rome and Capri, but both were unhappy and unhealthy. When he received the proofs from his novel he fretted over the title: ''Trimalchio in West Egg'', just ''Trimalchio'' or ''Gatsby'', ''Gold-hatted Gatsby'', or ''The High-bouncing Lover''. It was Zelda who preferred ''The Great Gatsby''.;  It was also on this trip, while ill with colitis, that Zelda began painting.

In April 1925, back in Paris, Scott met Ernest Hemingway, whose career he did much to promote. Hemingway and Scott Fitzgerald became firm friends, but Zelda and Hemingway disliked each other from their very first meeting, she openly described him as "bogus", and "phoney as a rubber check". She considered Hemingway's domineering macho persona to be merely a posture; Hemingway in turn, told Scott that Zelda was crazy. Her dislike was probably not helped by Scott's repeated insistence that she recount the story of her affair with Jozan to Hemingway and his wife Hadley. In an embellishment, the Fitzgeralds told the Hemingways that the affair ended when Jozan committed suicide. It was through Hemingway, however, that the Fitzgeralds were introduced to much of the Lost Generation expatriate community: Gertrude Stein, Alice B. Toklas, Robert McAlmon and others.

One of the most serious rifts occurred when Zelda told Scott that their sex life had declined because he was "a fairy" and likely having a homosexual affair with Hemingway. There is no evidence that either was homosexual, but Scott nonetheless decided to sleep with a prostitute to prove his masculinity. Zelda found condoms that he had purchased before any encounter occurred, and a bitter fight ensued, resulting in lingering jealousy. She later threw herself down a flight of marble stairs at a party because Scott, engrossed in talking to Isadora Duncan, was ignoring her.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3c6032ed7ebb48cee8d0a7ddcdc4039e" name="Copy_of_Last_Flapper_Act_1_10-8_132_0001" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/3c6032ed7ebb48cee8d0a7ddcdc4039e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>