<document id="0f1466f56fa095c86dfb9ab2aac2511e-2" name="Today_(The_Smashing_Pumpkins_song)" cat="20">
<text>
"Today" is written in the key of E-flat major (E) and played in standard tuning. While Corgan briefly considered simply tuning the guitar down a half-step and playing the song as if it were in the key of E, he said, "There was something about the E voicing that I liked. So it's absolutely, intentionally in E, not E."Aledort, Andrew. "Introduction," in ''Siamese Dream Songbook''. Miami: Warner Bros. Publications, 1994. "Today" is one of the ''Siamese Dream'' songs on which Corgan took over Iha and D'arcy's duties on guitar and bass to ensure quality; Wretzky later stated that Corgan "can do something in three takes where it would maybe take me 20."



The song, spanning three minutes and 21 seconds, begins with a one-measure opening guitar riff that alludes to the E major-pentatonic scale. Corgan uses this riff (along with variations on it) to emphasize certain parts and to indicate shifts in the song. After the riff is played four times, the rest of the band enters backed with feedback-driven guitars. Ned Raggett of Allmusic commented on the song's ability to "alternate between calmer, almost Cure-like sections and the louder crunches,  soon-to-be-trademark guitar style taking My Bloody Valentine's own hypnotic riffing to more accessible results." The chorus, consisting of multiple guitar tracks playing barre chords, is an example of the band's tendency to overdub several rhythm guitar tracks. While the song does not include a standard guitar solo, a short melodic guitar part appears during the bridge. Corgan explained: "The little guitar break over the C chord is actually a forwards sample that we laid in backwards. Then there's a weird vocal effect that moves across the speakers, a 'yan-yan-yan-yan' thing, which was generated by using a Roland Space Echo to regenerate on the last word of the vocal line, 'I wanna turn you on.'"

The dark, ironic lyrics of "Today", describing a day when Corgan was feeling depressed and suicidal, contrast with the instrumentation. Michael Snyder of the ''San Francisco Chronicle'' said that the song is "downright pretty as rock ballads go" but that "Corgan manages to convey the exhilaration and tragic release he seeks." Corgan told ''Rolling Stone'' that "I was really suicidal  I just thought it was funny to write a song that said today is the greatest day of your life because it can't get any worse." Corgan later compared writing the lyrics of "Today" and "Disarm" to "ripping  guts out."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9efd94703cced2cfbf69eace14727506" name="TodayIntro" sectnum="2#1">../img/9efd94703cced2cfbf69eace14727506.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>