<document id="0feb7fcea74d0b859f1f9a952e49079e-3" name="Crawford_expedition" cat="29">
<text>
On May 20, 1782, the volunteers began gathering at the rendezvous point at Mingo Bottom (present Mingo Junction, Ohio), on the Indian side of the Ohio River. They were mostly young men of Irish and Scots-Irish ancestry, and came primarily from Washington and Westmoreland counties in Pennsylvania.Butterfield, ''Expedition against Sandusky'', 67, 73–74. Many were Continental Army veterans.Brown, "Reconstructing Crawford's Army", 24; Rauch, "Crawford Expedition", 313. The exact number of men who took part in the expedition is unknown. An officer wrote to General Irvine on May 24 that there were 480 volunteers, although additional men may have subsequently joined the group, bringing the total to more than 500.Brown, "Reconstructing Crawford's Army", 34–35. After examining pension files and other records, Brown concluded that as many as 583 men may have taken part in the expedition, though an unknown number deserted before reaching Sandusky. Given the daunting nature of the task ahead of them, many of the volunteers made out their "last wills and testaments" before leaving.Butterfield, ''Expedition against Sandusky'', 64, 117. 

Because this was a volunteer expedition and not a regular army operation, the men elected their officers. The candidates for the top position were David Williamson, the militia colonel who had commanded the Gnadenhütten expedition, and William Crawford, a retired Continental Army colonel. Crawford, a friend and land agent of George Washington, was an experienced soldier and frontiersman. He was a veteran of these kinds of operations, having destroyed two Mingo villages during Dunmore's War in 1774.Anderson, ''Colonel William Crawford'', 8. He had also taken part in the failed "squaw campaign".Wallace, ''Travels of John Heckewelder'', 439.

Fifty-year-old Crawford had been reluctant to volunteer, but he did so at the request of General Irvine.Anderson, ''Colonel William Crawford'', 16–17; Butterfield, ''Expedition against Sandusky'', 115. Williamson, although popular with the militia, was in disfavor with regular army officers such as Irvine because he had allowed the Gnadenhütten massacre.For tensions between Continental officers and the local populace, see Sadosky, "Rethinking the Gnadenhutten Massacre". Hoping to avoid a repetition, Irvine made it known that he favored Crawford's election as commander.Butterfield, ''Expedition against Sandusky'', 121–22; Brown, "Battle of Sandusky", 120. John Heckewelder, the Moravian minister whose congregation had been murdered at Gnadenhütten, wrote an influential account of the Sandusky expedition in which he claimed that the real purpose of the campaign was to find and kill the remaining peaceful Moravian Indians. Butterfield could find no documented support for this accusation, arguing that the goal of the campaign was clearly the hostile Sandusky towns; Butterfield, ''Expedition against Sandusky'', 70, 78–80, 155–56. The election, which was acrimonious, ended in a close vote: Crawford received 235 votes to Williamson's 230. Colonel Crawford took command, and Williamson became second-in-command with the rank of major.Butterfield, ''Expedition against Sandusky'', 77; Brown, "Reconstructing Crawford's Army", 26; Rosenthal, ''Journal'', 137.

At Crawford's request, Irvine allowed Dr. John Knight, a Continental Army officer, to accompany the expedition as surgeon.Butterfield, ''Expedition against Sandusky'', 125; Anderson, ''Colonel William Crawford'', 18. Another volunteer from Irvine's staff was a foreigner with an aristocratic bearing who called himself "John Rose". Rose asked to serve as Crawford's aide-de-camp. Unknown even to General Irvine until several years later,Butterfield, ''Expedition against Sandusky'', 299. "Rose" was actually Baron Gustave Rosenthal, a Baltic German nobleman from the Russian empire who had fled to America after killing a man in a duel. Rosenthal is the only Russian known to have fought on the American side of in the Revolutionary War.Anderson, ''Colonel William Crawford'', 26; Butterfield, ''Expedition against Sandusky'', 301. Rosenthal survived to return home and eventually became the Grand Marshal of Livonia.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b206798fa3ddee282c0d430cc89e2521" name="Portrait_of_Colonel_William_Crawford" sectnum="3#1">../img/b206798fa3ddee282c0d430cc89e2521.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>