<document id="0feb7fcea74d0b859f1f9a952e49079e-2" name="Crawford_expedition" cat="29">
<text>
In September 1781, General William Irvine was appointed commander of the Western Department of the Continental Army, which was headquartered at Fort Pitt.Nester, ''Frontier War'', 303. Although a major British army under Lord Cornwallis had surrendered at Yorktown in October 1781, virtually ending the war in the east, the conflict on the western frontier continued. Irvine quickly learned that the Americans living on the frontier wanted the army to launch an expedition against Detroit to end ongoing British support for the American Indian war parties. Irvine investigated, then wrote to George Washington, the American commander-in-chief, on December 2, 1781:

It is, I believe, universally agreed that the only way to keep Indians from harassing the country is to visit them. But we find, by experience, that burning their empty towns has not the desired effect. They can soon build others. They must be followed up and beaten, or the British, whom they draw their support from, totally driven out of their country. I believe if Detroit was demolished, it would be a good step toward giving some, at least, temporary ease to this country.Butterfield, ''Expedition against Sandusky'', 26.

Washington agreed with Irvine's assessment that Detroit had to be captured or destroyed in order to end the war in the west.Nester, ''Frontier War'', 304. In February 1782, Irvine sent Washington a detailed plan for an offensive. Irvine estimated that with 2,000 men, five cannons, and a supply caravan, he could to capture Detroit.Nester, ''Frontier War'', 324. Washington replied that the bankrupt U.S. Congress would be unable to finance the campaign, writing that "offensive operations, except upon a small scale, can not just now be brought into contemplation."Butterfield, ''Expedition against Sandusky'', 41.

With no resources available from either Congress or the Continental Army, Irvine gave permission for volunteers to organize their own offensive. Detroit was too far and too strong for a small-scale operation, but militiamen such as David Williamson believed that an expedition against the American Indian towns on the Sandusky River was feasible.Butterfield, ''Expedition against Sandusky'', 50–51. It was to be a low-budget campaign. Each volunteer had to provide at his expense a horse, rifle, ammunition, rations, and other equipment.Butterfield, ''Expedition against Sandusky'', 57. Their only payment would be an exemption from two months of militia duty, plus whatever plunder might be taken from the Indians.Downes, ''Council Fires'', 273. Because of ongoing Indian raids—the wife and children of a Baptist minister were killed and scalped in western Pennsylvania on May 12, 1782—there was no shortage of men willing to volunteer.Butterfield, ''Expedition against Sandusky'', 61.

Because of Washington's reservations, Irvine believed he was not authorized to lead the expedition himself. However, he did what he could to influence the planning of the campaign. Irvine wrote detailed instructions for the yet to be chosen commander of the volunteers: 

The object of your command is, to destroy with fire and sword (if practicable) the Indian town and settlement at Sandusky, by which we hope to give ease and safety to the inhabitants of this country; but, if impracticable, then you will doubtless perform such other services in your power as will, in their consequences, have a tendency to answer this great end.Butterfield, ''Expedition against Sandusky'', 69–71.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d06e99cfc343bf34fda190ca81a174d7" name="General_William_Irvine" sectnum="2#1">../img/d06e99cfc343bf34fda190ca81a174d7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>