<document id="1069c82d37b07064ccce1142c2c908d3-2.5" name="Cape_Horn" cat="11">
<text>
The voyage of Willem Schouten and Jacob le Maire in 1615–1616

In 1525 the vessel ''San Lesmes'' commanded by Francisco de Hoces, member of the Loaísa Expedition, was blown south by a gale in front of the Atlantic end of Magellan Strait and reached 56° S where ''they thought to see Land's End''. 

In September 1578, Sir Francis Drake, in the course of his circumnavigation of the world, passed through the Strait of Magellan into the Pacific Ocean. Before he could continue his voyage north his ships encountered a storm, and were blown well to the south of Tierra del Fuego. The expanse of open water they encountered led Drake to guess that far from being another continent, as previously believed, Tierra del Fuego was an island with open sea to its south. This discovery went unused for some time, as ships continued to use the known passage through the Strait of Magellan., from The Golden Hind. Retrieved February 5, 2006.

By the early 1600s the Dutch East India Company was given a monopoly on all Dutch trade via the Straits of Magellan and the Cape of Good Hope, the only known routes at the time to the Far East.  To search for an alternate route and one to the unknown ''Terra Australis'', Isaac Le Maire,it seems to have been Le Maire who pursued the idea of such a passage  a wealthy Amsterdam merchant and Willem Schouten, a ship’s master of Hoorn, contributed in equal shares to the enterprise, with additional financial support from merchants of Hoorn.''THE RELATION OF a Wonderfull Voiage made by Willem Cornelison Schouten of Horne. Shewing how South from the Straights of Magelan in Terra Delfuego: he found and discovered a newe passage through the great South Seaes, and that way sayled round about the world''.  London: Imprinted by T.D. for Nathanaell Newbery, 1619 , The Preface.  “Translation thereof out of the Dutch, wherein it was written” by William Philip Jacob Le Maire, Isaac’s son, went on the journey as “chiefe Marchant and principall factor,” in charge of trading aspects of the endeavor.  The two ships that departed Holland at the beginning of June 1615 were the ''Eendracht''called ''Unitie'' in the Philip translation of 360 tons with Schouten and Le Maire aboard, and the ''Hoorn'' of 110 tons, of which Schouten’s brother Johan was master.  It was ''Eendracht'' then, with the crew of the recently wrecked ''Hoorn'' aboard,''Hoorn'' was accidentally burned and destroyed on December 19, 1615 with no loss of life in Patagonia during a bungled cleaning attempt of the hull that passed through the Le Maire Strait and Schouten and Le Maire made their great discovery:

:“In the evening 25 January 1616 the winde was South West, and that night wee went South with great waves or billowes out of the southwest, and very blew water, whereby wee judged, and held for certaine that ... it was the great South Sea, whereat we were exceeding glad to thinke that wee had discovered a way, which until that time, was unknowne to men, as afterward wee found it to be true.”''THE RELATION'', p. 22

:“... on 29 January 1616 we saw land againe lying north west and north northwest from us, which was the land that lay South from the straights of Magelan which reacheth Southward, all high hillie lande covered over with snow, ending with a sharpe point which wee called Cape Horne  ...”''THE RELATION'', p. 23

At the time it was discovered, the Horn was believed to be the southernmost point of Tierra del Fuego; the unpredictable violence of weather and sea conditions in the Drake Passage made exploration difficult, and it was only in 1624 that the Horn was discovered to be an island. It is a telling testament to the difficulty of conditions there that Antarctica, only 650 kilometres (400 mi) away across the Drake Passage, was discovered as recently as 1820, despite the passage having been used as a major shipping route for 200 years.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fec5960f04cdd46b8421924b3fcb20c4" name="Cape_Horn-650px" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/fec5960f04cdd46b8421924b3fcb20c4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>