<document id="10c6d56db14d84313524017e41471e65-1.2" name="Battle_of_Mount_Austen,_the_Galloping_Horse,_and_the_Sea_Horse" cat="29">
<text>
On November 5, 7, and 8, Tokyo Express missions landed most of the 38th Division's 228th Infantry Regiment and the 1st Battalion, 229th Infantry Regiment on Guadalcanal.  On November 10, Japanese destroyers landed Lieutenant General Tadayoshi Sano, commander of the 38th Infantry Division, plus his staff and 600 more troops from the 38th.  Hyakutake used the newly arrived troops to help stop an American attack west of the Matanikau from November 8 through November 11, then sent the 228th and 229th Regiment's units on November 11 to reinforce Oka's forces.  Japanese Major General Takeo Itō, commander of the 38th Division's Infantry Group, later took command of the defenses around Mount Austen.Frank, p. 421–425, 495, Miller, p. 204, 228, 237, Jersey, p. 303–304, 307, 361, Hough, p. 363–364.  At this time, Ito commanded about 1,000 troops of the 124th and 228th Infantry Regiments and supporting units on an inland line extending from Mount Austen to a point about  west. Of this force, Maj. Takeyosho Inagaki with the 2d Battalion, 228th Infantry, occupied the northeast slopes of Mount Austen. Colonel Oka, with part of the 124th Infantry and other units, held the center of the line between Mount Austen and the Matanikau, while Col. Masaichi Suemura commanded the 1st and 3d Battalions of the 228th Infantry on the high ground west of the Matanikau.  The 228th Regiment was commanded by Colonel Sadashichi Doi.  Doi was later killed on an unknown date by American artillery fire.  Suemura may have taken command of the 228th after Doi's death (Jersey, p. 303, 344, 368).  The 229th and 230th Regiment's units were apparently scattered at various places among the Japanese positions.

An attempt by the Japanese to deliver the rest of the 38th Division and its heavy equipment failed during the Naval Battle of Guadalcanal from November 12 through November 15.  Only 2,000 to 3,000 of the remaining 7,000 troops from the division reached the island and most of their supplies, ammunition, and equipment were lost.  Because of this failure, the Japanese cancelled their next planned attempt to recapture Henderson Field.Frank, p. 428–492.

As December began, the Japanese experienced considerable difficulty in keeping their troops on Guadalcanal resupplied because of Allied air and naval attacks on the Japanese supply chain of ships and bases.  The few supplies delivered to the island were not enough to sustain Japanese troops, who by December 7, 1942, were losing about 50 men each day from malnutrition, disease, and Allied ground or air attacks.  The Japanese had delivered almost 30,000 army troops to Guadalcanal since the campaign began, but by December only about 20,000 of that number were still alive.  Of those 20,000, about 12,000 remained more or less fit for combat duty.Frank, p. 493–527, Hough, p. 364–365.  On December 12, the Japanese Navy proposed that Guadalcanal be abandoned. Despite opposition from Japanese Army leaders, who still hoped that Guadalcanal could eventually be retaken from the Allies, Imperial General Headquarters, with approval from the Emperor, on December 31, agreed to the evacuation of all Japanese forces from the island and establishment of a new line of defense for the Solomons on New Georgia.  The Japanese titled the evacuation effort of their forces from Guadalcanal ''Operation Ke'' (ケ号作戦) and planned to execute the operation beginning January 14, 1943.Dull, p. 261, 268, Miller, p. 336–338, Griffith, p. 268–269.

In the meantime, the US continued to deliver additional troops to Guadalcanal.  The three infantry regiments of the US Army's Americal Division, the 164th, the 182nd and the 132nd were delivered to Guadalcanal on October 13, November 12, and December 8, respectively.  In addition, the US Army's independent 147th Infantry Regiment plus the 2nd Marine Division's 8th Marine Regiment landed on November 4.  The reinforcements also included additional artillery, construction, aviation, naval, and support units.Frank, p. 247–252, 293, 417–420, 430–431, 521, Griffith, p. 156, Miller, p. 143, 173–177, 183, 189, Jersey, p. 304–305, 345–346, Hough, p. 360.  The Americal Division infantry regiments were national guard units.  The 164th was from North Dakota, the 182nd from Massachusetts, and the 132nd from Illinois.  The 147th had previously been part of the 37th Infantry Division.

On December 9, US Army Major General Alexander Patch, commanding general of the Americal Division, succeeded Vandegrift as commander of Allied forces on Guadalcanal and Tulagi.  That same day, the 5th Marine Regiment departed the island, followed by the rest of the 1st Marine Division by the end of the month.  Patch was ordered to eliminate all Japanese forces remaining on Guadalcanal.  Patch told his superior, Millard Harmon, who commanded all US Army forces in the South Pacific, that he needed more troops to accomplish his mission.  In response, Harmon ordered the 25th Infantry Division, which was in the process of relocating from Hawaii to the South Pacific area, to ship directly to Guadalcanal.  The 25th's units would arrive at Guadalcanal in stages during the last two weeks of December and the first week of January 1943.  In addition, the rest of the 2nd Marine Division's units, including the 6th Marine Regiment, were ordered to Guadalcanal during the same time period.  By January 7, American forces on Guadalcanal would total just over 50,000 men.Miller, p. 213–219, Frank, p. 521–522, 529, Hough, p. 359–360, Hough, p. 360–362, Shaw, p. 46–47, Zimmerman, p. 156–157, 164, Jersey, p. 363, 365, Griffith, p. 257–259, 270.  During its time on Guadalcanal, the 1st Marine Division suffered 650 killed, 31 missing, 1,278 injured, and 8,580 who contracted some type of disease, mainly malaria.  The 2nd Marine Regiment had arrived at Guadalcanal with most of the 1st Marine Division, but remained behind to rejoin its parent unit, the 2nd Marine Division.  The US Army's 25th Infantry Division's 35th Regiment arrived at Guadalcanal on December 17, the 27th Regiment on January 1, and the 161st Regiment on January 4.  The 2nd Marine Division's headquarter's units, the 6th Marine Regiment, and various Marine weapons and support units also arrived on January 4 and January 6.  US Major General John Marston, commander of the 2nd Marine Division, remained in New Zealand because he was superior in time in rank to Patch.  Instead, Brigadier General Alphonse De Carre commanded the 2nd Marine Division on Guadalcanal.  The total number of Marines on Guadalcanal and Tulagi on January 6, 1943 was 18,383.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e0fb137cebce438eabe6dc559ac729d4" name="GuadPatch" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/e0fb137cebce438eabe6dc559ac729d4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>