<document id="10c6d56db14d84313524017e41471e65-1.1" name="Battle_of_Mount_Austen,_the_Galloping_Horse,_and_the_Sea_Horse" cat="29">
<text>
On August 7, 1942, Allied forces (primarily U.S.) landed on Guadalcanal, Tulagi, and Florida Islands in the Solomon Islands.  The landings on the islands were meant to deny their use by the Japanese as bases for threatening the supply routes between the U.S. and Australia, and to secure the islands as starting points for a campaign with the eventual goal of isolating the major Japanese base at Rabaul while also supporting the Allied New Guinea campaign.  The landings initiated the six-month-long Guadalcanal campaign.Hogue, p. 235–236.

The Japanese were taken by surprise.  By nightfall on August 8, the 11,000 Allied troops, primarily from the 1st Marine Division of the United States Marine Corps under the command of Lieutenant General Alexander Vandegrift, secured Tulagi and nearby small islands as well as the Japanese airfield under construction at Lunga Point on Guadalcanal.  The Allies later renamed the airfield Henderson Field.  Allied aircraft operating out of Henderson were called the "Cactus Air Force" (CAF) after the Allied code name for Guadalcanal.  To protect the airfield, the US Marines established a perimeter defense around Lunga Point.  Additional reinforcements over the next two months later increased the number of US troops at Lunga Point on Guadalcanal to more than 20,000.Morison, p. 14–15, Miller, p. 143, Frank, p. 338, and Shaw, p. 18.


In response to the Allied landings on Guadalcanal, the Japanese Imperial General Headquarters assigned the Imperial Japanese Army's 17th Army, a corps-sized command based at Rabaul and under the command of Lieutenant General Harukichi Hyakutake, with the task of retaking Guadalcanal.  Units of the 17th Army began to arrive on Guadalcanal on August 19 to drive Allied forces from the island.Griffith, p. 96–99, Dull, p. 225, Miller, p. 137–138.

Because of the threat by CAF aircraft based at Henderson Field, the Japanese were unable to use large, slow transport ships to deliver troops and supplies to the island.  Instead, the Japanese used warships based at Rabaul and the Shortland Islands to carry their forces to Guadalcanal.  The Japanese warships, mainly light cruisers or destroyers from the Eighth Fleet under the command of Vice Admiral Gunichi Mikawa, were usually able to make the round trip down "The Slot" to Guadalcanal and back in a single night, thereby minimizing their exposure to CAF air attack. Delivering the troops in this manner, however, prevented most of the soldiers' heavy equipment and supplies, such as heavy artillery, vehicles, and much food and ammunition, from being carried to Guadalcanal with them. These high-speed warship runs to Guadalcanal occurred throughout the campaign and were later called the "Tokyo Express" by Allied forces and "Rat Transportation" by the Japanese.Frank, p. 202, 210–211.

Using forces delivered to Guadalcanal in this manner, the Japanese tried three times to retake Henderson Field, but were defeated each time.  First, a reinforced battalion from the 28th Infantry Regiment was defeated in the Battle of the Tenaru on August 21.  Next, the augmented 35th Infantry Brigade was defeated in the Battle of Edson's Ridge September 12–14.  Finally, the complete 2nd Infantry Division plus one regiment from the 38th Infantry Division was defeated with heavy losses in the Battle for Henderson Field October 23–26, 1942.Frank, p. 141–158, 218–246, 337–367.

Throughout the campaign, the Japanese used Mount Austen (called Bear Height by the Japanese and Mount Mambulu by the local Solomon Islanders), located west of the Lunga River and about 6 miles (9.7 km) from Henderson Field, to observe the American defenses around Lunga Point. Emplaced artillery on Mount Austen delivered harassing fire on Henderson Field. The hill was also used as a defensive point to protect their positions around the upper Matanikau valley as well as to protect the Maruyama Road which was a trail used by the Japanese to move men and supplies into the interior of the island.  Mount Austen, with a summit of , was not a single peak, but a mixed jumble of rocky exposed and jungle-covered ridges and hilltops.  After the defeat in the Battle for Henderson Field, the Army Section of Imperial General Headquarters directed Hyakutake to increase the number of troops and artillery emplaced on Mount Austen to help prepare for the next planned attack on the Americans.  Therefore, Hyakutake directed some of the units that were retreating from the Henderson Field battle area to fortify Mount Austen and nearby hilltops.  The forces deployed to Mount Austen included the 124th Infantry Regiment under Colonel Akinosuka Oka and several artillery units.  Later, surviving troops from the 230th Infantry Regiment, which had taken heavy losses during the Koli Point action and subsequent retreat, joined Oka's forces around Mount Austen.Frank, p. 406–407, 411, 529, Miller, p. 233–237, Jersey, p. 344, 356, 360–362, Hough, p. 363–364.  The 8th Company, 230th Regiment took up positions near Mount Austen's summit.  The 3rd Company, 10th Mountain Artillery under Captain Kyohtaroh Oishi with two 75mm Type 41 mountain guns was located on Hill 89.  Nearby were several more Type 41 guns and crews from the 228th Infantry Howitzer Company.  All were short of ammunition.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1cc1d99657f29f1d9515e66b0e04a49b" name="GuadMapAug7" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/1cc1d99657f29f1d9515e66b0e04a49b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>