<document id="10c6d56db14d84313524017e41471e65-2.3" name="Battle_of_Mount_Austen,_the_Galloping_Horse,_and_the_Sea_Horse" cat="29">
<text>
On January 9, McClure's 2nd Battalion, commanded by Lieutenant Colonel Ernest Peters, replaced the three battalions from the 132nd Regiment and prepared to assault the Gifu.  Over the next four days, the Americans tried to feel out the Japanese positions with patrols.  At the same time, the Gifu defenders attempted to wear down the Americans with night infiltration attacks.  By January 13, the 2nd Battalion had lost 57 killed or wounded.  The battle casualties plus malaria reduced the battalion to 75% of its effective strength by the next day.  To assist the battalion, the 35th Regiment's anti-tank gun company personnel were attached to the battalion as infantry.Frank, p. 563–564, Miller, p. 290–294.

With the capture of the Sea Horse by the Americans, the Japanese in the Gifu were now isolated from the rest of the 17th Army.  In a last message over his field phone before the line was cut, Inagaki refused an order from Oka to abandon his position and attempt to infiltrate back to friendly lines, instead vowing that his command would "fight to the last".  Inagaki apparently refused the order because to do so would have meant leaving his sick and injured men behind.Frank, p. 564, Miller, p. 296, Griffith, p. 278.

An American attack on the Gifu by the entire 2nd Battalion on January 15 was completely repulsed by the Japanese.  In response, McClure relieved Peters of command on January 16 and replaced him with Major Stanley R. Larsen.  Larsen decided to completely surround the Gifu and try to reduce it with a massive artillery bombardment on January 17.Frank, p. 564–565, Miller, p. 295–298, Anderson, Jersey, p. 367–369.  Jersey states that Peters was relieved for, "not implementing an order" (Jersey p. 367).

In the meantime, the Americans used a loudspeaker to broadcast a surrender appeal in Japanese to the Gifu's defenders.  Only five Japanese soldiers responded.  One of the five reported that his company actually gathered to discuss the appeal, but decided not to surrender because they were too weak to carry their injured, non-ambulatory comrades with them to the American lines.  Instead, they elected to perish together as a unit.  One Japanese officer defending the Gifu wrote in his diary, "I heard the enemy talking in Japanese over a loud speaker.  He is probably telling us to come out - what fools the enemy are.  The Japanese Army will stick it out to the end.  Position must be defended in all conditions with our lives."Frank, p. 565, Miller, p. 298–299, Jersey, p. 369.

At 14:30 hours on January 17, twelve 155mm and thirty-seven 105mm cannons opened fire on the Gifu.  Over the next one and a half hours, the American artillery fired 1,700 shells into an area about  square.  Because of the lateness of the hour, the Americans were unable to follow the barrage with an immediate attack but instead had to wait until the next day, which allowed the Japanese time to recover.  On January 18, the Americans attacked into the weaker west side of the Gifu, making some headway and destroying several Japanese pillboxes over the next two days until heavy rain stopped the attack on January 20.  That night 11 Japanese were killed trying to escape from the Gifu.Frank, p. 565–566, Miller, p. 298–303.  The US artillery units involved included the 105-mm. howitzers of the 88th Field Artillery Battalion, one 105-mm. howitzer of the 8th, and the 155-mm. howitzers of the 90th and 221st Field Artillery Battalions in addition to the 105-mm. howitzers of the 64th Field Artillery Battalion.

On January 22, the Americans were able to move a light tank up their supply trail to Mount Austen.  The tank proved to be the decisive factor in the battle.  At 10:20, the tank, protected by 16–18 riflemen, blasted three Japanese pillboxes and penetrated into the Gifu pocket.  Proceeding onward, the tank completely traversed the Gifu and destroyed five more pillboxes, breaching a gap  wide in the Japanese line.  The American infantry surged through the gap and took positions in the middle of the Gifu.Frank, p. 566, Miller p. 303, Anderson, Jersey, p. 370, Gilbert, p. 50–51.  The tank was commanded by Captain Theodore Deese and crewed by men from the 25th Division Reconnaissance Troop.  Three tanks, formerly belonging to Marine units on Guadalcanal, actually moved up to Mount Austen, but two were disabled in the process and were unable to participate in the attack.

That night, around 02:30, apparently realizing that the battle was lost, Inagaki led his staff and most of the remaining survivors of his command, about 100 men, in a final charge on the Americans.  In the charge, Inagaki and the remainder of his troops were killed almost to the last man.  At sunrise on January 23, the Americans secured the rest of the Gifu.  Sixty-four men from the American 2nd Battalion, 35th Infantry were killed during the assaults on the Gifu between January 9 and January 23, bringing the total number of Americans killed taking Mount Austen to 175.  The Americans counted the bodies of 431 Japanese in the remains of the Gifu's fortifications and 87 elsewhere around Mount Austen.  Total Japanese losses in the Sea Horse and both Mount Austen battles were probably between 1,100 and 1,500 men.Frank, p. 566–567, Miller, p. 303–305, Anderson, Jersey, p. 371.  Also killed in the final Japanese charge was Major Nishihata, commander of the 2nd Battalion, 124th Infantry Regiment.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="61ebf93c2aff1020e3338123ce6a82da" name="Guad25thWouded" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/61ebf93c2aff1020e3338123ce6a82da.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>