<document id="1136c2ab5563b433db89dd8bc01418d1-3" name="New_Zealand_national_rugby_union_team" cat="26">
<text>
The All Blacks perform a haka (Māori war style dance) before each international match. The haka has been closely associated with New Zealand rugby ever since a tour of New South Wales in 1884. The New Zealand native team that toured Britain in 1889/89 used ''Ake Ake Kia Kaha'' and the 1903 team in Australia used a mocking haka, ''Tupoto koe, Kangaru!''. The 1905 All Blacks began the tradition of using ''Ka Mate'' and by 1914 this was firmly established as part of New Zealand rugby.  The 1924 All Blacks used a specially composed haka ''Kia Whaka-ngawari'', but later All Blacks reverted back to ''Ka Mate''.

In August 2005, before the Tri-Nations Test match between New Zealand and South Africa at Carisbrook stadium in Dunedin, New Zealand performed a new haka, ''Kapa o Pango'', specially composed by Derek Lardelli and "...designed to reflect the multi-cultural make-up of contemporary New Zealand &mdash; in particular the influence of Polynesian cultures". ''Kapa o Pango'' was to be performed on special occasions and was not intended to replace ''Ka Mate''. ''Kapa o Pango'' concludes with what has been interpreted as a "throat slitting" gesture that was a source of controversy and led to accusations that ''Kapa o Pango'' encourages violence, and sends the wrong message to All Blacks fans. However, according to Derek Lardelli, the gesture represents "drawing vital energy into the heart and lungs." 

In November 2006, at the Millennium Stadium, Cardiff, New Zealand performed the haka in the dressing room prior to the match &mdash; instead of on the field immediately before kick-off &mdash; after a disagreement with the Welsh Rugby Union, which had wanted Wales to sing their national anthem after the haka.

In 2008, New Zealand played Munster at Thomond Park. Before the match, Munster's four New Zealanders challenged New Zealand by performing the Haka first.http://www.stuff.co.nz/sport/725123 

On the same tour, Wales responded by silently refusing to move after New Zealand's haka, and the two teams simply stared at each other until the referee forced them to start the game.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="13ba2b27c7b6c536f0e986b5e2ba0942" name="Allblackhaka" sectnum="3#1">../img/13ba2b27c7b6c536f0e986b5e2ba0942.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>