<document id="12471fa7b776e267a9e2817faf032e24-4" name="Nuthatch" cat="3">
<text>
Members of the nuthatch family live in most of North America and Europe and throughout Asia down to the Wallace Line. Nuthatches are sparsely represented in Africa; one species lives in a small area of northeastern AlgeriaSnow & Perrins (1998) p1400&ndash;1401 "Algerian Nuthatch" and a population of the Eurasian Nuthatch subspecies, ''S. e. hispaniensis'', lives in the mountains of Morocco.Snow & Perrins (1998) p1402&ndash;1404 "Nuthatch" Most species are resident year-round. The only significant migrant is the Red-breasted Nuthatch, which winters widely across North America, deserting the northernmost parts of its breeding range in Canada; it has been recorded as a vagrant in Bermuda, Iceland and England.

Most nuthatches are woodland birds and the majority are found in coniferous or other evergreen forests, although each species has a preference for a particular tree type. The strength of the association varies from the Corsican Nuthatch, which is closely linked with Corsican Pine, to the catholic habitat of the Eurasian Nuthatch, which prefers deciduous or mixed woods but breeds in coniferous forests in the north of its extensive range.Snow & Perrins (1998) p1399&ndash;1400 "Corsican Nuthatch" However, the two species of rock nuthatches are not strongly tied to woodlands: they breed on rocky slopes or cliffs, although both move into wooded areas when not breeding.Snow & Perrins (1998) p1404&ndash;1406 "Eastern Rock Nuthatch" In parts of Asia where several species occur in the same geographic region, there is often an altitudinal separation in their preferred habitats.

Nuthatches prefer a fairly temperate climate; northern species live near sea level whereas those further south are found in cooler highland habitats. Eurasian and Red-breasted Nuthatches are lowland birds in the north of their extensive ranges, but breed in the mountains further south; for example, Eurasian Nuthatch, which breeds where the July temperature range is 16&ndash;27 °C, is found near sea level in Northern Europe, but between 1,750 and 1,850 m (5,700&ndash;6,100 ft) altitude in Morocco. The Velvet-fronted  Nuthatch is the sole member of the family which prefers tropical lowland forests.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="35c440d681e30f8eba5586d1a49fa48f" name="Pinus_ponderosa_8144t" sectnum="4#1">../img/35c440d681e30f8eba5586d1a49fa48f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>