<document id="125755043737763fcfa2db8929839ebf-6" name="Cheadle_Hulme" cat="11">
<text>
Bramall Hall, a Grade I listed building, is a 14th-century black and white timber framed Tudor manor house, located between Cheadle Hulme and Bramhall. Described by Stockport Metropolitan Borough Council (SMBC) as "the most prestigious and historically significant building in the Conservation Area", it is situated in the middle of  of landscaped parkland featuring lakes, woodland and gardens. Both house and grounds are open to the public and are in one of the 19 conservation areas in the borough.

The Swann Lane, Hulme Hall Road, and Hill Top Avenue conservation area contains 16th and 17th century timber-framed buildings, Victorian villas, churches, and some former farmsteads. There are two Grade II listed buildings in this area: Hulme Hall, a timber-framed manor house which dates from either the 16th or 17th century, and 1 Higham Street, formerly Hill Cottage, which is of a similar period and style to Hulme Hall. The Church Inn public house, which dates from either the late 18th or early 19th century, is situated on the edge of this area.

The cenotaph, on Ravenoak Road. It is on the corner of a busy junction, and suggestions to move it to a more peaceful area have been made.

Around 300 men from Cheadle Hulme served in the First World War,Squire, p.14 and it was decided that those who died should be commemorated. Various ideas, including a library and clock tower, were suggested and in the end a cenotaph was built on the corner of Ravenoak Road and Manor Road in 1921. Additions for later wars have been made, and due to the busy traffic around that particular place there have been suggestions for moving it to a quieter area.Wyke, p.340

Bruntwood Park has a variety of facilities, including orienteering, an 18-hole, par 3 pitch and putt golf course, children's play areas, football pitches, and a BMX track. Bruntwood Park is a Grade B Site of Biological Interest, and in 1999 was given a Green Flag Award for its high standards. The land it occupies was once a large estate, which at one time included a stud farm. Bruntwood Hall, a Victorian Gothic building constructed in 1861, has been used for various purposes, including serving as Cheadle and Gatley Town Hall from 1944 until 1959.Makepeace, p.30Hudson, p.51 It is now used as offices, and since the 1940s the park has been open to the public.

Oak Meadow Park is a small park on Station Road, with a large grass area and woodland. In the early 2000s it was renovated and refurbished, with new fences, benches and footpaths. The project to maintain and improve the park is a continuous process overseen by a local volunteer group. The park is used for special community events throughout the year.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="22add9c6ad56674f1785cfa07fb42d67" name="Bramall_Hall_2" sectnum="6#1">../img/22add9c6ad56674f1785cfa07fb42d67.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>