<document id="135e548976476c40cb57770eb813a5c6-1.4" name="Olivier_Messiaen" cat="20">
<text>
In 1952, Messiaen was asked to provide a test piece for flautists wishing to enter the Paris Conservatoire, and for this he composed the piece ''Le merle noir'' for flute and piano. While Messiaen had long been fascinated by birdsong, and birds had made appearances in several of his earlier works (for example ''La Nativité'', ''Quatuor'' and ''Vingt regards''), the flute piece is based entirely on the song of the blackbird.
He took this development to a new level with his 1953 orchestral work ''Réveil des oiseaux''—the work is composed almost entirely of birdsong, taking as its material the birds one might hear between midnight and noon in the Jura. From this period onwards Messiaen incorporated birdsong into all of his compositions, and indeed he composed several works for which birds provide the title and subject matter (for example the collection of thirteen pieces for piano ''Catalogue d'oiseaux'' completed in 1958, and ''La fauvette des jardins'' of 1971). Far from being simple transcriptions of birdsong, these works are sophisticated tone poems evoking the place and its atmosphere. Paul Griffiths comments that Messiaen was a more conscientious ornithologist than any previous composer, and a more musical observer of birdsong than any previous ornithologist.Griffiths (1985), p. 168; see also Kraft (2000)

Messiaen's first wife died in 1959 following her long illness, and in 1961 he married Yvonne Loriod. He began to travel widely, both to attend musical events and to seek out and transcribe the songs of more exotic birds. Loriod frequently assisted her husband's detailed studies of birdsongs, which he notated in the wild, by walking with him and making a tape recording for checking later. In 1962 his travels took him to Japan, where Gagaku music and Noh theatre inspired him to compose the orchestral "Japanese sketches", ''Sept haïkaï'', which contain stylised imitations of traditional Japanese instruments.

Messiaen's music was at this time championed by, among others, Pierre Boulez, who programmed first performances at his Domaine musical concerts and the Donaueschingen festival. Works performed here included ''Réveil des oiseaux'', ''Chronochromie'' (commissioned for the 1960 festival) and ''Couleurs de la cité céleste''. The latter piece was the result of a commission for a composition for three trombones and three xylophones; Messiaen added to this more brass, wind, percussion and piano, and specified a xylophone, xylorimba and marimba rather than three xylophones. Another work of this period, ''Et exspecto resurrectionem mortuorem'', was commissioned as a commemoration of the dead of the two World Wars, and was performed first semi-privately in the Sainte-Chapelle, then publicly in Chartres Cathedral with Charles de Gaulle in the audience.

His reputation as a composer continued to grow. In 1959 Messiaen was nominated as an ''Officier'' of the ''Légion d'honneur'',Hill & Simeone (2005), p. 245 and in 1966 he was officially appointed professor of composition at the Paris Conservatoire (although he had in effect been teaching composition for years). Further honours bestowed on Messiaen later included election to the Institut de France in 1967, the Erasmus Prize in 1971, the award of the Royal Philharmonic Society Gold Medal in 1975, the Sonning Award (Denmark's highest musical honour) in 1977, and the presentation of the ''Croix de Commander'' of the Belgian Order of the Crown in 1980.Hill & Simeone (2005), p. 333
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="37793d5b98ca135c0d3b20480569d40c" name="Sylvia_borin" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/37793d5b98ca135c0d3b20480569d40c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>