<document id="135e548976476c40cb57770eb813a5c6-1.3" name="Olivier_Messiaen" cat="20">
<text>
Shortly after his release from Görlitz in May 1941, Messiaen was appointed a professor of harmony at the Paris Conservatoire, where he taught until his retirement in 1978. He also compiled his ''Technique de mon langage musical'' ("Technique of my musical language") published in 1944, in which he quotes many examples from his music, particularly the Quartet.

Among Messiaen's early students at the Conservatoire were the composers Pierre Boulez and Karel Goeyvaerts, and the pianist Yvonne Loriod. Other pupils later included Karlheinz Stockhausen in 1952, Alexander Goehr in 1956–57, György Kurtág in 1957, Tristan Murail in 1967–72, and George Benjamin in the second half of the 1970s. The Greek Iannis Xenakis was briefly referred to him in 1951; Messiaen provided encouragement and exhorted Xenakis to take advantage of his background in mathematics and architecture, and use them in his music. Although Messiaen was only in his mid-thirties his students of the period later reported that he was already an outstanding teacher,Pierre Boulez in Hill (1995), pp. 266ff encouraging each of them to find their own voice rather than imposing his own ideas.

In 1943, Messiaen wrote ''Visions de l'Amen'' ("Visions of the Amen") for two pianos for Loriod and himself to perform, and shortly afterwards composed the enormous solo piano cycle ''Vingt regards sur l'enfant-Jésus'' ("Twenty gazes on the child Jesus") for her. He also wrote ''Trois petites Liturgies de la Présence Divine'' ("Three small liturgies of the Divine Presence") for female chorus and orchestra which includes a difficult solo piano part, again for Loriod. Messiaen thus continued to bring liturgical subjects into the piano recital and the concert hall.

Two years after ''Visions de l'Amen,'' in 1945, Messiaen composed the first of three works on the theme of human (as opposed to divine) love, particularly inspired by the legend of Tristan and Isolde. This was the song cycle ''Harawi''. The second of the ''Tristan'' works was the result of a commission from Serge Koussevitsky for a piece (Messiaen stated that the commission did not specify the length of the work or the size of the orchestra); this was the ten-movement ''Turangalîla-Symphonie''. This is not a conventional symphony, but rather an extended meditation on the joy of human love and union. It lacks the sexual guilt inherent in Richard Wagner's ''Tristan und Isolde'' because Messiaen's attitude was that sexual love is a divine gift. ('''') The third piece inspired by the ''Tristan'' myth was ''Cinq rechants'' for twelve unaccompanied singers, which Messiaen said was influenced by the alba of the troubadours.Griffiths (1985), p. 142

Messiaen visited the United States in 1947, his music being conducted there by Koussevitsky and Leopold Stokowski, and his ''Turangalîla-Symphonie'' was first performed there in 1949 conducted by Leonard Bernstein. During this period, as well as giving an analysis class at the Paris Conservatoire, he also taught in Budapest in 1947 and Tanglewood in 1949; in the summers of 1949 and 1950 he taught in the new music summer school classes at Darmstadt. Though he never employed twelve-tone technique himself, after three years teaching analysis of scores using it, such as works by Arnold Schoenberg, he did experiment with ways of making scales of other elements (including duration, articulation, and dynamics) analogous to the chromatic pitch scale. The results of these innovations was the piece "Mode de valeurs et d'intensités" for piano (from the ''Quatre Études de Rhythme'') which has been incorrectly described as the first work of total serialism, though it had a large influence on the earliest European serial composers, including Pierre Boulez, Karel Goeyvaerts, and Karlheinz Stockhausen. During this period he also experimented with musique concrète, music for recorded sounds.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3988fdd5dd10ade3575275489c2a6934" name="Olivier_Messiaen_1946" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/3988fdd5dd10ade3575275489c2a6934.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>