<document id="135e548976476c40cb57770eb813a5c6-1.2" name="Olivier_Messiaen" cat="20">
<text>
Messiaen's special relationship with the organ began in autumn 1927, when he joined Dupré's organ course. Dupré later reminisced that Messiaen, having never seen an organ console before, sat quietly for an hour while Dupré explained and demonstrated the instrument, and then came back a week later to play Johann Sebastian Bach's ''Fantasia in C minor'' to an impressive standard.Hill & Simeone (2005), p. 22 From 1929 Messiaen regularly deputised at the Église de la Sainte-Trinité, Paris for the organist, Charles Quef, who was ill. When Quef died in 1931 and the post became vacant, Dupré, Charles Tournemire and Widor among others supported Messiaen's candidacy to succeed him. With his formal application Messiaen enclosed a letter of recommendation from Widor, and the appointment was confirmed in 1931.Hill & Simeone (2005), pp. 34ff Messiaen remained the organist at la Sainte-Trinité for more than sixty years.

In 1932, Messiaen married the violinist and fellow composer Claire Delbos. Their marriage inspired him to compose works for her to play (''Thème et variations'' for violin and piano in the year they were married), and pieces to celebrate their domestic happiness (including the song cycle ''Poèmes pour Mi'' in 1936, which Messiaen orchestrated in 1937). ''Mi'' was Messiaen's affectionate nickname for his wife. In 1937 their son Pascal was born. Messiaen's marriage turned to tragedy when his wife lost her memory after an operation, and she spent the rest of her life in mental institutions.Yvonne Loriod, in Hill (1995), p. 294

In 1936, Messiaen, André Jolivet, Daniel-Lesur and Yves Baudrier formed the group ''La Jeune France'' ("Young France"). Their manifesto implicitly attacked the frivolity predominant in contemporary Parisian music, rejecting Jean Cocteau's manifesto ''Le coq et l'arlequin'' of 1918 in favour of a "living music, having the impetus of sincerity, generosity and artistic conscientiousness".from the programme for the opening concert of ''La Jeune France'', quoted in Griffiths (1985), p. 72 Messiaen's career soon departed from this public phase, however, as the music he was composing at this time was not for public commissions or conventional concerts.

An ondes Martenot
In 1937, in response to a commission for a piece to accompany light- and water-shows on the Seine during the ''Paris Exposition'', Messiaen demonstrated his interest in using the ondes Martenot, an electronic instrument, by composing the unpublished ''Fêtes des belles eaux'' for an ensemble of six.Hill & Simeone (2005), pp. 73f He included a part for the instrument in several of his subsequent compositions.

During this period Messiaen composed several multi-movement organ works. He arranged his orchestral suite ''L'Ascension'' ("The Ascension") for organ, replacing the orchestral version's third movement with an entirely new movement, ''Transports de joie d'une âme devant la gloire du Christ qui est la sienne'' ("Ecstasies of a soul before the glory of Christ, which is its own glory"). () This movement became one of Messiaen's most popular pieces. He also wrote the extensive cycles ''La Nativité du Seigneur'' ("The Nativity of the Lord") and ''Les corps glorieux'' ("The glorious bodies"). The final toccata of ''La Nativité'', ''Dieu parmi nous'' ("God among us"), has become another favourite recital piece.

At the outbreak of World War II Messiaen was called up to be in the French army, as a medical auxiliary rather than an active combatant due to his poor eyesight.Griffiths (1985), p. 139 In May 1940 he was captured at Verdun, and was taken to Görlitz where he was imprisoned at prison camp Stalag VIII-A. He soon encountered a violinist, a cellist, and a clarinettist among his fellow prisoners. Initially he wrote a trio for them, but gradually incorporated this trio into his ''Quatuor pour la fin du temps'' ("Quartet for the End of Time"). This was first performed in the camp to an audience of prisoners and prison guards, the composer playing a poorly maintained upright piano, in freezing conditions in January 1941. Thus the enforced introspection and reflection of camp life bore fruit in one of 20th-century European classical music's acknowledged masterpieces. The "end of time" of the title is not purely an allusion to the Apocalypse, the work's ostensible subject, but also refers to the way in which Messiaen, through rhythm and harmony, used time in a way completely different from the music of his predecessors or contemporaries.See extended discussion in Griffiths (1985), Chapter 6: ''A Technique for the End of Time'', particularly pp. 104–106
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b8dc831157810f0989f906e467557482" name="Eglise_de_la_sainte_trinite_Paris" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/b8dc831157810f0989f906e467557482.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>