<document id="1372c6e051d95a90adeb2d31ff003554-3.3" name="South_Side_(Chicago)" cat="11">
<text>
With its factories, steel mills, and meat-packing plants, the South Side saw a sustained period of immigration which began around the 1840s and continued through World War II. Irish, Italian, Polish and Lithuanian immigrants, in particular, settled in neighborhoods adjacent to industrial zones. African Americans resided in Bronzeville (around 35th and State Streets) in an area called "the Black Belt", and after World War II they spread across the South Side.  The Black Belt, which gave a new meaning to the term ghetto, arose from discriminatory real estate practices and the threat of violence in nearby ethnic white neighborhoods.

Post-Reconstruction black southerners migrated to Chicago in large numbers and caused the African American population to nearly quadruple from 4,000 to 15,000 between 1870 and 1890.  The population was concentrated on the South Side. 

In the 20th century, the numbers expanded with the Great Migration as African Americans voted with their feet and left the South's lynchings, disfranchisement, poor job opportunities and limited education.  By 1910 the black population in Chicago reached 40,000, with 78% residing in the South Side's "Black Belt".  It extended for 30 blocks along State Street and was only a few blocks wide.  The South Side had problems but was also the place where African Americans created a vibrant community with their own businesses, music, food and culture.  Compared to their previous conditions in the rural South, many saw opportunities for themselves and their children in Chicago.

After some time, as more blacks moved into the South Side, descendants of earlier immigrants, such as ethnic Irish, began to move out.  Later housing pressures and civic unrest caused more whites to leave the city, a complexity of what was a succession of different ethnic groups.  Older residents of means moved to newer housing developed in suburbs as new migrants entered the city., driving further demographic changes in the south side.


The South Side has had a history of racial segregation. During the 1920s and 1930s, housing cases on the South Side created legal debate in cases such as ''Hansberry v. Lee'', , which went to the U. S. Supreme Court.  It challenged racial restrictions in the Washington Park Subdivision.

Later, the construction of the Dan Ryan Expressway added a physical barrier between some white neighborhoods and black neighborhoods.  It was the divide between Bridgeport (traditionally Irish) and Bronzeville. 

After decades in the late 20th century of sustaining some of the poorest housing conditions in the United States, the Chicago Housing Authority has begun replacing the old high-rise public housing with mixed-income, lower-density developments in the Plan for Transformation. Many of the CHA's massive public housing projects, which lined several miles of South State Street, have been torn down. Among the largest were the Robert Taylor Homes.

Chinatown gate
Private sector redevelopment is occurring rapidly. Neighborhood rehabilitation (and, in some cases, gentrification) can also be seen in parts of Washington Park, Woodlawn (#42) and Bronzeville, as well as in Bridgeport and McKinley Park. Historic Pullman's redevelopment is another example of a work in progress. Chinatown is located on the South Side and has seen a surge in growth.  It has become an increasingly popular destination for both tourists and locals alike and is a cornerstone of the city's Chinese community. The South Loop's booming mid-decade construction suggests that the South Side will be populated with more Caucasians in the coming years. The South Side offers many outdoor amenities, such as miles of public lakefront parks and beaches, as it borders Lake Michigan on its eastern side.

Segregation meant that blacks became concentrated on the South Side, especially as some whites left.  Mid-century industrial restructuring in meat packing and the steel industry meant that many jobs were lost.  African Americans who became educated and achieved middle-class jobs also left after Civil Rights Movement achieved changes in housing, and the South Side became relatively depopulated, with a concentration of poor families.  It lost many of the businesses and cultural amenities of its peak days.  A large Mexican-American population resides in Little Village (South Lawndale) and areas south of 99th Street. Hyde Park is home to the University of Chicago as well as the South Side's largest Jewish population, which is centered on Chicago's oldest synagogue, the Chicago Landmark KAM Isaiah Israel.

Street gangs have been prominent in some South Side neighborhoods for over a century, beginning with those of Irish immigrants, who established the first territories against other European immigrants and black migrants.  Some other neighborhoods have been relatively safe for a big city. By the 1960s, gangs such as the Vice Lords began to improve their public image, moving from thuggish ventures to obtaining government and private grants. By 2000, gangs crossed gender lines to include about a 20% female composition. The deep South Side has a population of 752,496 that is over 93% African-American and that includes zip codes that are over 98% black or African-American.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7b7a4cd0d5c161dc3babcbc482fd304e" name="Robertaylorhome" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/7b7a4cd0d5c161dc3babcbc482fd304e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>