<document id="1372c6e051d95a90adeb2d31ff003554-5" name="South_Side_(Chicago)" cat="11">
<text>
The South Side is home to many official landmarks and other notable buildings and structures.  It hosts three of the four Chicago Registered Historic Places from the original October 15, 1966 National Register of Historic Places list (Chicago Pile-1, Robie House, & Lorado Taft Midway Studios).  Since its construction in 1968, 1700 East 56th Street has been the tallest building on the South Side.  However, One Museum Park, which is along Roosevelt Road, the northern border of the South Side, will soon take over this title.  One Museum Park West, which will be next door to One Museum Park, will also be one of the tallest buildings in Chicago. 1700 East 56th will continue to be the tallest building south of 13th street. Although most of the other tall buildings in Chicago are in the Loop or Near North Side community areas, many Chicago Landmarks are located on the South Side.


There is a large concentration of landmark buildings in the Black Metropolis-Bronzeville District. Also, buildings such as Powhatan Apartments, Robie House and John J. Glessner House are among the South Side landmarks. The South Side has many of Chicago's landmark places of worship such as Eighth Church of Christ, Scientist, First Church of Deliverance and K.A.M. Isaiah Israel Temple. The South Side also has several landmark districts including two located in Barack Obama's Kenwood community area: Kenwood District, and North Kenwood District. In addition to its art museums the South Side hosts the Museum of Science and Industry, which although not an art museum has its place in the artistic fabric of the city.  The Museum of Science and Industry is located in the Palace of Fine Arts, one of the few remaining buildings from the 1893 World's Columbian Exposition, which was hosted in South Side.


In addition to hosting Obama, the South Side is the residence of other currently prominent black leaders such as Jesse Jackson and Louis Farrakhan.  It is also place where United States Congressmen Jesse Jackson, Jr. and Bobby Rush (a former Black Panther leader) serve.

The South Side has been a place of political controversy. Although the locations of some of these notable controversies have not become officials landmarks, they remain important parts of Chicago history. The Chicago Race Riot of 1919 was the worst of the approximately 25 riots during the Red Summer of 1919 and required 6000 National Guard troops to quell.  As mentioned above, segregation has been a political theme of controversy for some time on the South Side as exhibited by Hansberry v. Lee, .
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="dc8770cb8e9529f55093b2793107aeb1" name="Chicago-race-riot" sectnum="5#1">../img/dc8770cb8e9529f55093b2793107aeb1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>