<document id="1372c6e051d95a90adeb2d31ff003554-3.5" name="South_Side_(Chicago)" cat="11">
<text>
The former Hyde Park Township
The Illinois Constitution gave rise to townships that provided municipal services in 1850. Several townships surrounding Chicago incorporated in order to better serve their residents. However, growth and prosperity led to an overburdened government system. In 1889, most of these townships determined that they would be better off as part of a larger Chicago. Lake View, Jefferson, Cicero, Lake, and Hyde Park Townships were annexed.  Today's South Side is mostly a combination of the old Hyde Park and Lake Townships. Within these townships many had made speculative bets on the future prosperity of the respective regions.  Much of the South Side has evolved from these speculative investments. Stephen A. Douglas, Paul Cornell, George Pullman and various business entities have developed South Chicago real estate. The Pullman District, a former company town, Hyde Park Township, various platted communities and subdivisions were the results of such efforts.


The Union Stock Yards, which were once located in the South Side's New City community area (#61), at one point employed 25,000 people and produced 82 percent of the domestic meat consumption.  They were so synonymous with the City for over a century that they were mentioned as part of the lyrics of Frank Sinatra's "My Kind of Town", in the phrase: "The Union Stockyard, Chicago is..." The Union Stock Yard Gate marking the old entrance to stockyards was designated a Chicago Landmark on February 24, 1972 and a National Historic Landmark on May 29, 1981.

By the 1930s, Chicago boasted a composition which included over 25% residential structures less than 10 years old, many of which were bungalows. These continued to be built in the working-class South Side into the 1960s. Kitchenettes, often including Murphy beds and Pullman kitchens, also composed a large part of the housing supply during and after the Great Depression, especially in the Black Belt. Chicago's South Side had a history of philanthropic subsidized housing dating back to 1919. 


In 1949, the United States Congress passed the Housing Act to fund public housing to try to improve housing in many cities. The CHA produced a plan of citywide projects, which was rejected by some of the Chicago City Council's white aldermen who opposed public housing in their wards. This led to a CHA policy of construction of family housing in black residential areas, concentrated on the South and West Sides of the city.

Gentrification of parts of the Douglas community area has bolstered the Black Metropolis-Bronzeville District. Gentrification in various parts of the South Side has displaced many African Americans. The South Side hosts numerous cooperatives. Hyde Park has several middle-income co-ops, and other South Side regions have limited equity (subsidized, price-controlled) co-ops. These regions have experienced condominium construction and conversion in the 1970s and 1980s.  In addition, the South Side has regions that have been known for great wealth, such as Prairie Avenue.  Its 21st century redevelopment includes One Museum Park and One Museum Park West.

The South Side has accommodated much of the city's conference business with various convention centers. The current McCormick Place Convention Center is the largest convention center in the United States, and the third largest in the world.  Previously, the South Side hosted conventions at the Chicago Coliseum and the International Amphitheatre. Although the South Side does not have any retail offerings that rival the Magnificent Mile, it does have the Ford City Mall and the surrounding shopping district, which includes several big-box retailers.


The South Side has been home some the most significant figures in the history of American politics. The first African-American United States President Barack Obama, the first female African-American United States Senator Carol Moseley Braun, and first African-American presidential candidate to win a primary, Jesse Jackson.  Before them, United States Congressman and the first African-American Mayor of Chicago Harold Washington and groundbreaking Congressman William L. Dawson achieved political success from from the South Side.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c6fce0058d104a705c6b9059c3a2c5bd" name="Livestock_chicago_1947" sectnum="3.5#1">../img/c6fce0058d104a705c6b9059c3a2c5bd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>