<document id="13b469287d2b28af5537045326f5e2d2-7" name="Weymouth,_Dorset" cat="11">
<text>
The Chesil Education Partnership pyramid area operates in south Dorset, and includes five infant schools, four junior schools, twelve primary schools, four secondary schools and two special schools. 73.3 % of Weymouth residents have qualifications, which is slightly below the Dorset average of 73.8 %. 8.8 % of residents have higher qualifications (Level 4 +), about half the Dorset average of 18.3 %.

There are three secondary schools in Weymouth&mdash;All Saints' Church of England School in Wyke Regis, Budmouth Technology College in Chickerell and Wey Valley School and Sports College in Broadwey which was added to the Government's Failing Schools list in 2007 as only 27% of the students achieved 5 A* to C passes. http://www.telegraph.co.uk/education/educationnews/3356423/Full-list-of-failing-schools.html. The fourth secondary school in the Chesil Education Partnership is Royal Manor Arts College on the Isle of Portland. All Saints' has 921 students on roll, Budmouth has 1560 and Wey Valley 1171. In 2006, 31 % of students at Wey Valley, and 58 % of students at All Saints' and Budmouth, attained five or more A* to C GCSEs including English and mathematics.

Budmouth College also has a sixth form centre which had 296 students in 2006. Weymouth College in Melcombe Regis is a further education college which has around 7,500 students from South West England and overseas, about 1500 studying A-Level courses. In 2006, Budmouth students received an average of 647.6 UCAS points, and Weymouth College students gained 614.1. Some secondary and A-Level students commute to Dorchester to attend The Thomas Hardye School; in 2007, 79 % of Hardye school students received five or more A* to C GCSEs, and 78 % of all A-Level results were A to C grades.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bf086f3130932e7d025ae45d4fcae041" name="Weymouthcollege" sectnum="7#1">../img/bf086f3130932e7d025ae45d4fcae041.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>