<document id="13b469287d2b28af5537045326f5e2d2-6" name="Weymouth,_Dorset" cat="11">
<text>
Weymouth railway station is the terminus of the route from London Waterloo and the route from Westbury and Bristol. Its size was appropriate for the rail traffic that came in and out of Weymouth on summer Saturdays, however it was oversized as trains became less popular, and was demolished in 1986. A smaller station took up part of the site, and the rest was given to commercial development. Parts of the South West Main Line west of Poole have been reduced from dual to single track; as part of preparations for the 2012 Olympic Games, local councils have lobbied the Department for Transport to relay the track and increase services to London and Bristol, and to introduce new direct services to Exeter. Services to London Waterloo began running every 30 minutes from December 2007, but services through Bristol to Cardiff were reduced.

An unusual feature of the railways in Weymouth was that until 1987, the town had street running of main-line trains though the streets and along the Weymouth Harbour Tramway to the Quay station at the eastern end of the harbour, to travel to mainland Europe by sea. Due to declining business, goods traffic ceased in 1972, but passenger services continued until 1987, when these services ceased from lack of use. The Quay Station houses the Condor Ferries Terminal; Condor Ferries' main UK port is Weymouth, and the HSC Condor Express runs from the harbour to the French port of St Malo, and the Channel Islands of Guernsey and Jersey.

Local bus services are run by First Hampshire & Dorset, which bought the local Southern National company. Services run from Weymouth to the Isle of Portland, Dorchester, Bournemouth, Wool, Beaminster, Axminster, other villages and the town's holiday parks. Weymouth is connected to towns and villages along the Jurassic Coast by the Jurassic Coast Bus service, which runs along the route of  from Exeter to Poole, through Sidford, Beer, Seaton, Lyme Regis, Charmouth, Bridport, Abbotsbury, Weymouth, Wool, and Wareham. This service is convenient for walkers who can ride the bus to or from a walk along the coast.


The A354 road connects the town to the A35 trunk road in Dorchester, and terminates at Easton on the Isle of Portland. The A353 road runs east from Weymouth to the south of Warmwell, where it connects with the A352 to the Isle of Purbeck and Wareham. In the 1980s the town centre was bypassed by the A354 to Portland, but the government's road building policy changed before a proposed relief road could be completed. The A354 follows its original route through Upwey and Broadwey, where traffic problems are common at peak tourist times, particularly on event days such as the carnival.

The relief road's construction was delayed by opposition from residents and environmental groups, including Transport 2000 and the Campaign to Protect Rural England, who object to the route's partial destruction of a nature reserve, which is an AONB and SSSI. With Weymouth and Portland scheduled to host 2012 Olympic sailing events the project reopened; the local authorities favouring a more environmentally friendly proposal than in the 1990s. On 5 April 2007, Dorset County Council granted planning permission for a modified proposal including a single carriageway running  north, and a 1000-space park-and-ride scheme, costing £84.5 million. Work commenced in 2008; it has been agreed that the work be completed in three years, in time for the 2012 Olympic sailing events.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="294e4ba478c9501c1c5c39386f879af8" name="Tramway_near_Ferrys_corner" sectnum="6#1">../img/294e4ba478c9501c1c5c39386f879af8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>