<document id="1404d91ef73f91e363fe2c8f774d19df-4.7" name="Albertosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
The Dry Island bonebed discovered by Barnum Brown and his crew contains the remains of 22 ''Albertosaurus'', the most individuals found in one locality of any Cretaceous theropod, and the second-most of any large theropod dinosaur behind the ''Allosaurus'' assemblage at the Cleveland Lloyd Dinosaur Quarry in Utah. The group seems to be composed of one very old adult; eight adults between 17 and 23 years old; seven sub-adults undergoing their rapid growth phases at between 12 and 16 years old; and six juveniles between the ages of 2 and 11 years, who had not yet reached the growth phase.

The near-absence of herbivore remains and the similar state of preservation between the many individuals at the ''Albertosaurus'' bonebed quarry led Phil Currie to conclude that the locality was not a predator trap like the La Brea Tar Pits in California, and that all of the preserved animals died at the same time. Currie claims this as evidence of pack behavior. Other scientists are skeptical, observing that the animals may have been driven together by drought, flood or for other reasons.(published abstract only)

There is abundant evidence for gregarious behavior among herbivorous dinosaurs, including ceratopsians and hadrosaurs. However, only rarely are so many dinosaurian predators found at the same site. Small theropods like ''Deinonychus'', ''Coelophysis'' and ''Megapnosaurus (Syntarsus) rhodesiensis'' have been found in aggregations, as have larger predators like ''Allosaurus'' and ''Mapusaurus''. There is some evidence of gregarious behavior in other tyrannosaurids as well. Fragmentary remains of smaller individuals were found alongside "Sue," the ''Tyrannosaurus'' mounted in the Field Museum of Natural History in Chicago, and a bonebed in the Two Medicine Formation of Montana contains at least three specimens of ''Daspletosaurus'', preserved alongside several hadrosaurs. These findings may corroborate the evidence for social behavior in ''Albertosaurus'', although some or all of the above localities may represent temporary or unnatural aggregations. Others have speculated that instead of social groups, at least some of these finds represent Komodo dragon-like mobbing of carcasses, where aggressive competition leads to some of the predators being killed and cannibalized.

Currie also offers speculation on the pack-hunting habits of ''Albertosaurus''. The leg proportions of the smaller individuals were comparable to those of Ornithomimids, which were probably among the fastest dinosaurs. Younger ''Albertosaurus'' were probably equally fleet-footed, or at least faster than their prey. Currie hypothesized that the younger members of the pack may have been responsible for driving their prey towards the adults, who were larger and more powerful, but also slower. Juveniles may also have had different lifestyles than adults, filling predator niches between the enormous adults and the smaller contemporaneous theropods, the largest of which were two orders of magnitude smaller than adult ''Albertosaurus'' in mass. A similar situation is observed in modern Komodo dragons, with hatchlings beginning life as small insectivores before growing to become the dominant predators on their islands. However, as the preservation of behavior in the fossil record is exceedingly rare, these ideas cannot readily be tested.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1404d91ef73f91e363fe2c8f774d19df" name="Albertosaurus" sectnum="4.7#1">../img/1404d91ef73f91e363fe2c8f774d19df.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>