<document id="140b555a48bea953d10e4d65ac6d11db-3" name="Rufus_Wilmot_Griswold" cat="17">
<text>
Griswold first met Edgar Allan Poe in Philadelphia in May 1841 while working for the ''Daily Standard''.Silverman, 211 At the outset, their relationship was cordial, at least superficially. In a letter dated March 29, 1841, Poe sent Griswold several poems for ''The Poets and Poetry of America'' anthology, writing that he would be proud to see "one or two of them in the book". Griswold included three of these poems: "Coliseum", "The Haunted Palace", and "The Sleeper". In November of that year Poe, who had previously praised Griswold in his "Autography" series as "a gentleman of fine taste and sound judgment", wrote a critical review of the anthology, on Griswold's behalf. Griswold paid Poe for the review and used his influence to have it published in a Boston periodical. The review was generally favorable, although Poe questioned the inclusion of certain authors and the omission of others.Silverman, 215–216 Poe also said that Griswold "unduly favored" New England writers.Omans, Glen A. "Poe and Washington Allston: Visionary Kin", collected in ''Poe and His Times: The Artist and His Milieu'', edited by Benjamin Franklin Fisher IV. Baltimore: The Edgar Allan Poe Society, 1990: 24. ISBN 0961644923. Griswold had expected more praise and Poe privately told others he was not particularly impressed by the book,Silverman, 216 even calling it "a most outrageous humbug" in a letter to a friend.Quinn, 352 In another letter, this time to fellow writer Frederick W. Thomas, Poe suggested that Griswold's promise to help get the review published was actually a bribe for a favorable review, knowing Poe needed the money.Quinn, 353

Making the relationship even more strained, only months later, Griswold was hired by George Rex Graham to take up Poe's former position as editor of ''Graham's Magazine''. Griswold, however, was paid more and given more editorial control of the magazine than Poe. Shortly after, Poe began giving a series of lectures called "The Poets and Poetry of America", the first of which was given in Philadelphia on November 25, 1843. Poe openly attacked Griswold in front of his large audience and continued to do so in similar lectures.Bayless, 75–76 Graham said that during these lectures, Poe "gave Mr. Griswold some raps over the knuckles of force sufficient to be remembered".Silverman, 218 In a letter dated January 16, 1845, Poe tried to reconcile with Griswold, promising him that his lecture now omitted all that Griswold found objectionable.Campbell, Killis. "The Poe-Griswold Controversy", ''The Mind of Poe and Other Studies''. New York: Russell & Russell, Inc., 1962: 67.

Another source of animosity between the two men was their competition for the attention of the poet Frances Sargent Osgood in the mid to late 1840s.Meyers, 209 While both she and Poe were still married to their respective spouses,Meyers, 174 the two carried on a public flirtation that resulted in much gossip among the literati. Griswold, who was smitten by Osgood, escorted her to literary salons and became her staunchest defender. "She is in all things the most admirable woman I ever knew", he wrote to publisher James T. Fields in 1848.Bayless, 144 Osgood responded by dedicating a collection of her poetry to Griswold, "as a souvenir of admiration for his genius, of regard for his generous character, and of gratitude for his valuable literary counsels".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f0b0ad8bf49e9b11e1ae8f9effc4c102" name="Edgar_Allan_Poe_2" sectnum="3#1">../img/f0b0ad8bf49e9b11e1ae8f9effc4c102.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>