<document id="141fda9d3524be1716761b17bc84fd68-4" name="Romeo_and_Juliet" cat="17">
<text>
It is unknown when exactly Shakespeare wrote ''Romeo and Juliet''. Juliet's nurse refers to an earthquake which she says occurred 11 years ago.''Romeo and Juliet'': I.iii.23. This may refer to the Dover Straits earthquake of 1580, which would date that particular line to 1591. Other earthquakes—both in England and in Verona—have been proposed in support of different dates.Gibbons (1980: 26–27). But the play's stylistic similarities with ''A Midsummer Night's Dream'' and other plays conventionally dated around 1594–95, place its composition sometime between 1591 and 1595.Gibbons (1980: 29–31). As well as ''A Midsummer Night's Dream'', Gibbons draws parallels with ''Love's Labour's Lost'' and ''Richard II''. One conjecture is that Shakespeare may have begun a draft in 1591, which he completed in 1595.Gibbons (1980: 29).

Shakespeare's ''Romeo and Juliet'' was published in two quarto editions prior to the publication of the First Folio of 1623. These are referred to as Q1 and Q2. The first printed edition, Q1, appeared in early 1597, printed by John Danter. Because its text contains numerous differences from the later editions, it is labelled a 'bad quarto'; the 20th-century editor T. J. B. Spencer described it as "a detestable text, probably a reconstruction of the play from the imperfect memories of one or two of the actors", suggesting that it had been pirated for publication.Spencer (1967: 284). An alternative explanation for Q1's shortcomings is that the play (like many others of the time) may have been heavily edited before performance by the playing company.Halio (1998: 1–2). In any event, its appearance in early 1597 makes 1596 the latest possible date for the play's composition.

The superior Q2 called the play ''The Most Excellent and Lamentable Tragedie of Romeo and Juliet''. It was printed in 1599 by Thomas Creede and published by Cuthbert Burby. Q2 is about 800 lines longer than Q1. Its title page describes it as "Newly corrected, augmented and amended". Scholars believe that Q2 was based on Shakespeare's pre-performance draft (called his foul papers), since there are textual oddities such as variable tags for characters and "false starts" for speeches that were presumably struck through by the author but erroneously preserved by the typesetter. It is a much more complete and reliable text, and was reprinted in 1609 (Q3), 1622 (Q4) and 1637 (Q5). In effect, all later Quartos and Folios of ''Romeo and Juliet'' are based on Q2, as are all modern editions since editors believe that any deviations from Q2 in the later editions (whether good or bad) are likely to arise from editors or compositors, not from Shakespeare.

The First Folio text of 1623 was based primarily on Q3, with clarifications and corrections possibly coming from a theatrical promptbook or Q1.Gibbons (1980: 21). Other Folio editions of the play were printed in 1632 (F2), 1664 (F3), and 1685 (F4).Gibbons (1980: ix). Modern versions—that take into account several of the Folios and Quartos—first appeared with Nicholas Rowe's 1709 edition, followed by Alexander Pope's 1723 version. Pope began a tradition of editing the play to add information such as stage directions missing in Q2 by locating them in Q1. This tradition continued late into the Romantic period. Fully annotated editions first appeared in the Victorian period and continue to be produced today, printing the text of the play with footnotes describing the sources and culture behind the play.Halio (1998: 8–9).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="04915e481dc2d94af254c3e1091542c3" name="Romeo_and_Juliet_Q2_Title_Page-2" sectnum="4#1">../img/04915e481dc2d94af254c3e1091542c3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>