<document id="141fda9d3524be1716761b17bc84fd68-3" name="Romeo_and_Juliet" cat="17">
<text>
''Romeo and Juliet'' borrows from a tradition of tragic love stories dating back to antiquity. One of these is Pyramus and Thisbe, from Ovid's Metamorphoses, which contains parallels to Shakespeare's story: the lovers' parents despise each other, and Pyramus falsely believes his lover Thisbe is dead.Halio (1998: 93). The ''Ephesiaca'' of Xenophon of Ephesus, written in the 3rd century, also contains several similarities to the play, including the separation of the lovers, and a potion which induces a deathlike sleep.Gibbons (1980: 33).

The earliest known version of the ''Romeo and Juliet'' tale is the story of Mariotto and Gianozza by Masuccio Salernitano, in the 33rd novel of his ''Il Novellino'' published in 1476. Salernitano sets the story in Siena and insists its events took place in his own lifetime. His version of the story includes the secret marriage, the colluding friar, the fray where a prominent citizen is killed, Mariotto's exile, Gianozza's forced marriage, the potion plot, and the crucial message that goes astray. In this version, Mariotto is caught and beheaded and Gianozza dies of grief.Gibbons (1980: 33–34); Levenson (2000: 4).

Luigi da Porto adapted the story as ''Giulietta e Romeo'' and included it in his ''Historia novellamente ritrovata di due Nobili Amanti'' published in 1530.Moore (1937: 38–44). Da Porto drew on ''Pyramus and Thisbe'' and Boccacio's Decameron. He gave it much of its modern form, including the names of the lovers, the rival families of Montecchi and Capuleti, and the location in Verona.Hosley (1965: 168). He also introduces characters corresponding to Shakespeare's Mercutio, Tybalt, and Paris. Da Porto presents his tale as historically true and claims it took place in the days of Bartolomeo II della Scala (a century earlier than Salernitano). Montecchi and Capuleti were actual 13th-century political factions, but the only connection between them is a mention in Dante's Purgatorio as an example of civil dissention.Moore (1930: 264–277) In da Porto's version Romeo takes poison and Giulietta stabs herself with his dagger.Gibbons (1980: 34–35).

In 1554, Matteo Bandello published the second volume of his ''Novelle'' which included his version of ''Giuletta e Romeo''. Bandello emphasises Romeo's initial depression and the feud between the families, and introduces the Nurse and Benvolio. Bandello's story was translated into French by Pierre Boaistuau in 1559 in the first volume of his ''Histories Tragiques''. Boaistuau adds much moralising and sentiment, and the characters indulge in rhetorical outbursts.Gibbons (1980: 35–36).

In his 1562 narrative poem ''The Tragical History of Romeus and Juliet'', Arthur Brooke translated Boaistuau faithfully, but adjusted it to reflect parts of Chaucer's ''Troilus and Criseyde''.Gibbons (1980: 37). There was a trend among writers and playwrights to publish works based on Italian ''novelles''—Italian tales were very popular among theatre-goers—and Shakespeare may well have been familiar with William Painter's 1567 collection of Italian tales titled ''Palace of Pleasure''.Keeble (1980: 18). This collection included a version in prose of the ''Romeo and Juliet'' story named ''"The goodly History of the true and constant love of Rhomeo and Julietta"''. Shakespeare took advantage of this popularity: ''The Merchant of Venice'', ''Much Ado About Nothing'', ''All's Well That Ends Well'', ''Measure for Measure'', and ''Romeo and Juliet'' are all from Italian ''novelle''. ''Romeo and Juliet'' is a dramatisation of Brooke's translation, and Shakespeare follows the poem closely, but adds extra detail to both major and minor characters (in particular the Nurse and Mercutio).Roberts (1902: 41–44); Gibbons (1980: 32, 36–37); Levenson (2000: 8–14).

Christopher Marlowe's ''Hero and Leander'' and ''Dido, Queen of Carthage'', both similar stories written in Shakespeare's day, are thought to be less of a direct influence, although they may have helped create an atmosphere in which tragic love stories could thrive.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5edae6af99107c530c7542d9d83af9f5" name="Arthur_Brooke_Tragicall_His" sectnum="3#1">../img/5edae6af99107c530c7542d9d83af9f5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>