<document id="141fda9d3524be1716761b17bc84fd68-7.12" name="Romeo_and_Juliet" cat="17">
<text>
All theatres were closed down by the puritan government on 6 September 1642. Upon the restoration of the monarchy in 1660, two patent companies (the King's Company and the Duke's Company) were established, and the existing theatrical repertoire divided between them.Marsden (2002: 21).


Sir William Davenant of the Duke's Company staged a 1662 adaptation in which Henry Harris played Romeo, Thomas Betterton Mercutio, and Betterton's wife Mary Saunderson Juliet: she was probably the first woman to play the role professionally.Van Lennep (1965).Halio (1998: 100–102). Another version closely followed Davenant's adaptation and was also regularly performed by the Duke's Company. This was a tragicomedy by James Howard, in which the two lovers survive.Levenson (2000: 71).

Thomas Otway's ''The History and Fall of Caius Marius'', one of the more extreme of the Restoration adaptations of Shakespeare, debuted in 1680. The scene is shifted from Renaissance Verona to ancient Rome; Romeo is Marius, Juliet is Lavinia, the feud is between patricians and plebeians; Juliet/Lavinia wakes from her potion before Romeo/Marius dies. Otway's version was a hit, and was acted for the next seventy years. His innovation in the closing scene was even more enduring, and was used in adaptations throughout the next 200 years: Theophilus Cibber's adaptation of 1744, and David Garrick's of 1748 both used variations on it.Marsden (2002: 26–27). These versions also eliminated elements deemed inappropriate at the time. For example, Garrick's version transferred all language describing Rosaline to Juliet, in order to heighten the idea of faithfulness and downplay the love-at-first-sight theme.Branam (1984: 170–179); Stone (1964: 191–206). In 1750 a "Battle of the Romeos" began, with Spranger Barry and Susannah Maria Arne (Mrs. Theophilus Cibber) at Covent Garden versus David Garrick and George Anne Bellamy at Drury Lane.Pedicord (1954: 14).

The earliest known production in North America was an amateur one: on 23 March 1730, a physician named Joachimus Bertrand placed an advertisement in the ''Gazette'' newspaper in New York, promoting a production in which he would play the apothecary.Morrison (2007: 231). The first professional performances of the play in North America were those of the Hallam Company.Morrison (2007: 232).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="713c50900e8abb9e593c4d5852550cdf" name="Mary_Saunderson_17th_century" sectnum="7.12#1">../img/713c50900e8abb9e593c4d5852550cdf.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>