<document id="14764de26f74fb2bff8e75c35c263b1b-4.10" name="Joseph_Johnson_(publisher)" cat="17">
<text>
During the 1790s alone, Johnson published 103 volumes of poetry&mdash;37% of his entire output in the genre. The bestselling poetical works of Cowper and Erasmus Darwin enriched Johnson's firm. Darwin's innovative ''The Botanic Garden'' (1791) was particularly successful: Johnson paid him 1,000 guineas before it was ever released and bought the copyright from him for £800, a staggeringly large sum.Chard (1977), 142–44. The poem contains three "interludes" in the form of dialogues between a poet and his bookseller. The bookseller asks the poet what Tyson calls "leading questions" in order to elucidate the poet's theory of poetry. Tyson comments "that although the flat questions of the practical-minded bookseller may be meant to parody Johnson's manner, most likely Darwin did not have him or any other particular bookseller in mind".Tyson, 110. After the success of ''The Botanic Garden'', Johnson published Darwin's work on evolution, ''Zoonomia'' (1794&ndash;96); his treatise ''A Plan on the Conduct of Female Education'' (1797); ''Phytologia; or, the Philosophy of Agriculture and Gardening'' (1800); and his poem ''The Temple of Nature'' (1803).Tyson, 142. According to Braithwaite, ''The Temple of Nature'' was ''Zoonomia'' in verse and "horrified reviewers with its warring, factious, overly materialistic view of the universe".Braithwaite, 174. 

Johnson continued to publish the poetic works of Aikin and Barbauld as well as those of George Dyer, Joseph Fawcett, James Hurdis, Joel Barlow, and Edward Williams. Most of the poets that Johnson promoted and published are not remembered today. However, in 1793, Johnson published William Wordsworth's ''An Evening Walk'' and ''Descriptive Sketches''; he remained Wordsworth's publisher until a disagreement separated them in 1799. Johnson also put out Samuel Taylor Coleridge's ''Fears of Solitude'' (1798). They were apparently close enough friends for Coleridge to leave his books at Johnson's shop when he toured Europe.Tyson, 109–13, 141–42, 171–75; Chard (1975), 51; Braithwaite, 127–31.

Johnson had a working relationship with illustrator William Blake for nearly twenty years: Johnson commissioned around 100 engravings from Blake—more than any other publisher—including the second edition of Wollstonecraft's ''Original Stories from Real Life'' (1791) and Darwin's ''Botanic Garden''.  Johnson may also have had some connection with Blake as a writer, judging from galley proofs of his ''French Revolution'' (1791). Yet, in ''An Island in the Moon'', Blake represents Johnson as "a bookseller without aesthetic values whose repetitive questions reveal his ignorance".Gaull, 265; Chard (1975), 51; Zall, 27.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="234e6c76c45b148bbf872c0abefcd9dd" name="BotanicGardenMeadia" sectnum="4.10#1">../img/234e6c76c45b148bbf872c0abefcd9dd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>