<document id="14764de26f74fb2bff8e75c35c263b1b-3.7" name="Joseph_Johnson_(publisher)" cat="17">
<text>
With time, Johnson's home became a nexus for radical thinkers, who appreciated his open-mindedness, generous spirit, and humanitarianism.  Although usually separated by geography, such thinkers would meet and debate with one another at Johnson's house in London, often over dinner.  This network not only brought authors into contact with each other, it also brought new writers to Johnson's business. For example, Priestley introduced John Newton to Johnson, Newton brought John Hewlett, and Hewlett invited Mary Wollstonecraft, who in turn attracted Mary Hays who brought William Godwin.Chard (1977), 150. With this broad network of acquaintances and reputation for free-thinking publications, Johnson became the favourite publisher of a generation of writers and thinkers. By bringing inventive, thoughtful people together, he "stood at the very heart of British intellectual life" for over twenty years.Chard (1975), 51; Zall, 26. Importantly, Johnson's circle was not made up entirely of either liberals or radicals. Chard emphasizes that it "was held together less by political liberalism than by a common interest in ideas, free enquiry, and creative expression in various fields".Chard (1975), 68; Zall, 26.

As Tyson notes, although "Johnson's circle" is usually used in the singular, there were at least two such "circles". The first was made up of a group of London associates: Fuseli, Gregory, Bonnycastle, and Geddes. The second consisted of Johnson's writers from farther afield, such as Priestley, Thomas Henry, Thomas Percival, Barbauld, Aikin, and Enfield. Later, more radicals would join, including Wollstonecraft, Wakefield, John Horne Tooke, and Thomas Christie.Tyson, 66.

Johnson's dinners became legendary and it appears, from evidence collected from diaries, that a large number of people attended each one.For a list of the most prominent attendees, see Tyson, 121. Although there were few regulars, except perhaps for Johnson's close London friends (Fuseli, Bonnycastle and, later, Godwin), the large number of luminaries, such as Thomas Paine, who attended attests to the reputation of these dinners.Lau, 104–09. The enjoyment and intellectual stimulation that these dinners provided is evidenced by the numerous references to them in diaries and letters. Barbauld wrote to her brother in 1784 that "our evenings, particularly at Johnson's, were so truly social and lively, that we protracted them sometimes till—but I am not telling tales."Qtd. in Tyson, 118. At one dinner in 1791, Godwin records that the conversation focused on "monarch, Tooke,  Johnson, Voltaire, ''pursuits'', and religion" .Qtd. in Tyson, 122. Although the conversation was stimulating, Johnson apparently only served his guests simple meals, such as boiled cod, veal, vegetables, and rice pudding. Many of the people that met at these dinners became fast friends, as did Fuseli and Bonnycastle; Godwin and Wollstonecraft eventually married.Tyson, 118; Gaull, 266; Chard (1975), 62–63.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ff456291551831cfbc4989a6d6f61c87" name="John_Henry_Fuseli_-_The_Nightmare" sectnum="3.7#1">../img/ff456291551831cfbc4989a6d6f61c87.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>