<document id="14764de26f74fb2bff8e75c35c263b1b-4.9" name="Joseph_Johnson_(publisher)" cat="17">
<text>
In 1790, with the publication of his ''Reflections on the Revolution in France'', philosopher and statesman Edmund Burke launched the first volley of a vicious pamphlet war in what became known as the Revolution Controversy. Because he had supported the American Revolution, friends and enemies alike expected him to support the French Revolution. His book, which decries the French Revolution, therefore came as a shock to nearly everyone. Priced at an expensive five shillings, it still sold over 10,000 copies in a few weeks.Braithwaite, 102. Reformers, particularly Dissenters, felt compelled to reply. Johnson's periodical, the ''Analytical Review'', published a summary and review of Burke's work within a couple of weeks of its publication. Two weeks later, Wollstonecraft responded to Burke with her ''Vindication of the Rights of Men''. In issuing one of the first and cheapest replies to Burke (''Vindication'' cost only one shilling), Johnson put himself at some risk. Thomas Cooper, who had also written a response to Burke, was later informed by the Attorney General that "although there was no exception to be taken to his pamphlet when in the hands of the upper classes, yet the government would not allow it to appear at a price which would insure its circulation among the people".Qtd. in Chard (1977), 147; see also Tyson, 126–27; Braithwaite, 132. Many others soon joined in the fray and Johnson remained at the centre of the maelstrom. By Braithwaite's count, Johnson published or sold roughly a quarter of the works responding to Burke within the following year.Tyson, 122, 135–40; Zall, 27–28; Braithwaite, 101–06. 

The most notable of all of these responses was Thomas Paine's ''Rights of Man''. Johnson originally agreed to publish the controversial work, but he backed out later for unknown reasons and J. S. Jordan distributed it (and was subsequently tried and imprisoned for its publication). Braithwaite speculates that Johnson did not agree with Paine's radical republican statements and was more interested in promoting the rights of Dissenters outlined in the other works he published.  After the initial risk was taken by Jordan, however, Johnson published Paine's work in an expensive edition, which was unlikely to be challenged at law.Tyson, 123–26; Chard (1975), 70; Braithwaite, 107–10. Yet, when Paine was himself later arrested, Johnson helped raise funds to bail him out and hid him from the authorities.Chard (1977), 139. A contemporary satire suggested that Johnson saved Paine from imprisonment:

Alarmed at the popular appeal of Paine's ''Rights of Man'', the king issued a proclamation against seditious writings in May 1792.  Booksellers and printers bore the brunt of this law, the effects of which came to a head in the 1794 Treason Trials.Tyson, 131–32; Chard (1975), 69. Johnson testified, publicly distancing himself from Paine and Barlow, despite the fact that the defendants were received sympathetically by the juries.Braithwaite, 144–46.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e259348ce584265d62ae1ab974479792" name="WollstonecraftVRM" sectnum="4.9#1">../img/e259348ce584265d62ae1ab974479792.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>