<document id="14764de26f74fb2bff8e75c35c263b1b-2.2" name="Joseph_Johnson_(publisher)" cat="17">
<text>
Immediately upon reopening his business, Johnson started publishing theological and political works by Priestley and other Dissenters. Starting in the 1770s, Johnson published more specifically Unitarian works, as well as texts advocating religious toleration; he also became personally involved in the Unitarian cause. He served as a conduit for information between Dissenters across the country and supplied provincial publishers with religious publications, thereby enabling Dissenters to spread their beliefs easily. Johnson participated in efforts to repeal the Test and Corporation Acts, which restricted the civil rights of Dissenters. In one six-year period of the 1770s, Johnson was responsible for publishing nearly one-third of the Unitarian works on the issue. He continued his support in 1787, 1789, and 1790, when Dissenters introduced repeal bills in Parliament, and he published much of the pro-repeal literature written by Priestley and others.Chard (2002), 95–101.Tyson, 38–44, 67–73, 93–94, 146–48, 184–88; Chard (1975), 59, 66; Braithwaite, 52.

Johnson was also instrumental in Theophilus Lindsey's founding of the first Unitarian chapel in London. He both obtained the building for it on Essex Street and its licence (with some difficulty, as Unitarians were feared in the eighteenth century). To capitalize on the opening of the new chapel in addition to helping out his friends, Johnson published Lindsey's inaugural sermon, which sold out in four days. Johnson continued to attend and participate actively in this congregation throughout his life. Lindsey and the church's other minister, John Disney, became two of Johnson's most active writers. In the 1780s, Johnson continued to advocate Unitarianism and published a series of controversial writings by Priestley arguing for its legitimacy. These writings did not make Johnson much money, but they agreed with his philosophy of open debate and religious toleration. Johnson also became the publisher for the Society for Promoting the Knowledge of the Scriptures, a Unitarian group determined to release new worship materials and commentaries on the Bible.Chard (2002), 95–101.Tyson, 38–44, 67–73, 93–94, 146–48, 184–88; Chard (1975), 59, 66; Braithwaite, 27–28, 65–66.

Although Johnson is known for publishing Unitarian works, particularly those of Priestley, he also published the works of other Dissenters, Anglicans, and Jews. The common thread uniting his disparate religious publications was religious toleration.Tyson, 69. For example, he published the Reverend George Gregory's 1787 English translation of Bishop Robert Lowth's seminal book on Hebrew poetry, ''De Sacra Poesi Hebraeorum''. Gregory published several other works with Johnson, such as ''Essays Historical and Moral'' (1785) and ''Sermons with Thoughts on the Composition and Delivery of a Sermon'' (1787).  Gregory exemplified the type of author that Johnson preferred to work with: industrious and liberal-minded, but not bent on self-glorification.Tyson, 61–62. Yet, as Helen Braithwaite writes in her study of Johnson, his "enlightened pluralistic approach was also seen by its opponents as inherently permissive, opening the door to all forms of unhealthy questioning and scepticism, and at odds with the stable virtues of established religion and authority".Braithwaite, 29.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="53ab151a36c23f0a88ec4f64d16cde9d" name="PriestleyFormsOfPrayer" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/53ab151a36c23f0a88ec4f64d16cde9d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>