<document id="14764de26f74fb2bff8e75c35c263b1b-4.13.5" name="Joseph_Johnson_(publisher)" cat="17">
<text>
Following the publication of Paine's provocative ''Rights of Man'' in 1791, a sedition law was passed in Britain and, in 1798, Johnson and several others were put on trial for selling Gilbert Wakefield's ''A Reply to Some Parts of the Bishop Llandaff's Address to the People of Great Britain'', a Unitarian work attacking the privileged position of the wealthy. The indictment against Johnson, written on a six-foot parchment roll, read (in part):


Braithwaite explains, "an English jury, in effect, was being asked to consider whether Joseph Johnson's intentions as a bookseller were really as dangerous and radical as those of Thomas Paine".Braithwaite, 155. An issue of the ''Analytical Review'' was even offered as evidence against Johnson. Despite having retained Thomas Erskine as his lawyer, who had successfully defended Hardy and Horne Tooke at the 1794 Treason Trials, and character references from George Fordyce, Aikin, and Hewlett, Johnson was fined £50 and sentenced to six months imprisonment at King's Bench Prison in February 1799. Braithwaite speculates:

Johnson's friends accused Erskine of using the trial as a political platform and not thinking of the best interests of his client. Johnson's imprisonment was not harsh; being relatively wealthy, Johnson rented a home for himself within the prison, where he continued to hold his weekly ''soirées''.Chard (1975), 71–72; Zall, 28–29; Tyson; 154–66; see Smyser for a detailed account of the trial; Braithwaite, 155–64.

Although Johnson still believed in the free exchange of ideas and was not embittered by his stay in prison, his publishing habits changed dramatically. After he was released, Johnson published very few political works and none were controversial.  Other booksellers followed suit, and Johnson's friend, Unitarian minister Theophilus Lindsey, wrote that "Johnson's fate deters them all". Johnson lost authors after the trial and experienced a noticeable decline in business. Furthermore, he gained fewer new authors, his stalwarts like Priestley began to complain that he was not attending to their business, and he was forced to cease publishing the ''Analytical Review''.Chard (1975), 73.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="45cea9793eb493e3070e98c2021a1a00" name="Kings_Bench_Prison_Microcosm_edited" sectnum="4.13.5#1">../img/45cea9793eb493e3070e98c2021a1a00.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>