<document id="1491ee65a9de339fe5777cbcb1513033-2.7.3" name="Battle_of_the_Coral_Sea" cat="29">
<text>
At 06:15 on May 8, from a position  southeast of Rossel Island (), Hara launched seven torpedo bombers to search the area bearing 140 to 230 degrees south and out to  from the Japanese carriers.  Assisting in the search were three Kawanishi Type 97s from Tulagi and four Type 1 bombers from Rabaul.  At 07:00, the carrier striking force turned to the southwest and was joined by two of Gotō's cruisers, ''Kinugasa'' and ''Furutaka'', for additional screening support.  The invasion convoy, Gotō, and Kajioka steered towards a rendezvous point  east of Woodlark Island to await the outcome of the carrier battle.  During the night the warm frontal zone with low-hanging clouds which had helped hide the American carriers on May 7 had moved north and east and now covered the Japanese carriers, limiting visibility to between  and .Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 219–221; Millot, pp. 72 & 80; Dull, p. 132; Lundstrom (2006), pp. 181 & 186; Morison, p. 46.  The carrier search aircraft included four from ''Shōkaku'' and three from ''Zuikaku''.  The floatplanes at Deboyne patrolled the area directly south of the Louisiades.  ''Furutaka'' and ''Kinugasa'' joined the striking force at 07:50.  After the previous day's losses, the striking force at this time consisted of 96 operational aircraft: 38 fighters, 33 dive bombers, and 25 torpedo bombers (Lundstrom 2006, p. 186).

''Yorktown'' (foreground) and ''Lexington'' prepare to launch aircraft at sunrise on May 8.

At 06:35 TF17, operating under Fitch's tactical control and positioned  southeast of the Lousiades, launched 18 SBDs to conduct a 360-degree search out to .  The skies over the American carriers were mostly clear, with  visibility.Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 221–222; Hoyt, p. 75; Cressman, p. 103; Woolridge, p. 48; Millot, pp. 82–83 & 87; Dull, p. 132; Lundstrom (2006), pp. 181–184. Twelve SBDs were assigned to the northern search area where the Japanese carriers were expected to be.  The six SBDs assigned to the southern sector were to fly out only  and then assume close-in anti-submarine patrol duty upon their return to TF17.  At this time operational aircraft strength for TF17 was 117, including 31 fighters, 65 dive bombers, and 21 torpedo planes (Lundstrom 2006, p. 183)  Eight SBDs were assigned as close-in anti-submarine patrol, and 16 fighters, eight from each ship, to the CAP (Lundstrom 2006, p. 183).  Around 01:10, Fletcher detached the destroyer ''Monaghan'' to try to find out what had happened to ''Neosho''. ''Monaghan'' searched throughout the day, but, basing her search on the erroneous coordinates in the tanker's last message, was unable to locate her and returned to TF17 that evening.  While separated from TF17, ''Monaghan'' sent several messages to Nimitz and MacArthur, to allow TF17 to maintain radio silence (Cressman, p. 103; Hoyt, p. 127; Lundstrom 2006, p. 181).  Fitch was not actually notified by Fletcher he was in tactical control of the carriers until 09:08 (Lundstrom 2006, p. 186).  According to Parker (p. 29), Fletcher was informed early on May 8 his Fleet Radio Unit (an onboard intelligence team) had located Japanese carriers northeast of his position.

At 08:20, a ''Lexington'' SBD piloted by Joseph G. Smith spotted the Japanese carriers through a hole in the clouds and notified TF17.  Two minutes later, a ''Shōkaku'' search plane commanded by Kenzō Kanno sighted TF17 and notified Hara.  The two forces were about  away from each other.  Both sides raced to launch their strike aircraft.Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 222–225; Hoyt, pp. 76–77; Cressman, p. 103; Woolridge, pp. 40–41; Hoehling, pp. 52–53; Millot, pp. 81–85; Dull, pp. 132–133; Lundstrom (2006), pp. 185–187; Morison, pp. 48–49.  Kanno, a warrant officer, was the middle-seat observer on a plane piloted by Petty Officer First Class Tsuguo Gotō. The radioman was Petty Officer Second Class Seijirō Kishida (Werneth, p. 67).  Radio interception analysts in TF17 copied Kanno's messages and alerted Fletcher his carrier's location was known to the Japanese.  Smith's report mistakenly placed the Japanese carriers  south of their actual position.  An SBD piloted by Robert E. Dixon took over for Smith and stayed on station near the Japanese carriers to help guide in the U.S. strike until 10:45 (Morison).

At 09:15, the Japanese carriers launched a combined strike of 18 fighters, 33 dive bombers, and 18 torpedo planes, commanded by Lieutenant Commander Kakuichi Takahashi.  The American carriers each launched a separate strike. ''Yorktown's'' group consisted of six fighters, 24 dive bombers, and nine torpedo planes and was on its way by 09:15.  ''Lexington's'' group of nine fighters, 15 dive bombers, and 12 torpedo planes was off at 09:25.  Both the American and Japanese carrier warship forces turned to head directly for each other's location at high speed in order to shorten the distance their aircraft would have to fly on their return legs.Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 224–227 & 243–246; Hoyt, pp. 79 & 89; Cressman, p. 104; Millot, p. 85; Dull, pp. 132–133; Lundstrom (2006), pp. 186–187; Morison, p. 49.  An odd number of fighters took part in ''Lexington's'' attack because one of VF-2's Wildcats, piloted by Doc Sellstrom, was damaged during launch preparations and was forced to stay behind.  TF17 recovered its returning scout aircraft between 09:20 and 10:50, and launched 10 SBDs for anti-submarine patrol at 10:12.  The Japanese strike force included nine fighters, 19 dive bombers, and 10 torpedo planes from ''Shōkaku'' and nine fighters, 14 dive bombers, and 8 torpedo planes from ''Zuikaku''.  The fighters were Type 0s, the dive bombers were Type 99 ''kanbaku'', and the torpedo planes were Type 97 ''kankō''.  Takahashi was in one of ''Shōkaku's'' ''kanbaku''.  By heading south, Takagi unwittingly moved his carriers into the range of the American TBD torpedo planes, which otherwise would have been forced to turn back without participating in the attack (Lunstrom 2006, p. 187).  Shortly after 10:00, two ''Yorktown'' CAP Wildcats shot down a Japanese Type 97 scout aircraft (Lundstrom 2006, p. 187).

''Yorktown's'' dive bombers, led by William O. Burch, reached the Japanese carriers at 10:32 and paused to allow the slower torpedo squadron to arrive so that they could conduct a simultaneous attack.  At this time ''Shōkaku'' and ''Zuikaku'' were about  apart, with ''Zuikaku'' hidden under a rain squall of low-hanging clouds.  The two carriers were protected by 16 CAP Zero fighters.  The ''Yorktown'' dive bombers commenced their attacks at 10:57 on ''Shōkaku'' and hit the radically maneuvering carrier with two  bombs, tearing open the forecastle and causing heavy damage to the carrier's flight and hangar decks.  The ''Yorktown'' torpedo planes missed with all of their ordnance.  Two U.S. dive bombers and two CAP Zeros were shot down during the attack.Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 228–231; Hoyt, pp. 79–84; Cressman, pp. 104–106; Hoehling, p. 62; Millot, pp. 87–88 & 91; Dull, p. 133; Lundstrom (2006), pp. 192–195; D'Albas, p. 105; Hata, pp. 42–43.  The second hit was scored by SBD pilot John James Powers, who was shot down by a CAP Zero and killed during his dive.  Tetsuzō Iwamoto was one of the CAP pilots airborne at the time.  Cressman states that Iwamoto flew from ''Shōkaku'' but Hata (p. 241) states he was with ''Zuikaku''.  Another VS-5 squadron SBD, crewed by Davis Chafee and John A. Kasselman, was shot down by a CAP Zero during the attack.  During ''Yorktown's'' attack, a CAP Zero flown by Takeo Miyazawa was shot down by a Wildcat piloted by William S. Woolen, and a CAP Zero flown by Hisashi Ichinose was shot down by a Wildcat piloted by Elbert Scott McCuskey.  Lundstrom states that both Zeros were from ''Zuikaku''.  Hata, however, states that Miyazawa was a member of ''Shōkaku's'' fighter group and that he died after shooting down a U.S. torpedo plane and then deliberately crashing his Zero into another (Hata, p. 42).  Also flying in the Japanese CAP were future aces Yoshinao Kodaira and Kenji Okabe (Hata, pp. 286 & 329).  Aces Yoshimi Minami and Sadamu Komachi were members of ''Shōkaku's'' fighter group at this time (Hata, p. 265 & 281) but Hata does not say if they were with the CAP or the strike escort.



''Lexington's'' aircraft arrived and attacked at 11:30.  Two dive bombers attacked ''Shōkaku'', hitting the carrier with one  bomb, causing further damage.  Two other dive bombers dove on ''Zuikaku'', missing with their bombs.  The rest of ''Lexington's'' dive bombers were unable to find the Japanese carriers in the heavy clouds.  ''Lexington's'' TBDs missed ''Shōkaku'' with all 11 of their torpedoes.  The 13 CAP Zeros on patrol at this time shot down three Wildcats.Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 236–243; Hoyt, pp. 84–85; Cressman, p. 106; Hoehling, pp. 63–65; Millot, pp. 88–92; Dull, p. 133; Lundstrom (2006), pp. 195 & 559; D'Albas, p. 106.  One of ''Lexington's'' bomber pilots was Harry Brinkley Bass.  The three Wildcat pilots killed, from VF-2 squadron, were John B. "Bull" Bain, Dale W. Peterson, and Richard M. Rowell (Lundstrom).  The Japanese CAP claimed to have shot down 24 U.S. aircraft (Hata, p. 48).

With her flight deck heavily damaged and 223 of her crew killed or wounded, ''Shōkaku'' was unable to conduct further aircraft operations.  Her captain, Takaji Joshima, requested permission from Takagi and Hara to withdraw from the battle, to which Takagi agreed.  At 12:10, ''Shōkaku'', accompanied by two destroyers, retired to the northeast.Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 242–243; Hoyt, p. 86; Cressman, p. 106; Millot, pp. 91–92; Parshall, p. 63; Dull, p. 133; Lundstrom (2006), p. 195; Tully, "IJN Shokaku" (Tully reports only 40 wounded).  ''Shōkaku's'' total losses were 108 killed and 114 wounded.  The Japanese CAP fighter pilots claimed to have shot down 39 U.S. aircraft during the attack, at a cost of two Zeros destroyed and two damaged.  Actual U.S. losses in the attack were two SBDs (from ''Yorktown'') and three Wildcats (from ''Lexington'').  More U.S. aircraft were lost during the subsequent return to their carriers.  The destroyers which accompanied ''Shōkaku's'' retirement were ''Ushio'' and ''Yugure'' (Tully).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4280f727a9e8d8a906dde80b7a68e805" name="BattleCoralSea_Shokaku_g17031" sectnum="2.7.3#1">../img/4280f727a9e8d8a906dde80b7a68e805.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>