<document id="1491ee65a9de339fe5777cbcb1513033-2.6.1" name="Battle_of_the_Coral_Sea" cat="29">
<text>
At 06:25 on May 7, TF17 was  due south of Rossel Island ().  At this time, Fletcher sent Crace's cruiser and destroyer force, now designated Task Group (TG) 17.3, to block the Jomard Passage.  Fletcher understood that Crace would be operating without air cover since TF17's carriers would be busy trying to locate and attack the Japanese carriers.  The detachment of Crace's warships reduced the anti-aircraft defenses for Fletcher's carriers.  Nevertheless, Fletcher decided that the risk was necessary in order to ensure that the Japanese invasion forces could not slip through to Port Moresby while he was engaged with the Japanese carriers.Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 189–190 & 206–209; Hoyt, pp. 51–52; Cressman, p. 94; Millot, pp. 62–63; Lundstrom (2006), pp. 161–162; Henry, p. 50; Morison, p. 37.  At this time, TG17.3 consisted of cruisers ''Chicago'', ''Australia'', and ''Hobart'' and destroyers ''Walke'', ''Perkins'', and ''Farragut''.  ''Farragut'' was detached from TF17's screen (Millot and Morison).

Believing Takagi's carrier force was somewhere north of his location, in the vicinity of the Louisiades, Fletcher directed ''Yorktown'' to send 10 SBD dive bombers as scouts to search that area beginning at 06:19.  In the meantime, Takagi, located approximately  due east of Fletcher (), launched 12 Type 97 carrier bombers at 06:00 to scout for TF17.  Hara believed that Fletcher's ships were located to the south and advised Takagi to send the aircraft to search that area.  Around the same time, Gotō's cruisers ''Kinugasa'' and ''Furutaka'' launched four Kawanishi E7K2 Type 94 floatplanes to search southeast of the Louisiades.  Augmenting their search were several floatplanes from Deboyne, four Kawanishi Type 97s from Tulagi, and three Mitsubishi Type 1 bombers from Rabaul.  Each side readied the rest of its carrier attack aircraft to launch immediately once the enemy was located.Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 189–190; Hoyt, pp. 37–38 & 53; Millot, pp. 57–58 & 63; Lundstrom (2006), pp. 159 & 165–166; Morison, pp. 33–34.  At this time TF17 had 128 and Takagi 111 operational aircraft (Lundstrom 2006, p. 159).  Also this day, Inoue ordered the four ''I''-class submarines to deploy further south to intercept any Allied ships returning to Australia following the impending battle (Lundstrom 2006, p. 159).

Japanese carrier dive bombers head towards the reported position of American carriers on May 7.

At 07:22 one of Takagi's carrier scouts, from ''Shōkaku'', reported that it had located American ships 182 degrees,  from Takagi.  At 07:45 the scout confirmed that it had located "one carrier, one cruiser, and three destroyers".  Another ''Shōkaku'' scout aircraft quickly confirmed the sighting.Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', p. 190; Cressman, p. 95; Dull, p. 130; Lundstrom (2006), p. 166.  The ''Shōkaku'' aircraft had actually sighted and misidentified the ''Neosho'' and ''Sims''.  Believing that he had located the American carriers, Hara, with Takagi's concurrence, immediately launched all of his available aircraft.  A total of 78 aircraft—18 Zero fighters, 36 Type 99 dive bombers, and 24 torpedo aircraft—began launching from ''Shōkaku'' and ''Zuikaku'' at 08:00 and were on their way by 08:15 towards the reported sighting.Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 190–191; Hoyt, p. 38; Cressman, p. 95; Millot, pp. 58–59; Lundstrom (2006), p. 166.  Shigekazu Shimazaki led ''Zuikaku's'' torpedo bombers in this attack.

At 08:20, one of the ''Furutaka'' aircraft found Fletcher's carriers and immediately reported it to Inoue's headquarters at Rabaul, which passed the report on to Takagi.  The sighting was confirmed by a ''Kinugasa'' floatplane at 08:30.  Takagi and Hara, confused by the conflicting sighting reports they were receiving, decided to continue with the strike on the ships to their south, but turned their carriers towards the northwest to close the distance with ''Furutaka's'' reported contact.Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 192–193; Cressman, p. 95; Millot, p. 59; Lundstrom (2006), pp. 166–167; Werneth, p. 67.  Cressman reports that a scout SBD piloted by John L. Nielsen shot down an Aichi E13A from Deboyne, killing its crew including plane commander Eiichi Ogata.  Another SBD, piloted by Lavell M. Bigelow, destroyed an E13 from ''Furutaka'' commanded by Chuichi Matsumoto.  Takagi and Hara considered that the conflicting reports might mean that the U.S. carrier forces were operating in two separate groups.Bullard, p. 63.

At 08:15, a ''Yorktown'' SBD piloted by John L. Nielsen sighted Gotō's force screening the invasion convoy.  Nielsen, making an error in his coded message, reported the sighting as "two carriers and four heavy cruisers" at ,  northwest of TF17.Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', p. 193; Hoyt, p. 53; Cressman, p. 95; Dull, p. 131; Millot, pp. 66–69; Lundstrom (2006), pp. 163–164; Henry, p. 54; Morison, p. 40.  The SBD's coding system was a board with pegs and holes to allow for rapid transmission of coded ship types.  In Nielsen's case, the board was apparently not aligned properly (Cressman).  Many of the sources are not completely clear on who exactly Nielsen spotted.  Dull says he spotted the "Close Cover Force".  Gotō's unit was called the "Distant Cover Force" or "Covering Group" and Marumo's was called the "Cover Force" or "Support Group".  Millot and Morison state that Nielsen sighted "Marushige's" cruisers, not Gotō's.  Marushige is presumably Marumo's cruiser force.  Lundstrom (2006) states that Nielsen sighted Gotō.  Fletcher concluded that the Japanese main carrier force had been located and ordered the launch of all available carrier aircraft to attack.  By 10:13, the American strike of 93 aircraft—18 Wildcat fighters, 53 SBD dive bombers, and 22 TBD Devastator torpedo bombers—was on its way.  At 10:19, Nielsen landed and discovered his coding error.  Although Gotō's force included ''Shōhō'', Nielsen thought that he had seen two cruisers and four destroyers.  At 10:12, however, Fletcher had received a report from a flight of three United States Army B-17s of an aircraft carrier, ten transports, and 16 warships  south of Nielsen's sighting at .  The B-17s actually saw the same thing as Nielsen:  ''Shōhō'', Gotō's cruisers, plus the Port Moresby Invasion Force.  Believing that the B-17 sighting was the main Japanese carrier force, Fletcher directed the airborne strike force towards this target.Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 193–196; Hoyt, pp. 53–54; Cressman, pp. 95–96; Millot, pp. 66–69; Dull, pp. 131–132; Lundstrom (2006), pp. 165–167; Henry, p. 54; Morison, pp. 40–41.  Lundstrom says the B-17 sighting was  from the cruisers but Cressman says . USACMH (Vol 1) (p. 47) states that 10 B-17s were involved.  At 11:00, TF17's combat air patrol (CAP) shot down a Kawanishi Type 97 from Tulagi (Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 196–197, Lundstrom 2006, p. 168).  Ten F4Fs, 28 SBDs, and 12 TBDs were from ''Lexington'' and eight F4F, 25 SBD, and 10 TBD were from ''Yorktown'' (Cressman and Lundstrom 2006).  The ''Kinugasa'' floatplane reported the launch of the U.S. strike force (Lundstrom 2006, p. 167).  The three B-17s, after making their sighting report, bombed the ''Kamikawa Maru'' at Deboyne but caused only minor damage (Lundstrom 2006, p. 166).

''Neosho'' (upper center) is left burning and slowly sinking at the completion of the Japanese dive bombing attack.

At 09:15, Takagi's strike force reached its target area, sighted the ''Neosho'' and ''Sims'', and searched in vain for the American carriers.  Finally, at 10:51 the ''Shōkaku'' scout aircraft realized they were mistaken in their identification of the oiler and destroyer as aircraft carriers.  Takagi now realized the American carriers were between him and the invasion convoy, placing the invasion forces in extreme danger.  Takagi ordered his aircraft to immediately attack the ''Neosho'' and ''Sims'' and then return to their carriers as quickly as possible.  At 11:15, the torpedo bombers and fighters abandoned the mission and headed back towards the carriers with their ordnance while the 36 dive bombers attacked the two American ships.A ''Shōkaku'' torpedo plane which ditched at Indispensible Reefs on May 7, 1942, photographed on June 9.Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 205–206; Hoyt, pp. 38–39; Cressman, p. 95; Millot, pp. 60–61; Dull, pp. 130–131; Lundstrom (2006), p. 167.  The two ''Shōkaku'' scout aircraft, which had lingered over the target area trying to assist the strike force in locating the American ships, did not have sufficient fuel to return to their carrier and ditched on the Indispensable Reefs (see photo at right).  The two crews were rescued by a Japanese destroyer, perhaps ''Ariake'' (Cressman, p. 92), on May 7.  ''Ariake'' sighted the two unrecovered ''Yorktown'' airmen from the Tulagi strike floating off Guadalcanal, but did not attempt to capture them (Cressman, p. 92).

Four dive bombers attacked ''Sims'' and the rest dived on ''Neosho''.  The destroyer was hit by three bombs, broke in half, and sank immediately, killing all but 14 of her 192-man crew. ''Neosho'' was hit by seven bombs.  One of the dive bombers, hit by anti-aircraft fire, crashed into the oiler.  Heavily damaged and without power, ''Neosho'' was left drifting and slowly sinking ().  Before losing power, ''Neosho'' was able to notify Fletcher by radio that it was under attack and in trouble, but garbled any further details as to just who or what was attacking her and gave wrong coordinates () for its position.ONI, p. 19; Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 205–206; Hoyt, pp. 38–50, 71, 218 & 221; Cressman, p. 95; Hoehling, p. 43; Millot, pp. 60–62 & 71; Dull, pp. 130–131; Lundstrom (2006), pp. 164–167; Morison, pp. 34–35.  Several sources, including Hoyt, Millot, and Morison state that ''Neosho'' was attacked first by one, then three or more horizontal bombers around 09:05 before the main Japanese strike.  What had, in fact, occurred was that several Japanese torpedo aircraft had dropped target designators near the oiler while the main strike force approached (Lundstrom 2006, p. 167).  The dive bomber which crashed into ''Neosho'' was piloted by Petty Officer Second Class Shigeo Ishizuka with Petty Officer Third Class Masayoshi Kawazoe as the rear gunner/observer (Werneth, p. 66).  Both were killed.  Sixteen survivors from ''Sims'' were taken aboard ''Neosho'', but one died soon after and another died after rescue four days later.  The captain of ''Sims'', Willford Hyman, was killed in the attack.  One of ''Neosho's'' crewmen, Oscar V. Peterson, was posthumously awarded the Medal of Honor for his efforts to save the ship in spite of severe and ultimately fatal injuries suffered during the attack.  At the time of the attack, ''Neosho's'' crew numbered 288 officers and men.  Twenty are known to have died in the attack.  A post-attack muster counted 110 personnel.  The remaining 158 crewmen (including four officers) panicked and abandoned ship during or shortly after the attack.  Of the men who abandoned ship, only four were eventually recovered; the rest died or vanished (ONI, pp. 48–53; Phillips, Hoyt, p. 130 & 192–193; Morison, pp. 35–37).

The American strike aircraft sighted ''Shōhō'' a short distance northeast of Misima Island at 10:40 and deployed to attack.  The Japanese carrier was protected by six Zeros and two Type 96 fighters flying combat air patrol (CAP), as the rest of the carrier's aircraft were being prepared below decks for a strike against the American carriers.  Gotō's cruisers surrounded the carrier in a diamond formation,  to  off each of ''Shōhō's'' corners.Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 197–198 (says  for the cruisers with ''Shōhō''); Hoyt, pp. 54–55; Cressman, pp. 96–97; Millot, p. 69; Dull, p. 132; Lundstrom (2006), pp. 168–169; Henry, pp. 54–56.  ''Shōhō'' was preparing a strike of five torpedo planes and three Zeros belowdecks when the American attack occurred.  Three Zeros were aloft at the beginning of the attack and three more were launched as the attack commenced. ''Senshi Sōshō'', Japan's War Ministry's official history, apparently specifies that Gotō's cruisers were  to  away in order to warn the carrier of incoming aircraft, not to provide anti-aircraft support (Lundstrom 2006, p. 169 and ).  Japanese carrier defense doctrine at that time relied on maneuvering and fighter defenses to avoid air attack instead of concentrated anti-aircraft fire from escorting warships (Lundstrom).



Attacking first, ''Lexington's'' air group, led by Commander William B. Ault, hit ''Shōhō'' with two  bombs and five torpedoes, causing severe damage.  At 11:00, ''Yorktown's'' air group attacked the burning and now almost stationary carrier, scoring with up to 11 more  bombs and at least two torpedoes.  Torn apart, ''Shōhō'' sank at 11:35 ().  Fearing more air attacks, Gotō withdrew his warships to the north, but sent the destroyer ''Sazanami'' back at 14:00 to rescue survivors.  Only 203 of the carrier's 834-man crew were recovered.  Three American aircraft were lost in the attack, including two SBDs from ''Lexington'' and one from ''Yorktown''.  All of ''Shōhō's'' aircraft complement of 18 was lost but three of the CAP fighter pilots were able to ditch at Deboyne and survived.  At 12:10, using a prearranged message to signal TF17 on the success of the mission, ''Lexington'' SBD pilot and squadron commander Robert E. Dixon radioed "Scratch one flat top!  Signed Bob."Chart of bomb and torpedo hits on ''Shōhō''Brown, p. 62, Lundstrom, ''Pearl Harbor to Midway'', pp. 198–206; Hoyt, pp. 55–61; Tully, "IJN Shoho"; Cressman, pp. 96–98; Millot, pp. 69–71; Dull, p. 132; Lundstrom (2006), pp. 168–169; Hata, p. 59; Morison, pp. 41–42; Willmott (2002), p. 43; United States Strategic Bombing Survey, p. 57.  One of the shot-down SBD crews, from ''Yorktown'', was rescued.  Dixon's phrase was quoted by ''Chicago Tribune'' war correspondent Stanley Johnston in a June 1942 article and subsequently requoted in most accounts of the Pacific War.  ''Lexington's'' commanding officer, Captain Frederick C. Sherman, credited Dixon, commanding officer of squadron VS-2, with coining the word "flattop" which became standard slang for an aircraft carrier.  Of the 203 ''Shōhō'' crewmen rescued, 72 were wounded.  ''Shōhō's'' captain, Izawa Ishinosuke, survived.  ''Sazanami'' was ''Shōhō's'' plane guard destroyer.  Four Zeros and one Type 96 fighter were shot down during the attack.  The remaining two Zeros and one Type 96 ditched at Deboyne.  The surviving Type 96 pilot was Shiro Ishikawa.  One of the surviving Zero pilots was Kenjiro Nōtomi, commander of ''Shōhō's'' fighter group (Lundstrom).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="58416c830ae8acc50f24041451d476cf" name="Shoho_g17026" sectnum="2.6.1#1">../img/58416c830ae8acc50f24041451d476cf.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>