<document id="14c817c266c53341fcab089476e16262-6" name="Gillingham_F.C." cat="26">
<text>
For the first three years of the club's existence, team matters were handled by a committee.  In 1896 William Ironside Groombridge, the club's secretary, took sole charge of team affairs to become Gillingham's first recognised manager.   Former England international Stephen Smith was appointed as full-time manager in 1906, but left in 1908, with Groombridge once again taking on team responsibilities.  Groombridge was associated with the club, as manager and secretary, for over 25 years.  When the club was admitted to the Football League in 1920, Robert Brown was appointed as manager, but he resigned a month later before the season had even begun.  His replacement, Scotsman John McMillan, thus became the first manager to take charge of the team in a Football League match.

In 1939, a year after the club was voted back out of the Football League, Archie Clark took over as manager, and was still in charge when the club was elected back to the Football League in 1950.  Clark remained in the job until 1957.  Freddie Cox took over in 1962 and led the club to the Football League Fourth Division championship in the 1963&ndash;64 season, making him the only manager to win a Football League divisional title with the club.  Basil Hayward was sacked in 1971 after the club was relegated back to the Fourth Division in the 1970&ndash;71 season, but his successor Andy Nelson led the club to promotion back to Division Three three years later before controversially resigning.  

Tony Pulis took over in 1995, with Gillingham once again in the bottom division, and managed the club to promotion in his first season in charge.  Three years later he led the team to the Second Division play-off final, but was sacked immediately after this after being accused of gross misconduct.  Peter Taylor replaced him and took the club to a second consecutive play-off final, where Gillingham gained promotion to the second tier of English football for the first time.  Current manager Mark Stimson was appointed in November 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e0f9b8b0e6d1c84f11b39884d607d84c" name="Mark_Stimson" sectnum="6#1">../img/e0f9b8b0e6d1c84f11b39884d607d84c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>