<document id="15624eb02bcb55f2b42a360c31562590-6" name="James_I_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
The Gunpowder Plot reinforced James's oppression of non-conforming English Catholics; and he sanctioned harsh measures for controlling them. In May 1606, Parliament passed the Popish Recusants Act requiring every citizen to take an Oath of Allegiance denying the Pope's authority over the king.Stewart, p 225.  James was conciliatory towards Catholics who took the Oath of Allegiance,Willson, p 228. and he tolerated crypto-Catholicism even at court.A crypto-Catholic was someone who outwardly conformed to protestantism but inwardly remained a Catholic. Henry Howard, for example, was a crypto-Catholic, received back into the Church in his final months. Before ascending the English throne, James, suspecting he might need the support of Catholics in succeeding to the throne, had assured Northumberland he would not persecute "any that will be quiet and give but an outward obedience to the law". Croft, p 162. However, in practice he enacted even harsher measures against Catholics than were laid upon them by Elizabeth.  Towards the Puritan clergy, with whom he debated at the Hampton Court Conference of 1604,Croft, p 156; In the Millenary Petition of 1603, the Puritan clergy demanded, among other things, for the abolition of confirmation, wedding rings, and the term "priest", and that the wearing of cap and surplice, "outward badges of Popish errours", become optional. Willson, p 201.  James was at first strict in enforcing conformity, inducing a sense of persecution amongst many Puritans;“In things indifferent,” James wrote in a new edition of ''Basilikon Doron'', "they are seditious which obey not the magistrates". Willson, p 201, p 209; Croft, p 156; "In seeking conformity, James gave a name and a purpose to nonconformity." Stewart, p 205. but ejections and suspensions from livings became fewer as the reign wore on. A notable success of the Hampton Court Conference was the commissioning of a new translation and compilation of approved books of the Bible to confirm the divine right of kings to rule and to maintain the social hierarchy, completed in 1611, which became known as the King James Bible, considered a masterpiece of Jacobean prose.Willson, pp 213–215; Croft, p 157.

In Scotland, James attempted to bring the Scottish kirk "so neir as can be" to the English church and reestablish the episcopacy, a policy which met with strong opposition.In March 1605, Archbishop Spottiswood wrote to James warning him that sermons against bishops were being preached daily in Edinburgh. Croft, p 164. In 1618, James's bishops forced his Five Articles of Perth through a General Assembly; but the rulings were widely resisted.Croft, p 166; Willson, p 320. James was to leave the church in Scotland divided at his death, a source of future problems for his son.Historians have differed in their assessments of the kirk at James's death: some consider that the Scots might have accepted James’s policies eventually; others that James left the kirk in crisis. Croft, p 167.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="dd5cc3b534d780b6bc87b3d8aea75ffd" name="James_I_by_Paul_van_Somer" sectnum="6#1">../img/dd5cc3b534d780b6bc87b3d8aea75ffd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>