<document id="15624eb02bcb55f2b42a360c31562590-1.1" name="James_I_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
James Charles Stuart was the son of Mary, Queen of Scots, and her second husband, Henry Stuart, Lord Darnley. He was a descendant of Henry VII of England through his great-grandmother Margaret Tudor, older sister of Henry VIII.

He was King James I of England and King James VI of Scotland.Margaret Tudor was the mother of Margaret Douglas, the future Countess of Lennox and mother of Henry Stuart, Lord Darnley. She was also the grandmother of Mary, Queen of Scots, through her son James V. Guy, p 54. Mary's rule over Scotland was insecure, for both she and her husband, being Roman Catholics, faced a rebellion by the Protestant population. Lord Darnley secretly allied himself with the rebels and murdered the Queen's private secretary, David Rizzio.Guy, pp 248–50.

James was born on 19 June 1566 at Edinburgh Castle, and as the eldest son of the monarch and heir-apparent, automatically became Duke of Rothesay and Prince and Great Steward of Scotland. Elizabeth I of England, as godmother ''in absentia'', sent a magnificent gold baptismal font as a christening gift.Croft, p 11.

James's father, Henry, was murdered on 10 February 1567 at the Hamiltons' house, Kirk o' Field, Edinburgh, perhaps in revenge for Rizzio's death. Mary was already an unpopular queen, and her marriage on 15 May 1567 to James Hepburn, 4th Earl of Bothwell, who was widely suspected of murdering Henry, heightened widespread bad feeling towards her. Elizabeth I wrote to Mary: "My ears have been so astounded, my mind so disturbed and my heart so appalled at hearing the horrible report of the abominable murder of your late husband and my slaughtered cousin, that I can scarcely as yet summon the spirit to write about it… I will not conceal from you that people for the most part are saying that you will look through your fingers at this deed instead of avenging it and that you don't care to take action against those who have done you this pleasure." Historian John Guy nonetheless concludes: "Not a single piece of uncontaminated evidence has ever been found to show that Mary had foreknowledge of Darnley's murder." Guy, pp 312–13. In historian David Harris Willson's view, however: "That Bothwell was the murderer no one can doubt; and that Mary was his accomplice seems equally certain." Willson, p 18. In June 1567, Protestant rebels arrested Mary and imprisoned her in Loch Leven Castle; she never saw her son again. She was forced to abdicate on 24 July in favour of the infant James and to appoint her illegitimate half-brother, James Stewart, Earl of Moray, as regent.Guy, pp 364–65. James was known to be superstitious.http://books.google.com/books?id=6IeeA1apBU0C&pg=PA98&lpg=PA98&dq=james+vI+superstitious&source=bl&ots=mA7vZ6CY2A&sig=YX6iz5RNz0C-vgFDntr26zfNrTg&hl=en&ei=9F9LSoLnJtWMjAeEnYXsAg&sa=X&oi=book_result&ct=result&resnum=1
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2e95727f5bda87ad2a06d9ec11584047" name="Memorial_to_Darnley" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/2e95727f5bda87ad2a06d9ec11584047.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>