<document id="158407093ae1acfc7c8639418b466705-5" name="Edmund_Herring" cat="29">
<text>
On 2 February 1944, the Victorian government decided to appoint Herring as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Victoria. Blamey advised the Prime Minister that:

It was not quite the end of his military service. Herring was recalled to duty for a year as Director General of Recruiting in August 1950 when the Korean War spurred efforts to build up the Army again.Sayers, ''Ned Herring'', p. 304  In January 1953, Herring was selected as leader of the Australian Services Contingent for the coronation of Queen Elizabeth II. This saw Australian soldiers as the Queen's Guard at Buckingham Palace on 26 May 1953, with Herring personally taking part in the procession. On 10 July, he was made a Knight of the Order of St John at Buckingham Palace. At the same time, Mary was made a commander of the same order for her charity work.Sayers, ''Ned Herring'', pp. 320&ndash;327

Herring maintained connections with his comrades from both World Wars. On the way back from the coronation, the Herrings stayed with the Eichelbergers in Asheville, North Carolina. The two generals remained close friends, exchanging regular letters until Eichelberger's death in 1961. In 1962, Herring visited Richard O'Connor at his home in Ross. In 1967 and 1971, the Herrings again travelled to America where they were guests of Dwight Johns and his wife. In 1973, he visited Washington, D.C. for the annual reunion of MacArthur's staff, and resolved that the next reunion should be held in Australia. He obtained government backing for his idea, and arranged for more than twenty former American generals, including Leif J. Sverdrup, Hugh John Casey, William C. Chase, Clyde D. Eddleman, and LeGrande A. Diller, and their wives to visit Australia in 1974, with commemorative functions being held in Melbourne, Sydney and Brisbane. Herring steadfastly believed that MacArthur, like Blamey, was a great commander who was not fully appreciated in his own country.Sayers, ''Ned Herring'', pp. 338&ndash;340, 345, 347

Herring's twenty years as Chief Justice was a period of significant change and growth in the administration of the law. During his period of office the number of judges on the Court increased from six to fourteen, reflecting the growth in cases. Herring earned a reputation as a fine judge and able administrator. He set up the Chief Justice's Law Reform Committee to try to ensure justice in Victoria's courts was abreast of the times, and a committee for religious observances and services to arrange the religious services marking the opening of the legal year. Herring retired as Chief Justice in 1964 but stayed on as Lieutenant Governor until his 80th birthday in 1972, serving in the position for a record 27 years.Innes, Prue, "", The Age (Melbourne), 6 January 1982. Accessed 13 October 2008. For his service as Lieutenant Governor, Herring was made a Knight Commander Commander of the Order of St Michael and St George in the King's Birthday Honours of 9 June 1949.

In a speech given on the occasion of his retiring as Chief Justice of Victoria, Herring said:


While opening the Victorian Returned Services League Conference shortly before his retirement as Lieutenant Governor, Herring criticised anti-war protesters and praised Australian soldiers who had served in the Vietnam War. "People who throw stones at Americans," he said, "should stop and think where we would have been in 1942 without the Americans." Such remarks earned him a rebuke from the then acting State Opposition Leader, Frank Wilkes, as "untactful" for a representative of the Crown.

Herring again became the subject of controversy in May 1978 when Barry Jones revealed in Federal Parliament that during World War II Herring had confirmed death sentences on 22 Papuans convicted of handing over seven Anglican missionaries to the Japanese, which Jones called "the darkest secret in modern Australian history".Jones, ''A Thinking Reed'', pp. 96&ndash;97 The Papuans had been convicted of offences including murder and treason. Herring claimed that they had been treated fairly under the conventions and circumstances applicable in wartime. "I have a clear conscience about it" he said. The seven missionaries had all been murdered by the Japanese. Four of them were women who had been raped as well. The Papuans had also handed over to the Japanese for execution two planters, six Australian soldiers, and two American airmen, and they had murdered Australian soldiers of the 39th Infantry Battalion near Kokoda. They were handed over to ANGAU, which had carried out the executions at Higaturu in September 1943.Sayers, ''Ned Herring'', pp. 232&ndash;233

Herring was president of the Boy Scouts' Association of Victoria for 23 years, and was later the first president of the Australian Boy Scouts' Association from 1959 to 1977. He was chairman of trustees of the Shrine of Remembrance from 1945 to 1978 (and remained a trustee until his death) and chairman of trustees of the Australian War Memorial from 1959 to 1974. He was made a fellow of New College, Oxford in 1949, received an honorary DCL from Oxford in 1953, became an honorary bencher of the Inner Temple in 1963 and received an honorary LLD from Monash University in 1973.Sayers, ''Ned Herring'', pp. 320, 334, 345 He was also active in the Anglican Church, and for many years was chancellor of the diocese of Melbourne, the highest church office that could be held by a layman.

Herring died at a Camberwell, Victoria nursing home on 5 January 1982. He was given a state funeral at St Paul's Cathedral, Melbourne, planned by Mary, who had died three months before.Hilton, ''Dr. Mary'', p. 88

Victoria's Herring Island is named after him. His wartime portraits are in the Australian War Memorial, which featured him as one of the fifty most prominent Australians with a military background. His papers are in the State Library of Victoria.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e846bd6068576c3fa24d1f3990fb6e72" name="Mary_Herring" sectnum="5#1">../img/e846bd6068576c3fa24d1f3990fb6e72.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>