<document id="159de799c0a47c698b9416a93499e833-2" name="Emperor_Penguin" cat="3">
<text>
The adult Emperor Penguin stands up to  tall. The weight ranges from 22 to 45 kg (48-99 lb) and varies by sex,with males weighing more than females. The weight also varies by season, as both male and female penguins lose substantial mass while raising hatchlings and incubating eggs. The mean weight of males at the start of the breeding season is 38 kg (83 lb) and that of females is 29.5 kg  (65 lb). After the breeding season this drops to 23 kg (50 lb) for both sexes. Like all penguin species, the Emperor has a streamlined body to minimise drag while swimming, and wings that have become stiff, flat flippers.Williams (''The Penguins'') p. 3 The tongue is equipped with rear-facing barbs to prevent prey from escaping when caught. Males and females are similar in size and colouration. The adult has deep black dorsal feathers, covering the head, chin, throat, back, dorsal part of the flippers, and tail. The black plumage is sharply delineated from the light-coloured plumage elsewhere. The underparts of the wings and belly are white, becoming pale yellow in the upper breast, while the ear patches are bright yellow. The upper mandible of the  long bill is black, and the lower mandible can be pink, orange or lilac.Williams (''The Penguins'') p. 152 In juveniles, the auricular patches, chin and throat are white, while its bill is black. The Emperor Penguin chick is typically covered with silver-grey down and has a black head and white mask. A chick with all-white plumage was found in 2001, but was not considered to be an albino as it did not have pink eyes. Chicks weigh around  after hatching, and fledge when they reach about 50% of adult weight.

The Emperor Penguin's dark plumage fades to brown from November until February, before the yearly moult in January and February. Moulting is rapid in this species compared with other birds, taking only around 34 days. Emperor Penguin feathers emerge from the skin after they have grown to a third of their total length, and before old feathers are lost, to help reduce heat loss. New feathers then push out the old ones before finishing their growth..

The average yearly survival rate of the Emperor Penguin has been measured at 95.1%, with an average life expectancy of 19.9 years. The same researchers estimated that 1% of Emperor Penguins hatched could feasibly reach an age of 50 years.  In contrast, only 19% of chicks survive their first year of life.. Therefore, 80% of the Emperor Penguin population comprises adults five years and older.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="00cdd82e0518c1837620e58b9a20236d" name="Kaiserpinguine_mit_Jungen" sectnum="2#1">../img/00cdd82e0518c1837620e58b9a20236d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>