<document id="159de799c0a47c698b9416a93499e833-2.2" name="Emperor_Penguin" cat="3">
<text>
The Emperor Penguin breeds in the coldest environment of any bird species; air temperatures may reach , and wind speeds may reach . Water temperature is a frigid ,which is much lower than the Emperor Penguin's average body temperature of . The species has adapted in several ways to counteract heat loss.. Feathers provide 80–90% of its insulation, and it has a layer of sub-dermal fat which may be up to  thick before breeding.. This resultant blubber layer impedes the mobility of the Emperor on land compared to its less well fat-insulated cousin, the Magellanic Penguin.C. Michael Hogan (2008) 
 Its stiff feathers are short, lanceolate (spear-shaped), and densely packed over the entire skin surface. With around 100 feathers covering one square inch (15 feathers per cm2), it has the highest feather density of any bird species. An extra layer of insulation is formed by separate shafts of downy filaments between feathers and skin. Muscles allow the feathers to be held erect on land, reducing heat loss by trapping a layer of air next to the skin. Conversely, the plumage is flattened in water, thus waterproofing the skin and the downy underlayer.. Preening is vital in facilitating insulation and in keeping the plumage oily and water-repellent.

The Emperor Penguin is able to thermoregulate (maintain its core body temperature) without altering its metabolism, over a wide range of temperatures. Known as the thermoneutral range, this extends from −10 to 20 °C (10 to 70 °F). Below this temperature range, its metabolic rate increases significantly, although an individual can maintain its core temperature between 37.6 and 38.0 °C (99.7 to 100.4 °F) down to .. Movement by swimming, walking, and shivering are three mechanisms for increasing metabolism; a fourth process involves an increase in the breakdown of fats by enzymes, which is induced by the hormone glucagon.. At temperatures above , an Emperor Penguin may become agitated as its body temperature and metabolic rate rise to increase heat loss. Raising its wings and exposing the undersides increases the exposure of its body surface to the air by 16%, facilitating further heat loss..
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2e9fbd7a704050f21be65e1f77879f80" name="Diving_emperor_penguin" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/2e9fbd7a704050f21be65e1f77879f80.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>