<document id="159de799c0a47c698b9416a93499e833-4" name="Emperor_Penguin" cat="3">
<text>
The Emperor Penguin is a social animal in its nesting and its foraging behaviour; birds hunting together may coordinate their diving and surfacing. Individuals may be active day or night. A mature adult travels throughout most of the year between the nesting area and ocean foraging areas; the species disperses into the oceans from January to March.

The American physiologist Gerry Kooyman revolutionized the study of penguin foraging behaviour in 1971 when he published his results from attaching automatic dive-recording devices to Emperor Penguins. He found that the species reaches depths of , with dive periods of up to 18 minutes. Later research revealed a small female had dived to a depth of  near McMurdo Sound. It is possible that the Emperor Penguin can dive even deeper, as the accuracy of the recording devices is diminished at greater depths.. Further study of one bird's diving behaviour revealed regular dives to  in water around  deep, and shallow dives of less than , interspersed with deep dives of more than  in depths of 450 to 500 m (1500 to 1600 ft). This was suggestive of feeding near or at the sea bottom..

Both male and female Emperor Penguins forage for food up to  from colonies while collecting food to feed chicks, covering  per individual per trip. A male returning to the sea after incubation heads directly out to areas of permanent open water, known as polynyas, around  from the colony.

An efficient swimmer, the Emperor Penguin exerts pressure with both its upward and downward strokes while swimming. The upward stroke works against buoyancy and helps maintain depth. Its average swimming speed is 6–9 km/h (4–6 mph). On land, the Emperor Penguin alternates between walking with a wobbling gait and tobogganing—sliding over the ice on its belly, propelled by its feet and wing-like flippers. Like all penguins, it is flightless.

As a defence against the cold, a colony of Emperor Penguins forms a compact huddle (also known as the turtle formation) ranging in size from ten to several hundred birds, with each bird leaning forward on a neighbour. Those on the outside tend to shuffle slowly around the edge of the formation, producing a slow churning action, and giving each bird a turn on the inside and the outside.Pinshow B., Fedak M.A. , Battles D.R, & Schmidt-Nielsen K. (1976) "Energy expenditure for thermoregulation and locomotion in emperor penguins" ''American Journal of Physiology'' '''231'''(3): 903–12
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="70677975dd0711b17e9532f88033b1a1" name="EmperorPenguinColonyClose" sectnum="4#1">../img/70677975dd0711b17e9532f88033b1a1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>