<document id="15bd3b40ddecd836f9a4c74a1db1375d-2.2" name="The_Notorious_B.I.G." cat="20">
<text>
In August 1995, Wallace's protegé group, Junior M.A.F.I.A. ("Junior Masters At Finding Intelligent Attitudes"), consisting of his friends from childhood released their debut album entitled ''Conspiracy''. The group included rappers such as Lil' Kim and Lil' Cease, who went on to have solo careers.Lane, Hai, Lydia  Allmusic. Retrieved on 2007-02-18 The record went Gold and its singles, "Player's Anthem" and "Get Money" both featuring Wallace, went Gold and Platinum. Wallace continued to work with R&B artists, collaborating with Bad Boy groups 112 (on "Only You") and Total (on "Can't You See"), with both reaching the top 20 of the Hot 100.



By the end of the year, Wallace was the top-selling male solo artist and rapper on the U.S. pop and R&B charts. In July 1995, he appeared on the cover of ''The Source'' with the caption "The King of New York Takes Over". At the ''Source'' Awards, he was named Best New Artist (Solo), Lyricist of the Year, Live Performer of the Year, and his debut Album of the Year. At the Billboard Awards, he was Rap Artist of the Year.

In his year of success, Wallace became involved in a quarrel between the East and West Coast hip-hop scenes with Tupac Shakur, his former associate. In an interview with ''Vibe'' magazine in April 1995, while serving time in Clinton Correctional Facility, Shakur accused Uptown Records' founder Andre Harrell, Sean "Puffy" Combs, and Wallace of having prior awareness of a robbery that resulted in him being shot repeatedly and losing thousands of dollars worth of jewelry on the night of November 30, 1994. Though Wallace and his entourage were in the same Manhattan-based recording studio at the time of the occurrence, they denied the accusation.



Following release from prison, Shakur signed to Death Row Records on October 15, 1995. Bad Boy Records and Death Row, now business rivals, became involved in an intense quarrel.Carney, Thomas  ''PBS''. Retrieved on 2006-12-09
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6b69ad93579a8cde59b03a4ac3c96736" name="Biggie_and_Tupac_still" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/6b69ad93579a8cde59b03a4ac3c96736.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>