<document id="15fc7d9f85191fc4cc3e377a5178d502-1.5" name="Literature_in_the_Hoysala_Empire" cat="17">
<text>
Keshiraja was a notable writer and grammarian of the 13th century. He came from a family of famous poet-writers. Although five of Keshiraja's writings are not traceable, his most enduring work on Kannada grammar, ''Shabdamanidarpana'' ("Mirror of Word Jewels", 1260), is available and testifies to his scholarly acumen and literary taste.E.P.Rice (1921), p. 45Sahitya Akademi (1988), p. 1476Sastri (1955), p. 359 True to his wish that his writing on grammar should "last as long as the sun, the moon, the oceans and the Meru mountain lasted", ''Shabdamanidarpana'' is popular even today and is considered a standard authority on old Kannada grammar. It is prescribed as a textbook for students of graduate and post-graduate studies in the Kannada language. Although Keshiraja followed the model of Sanskrit grammar (of the Katantra school) and that of earlier writings on Kannada grammar (by King Amoghavarsha I of the 9th century and grammarian Nagavarma II of 1145), his work has originality. Keshiraja's lost writings are ''Cholapalaka Charitam'', ''Sri Chitramale'', ''Shubhadraharana'', ''Prabodhachandra'' and ''Kiratam'' (or ''Kiratarjuniyam'').

A major development of this period that would have a profound impact on Kannada literature even into the modern age was the birth of the Haridasa ("servants of Hari or Vishnu") movement. This devotional movement, although reminiscent in some ways of the Veerashaiva movement of the 12th century (which produced Vachana poetry and taught devotion to the god Shiva), was in contrast intimately devoted to the Hindu god Vishnu as the supreme God.Shiva Prakash (1997), pp. 192&ndash;193 The inspiration behind this movement was the philosophy of Madhvacharya of Udupi. Naraharitirtha (1281) is considered the first well-known haridasa and composer of Vaishnava devotional songs in Kannada. Before his induction into the Madhva order, he had served as a minister in the court of Kalinga. The Vaishnava poetry however disappeared for about two centuries after Naraharitirtha's death before resurfacing as a popular form of folk literature during the rule of the Vijayanagara Empire.Shiva Prakash (1997), p. 192 Only three of Naraharitirtha's  compositions are available today.Shiv Prakash (1997), p. 195

Other writers worthy of mention are Mahabala Kavi, the author of ''Neminathapurana'' (1254), an account of the 22nd Jain tirthankar Neminatha, and Kumudendu, author of a Jain version of the epic Ramayana in ''shatpadi'' metre in 1275. The effort was influenced by ''Pampa Ramayana'' of Nagachandra.Rice E. P. (1921), p. 45 Kumara Padmarasa, son of Kereya Padmarasa, wrote the ''Sananda Charitre'' in ''shatpadi'' metre.Sahitya Academi (1992), p. 4003 Ratta Kavi, a Jain noble, wrote a quasi-scientific piece called  ''Rattasutra'' (or ''Rattamala'') in 1300. The writing bears on natural phenomena such rain, earthquakes, lightning, planets and omens. Towards the end of the Hoysala rule, Nagaraja wrote ''Punyasrava'' in 1331 in ''champu'' style, a work that narrates the stories of puranic heroes in 52 tales and is said to be a translation from Sanskrit.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="833a0f4eb3eb7989305e4380c2deac43" name="Basaral_kannada_inscription" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/833a0f4eb3eb7989305e4380c2deac43.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>