<document id="15fc7d9f85191fc4cc3e377a5178d502-2" name="Literature_in_the_Hoysala_Empire" cat="17">
<text>
The Vaishnava movement in the Kannada-speaking regions found momentum after the arrival of the philosopher Ramanujacharya (1017&ndash;1137). Fleeing possible persecution from the Chola King (who was a Shaiva), Ramanujacharya sought refuge initially in Tondanur and later moved to Melkote.Kamath (2001), p. 151 But this event had no impact on Vaishnava literature in Hoysala lands at that time. However, the teachings of Madhvacharya (1238&ndash;1317), propounder of the ''Dvaita'' philosophy, did have a direct impact on Vaishnava literature, in both the Sanskrit and Kannada languages. This body of writings is known as ''haridasa sahitya'' (haridasa literature).Shiva Prakash (1997), p. 192 

Born as Vasudeva in Pajaka village near Udupi in 1238, he learnt the Vedas and Upanishads under his guru Achyutapreksha. He was initiated into ''sanyasa'' (asceticism) after which he earned the name Madhvacharya (or Anandatirtha).Kamath (2001), p. 154 Later, he disagreed with the views of his guru and began to travel India. He successfully debated with many scholars and philosophers during this time and won over Naraharitirtha, a minister in Kalinga, who would later become Madhvacharya's first  notable disciple. Unlike Adi Shankaracharya (788&ndash;820) who preached Advaita philosophy (monism) and Ramanujacharya who propounded Vishishtadvaita philosophy (qualified monism), Madhvacharya taught the Dvaita philosophy (dualism).Kamath (2001), pp. 150, 155  

Madhvacharya taught complete devotion to the Hindu god Vishnu, emphasising ''Jnanamarga'' or the "path of knowledge", and insisted that the path of devotion "can help a soul to attain elevation" (''Athmonathi''). He was however willing to accept devotion to other Hindu deities as well.Shiva Prakash (1997), p. 193 He wrote 37 works in Sanskrit including  ''Dwadasha Sutra'' (in which his devotion to the god Vishnu found full expression), ''Gita Bhashya'', ''Gita Tatparya Nirnaya'', ''Mahabharata Tatparya Nirnaya'', ''Bhagavata Tatparya Nirnaya'', ''Mayavada Khandana'' and ''Vishnu Tattwa Nirnaya''. To propagate his teachings he established eight monasteries near Udupi, the Uttaradhi monastery, and the Raghavendra monastery in Mantralayam (in modern Andhra Pradesh) and Nanjanagud (near modern Mysore).Kamath (2001), pp. 155&ndash;156   

The writings of Madhvacharya and Vidyatirtha (author of ''Rudraprshnabhashya'') may have been absorbed by Sayanacharya, brother of Vidyaranya, the patron saint of the founders of the Vijayanagara empire in the 14th century.K. T. Pandurangi in Kamath 2001, pp. 132&ndash;133 Bharatasvamin (who was patronised by Hoysala King Ramanatha) wrote a commentary on ''Samaveda'',Sastri (1955), p. 310 Shadgurusishya wrote commentary on ''Aitareya Brahmana'' and ''Aranyaka'', and Katyayana wrote ''Sarvanukramani''. A family of hereditary poets whose names have not been identified held the title "Vidyacharkravarti" (poet laureate) in the Hoysala court. One of them wrote ''Gadyakarnamrita'', a description of the war between Hoysala king Vira Narasimha II and the Pandyas, in the early 13th century.Sastri (1955), p. 316 His grandson with the same title, in the court of king Veera Ballala III, composed a poem called ''Rukminikalyana'' in 16 ''kandas'' (chapters) and wrote commentaries (on poetics) on the ''Alankarasarvasva'' and ''Kavyaprakasa''. Kalyani Devi, a sister of Madhvacharya, and Trivikrama, his disciple, wrote commentaries on the Dvaita philosophy. To Trivikrama is ascribed a poem narrating the story of Usha and Aniruddha called ''Ushaharana''. Narayana Pandita composed ''Madhwavijaya'', ''Manimanjari'' and a poem called ''Parijataharana''. The Jain writer Ramachandra Maladhari authored ''Gurupanchasmriti''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1cb17c49495d288ba07064302dfa3a71" name="Melukote_Cheluvarayaswami_temple" sectnum="2#1">../img/1cb17c49495d288ba07064302dfa3a71.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>