<document id="15fc7d9f85191fc4cc3e377a5178d502-1.4" name="Literature_in_the_Hoysala_Empire" cat="17">
<text>
Harihara's nephew and protege, the dramatic poet Raghavanka of Hampi, whose style is compared to that of 10th-century poet Ranna, was the first to establish the ''shatpadi'' metre in Kannada literature in  the epic ''Harishchandra Kavya'' (1200).Sastri (1955), p. 362Narasimhacharya (1988), p. 20 According to L. S. Seshagiri Rao, it is believed that in no other language has the story of King Harishchandra been interpreted in this way. The writing is an original in tradition and inspiration that fully develops the potential of the ''shatpadi'' metre.Sahitya Akademi (1988), p. 1181Shiva Prakash (1997), p. 207 The narration has many noteworthy elegiac verses such as the mourning of Chandramati over the death of her young son Lohitashva from snake bite.Sahitya Akademi (1988), p. 1149 The very writing that made Raghavanka famous was rejected by his guru, Harihara. His other well-known writings, adhering to strict Shaiva principles and written to appease his guru, are the ''Siddharama charitra'' (or ''Siddharama Purana''), a larger than life stylistic eulogy of the compassionate 12th-century Veerashaiva saint, Siddharama of Sonnalige; the ''Somanatha charitra'', a propagandist work that describes the life of saint Somayya (or Adaiah) of Puligere (modern Lakshmeshwar), his humiliation by a Jain girl and his revenge; the ''Viresvara charita'', a dramatic story of the blind wrath of a Shaiva warrior, Virabhadra; the ''Hariharamahatva'', an account of the life of Harisvara of Hampi; and ''Sarabha charitra''. The last two classics are considered lost.Sastri (1955), p. 362

In 1209, the  Jain scholar, minister, builder of temples and army commander Janna wrote, among other classics, ''Yashodhara Charite'', a unique set of stories in 310 verses dealing with sadomasochism, transmigration of the soul, passion gone awry and cautionary morals for human conduct. The writing, although inspired by Vadiraja's Sanskrit classic of the same name, is noted for its original interpretation, imagery and style.Sahitya Akademi (1992), p. 4629 In one story, the poet tells of the infatuation of a man for his friend's wife. Having killed his friend, the man abducts the wife, who dies of grief. Overcome by repentance, he burns himself on the funeral pyre of the woman.Sahitya Akademi (1988), p. 1181Rice E. P. (1921), pp. 43&ndash;44 The stories of infatuation reach a peak when Janna writes about the attraction of Amrutamati, the queen, to the ugly mahout Ashtavakra, who pleases the queen with kicks and whip lashes. This story has piqued the interest of modern researchers.Shiva Prakash (1997), p. 204 In honour of this work, Janna received the title ''Kavichakravarthi'' ("Emperor among poets") from his patron, King Veera Ballala II.Narasimhacharya (1988), p. 20 His other classic, ''Anathanatha Purana'' (1230), is an account of the life of the 14th tirthankar Ananthanatha.Sahitya Akademi (1987), p. 620Nagaraj (2003), p. 377

Andayya, taking a non-conformist path that was never repeated in Kannada literature, wrote ''Madana Vijaya'' ("Triumph of cupid", 1217&ndash;1235) using only pure Kannada words (''desya'') and naturalised Sanskrit words (''tadbhava'') and totally avoiding assimilated Sanskrit words (''tatsamas''). This is seen by some as a rebuttal meant to prove that writing Kannada literature without borrowed Sanskrit words was possible.Sahitya Akademi (1987), p. 170 The poem narrates the story of the moon being imprisoned by the god Shiva in his abode in the Himalayas. In his anger, Kama (Cupid, the god of love, also called Manmata) assailed Shiva with his arrows only to be cursed by Shiva and separated from his beloved. Kama then contrived to rid himself of Shiva's curse. The work also goes by other names such as ''Sobagina Suggi'' ("Harvest of Beauty"), ''Kavane Gella'' ("Cupid's Conquest") and ''Kabbigara-kava'' ("Poets defender").Sastri (1955), p. 359 Kama has an important place in Jain writings even before Andayya. The possibility that this writing was yet another subtle weapon in the intensifying conflict between the dominant JainsNarasimhacharya (1988), p. 65 and the Veerashaivas, whose popularity was on the rise, is not lost on historians.Nagaraj (2003), p. 366 

Mallikarjuna, a Jain ascetic, compiled an anthology of poems called ''Suktisudharnava'' ("Gems from the poets") in 1245 in the court of King Vira Someshwara.Rice E.P. (1921), p. 44&ndash;45 Some interesting observations have been made by scholars about this important undertaking. While the anthology itself provides insight into poetic tastes of that period (and hence qualifies as a "history of Kannada literature"), it also performs the function of a "guide for poets", an assertive method of bridging the gap between courtly literary intelligentsia and folk poetry.Nagaraj (2003), p. 363 Being a guide for "professional intellectuals", the work, true to its nature, often includes poems eulogising kings and royalty but completely ignoring poems of the 12th-century vachana canon (Veerashaiva folk literature). However, the selection of poems includes contributions from Harihara, the non-conformist Veerashaiva writer. This suggests a compromise by which the author attempts to include the "rebels".

Other notable writers of the early 13th century were Bhanduvarma, author of ''Harivamsabhyudaya'' and ''Jiva sambhodana'' (1200), the latter bearing on morals and renunciation, and written addressing the soul; Maghanandycharya, author of ''Sastrasara Samuccaya-tiku'' (1209);Singh (2001), p. 975  Hastimalla, who worte ''Purvapurana''; Chandrama, author of ''Karkala Gomateshvara charite'',Singh (2001), p. 979 and Sisumayana, who introduced a new form of composition called ''sangatya'' in 1232. He wrote an allegorical poem called ''Tripuradahana'' ("Burning of the triple fortress") and ''Anjanacharita''. The latter work was inspired by Ravisena's Sanskrit ''Padma charitra''.Sastri (1955), p. 359 Somaraja, a Veerashaiva scholar, wrote a eulogy of Udbhata, the ruler of Gersoppa, and called it ''Sringarasara'' (or ''Udbhatakavya'', 1222).Narasimhacharya (1988), p. 21 Other Jain writers were Parsva Pandita, author of ''Paravanathapurana'', and Gunavarma II, the author of the story of the ninth Jain tirthankar Pushpadanta called ''Pushpadanta purana'' (both were patronised by the Ratta kings of Saundatti).E.P.Rice (1921), pp. 43&ndash;44Narasimhacharya (1988), pp. 20&ndash;21 Polalva Dandanatha, a commander, minister, and the builder of the Harihareshwara temple in Harihar, wrote ''Haricharitra'' in 1224. He was patronised by King Veera Ballala II and his successor, King Vira Narasimha II. Puligere Somanatha authored a book on morals called ''Somesvarasataka''.Sastri (1955), p. 362
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7c610872d3e0bc222cb88523870643b7" name="Old-Kannada_inscription_at_Arasikere_Ishwara_temple" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/7c610872d3e0bc222cb88523870643b7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>