<document id="160359a56c4d86f1e69e21dec758ece6-4.1" name="2007_United_States_Air_Force_nuclear_weapons_incident" cat="29">
<text>
On October 24, 2007, Secretary of the Air Force Wynne told the House Armed Services Committee that he believed that the 5th Bomb Wing could be recertified and could resume ferrying the AGM-129 cruise missiles to Barksdale for retirement.  He did not provide a timeline for that recertification process.  On November 1, 2007 Colonel Joel Westa took command of the 5th Bomb Wing.Holmes, "Minot bomb wing gets new commander Thursday"  That same day, General Keys retired from the Air Force.Air Force Link, .

Personnel from Barksdale's 2nd Bomb Wing temporarily took over maintenance duties of Minot's nuclear stockpile until the 5th Bomb Wing could be recertified.  A nuclear surety inspection (NSI), required for recertification, originally scheduled for the 5th Bomb Wing for January 23, 2008 was postponed after the wing failed an initial NSI that took place on December 16, 2007.Hoffman, Michael, "Minot Nuke Handlers Still Not Ready For Inspection", ''Military Times'', January 14, 2008, MacPherson, "Minot chief sets bar high after nuke gaffe".  Another initial NSI was completed on March 29 and Corley recertified the wing on March 31, 2008.  A full NSI was scheduled for May 2008.  The wing needed to regain its certification in order to hold the full NSI, said Major Elizabeth Ortiz, a Minot spokeswoman.  Units handling nuclear weapons must pass NSIs every 18 months in order to retain their certifications.Hoffman, Michael, "Minot bomb wing recertified for nukes", ''Military Times'', April 4, 2008; ''Los Angeles Times'', "Bomb Wing Recertified", April 4, 2008.

The USAF issued a new policy directive regarding the handling of nuclear weapons and delivery systems, which prohibits the storing of nuclear armed and nonnuclear armed weapons in the same storage facility.  The directive further instructs that all nonnuclear munitions and missiles must be labeled with placards clearly stating that they are not armed with nuclear warheads.  Wing commanders are now charged with approving any movement of nuclear weapons from weapons storage areas and must appoint a single individual as a munitions accountability system officer and weapons custodian.  All units that handle nuclear weapons must develop a coordinated visual inspection checklist.  The policy further directs that airmen charged with handling or maintaining nuclear weapons cannot be on duty for longer than 12 hours, unless during an emergency, when their duty period can be extended to a maximum of 16 hours.Pincus, "Air Force Alters Rules for Handling of Nuclear Arms", Hoffman, "New nuke-handling procedures issued".  The USAF has since instituted a program of surprise inspections at nuclear-armed bases.Barnes, Julian E., "Better Oversight Of Nuclear Arms Urged", ''Los Angeles Times'', November 26, 2008, p. 8.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d48cc8ef11d460b8e31fff8d7bc45e7c" name="JoelWesta" sectnum="4.1#1">../img/d48cc8ef11d460b8e31fff8d7bc45e7c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>