<document id="160359a56c4d86f1e69e21dec758ece6-4.3" name="2007_United_States_Air_Force_nuclear_weapons_incident" cat="29">
<text>
Minot's full NSI took place beginning on May 17, 2008, and was conducted by inspectors from the Defense Threat Reduction Agency (DTRA) and the AF's Air Combat Command (ACC).  On May 25, the DTRA issued the 5th Bomb Wing an "unsatisfactory" rating, the lowest rating possible, from the inspection.  The 5th passed the inspection in nine of ten areas, but failed in the area of nuclear security.  Following the inspection, Westa stated, "Overall their assessment painted a picture of some things we need to work on in the areas of training and discipline".Hoffman, "Minot’s 5th Bomb Wing flunks nuclear inspection"  The 5th Bomb Wing Security Forces Squadron Commander, Lieutenant Colonel John Worley, was replaced by Lieutenant Colonel Stephen Weaver on June 16, 2008.Hoffman, "Minot nuke handlers pass re-inspection"  In spite of failing the NSI, the wing kept its nuclear certification.  Said Hans Kristensen, director of the Nuclear Information Project at the Federation of American Scientists about the 5th's failure in the inspection, "It makes you wonder what’s going on elsewhere, like the nuclear weapons stationed at bases overseas, and at Barksdale Air Force Base and Whiteman Air Force Base."Associated Press, "Air Force wing in nuclear goof has more trouble", Hoffman, "Minot’s 5th Bomb Wing flunks nuclear inspection"  Minot passed the follow-up inspection on August 15, 2008.

On June 5, 2008, Robert Gates announced the results of an investigation into the misshipment of four MK-12 forward-section reentry vehicle assemblies to Taiwan.  The investigation, conducted by Admiral Kirkland H. Donald, director of US Naval Propulsion, found that the Taiwan missile incident was, in Gates' words, "A degradation of the authority, standards of excellence and technical competence within the nation's ICBM force. Similar to the bomber-specific August 2007 Minot-Barksdale nuclear weapons transfer incident, this incident took place within the larger environment of declining Air Force nuclear mission focus and performance" and that "the investigation identified commonalities between the August 2007 Minot incident and this  event."  In his investigation report, Donald stated that the issues identified by his investigation were, "Indicative of an overall decline in Air Force nuclear weapons stewardship, a problem that has been identified but not effectively addressed for over a decade. Both the Minot-Barksdale nuclear weapons transfer incident and the Taiwan misshipment, while different in specifics, have a common origin: the gradual erosion of nuclear standards and a lack of effective oversight by Air Force leadership"US DoD, "DoD News Briefing with Secretary Gates from the Pentagon", ''Military Times'', "Moseley and Wynne forced out", Shanker, "2 Leaders Ousted From Air Force in Atomic Errors".

As a result of the investigation, Gates announced that, "A substantial number of Air Force general officers and colonels have been identified as potentially subject to disciplinary measures, ranging from removal from command to letters of reprimand,"  and that he had accepted the resignations of USAF Secretary Michael Wynne and USAF Chief of Staff Michael Moseley.  Gates added that he had asked James R. Schlesinger to lead a senior-level task force to recommend improvements in the stewardship and operation of nuclear weapons, delivery vehicles and sensitive components by the US DoD.  Members of the task force came from the Defense Policy Board and the Defense Science Board.US DoD, "DoD News Briefing with Secretary Gates from the Pentagon", June 5, 2008, ''Military Times'', "Moseley and Wynne forced out", Shanker, "2 Leaders Ousted From Air Force in Atomic Errors".

On September 13, 2008, Gates announced Schlesinger's task force's recommendations by calling on the USAF to place all nuclear weapons under a single command.  The task force suggested that the new command be called Air Force Strategic Command, which would replace the current Air Force Space Command, and make it accountable for the nuclear mission. It also called for all USAF bombers to be placed under a single command.  The task force also recommended that the USAF move an additional 1,500 to 2,000 airmen into nuclear-related jobs.  Gates announced that acting Air Force Secretary Michael B. Donley and Chief of Staff General Norton A. Schwartz were "reviewing the recommendations" for disciplinary action against USAF officers previously involved in the nuclear mission.Tyson, Ann Scott, "", Washington Post, September 13, 2008, pg. 8.  The task force found an, "an unambiguous, dramatic and unacceptable decline in the Air Force’s commitment to perform the nuclear mission and, until very recently, little has been done to reverse it."Associated Press, "", New York Times, September 13, 2008, Pg. 15.

On September 25, 2008, the United States Department of Defense announced that six Air Force and two Army generals and nine colonels had received letters of reprimand, admonishment, or concern. Two Air Force major generals were asked to stay in their current position; the others either retired, planned to retire, or were removed from their position. Air Force Chief of Staff Norton Schwartz met with each officer personally before issuing the letters. He noted they committed no offense under the UCMJ, but "did not do enough to carry out their leadership responsibilities for nuclear oversight. "For that they must be held accountable."  The Air Force stated that the discipline was in response to the mistaken shipment of nuclear fuses to Taiwan, not for the Minot nuclear weapons incident.The Associated Press. "Military cites poor oversight in mistaken shipment of warheads to Taiwan". MSNBC, Thurs., Sept. 25, 2008, http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/26892774/; accessed 2008-09-26.

In November 2008, the 341st Missile Wing at Malmstrom Air Force Base failed its nuclear surety inspection.  The 90th Missile Wing at F. E. Warren Air Force Base, failed its nuclear surety inspection one month later.Shane, Leo III, "Report: Wyo. Unit Fails Nuke Security Inspection", ''Stars and Stripes'', December 17, 2008; Gertz, Bill, "Air Force Fails New Nuclear Reviews", ''Washington Times'', February 4, 2009.

On January 8, 2009 Schlesinger's task force released its report regarding the overall DoD's management of the country's nuclear weapons mission.  The report criticized the DoD for a lack of focus and oversight on its nuclear weapons programs and recommended that the DoD create a new assistant secretary position to oversee its nuclear management.  The task force found that within the DoD only the United States Navy was effectively managing its nuclear arsenal.Baldor, Lolita C., (Associated Press) "Report Slams Pentagon Nuke Oversight", ''Washington Post'', January 7, 2009.  The panel stated that it found, "a distressing degree of inattention to the role of nuclear weapons in deterrence among many senior DoD military and civilian leaders."AFP-JiJi, "Faith in U.S. nuclear deterrent shaken", ''Japan Times'', January 10, 2009.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6cab8a01c20f9795d05f932a005cd689" name="Robert_Gates,_official_DoD_photo_portrait,_2006" sectnum="4.3#1">../img/6cab8a01c20f9795d05f932a005cd689.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>