<document id="160359a56c4d86f1e69e21dec758ece6-1" name="2007_United_States_Air_Force_nuclear_weapons_incident" cat="29">
<text>
As of August 2007, Minot Air Force Base was the home of the 5th Bomb Wing and Barksdale Air Force Base the home of 2nd Bomb Wing, both of which fell under the 8th Air Force, also based at Barksdale.  The 8th was part of Air Combat Command (ACC) in the USAF.  In August 2007 the 5th Bomb Wing was commanded by Colonel Bruce Emig, the 2nd Bomb Wing by Colonel Robert Wheeler, the 8th Air Force by Lieutenant General Robert Elder Jr., and ACC by General Ronald Keys.Ricks, "Tough Punishment Expected for Warhead Errors", Baker, "Air Force Relieves Commanders Involved in Nuclear Weapons Incident," Air Force Link, .  The 5th Bomb Wing, according to the USAF's statement on the wing's mission, served with its B-52 bombers as part of the USAF's conventional and strategic combat force.USAF,   The "strategic" portion of the 5th's mission included the ability to deliver nuclear weapons against potential targets worldwide.  Thus, Minot Air Force Base stored and maintained a ready arsenal of nuclear bombs, nuclear warheads, and associated delivery systems, including, as of August 2007, the AGM-129 Advanced Cruise Missile.Warrick, ''Missteps in the Bunker''.



The AGM-129 was fielded in 1987 as a stealthy cruise missile platform to deliver the W80-1 variable yield nuclear warhead.  Although originally designed to equip the B-1 bomber, it was later decided that the AGM-129 would only be carried by the B-52, mounted on external pylons on the wings, or internally in the bomb bay. Parsch, Andreas, 

In March 2007, the USAF decided to retire its AGM-129 complement in order to help comply with international arms-control treaties and to replace them with AGM-86 missiles., Pincus, "4 Colonels Lose Their Air Force Commands," USDoD, "DoD Press Briefing with Maj. Gen. Newton"  In order to do so, the USAF began to transport its AGM-129s stored at Minot by B-52s to Barksdale Air Force Base in Louisiana for ultimate disposal.  By August 29, 2007 according to the Washington Post, more than 200 AGM-129s had been shipped from Minot to Barksdale in this manner.Parsch, Andreas, , Warrick, ''Missteps in the Bunker''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="31b74f3250bd5f4546162d0ce8673c55" name="Agm-129_acm" sectnum="1#1">../img/31b74f3250bd5f4546162d0ce8673c55.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>