<document id="161da9e3ff6d804e321511e8c6f390e7-1.5" name="Alice_in_Chains" cat="20">
<text>
While Alice in Chains was inactive during 1995, Staley joined the "grunge supergroup" Mad Season, which also featured Pearl Jam guitarist Mike McCready, John Baker Saunders from The Walkabouts and Screaming Trees drummer Barrett Martin. Mad Season released one album, ''Above'', for which Staley provided lead vocals and the album artwork. The album spawned a number-two single, "River of Deceit", as well as a home video release of ''Live at the Moore''. In April 1995, Alice in Chains entered Bad Animals Studio in Seattle with producer Toby Wright, who had previously worked with Corrosion of Conformity and Slayer. While in the studio, an inferior version of the song "Grind" was leaked to radio, and received major airplay. On October 6, 1995, the band released the studio version of the song to radio via satellite uplink.

On November 7, 1995, Columbia Records released the eponymous ''Alice in Chains'', which debuted at number one on the ''Billboard'' 200, and has since been certified double platinum. Of the album's four singles, "Grind", "Again", "Over Now", and "Heaven Beside You", three feature Cantrell on lead vocals. Jon Wiederhorn of ''Rolling Stone'' called the album "liberating and enlightening, the songs achieve a startling, staggering and palpable impact." The song "Got Me Wrong" unexpectedly charted three years after its release on the ''Sap'' EP. The song was re-released as a single on the soundtrack for the independent film ''Clerks'' in 1995, reaching number seven on the Mainstream Rock Tracks chart. The band opted not to tour in support of ''Alice in Chains'', adding to the rumors of drug abuse.

Alice in Chains resurfaced on April 10, 1996, to perform their first concert in three years for ''MTV Unplugged'', a program featuring all-acoustic set lists. The performance featured some of the band's highest charting singles, including "Down in a Hole", "Heaven Beside You", and "Would?", and introduced a new song, "The Killer Is Me". The show marked Alice in Chains' only appearance as a five-piece band, adding second guitarist Scott Olson. A live album of the performance was released in July 1996, which debuted at number three on the ''Billboard'' 200, and was accompanied by a home video release, both of which received platinum certification by the RIAA. Alice in Chains performed four shows following the 1993 ''Lollapalooza'' tour supporting the reunited original Kiss-lineup, with the final live appearance of Layne Staley on July 3, 1996, in Kansas City, Missouri.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="086478098f816c120ed04ce5574930bd" name="Laynemtv" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/086478098f816c120ed04ce5574930bd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>