<document id="161da9e3ff6d804e321511e8c6f390e7-3" name="Alice_in_Chains" cat="20">
<text>
Alice in Chains has sold more than 14 million albums in the United States, released two number-one albums and 21 top 40 singles, and has received six Grammy nominations. The band was ranked number 34 on VH1's ''100 Greatest Artists of Hard Rock''. Alice in Chains was named 15th greatest live band by ''Hit Parader'',"Hard Rock's All-Time Top 100 Live Bands". ''Hit Parader''. February 2008. with vocalist Layne Staley placing as 27th greatest vocalist of all time."Heavy Metal's All-Time Top 100 Vocalists". ''Hit Parader''. November 2006. The band's second album, ''Dirt'', was named 5th best album in the last two decades by ''Close-Up'' magazine.. ultimate-guitar.com. April 30, 2008. In August 2009, Alice in Chains won the ''Kerrang!'' Icon Award.. ''Kerrang!''. August 3, 2009.

Alice in Chains has had a large impact on many bands, such as Godsmack, who, according to Jon Wiederhorn of MTV, "have sonically followed Alice in Chains' lead while adding their own distinctive edge". Godsmack singer and founder Sully Erna has also cited Layne Staley as his primary influence. The band's name is actually inspired by an Alice in Chains song, "God Smack". Staind has covered Alice in Chains' song "Nutshell" live, which appears on the compilation ''The Singles: 1996-2006'', and also wrote a song entitled "Layne", in Staley's dedication, on the album ''14 Shades of Grey''. Three Days Grace also performs a cover of "Rooster", which can be seen on the DVD ''Live at the Palace''. Other bands that have been inspired by Alice in Chains include Taproot, Puddle of Mudd, Smile Empty Soul, Cold, and Tantric. Metallica said they've always wanted to tour with the band, citing Alice in Chains as a major influence on the vocal melodies for Metallica's eighth studio album ''St. Anger'', and also used the band, and Staley, as inspiration for their 2008 release, ''Death Magnetic''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="12478b105178de047494bd18f23e141d" name="William_Duvall" sectnum="3#1">../img/12478b105178de047494bd18f23e141d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>