<document id="161da9e3ff6d804e321511e8c6f390e7-1.2" name="Alice_in_Chains" cat="20">
<text>
Alice in Chains soon became a top priority of the label, who released the band's first official recording in July 1990, a promotional EP ''We Die Young''. The EP's lead single, "We Die Young", became a hit at metal radio. After its success, the label rushed Alice in Chains' debut album into production with producer Dave Jerden. Cantrell stated the album was intended to have a "moody aura" that was a "direct result of the brooding atmosphere and feel of Seattle".

The resulting album, ''Facelift'', was released on August 21, 1990, peaking at number 42 in the summer of 1991 on the ''Billboard 200'' chart. ''Facelift'' was not an instant success, selling under 40,000 copies in the first six months of release, until MTV added "Man in the Box" to regular daytime rotation.Gill, Chris (September 1999). "Dirt". ''Guitar World''. The single hit number 18 on the Mainstream rock charts, with the album's follow up single, "Sea of Sorrow", reaching number 27, and in six weeks ''Facelift'' sold 400,000 copies in the US. The album was a critical success, with Steve Huey of Allmusic citing ''Facelift'' as "one of the most important records in establishing an audience for grunge and alternative rock."

''Facelift'' was certified gold by the Recording Industry Association of America by the end of 1990, while the band continued to hone its audience, opening for such artists as Iggy Pop, Van Halen, Poison, and Extreme. In early 1991, Alice in Chains landed the opening slot for the Clash of the Titans with Anthrax, Megadeth, and Slayer, exposing the band to a wide metal audience. Alice in Chains was nominated for a Best Hard Rock Performance Grammy Award in 1992 for "Man in the Box", but lost to Van Halen for their 1991 album ''For Unlawful Carnal Knowledge''.


Following the tour, Alice in Chains entered the studio to record demos for its next album, but ended up recording five acoustic songs instead. While in the studio, drummer Sean Kinney had a dream about "making an EP called ''Sap''". The band decided "not to mess with fate", and on March 21, 1992, Alice in Chains released their second EP, ''Sap''. The EP was released while Nirvana's ''Nevermind'' was at the top of the ''Billboard'' 200 charts, resulting in a rising popularity of Seattle-based bands, and the term grunge music. ''Sap'' was soon certified gold. The EP features guest vocals by Ann Wilson from the band Heart, who joined Staley and Cantrell for the choruses of "Brother", "Am I Inside" and "Love Song". The EP also features Mark Arm of Mudhoney and Chris Cornell of Soundgarden, who appeared together on the song "Right Turn", credited to "Alice Mudgarden" in the liner notes. In 1992, Alice in Chains appeared in the Cameron Crowe film ''Singles'', performing as a "bar band". The band also contributed the song "Would?" to the film's soundtrack, whose video received an award for Best Video from a Film at the 1993 MTV Video Music Awards.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="147f221a5954823ba935853fc166bfe9" name="Jerry_Cantrell_2" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/147f221a5954823ba935853fc166bfe9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>