<document id="16a968cdb906137a952161789b5c1ea3-1.6" name="Radiohead" cat="20">
<text>
Radiohead began work on their seventh album in February 2005. In September 2005, the band recorded a piano-based song, "I Want None of This", for the War Child charity album ''Help: A Day in the Life''. The album was sold online, with "I Want None of This" being the most downloaded track, although it was not released as a single.
  Radiohead had already begun recording their next album on their own and then with producer Mark Stent. However, in late 2006, after touring Europe and North America and debuting 13 new songs there, the band resumed work with Nigel Godrich in London, Oxford and several rural locations in Somerset, England.
 Work was finished in June 2007 and the recordings were mastered the following month.


Radiohead's seventh album, ''In Rainbows'', was released through the band's own website on 10 October 2007 as a digital download for which customers could make whatever payment that they wanted, including nothing; the site only advised, "it's up to you". Following the band's sudden announcement 10 days beforehand, Radiohead's unusual strategy received much notice within the music industry and beyond.
 1.2 million downloads were reportedly sold by the day of release,
 but the band's management did not release official sales figures, claiming that the Internet-only distribution was intended to boost later retail sales.
 A "discbox", including a second disc from the recording sessions, vinyl and CD editions of the album, and a hardcover book of artwork, was sold and shipped in late 2007.

''In Rainbows'' was physically released in the UK in late December on XL Recordings and in North America in January 2008 on TBD Records, charting at number one both in the UK and in the US. 
 The album's success in the US marked Radiohead's highest chart success in that country since ''Kid A'', while it was their fifth UK number one album. "Jigsaw Falling into Place", the first single from the album, was released in the UK in January 2008.
 The second single, "Nude", debuted at number 37 in the Billboard Hot 100, Radiohead's first song to make that chart since 1995's "High and Dry" and their first top 40 hit in the US since "Creep". A greatest hits album, titled ''Radiohead: The Best Of'', was released by EMI in June 2008. The compilation was made without the input of the band and also did not contain any songs from ''In Rainbows'', as the band had already left their label. Radiohead continued to put out tracks from ''In Rainbows'' as singles and videos; in July a digitally-shot video for "House of Cards" was made available. "House of Cards", along with "Bodysnatchers", also received a single release on radio. In September the band announced a fourth single, "Reckoner", and a remix competition similar to one organised for "Nude".

''In Rainbows'' received overwhelmingly positive reviews, among the best of Radiohead's career. Critics praised the album for having a more accessible sound and personal style of lyrics than their past work.
 In July 2008, ''In Rainbows'' was nominated for the short list of the Mercury Music Prize. At the 2009 Grammy Awards, the band won Best Alternative Music Album. Their production team also won the Grammy for Best Boxed or Special Limited Edition Package. The band received their third nomination for Album of the Year, along with three other nominations for the band, plus nominations for Godrich's production work and for the "House of Cards" video.

From mid-2008 to early 2009, Radiohead toured North America, Europe, Japan, Mexico, Brazil, Argentina and Chile (the band's first ever tour in South America) - to promote ''In Rainbows''. The band headlined the Reading and Leeds Festivals in August 2009.. ''NME''. 30 Mar 2009
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3edfc9c502a4cbec61acad7a41916d4d" name="Thom_Yorke" sectnum="1.6#1">../img/3edfc9c502a4cbec61acad7a41916d4d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>