<document id="16b8361e85bb1b53fd02c6b82bca5a79-1" name="Body_Count_(album)" cat="20">
<text>
While Ice-T was primarily known for his work in the hip hop genre, he had long been a fan of various genres of rock music and had sampled songs by Jimi Hendrix, Black Sabbath and Led Zeppelin, among other artists. He formed Body Count out of this interest. The band comprised musicians Ice-T had known from Crenshaw High School. Ice-T states that "I knew we didn't want to form an R&B group.  Where am I gonna get the rage and the anger to attack something with that?  We knew Body Count had to be a rock band. The name alone negates the band from being R&B."

Ice-T co-wrote the band's music and lyrics with lead guitarist Ernie C, and took on the duties of lead vocalist. Ice-T states that "I knew I couldn't sing, but then I thought, 'Who ''can'' sing in rock 'n' roll?'" Aside from Ice-T and Ernie C, the original line-up consisted of Mooseman on bass, Beatmaster V on drums and D-Roc on rhythm guitar. According to Ice-T, "We named the group Body Count because every Sunday night in L.A., I'd watch the news, and the newscasters would tally up the youths killed in gang homicides that week and then just segue to sports. 'Is that all I am,' I thought, 'a body count?'"

Ice-T introduced the band at Lollapalooza in 1991, devoting half of his set to his hip hop songs, and half to Body Count songs, increasing his appeal with both alternative rock fans and middle-class teenagers. Many considered the Body Count performances to be the highlight of the tour. The group made its first album appearance on Ice-T's 1991 solo album ''O.G. Original Gangster''. The song "Body Count" was preceded by a staged interview in which the performer referred to the group as a "black hardcore band," stating that "as far as I'm concerned, music is music. I don't look at it as rock, R & B, or all that kind of stuff. I just look at it as music.  I do what I like and I happen to like rock 'n' roll, and I feel sorry for anybody who only listens to one form of music."Ice-T (1991). "Body Count". ''O.G. Original Gangster''. Sire/Warner Bros. Records. ISBN 7599264922

Recording sessions for the group's self-titled debut took place from September to December 1991. The album was released on March 31, 1992, on compact disc, vinyl, and audio cassette. Ice-T states that ''Body Count'' was intentionally different from his solo hip hop albums in that "An Ice T album has intelligence, and at times it has ignorance. Sometimes it has anger, sometimes it has questions. But ''Body Count'' was intended to reflect straight anger. It was supposed to be the voice of the angry brother, without answers.  If you took a kid and you put him in jail with a microphone and asked him how he feels, you'd get ''Body Count'': 'Fuck that. Fuck school. Fuck the police.' You wouldn't get intelligence or compassion. You'd get raw anger." From the album, "There Goes The Neighborhood" was released as a single, while "Body Count's in the House" was featured in the film ''Universal Soldier''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fe84d62319fc644d31533f2b1d4b2fc7" name="Body_Count" sectnum="1#1">../img/fe84d62319fc644d31533f2b1d4b2fc7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>