<document id="16b8361e85bb1b53fd02c6b82bca5a79-3" name="Body_Count_(album)" cat="20">
<text>
Like Ice-T's gangsta rap albums, ''Body Count'''s material focused on various social and political issues, with songs focusing on topics ranging from police brutality to drug abuse. According to Ernie C, "Everybody writes about whatever they learned growing up, and we were no exception. Like The Beach Boys sing about the beach, we sing about the way we grew up." Ice-T states that "''Body Count'' was an angry record. It was meant to be a protest record. I put my anger in it, while lacing it with dark humor." The spoken introduction, "Smoked Pork" features Ice-T taking on the roles of a seemingly stranded motorist and a police officer who refuses to aid, telling him that "my job is eatin' these doughnuts". When the officer recognizes the motorist, gunshots are heard. The final voice on the track is the motorist confirming his identity.Body Count (1992). "Smoked Pork". ''Body Count''. Sire/Warner Bros. Records. ISBN 7599268782

In the lyrics of "KKK Bitch," Ice-T describes a sexual encounter with a woman whom he soon learns is the daughter of the Grand Wizard of the Ku Klux Klan. The lyrics go on to describe a scenario in which members of Body Count "crash" a Klan meeting to "get buck wild with the white freaks". Ice-T makes humorous reference to " in love with Tipper Gore's two twelve year old nieces", and ponders the possibility of the Grand Wizard coming after him "when his grandson's named little Ice-T."Body Count (1992). ''Body Count''. Lyrics sheet. Sire/Warner Bros. Records. ISBN 7599268782 In ''The Ice Opinion: Who Gives a Fuck?'', Ice-T wrote that "'KKK Bitch' was ironic because the sentiments were true. We'd play Ku Klux Klan areas in the South and the girls would always come backstage and tell us how their brothers and fathers didn't like black folks.  We knew that 'KKK Bitch' would totally piss off the Ku Klux Klan. There's humor in the song, but it fucks with them. It's on a punk tip."

"Voodoo" describes a fictional encounter between Ice-T and an old woman with a voodoo doll. "The Winner Loses" describes the downfall of a crack cocaine user. "There Goes the Neighborhood" is a sarcastic response to critics of Body Count, sung from the point of view of a racist white rocker who wonders "Don't they know rock's just for whites? / Don't they know the rules? / Those niggers are too hardcore / This shit ain't cool." For the song's music video, the word "nigger" was replaced with the phrase "black boys". The music video ends with a black musician implanting an electric guitar into the ground and setting it on fire. The final image is similar to that of a burning cross.Body Count (1992). "There Goes The Neighborhood". Music video. ''Body Count''. Sire/Warner Bros. Records. ISBN 7599268782

"Evil Dick" focuses on male promiscuity. Its lyrics describe a married man who is led to seek after strange women after his "evil dick" tells him "Don't sleep alone, don't sleep alone." "Momma's Gotta Die Tonight" follows the account of a black teenager who murders and dismembers his racist mother after she reacts negatively when he brings a white girl home. In ''The Ice Opinion: Who Gives a Fuck?'', Ice-T wrote that the song's lyrics are metaphorical, explaining that "Whoever is still perpetuating racism has got to die, not necessarily physically, but they have to kill off that part of their brain. From now on, consider it dead. The entire attitude is dead."

Ice-T referred to the album's final track, "Cop Killer" as a protest song, stating that the song is " in the first person as a character who is fed up with police brutality." The song was written in 1990, and had been performed live several times, including at Lollapalooza, before it had been recorded in a studio. The album version mentions then-Los Angeles police chief Daryl Gates and the black motorist Rodney King, whose beating by LAPD officers was recorded on videotape. In ''The Ice Opinion: Who Gives a Fuck?'', Ice-T wrote that the song " a warning, not a threat—to authority that says, 'Yo, police: We're human beings. Treat us accordingly.'" In an interview for ''Rolling Stone'', Ice-T stated that "We just celebrated the fourth of July, which is really just national Fuck the Police Day  I bet that during the Revolutionary War, there were songs similar to mine."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="be4d77882be12a924913025ce9d6319e" name="There_Goes_the_Neighborhood_music_video" sectnum="3#1">../img/be4d77882be12a924913025ce9d6319e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>