<document id="17c11bc5bc44bda24a18f2b579372fdd-6" name="Coronation_of_the_British_monarch" cat="25">
<text>
The Sovereign is then borne into the Throne. The Archbishops and Bishops swear their fealty, saying "I, N., Archbishop  of N., will be faithful and true, and faith and truth will bear unto you, our Sovereign Lord , King  of this Realm and Defender of the Faith, and unto your heirs and successors according to law. So help me God." The peers then proceed to pay their homage, saying "I, N., Duke  of N., do become your liege man of life and limb, and of earthly worship; and faith and truth will I bear unto you, to live and die, against all manner of folks. So help me God." The clergy pay homage together, led by the Archbishop of Canterbury. Next, members of the Royal Family pay homage individually. The peers are led by the premier peers of their rank: the Dukes by the Premier Duke, the Marquesses by the Premier Marquess, and so forth. 

If there is a Queen Consort, she is crowned in a very simple ceremony immediately before homage is paid. A Queen Regnant's husband, however, is not separately crowned. The Communion ceremony interrupted earlier is resumed and completed.

The Sovereign then exits the Coronation Theatre, entering St Edward's Chapel (also within the Abbey), preceded by the bearers of the Sword of State, the Sword of Spiritual Justice, the Sword of Temporal Justice and the Sword of Mercy (the last has a blunt tip).Hilliam, ''Crown, Orb & Sceptre'', p211–2 The Crown and Sceptres worn by the Sovereign, as well as all other regalia, are laid at the Altar; the Sovereign removes the ''Robe Royal'' and ''Stole Royal'', exchanges the ''crimson surcoat'' for the ''purple surcoat'' and is enrobed in the ''Imperial Robe of purple velvet''. He or she then wears the Imperial State Crown and takes into his or her hands the Sceptre with the Cross and the Orb and leaves the chapel while all present sing the National Anthem.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4ac2b9da715b8f061f297ccbe6e22414" name="Elizabeth_I_in_coronation_robes" sectnum="6#1">../img/4ac2b9da715b8f061f297ccbe6e22414.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>