<document id="17c11bc5bc44bda24a18f2b579372fdd-5" name="Coronation_of_the_British_monarch" cat="25">
<text>
After the Communion service is interrupted, the ''crimson robe'' is removed, and the Sovereign proceeds to King Edward's Chair, which has been set in a most prominent position, wearing the ''anointing gown''. (In 1953, King Edward's Chair stood atop a dais of several steps.), Image of 'Completed Coronation Theatre' at bottom. This ancient mediaeval chair has a slot in the base into which the Stone of Scone is fitted for the ceremony. Also known as the "stone of destiny", it was used for ancient Scottish coronations until brought to England by Edward I. It has been used for every coronation at Westminster Abbey since. Until 1996 the stone was kept with the chair in Westminster Abbey between coronations; but it was returned that year to Scotland, where it will remain on display in Edinburgh Castle until it is needed for a coronation.

Once seated in this chair, a canopy is held over the monarch's head for the anointing. The duty of acting as canopy-bearers was performed in recent coronations by four Knights of the Garter. This element of the coronation service is considered sacred and is concealed from public gaze; it was not photographed in 1937 or televised in 1953. The Dean of Westminster pours consecrated oil from an eagle-shaped ampulla into a spoon; the Archbishop of Canterbury then anoints the Sovereign on the hands, breast, and head. The filigreed spoon is the only part of the mediaeval crown jewels which survived the commonwealth. The Archbishop concludes by stating a blessing.

The Sovereign is then enrobed in the ''colobium sindonis'', over which is placed the ''supertunica''.

The Lord Great Chamberlain presents the spurs, which represent chivalry. The Archbishop of Canterbury, assisted by other bishops, then presents the Sword of State to the Sovereign. The Sovereign is then further robed, this time putting the ''Robe Royal'' and ''Stole Royal'' on top of the ''supertunica''. The Archbishop then delivers several Crown Jewels to the Sovereign. First, he delivers the Orb, a hollow golden sphere set with numerous precious and semi-precious stones. The Orb is surmounted by a cross, representing the rule of Jesus over the world;Hilliam, ''Crown, Orb & Sceptre'', p209 it is returned to the Altar immediately after being received. Next, the Sovereign receives a ring representing the "marriage" between him or her and the nation.Hilliam, ''Crown, Orb & Sceptre'', p212–3 The Sceptre with the Dove (so called because it is surmounted by a dove representing the Holy Spirit) and the Sceptre with the Cross (which incorporates Cullinan I, the largest cut diamond in the world) are delivered to the Sovereign.Hilliam, ''Crown, Orb & Sceptre'', p210 As the Sovereign holds the two sceptres, the Archbishop of Canterbury places St Edward's Crown on his or her head. All cry "God Save the King ", placing their coronets and caps on their heads. Cannon are fired from the Tower of London.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d731f748d111a2741c9df06d592dc658" name="Marquess_of_Anglesey_carrying_St_Edward's_Crown" sectnum="5#1">../img/d731f748d111a2741c9df06d592dc658.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>