<document id="185a5eb309e9ba14f65e6486f08b3032-14" name="Karnataka" cat="11">
<text>
Karnataka has a rich diversity of flora and fauna. It has a recorded forest area of  which constitutes 20.19% of the total geographical area of the state. These forests support 25% of the elephant and 10% of the tiger population of India. Many regions of Karnataka are as yet unexplored, so new species of flora and fauna are found periodically. The Western Ghats, a biodiversity hotspot, includes the western region of Karnataka. Two sub-clusters in the Western Ghats, viz. Talacauvery and Kudremukh, both in Karnataka, are on the tentative list of World Heritage Sites of UNESCO.  The Bandipur and Nagarahole National Parks, which fall outside these subclusters, were included in the Nilgiri Biosphere Reserve in 1986, a UNESCO designation. The Indian roller and the Indian elephant are recognized as the state bird and animal while sandalwood and the lotus are recognized as the state tree and flower respectively. Karnataka has five national parks: Anshi, Bandipur, Bannerghatta, Kudremukh and Nagarhole. A Walk on the Wild Side, An Information Guide to National Parks and Wildlife Sanctuaries of Karnataka, Compiled and Edited by Dr. Nima Manjrekar, Karnataka Forest Department, Wildlife Wing, October 2000 It also has 25 wildlife sanctuaries of which seven are bird sanctuaries.

Wild animals that are found in Karnataka include the elephant, the tiger, the leopard, the gaur, the sambar deer, the chital or spotted deer, the muntjac, the bonnet macaque, the slender loris, the common palm civet, the small Indian civet, the sloth bear, the dhole, the striped hyena and the golden jackal. Some of the birds found here are the Great Hornbill, the Malabar Pied Hornbill, the Ceylon frogmouth, herons, ducks, kites, eagles, falcons, quails, partridges,  lapwings, sandpipers, pigeons, doves, parakeets, cuckoos, owls, nightjars, swifts, kingfishers, bee-eaters and munias. Some species of trees found in Karnataka are ''Callophyllum tomentosa'', ''Callophyllum wightianum'', ''Garcina cambogia'', ''Garcina morealla'', ''Alstonia scholaris'', '''', ''Artocarpus hirsutus'', ''Artocarpus lacoocha'', ''Cinnamomum zeylanicum'', ''Grewia tilaefolia'', ''Santalum album'', ''Shorea talura'', ''Emblica officinalis'', ''Vitex altissima'' and ''Wrightia tinctoria''. Wildlife in Karnataka is threatened by poaching, habitat destruction, human-wildlife conflict and pollution.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="43b7d18ef3901763999f2120674f99d1" name="Coraciasbenghalensis" sectnum="14#1">../img/43b7d18ef3901763999f2120674f99d1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>