<document id="187859a255197631a4d518fd62315e4d-2.7" name="Edward_III_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
Central to Edward III's policy was reliance on the higher nobility for purposes of war and administration. While his father had regularly been in conflict with a great portion of his peerage, Edward III successfully created a spirit of camaraderie between himself and his greatest subjects.

Both Edward I and Edward II had conducted a policy of limitation, allowing the creation of few peerages during the sixty years preceding Edward III's reign. The young king reversed this policy when, in 1337, as a preparation for the imminent war, he created six new earls on the same day.K.B. McFarlane (1973) ''The Nobility of Later Medieval England'', Oxford: Clarendon Press, pp. 158-9 ISBN 0-19-822362-5. At the same time, Edward expanded the ranks of the peerage upwards, by introducing the new title of duke for close relatives of the king.

Furthermore, Edward bolstered the sense of community within this group by the creation of the Order of the Garter, probably in 1348. A plan from 1344 to revive the Round Table of King Arthur never came to fruition, but the new order carried connotations from this legend by the circular shape of the garter. Polydore Vergil tells of how the young Joan of Kent, Countess of Salisbury —the king's favourite at the time—accidentally dropped her garter at a ball at Calais. King Edward responded to the ridicule of the crowd by tying the garter around his own knee with the words ''honi soit qui mal y pense''—shame on him who thinks ill of it.McKisack, ''Fourteenth Century'', 251-2. Another candidate for the owner of the original garter was her mother-in-law Catherine Grandisson, the Dowager Countess of Salisbury.

This reinforcement of the aristocracy must be seen in conjunction with the war in France, as must the emerging sense of national identity. Just like the war with Scotland had done, the fear of a French invasion helped strengthen a sense of national unity, and nationalise the aristocracy that had been largely Anglo-French since the Norman conquest. Since the time of Edward I, popular myth suggested that the French planned to extinguish the English language, and like his grandfather had done, Edward III made the most of this scare.Prestwich, ''Three Edwards'', 209–10. As a result, the English language experienced a strong revival; in 1362, a Statute of Pleading ordered the English language to be used in law courts and, the year after, Parliament was for the first time opened in English.McKisack, ''Fourteenth Century'', 524. At the same time, the vernacular saw a revival as a literary language, through the works of William Langland, John Gower and especially ''The Canterbury Tales'' by Geoffrey Chaucer.

Yet the extent of this Anglicisation must not be exaggerated. The statute of 1362 was in fact written in the French language and had little immediate effect, and parliament was opened in that language as late as 1377.Prestwich, ''Plantagenet England'', 556. The Order of the Garter, though a distinctly English institution, included also foreign members such as John V, Duke of Brittany and Sir Robert of Namur.McKisack, ''Fourteenth Century'', 253; Prestwich, ''Plantagenet England'', 554. Edward III—himself bilingual—viewed himself as legitimate king of both England and France, and could not show preferential treatment for one part of his domains over another.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="245fa7f20b6a9bd107c9f3137bc98dcc" name="The_Great_Seal_of_Edward_III" sectnum="2.7#1">../img/245fa7f20b6a9bd107c9f3137bc98dcc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>