<document id="19099abc83b37014b75a2506ffa4c2d6-4.2" name="Tenebrae_(film)" cat="19">
<text>
In his study of the film, Flanagan argues that in ''Tenebrae'', “male and female sexual deviancy are the central issues,”  noting that Berti targets those he considers to be “filthy, slimy perverts ”.  The first victim is a sexually promiscuous shoplifter, and his next two are the lesbian reporter and her bisexual lover.  He kills the comparatively “normal” Maria only because she inadvertently discovers his twisted compulsion.  

McDonagh notes that ''Tenebrae'' expands a theme already introduced in Argento’s earlier ''giallo'' films.  "''The Bird with the Crystal Plumage'', ''The Cat o' Nine Tails'', ''Four Flies on Grey Velvet'' (1972), and ''Deep Red'' are full of sex, of course: transvestitism and sexual role playing are in all four films central factors and none lacks for imagery dealing in diverse sexual behavior.  But ''Tenebrae''’s overall sensuality sets it apart from Argento’s other ''gialli''.”  She says that the film’s sexual content and abundant nudity make it “the first of Argento’s films to have an overtly erotic aspect,” and further notes that  “''Tenebrae'' is fraught with free-floating anxiety that is specifically sexual in nature.”     



Flanagan and McDonagh – and, indeed, most critics – have noted that two sexually charged flashbacks are key to understanding ''Tenebrae''.  These distinct but strongly related memory fragments are introduced repeatedly throughout the course of the film, usually immediately following a murder sequence.  Although these flashbacks are never fully explained, the first of these memories reveals a beautiful young woman’s sexual humiliation (basically, an oral rape) of a teenaged boy (presumably Peter Neal) on a pale-white beach, followed (in the second flashback) by the vicious revenge-murder of the woman some time later.  The young woman (played by transgender actress Eva Robin's) is mostly topless during this first sequence, and she humiliates the young man by jamming the heel of one of her Freudian shiny red shoes into his mouth while he is held down by a group of gleeful boys.  McDonagh notes that all of the fetishistic imagery of these flashbacks, combined with the sadistic details of the murder sequences in the main narrative,  “set the parameters of ''Tenebrae''’s fetishistic and fetishicized visual vocabulary, couched in terms both ritualistic and orgiastically out of control…Peter Neal indulges in sins of the flesh and ''Tenebrae'' revels in them, inviting the spectator to join in; in fact, it dares the viewer not to do so.”
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e505960b4372e7fa70659a026343f285" name="TenebraeNightmare" sectnum="4.2#1">../img/e505960b4372e7fa70659a026343f285.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>