<document id="19099abc83b37014b75a2506ffa4c2d6-3" name="Tenebrae_(film)" cat="19">
<text>
''Tenebrae'' had a wide theatrical release throughout Italy and Europe,  something the director very much needed after having suffered major distribution problems with his previous film, ''Inferno''. In the United States, however, the film fared far less well.  It remained unseen until 1984, when Bedford Entertainment briefly released a heavily edited version under the title ''Unsane''.  It was approximately ten minutes shorter than the European release version and was missing nearly all of the film’s violence, which effectively rendered the numerous horror sequences incomprehensible.  In addition, certain scenes that established the characters and their relationships were excised, making the film's narrative difficult to follow. Predictably, this version of ''Tenebrae'' received nearly unanimously negative reviews.Lucas, Tim.  ''The Video Watchdog Book'', Video Watchdog, 1992.  ISBN 0-9633756-0-1  



In the United Kingdom, the film was shorn of five seconds of  "sexualized violence" by the British Board of Film Classification prior to its theatrical release.  It later became one of the thirty-nine so-called "Video Nasties" that were successfully prosecuted and banned from sale in UK video stores under the Video Recordings Act 1984.  This ban lasted until 1999, when ''Tenebrae'' was legally rereleased on videotape, with an additional one second of footage removed from the film (this version was also missing the previously censored five seconds). In 2003, the BBFC reclassified the film and passed it without any cuts.    

The film has since been released basically uncut (minus approximately 20 seconds of extraneous material) on DVD in the US, allowing the film to be properly evaluated for the first time.   Ed Gonzalez, of ''Slant Magazine'', said that "''Tenebre'' is a riveting defense of auteur theory, ripe with self-reflexive discourse and various moral conflicts. It's both a riveting horror film and an architect's worst nightmare."
Keith Phipps, of The Onion's ''A.V. Club'', noted "...Argento makes some points about the intersection of art, reality, and personality, but the director's stunning trademark setpieces, presented here in a fully restored version, provide the real reason to watch."  Almar Haflidason, in a review for BBC.co.uk, opined, "Sadistically beautiful and viciously exciting, welcome to true terror with Dario Argento's shockingly relentless ''Tenebrae''."  Tim Lucas, in ''Video Watchdog,'' said,   "Though it is in some ways as artificial and deliberate as a De Palma thriller, ''Tenebrae'' contains more likeable characters, believable relationships, and more emphasis on the erotic than can be found in any other Argento film."Lucas, Tim.  ''Video Watchdog'' Magazine, issue #49, pgs. 68-72.  Review of ''Tenebrae'' Laserdisc

Not all of the recent critical reaction to ''Tenebrae'' has been positive.   Gary Johnson, editor of ''Images'', complained that "Not much of ''Tenebre'' makes much sense. The plot becomes little more than an excuse for Argento to stage the murder sequences. And these are some of the bloodiest murders of Argento's career."  In 2004, Tim Lucas   reevaluated the film and found that some of his earlier enthusiasm had dimmed considerably, noting that, "''Tenebre'' is beginning to suffer from the cheap 16 mm-like softness of Luciano Tovoli's cinematography, its sometimes over-storyboarded violence (the first two murders in particular  look stilted), the many bewildering lapses in logic...and the overdone performances of many of its female actors..."Lucas, Tim.  ''Video Watchdog'' Magazine, issue #108, pgs. 71–72.  Review of ''Tenebrae'' DVD
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="77e5f02e012c1a9f613e85e1905a416e" name="Tenebrae_ribbon" sectnum="3#1">../img/77e5f02e012c1a9f613e85e1905a416e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>