<document id="19d63963dbc21d95845f4fa5bdafb89c-4.1" name="Barbara_McClintock" cat="3">
<text>
In the summer of 1944 at Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, McClintock began systematic studies on the mechanisms of the mosaic color patterns of maize seed and the unstable inheritance of this mosaicism. She identified two new dominant and interacting genetic loci that she named ''Dissociator'' (''Ds'') and ''Activator'' (''Ac''). She found that the ''Dissociator'' did not just dissociate or cause the chromosome to break, it also had a variety of effects on neighboring genes when the ''Activator'' was also present. In early 1948, she made the surprising discovery that both ''Dissociator'' and ''Activator'' could transpose, or change position, on the chromosome. 

She observed the effects of the transposition of ''Ac'' and ''Ds'' by the changing patterns of coloration in maize kernels over generations of controlled crosses, and described the relationship between the two loci through intricate microscopic analysis. She concluded that ''Ac'' controls the transposition of the ''Ds'' from chromosome 9, and that the movement of ''Ds'' is accompanied by the breakage of the chromosome. When ''Ds'' moves, the aleurone-color gene is released from the suppressing effect of the ''Ds'' and transformed into the active form, which initiates the pigment synthesis in cells. The transposition of ''Ds'' in different cells is random, it may move in some but not others, which causes color mosaicism. The size of the colored spot on the seed is determined by stage of the seed development during dissociation. McClintock also found that the transposition of ''Ds'' and the is determined by the number of ''Ac'' copies in the cell.

Between 1948 and 1950, she developed a theory by which these mobile elements regulated the genes by inhibiting or modulating their action. She referred to ''Dissociator'' and ''Activator'' as "controlling units"—later, as "controlling elements"—to distinguish them from genes. She hypothesized that gene regulation could explain how complex multicellular organisms made of cells with identical genomes have cells of different function. McClintock's discovery challenged the concept of the genome as a static set of instructions passed between generations. In 1950, she reported her work on ''Ac/Ds'' and her ideas about gene regulation in a paper entitled "The origin and behavior of mutable loci in maize" published in the journal ''Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences''. In summer 1951, when she reported on her work on gene mutability in maize at the annual symposium at Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, the paper she presented was called "Chromosome organization and genic expression".McClintock, Barbara. (1950) "The origin and behavior of mutable loci in maize". Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. 36:344–55. 

Her work on controlling elements and gene regulation was conceptually difficult and was not immediately understood or accepted by her contemporaries; she described the reception of her research as "puzzlement, even hostility".McClintock, Barbara. "Introduction" in ''The discovery and characterization of transposable elements: the collected papers of Barbara McClintock''. Nevertheless, McClintock continued to develop her ideas on controlling elements. She published a paper in ''Genetics'' in 1953 where she presented all her statistical data, and undertook lecture tours to universities throughout the 1950s to speak about her work.McClintock, Barbara. (1953) "Induction of instability at selected loci in maize". ''Genetics'' 38:579–99. She continued to investigate the problem and identified a new element that she called ''Suppressor-mutator'' (''Spm''), which, although similar to ''Ac/Ds'', displays more complex behavior. Based on the reactions of other scientists to her work, McClintock felt she risked alienating the scientific mainstream, and from 1953 stopped publishing accounts of her research on controlling elements.Comfort, Nathaniel, C.(1999) ""The real point is control": The reception of Barbara McClintock's controlling elements". ''Journal of the History of Biology'' 32:133–6.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="efefca33bfa8c64c9f1ca18311536ea9" name="Corn_mosaic" sectnum="4.1#1">../img/efefca33bfa8c64c9f1ca18311536ea9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>