<document id="19e21d7cc4c969dbf07e1336e4769874-2.1" name="Bart_Simpson" cat="19">
<text>
Matt Groening first conceived of Bart and the rest of the Simpson family in 1986, while waiting in the lobby of producer James L. Brooks' office. Groening had been called in to pitch a series of animated shorts for ''The Tracey Ullman Show'', and had intended to present an adaptation of his ''Life in Hell'' comic strip. When he realized that animating ''Life in Hell'' would require him to rescind publication rights, Groening decided to go in another direction. He hurriedly sketched out his version of a dysfunctional family, naming the characters after members of his own family. For the rebellious son, he substituted "Bart", an anagram of the word ''brat'', for his own name, as he decided it would have been too obvious for him to have named the character Matt.

Bart had originally been envisioned as "a much milder, troubled youth given to existential angst who talks to himself", but the character was changed based on Cartwright's voice acting. Groening has credited several different figures with providing inspiration for Bart: Matt Groening's older brother Mark provided much of the motivation for Bart's attitude.Groening, Matt. (2006). Commentary for "My Sister, My Sitter", in ''The Simpsons: The Complete Eighth Season'' . 20th Century Fox.Groening, Matt. (2006). Commentary for "Bart Carny", in ''The Simpsons: The Complete Ninth Season'' . 20th Century Fox. Bart was conceived as an extreme version of the typical misbehaving child character, merging all of the extreme traits of characters such as Tom Sawyer and Huckleberry Finn into one person. Groening describes Bart as "what would happen if Eddie Haskell  got his own show". Groening has also said that he found the premise of ''Dennis the Menace'' disappointing and was inspired to create a character who was actually a menace.Groening, Matt. (2005). Commentary for "Two Bad Neighbors", in ''The Simpsons: The Complete Seventh Season'' . 20th Century Fox. Bart's middle initial ''J'' is a "tribute" to animated characters such as Bullwinkle J. Moose and Rocket J. Squirrel from ''The Rocky and Bullwinkle Show'', who received their middle initial from Jay Ward.Groening, Matt. (2007). Commentary for "D'oh-in in the Wind", in ''The Simpsons: The Complete Tenth Season'' . 20th Century Fox. According to the book ''Bart Simpson's Guide to Life'', Bart's full middle name is JoJo.

Bart made his debut with the rest of the Simpson family on April 19, 1987 in ''The Tracey Ullman Show'' short "Good Night".Richmond, p. 14 In 1989, the shorts were adapted into ''The Simpsons'', a half-hour series airing on the Fox Broadcasting Company. Bart and the Simpson family remained the main characters on this new show.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4d1867c327676ff0a3bb0f315dbc07eb" name="Matt_Groening_by_Gage_Skidmore" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/4d1867c327676ff0a3bb0f315dbc07eb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>