<document id="19e801b84b886c851887edf203b8bd50-2" name="Thylacine" cat="3">
<text>
The indigenous peoples of Australia made first contact with the Thylacine. Numerous examples of Thylacine engravings and rock art have been found dating back to at least 1000 BC. Petroglyph images of the Thylacine can be found at the Dampier Rock Art Precinct on the Burrup Peninsula in Western Australia. By the time the first explorers arrived, the animal was already rare in Tasmania. Europeans may have encountered it as far back as 1642 when Abel Tasman first arrived in Tasmania. His shore party reported seeing the footprints of "wild beasts having claws like a ''Tyger''".Rembrants. D. (1682). "A short relation out of the journal of Captain Abel Jansen Tasman, upon the discovery of the ''South Terra incognita''; not long since published in the Low Dutch". ''Philosophical Collections of the Royal Society of London'', (6), 179-86. Quoted in Paddle (2000) p.3 Marc-Joseph Marion du Fresne, arriving with the ''Mascarin'' in 1772, reported seeing a "tiger cat".Roth H.L. (1891). "Crozet's Voyage to Tasmania, New Zealand, etc....1771–1772.". London. Truslove and Shirley. Quoted in Paddle (2000) p.3 Positive identification of the Thylacine as the animal encountered cannot be made from this report since the Tiger Quoll (''Dasyurus maculatus'') is similarly described. The first definitive encounter was by French explorers on 13 May 1792, as noted by the naturalist Jacques Labillardière, in his journal from the expedition led by D'Entrecasteaux. However, it was not until 1805 that William Paterson, the Lieutenant Governor of Tasmania, sent a detailed description for publication in the ''Sydney Gazette''. 

The first detailed scientific description was made by Tasmania's Deputy Surveyor-General, George Harris in 1808, five years after first settlement of the island. Harris originally placed the Thylacine in the genus ''Didelphis'', which had been created by Linnaeus for the American opossums, describing it as ''Didelphis cynocephala'', the "dog-headed opossum". Recognition that the Australian marsupials were fundamentally different from the known mammal genera led to the establishment of the modern classification scheme, and in 1796 Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire created the genus ''Dasyurus'' where he placed the Thylacine in 1810. To resolve the mixture of Greek and Latin nomenclature the species name was altered to ''cynocephalus''. In 1824, it was separated out into its own genus, ''Thylacinus'', by Temminck. The common name derives directly from the genus name, originally from the Greek ''θύλακος'' (thýlakos), meaning "pouch" or "sack".

Several studies support the Thylacine as being a basal member of the Dasyuromorphia and that the Tasmanian Devil is its closest living relative. However, research published in Genome Research in January 2009 suggests that the Numbat may be more basal than the Devil and more closely related to the Thylacine.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e103fbc03ef1885e32515e163dc9c4dd" name="Aboriginal_thylacine" sectnum="2#1">../img/e103fbc03ef1885e32515e163dc9c4dd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>