<document id="1a24a2fbbfbfc8a5cda39493a4405ac4-3" name="Hockey_Hall_of_Fame" cat="26">
<text>
The Hockey Hall of Fame has 15 exhibit areas covering . Visitors can view trophies,  memorabilia and equipment worn by players during special games. The ''MCI Great Hall'', described as "a Cathedral to the icons of Hockey", contains portraits and biographical information about every Hall of Fame honoured member. The centrepiece of the Great Hall is the Stanley Cup; for part of the year a replica is put on display when the presentation cup travels outside of the Hall of Fame. The original version of the Cup and the older rings, as well as all of the current National Hockey League trophies, are displayed in the bank vault, an alcove off the Great Hall. The Hall of Fame induction ceremony is annually held in the Great Hall.

The ''NHL Zone'' is a large area featuring displays relating to the NHL. Current teams and players are highlighted in the ''NHL Today'' area, while the ''NHL Retro'' displays include memorabilia and information about every NHL team past and present. The ''NHL Legends'' area features rotating exhibits focusing on honoured members; and ''NHL Milestones'' displays exhibits of noteworthy records including Darryl Sittler's ten-point game and Wayne Gretzky's all-time points record. The ''Stanley Cup dynasties'' exhibit features displays that include memorabilia from the rosters of nine teams considered to be dynasties because they dominated the NHL for several years at a time." This area also has a replica of the Montreal Canadiens' dressing room as it existed at the old Montreal Forum. The ''Panasonic Hometown Hockey'' section is dedicated to grass roots hockey in North America; it includes exhibits about various leagues and sections on women's and disabled hockey leagues. Special exhibits in the past included an exhibit in 2000 showcasing Gretzky memorabilia.

Interactive displays are featured in the ''NHLPA Be A Player Zone''. At the ''Source For Sports Shoot Out'', visitors take shots using real pucks at a computer simulation of goaltender Ed Belfour. Its counterpart, ''Lay's Shut Out'', has visitors playing goaltender, blocking shots from computer simulations of players Wayne Gretzky and Mark Messier. The ''TSN/RDS Broadcast Zone'' provides a look at how hockey broadcasting works and allows users to record messages that may be displayed on both the Hockey Hall of Fame's website, and the TSN/RDS networks.

While many of the Hall of Fame exhibits are dedicated to the NHL, there is a large section devoted to hockey leagues and players outside North America. On June 29, 1998, the ''World of Hockey Zone'' opened. Sponsored by the Royal Canadian Mint, it is a  area dedicated to international hockey, including World and Olympic competition and contains profiles on all IIHF member Countries.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="cf5b11115e1556763d98e7142fd4a5f7" name="Hhof_be_a_player1" sectnum="3#1">../img/cf5b11115e1556763d98e7142fd4a5f7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>