<document id="1a24a2fbbfbfc8a5cda39493a4405ac4-4.4" name="Hockey_Hall_of_Fame" cat="26">
<text>
Frank J. Selke served as Chairman of the selection committee from 1960 until 1971, when he resigned because of the induction of Harvey "Busher" Jackson. Jackson, known for his off-ice lifestyle, had died in 1966 of liver failure. Selke would not condone the induction and even tried to block it because he considered Jackson a poor role model.''Honoured members: the Hockey Hall of Fame'', p. 91

On March 30, 1993, it was announced that Gil Stein, who at the time was the president of the National Hockey League, would be inducted into the Hall of Fame. There were immediate allegations that he had engineered his election through manipulation of the hall's board of directors. Due to these allegations, NHL commissioner Gary Bettman hired two independent lawyers, Arnold Burns and Yves Fortier, to lead an investigation. They concluded that Stein had "improperly manipulated the process" and "created the false appearance and illusion" that his nomination was the idea of Bruce McNall. They concluded that Stein pressured McNall to nominate him and had refused to withdraw his nomination when asked to do so by Bettman. There was a dispute over McNall's role and Stein was "categorical in stating that the idea was Mr. McNall's." They recommended that Stein's selection be overturned, but it was revealed Stein had decided to turn down the induction before their announcement.

In 1989, Alan Eagleson, a long time executive director of the National Hockey League Players Association, was inducted as a builder. He resigned nine years later from the Hall after pleading guilty to mail fraud and embezzling hundreds of thousands of dollars from the NHL Players Association pension funds.''Honoured members: the Hockey Hall of Fame'', p. 167 His resignation came six days before a vote was scheduled to determine if he should be expelled from the Hall. Originally, the Hall of Fame was not going to become involved in the issue, but was forced to act when dozens of inductees, including Bobby Orr, Ted Lindsay and Brad Park, campaigned for Eagleson's expulsion, even threatening to renounce their membership if he was not removed. He became the first member of a sports hall of fame in North America to resign.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a9f0e519829be051e0092e0565b9114b" name="Hockey_Hall_of_Fame_Toronto_A" sectnum="4.4#1">../img/a9f0e519829be051e0092e0565b9114b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>