<document id="1ad86455a96bfa44915e2eb8ceef82ef-3" name="Triceratops" cat="3">
<text>
''Triceratops'' is the best known genus of the Ceratopsidae, a family of large North American horned dinosaurs. The exact location of ''Triceratops'' among the ceratopsians has been debated over the years. Confusion stemmed mainly from the combination of short, solid frills (similar to that of Centrosaurinae), and the long brow horns (more akin to Ceratopsinae, also known as Chasmosaurinae). In the first overview of horned dinosaurs, R. S. Lull hypothesized two lineages, one of ''Monoclonius'' and ''Centrosaurus'' leading to ''Triceratops'', the other with ''Ceratops'' and ''Torosaurus'', making ''Triceratops'' a centrosaurine as the group is understood today.Hatcher, J. B., Marsh, O. C. and Lull, R. S. (1907) ''The Ceratopsia''. Government Printing Office, Washington, D.C. ISBN 0405127138. Later revisions supported this view, formally describing the first, short-frilled group as Centrosaurinae (including ''Triceratops''), and the second, long-frilled group as Chasmosaurinae.Lambe, L.M. (1915). On ''Eoceratops canadensis'', gen. nov., with remarks on other genera of Cretaceous horned dinosaurs. ''Canada Department of Mines Geological Survey Museum Bulletin'' '''12''':1–49.Lull, R. S. (1933) A revision of the Ceratopsia or horned dinosaurs. ''Memoirs of the Peabody Museum of Natural History'' '''3'''(3):1–175.

In 1949, C. M. Sternberg was the first to question this and favoured instead that ''Triceratops'' was more closely related to ''Arrhinoceratops'' and ''Chasmosaurus'' based on skull and horn features, making ''Triceratops'' a ceratopsine (chasmosaurine of his usage) genus.Sternberg, C. M. (1949). The Edmonton fauna and description of a new ''Triceratops'' from the Upper Edmonton member; phylogeny of the Ceratopsidae. ''National Museum of Canada Bulletin'' '''113''':33–46. However, he was largely ignored with John Ostrom,Ostrom, J. H. (1966). Functional morphology and evolution of the ceratopsian dinosaurs. ''Evolution'' '''20''':220–227. and later David Norman, both placing ''Triceratops'' within Centrosaurinae.

Subsequent discoveries and analyses upheld Sternberg's view on the position of ''Triceratops'', with Lehman defining both subfamilies in 1990 and diagnosing ''Triceratops'' as ceratopsine (chasmosaurine of his usage) on the basis of several morphological features. In fact, it fits well into the ceratopsine subfamily, apart from its one feature of a shortened frill.Lehman, T. M. (1990). The ceratopsian subfamily Chasmosaurinae: sexual dimorphism and systematics. in: Carpenter, K., and Currie, P. J. (eds.). ''Dinosaur Systematics: Perspectives and Approaches'', Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, pp. 211–229. ISBN 0-521-36672-0. Further research by Peter Dodson, including a 1990 cladistic analysisDodson, P., and Currie, P. J. (1990). Neoceratopsia. 593–618. in Weishampel, D. B., Dodson, P., & Osmólska, H. (eds.). ''The Dinosauria'' University of California Press:Berkeley, pp. 593–618. ISBN 0-520-06727-4. and a 1993 study using RFTRA (resistant-fit theta-rho analysis),Dodson, P. (1993).  In: ''American Journal of Science'' '''293''', pp. 200–234. a morphometric technique which systematically measures similarities in skull shape, reinforces ''Triceratops''' placement in the ceratopsine subfamily.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="dc0574aa83c686de8695f888760c30ea" name="Triceratops_BW" sectnum="3#1">../img/dc0574aa83c686de8695f888760c30ea.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>