<document id="1b23df173de2bde33e6c445928329539-3" name="Pierre_Rossier" cat="1">
<text>
Rossier first arrived in Japan in 1859, at a time when early experiments in photography were being conducted in Kyūshū, particularly in Nagasaki. The city was the centre of ''rangaku'', the study of Western science, and it was here that physicians Jan Karel van den Broek and J. L. C. Pompe van Meerdervoort were instrumental in teaching their Japanese students not only medicine but also chemistry and photography.More precisely, it was the Dutch enclave of Deshima within Nagasaki harbour that provided the locale for these studies, with the experiments in photography beginning in the mid-1850s. Similar research began about the same time in the nearby Satsuma han at Kagoshima (Himeno, 18, 20&ndash;21). Neither Van den Broek nor Pompe van Meerdervoort was an experienced photographer, and their attempts to produce photographs were largely failures.Even with the help of the user's manual that accompanied the camera he had imported, it seems that Van den Broek never made a satisfactory photographic image and he decided that only an experienced photographer would be able to teach the use of the camera. Pompe van Meerdervoort was hardly more successful; one result of his experiments was described by Matsumoto Jun as "a meagre black shadow" (Himeno, 21&ndash;22). Nevertheless, in turn they taught wet-collodion process photography to Keisai Yoshio,Keisai was an uncle and teacher of the photographer Uchida Kuichi (Himeno, 24&ndash;25). Furukawa Shumpei, Kawano Teizō, Maeda Genzō, Ueno Hikoma, and Horie Kuwajirō, among others.Himeno, 21&ndash;22.

On his arrival in Japan, Rossier presumably introduced himself as a photographer despatched to Japan by ''Negretti and Zambra'', perhaps thereby inspiring a misconception, for while he remained in the country he was often referred to as an "English" photographer. In Nagasaki, Rossier was assisted in his work by Maeda Genzō, who had been instructed to accompany the "Englishman" and to further learn photography.Matsumoto Jun ordered Maeda to assist Rossier. Yet another link between Matsumoto and photography dates from some point between 1857 and 1859 when he adopted the 13-year-old future photographer Uchida Kuichi (Bennett EJI, 54). With Maeda and other students escorting him around the city, Rossier took photographs of priests, beggars, the audience of a sumo match, the foreign settlement, and the group portrait of Alexander von Siebold and samurai. Rossier believed that Pompe van Meerdervoort's failures in photography were due to a lack of the necessary chemicals and so he provided Maeda with a letter of recommendation to procure photographic apparatus and chemicals from a source in Shanghai. Both Maeda and Furukawa bought lenses, chemicals and albumen paper through Rossier.Himeno, 21&ndash;22. Maeda and Furukawa succeeded in taking a photograph with these materials on 28 October 28 1860, a day still commemorated in Fukuoka where the photograph was taken (Himeno, 22)

At this time, Ueno Hikoma and Horie Kuwajirō also received photographic instruction from Rossier. Apparently Ueno had originally intended to learn not only the practice of photography but also the manufacture of cameras. The encounter with Rossier seems to have convinced Ueno to pursue photography as a career, but he was so overwhelmed by the technology of the camera that he quickly dropped the notion of making one himself. Within a few months, he and Horie had purchased a French camera and chemicals, thereafter launching their independent photographic careers.Himeno, 22. Ueno went on to become one of the most important and successful photographers in nineteenth century Japan.

Although Rossier's time in Japan was brief and the surviving photographic legacy of his sojourn is scant, he nevertheless had a lasting impact on photography in the country.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f22927f86060e28b3169df0dec650364" name="Yokohama_1859" sectnum="3#1">../img/f22927f86060e28b3169df0dec650364.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>