<document id="1b23df173de2bde33e6c445928329539-2" name="Pierre_Rossier" cat="1">
<text>
Rossier was in Hong Kong in 1858, and he soon began taking photographs, mostly in and around Canton (now Guangzhou).Bennett. Worswick places Rossier in China from 1857 to 1859, but does not provide any further information (Worswick, 146). In November 1859 ''Negretti and Zambra'' published a set of fifty of Rossier's views, including stereographs. These received favourable reviews in photographic periodicals of the day. In 1858 or 1859 Rossier travelled to the Philippines where he visited and photographed the Taal Volcano. Rossier was in Japan by 1859, producing photographs first in Nagasaki, then in Kanagawa, Yokohama and Edo (now Tokyo); he was the first professional photographer to arrive in Japan.Yokoe, 167. One of the photographs Rossier took during the summer of 1859, while in Nagasaki, was a portrait of Philipp Franz von Siebold's son Alexander and a group of samurai from the Nabeshima clan.This photograph is in the collection of the Siebold Memorial Museum in Nagasaki (Himeno, 22).

At the end of June 1860, Rossier was in Shanghai, and it is likely that he visited the city in an attempt to gain permission to accompany the Anglo-French military expedition that had already arrived in northern China and thereby fulfill his commission to document the Second Opium War. The British and French military forces were already assembling at Talien Bay and Chefoo, respectively, in June 1860 (Harris, 17) and it is known that Rossier was in Shanghai on 27 June 1860. There is a further possibility that Rossier visited Shanghai in order to procure photographic chemicals (Bennett). If so, he was unsuccessful; both forces had already hired photographers to document the mission. The British forces were accompanied by the photographers Felice Beato and John Papillon, and the French by Antoine Fauchery, Lieutenant-Colonel Du Pin, and possibly also by Louis Legrand.Bennett; Thiriez. Papillon produced images taken between Canton and the Taku Forts but became ill and was evacuated before completing his mission. Photographs of the expedition by Fauchery have not been positively identified, but probably include twenty-four stereographs of the French forces in Canton, Shanghai, Tientsin and Peking. No evidence has been found that either Du Pin or Legrand actually took photographs during the expedition. Thiriez, 6&ndash;7. Although Rossier failed even to embark on the mission he had been hired to document, he remained in East Asia for some time longer.

By October 1860, Rossier had returned to Nagasaki, where he took photographs of the harbour on behalf of the British Consul, George S. Morrison, for which Rossier was paid $70.In a letter dated 13 October 1860, Morrison wrote, "... considering that M. Rossier's time is specifically devoted to other purposes, and that he was occupied with them for several days... as he is not a tradesman here for the sale of photographs,  was not in a position to bargain..." (Bennett). Seventy dollars was a substantial sum; to put it in some perspective, fourteen years later Henry Smith Munroe, an American employee of the Japanese government, was considering buying a complete set of 500 photographs by Uchida Kuichi that cost $250 or three-quarters of Munroe's monthly salary as a well-paid foreign advisor (Dobson, 20; Clark, Fraser, and Osman, 137&ndash;138). Although Rossier's photographs of Japan were advertised by ''Negretti and Zambra'' on at least two occasions in 1860, the firm did not publish them until October or November 1861.In the 28 May 1860 edition of ''The Times'' there appeared an advertisement for a "full coloured" stereograph of "Japanese ladies in full dress" by Rossier. An advertisement in ''The Times'', 3 October 1860, referred to the "expected" arrival of "photographs from Japan &mdash; A case of rare and curious photographs of the scenery of this interesting country, and illustrative of the manners and customs of the Japanese tribes, which have been executed by a special artist sent out for the purpose by the enterprising firm of Negretti and Zambra of London". Bennett speculates that ''Negretti and Zambra'' may have delayed publishing the images because of problems with the quality of the negatives, either because they were damaged in transit or because of Rossier's known difficulties in finding the correct photographic chemicals in Asia (Bennett). Five of Rossier's views of Japan appeared earlier, in George Smith's book, ''Ten Weeks in Japan'', in April 1861, and that July, eight of Rossier's Japan photographs appeared in the form of lithographs in Henry Arthur Tilley's book, ''Japan, the Amoor, and the Pacific''.Bennett PiJ, 49. An 1861 edition of the Illustrated London News included several engravings under the collective title ''Domestic Life in China'', the images having been taken from Rossier's stereographs.Bennett OJP, 119. One of the photographs ''Negretti and Zambra'' had advertised in 1860 became the first commercial photograph taken in Japan to be published, and is the earliest known hand-coloured Japanese photograph.This being the photograph titled "Japanese ladies in full dress" (Bennett PiJ, 47; 49, fig. 45).

Thanks to a number of documents of the time, it is now certain that ''Negretti and Zambra'''s photographs of China and Japan were taken by Rossier, but for many years it was thought that they might have been taken by either Walter B. Woodbury, who also had dealings with ''Negretti and Zambra'' but was based in Batavia (now Jakarta), or Abel Gower, who was an amateur photographer in Japan. Interestingly, the Leiden University photograph collection includes a portrait, allegedly of Gower, signed "P. Rossier", and in 1859 Rossier and Gower shared passage aboard ''HMS Sampson'' from Nagasaki to Edo.Rather than Gower, the portrait sitter is now considered to be John MacDonald, a member of the British Legation (Bennett PiJ, 45; 117, fig. 141).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4b86dfa7d623d96a567738032f907205" name="French_Sailors_at_Canton" sectnum="2#1">../img/4b86dfa7d623d96a567738032f907205.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>