<document id="1b24fac01a79911a6151f9f1462e54a3-2.1" name="The_Great_American_Bash_(2005)" cat="26">
<text>
The first match on the card was between MNM (Johnny Nitro and Joey Mercury) (managed by Melina) and The Legion of Doom (Heidenreich and Road Warrior Animal) for the WWE Tag Team Championship. During the match, Nitro hit Animal with one of the championship belts, but Animal retaliated by lifting Nitro off of the ground and slamming him on the ring mat, a maneuver known as a powerslam. Animal and Heidenreich then performed the doomsday device, executed by one wrestler lifting his opponent atop of his shoulders thus allowing his partner knock him down by jumping off the top rope, on Nitro and got the pin to win the match and capture the title. This began their reign as WWE Tag Team Champions.

The next match was between Booker T (managed by Sharmell) and Christian. Booker T won the match after kicking Christian, who was bent over forward, using his scissor kick. The following match was between Orlando Jordan and Chris Benoit for the WWE United States Championship. During the match, Jordan removed the top turnbuckle pad before Benoit attempted to lift Jordan off of the ground and drive him to the ring mat. Jordan avoided the attack and instead forced Benoit to run into the exposed turnbuckle. Jordan got the pin to win the match and retain the title.

The fourth match was between The Undertaker and Muhammad Hassan (managed by Daivari). During Hassan's entrance, men in masks accompanied him to the ring to represent his Arabic culture. The masked men proceeded to interfered in the match, but Undertaker retaliated and removed all of the masked men from the ring. Midway through the match, Undertaker attempted to lift Hassan upside down to drop his head onto the mat, but Hassan escaped the move and attempted to hit Undertaker with his forearm. The Undertaker countered by lifting Hassan up by the throat and slamming him down to the ring mat, a move known as a chokeslam. Undertaker scored the pinfall on Hassan to win the match.

The next match was between The Mexicools and the Blue World Order in a six-man tag team match. At the match's end, Super Crazy executed a backflip onto Big Stevie Cool from the top ring rope, and Psicosis performed a leg drop. Psicosis proceeded to pin Big Stevie and win the match for his team.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="626a7e08108d75a3f2c9d1a0babaef49" name="Christian20061020" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/626a7e08108d75a3f2c9d1a0babaef49.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>