<document id="1b24fac01a79911a6151f9f1462e54a3-2.2" name="The_Great_American_Bash_(2005)" cat="26">
<text>
The following match was between Rey Mysterio and Eddie Guerrero, where the stipulation was that if Guerrero won the match, he would reveal the secret he has been hiding from the public that neither Mysterio’s nor Guerrero’s families wanted revealed. If Mysterio won, however, Guerrero would not reveal the secret. Guerrero lifted Mysterio onto his shoulders vertically and dropped him in a move known as a suplex to the ring mat, which he did three times. Afterward, Guerrero performed a body splash from the top rope, which he had dubbed the frog splash. Guerrero then tried to score the pinfall, but Mysterio countered by pinning Guerrero to win the match. As a result, Guerrero was not able to reveal the secret.

The seventh match was between Melina and Torrie Wilson (managed by Candice Michelle), who was also the guest referee), in a Bra and Panties match. The only way to win a "Bra and Panties" match is for a wrestler to strip her opponent down to her underwear. At the start of the match, Melina pulled off Wilson's shirt to reveal her bra, but Wilson retaliated and pulled off Melina's shirt. Wilson then lifted Melina to her shoulders and dropped her to the mat, while she attempted to pull off her pants, but Melina countered the attack by pulling Wilson's pants off to win the match. Afterward, Michelle stripped Melina and then removed her own clothes, as well.

The main event was between JBL (managed by Orlando Jordan) and Batista for the World Heavyweight Championship. Jordan interfered by attempting to hit Batista with a folding chair, but Batista grabbed the chair from him. Batista then used the chair to hit Jordan and JBL, and JBL was declared the winner, via disqualification. In WWE, a title cannot be won by disqualification, but only by pinfall or submission (the normal scoring conditions in professional wrestling matches). As a result, Batista retained the title.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d1973e4a8d32db80c0692cddedc958ed" name="Eddie_Guerrero_on_SmackDown_cropped" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/d1973e4a8d32db80c0692cddedc958ed.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>