<document id="1bb208760b92937313e17130e7e0a0a3-4" name="British_anti-invasion_preparations_of_World_War_II" cat="29">
<text>
Other basic defensive measures included the removal of signposts, milestones (some had the carved details obscured with cement) and railway station signs making it more likely that an enemy would become confused. Petrol pumps were removed from service stations near the coast and there were careful preparations for the destruction of those that were left.Evans, 2004, p64. Detailed plans were made for the destruction of anything that might prove useful to the invader such as port facilities, key roads and rolling stock.Churchill, 2005, p156.

In certain areas non-essential citizens were evacuated. In the county of Kent, 40% of the population was relocated; in East Anglia, the figure was 50%.



Perhaps most importantly, the population was told what was expected from them. In June 1940, the Ministry of Information published ''If the Invader Comes, what to do—and how to do it'',Lowry, 2004, p43. it began:



The first instruction given quite emphatically is that, unless ordered to evacuate, "THE ORDER IS 'STAY PUT' " . The roads were not to be blocked by refugees. Further warnings were given not to believe rumours and not to spread them, to be distrustful of orders that might be faked and even to check that an officer giving orders really is British. Further: keep calm and report anything suspicious quickly and accurately; deny useful things to the enemy such as food, fuel, maps or transport; be ready to block roads&mdash;when ordered to do so&mdash;"by felling trees, wiring them together or blocking the roads with cars"; to organise resistance at shops and factories; and, finally:

:"THINK BEFORE YOU ACT. BUT THINK ALWAYS OF YOUR COUNTRY BEFORE YOU THINK OF YOURSELF."

On 13 June 1940 the ringing of church bells was banned; henceforth they would only be rung by the military or the police to warn that an invasion—generally meaning by parachutists—was in progress.Fleming, 1957, p96.

In 1941, in towns and villages invasion committees were formed to cooperate with the military and plan for the worst should their communities be isolated or occupied. The members of committees typically included representatives of the local council, the Air Raid Precautions service, the fire service, the police, the Women’s Voluntary Service and the Home Guard, as well as officers for medicine, sanitation and food. Plans of these committees were kept in secret ''War Books'' although few remain. Detailed inventories of anything useful were kept: vehicles, animals and basic tools, and lists were made of contact details for key personnel. Plans were made for a wide range of emergencies, including improvised mortuaries and places to bury the dead. Instructions to the Invasion Committees stated: "...every citizen will regard it as his duty to hinder and frustrate the enemy and help our own forces by every means that ingenuity can devise and common sense suggest."Consolidated Instructions to Invasion Committees, 1942, p19.

It is clear that more than merely passive resistance was expected&mdash;or at least hoped for&mdash;from the population. Churchill considered the formation of a Home Guard Reserve, given only an armband and basic training on the use of simple weapons such as Molotov cocktails. The reserve would only have been expected to report for duty in an invasion.Churchill, 2005, p582. Later, Churchill wrote how he envisaged the use of the sticky bomb: "We had the picture in mind that devoted soldiers ''or civilians'' would run close up to the tank and even thrust the bomb upon it, though its explosion cost them their lives ."Churchill, 2005, p149. He also later recorded how he intended to use the slogan "You can always take one with you."Churchill, 2005, p246.

When Great Britain went to War on 3 September 1939, the strength of the Metropolitan Police stood at 18,428, which was 900 officers short of full strength. Due to the threat of invasion three reserve groups were mobilised, the first consisted of 2,737 police pensioners who were re-engaged, a second reserve of 5,380 Special Constables serving on a temporary full time basis for the duration of the war, and 18,868 War Reserve Constables employed on the same basis as the Special Constables. On the same day as the Battle of Dunkirk, Scotland Yard issued a memorandum detailing the police use of firearms in wartime. This detailed the planned training for all officers in the use of pistols and revolvers, as it was decided that even though the police was non-combatant, they would provide armed guarding at sites deemed a risk from enemy sabotage, and would assist the British Armed Forces in the event of an invasion. Because of the possibility of the police assisting the armed forces, firearms and ammunition supplied to divisions were increased. On 1 June 1940, 3,500 Canadian Ross Rifles, which had last seen service in 1916, 72,384 rounds of .303 ammunition were received from the military and were distributed among divisions. Thames division had the smallest rifle allocation with 61, and "S" Division the largest with 190. Fifty rifles were also issued to the London Fire Brigade, and Port of London Authority Police.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c386db0aef593f074043a9bcd21efed2" name="Spot_on_sight_chart_No_1" sectnum="4#1">../img/c386db0aef593f074043a9bcd21efed2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>