<document id="1bc99cb2f4153c2d0d8025ee5575b2a0-10" name="Bangalore" cat="11">
<text>
Until the early 19th century, education in Bangalore was mainly run by religious leaders and restricted to students of that religion.Hayavadana Rao (1929), p494 The western system of education was introduced during the rule of Mummadi Krishnaraja Wodeyar, when two schools were established in Bangalore. Subsequently, Wesleyan Mission established a school in 1851 and the Bangalore High School which was started by the Government in 1858.Hayavadana Rao (1929), p497

In post-independent India, schools for young children are mainly based on the kindergarten form of education. Primary and secondary education in Bangalore is offered by various schools which are affiliated to one of the boards of education, such as the Secondary School Leaving Certificate (SSLC), ICSE and CBSE. Schools in Bangalore are either government run or are private (both aided and un-aided by the government). After completing their secondary education, students typically attend Pre Univiersity (PUC) in one of three ''streams'' – Arts, Commerce or Science.  Upon completing the required coursework, students enroll in general or professional degrees in univerities. The Bangalore University,established in 1964, provides affiliation to about 500 colleges, with a total student enrollment exceeding 300,000. The university has two campuses within Bangalore – Jnanabharathi and Central College.

Indian Institute of Science, which was established in 1909 in Bangalore, is the premier institute for scientific research and study in India. Nationally renouned professional institutes such as the National Law School of India University (NLSIU), the Indian Institute of Management, Bangalore (IIM-B) and the Indian Statistical Institute are located in Bangalore. The city is also home to the premier mental health institution in India National Institute of Mental Health and Neuro Sciences (NIMHANS).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f69a68194072520f1957b512b33763a3" name="Bangalore_College" sectnum="10#1">../img/f69a68194072520f1957b512b33763a3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>