<document id="1bc99cb2f4153c2d0d8025ee5575b2a0-7" name="Bangalore" cat="11">
<text>
With an estimated population of 5.3 million in 2009, Bangalore is the third most populous city in India and the 28th most populous city in the world. Bangalore was the fastest-growing Indian metropolis after New Delhi between 1991–2001, with a growth rate of 38% during the decade. Residents of Bangalore are referred to as ''Bangaloreans'' in English or ''Bengaloorinavaru'' in Kannada, whose native speakers form about 39% of the city's population.Ramachandran, Sudha. . Asia Times. 2 April 2008.. Yahoo! News. 11 February 2008.

The cosmopolitan nature of the city has resulted in the migration of people from other states to Bangalore.. The Hindu. 2006. The Hindu Group. 23 July 2004. Scheduled Castes and Tribes account for 14.3% of the city's population. Apart from Kannada and English, other major languages spoken in the city are Tamil, Telugu and Hindi.. According to the 2001 census of India, 79.37% of Bangalore's population is Hindu, roughly the same as the national average.. censusindiamaps.net. 2006. Muslims comprise 13.37% of the population, which again is roughly the same as the national average, while Christians and Jains account for 5.79% and 1.05% of the population, respectively, double that of their national averages. Anglo-Indians also form a substantial group within the city. Women make up 47.5% of Bangalore's population. Bangalore has the second highest literacy rate (83%) for an Indian metropolis, after Mumbai. Roughly 10% of Bangalore's population lives in slums Census of India, 2001. 2006. Government of India — a relatively low proportion when compared to other cities in the developing world such as Mumbai (42%) and Nairobi (60%).Warah, Rasna. . The EastAfrican. 2006. National Media Group Ltd. 6 October 2003 The 2004 National Crime Records Bureau statistics indicate that Bangalore accounts for 9.2% of the total crimes reported from 35 major cities in India.. National Crime Records Bureau. 2006. Government of India. 2004.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="668628229d5e22bf4558189ad6bdb0ca" name="Bangalore_Nandi_Temple" sectnum="7#1">../img/668628229d5e22bf4558189ad6bdb0ca.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>