<document id="1bfbdda26895557e3b76ef417d88fcb4-1.2" name="Jabba_the_Hutt" cat="19">
<text>
The first appearances of Jabba the Hutt in Star Wars Expanded Universe literature was in Marvel Comics' adaptations of ''A New Hope''. In ''Six Against the Galaxy'' (1977) by Roy Thomas and ''What Ever Happened to Jabba the Hut?'' (1979) and ''In Mortal Combat'' (1980), both by Archie Goodwin, Jabba the Hutt (originally spelled ''Hut'') appeared as a tall humanoid with a walrus-like face, a topknot, and a bright uniform.

While awaiting the sequel to ''Star Wars'', Marvel kept the monthly comic going with their own stories, one of which includes Jabba tracking Han Solo and Chewbacca down to an old hideaway they use for smuggling. However, circumstances  force Jabba to lift the bounty on Solo and Chewbacca, thus enabling them to return to Tatooine for an adventure with Luke Skywalker&mdash;who has returned to the planet in order to recruit more pilots for the Rebel Alliance. In the course of another adventure, Solo kills the space pirate Crimson Jack and busts up his operation, which Jabba bankrolled. Jabba thus renews the reward for Solo's head and Solo later kills a bounty hunter who tells him why he is hunted once more. He and Chewbacca return to the rebels. (Solo mentions an incident with a "bounty hunter we ran into on Ord Mantell" in the opening scenes of ''The Empire Strikes Back''.)

The Marvel artists based Jabba on a character later named Mosep Binneed, an alien visible only briefly in the Mos Eisley cantina scene of ''A New Hope''.Roy Thomas, ''Marvel Star Wars #2: Six Against the Galaxy'' (Marvel, August 1977).Archie Goodwin, ''Marvel Star Wars #28: What Ever Happened to Jabba the Hut?'' (Marvel, October 1979).Archie Goodwin, ''Marvel Star Wars #37: In Mortal Combat'' (Marvel, July 1980).Jabba the Hutt, Behind the Scenes, ; last accessed July 3, 2006. The 1977 mass market paperback novelization of Lucas's ''Star Wars'' script describes Jabba as a "great mobile tub of muscle and suet topped by a shaggy scarred skull", but gives no further detail as to the character's physical appearance or species.George Lucas, ''Star Wars: From the Adventures of Luke Skywalker'' (paperback; New York: Del Rey, 1977), p. 107, ISBN 0-345-26079-1.

Later Expanded Universe novels and comics adopt the character's image as seen in the film. They also elaborate on his background prior to the events of the ''Star Wars'' films. For example, ''Zorba the Hutt's Revenge'' (1992), a young adult novel by Paul and Hollace Davids, reveals that Jabba's father is a powerful crime lord named Zorba the Hutt and that Jabba was born 596 years before the events of ''A New Hope'', making him around 600 years old at the time of his death in ''Return of the Jedi''.Paul Davids and Hollace Davids, ''Zorba the Hutt's Revenge'' (New York: Bantam Spectra, 1992), ISBN 0-553-15889-9. Ann C. Crispin's novel ''The Hutt Gambit'' (1997) explains how Jabba the Hutt and Han Solo become business associates and portrays the events that lead to a bounty being placed on Han's head.A. C. Crispin, ''The Hutt Gambit'' (New York: Bantam Spectra, 1997), ISBN 0-553-57416-7. Other Expanded Universe stories—especially the anthology of Dark Horse comics by Jim Woodring titled ''Jabba the Hutt: The Art of the Deal'' (1998)—likewise detail Jabba the Hutt's rise to the head of the Desilijic clan, his role in the criminal underworld of the ''Star Wars'' universe, and the establishment of his crime syndicate on Tatooine in the ''Star Wars'' galaxy's Outer Rim Territories.Jim Woodring, ''Jabba the Hutt: The Art of the Deal'' (Dark Horse Comics, 1998), ISBN 1-56971-310-3.

''Tales From Jabba's Palace'' (1996), a collection of short stories edited by science fiction author Kevin J. Anderson, pieces together the lives of Jabba the Hutt's various minions in his palace and their relationship to him during the last days of his life. The stories reveal that few of the Hutt's servants are loyal to him and most are in fact plotting to have him assassinated. When Jabba the Hutt is killed in ''Return of the Jedi'', his surviving former courtiers join forces with his rivals on Tatooine and his family on the Hutt homeworld Nal Hutta make claims to his palace, fortune, and criminal empire.Kevin J. Anderson, ed., ''Tales from Jabba's Palace'' (paperback; New York: Bantam Spectra, 1996), ISBN 0-553-56815-9. Timothy Zahn's novel ''Heir to the Empire'' (1991) reveals that a smuggler named Talon Karrde eventually replaces Jabba as the "big fish in the pond", and moves the headquarters of the Hutt's criminal empire off Tatooine.Timothy Zahn, ''Heir to the Empire'' (paperback; New York: Bantam Spectra, 1991), p. 27, ISBN 0-553-29612-4.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="93ce9e7a0319e459331db6bfa150b7ef" name="JabbaHut" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/93ce9e7a0319e459331db6bfa150b7ef.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>