<document id="1bfbdda26895557e3b76ef417d88fcb4-4" name="Jabba_the_Hutt" cat="19">
<text>
With the premiere of ''Return of Jedi'' in 1983 and the accompanying merchandising campaign, Jabba the Hutt became an icon in American popular culture. The character was produced and marketed as a series of action figure play sets by Kenner/Hasbro from 1983 to 2004.A complete Jabba the Hutt play sets sold by Kenner in 1983 was valued at $70 in 2003 by collectors if in mint condition and with original packaging. See Geoffrey T Carlton, ''Star Wars Super Collector's Wish Book: Identification & Values'' (Paducah, Ky.: Collector Books, 2003), p. 13, ISBN 1574323342. In the 1990s, Jabba the Hutt became the protagonist in his own comic book series collectively titled ''Jabba the Hutt: The Art of the Deal''.Richard von Busack, "Jabba the Hutt slimes her way through a new graphic novel," review of ''Jabba the Hutt: The Art of the Deal'' at .

Jabba's role in popular culture extends beyond the ''Star Wars'' universe and its fans. In Mel Brooks' ''Star Wars'' spoof ''Spaceballs'' (1987), Jabba the Hutt is parodied as the character Pizza the Hutt, a cheesy blob shaped like a slice of pizza whose name is a double pun on Jabba the Hutt and the restaurant franchise Pizza Hut. Like Jabba, Pizza the Hutt is a loan shark and mobster. The character meets his demise at the end of ''Spaceballs'' when he becomes "locked in his car and  himself to death."''Spaceballs'', Dr. Mel Brooks (MGM, 1987). The Smithsonian Institution's National Air and Space Museum in Washington, D.C., included a display on Jabba the Hutt in the temporary exhibition ''Star Wars: The Magic of Myth'', which closed in 1999. Jabba's display was called "The Hero's Return," referencing Luke Skywalker's journey toward becoming a Jedi."The Hero's Return", ''Star Wars: The Myth of Magic'' exhibition at . In Dan Brown's first novel Digital Fortress, an NSA technician is affectionately nicknamed Jabba the Hutt.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="78a9c0c12561d15a40ce3146fd344436" name="JabbatheHuttPlayset" sectnum="4#1">../img/78a9c0c12561d15a40ce3146fd344436.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>