<document id="1bfbdda26895557e3b76ef417d88fcb4-4.6" name="Jabba_the_Hutt" cat="19">
<text>
Since the release of ''Return of the Jedi'', the name ''Jabba the Hutt'' has become synonymous in American mass media with repulsive obesity and corruption. The name is frequently utilized as a literary device&mdash;either as a simile or metaphor&mdash;to illustrate character flaws. For example, in ''Under the Duvet'' (2001), Marian Keyes references a problem with gluttony when she writes, "wheel out the birthday cake, I feel a Jabba the Hutt moment coming on."Marian Keyes, ''Under the Duvet: Shoes, Reviews, Having the Blues, Builders, Babies, Families and Other Calamities'' (New York: HarperCollins, 2001), p. 199, ISBN 0060562080. Likewise, in the novel ''Steps and Exes: A Novel of Family'' (2000), Laura Kalpakian uses Jabba the Hutt to emphasize the weight of a character's father: "The girls used to call Janice's parents Jabba the Hutt and the Wookiee . But then Jabba (Janice's father) died, and it didn't seem right to speak of the dead on those terms."Laura Kalpakian, ''Steps and Exes: A Novel of Family'' (New York: HarperCollins, 2000), p. 58, ISBN 0380806592.

In his book of humor and popular culture, ''The Dharma of Star Wars'' (2005), writer Matthew Bortolin attempts to show similarities between Buddhist teachings and aspects of ''Star Wars'' fiction. Bartolin insists that if a person makes decisions that Jabba the Hutt would make, then that person is not practicing the proper spiritual concept of dharma. Bortolin's book reinforces the idea that Jabba's name is synonymous with negativity:One way to see if we are practicing right livelihood is to compare our trade with that of Jabba the Hutt. Jabba has his fat, stubby fingers in many of the pots that led to the dark side. He dealt largely in illegal "spice" trade—an illicit drug in the Star Wars galaxy. He also transacts business in the slave trade. He has many slaves himself, and some he fed to the Rancor, a creature he kept caged and tormented in his dungeon. Jabba uses deception and violence to maintain his position.Matthew Bortolin, ''The Dharma of Star Wars'' (Somerville, Mass.: Wisdom Publications, 2005), p. 139, ISBN 0861714970.

Outside literature, the character's name has become an insulting term of disparagement. To say that someone "looks like Jabba the Hutt" is commonly understood as a slur to impugn that person's weight and/or appearance.For example, see "Fat Wars: The Obesity Empire Strikes Back" at . The term is often employed by the media as an attack on prominent figures. For instance, actress and comedian Roseanne endured what W. C. Goodman called "vitriolic attacks based on her weight" at the hands of ''The New York Observer'' columnist Michael Thomas who often compared her with "''Star Wars'' blob monster" Jabba the Hutt.W. C. Goodman, ''The Invisible Woman: Confronting Weight Prejudice in America'' (Carlsbad Calif.: Gürze Books, 1995), p. 57, ISBN 0936077107. In an episode of the animated television series ''South Park'' titled "Starvin' Marvin in Space" that aired in 1999, Christian Children's Fund spokeswoman Sally Struthers is portrayed as the Hutt and accused of gorging herself on food relief meant for starving Ethiopians."Starvin' Marvin in Space", Episode 311, ''South Park'', 17 November 1999 (DVD, Paramount, 2003).  Another reference appears in the Family Guy episode He's Too Sexy for His Fat when Peter mentions his husky ancestor Jabba the Griffin.  Movie Connections at the  

In another sense of the term, Jabba the Hutt has come to represent greed and anarchy, especially in the business world.Koenraad Kuiper, "Star Wars: An Imperial Myth," ''Journal of Popular Culture'' 21.4 (Spring 1988): p. 78. For instance, Michael Jordan biographer Mitchell Krugel uses the term to disparage Chicago Bulls's general manager Jerry Krause after Krause made a comment about Jordan and other players' multi-million dollar contracts: "Krause added to his Jabba the Hutt image during the media gathering that preceded the opening of camp when he answered a question about the prospect of rebuilding the Bulls without Phil or Michael in the imminent future by saying, 'Organizations win championships. Players and coaches are parts of organizations'."Mitchell Krugel, ''One Last Shot: The Story of Michael Jordan's Comeback'' (New York: St. Martin's Press, 2003), p. 55, ISBN 0312992238.

Jabba the Hutt has likewise become a popular means of caricature in American politics. For example, opponents of California Democratic legislator Jackie Goldberg commonly depict the politician as the ''Star Wars'' character. The ''Los Angeles Daily News'' has caricatured her in cartoons as a grotesquely overweight Jabba the Hutt-like figure and the ''New Times LA'' referred to Goldberg as "a human Jabba the Hutt who consumes the good while producing the bad."Patrick Mallon, ''California Dictatorship'' (Philadelphia: Xlibris, 2004), p. 235, ISBN 1413467970. William G. Ouchi uses the term to describe what he sees as the inefficient bureaucracy of the public school system: "With all of these unnecessary layers of organizational fat, school districts have come to resemble Jabba the Hutt—the pirate leader in ''Star Wars''."William G. Ouchi, ''Making Schools Work: A Revolutionary Plan to Get Your Children the Education They Need'' (New York: Simon and Schuster, 2003), p. 96, ISBN 0743246306.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fda4b0ce8abcff293bf2d24b4abcc41d" name="311_sallys" sectnum="4.6#1">../img/fda4b0ce8abcff293bf2d24b4abcc41d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>