<document id="1bfbdda26895557e3b76ef417d88fcb4-3.3" name="Jabba_the_Hutt" cat="19">
<text>
The original script to ''A New Hope'' describes Jabba as a "fat, slug-like creature with eyes on extended feelers and a huge ugly mouth", but Lucas stated in an interview that the initial character he had in mind was much furrier and resembled a Wookiee. When filming the scene between Han Solo and Jabba in 1976, Lucas employed Northern Irish actor Declan Mulholland to play the stand-in and read Jabba the Hutt's lines wearing a shaggy brown suit. Lucas planned to replace Mulholland in post-production with a stop-motion creature. The scene was meant to connect ''A New Hope'' to ''Return of the Jedi'' and explain why Han Solo was imprisoned at the end of ''The Empire Strikes Back''.George Lucas interview, ''Star Wars Episode IV: A New Hope'', Special Edition (VHS, 20th Century Fox, 1997). Nevertheless, Lucas decided to leave the scene out of the final film on account of budget and time constraints and because he felt that it did not enhance the film's plot.George Lucas commentary, ''Star Wars Episode IV: A New Hope'', Special Edition, dir. George Lucas, (DVD, 20th Century Fox, 2004). The scene remained in the novelization, comic book, and radio adaptations of the film.


Lucas revisited the scene in the 1997 Special Edition release of ''A New Hope'', restoring the sequence and replacing Mulholland with a CGI version of Jabba the Hutt and the English dialogue with Huttese, a fictional language created by sound designer Ben Burtt. Joseph Letteri, the visual effects supervisor for the Special Edition, explained that the ultimate goal of the revised scene was to make it look as if Jabba the Hutt was actually on the set talking to and acting with Harrison Ford and that the crew had merely photographed it. Letteri stated that the new scene consisted of five shots that took over a year to complete.Joseph Letteri interview, ''Star Wars Episode IV: A New Hope'', Special Edition (VHS, 20th Century Fox, 1997)."''A New Hope'': Special Edition — What has changed?: Jabba the Hutt", January 15, 1997, at ; last accessed July 3, 2006. The scene was polished further for the 2004 release on DVD, improving Jabba's appearance with advancements in CGI techniques, although neither release looks exactly like the original Jabba the Hutt puppet."Star Wars: The Changes — Part One" at ; last accessed July 3, 2006.

At one point of the original scene, Ford walks behind Mulholland. This became a problem when adding the CGI Jabba, since he had a tail that happened to be in the way. Eventually, this problem was solved by having Han stepping on Jabba's tail, causing the Hutt to react with a yelp of pain.

Lucas confesses that some people were upset about the CGI Jabba's appearance, most complaining that the character (and others like it) "looked completely fake". Lucas dismisses this, stating that whether a character is portrayed as a puppet or as CGI, it will always be "fake" since the character is not real. He says he sees no difference between a puppet made of latex and one generated by a computer.George Lucas commentary, ''Star Wars Episode VI: Return of the Jedi'', Special Edition, dir. Richard Marquand (DVD, 20th Century Fox, 2004). The CGI character performed actions that the puppet could not, such as walking. Jabba's film appearance in ''The Phantom Menace'' was as a CGI based on the character from ''A New Hope''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0ef09f0f895e995f6c6a2e03ff283f29" name="FordandMulholland" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/0ef09f0f895e995f6c6a2e03ff283f29.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>