<document id="1bfbdda26895557e3b76ef417d88fcb4-3.5" name="Jabba_the_Hutt" cat="19">
<text>
Designed by visual effects artist Phil Tippett,Biography of Phil Tippett at ; last accessed July 3, 2006. Jabba the Hutt was inspired by the anatomy of several animal species. His body structure and reproductive processes were based on annelid worms, hairless animals that have no skeleton and are hermaphroditic. Jabba's head was modeled after that of a snake, complete with bulbous, slit-pupilled eyes and a mouth that opens wide enough to swallow large prey. His skin was given moist, amphibian qualities. Jabba's design would come to represent almost all members of the Hutt species in subsequent ''Star Wars'' fiction.

In ''Return of the Jedi'', Jabba is portrayed by a one-ton puppet that took three months and half a million dollars to construct. While filming the movie, the puppet had its own makeup artist. The puppet required three puppeteers to operate, making it one of the largest ever used in a motion picture. Stuart Freeborn designed the puppet, while John Coppinger sculpted its latex, clay, and foam pieces. Puppeteers included David Alan Barclay, Toby Philpott, and Mike Edmonds, who were members of Jim Henson's Muppet group. Barclay operated the right arm and mouth and read the character's English dialogue, while Philpott controlled the left arm, head, and tongue. Edmonds, the shortest of the three men (he also played the Ewok Logray in later scenes) was responsible for the movement of Jabba's tail. The eyes and facial expressions were operated by radio control.


Lucas voiced displeasure in the puppet's appearance and immobility, complaining that the puppet had to be moved around the set to film different scenes. In the DVD commentary to the Special Edition of ''Return of the Jedi'', Lucas notes that if the technology had been available in 1983, Jabba the Hutt would have been a CGI character similar to the one that appears in the Special Edition scene of ''A New Hope''.

Jabba the Hutt only speaks Huttese on film, but his lines are subtitled in English. His voice and Huttese-language dialogue were performed by voice actor Larry Ward, whose work is not listed in the end credits.Larry Ward at the ; last accessed July 3, 2006. A heavy, booming quality was given to Ward's voice by pitching it an octave lower than normal and processing it through a subharmonic generator.Tomlinson Holman, ''Sound for Film and Television'' (Burlington, Mass.: Focal Press, 2002), p. 11, ISBN 0-240-80453-8. A soundtrack was recorded to accompany the movement of the puppet's limbs and mouth. The sound effects were created by a hand running through a bowl of cheese casserole and a muddy towel scraping along the inside of a garbage can.Ben Burtt commentary, ''Star Wars Episode VI: Return of the Jedi'', Special Edition, dir. Richard Marquand (DVD, 20th Century Fox, 2004).

Jabba the Hutt's musical theme throughout the film, composed by John Williams, is played on a tuba. One reviewer of ''Return of the Jedi'''s soundtrack comments, "Among the new thematic ideas  Jabba the Hutt's cute tuba piece (playing along the politically incorrect lines of tubas representing fatness) ...."Review of ''Return of the Jedi'' soundtrack by ; last accessed July 3, 2006.  The theme is very similar to one Williams wrote for a heavyset character in ''Fitzwilly'' (1967), though the theme does not appear on that film's soundtrack album. Williams later turned the theme into a symphonic piece performed by the Boston Pops Orchestra featuring a tuba solo by Chester Schmitz. The role of the piece in film and popular culture has become a focus of study by musicologists such as Gerald Sloan, who says Williams' piece "blends the monstrous and the lyrical."Gerald Sloan, "Yuba Meets Jabba: The Expanding Role of Tuba in Film Music", ''TUBA Journal'', quoted in "Evening The Score: UA Professor Explores Tuba Music In Film", June 27, 2000, at ; last accessed July 3, 2006.

According to film historian Laurent Bouzereau, Jabba the Hutt's death in ''Return of the Jedi'' was suggested by script writer Lawrence Kasdan. Lucas decided Leia should strangle him with her slave chain. He was inspired by a scene from ''The Godfather'' (1972) where an obese character named Luca Brasi (Lenny Montana) is garroted by an assassin.Bourezeau, ''Annoted Screenplays'', p. 259.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="409ab872b9284d5ac21eeb4b71ca1b58" name="In_jabba" sectnum="3.5#1">../img/409ab872b9284d5ac21eeb4b71ca1b58.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>