<document id="1c174cc1abdbf7e474cce05a59465c2d-2.2" name="Abbas_Kiarostami" cat="19">
<text>
In the early 1980s, Kiarostami directed several short films including ''Dental Hygiene'' (1980), ''Orderly or Disorderly'' (1981), and ''The Chorus'' (1982). In 1983, he directed ''Fellow Citizen'', but it was not until 1987 that Abbas began to gain recognition outside of Iran with the release of ''Where Is the Friend's Home?''. 


''Where Is the Friend's Home?'' tells a deceptively simple account of a conscientious eight-year-old schoolboy's quest to return his friend's notebook in a neighboring village failing which his friend will be expelled from school. The traditional beliefs of Iranian rural people were depicted throughout the movie. The film has been noted for its poetic use of the Iranian rural landscape and its earnest realism, both important elements of Kiarostami's work. Kiarostami also made the film from a child's point of view, without the condescending tone common to many films about children.

''Where Is the Friend's Home?'', ''And Life Goes On'' (1992) (also known as ''Life and Nothing More''), and ''Through the Olive Trees'' (1994) are described by critics as the ''Koker trilogy'', because all three films feature the village of Koker in northern Iran. The films are based around the 1990 earthquake disaster in which 50,000 people lost their lives; Kiarostami uses the themes of life, death, change, and continuity to connect the films. The trilogy went on to be become successful in France in the 1990s and other countries such as the Netherlands, Sweden, Germany and Finland. However, Kiarostami does not consider the 3 films as part of a trilogy, suggesting instead that the last two titles plus ''Taste of Cherry'' (1997) comprise a trilogy, given their common theme — the preciousness of life. In 1987, Kiarostami was involved in the screenwriting of ''The Key'', which he edited but did not direct. In 1989, he released ''Homework''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b65d7548ae915ed328fbae9301a4ea1b" name="Where_is_the_friends_home" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/b65d7548ae915ed328fbae9301a4ea1b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>