<document id="1c174cc1abdbf7e474cce05a59465c2d-3.8" name="Abbas_Kiarostami" cat="19">
<text>
Kiarostami's style is notable for the use of panoramic long shots, such as in the closing sequences of ''Life and Nothing More'' and''Through the Olive Trees'', where the audience is intentionally distanced physically from the characters in order to stimulate reflection on their fate. ''Taste of Cherry'' is punctuated throughout by shots of this kind, including distant overhead shots of the suicidal Badii's car moving across the hills, usually while he is conversing with a passenger. However, the visual distancing techniques stand in juxtaposition to the sound of the dialog, which always remains in the foreground. Like the coexistence of a private and public space, or the frequent framing of landscapes through car windows, this fusion of distance with proximity can be seen as a way of generating suspense in the most mundane of moments.

This relationship between distance and intimacy, between imagery and sound, is also present in the opening sequence to ''The Wind Will Carry Us''. Michael J. Anderson has argued that such a thematic application of this central concept of ''presence without presence'', through using such techniques, and by often referring to characters which the viewer does not see and sometimes not hear directly affects the nature and concept of space in the geographical framework in which the world is portrayed. Kiarostami's use of sound and imagery conveys a world beyond what is directly visible and/or audible, which Anderson believes emphasizes the interconnectedness and shrinking of time and space in the modern world of telecommunications.

Other commentators such as film critic Ben Zipper believe that Kiarostami’s work as a landscape artist is evident in his compositional distant shots of the dry hills throughout a number of his films directly impacting on his construction on the rural landscapes within his films.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ef33583483a82b363af3a3306ef268a8" name="Life_and_nothing_more" sectnum="3.8#1">../img/ef33583483a82b363af3a3306ef268a8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>