<document id="1c5d6ec95f8d0b67318281364337c1fc-5.6.2" name="Bhumibol_Adulyadej" cat="25">
<text>
In the evening of 19 September, the Thai military overthrew the Thaksin government and seized control of Bangkok in a bloodless coup. The junta, led by the Sonthi Boonyaratglin, Commander of the Army,  called itself the Council for Democratic Reform under the Constitutional Monarchy, accused the deposed prime minister and his regime of many crimes, including lèse majesté, and pledged its loyalty to Bhumibol.  Martial law was declared, the Constitution repealed and the October elections cancelled. Hundreds of Bangkokians came out to flock around the coup makers' stationed forces. Protests were banned and protesters were arrested.  On 20 September, Bhumibol endorsed the coup, and ordered civil servants to take orders from Sonthi.

The King's role in the coup was the subject of much speculation among Thai analysts and the international media.  The King had an audience with Privy Council President Prem Tinsulanonda at the same time as the First Special Forces were ordered mobilised.  Anti-coup protesters claimed that Prem was a key mastermind of the coup, although the military claimed otherwise and banned any discussion of the topic.  In a BBC interview, Thitinan Pongsudhirak of Chulalongkorn University noted, "This coup was nothing short of Thaksin versus the King...  He is widely seen as having implicitly endorsed the coup."  In the same interview, social critic Sulak Sivaraksa claimed, "Without his involvement, the coup would have been impossible."  Sulak added that the King is "very skillful. He never becomes obviously involved. If this coup goes wrong, Sonthi will get the blame, but whatever happens, the King will only get praise."  On Saturday 23 September 2006, the junta warned they would "urgently retaliate against foreign reporters whose coverage has been deemed insulting to the monarchy."  The President of Bhumibol's Privy Council, General Prem Tinsulanonda, supported the coup.  The junta later appointed Privy Council member General Surayud Chulanont as Prime Minister.

On 20 April 2009, Thaksin claimed in an interview with the Financial Times that King Bhumibol had been briefed by Privy Councillors Prem Tinsulanonda and Surayud Chulanont about their plans to stage the 2006 coup.  He claimed that General Panlop Pinmanee, a leader of the People's Alliance for Democracy, had told him of the briefing.The Malaysian Insider, , 1 September 2008Financial Times, , also available at  and  page, 20 April 2009  The Thai embassy in London denied Thaksin's claims.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3b4ffc53eb12f6bfd4fff453061e896d" name="BKK24090611" sectnum="5.6.2#1">../img/3b4ffc53eb12f6bfd4fff453061e896d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>