<document id="1c5d6ec95f8d0b67318281364337c1fc-6" name="Bhumibol_Adulyadej" cat="25">
<text>
:''For a historical perspective on how Bhumibol's constitutional powers have changed over time, see the Constitutions of Thailand article''

Bhumibol retains enormous powers, partly because of his immense popularity and partly because his powers  - although clearly defined in the Thai Constitution  - are often subject to conflicting interpretations.  This was highlighted by the controversy surrounding the appointment of Jaruvan Maintaka as Auditor-General. Jaruvavn had been appointed by The State Audit Commission. However, the Constitutional Court ruled in July 2004 that her appointment was unconstitutional. Jaruvan refused to vacate her office without an explicit order from Bhumibol, on the grounds that she had previously been royally approved. When the Senate elected a replacement for Jaruvan, Bhumibol refused to approve him. The Senate declined to vote to override Bhumibol's veto. Finally in February 2006 the Audit Commission reinstated Jaruvan when it became clear from a memo from the Office of the King's Principal Private Secretary that King Bhumibol supported her appointment.-->

Bhumibol has vetoed legislation very rarely. In 1976, when the Parliament voted 149-19 to extend democratic elections down to district levels, Bhumibol refused to sign the law.  The Parliament refused to vote to overturn the King's veto.  In 1954, Bhumibol vetoed parliamentary-approved land reform legislation twice before consenting to sign it.  The law limited the maximum land an individual could hold to 50 rai (20 acres), at a time when the Crown Property Bureau was the Kingdom's largest land-owner. The law was repealed after General Sarit overthrew the elected government in a coup.

Bhumibol's popularity was demonstrated following the 2003 Phnom Penh riots in Cambodia, when hundreds of Thai protesters, enraged by the burning of the Thai embassy in Phnom Penh, gathered outside the Cambodian embassy in Bangkok. The situation was resolved peacefully when Police General Sant Sarutanonda told the crowd that he had received a call from royal secretary Arsa Sarasin conveying Bhumibol's request for calm. The crowd dispersed.

Bhumibol has the constitutional prerogative to pardon criminals, although there are several criteria for receiving a pardon, including age and remaining sentence.  The 2006 pardoning of several convicted paedophiles, including an Australian rapist and child pornographer, caused controversy.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="10462df2efb0cdcccf252c322837770e" name="King_bhumibol_monument" sectnum="6#1">../img/10462df2efb0cdcccf252c322837770e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>