<document id="1c74b7c7caa5527dca582f4e84cdd770-4.2" name="Battle_of_Dyrrhachium_(1081)" cat="29">
<text>
In the meantime, the Byzantine right and centre had been engaging in skirmishes with the Normans opposite them. However, with the collapse of the Norman right, the knights were in danger of being outflanked. At this point, the Varangians (mainly Anglo-Saxons who had left England after the Norman Conquest) joined in the pursuit of the Norman right. With their massive battle axes, the Varangians attacked the Norman knights, who were driven away after their horses panicked. The Varangians soon became separated from the main force and exhausted so they were in no position to resist an assault. Guiscard sent a strong force of spearmen and crossbowmen against the Varangian flank and inflicted heavy casualties on them. The few remaining Varangians fled into the church of the Archangel Michael. The Normans immediately set the church on fire, and all Varangians perished in the blaze.John Haldon, ''Byzantine Wars'', 135* Anna Comnena, ''The Alexiad'', 4.6* Norwich, ''Byzantium: Decline and Fall'', p. 19.* Holmes, ''The World Atlas of Warfare: Military Innovations That Changed the Course of History'', p. 33.

Meanwhile, George Palaeologus sortied out of Dyrrhachium, but failed to save the situation. Worse, Alexius's vassal, King Constantine Bodin of Duklja, betrayed him. The Turks who had been lent to him by the Seljuk Sultan Suleyman I followed Constantine's example and deserted.Norwich, ''Byzantium: Decline and Fall'', p. 20.* Warren Treadgold, ''A History of Byzantine State and Society'', p. 614.

Deprived of his left wing (still in pursuit of the Norman right) Alexius was exposed in the centre. Guiscard sent his heavy cavalry against the Byzantine centre. They first routed the Byzantine skirmishers before breaking into small detachments and smashing into various points of the Byzantine line. This charge broke the Byzantine lines and caused them to rout. The imperial camp, which had been left unguarded, fell to the Normans.John Haldon, ''Byzantine Wars'', p. 135.* Anna Comnena, ''The Alexiad'', 4.7

Alexius and his guards resisted as long as they could before retreating. As they retreated, Alexius was separated from his guard and was attacked by Norman soldiers. While escaping he was wounded in his forehead and lost a lot of blood, but eventually made it back to Ohrid, where he regrouped his army.John Haldon, ''Byzantine Wars'', p. 135.* Anna Comnena, ''The Alexiad'', 4.7* Norwich, ''Byzantium: Decline and Fall'', p. 20.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e9bbb08d233642f62c5b50f2f90e588a" name="Skylitzis_Chronicle_VARANGIAN_GUARD" sectnum="4.2#1">../img/e9bbb08d233642f62c5b50f2f90e588a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>