<document id="1d77d915e1e28f06309d402ba1ec7e87-6" name="Political_history_of_medieval_Karnataka" cat="14">
<text>
The Vijayanagara Empire quickly rose to imperial status as early as the late 14th century. During the reign of Bukka Raya I, the island of Lanka paid tributes and ambassadors were exchanged with the Ming Dynasty of China.Sastri (1955), p241Chopra (2003), p28, part2Indicated by records of the Ming dynasty (Kamath 2001, p162) The  empire's most famous rulers were Deva Raya II and the  Tuluva king Krishnadevaraya. Deva Raya II (known as ''Gajabetekara'' or hunter of elephants) ascended the throne in 1424 and was the most  effective of the Sangama dynasty rulers.Sastri (1955), p244Chopra (2003), p32, part2 He quelled rebelling feudal lords, the Zamorin of Calicut and the Quilon in the south, and invaded the island of Lanka while becoming overlord of the kings of Burma at Pegu and Tanasserim.Chopra (2003), p32, part2; From the notes of Persian Abdur Razzak. Writings of Nuniz confirms that the kings of Burma paid tributes to Vijayanagara empire (Sastri 1955, p245)Kamath (2001), p164 After a brief decline, the empire reached its peak in early 16th century during the rule of Krishnadevaraya when the Vijayanagara armies were consistently victorious. The empire annexed areas formerly under the Sultanates in the northern Deccan and the territories in the eastern Deccan, including Kalinga, while simultaneously maintaining control over all its subordinates in the south.Chopra (2003), pp37&ndash;39, part2; The notes of Portuguese Barbosa during the time of Krishnadevaraya confirms a very rich and well provided Vijayanagara city (Kamath 2001, p186)

Many important monuments at Hampi were either completed or commissioned during the reign of Krishnadevaraya. The enduring legacy of this empire is the vast open air theatre of monuments at the regal capital, Vijayanagara, which is now a UNESCO World Heritage site. Vijayanagara architecture is a vibrant blend of the preceding Chalukya, Hoysala, Pandya and Chola styles.Chopra (2003), p177, part2; Art critic, Percy Brown calls Vijayanagar architecture a blossoming of Dravidian style&ndash;Kamath (2001), p182 Literature in Telugu, Kannada, Tamil and Sanskrit languages found royal patronage. Telugu attained its height in popularity and reached its peak under Krishnadevaraya.Chopra (2003), pp171&ndash;173, part2; Kamath (2001), pp181–182 The Kannada Haridasa movement contributed greatly to Carnatic music and fostered a strong Hindu sentiment across South India.Owing to his contributions to carnatic music, Purandaradasa is known as ''Karnataka Sangita Pitamaha''. With the defeat of the Vijayanagara Empire in the Battle of Talikota in 1565 by the Deccan sultanates, the Karnataka region and South India in general became fragmented and subsumed under the rule of various former feudatories of the empire. A diminished Vijayanagara Empire moved its capital to Penukonda in modern Andhra Pradesh and later to Chandragiri and Vellore before disintegrating. In the south and coastal Karnataka region, the Kingdom of Mysore and  the Keladi Nayaka of Shimoga held sway while the northern regions  were under the control of the Bijapur Sultanate.Kamath (2001), p174 The Nayaka kingdom lasted into the 18th century before merging with the Kingdom of Mysore which remained a princely state until Indian independence in 1947, though they came under the British Raj (rule) in 1799 following the defeat and death of the last independent Mysore king, Tipu Sultan.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="16a1df42c11991fffdead37d60ca63f0" name="Stone_Chariot_at_the_Vitthala_Temple_in_Hampi" sectnum="6#1">../img/16a1df42c11991fffdead37d60ca63f0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>