<document id="1d77d915e1e28f06309d402ba1ec7e87-4" name="Political_history_of_medieval_Karnataka" cat="14">
<text>
In the late 10th century, the Western Chalukyas, also known as the Kalyani Chalukyas or 'Later' Chalukyas rose to power by overthrowing the Rashtrakutas under whom they had been serving as feudatories.  Manyakheta was their capital early on before they moved it to Kalyani (modern Basavakalyan). Whether the kings of this empire belonged to the same family line as their namesakes, the Badami Chalukyas is still debated.Chopra (2003), p137, part1Fleet, Bhandarkar and Altekar and Gopal B.R in (Kamath 2001, p100) Whatever the Western Chalukya origins, Kannada remained their language of administration and the Kannada and Sanskrit literature of their time was prolific.Narasimhacharya (1988), p68, p17–21Sen (1999), p. 393Sastri (1955), pp356&ndash;358; Kamath (2001), p114More inscriptions in Kannada are attributed to the Chalukya King Vikramaditya VI than to any other king prior to the 12th century,  Tailapa II, a feudatory ruler from Tardavadi (modern Bijapur district), re-established the Chalukya rule by defeating the Rashtrakutas during the reign of Karka II. He timed his rebellion to coincide with the confusion caused by the invading Paramara of Central India to the Rashtrakutas capital in 973.From the 957 and 965 records (Kamath 2001, p101)Sastri 1955, p162Tailapa II was helped in this campaign by the Kadambas of Hanagal (Moraes 1931, pp 93–94) This era produced prolonged warfare with the Chola dynasty of Tamilakam for control of the resources of the Godavari River-Krishna River doab region in Vengi. Somesvara I, a brave Chalukyan king, successfully curtailed the growth of the Chola Empire to the south of the Tungabhadra River region despite suffering some defeatsGanguli in Kamath 2001, p103Sastri (1955), p167–168 while maintaining control over his feudatories in the Konkan, Gujarat, Malwa and Kalinga regions.Kamath (2001), p104 For approximately 100 years, beginning in the early 11th century, the Cholas occupied large areas of South Karnataka region (Gangavadi).Sastri (1955), p164, p174; The Cholas occupied Gangavadi from 1004–1114 (Kamath 2001, p118)

In 1076, the ascent of the most famous king of this Chalukya family, Vikramaditya VI, changed the balance of power in favour of the Chalukyas.Chopra (2003), p139, part1 His fifty year reign was an important period in Karnataka's history and is referred to as the "Chalukya Vikrama era".Thapar, 2003, pp 468–469 His victories over the Cholas in the late 11th and early 12th centuries put an end to the Chola influence in the Vengi region permanently. Some of the well known contemporaneous feudatory families of the Deccan under Chalukya control were the Hoysalas, the Seuna Yadavas of Devagiri, the Kakatiya dynasty and the Southern Kalachuri.Chopra (2003), p139, part 1 At their peak, the Western Chalukyas ruled a vast empire stretching from the Narmada River in the north to the Kaveri River in the south. Vikramaditya VI is considered  one of the most influential kings of Indian history.Poet Bilhana in his Sanskrit work wrote "Rama Rajya" regarding his rule, poet Vijnaneshwara called him  "A king like none other" (Kamath 2001, p106)Sastri (1955), p6 Important architectural works were created by these Chalukyas, especially in the Tungabhadra river valley, that served as a conceptual link between the building idioms of the early Badami Chalukyas and the later Hoysalas.Sastri (1955), pp 427&ndash;428; Quote:"Their creations have the pride of place in Indian art tradition" (Kamath 2001, p115)Quote:"Of the city of Kalyana, situated in the north of Karnataka nothing is left, but a fabulous revival in temple building during the 11th century in central Karnataka testifies to the wealth during Kalyan Chalukya rule"(Foekema (1996), p14) With the weakening of the Chalukyas in the decades following the death of Vikramaditya VI in 1126, the feudatories of the Chalukyas gained their independence.

The Kalachuris of Karnataka, whose ancestors were immigrants into the southern deccan from central India, had ruled as a feudatory from Mangalavada (modern Mangalavedhe in Maharashtra).Kamath (2001), p107 Bijjala II, the most powerful ruler of this dynasty, was a commander (''mahamandaleswar'') during the reign of Chalukya Vikramaditya VI.From the 1142 and 1147 records, Kamath (2001), p108 Seizing an opportune moment in the waning power of the Chalukyas, Bijjala II declared independence in 1157 and annexed their capital Kalyani.Chopra (2003), p139, part1; From the Chikkalagi records (Kamath 2001, p108) His rule was cut short by his assassination in 1167 and  the ensuing civil war caused by his sons fighting over the throne ended the dynasty as the last Chalukya scion regained control of Kalyani. This victory however, was short-lived as the Chalukyas were eventually driven out by the Seuna Yadavas.Chopra (2003), p140, part1; Kamath (2001) p109
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="88e63411ad7776e67ef075e39aee7c7c" name="Gadag_Saraswati_temple_pillars" sectnum="4#1">../img/88e63411ad7776e67ef075e39aee7c7c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>