<document id="1d77d915e1e28f06309d402ba1ec7e87-1" name="Political_history_of_medieval_Karnataka" cat="14">
<text>
Prior to and during the early centuries of the first millennium, large areas of the Karnataka region was ruled by such imperial powers as the Mauryas of Maghada and later the Satavahanas, empires whose centres of power were in the Gangetic plains and Central India respectively. With the weakening of the Satavahanas, the Pallavas of Kanchi took control for a brief duration.Ramesh (1984), pp1–3 In the 4th century, the rise to power of the Kadamba Dynasty of Banavasi identified the Karnataka region as  an independent political entity and Kannada as an administrative language from the middle of 5th century.From the Halmidi inscription (Ramesh 1984, pp10–11) The Kadambas were natives of the Talagunda region (in modern Shivamogga district) as proven by inscriptions.The Kadambas were Kanarese speaking dravidians inducted into the Brahmin fold (Moraes 1931, p11)Their local tribal origins is attested by the Talagunda inscription, R.N. Nandi in Adiga (2006), p93Ramesh (1984), p3Some inscriptions claim the Kadambas came from a Naga descent (snake worshippers) making them natives of Karnataka region, Moraes (1931), p10Kamath (2001), p30 Mayurasharma, a brahmin native of Talagunda who was humiliated by a Pallava guard, rose in rage against the Pallava control of the Banavasi region and declared his independence in 345.From the Talagunda inscription (B.L. Rice in Kamath 2001, pp 30–31)Ramesh (1984), 1984, p6Moraes (1931), p10 After many wars, the Pallava king had to accept the sovereignty of the Kadambas and Mayurasharma, the founding king, crowned himself at Banavasi (in the present day Uttara Kannada district).Chopra (2003), p161, part1; Kamath (2001), p30

The fact that the Kadambas cultivated marital ties with the imperial Vakatakas and Gupta dynasties attests to their power.Moraes (1931), p26 Kakusthavarma, the most powerful ruler of the dynasty whom inscriptions describe as "ornament of the Kadamba family"  and "Sun among the kings of wide spread flame", gave one daughter in marriage to Vakataka Narendrasena  and another to Skandagupta, grandson of Chandragupta II of the Gupta dynasty.From the Talagunda inscription (Moraes 1931, pp26–27)From the Balaghat inscription of Vakataka Prithvisena (Kamath 2001, p33) Historians trace their rise to political power through the examination of the contemporaneous Sanskrit writing, ''Aichitya Vichara Charcha'' by Kshemendra, which quotes portions of a writing ''Kunthalesvara Dautya'' by the famous poet Kalidasa. Here Kalidasa describes his visit to the Kadamba kingdom as an ambassador where he was not offered a seat in the court of the Kadamba king and had to sit on the ground. Historians view this act as one of assertion by the Kadambas who considered themselves equal to the imperial Gupta dynasty.Moraes, Desai and Panchamukhi in Kamath (2001), p33

Family feuds and conflicts ended the Kadamba rule in the middle of 6th century when the last Kadamba ruler Krishna Varma II was subdued by Pulakesi I of the Chalukya feudatory, ending their sovereign rule. The Kadambas would continue to rule parts of Karnataka and Goa for many centuries to come but never again as an independent kingdom.Chopra (2003), p162, part1; Kamath (2001), p35 Some historians view the Kadambas as the originators of the Karnataka architectural tradition although there were elements in common with the structures  built by the contemporaneous Pallavas of Kanchi.Moraes in Kamath (2001), p37 The oldest surviving Kadamba structure is one dating to late 5th century in Halsi in modern Belgaum district. The most prominent feature of their architectural style, one that remained popular centuries later and was used by the Hoysalas and the Vijayanagar kings, is the ''Kadamba Shikara'' (Kadamba tower) with a ''Kalasa'' (pot) on top.Kamath (2001), p38

The Western Ganga Dynasty, contemporaries of the Kadambas, came to power from Kolar but in the late 4th century - early 5th century moved their capital to Talakad in modern Mysore district.Chopra (2003), p159, part1; Kamath (2001), p40 They ruled the region historically known as Gangavadi comprising most of the modern southern districts of Karnataka. Acting as a buffer state between the Kannada kingdoms of Karnataka region and the Tamil kingdoms of Tamilakam, the Western Ganga architectural innovations show mixed influences.The impact of the Pallava, early Chalukya and a distinct Jain influence added to their own innovations are the main features of their architectural idiom (Reddy, Sharma and Rao in Kamath 2001, p50) Their sovereign rule ended around the same time as the Kadambas when they came under the Badami Chalukya control. The Western Gangas continued to rule as a feudatory till the beginning of the eleventh century when they were defeated by the Cholas of Tanjavur.Chopra (2003), p160, part1 Important figures among the Gangas were King Durvinita and Shivamara II, admired as able warriors and scholars,Narasimhacharya (1988), p2 and minister Chavundaraya who was a builder, a warrior and a writer in Kannada and Sanskrit.Narasimhacharya (1988), p18Chopra (2003), pp159&ndash;160, part1; Kamath (2001), p50 The most important architectural contributions of these Gangas are the monuments and basadis of Shravanabelagola, the monolith of Gomateshwara termed as the mightiest achievement in the field of sculpture in ancient Karnataka and the ''Panchakuta'' basadi ( five towers) at Kambadahalli.Kamath (2001), pp51–52 Their free standing pillars (called ''Mahasthambhas'' and ''Brahmasthambhas'') and Hero stones (''virgal'') with sculptural detail are also considered a unique contribution.Fergusson in Kamath (2001), p52
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b5738939db657cc8a10b916d3002fb68" name="Panchakuta_Basadi_roofcarving_7" sectnum="1#1">../img/b5738939db657cc8a10b916d3002fb68.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>