<document id="1d77d915e1e28f06309d402ba1ec7e87-5" name="Political_history_of_medieval_Karnataka" cat="14">
<text>
The Hoysalas had become a powerful force even during their rule from Belur in the 11th century as a feudatory of the Chalukyas (in the south Karnataka region).Sen (1999), p498 In the early 12th century they successfully fought the Cholas in the south, convincingly defeating them in the battle of Talakad and moved their capital to nearby Halebidu.Sen (1999), p499Vishnuvardhana made many military conquests later to be further expanded by his successors into one of the most powerful empires of South India—William Coelho. He was the true maker of the Hoysala kingdom—B.S.K. Iyengar in Kamath (2001), p124–126 Historians refer to the founders of the dynasty as natives of Malnad Karnataka, based on the numerous inscriptions calling them ''Maleparolganda'' or "Lord of the Male (hills) chiefs" (''Malepas'').B.L.Rice in Kamath (2001), p123Keay (2000), p251Thapar (2003), p367Kamath (2001), p123Natives of south Karnataka (Chopra, 2003, p150 Part1) With the waning of the Western Chalukya power, the Hoysalas declared their independence in the late twelfth century.

During this period of Hoysala control, distinctive Kannada literary metres such as ''Ragale'' (blank verse), ''Sangatya'' (meant to be sung to the accompaniment of a musical instrument), ''Shatpadi'' (seven line) etc. became widely accepted.Shiva Prakash in Ayyappapanicker (1997), pp164, 203; Rice E. P. (1921), p59Kamath (2001), pp132–134Sastri (1955), p359, p361 The Hoysalas expanded the Vesara architecture stemming from the Chalukyas,Sastri (1955), p427 culminating in the Hoysala architectural articulation and style as exemplified in the construction of the Chennakesava Temple at Belur and the Hoysaleswara temple at Halebidu.Sen (1999), pp500–501 Both these temples were built in commemoration of the victories of the Hoysala Vishnuvardhana against the Cholas in 1116.Foekema (1996), p14Kamath (2001), p124 Veera Ballala II, the most effective of the Hoysala rulers, defeated the aggressive Pandya when they invaded the Chola kingdom and assumed the titles "Establisher of the Chola Kingdom"
(''Cholarajyapratishtacharya''), "Emperor of the south" (''Dakshina Chakravarthi'') and "Hoysala emperor" (''Hoysala Chakravarthi'').The most outstanding of the Hoysala kings according to Barrett and William Coelho in Kamath (2001), p126 The Hoysalas extended their foothold in areas known today as Tamil Nadu around 1225, making the city of Kannanur Kuppam near Srirangam a provincial capital.Sen (1999), p499 This gave them control over South Indian politics that began a period of Hoysala hegemony in the southern Deccan.B.S.K. Iyengar in Kamath (2001), p126Keay (2000), p252

In the early 13th century, with the Hoysala power remaining unchallenged, the first of the Muslim incursions into South India began. After over two decades of waging war against a foreign power, the Hoysala ruler at the time, Veera Ballala III, died in the battle of Madurai in 1343.Sen (1999), p500 This resulted in the merger of the sovereign territories of the Hoysala empire with the areas administered by Harihara I, founder of the Vijayanagara Empire, located in the Tungabhadra region in present day Karnataka. The new kingdom thrived for another two centuries with Vijayanagara as its capital.Two theories exist about the origin of Harihara I and his brother Bukka Raya I. One states that they were Kannadiga commanders of the Hoysala army and another that they were Telugu speakers and commanders of the earlier Kakatiya Kingdom (Kamath 2001, pp 159–160)
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="18c802f931d40071a6313969a93b735b" name="Belur_shilabalika" sectnum="5#1">../img/18c802f931d40071a6313969a93b735b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>