<document id="1d77d915e1e28f06309d402ba1ec7e87-3" name="Political_history_of_medieval_Karnataka" cat="14">
<text>
In the middle of 8th century  the Chalukya rule was ended by their feudatory, the Rashtrakuta family rulers of Berar (in present day Amravati district of Maharashtra). Sensing an opportunity during a weak period in the Chalukya rule, Dantidurga trounced the great Chalukyan "Karnatabala" (power of Karnata).From the Rashtrakuta inscriptions (Kamath 2001, p57, p64)The Samangadh copper plate grant (753) confirms that feudatory Dantidurga defeated the Chalukyas and humbled their great ''Karnatik'' army (referring to the army of the Badami Chalukyas) (Reu 1933, p54) Having overthrown the Chalukyas, the Rashtrakutas  made Manyakheta their capital (modern Malkhed in Gulbarga district).A capital which could put to shame even the capital of gods-From Karda plates (Altekar 1934, p47)A capital city built to excel that of Indra (Sastri, 1955, p4, p132, p146) Although the origins of the early Rashtrakuta ruling families in central India and the Deccan in the 6th and 7th centuries is controversial, during the eighth through the tenth centuries they emphasised the importance of the Kannada language in conjunction with Sanskrit in their administration. Rashtrakuta inscriptions are in Kannada and Sanskrit only. They encouraged literature in both languages and thus literature flowered under their rule.Altekar (1934), pp411–413Chopra (2003), p87, part1; Literature in Kannada and Sanskrit flowered during the Rashtrakuta rule (Kamath 2001, p73, pp 88–89)Even royalty of the empire took part in poetic and literary activities (Thapar 2003, p334)Reu (1933), pp37–38


The Rashtrakutas quickly became the most powerful Deccan empire, making their initial successful forays into the doab region of Ganga River and Jamuna River during the rule of Dhruva Dharavarsha.Chopra (2003), p89, part1; His victories were a "digvijaya"  gaining only fame and booty in that region (Altekar in Kamath 2001, p75) The rule of his son Govinda III signaled a new era with Rashtrakuta victories against the Pala Dynasty of Bengal and Gurjara Pratihara of north western India resulting in the capture of Kannauj. The Rashtrakutas held Kannauj intermittently during a period of  a tripartite struggle for the resources of the rich Gangetic plains.Chopra (2003), p90, part1 Because of Govinda III's victories, historians have compared him to Alexander the Great and Pandava Arjuna of the Hindu epic Mahabharata.Keay (2000), p199)
The Sanjan inscription states the horses of Govinda III drank the icy water of the Himalayan stream and his war elephants tasted the sacred waters of the Ganges River. Kamath 2001, p76 Amoghavarsha I, eulogised by contemporary Arab traveller Sulaiman as one among the four great emperors of the world, succeeded Govinda III to the throne and ruled during an important cultural period that produced landmark writings in Kannada and Sanskrit.Kavirajamarga in Kannada and ''Prashnottara Ratnamalika'' in Sanskrit (Reu 1933, p38)Kamath (2001), p90 The benevolent development of Jain religion was a hallmark of his rule. Because of his religious temperament, his interest in the arts and literature and his peace loving nature,Chopra (2003), p91, part1 he has been compared to emperor Ashoka.Panchamukhi in Kamath (2001), p80 The rule of Indra III in the tenth century enhanced the Rashtrakuta position as an imperial power as they conquered and held Kannauj again.Chopra (2003), p92, part1; Altekar in Kamath 2001, p81 Krishna III followed Indra III to the throne in 939. A patron of Kannada literature and a powerful warrior, his reign marked the submission of the Paramara of Ujjain in the north and Cholas in the south.Chopra (2003), p92&ndash;93, part1

An Arabic writing ''Silsilatuttavarikh'' (851) called the Rashtrakutas one among the four principle empires of the world.Reu (1933), p39 ''Kitab-ul-Masalik-ul-Mumalik'' (912) called them the "greatest kings of India" and there were many other contemporaneous books written in their praise.''Murujul Zahab'' by Al Masudi (944), ''Kitabul Akalim'' by Al Istakhri (951), ''Ashkal-ul-Bilad'' by Ibn Haukal (976) (Reu 1933, p41–42) The Rashtrakuta empire at its peak spread from Cape Comorin in the south to Kannauj in the north and from Banaras in the east to Broach (Bharuch) in the west.From the Sanjan inscriptions, 
While the Rashtrakutas built many fine monuments in the Deccan, the most extensive and sumptuous of their work is the monolithic Kailasanatha temple at Ellora, the temple being a splendid achievement.Keay (2000), p200 In Karnataka their most famous temples are the Kashivishvanatha temple and the Jain Narayana temple at Pattadakal. All of the monuments are designated UNESCO World Heritage Sites.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="15cb5939d5e6b4198f418ad1fc5d5b54" name="Kailasha_temple_at_ellora" sectnum="3#1">../img/15cb5939d5e6b4198f418ad1fc5d5b54.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>