<document id="1d8045a0d8979fd088b85b6e99cf8b09-1.2" name="Common_Raven" cat="3">
<text>
The Common Raven evolved in the Old World and crossed the Bering land bridge into North America.Marzluff and Angell p86 Recent genetic studies, which examined the DNA of Common Ravens from across the world, have determined that the birds fall into at least two clades: a California clade, found only in the southwestern United States, and a Holarctic clade, found across the rest of the northern hemisphere. Birds from both clades look alike, but the groups are genetically distinct and began to diverge about two million years ago.

The findings indicate that based on mitochondrial DNA, Common Ravens from the rest of the United States are more closely related to those in Europe and Asia than to those in the California clade, and that Common Ravens in the California clade are more closely related to the Chihuahuan Raven ''(C. cryptoleucus)'' than to those in the Holarctic clade. Ravens in the Holarctic clade are more closely related to the Pied Crow ''(C. albus)'' than they are to the California clade. Thus, the Common Raven species as traditionally delimited is considered to be paraphyletic. 

One explanation for these surprising genetic findings is that Common Ravens settled in California at least two million years ago and became separated from their relatives in Europe and Asia during an ice age. One million years ago, a group from the California clade evolved into a new species, the Chihuahuan Raven. Other members of the Holarctic clade arrived later in a separate migration from Asia, perhaps at the same time as humans.Marzluff and Angell p86-87

A recent study of raven mitochondrial DNA showed that members of the ''C. c. tingitanus'' subspecies have significant genetic differences from the rest of the Holarctic clade. This subspecies occurs only in North Africa and the Canary Islands. The study also demonstrated that ''C. c. tingitanus'' ravens do not interbreed with other subspecies.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c1b3d14f20bd7801af26fe2d73697ff9" name="Raven_Cypress_Provincial_Park" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/c1b3d14f20bd7801af26fe2d73697ff9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>