<document id="1f567cd562e7b6d83dba586f77cff6eb-3" name="USS_Nevada_(BB-36)" cat="29">
<text>
After fitting out in the Boston and New York Navy Yards, ''Nevada'' joined the Atlantic Fleet in Newport, Rhode Island on 26 May 1916. Prior to the United States' entry into World War I, she conducted many training cruises and underwent many exercises out of her base in Norfolk, Virginia, sailing as far south as the Caribbean on these cruises. The US entered the war in 1917, but the ''Nevada'' was not sent to the other side of the Atlantic because of a shortage of fuel oil in Britain.Miller (1997), p. 185 Instead, four coal-burning battleships of Battleship Division 9 (BatDiv 9) (, , , and ) departed the US to join the British Grand Fleet on 25 November 1917. They arrived on 7 December and were designated as the 6th Battle Squadron of the Grand Fleet.  joined them after damage from a grounding on Block Island was repaired; she departed 30 January and arrived in Scotland on 11 February. It was not until 13 August 1918 that ''Nevada'' left the US for Britain, becoming the last American ship to join the Fleet.

After a 10-day voyage, she arrived in Berehaven, Ireland, on 23 August. Along with  and her sister , the three were nicknamed the "Bantry Bay Squadron";Venzon and Miles (1999), p. 755 officially, they were Battleship Division 6 under the command of Rear Admiral Thomas S. Rodgers, who chose ''Utah'' as his flagship.Halpern (1995), p. 436Russell and Moore (1921), p. 97 For the rest of World War I, the three ships operated from the bay, escorting the large and valuable convoys bound for the British Isles to ensure no German heavy surface ships could slip past the British Grand Fleet and annihilate the merchant ships and their weak escorts of older cruisers. This never came to pass, and the war ended on 11 November with ''Nevada'' not getting a chance to engage an enemy during the war. Also, at some point during her time on the eastern side of the Atlantic, ''Nevada'' apparently made a patrol through the North Sea, but sources do not give any date. See the ''DANFS'' article on ''Nevada'' and Bonner (1996), p. 102.

On 13 December, 10 battleships, including ''Nevada'',The other nine battleships were , , , , , , ,  and . and 28 destroyers escorted the ocean liner , with President Woodrow Wilson embarked, into Brest, France, during the last day of Wilson's journey to the country so he could attend the Paris Peace Conference. Though it was originally planned for the flotilla to meet ''George Washington'' and her escorts (''Pennsylvania'' and four destroyers) 1,500 mi (2,414 km) out of Brest, it was changed; the other nine battleships and 24 destroyers instead met the President "a short distance" away from Brest and escorted him into port from there. The 10 battleships sailed for home at 1400 on the next day, 14 December. They took less than two weeks to cross the Atlantic, and arrived in New York on 26 December to parades and celebrations.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="578ccf30b0eb7ad2e965ad412a9c7836" name="USS_Nevada_(BB-36)_during_WWI" sectnum="3#1">../img/578ccf30b0eb7ad2e965ad412a9c7836.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>