<document id="1f567cd562e7b6d83dba586f77cff6eb-5.3" name="USS_Nevada_(BB-36)" cat="29">
<text>
After D-Day, the Allies headed to Toulon for another amphibious assault, codenamed Operation Dragoon. To support this, many ships were sent from the beaches of Normandy to the Mediterranean, including five battleships (the United States' ''Nevada'', , , the British , and the Free French ), three US heavy cruisers (,  and ), and many destroyers and landing craft were transferred south.Morison (1963), p. 414

''Nevada'' supported this operation from 15 August-25 September 1944, "dueling" with "Big Willie": a heavily reinforced fortress with four  guns in two dual turrets. These guns had been salvaged from the French battleship ''Provence'' after the scuttling of the French fleet in Toulon; the guns had a range of nearly 22 mi (35 km) and they commanded every approach to the port of Toulon. In addition, they were fortified with heavy armor plate bedded into the rocky sides of the island of Saint Mandrier. Due to these dangers, the fire-support ships assigned to the operation were ordered to level the fortress. Beginning on 19 August, and continuing on subsequent days, one or more heavy warships bombarded it in conjunction with low-level bomber strikes. On the 23rd, a bombardment force headed by ''Nevada'' struck the "most damaging" blow to the fort during a 6½ hour battle, which saw 354 salvos fired by ''Nevada''. Toulon fell on the 25th, but the fort, though it was "coming apart at the seams", held out for three more days.Karig, Burton and Freeland (1946), p. 386&ndash;387



''Nevada'' then headed to New York to have her gun barrels relined. In addition, her /45 cal guns from turret 1 were replaced with the Mark 8 guns from turret 2 of ; these new guns were relined to Mark 12 specifications.Campbell (1985), p. 123 After that was completed, she sailed for the Pacific, arriving off Iwo Jima on 16 February 1945 to " the island for invasion with heavy bombardment"; which she did through 7 March. During the invasion, she moved to be within  from shore to provide maximum firepower for the troops that were advancing.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="cba896666ec7b69eab91a97aef2f8da0" name="USS_Nevada_(BB-36)_bombarding_Iwo_Jima" sectnum="5.3#1">../img/cba896666ec7b69eab91a97aef2f8da0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>