<document id="1f567cd562e7b6d83dba586f77cff6eb-5.1" name="USS_Nevada_(BB-36)" cat="29">
<text>
When the weekend of 6–7 December arrived, all of the Pacific Fleet's battleships were in port for the weekend for the first time since 4 July. Normally they "took turns" spending time in port—six would be out with Vice Admiral William S. Pye's battleship task force one weekend, while the next weekend would find three ranging with Vice Admiral William Halsey, Jr.'s aircraft carrier task force. However, because Halsey could not afford to take the slow These were normal cruising speeds, not their top speeds. battleships with his  aircraft carriers with him on his dash to reinforce Wake Island's Marine detachment with additional fighters, and it was Pye's turn to rest in port and the harbor was where "it was safe", all of the battleships were not sailing on that morning.Lord (2001), pp. 1–2 When the sun rose over ''Nevada'' on the 7th, the ship's band was playing "Morning Colors"; but planes then appeared on the horizon and the attack on Pearl Harbor began.

Aft of ''Arizona'' during the attack, ''Nevada'' was not moored alongside another battleship off Ford Island, and therefore was able to maneuver, unlike the other seven battleships present. was in drydock at the time of the attack. Of the anchored ships on Battleship Row (in order, north to south), ''Nevada'' was moored singly;  had  moored outboard of her;  and  were moored together; and  and  were moored together.  was moored singly at the bottom of the "row", similar to ''Nevada'', and should have had the ability to maneuver like ''Nevada'' did. However, ''California'', as "she was about to undergo a material inspection  watertight integrity was not at its maximum" (), started settling as soon as she was hit by Japanese bombs and torpedoes. As a result, she sank soon after the attack began after being hit with just two bombs and two torpedoes. By comparison, ''Nevada'' took at least six bombs and one torpedo, and was still afloat when she was ordered to be beached by Hospital Point. As her gunners opened fire and her engineers started to raise steam, a single  Type 91 Mod 2 torpedo exploded against Frame 41 about  above the keel at 0810.Wallin (1968), p. 212 The torpedo bulkhead held, but leaking through joints caused flooding and a list of 4-5°. ''Nevada'' corrected the list through counter-flooding and got underway at 0840, her gunners already having shot down four planes.

As she steamed past Ten-Ten DockNamed for its length, 1010 feet. at about 0950, ''Nevada'' was struck by five bombs. One exploded over the crew's galley at Frame 80. Another struck the port director platform and exploded at the base of the stack on the upper deck. Yet another hit near No. 1 turret inboard from the port waterway and blew large holes in the upper and main decks. Two struck the forecastle near Frame 15; one passed out through the side of the second deck before exploding, but the other exploded within the ship near the gasoline tank; leakage and vapors from this tank caused intense fires around the ship.

The gasoline fires that flared up around Turret 1 might have caused more critical damage if the main magazines had not been empty. For several days prior to the attack, all of the  gun battleships had been replacing their standard-weight, main-battery projectiles with a new heavier projectile that offered greater penetration and a larger explosive charge in exchange for a slight decrease in range. All of the older projectiles and powder charges had been removed from the magazines of ''Nevada'', and the crew had taken a break after loading the new projectiles in anticipation of loading the new powder charges on Sunday.Sabin, L. A., Vice Admiral, USN. "Comment and Discussion", ''United States Naval Institute Proceedings'', September 1973, 97.



As bomb damage became evident, ''Nevada'' was ordered to proceed to the west side of Ford Island to prevent her from being sunk in the channel which would "effectively cork the rest of the fleet in a bottle."Bonner (1996), p. 105 Instead, she was grounded off Hospital Point at 1030,Wallin (1968), pp. 212–213 with the help of  and , though she managed to force down three planes before she hit bottom.

Over the course of the morning, ''Nevada'' suffered a total of 60 killed and 109 wounded. Two more men died aboard during salvage operations on 7 February 1942 when they were overcome by hydrogen sulfide gas from decomposing paper and meat.Wallin (1968), p. 218 The ship suffered a minimum of six bomb hits and one torpedo hit, but "it is possible that as many as ten bomb hits may have been received,  as certain damaged areas  of sufficient size to indicate that they were struck by more than one bomb."

The day after the attack, the crewmen ran "repel boarders" drills with "broomsticks, baseball bats and the few small arms that were available" to practice for the expected Japanese invasion of Hawaii. During this time, they were "virtually homeless": their records were lost in the shambles left after the attack, and they were effectively reduced to begging for essentials such as food, shelter, and uniforms.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c7046181cd1edd116c8674e8dfa1c535" name="USS_Nevada_temporarily_beached_on_hospital_point_925AM_NARA-80-G-19940" sectnum="5.1#1">../img/c7046181cd1edd116c8674e8dfa1c535.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>