<document id="1f567cd562e7b6d83dba586f77cff6eb-1" name="USS_Nevada_(BB-36)" cat="29">
<text>
Being both the first second-generation battleshipMorison and Polmar (2003), p. 63 and the first "super-dreadnought" in the US Navy, ''Nevada'' has been described as "revolutionary"Gardiner and Gray (1984), p. 115 and "as radical as  was in her day"Worth (2002), p. 290 by present-day historians. At the time of her completion in 1916,Although ''Nevada'' was launched in 1914, construction was not completed until 1916. For larger ships, drydocks are typically only used for work that must be done ''in'' the drydock; once the hull is complete, the ship is normally launched into the water, where the rest of the work is completed. This is normally done to free up the drydock for other work. ''The New York Times'' remarked that the new warship was "the greatest  afloat" because she was so much larger than other contemporary American battleships: her tonnage was nearly three times as great as that of the obsolete 1890 pre-dreadnought , almost two times as great as that of the 1904 battleship , and almost 8,000 tons (7,257 tonnes) greater than that of one of the first American dreadnoughts, , which had been built just seven years prior to ''Nevada''.

''Nevada'' was the first battleship in the US Navy to have triple gun turrets,The idea for turrets with more than two guns each came from the French, as they were planning to use quadruple turrets in their planned  battleships. Only one of these ships was completed, , but she was converted to an aircraft carrier. See:  a single funnel, and oil-fired steam power plants. In particular, using oil gave the ship an engineering advantage over the earlier coal-fired plants, as oil is much more efficient than coal because it yields "a far greater steaming radius for a given amount of fuel". The ability to steam great distances without refueling was a major concern of the General Board at that time. In 1903, the Board felt all American battleships should have a minimum steaming radius of 6,000 mi (9,656 km) so that the US could enforce the Monroe Doctrine. One of the main purposes of the Great White Fleet, which sailed around the world in 1907–1908, was to prove to Japan that the US Navy could "carry any naval conflict into Japanese home waters". Possibly as a result of this, battleships after 1908 were mainly designed to "steam 8,000 miles at cruising speeds"; given the distance between San Pedro, where the fleet would be based, and Manila, where the Fleet was expected to have to fight under War Plan Orange, was 6,550 nmiPrange, Dillon, and Goldstein (1991), p. 217 (12,100 km, 7,500 mi), endurance was obviously a major concern for the U.S. Navy.Hone and Friedman (1981), p. 59Friedman (1986), p. 104 Also, oil allowed for the boiler-room crew to be reducedGardiner and Gray (1984), p. 116 — the engineer on  estimated that 100 firemen (stokers) and 112 coal passers could be adequately replaced by just 24 men, which would allow some crew quarters to be eliminated; this would save weight and also reduce the amount of fresh water and provisions that the ship would have to carry.Friedman (1986), pp. 104–105

In addition to all of this, ''Nevada'' had maximum armor over critical areas, such as the magazines and engines, and none over less-important places, even though previous battleships had armor of varying thickness depending on the importance of the area it was protecting. This radical change became known as the "all or nothing" principle, which most major navies later adopted for their own battleships.Bonner (1996), p. 102 With this new armor scheme, the armor on the battleship was increased to 41.1% of the displacement.Friedman (1978), pp. 166–167

As a result of all of these design modifications from previous battleships, ''Nevada'' was the first of the so-called "Standard" type of battleship.Worth (2002), pp. 289–290 "Standards" were characterized by the use of oil fuel, the "all or nothing" armor scheme, and the arrangement of the main armament in four triple or twin turrets without any turrets located in the middle of the ship.Friedman (1986), p. 101

The two battleships of the ''Nevada''-class were virtually identical except in their propulsion. ''Nevada'' and her sister were fitted with different engines to compare the two, putting them 'head-to-head': ''Oklahoma'' received older vertical triple expansion engines, while ''Nevada'' received Curtis steam turbines.See this book for more information on Curtis turbines (Scroll down to the bottom of the page):
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b4dae870c9aa333d0fc1cca70d52932d" name="USS_Nevada_(BB-36)_specs" sectnum="1#1">../img/b4dae870c9aa333d0fc1cca70d52932d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>