<document id="1f8c305889264e046100b0f069d5993a-1.2" name="Palpatine" cat="19">
<text>
Palpatine is a central character in Genndy Tartakovsky's ''Star Wars: Clone Wars'', an animated miniseries set between ''Attack of the Clones'' and ''Revenge of the Sith''. The character is based on McDiarmid's likeness in ''The Phantom Menace'' and ''Attack of the Clones''. In the first chapter, Obi-Wan informs Palpatine that the Jedi have discovered that the InterGalactic Banking Clan has established battle droid factories on the planet Muunilinst. Palpatine agrees to send a strike force that includes Obi-Wan and Anakin, but Palpatine suggests that Anakin be given "special command" of Obi-Wan's fighters. Yoda and Obi-Wan initially speak against it, but reluctantly concede to the Chancellor.Chapter 1, ''Star Wars: Clone Wars'', episode 101, aired November 7, 2003. In another chapter, Darth Sidious appears to Count Dooku as a holographic image shortly after Dooku trains Asajj Ventress, a Force-sensitive female Rattatakian adept in the dark side. Sidious orders her to track down and kill Anakin Skywalker. He remarks to Count Dooku that her failure is certain, but the point of her mission is to test Anakin.Chapter 7, ''Star Wars: Clone Wars'', episode 107, aired November 17, 2003. Chapter 22 features the training of General Grievous by Count Dooku. Darth Sidious appears as a hologram and orders Grievous to begin the special mission: an assault on the galactic capital.Chapter 22, ''Star Wars: Clone Wars'', episode 202, aired March 22, 2005. The Separatist invasion of Coruscant begins in the next episode, and Palpatine watches from the window in his private residence. He is protected by Jedi Shaak Ti, Roron Corobb, and Foul Moudama. Grievous breaks through the Chancellor's window and kidnaps him.Chapter 23, ''Star Wars: Clone Wars'', episode 203, aired March 23, 2005. Grievous kills Roron and Foul and captures Shaak Ti as Palpatine is taken to the ''Invisible Hand'', Grievous's flagship.Chapter 24, ''Star Wars: Clone Wars'', episode 204, aired March 24, 2005.Chapter 25, ''Star Wars: Clone Wars'', episode 205, aired March 25, 2005.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="108c8967acbdcc385d09503b817a3a29" name="PalpatineCloneWar" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/108c8967acbdcc385d09503b817a3a29.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>