<document id="1f8c305889264e046100b0f069d5993a-1.1.2" name="Palpatine" cat="19">
<text>
In ''Star Wars Episode I: The Phantom Menace'', set 32 years before ''Star Wars Episode IV: A New Hope'', Palpatine is introduced as the senior Galactic Senator from the planet Naboo. The Trade Federation blockades and invades Naboo under the influence and advice of Palpatine's Sith alter ego, Darth Sidious. Queen Padmé Amidala (played by Natalie Portman) flees to the galactic capital planet of Coruscant to receive counsel from the senator. After a plea for help from the senate results in bureaucratic delays, Palpatine persuades her to make a motion to have Supreme Chancellor Finis Valorum (Terence Stamp) removed from office. Palpatine, as Sidious, sends his Sith apprentice Darth Maul (played by Ray Park) to Naboo to oversee the invasion and find the queen. The invasion, however, is thwarted by Jedi Qui-Gon Jinn (played by Liam Neeson) and Obi-Wan Kenobi (played by Ewan McGregor); in the ensuing lightsaber duel, both Maul and Jinn are killed. Palpatine returns to Naboo, having been elected the new Chancellor. He tells nine-year-old Anakin Skywalker (played by Jake Lloyd) that "we will watch your career with great interest".''Star Wars Episode I: The Phantom Menace'' (DVD, 20th Century Fox, 1999), disc 1.

In ''Star Wars Episode II: Attack of the Clones'', set ten years later, the galaxy is on the verge of civil war, as a growing Separatist movement of planets seeks to secede from the Republic to form the Confederacy of Independent Systems. They are led by Count Dooku (played by Christopher Lee), a former Jedi and Darth Sidious' new apprentice. After Kenobi discovers that the Separatists are building a secret battle droid army, Palpatine uses the situation to have himself granted emergency powers. Palpatine feigns reluctance to accept this authority, promising to return it to the Senate once the crisis has ended. His first act is to create an army of cloned human warriors (the Grand Army of the Republic) to counter the Separatist threat. The clones had recently been discovered by Kenobi as having been secretly ordered by "deceased Jedi Master Sifo-Dyas" many years earlier. Palpatine is also influential in having Anakin (played by Hayden Christensen) guard Padmé, which leads to their marriage at the end of the film.''Star Wars Episode II: Attack of the Clones'' (DVD, 20th Century Fox, 2002), disc 1.

In ''Star Wars Episode III: Revenge of the Sith'', set three years later, Palpatine is captured by Separatist leader General Grievous (voiced by Matthew Wood). Palpatine is rescued by Kenobi and Anakin Skywalker, but not before the Jedi confront Count Dooku; Skywalker decapitates him in cold blood during the lightsaber duel, at Palpatine's urging. By this point, Palpatine has acquired additional emergency powers, and can now take virtually any action without Senate approval.  This effectively makes him a dictator, though he commands a supermajority in the Senate in any case.

The Jedi Council, as well as a number of Senators, are troubled by Palpatine's power and fears he will not relinquish it when the Clone Wars end. Palpatine raises the Jedi's suspicions further when he has the Senate grant him direct control over the Jedi Council, and appoints Anakin as his personal representative, effectively granting him a vote in Jedi affairs. He tries to turn Anakin against the Jedi by suggesting that he deserves the rank of Jedi Master, which the Council refuses him out of concern for Palpatine's influence on him. The Council orders Anakin to spy on Palpatine, but he instead reveals the Jedi's plan to him. Palpatine tells Anakin the story of Darth Plagueis, a powerful Sith Lord who was able to manipulate life and death, but was killed by his apprentice. Palpatine reveals his secret identity to Anakin, and reveals that he killed Darth Plagueis.  He tempts him with promises of power that he could never have as a Jedi, including power over life and death. Palpatine knows that Anakin has been having visions of Padmé, who is now pregnant with Anakin's child, dying in childbirth and offers to teach him Plagueis' secrets to save her life. Confused, Anakin informs Jedi Master Mace Windu (played by Samuel L. Jackson) that Palpatine is a Sith Lord. Windu and a group of fellow Jedi Masters go to arrest Palpatine, but the Chancellor surprises them with a lightsaber and quickly dispatches all but Windu. In the ensuing duel, Windu manages to disarm his opponent , and deforms Palpatine's face by deflecting his own Force lightning back at him. He is poised to execute the Sith Lord when Anakin appears and intercedes on Palpatine's behalf, cutting off Windu's hand. Palpatine shoots Windu with another blast of lightning, hurtling him through the window to his death. Palpatine then accepts Anakin as his new apprentice, Darth Vader.

Palpatine then sets the destruction of the Jedi in motion: he sends Vader to destroy the Jedi Temple and instructs all of the clone troopers to kill their Jedi generals. He then sends Vader to Mustafar to wipe out the Separatist leaders. He announces to the Senate that the Jedi were planning to overthrow the Republic, and that the Republic will be reorganized into the Galactic Empire, with himself as Emperor for life. Jedi Master Yoda (Frank Oz) returns to Coruscant and confronts Palpatine in his Senate office. A lightsaber duel erupts between them which ends in stalemate, forcing Yoda to retreat into exile. Sensing his apprentice is in trouble, Palpatine travels to Mustafar, where he finds Vader maimed and burned almost to the point of death following a duel with Kenobi. Palpatine returns to Coruscant with Vader and provides him with the black armor suit first seen in the original trilogy. When Vader regains consciousness, Palpatine tells him that he (Vader) killed his own wife in anger, breaking what remains of his apprentice's spirit. Palpatine is last seen watching the first Death Star under construction with Vader and Grand Moff Wilhuff Tarkin (Wayne Pygram) at his side.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d7b006186c2f28bc41c30eb8a4163a27" name="Palpatine1" sectnum="1.1.2#1">../img/d7b006186c2f28bc41c30eb8a4163a27.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>