<document id="1f8c305889264e046100b0f069d5993a-4.7" name="Palpatine" cat="19">
<text>
Palpatine's role in popular culture extends beyond the ''Star Wars'' universe and its fans. Since the release of ''Return of the Jedi'', Palpatine has become synonymous in American mass media with evil, deception, manipulation, and power.Koenraad Kuiper, "Star Wars: An Imperial Myth," ''Journal of Popular Culture'' 21 (No. 4, Spring 1988): p. 81. The character is used as a literary device &mdash; either as a simile or metaphor &mdash; to emphasize these traits. For example, one of the characters from Orland Outland's novel ''Every Man for Himself'' (1999) is described as "rubbing his hands together in imitation of the emperor in ''Return of the Jedi''." He says, "Everything is happening exactly as I have foreseen!"Orland Outland, ''Every Man for Himself'' (New York: Kensington Books, 1999), p. 188, ISBN 1-57566-553-0; The Emperor actually tells Darth Vader in ''Return of the Jedi'': "Everything is proceeding as I have foreseen it."

 In film and television, Palpatine's likeness is similarly used as a parody.  Animated television series such as ''The Simpsons'',"Hungry, Hungry Homer," ''The Simpsons'', episode 262, aired March 4, 2001. ''American Dad!'',"Deacon Stan, Jesus Man," ''American Dad!'', episode 7, aired June 19, 2005. and ''Family Guy''"The Cleveland-Loretta Quagmire," ''Family Guy'', episode 55, aired June 12, 2005. have employed Palpatine's image to satirize characters and public figures.  For instance, "Deacon Stan, Jesus Man," an episode of ''American Dad!'' portrays George W. Bush's then-current senior advisor, Karl Rove, as Palpatine from ''Revenge of the Sith''. The main character, Stan Smith, uses Rove to help him become a deacon at his church through deceit. He is also set to appear as the main villain in the series ''Kingdom Comedy'', which will debut in 2010.

Since ''Return of the Jedi'' and the prequel films, Palpatine's name has been invoked as a caricature in politics. The liberal website BuzzFlash remarked in 2004, "When we saw ...  Zell Miller ties." ''Star Wars Insider'' 88 (June 2006).
* Reynolds, David West. ''Episode I: The Visual Dictionary'' New York: DK Publishing, 1999. ISBN 0-7894-4701-0.
* Reynolds, David West. ''Star Wars: Attack of the Clones: The Visual Dictionary''. New York: DK Publishing, 2002. ISBN 0-7894-8588-5.
* Smith, Jeffrey A. "Hollywood Theology: The Commodification of Religion in Twentieth-Century Films." ''Religion and American Culture'' 11 (No. 2, Summer 2001): pp. 191–231.
* Velasco, Raymond L. ''A Guide to the Star Wars Universe''. New York: Del Rey, 1984. ISBN 0-345-31920-6.
* Wallace, Daniel. ''The New Essential Guide to Characters''. New York: Del Rey, 2002. ISBN 0-345-44900-2.
* Wallace, Daniel, and Kevin J. Anderson. ''The New Essential Chronology''. New York: Del Rey, 2005. ISBN 0-345-44901-0.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a95b1a1c334039022b4c57d75d87d01b" name="Karl_Rove_Cartoon" sectnum="4.7#1">../img/a95b1a1c334039022b4c57d75d87d01b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>