<document id="1ff6e9d545f63633959771e856dc600f-4.13" name="William_Gibson" cat="17">
<text>
In ''Neuromancer'', Gibson first used the term "matrix" to refer to the visualised Internet, two years after the nascent Internet was formed in the early 1980s from the computer networks of the 1970s. Gibson thereby imagined a worldwide communications network years before the origin of the World Wide Web, although related notions had been previously been imagined by others, including science fiction writers. At the time he wrote "Burning Chrome", Gibson "had a hunch that  would change things, in the same way that the ubiquity of the automobile changed things." In 1995, he identified the advent, evolution and growth of the Internet as "one of the most fascinating and unprecedented human achievements of the century", a new kind of civilization that is – in terms of significance &mdash; on a par with the birth of cities,  and in 2000 predicted it would lead to the death of the nation state.

Observers contend that Gibson's influence on the development of the Web reached beyond prediction; he is widely credited with creating an iconography for the information age, long before the embrace of the Internet by the mainstream. Gibson introduced, in ''Neuromancer'', the notion of the "meatpuppet", and is credited with inventing—conceptually rather than participatorally—the phenomenon of virtual sex.  His influence on early pioneers of desktop environment digital art has been acknowledged, and he holds an honorary doctorate from Parsons The New School for Design.

 Steven Poole claims that in writing the Sprawl trilogy Gibson laid the "conceptual foundations for the explosive real-world growth of virtual environments in video games and the Web". In his afterword to the 2000 re-issue of ''Neuromancer'', fellow author Jack Womack suggests that Gibson's vision of cyberspace may have inspired the way in which the Internet (and the Web particularly) developed, following the publication of ''Neuromancer'' in 1984, asking "what if the act of writing it down, in fact, ''brought it about''?"


Gibson scholar Tatiani G. Rapatzikou has commented, in ''Gothic Motifs in the Fiction of William Gibson'', on the origin of the notion of cyberspace:


In his Sprawl and Bridge trilogies, Gibson is credited with being one of the few observers to explore the portents of the information age for notions of the sociospatial structuring of cities. Not all responses to Gibson's visions have been positive, however; virtual reality pioneer Mark Pesce, though acknowledging their heavy influence on him and that "no other writer had so eloquently and emotionally effected the direction of the hacker community," dismissed them as "adolescent fantasies of violence and disembodiment". In ''Pattern Recognition'', the plot revolves around snippets of film footage posted anonymously to various locations on the Internet. Characters in the novel speculate about the filmmaker's identity, motives, methods and inspirations on several websites, anticipating the 2006 Lonelygirl15 internet phenomenon. However, Gibson later disputed the notion that the creators of Lonelygirl15 drew influence from him.August 14, 2006 edition of the free daily ''Metro International'', interview by Amy Benfer (amybenfer (at) metro.us) Another phenomenon anticipated by Gibson is the rise of reality television, for example in ''Virtual Light'', which featured a satirical extrapolated version of ''COPS''.
 
For his part, Gibson rejects any notion of prophecy, never having had a special relationship with computers; until 1996 he had neither an email address nor a modem, a lack he explained at the time to have been motivated by a desire to avoid correspondence that would distract him from writing. His first exposure to a website came while writing ''Idoru'' when he was persuaded to let a web developer, Chris Halcrow, build one for him. An anecdote often recited in cybercultural enclaves and English departments holds that ''Neuromancer'' was written on a manual typewriter; the author has confirmed that the novel was written on a 1927 model of an olive-green Hermes portable typewriter, which looked to him as "the kind of thing Hemingway would have used in the field". In 2007, he said:
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d18ad96001447b77b228d6caade114b6" name="Scylla-_a_book_of_the_dead" sectnum="4.13#1">../img/d18ad96001447b77b228d6caade114b6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>