<document id="1ff6e9d545f63633959771e856dc600f-3.9" name="William_Gibson" cat="17">
<text>
Gibson was first solicited to work as a screenwriter after a film producer discovered a waterlogged copy of ''Neuromancer'' on a beach at a Thai resort. His early efforts to write film scripts failed to manifest themselves as finished product; "Burning Chrome" (which was to be directed by Kathryn Bigelow) and "Neuro-Hotel" were two attempts by the author at film adaptations that were never made. In the late 1980s he wrote an early version of ''Alien 3'' (which he later characterized as "Tarkovskian"), few elements of which survived in the final version.
Gibson's early involvement with the film industry extended far beyond the confines of the Hollywood blockbuster system. At one point, he collaborated on a script with Kazakh director Rashid Nugmanov after an American producer had expressed an interest in a Soviet-American collaboration to star Russian-Korean star Victor Tsoi. Despite being occupied with writing a novel, Gibson was reluctant to abandon the "wonderfully odd project" which involved "ritualistic gang-warfare in some sort of sideways-future Leningrad" and sent Jack Womack to Russia in his stead. Rather than producing a motion picture, a prospect that ended after Tsoi's death in an automotive accident, Womack's experiences in Russia ultimately culminated in his novel ''Let's Put the Future Behind Us'' and informed much of the Russian content of Gibson's ''Pattern Recognition''. A similar fate befell Gibson's collaboration with Japanese filmmaker Sogo Ishii in 1991, a film they plotted on shooting in the Walled City of Kowloon until the city was demolished in 1993.

Adaptations of Gibson's fiction have frequently been optioned and proposed, to limited success. Two of the author's short stories, both set in the Sprawl trilogy universe, have been loosely adapted as films: ''Johnny Mnemonic'' (1995) with screenplay by Gibson and starring Keanu Reeves, Dolph Lundgren and Takeshi Kitano, and ''New Rose Hotel'' (1998), starring Christopher Walken, Willem Dafoe, and Asia Argento. The former was the first time in history that a book was launched simultaneously as a film and a CD-ROM interactive video game. ''Neuromancer'', after a long stay in development hell, is in the process of adaptation , ''Count Zero'' was at one point being developed as ''The Zen Differential'' with director Michael Mann attached, and the third novel in the Sprawl trilogy, ''Mona Lisa Overdrive'', has also been optioned and bought. An anime adaptation of ''Idoru'' was announced as in development in 2006, and ''Pattern Recognition'' was in the process of development by director Peter Weir, although according to Gibson the latter is no longer attached to the project.

Television is another arena in which Gibson has collaborated; he co-wrote with friend Tom Maddox, ''The X-Files'' episodes "Kill Switch" and "First Person Shooter", broadcast in the U.S. on 20th Century Fox Television in 1998 and 2000. In 1998 he contributed the introduction to the spin-off publication ''Art of the X-Files''. Gibson made a cameo appearance in the television miniseries ''Wild Palms'' at the behest of creator Bruce Wagner. Director Oliver Stone had borrowed heavily from Gibson's novels to make the series, and in the aftermath of its cancellation Gibson contributed an article, "Where The Holograms Go", to the ''Wild Palms Reader''. He accepted another acting role in 2002, appearing alongside Douglas Coupland in the short film ''Mon Amour Mon Parapluie'' in which the pair played philosophers. Appearances in fiction aside, Gibson was the focus of a biographical documentary by Mark Neale in 2000 called ''No Maps for These Territories''. The film follows Gibson over the course of a drive across North America discussing various aspects of his life, literary career and cultural interpretations. It features interviews with Jack Womack and Bruce Sterling, as well as recitations from ''Neuromancer'' by Bono and The Edge.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="15d168fa6c710a906f1594b8f464a32e" name="The_Neuromancer" sectnum="3.9#1">../img/15d168fa6c710a906f1594b8f464a32e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>