<document id="200b0491fda29647e3eeb0a0c0c0deec-4" name="Farthest_South" cat="14">
<text>
In the wake of Shackleton’s near miss, Captain Scott organised the Terra Nova Expedition, 1910&ndash;13, in which securing the South Pole for the British Empire was an explicitly stated prime objective.Crane, p. 397 As he planned his expedition, Scott saw no reason to believe that his effort would be contested. However, the Norwegian explorer Roald Amundsen, who had been developing plans for a North Pole expedition, changed his mind when, in September 1909, the North Pole was claimed in quick succession by the Americans Frederick Cook and Robert Peary. Amundsen resolved to go south instead.Huntford, pp. 207&ndash;08

Amundsen concealed his revised intentions until his ship, ''Fram'', was in the Atlantic and beyond communication.Huntford, pp. 283&ndash;88 Scott was notified by telegram that a rival was in the field, but had little choice other than to continue with his own plans.Huntford, p. 299 Meanwhile, ''Fram'' arrived at the Ross Ice Shelf on 11 January 1911, and by 14 January had found the inlet, or "Bay of Whales", where Borchgrevink had made his landing eleven years earlier. This was to be the location of Amundsen's base camp, ''Framheim''.Huntford, pp. 297&ndash;98

After nine months’ preparation, Amundsen's polar journey began on 20 October 1911.Amundsen, p. 1 Avoiding the known route to the polar plateau via the Beardmore Glacier,  Amundsen led his party of five  due south, reaching the Transantarctic Mountains on 16 November.Amundsen, pp. 33&ndash;40  They ascended to the plateau via the newly discovered Axel Heiberg Glacier, and made the final march to the Pole. Shackleton's Farthest South was passed on 7 December and the Pole itself, at 90°S, was reached on 15 December 1911.Amundsen, pp 120&ndash;30  The Norwegian party's greater skills with the techniques of ice travel, using ski and dogs, had proved decisive.   Captain Scott's five-man team reached the same point 33 days later, and perished during their return journey.Crane, p. 543  Since Cook's journeys, every expedition that had held the Farthest South record before Amundsen's conquest had been British;  however, the final triumph indisputably belonged to the Norwegians.Huntford, p.511
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8860f9a09b575349b6fbc9b8dfb73dea" name="Amundsen-in-ice" sectnum="4#1">../img/8860f9a09b575349b6fbc9b8dfb73dea.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>