<document id="200b0491fda29647e3eeb0a0c0c0deec-1.3" name="Farthest_South" cat="14">
<text>
Drake sailed from Plymouth on 15 November 1577, in command of a fleet of five ships under his flagship ''Pelican'', later renamed the ''Golden Hinde''. His principal objective was plunder, not exploration; his initial targets were the unfortified Spanish towns on the Pacific coasts of Chile and Peru. Following Magellan's route, Drake reached Puerto San Julian on 20 June. After nearly two months in harbour, Drake left the port with a reduced fleet of three ships and a small pinnace.  His ships entered the Magellan Strait on 23 August and emerged in the Pacific Ocean on 6 September.Knox-Johnston, pp. 40&ndash;45

Drake set a course to the north-west, but on the following day a gale scattered the ships. The ''Marigold'' was sunk by a giant wave; the ''Elizabeth'' managed to return into the Magellan Strait, later sailing eastwards back to England; the pinnace was lost later. The gales persisted for more than seven weeks. The ''Golden Hinde'' was driven far to the west and south, before clawing its way back towards land. On 22 October the ship anchored off an island which Drake named "Elizabeth Island", where wood for the galley fires was collected and seals and penguins captured for food.

According to Drake's Portuguese pilot, Nuño Da Silva, their position at the anchorage was 57°S. However, there is no island at that latitude. The as yet undiscovered Diego Ramirez Islands, at 56°30'S, are treeless and cannot have been the islands where Drake's crew collected wood. This indicates that the navigational calculation was faulty, and that Drake landed at or near Cape Horn, possibly on Horn Island itself. His final southern latitude can only be speculated as that of Cape Horn, at 55°59'S. In his report, Drake wrote: "The Uttermost Cape or headland of all these islands stands near 56 degrees, without which there is no main island to be seen to the southwards but that the Atlantic Ocean and the South Sea meet." This open sea south of Cape Horn became known as the Drake Passage.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="730e48546fe2fa1ad1acf2201a9acfce" name="1590_or_later_Marcus_Gheeraerts,_Sir_Francis_Drake_Buckland_Abbey,_Devon" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/730e48546fe2fa1ad1acf2201a9acfce.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>