<document id="2073fc20368af309007bb4adef0f086b-8.10" name="The_Protocols_of_the_Elders_of_Zion" cat="14">
<text>
''United We Fall, Divided We Stand'' Patriotic Publishing Co. (1934), Cover

In 1920-1921, the history of the concepts found in the ''Protocols'' was traced back to the works of Goedsche and Jacques Crétineau-Joly by Lucien Wolf (an English Jewish journalist), and published in London in August 1921. But a dramatic expose occurred in the series of articles in ''The Times'' by its Constantinople reporter, Philip Graves, who discovered the plagiarism from the work of Maurice Joly.


According to writer Peter Grose, Allen Dulles, who was in Constantinople developing relationships in post-Ottoman political structures, discovered 'the source' of the documentation ultimately provided to ''The Times''. Grose writes that ''The Times'' extended a loan to the source, a Russian émigré who refused to be identified, with the understanding the loan would not be repaid.Peter Grose, in ''Gentleman Spy: The Life of Allen Dulles'' (Houghton Mifflin 1994) Colin Holmes, a lecturer in economic history of Sheffield University, identified the émigré as Michael Raslovleff, a self-identified antisemite, who gave the information to Graves so as not to "give a weapon of any kind to the Jews, whose friend I have never been."Poliakov, Leon (1997). "Protocols of the Learned Elders of Zion". ''Encyclopedia Judaica'' (CD-ROM Edition Version 1.0). Ed. Cecil Roth. Keter Publishing House. ISBN 965-07-0665-8

In the first article of Graves' series, titled "A Literary Forgery", the editors of ''The Times'' wrote, "our Constantinople Correspondent presents for the first time conclusive proof that the document is in the main a clumsy plagiarism. He has forwarded us a copy of the French book from which the plagiarism is made." by Philip Graves published at ''The Times'', August 16–18, 1921 ''The New York Times'' reprinted the articles on September 4, 1921.''The New York Times'', September 4, 1921. Front page, Section 7 In the same year, an entire book documenting the hoax was published in the United States by Herman Bernstein. Despite this widespread and extensive debunking, the ''Protocols'' continued to be regarded as important factual evidence by antisemites.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="dff1e4b015fe249bbc3ebbfa351dbc74" name="19210816_TheTimes_exposes_TheProtocols_as_a_forgery" sectnum="8.10#1">../img/dff1e4b015fe249bbc3ebbfa351dbc74.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>