<document id="209b0d8044e70a837f15e22d7566b41c-5" name="War_of_the_League_of_Cambrai" cat="29">
<text>
In late May 1513, a French army commanded by Louis de la Trémoille crossed the Alps and advanced on Milan; at the same time, Bartolomeo d'Alviano and the Venetian army marched west from Padua.  The unpopularity of Maximilian Sforza, who was seen by the Milanese as a puppet of his Swiss mercenaries, enabled the French to move through Lombardy with little resistance; Trémoille, having seized Milan, besieged the remaining Swiss in Novara.  On 6 June, the French were attacked by a Swiss relief army at the Battle of Novara, and were routed despite having superior numbers.Oman, ''Art of War'', 153–154; Taylor, ''Art of War in Italy'', 123.  Detachments of the Swiss army pursued the fleeing French over the Alps and had reached Dijon before being bribed into withdrawing.Goubert, ''Course of French History'', 135.

The rout at Novara inaugurated a period of continuous defeats for the French alliance.  English troops under Henry VIII attacked La Palice at the Battle of Guinegate, scattered the French forces, and proceeded to sack Thérouanne.  In Navarre, resistance to Ferdinand's invasion collapsed; he rapidly consolidated his hold over the entire region and moved to support another English offensive in the Guyenne.Kamen, ''Empire'', 35.  James IV of Scotland invaded England at the behest of Louis;Guicciardini, ''History of Italy'', 280. but he failed to draw Henry's attention from France, and his death—and the Scots' disastrous defeat—at the Battle of Flodden Field on 9 September 1513, ended Scotland's brief involvement in the war.



Meanwhile, Alviano, unexpectedly left without French support, retreated into the Veneto, pursued closely by the Spanish army under Cardona. While the Spanish were unable to capture Padua in the face of determined Venetian resistance, they penetrated deep into Venetian territory and by late September were in sight of Venice itself.  Cardona attempted a bombardment of the city that proved largely ineffective; then, having no boats with which to cross the lagoon, turned back for Lombardy. Alviano, having been reinforced by hundreds of volunteers from the Venetian nobility, pursued Cardona and confronted him outside Vicenza on 7 October. In the resulting Battle of La Motta, the Venetian army was decisively defeated, with many prominent noblemen cut down outside the city walls as they attempted to flee.Norwich, ''History of Venice'', 429.

However, the Holy League failed to follow up on these victories.  Cardona and Alviano continued to skirmish in the Friuli for the rest of 1513 and through 1514, fighting several inconclusive battles, but Cardona was unable to make any real progress. Henry VIII, having failed to gain any significant territory, concluded a separate peace with France.Guicciardini, ''History of Italy'', 282.  Finally, the death of Julius left the League without a leader; Julius' successor to the Papacy, Leo X, was rather less concerned with military matters.

The death of Louis XII on 1 January 1515 brought Francis I to the throne. Having assumed the title of Duke of Milan at his coronation, Francis immediately moved to reclaim his holdings in Italy. By July, Francis had assembled an army in the Dauphiné. A combined Swiss and Papal force moved north from Milan to block the Alpine passes against him, but Francis, following the advice of Gian Giacomo Trivulzio, avoided the main passes and marched instead through the valley of the Stura.Norwich, ''History of Venice'', 430.  The French vanguard surprised the Milanese cavalry at Villafranca, capturing Prospero Colonna;Taylor, ''Art of War in Italy'', 67. meanwhile, Francis and the main body of the French confronted the Swiss at the Battle of Marignano on 13 September. The Swiss advance initially made headway; however, Francis's superiority in cavalry and artillery, together with the timely arrival of Alviano (who had successfully avoided Cardona's army at Verona) on the morning of 14 September, led to a strategically decisive victory for Francis and the Venetians.Norwich, ''History of Venice'', 431.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="970a65c985d96ad55d9ad2d005027f28" name="Marignano" sectnum="5#1">../img/970a65c985d96ad55d9ad2d005027f28.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>