<document id="210b96cec978233c16313a9ea1e7e9ee-5" name="Sebastian_Shaw_(actor)" cat="19">
<text>
In 1982, Shaw was chosen for the small but crucial role of Anakin Skywalker in ''Return of the Jedi'', the third and final movie in the original Star Wars trilogy. Although David Prowse played the costumed scenes and James Earl Jones voiced Skywalker's Darth Vader alter-ego, just as they had in the first two films, Shaw was cast in a single scene with Mark Hamill, during the moment aboard ''Death Star II'' when Anakin's son Luke unmasks his dying father. Since the scene was arguably the emotional climax of the film, the casting crew wanted an experienced actor for the role. 

When Shaw arrived at the set for filming, he ran into his friend Ian McDiarmid, the actor playing Emperor Palpatine. When McDiarmid asked him what he was doing there, Shaw responded, "I don't know, dear boy, I think it's something to do with science-fiction."Chernoff, Scott. "Ian McDiarmid: An Interview with the Emperor." ''Star Wars Insider'', iss. 37, April/May 1998, pg. 33. His presence during the filming was kept secret from all but the minimum cast and crew, and Shaw himself was contractually obligated not to discuss any film secrets with anyone, even his family. The unmasking scene, directed by Richard Marquand, was filmed in one day and required only a few takes, with no alteration from the original dialogue. 

''Star Wars'' creator George Lucas also personally directed Shaw for his appearance in the final scene of the movie, in which he is a Force ghost of Anakin Skywalker. When the movie was re-released on DVD in 2004, Shaw's image in this scene was replaced with that of Hayden Christensen, who played Anakin in two of the prequel films. This attempt to tie the prequel and original trilogies together proved to be one of the least popular changes in the ''Star Wars'' re-releases, although some defended the move.Johnson, Derek. "Star Wars fans, DVD, and cultural ownership: an interview with Will Brooker; Interview," ''Velvet Light Trap'', 22 September 2005, pg. 36–44.Ebert, Roger. "Anakin's fans strike back," ''Chicago Sun-Times'', 1 May 2005, Sunday Showcase (section), pg. 3.
  
Although Shaw's unmasking scene lasted only two minutes and seven seconds and included just 24 words of dialogue spoken by Shaw,''Star Wars Episode VI: Return of the Jedi'' (1983), written by George Lucas and Lawrence Kasdan, directed by Richard Marquand. he received more fan mail and autograph requests from ''Return of the Jedi'' than he had for any role in his career. He later reflected that he very much enjoyed his experience filming for ''Return of the Jedi'' and expressed particular surprise that an action figure was made of him from the film.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3c81a8f84764fc1d59a812758d230e51" name="Sebastian_Shaw_as_Anakin_Skywalker" sectnum="5#1">../img/3c81a8f84764fc1d59a812758d230e51.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>