<document id="217933d54f2bc79e513ec03e29e330e9-2.1" name="Trevor_Linden" cat="26">
<text>
Linden made his NHL debut on October 6, 1988 against the Winnipeg Jets, aged 18. He scored his first goal on October 18, 1988, against Kelly Hrudey of the New York Islanders and later, on November 17, he scored his first hat trick against the Minnesota North Stars. Linden finished the season tied for the team lead in goals (30) and second for points (59). He was the first Canucks rookie to score 30 goals. Linden also became the first rookie to win the Cyclone Taylor Award, given to the Canucks' most valuable player. He was named to the NHL All-Rookie Team, and finished second to Brian Leetch, of the New York Rangers, in voting for the Calder Trophy, given to the rookie of the year. The Canucks made the playoffs in the 1988–89 season, for the first time in three years, and Linden scored seven points in the Canucks' seven-game series loss to the eventual Stanley Cup champion Calgary Flames.

In his sophomore NHL season, Linden finished second on the team in goals, with 21, and points, 51, and finished third in assists with 30. The following year, he was one of three Canucks to share a rotating captaincy (the others being Doug Lidster and Dan Quinn). Linden led the team with 37 assists and 70 points, and made his first appearance in an NHL All-Star Game, where he was the youngest player. At the age of 21, he was made sole captain of the team, becoming the youngest Canucks captain. That season, Linden led the Canucks in scoring for a second straight year with 75 points (31 goals and 44 assists), leading the Canucks to their first division title since the 1974–75 season.  They repeated as Smythe Division champions the following year, setting franchise records for wins and points. For the third straight season, Linden surpassed 30 goals and 70 points, finishing with totals of 33 goals and 72 points.


In the 1993–94 season, Linden scored 32 goals, the fifth time in six seasons he had scored at least 30, but his points total fell to 61 as the Canucks finished 10 points behind the division leader. Although they were the seventh seed in the playoffs, the Canucks reached the Stanley Cup Finals for the first time in 12 years and second time in team history. Playing the New York Rangers, Linden went up against Rangers captain Mark Messier and led the Canucks to a seventh and deciding game. Despite two goals by Linden, the Canucks lost, 3–2. Linden finished second on the team in playoff scoring, with 12 goals and 25 points.

In the 1995–96 season, Linden had 33 goals, 47 assists and 80 points, the most he has ever collected in all three statistical categories. The following season marked the end of Linden's ironman streak; between October 4, 1990 and December 3, 1996, he appeared in 482 consecutive games, the longest in the league at the time. The streak established a Canucks record (broken in 2007 by Brendan Morrison). In his 49 games that season, he scored nine goals and 31 assists. At the conclusion of the season, the NHL recognized Linden's contributions to the Vancouver community and awarded him the King Clancy Memorial Trophy.

At the start of the 1997–98 season, the Canucks added free agent Mark Messier, a six-time Stanley Cup winner, and coach Mike Keenan, who were, respectively,  captain and coach, of the New York Rangers when they defeated Vancouver in the Stanley Cup finals. Friction developed between Linden and Keenan early in the season.  As the relationship worsened, Keenan claimed that it was evident that Linden would be traded. After a 5-1 loss to the St. Louis Blues, Keenan openly blamed Linden for the loss, a moment Linden refers to as his "darkest time". Playing in 42 games with the Canucks before the February Olympic break, Linden had seven goals and 21 points.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e3bedcc0454d1f5e442fc4af02a676aa" name="Lindenmclean1994" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/e3bedcc0454d1f5e442fc4af02a676aa.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>