<document id="217b135bb5d9d6250ed8fba9bbf03a38-6" name="California_Condor" cat="3">
<text>
Throughout its historic range, the California Condor has been a popular subject of mythology and an important symbol to Native Americans. Unusually,Nielsen 2006, p. 39 this bird takes on different roles in the storytelling of the different tribes.

The Wiyot tribe of California say that the condor recreated mankind after Above Old Man wiped humanity out with a flood.Nielsen 2006, p. 37 However, other tribes, like California's Mono, viewed the condor as a destroyer, not a creator. They say that Condor seized humans, cut off their heads, and drained their blood so that it would flood Ground Squirrel's home. Condor then seized Ground Squirrel after he fled, but Ground Squirrel managed to cut off Condor's head when Condor paused to take a drink of the blood.Nielsen 2006, p. 38 According to the Yokut tribe, the condor sometimes ate the moon, causing the lunar cycle, and his wings caused eclipses.Nielsen 2006, p. 40 The Chumash tribe of Southern California believed that the condor was once a white bird, but it turned black when it flew too close to a fire.

Condor bones have been found in Native American graves, as have condor feather headdresses. Cave paintings of condors have also been discovered.Nielsen 2006, p. 36 Some tribes ritually killed condors to make ceremonial clothing out of their feathers. Shamans then danced while wearing these to reach the upper and lower spiritual worlds. Whenever a shaman died, his clothes were said to be cursed,Nielsen 2006, p. 41 so new clothing had to be made for his successor. Some scientists, such as Noel Snyder, believe that this process of making ceremonial clothing helped contribute to the condor's decline. If so, this would be the only known species that was endangered by the California natives.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="09abe89217c160dd92c554fa41e523f2" name="Rafael,_a_Chumash_who_shared_cultural_knowledge_with_Anthropologists" sectnum="6#1">../img/09abe89217c160dd92c554fa41e523f2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>