<document id="221cdfb73049678e244380b45872cbb2-9" name="Turkey" cat="11">
<text>
The population of Turkey stood at 71.5 million with a growth rate of 1.31% per annum, based on the 2008 Census. It has an average population density of 92 persons per km². The proportion of the population residing in urban areas is 70.5%. People within the 15–64 age group constitute 66.5% of the total population, the 0–14 age group corresponds 26.4% of the population, while 65 years and higher of age correspond to 7.1% of the total population. Life expectancy stands at 70.67 years for men and 75.73 years for women, with an overall average of 73.14 years for the populace as a whole. Education is compulsory and free from ages 6 to 15. The literacy rate is 95.3% for men and 79.6% for women, with an overall average of 87.4%. The low figures for women are mainly due to the traditional customs of the Arabs and Kurds who live in the southeastern provinces of the country.


Article 66 of the Turkish Constitution defines a "Turk" as "anyone who is bound to the Turkish state through the bond of citizenship"; therefore, the legal use of the term "Turkish" as a citizen of Turkey is different from the ethnic definition. However, the majority of the Turkish population are of Turkish ethnicity. Other major ethnic groups (large portions of whom have been extensively Turkicized since the Seljuk and Ottoman periods) include the Abkhazians, Adjarians, Albanians, Arabs, Assyrians, Bosniaks, Circassians, Hamshenis, Kurds, Laz, Pomaks, Roma, Zazas and the three officially recognized minorities (per the Treaty of Lausanne), i.e. the Armenians, Greeks and Jews. Signed on January 30, 1923, a bilateral accord of population exchange between Greece and Turkey took effect in the 1920s, with close to 1.5 million Greeks moving from Turkey and some 500,000 Turks coming from Greece.. Spiegel Online. November 28, 2006. Minorities of West European origin include the Levantines (or ''Levanter'', mostly of French, Genoese and Venetian descent) who have been present in the country (particularly in Istanbul and İzmir) since the medieval period; or the Bosporus Germans and Istanbul Poles who have lived in Turkey since the 19th century. There is also a population of Afro-Turks within Turkey who mostly live in the western coastal cities of the country and are largely mixed with the local population through intermarriage. The Kurds, a distinct ethnic group concentrated mainly in the southeastern provinces of the country, are the largest non-Turkic ethnicity. Minorities other than the three officially recognized ones do not have any special group privileges, while the term "minority" itself remains a sensitive issue in Turkey. Reliable data on the exact ethnic repartition of the population is not available since the Turkish census figures do not include racial figures. 

The Sultan Ahmed Mosque in Istanbul
Turkish is the sole official language throughout Turkey. Reliable figures for the linguistic repartition of the populace are not available for reasons similar to those cited above. Nevertheless, the public broadcaster TRT broadcasts programmes in local languages and dialects of Arabic, Bosnian, Circassian and Kurdish a few hours a week. A fully fledged Kurdish language television channel, TRT 6, was opened in early 2009. 

Turkey is a secular state with no official state religion, the Turkish Constitution provides for freedom of religion and conscience. According to 2009 data on the world's Muslim populations, 73.6 million people in Turkey are Muslims or 98% of the total population. The majority of the Muslims are Sunni (85-90%) and a large minority are Alevi (10-15%), a sect within Twelver Shi'a Islam, numbering from 7–11 million. The highest Islamic religious authority is the Presidency of Religious Affairs (), it interprets the Hanafi school of law, and is responsible for regulating the operation of the country's 75,000 registered mosques and employing local and provincial imams. Based on a nationwide survey in 2007 however, it showed 96.8% of Turkish citizens have a religion, while 3.2% are irreligious and atheists. There are less than 100,000 minorities which follow other religions, Today's Zaman (2008-12-15). Retrieved on 2009-08-23. mainly Christians, mostly Armenian Apostolic and Greek Orthodox (64,000 people) and Jews, mainly Sephardi (26,000 people). According to a Pew Research Center report in 2002, 65% of the people believe ''"religion is very important"'', while according to a Eurobarometer poll in 2005, 95% of citizens responded that they believe ''"there is a God"''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9002bc82ace4a8106a439b012b30e3b6" name="Istiklal_Avenue_in_Istanbul_on_3_June_2007" sectnum="9#1">../img/9002bc82ace4a8106a439b012b30e3b6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>