<document id="221e9180b4ea873a01f2097990d22358-3.11.3" name="John_Churchill,_1st_Duke_of_Marlborough" cat="25">
<text>
While Marlborough fought in the Low Countries a series of personal and party rivalries instigated a general reversal of fortune.Churchill: ''Marlborough: His Life and Times, Bk. 2'', 193 The Whigs, who were the main prop of the war, had been laying siege Godolphin. As a price for supporting the government in the next parliamentary session, the Whigs demanded a share of public office with the appointment of a leading member of their Junto, the Earl of Sunderland (Marlborough's son-in-law), to the post of Secretary of State.Churchill: ''Marlborough: His Life and Times, Bk. 2'', 196 The Queen, who loathed Sunderland and the Junto, and who refused to be dominated by any single party, bitterly opposed the move; but Godolphin, increasingly dependent on Whig support, had little room for manoeuvre. With Sarah's tactless, unsubtle backing, Godolphin relentlessly pressed the Queen to submit to Whig demands. In despair, Anne finally relented and Sunderland received the seals of office; but the special relationship between Godolphin, Sarah, and the Queen had taken a severe blow and she began to turn increasingly to a new favourite –  Sarah's cousin, Abigail Masham. Anne also became ever more reliant on the advice of Harley, who, convinced that the ''duumvirate's'' policy of appeasing the Whig Junto was unnecessary, had set himself up as alternative source of advice to a sympathetic Queen.Barnet: ''Marlborough'', 195 

John Churchill, 1st Duke of Marlborough, by Godfrey Kneller. Late 17th or early 18th century.

Following his victory at Ramillies Marlborough returned to England and the acclamation of Parliament; his titles and estates were made perpetual upon his heirs, male or female, in order that 'the memory of these deeds should never lack one of his name to bear it'.Churchill: ''Marlborough: His Life and Times Bk. 2'', 214 However, the Allied successes were followed in 1707 with a resurgence in French arms in all fronts of the war, and a return to political squabbling and indecision within the Grand Alliance. The Great Northern War also threatened dire consequences. The French had hoped to entice Charles XII, King of Sweden, to attack the Empire regarding grievances over the Polish Succession, but in a pre-campaign visit to the King's headquarters at Altranstädt, Marlborough's diplomacy helped placate Charles and prevent his interference regarding the Spanish Succession. Nevertheless, major setbacks in Spain at Almanza and along the Rhine in Southern Germany, had caused Marlborough great anxiety and made the Dutch even less cooperative, vetoing the Duke's plans for any major action in the Low Countries.Chandler: ''Marlborough as Military Commander'', 195 Prince Eugene's retreat from Toulon (Marlborough's major goal for 1707), ended any lingering hopes of a war-winning blow that year.Chandler: ''Marlborough as Military Commander'', 199

Marlborough returned from these tribulations to a political storm as the Ministry's critics turned to attack the overall conduct of the war. The Duke and Godolphin had initially agreed to explore a 'moderate scheme' with Harley and reconstruct the government, but they were incensed when Harley privately criticised the management of the war in Spain to the Queen, and his associate Henry St John, the Secretary at War, raised the issue in Parliament. Convinced of Harley’s caballing, the duumvirs threatened the Queen with resignation unless she dismissed him. Anne fought stubbornly to keep her favourite minister, but when the Duke of Somerset and the Earl of Pembroke refused to act without 'the General nor the Treasurer', Harley resigned: Henry Boyle replaced him as Secretary of State, and his fellow Whig, Robert Walpole, replaced St John as Secretary at War.Churchill: ''Marlborough: His Life and Times, Bk. 2'', 313 The struggle had given Marlborough a final lease of power but it was a Whig victory, and he had to a large extent lost his hold on the Queen.Churchill: ''A History of the English-Speaking Peoples: Age of Revolution'', 58
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0c6219119987f0d05f918e253d1339bc" name="RobertHarley1710" sectnum="3.11.3#1">../img/0c6219119987f0d05f918e253d1339bc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>