<document id="221e9180b4ea873a01f2097990d22358-2.4" name="John_Churchill,_1st_Duke_of_Marlborough" cat="25">
<text>
Under the Earl of Danby the government now undertook a political realignment, and prepared to enter the war against France. The new alliance with the Dutch, together with the expansion of the English army, opened important prospects for Churchill in military and diplomatic spheres. In April 1678, Churchill (accompanied by his friend and rising politician, Sidney Godolphin), departed for The Hague to negotiate a convention on the deployment of the English army in Flanders. The young diplomat's essay in international statecraft proved personally successful, bringing him into contact with William, Prince of Orange, who was highly impressed by the shrewdness and courtesy of Churchill's negotiating skills.Barnett: ''Marlborough'', 43 The assignment had helped Churchill develop a breadth of experience that other mere soldiers were never to achieve, yet because of the duplicitous dealings of Charles II's secret negotiations with Louis XIV (Charles had no intention of waging war against France), the mission ultimately proved abortive. In May, Churchill was appointed temporary rank of Brigadier-General of Foot, but hopes of promised action on the Continent proved illusory as the warring factions sued for peace and signed the Treaty of Nijmegen.Chandler: ''Marlborough as Military Commander'', 10 



When Churchill returned to England at the end of 1678 he found grievous changes in English society. The iniquities of the Popish Plot (Titus Oates' fabricated conspiracy aimed at excluding the Catholic Duke of York from the English accession), meant temporary banishment for James – an exile that would last nearly three years. James obliged Churchill to attend him, first to The Hague then to Brussels, before gaining permission to move to Edinburgh. Yet it was not until 1682, after Charles II's complete victory over the exclusionists, that the Duke of York was allowed to return to London.Holmes: ''Marlborough: England's Fragile Genius'', 92. In the meantime Churchill was dispatched on various important diplomatic missions, including to Paris to further negotiations for a subsidy from Louis XIV, which could help Charles II survive without calling another Parliament, and thus reduce the risk of an Exclusion Bill being passed. For his services during the crisis Churchill was made Lord Churchill of Eyemouth in the peerage of Scotland on 21 December 1682 (O.S), and the following year, on 19 November (O.S), appointed colonel of the King's Own Royal Regiment of Dragoons. Churchill: ''Marlborough: His Life and Times, Bk. 1'', 164

The Churchills' combined income now ensured a life of some style and comfort; as well as maintaining their residence in London (staffed with seven servants), they were also able to purchase Holywell House in St Albans (Sarah Jennings' family home) where their own family could enjoy the benefits of country life. While in Edinburgh Sarah had given birth to Henrietta on 19 July 1681 (O.S). Another daughter, Anne, arrived in 1684, followed by John in 1686, Elizabeth in 1687, Mary in 1689, and Charles in 1690 who lived for only two years.Holmes: ''Marlborough: England's Fragile Genius'', 102

Churchill resumed court life with enthusiasm. In July 1683 he was sent to the Continent to conduct Prince George of Denmark to England for his arranged marriage to the 18-year-old Princess Anne, the Duke of York's younger daughter. Anne lost no time in appointing Sarah – of whom she had been passionately fond since childhood – one of her Ladies of the Bedchamber. Their relationship continued to blossom, so much so that years later Sarah wrote – "To see  was a constant joy; and to part with  for never so short a time, a constant uneasiness … This worked even to the jealousy of a lover."Hibbert: ''The Marlboroughs'', 28 For his part, Churchill treated the princess with respectful affection and grew genuinely attached to her, assuming – in his reverence to royalty – the chivalrous role of a knightly champion.Barnett: ''Marlborough'', 135 From this time forward the Churchills were increasingly detached from James's Catholic inner circle and more noticeably associated with the Princess.Churchill: ''Marlborough: His Life and Times, Bk. 1'', 179
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7ce11be7f8de3df13ff79cfbba6fcbbc" name="The_Marlborough_Family" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/7ce11be7f8de3df13ff79cfbba6fcbbc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>