<document id="221e9180b4ea873a01f2097990d22358-4" name="John_Churchill,_1st_Duke_of_Marlborough" cat="25">
<text>
Resting place of the Duke and Duchess in the chapel at Blenheim Palace.

To military historians David Chandler and Richard Holmes, Marlborough is the greatest British commander in history, an assessment that is shared by others, including the Duke of Wellington who could "conceive nothing greater than Marlborough at the head of an English army." However, the Whig historian, Thomas Macaulay, denigrates Marlborough throughout the pages of his ''History of England'' who, in the words of historian John Wilson Croker, pursues the Duke with "more than the ferocity, and much less than the sagacity, of a bloodhound."Macaulay: ''The History of England'', 32 Macaulay adopted his unfavourable reading of Marlborough straight from Swift and the Tory pamphleteers of the latter part of Anne's reign. According to George Trevelyan, Macaulay 'instinctively desired to make Marlborough's genius stand out bright against the background of his villainy'.Trevelyan: ''England Under Queen Anne'', I, 178 It was in response to Macaulay's ''History'' that Winston Churchill wrote his four volume work, ''Marlborough: His Life and Times''. 

Marlborough was ruthlessly ambitious, relentless in the pursuit of wealth, power and social advancement, earning him a reputation for avarice and miserliness. These traits may have been exaggerated for the purposes of party faction but, notes Trevelyan, nearly all other statesmen of the day were engaged in founding families and amassing estates at the public expense; Marlborough only differed in that he gave the public much more value for their money.Trevelyan: ''England Under Queen Anne'', I, 182 In his quest for fame and personal interests he could be unscrupulous, as his desertion of James II testifies. To Macaulay this is regarded as a piece of selfish treachery against his patron; an analysis shared by G. K. Chesterton: "Churchill, as if to add something ideal to his imitation of Iscariot, went to James with wanton professions of love and loyalty … and then calmly handed over the army to the invader."Chesterton:  ''A Short History of England'', 137 To Trevelyan, Marlborough's behaviour during the 1688 revolution was a sign of his 'devotion to the liberties of England and the Protestant religion'.Trevelyan: ''England Under Queen Anne'', I, 180 However, his continuing correspondence with Saint-Germain was not noble. Although Marlborough did not wish for a Jacobite restoration his double-dealing ensured that William III and George I would never be fully disposed to trust him.Chandler: ''Marlborough as Military Commander'', 317 

Marlborough's weakness during Anne’s reign lay in the English political scene. His determination to preserve the independence of the Queen's administration from control of party faction initially enjoyed full support, but once royal favour turned elsewhere, the Duke, like his key ally Godolphin, found himself isolated; first becoming little more than a servant of the Whigs, then a victim of the Tories.Chandler: ''Marlborough as Military Commander'', 321 His reputation, however, rests more on his record as a soldier than as a statesman or courtier.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1cd0dd388eb685a82388417cc428ff94" name="Blenheim_Column_of_Victory" sectnum="4#1">../img/1cd0dd388eb685a82388417cc428ff94.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>