<document id="22216c7fcd27bcd8759ddac752b81dae-2" name="Red-necked_Grebe" cat="3">
<text>
The Red-necked Grebe is a medium-large grebe, smaller than the Great Crested Grebe of Eurasia, and the Western and Clark's Grebes of North America.Snow & Perrin (1998) 17-20 Sibley (2000) 29 The adult of the nominate European subspecies is 40&ndash;50 cm (15.7&ndash;19.7 in) long with a 77&ndash;85 cm (30.3&ndash;33.5 in) average wingspan,Snow & Perrin (1998) 20&ndash;22 and weighs 692&ndash;925 g (25&ndash;33 oz).  In breeding plumage, it has a black cap that extends below the eye, very pale grey cheeks and throat, a rusty red neck, dark grey back and flanks, and white underparts. The eyes are dark brown and the long, pointed bill is black with a yellow base.Mullarney ''et al.'' 18 


The winter plumage of the Red-necked Grebe is duskier than that of other grebes; its dark grey cap is less defined, and merges into the grey face, and a pale crescent that curves around the rear of the face contrasts with the rest of the head. The front of the neck is whitish or light grey, the hind neck is darker grey, and the yellow of the bill is less obvious than in summer.Mullarney ''et al.'' 18 Although the Red-necked Grebe is unmistakable in breeding plumage, it is less distinctive in winter and can be confused with similar species. It is larger than the  Slavonian (Horned) Grebe, with a relatively larger bill and a grey, rather than white face. It is closer in size to the Eurasian Great Crested Grebe, but that species is longer-necked, has a more contrasting head pattern, and always shows white above the eye.

The sexes are similar in appearance, although the male averages heavier than the female. Chicks have a striped head and breast, and older juveniles have a striped face, diffuse blackish cap, pale red neck and extensive yellow on the bill.

The subspecies ''P. g. holboelii'' is larger than the nominate race at 43&ndash;56 cm (17&ndash;22 in) length, with a 61&ndash;88 cm (24&ndash;35 in) wingspan, and a weight of 750&ndash;1,600 g (27&ndash;57 oz).Ogilvie & Rose (2002) 92 The plumages are the same as those of the nominate race, although the adult's bill is more extensively yellow. Retrieved 26 August 2008  The difference in size between the sexes is greater than for this subspecies that for ''P. g. grisegena''.

The Red-necked Grebe flies with its long neck extended and its large feet trailing behind the body, which gives it a stretched-out appearance. Fjeldsa (2004) 140 The relatively small wings are grey with white secondaries, and beat very rapidly. Its small wing area means that the grebe is unable to take off from land, Fjeldsa (2004) 31 and needs a lengthy run across water to gain the speed needed for take-off. Johnsgard (1987)  26&ndash;36 Like all grebes, the Red-necked is an expert swimmer; it uses its feet for propulsion underwater, and steers by rotating its legs, since its tail is too short for this purpose. Fjeldsa (2004) 10

This is one of the most vocal grebes during the breeding season, but, like its relatives, it is mainly silent for the rest of the year. It has a loud, wailing or howling display call ''uooooh'', given by a single bird or a pair in duet, by night or during the day, and often from cover. Long sequences of up to 60 consecutive notes may be delivered during singing encounters between rival territorial birds. A great variety of quacking, clucking, hissing, rattling and purring calls are also given, with much individual variation.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0c35c286f098ee5ceca6f93ed59fb40e" name="Podiceps_grisegena9" sectnum="2#1">../img/0c35c286f098ee5ceca6f93ed59fb40e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>