<document id="2245946ee1377bab07388094721a6028-4.3" name="Fighting_in_ice_hockey" cat="26">
<text>
Of the many reasons for fighting, the foremost is for retaliation. When players engage in play that members of the opposing team consider unscrupulous, a fight can ensue. On rare occasions, the fight may be between the assailant and the victim or between the assailant and an enforcer from the victim's team, but most of the time the fight is between any two opposing enforcers. Fights that occur for retaliation purposes can be in immediate response to an on-ice incident, to incidents from earlier in the game, or to actions from past games. Enforcers who intend to start a fight have to consider their timing due to the Instigator rule. For example, putting the opposing team on a power play due to penalties incurred from fighting is less advisable when the game is close.

Enforcers sometimes start fights to build game momentum and provide a psychological advantage over the opposing team. These fights usually involve two enforcers, but may involve any player who is agitating the opposition. This type of fight raises morale on the team of the player who wins, and often gets the home crowd into the game as well. For that reason, it can also be a gamble to start a fight for momentum; if an enforcer loses the fight, the momentum can swing the wrong way.

Intimidation is an important element of a hockey game and some enforcers start fights just to intimidate opposing players in hopes that they will refrain from agitating skilled players. For example, in the late 1950s, Gordie Howe helped establish himself as an enforcer by defeating Lou Fontinato, a notable tough guy who tallied over 1,200 penalty minutes in his career. Fontinato suffered a broken nose from the fight. After that incident, Howe got a lot more space on the ice and was able to score many goals over the span of his career because he intimidated other players. Conversely, games in European professional leagues are known to be less violent than North American games because fighting is discouraged in Europe by ejection and heavy fines. Since the penalties for fighting are so severe, the enforcers are less able to intimidate opposing players with fighting and said players take more liberties on the ice.

For teams that face each other frequently, players may fight just to send the message to the opposing players that they will be the target of agitation or aggression in future games. Teams that are losing by a considerable margin often start these fights near the end of the game when they have nothing to lose. Enforcers may start fights with more skilled players to draw what is called a "reaction penalty", an undisciplined reaction to aggressive play on the part of the enforcer. This practice is also known to be difficult due to the Instigator rule.

Another reason is the protection of star players. Over the history of hockey, many enforcers have been signed simply to protect players like Gretzky, who was protected by Semenko, McSorley and others, and Brett Hull, who was protected by Chase and others.  The NHL averaged twice as many fights during Gretzky's prime with the Edmonton Oilers than it did during the 1970s; some sources credit Gretzky with being a major cause in the statistical rise.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4034eac373d7f8c598b3a15ae76e858e" name="hockeyfight" sectnum="4.3#1">../img/4034eac373d7f8c598b3a15ae76e858e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>