<document id="225e802573317a6a717336ecd2fa0afd-6" name="Henry_Moore" cat="1">
<text>
Most sculptors who emerged during the height of Moore's fame, and in the aftermath of his death, found themselves cast in his shadow. By the late 1930s, Moore was a worldwide celebrity; he was the voice of British sculpture, and of British modernism in general. The next generation was constantly compared against him, and reacted by challenging his legacy, his "establishment" and his position. At the 1952 Venice Biennale, eight new British sculptors produced their ''Geometry of Fear'' works as a direct contrast to the ideals behind Moore's idea of ''Endurance, Continuity''.Causey, 71. 


Herbert Read coined the phrase for these "Young British Sculptors" when he wrote of the Biennale, "Here are images of flight, of ragged claws 'scuttling across the floors of silent seas', of excoriated flesh, frustrated sex, the geometry of fear."Turner, Chris. "", ''Tate Magazine'', issue 6, July/August 2003. Retrieved on 12 September 2008. The works alluded to rib and cage forms, insect shapes, and to aggression and predation. Read drew a direct connection and continuity between these new sculptors—all were under 40—and Moore, but in fact they were driven by a need to find a new beginning in art. Some had no formal artistic education, and, coming from a generation decimated by the war, only sought to be rid of the past.Causey, 72.

Yet Moore had a direct influence on several generations of sculptors of both British and international reputation. Among the artists who have acknowledged Moore's importance to their work are Sir Anthony Caro,. anthonycaro.org. Retrieved on 04 September 2008. Phillip King"". sculpture.org.uk. Retrieved on 06 September 2008. and Isaac Witkin,". ''The Times'', 10 May 2006. Retrieved on 29 August 2008. all three having been assistants to Moore. Other artists whose work was influenced by him include Lynn Chadwick, Eduardo Paolozzi, Bernard Meadows, Reg Butler, William Turnbull, Robert Adams, Kenneth Armitage, and Geoffrey Clarke."". ''Tate Magazine'', Issue 6, 2008. Retrieved 23 August 2008. 

Today, the Henry Moore Foundation manages the Henry Moore Institute in Leeds which supports exhibitions and research activities in international sculpture. By the Foundation's own admission, popular interest in Moore's work has declined since his death, yet the institutions he endowed continue to play an essential role in promoting contemporary art in the United Kingdom."". Henry Moore Foundation, 2008. Retrieved on 22 September 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e2dec864299bec243ea9c4d1a7d9508b" name="Caro_DreamCity_1996" sectnum="6#1">../img/e2dec864299bec243ea9c4d1a7d9508b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>