<document id="2284399857f7b5e1b8ceec9c66c13f0c-1.4.8" name="AC/DC" cat="20">
<text>
In 1994, Angus and Malcolm invited Rudd to several jam sessions. He was eventually rehired to replace Slade, whose amicable departure arose in part because of the band's strong desire to again work with Rudd. In 1995, with the 1980–83 line-up back together, the group released ''Ballbreaker'', recorded at the Ocean Way Studios in Los Angeles, California, and produced by Rick Rubin. The first single from the album was "Hard as a Rock". Two more singles were released from the album: "Hail Caesar" and "Cover You in Oil".
In 1997, a box set named ''Bonfire'' was released. It contained four albums; a remastered version of ''Back in Black''; ''Volts'' (a disc with alternate takes, outtakes, and stray live cuts) and two live albums, ''Live from the Atlantic Studios'' and ''Let There Be Rock: The Movie''. ''Live from the Atlantic Studios'' was recorded on 7 December 1977 at the Atlantic Studios in New York. ''Let There Be Rock: The Movie'' was a double album recorded in 1979 at the Pavillon de Paris and was the soundtrack of a motion picture, ''AC/DC: Let There Be Rock''. The US version of the box set included a colour booklet, a two-sided poster, a sticker, a temporary tattoo, a keychain bottle opener, and a guitar pick.

In 2000, the band released ''Stiff Upper Lip'', produced by brother George Young at the Warehouse Studio, again in Vancouver. The album was better received by critics than ''Ballbreaker'' but was considered lacking in new ideas. The Australian release included a bonus disc with three promotional videos and several live performances recorded in Madrid, Spain in 1996. ''Stiff Upper Lip'' reached #1 in five countries, including Argentina and Germany; #2 in three countries, Spain, France and Switzerland; #3 in Australia; #5 in Canada and Portugal; and #7 in Norway, the US and Hungary. The first single, "Stiff Upper Lip", remained at #1 on the US Mainstream Rock charts for four weeks. The other singles released also did very well; "Satellite Blues" and "Safe in New York City" reached #7 and #31 on Billboard's Mainstream Rock Tracks, respectively.

In 2002, AC/DC signed a long-term, multi-album deal with Sony Music, who went on to release a series of remastered albums as part of their AC/DC remasters series. Each release contained an expanded booklet featuring rare photographs, memorabilia, and notes. In 2003, the entire back-catalogue (except ''Ballbreaker'' and ''Stiff Upper Lip'') was remastered and re-released. ''Ballbreaker'' was eventually re-released in October 2005; ''Stiff Upper Lip'' was later re-released in April 2007.

On 30 July 2003, the band performed with the Rolling Stones and Rush at Molson Canadian Rocks for Toronto. The concert, held before an audience of half a million, was intended to help the city overcome the negative publicity stemming from the effects of a 2003 SARS epidemic. The concert holds the record for the largest paid music event in North American history. The band came second in a list of Australia's highest-earning entertainers for 2005, and sixth for 2006, despite having neither toured since 2003 nor released an album since 2000. Verizon Wireless has gained the rights to release AC/DC's full albums and the entire ''Live at Donington'' concert to download in 2008.

On 16 October 2007, Columbia Records released a double and triple DVD titled ''Plug Me In''. The set consists of five and seven hours of rare footage, and even a recording of AC/DC at a high school performing "School Days", "T.N.T.", "She's Got Balls", and "It's a Long Way to the Top (If You Wanna Rock 'n' Roll)". As with ''Family Jewels'', disc one contains rare shows of the band with Bon Scott, and disc two is about the Brian Johnson era. The collector's edition contains an extra DVD with 21 more rare performances of both Scott and Johnson and more interviews.

AC/DC made their video game debut on ''Rock Band 2'', with "Let There Be Rock" included as a playable track. The setlist from their ''Live at Donington'' live album was released as playable songs for the ''Rock Band'' series by means of a Wal-Mart-exclusive retail disc titled ''AC/DC Live: Rock Band Track Pack''.

''No Bull: The Directors Cut'', a newly edited, comprehensive Blu-Ray and DVD of the band's July 1996 Plaza De Toros de las Ventas concert in Madrid, Spain, was released on 9 September 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0cc4635e5e4cee910872f2b01b0d7554" name="AngusYoung1" sectnum="1.4.8#1">../img/0cc4635e5e4cee910872f2b01b0d7554.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>