<document id="2284399857f7b5e1b8ceec9c66c13f0c-1.4.9" name="AC/DC" cat="20">
<text>
On 18 August 2008, Columbia Records announced the 18 October Australian release, and 20 October worldwide release, of the studio album ''Black Ice''. The 15-track album was the band's first studio release in eight years, and was produced by Brendan O'Brien. Like ''Stiff Upper Lip'', it was recorded at The Warehouse Studio in Vancouver, British Columbia. ''Black Ice'' was sold in the US exclusively at Wal-Mart and Sam's Club and the band's official website.

"Rock 'n' Roll Train", the album's first single, was released to radio on 28 August. On 15 August, AC/DC recorded a video for a song from the new album in London with a special selection of fans getting the chance to be in the video.

The 18-month Black Ice World Tour supporting the new album was announced on September 11 and began on 28 October in Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania. They band played 42 dates in North America, ending in Nashville, Tennessee on 31 January 2009. The Answer was the opening act during the North American portion of the tour.

On 15 September 2008, AC/DC Radio debuted on Sirius Channel 19 and XM channel 53.  The channel plays AC/DC music along with interviews with the band members.

With the North American release of ''Black Ice'' on 20 October 2008, Columbia Records and Walmart created "Rock Again AC/DC Stores" to promote the album. In October 2008, MTV, Walmart, and Columbia created "AC/DC Rock Band Stores" in New York City, at Times Square, and in Los Angeles. "Black Ice" trucks were also dispatched on the streets of these two cities after the release, playing AC/DC music aloud and making various stops each day to sell merchandise.

In late September 2009, the band rescheduled six shows when Brian Johnson underwent an operation for ulcers. On September 29, the band announced a collection of studio and live rarities, ''Backtracks'', due for release on November 10, 2009 as a 3-CD/2-DVD/1-LP box-set.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f1a1226b459f38419251eb1622fa807a" name="ACDC_-_Toronto_November_7,2008" sectnum="1.4.9#1">../img/f1a1226b459f38419251eb1622fa807a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>