<document id="2284399857f7b5e1b8ceec9c66c13f0c-2" name="AC/DC" cat="20">
<text>
AC/DC were inducted into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame in March 2003. During the ceremony the band performed "Highway to Hell" and "You Shook Me All Night Long", with guest vocals provided by host Steven Tyler of Aerosmith. He described the band's power chords as "the thunder from down under that gives you the second-most-powerful surge that can flow through your body." During the acceptance speech, Brian Johnson quoted their 1977 song "Let There Be Rock".

In May 2003, Malcolm Young accepted a Ted Albert Award for Outstanding Service to Australian Music at the 2003 Music Winners Awards, during which he paid special tribute to Bon Scott.

On 1 October 2004, a central Melbourne thoroughfare, Corporation Lane, was renamed ACDC Lane in honour of the band. However, the City of Melbourne forbade the use of the slash character in street names, so the four letters were combined. The lane is near Swanston Street where, on the back of a truck, the band recorded their video for the 1975 hit "It's a Long Way to the Top (If You Wanna Rock 'n' Roll)". Additionally, a street in Leganés (Comunidad de Madrid - Spain), Spain was named "Calle de AC/DC" on 2 March 2000.

Since Nielsen SoundScan began to track music sales in 1991, AC/DC have sold over $26.4 million worth of albums, making their sales figures second only to The Beatles, outselling both The Rolling Stones and The Who. Over the last five years, as CD sales have declined in general, AC/DC albums have sold just as well or better. They sold over 1.3 million CDs in the US during 2007 despite not having released a new album since 2001 at that point.

In 2009 the Recording Industry Association of America upgraded the group's US sales figures from 69 million to 71 million, making AC/DC the fifth-best-selling band in US history and the ninth-best-selling artist, selling more albums than Madonna, Mariah Carey and Michael Jackson. The RIAA also certified ''Back in Black'' as double Diamond (20 million) in US sales, and by 2007 the album had sold 22 million copies, which moved it into fifth place.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a09e3a2371a2b29934250fa6d1a5bd3f" name="ACDC_Lane" sectnum="2#1">../img/a09e3a2371a2b29934250fa6d1a5bd3f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>