<document id="22a491f82ae4ba10c4423a875ea2fd9a-4.5" name="Ocean_sunfish" cat="3">
<text>
Sunfish are not widely held in aquarium exhibits, due to the unique and demanding requirements of their care. Some Asian aquariums display them, particularly in Japan. The Kaiyukan Aquarium in Osaka, Japan, is one of few aquariums with ''mola'' on display, where it is reportedly as popular an attraction as the larger whale sharks.
The Lisbon Oceanarium in Portugal is another aquarium where sunfish are showcased in the main tank, and in Spain, both the Barcelona Aquarium and  L'Oceanogràfic in Valencia have excellent specimens.

The first ocean sunfish to be held in an aquarium in the United States arrived at the Monterey Bay Aquarium in August 1986. 
Because sunfish had not been kept in captivity on a large scale before, the staff at Monterey Bay were forced to innovate and create their own methods for capture, feeding, and parasite control. By 1998, these issues were overcome, and the aquarium was able to hold a specimen for more than a year, later releasing it after its weight increased by more than fourteen times. ''Mola mola'' have since become a permanent feature of the Outer Bay exhibit. Monterey Bay Aquarium's largest sunfish specimen was euthanized on February 14, 2008 after an extended period of poor health. 

As the ocean sunfish is not highly maneuverable, preventing specimens from injuring themselves by rubbing against the walls of a tank is of major concern to curators. In a smaller tank, hanging a vinyl curtain has been used as a stopgap measure to convert a cuboid tank to a rounded shape and prevent the fish from scraping against the sides. A more effective solution is simply to provide enough room for the sunfish to swim in wide circles. The tank must also be sufficiently deep to accommodate the vertical height of the sunfish, which can be nearly as tall as it is long, and may reach a height of .

Feeding captive sunfish in a tank with other faster-moving, more aggressive fish can also present a challenge. Eventually, the fish can be taught to feed from the end of a pole or from human hands.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8aac0a9a4f2b6af9fc620056f078006f" name="Mola_mola_ocean_sunfish_Monterey_Bay_Aquarium_2" sectnum="4.5#1">../img/8aac0a9a4f2b6af9fc620056f078006f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>