<document id="22ef5d9468d7aa2f806d865b88a27a52-2.2" name="Cannon" cat="29">
<text>
Ahmad Y. al-Hassan claims that the Battle of Ain Jalut in 1260 saw the Mamluks use against the Mongols in "the first cannon in history" gunpowder formulae which were almost identical with the ideal composition for explosive gunpowder, which he claims were not known in China or Europe until much later. However, Iqtidar Alam Khan states that it was invading Mongols who introduced gunpowder to the Islamic world. and cites Mamluk antagonism toward early riflemen in their infantry as an example of how gunpowder weapons were not always met with open acceptance in the Middle East..

The earliest surviving documentary evidence for the use of the hand cannon, considered the oldest type of portable firearm and a forerunner of the handgun, are from several Arabic manuscripts dated to the 14th century. ( and ) Al-Hassan argues that these are based on earlier originals and that they report hand-held cannons being used by the Mamluks at the Battle of Ain Jalut in 1260.

Al-Hassan interprets Ibn Khaldun as reporting the use of cannon as siege machines by the Marinid sultan Abu Yaqub Yusuf at the siege of Sijilmasa in 1274. Sixty-eight super-sized bombards, often referred to as Great Turkish Bombards, were used by the troops of Mehmed II to capture Constantinople, in 1453. Orban, a Hungarian cannon engineer, is credited with the introduction of this cannon from Central Europe to the Ottoman realm. These cannon could fire heavy stone balls a mile, and the sound of their blast could reportedly be heard from a distance of . Great Bombards, also called Dardanelles Guns because of their use in the Dardanelles Operation in the Anglo-Turkish War (1807-1809), were cast in bronze and made in two parts: the chase and the breech, which, together, weighed 18.4 tonnes. The two parts were screwed together using levers to facilitate the work. The Dardanelles Guns were created by Munir Ali in 1464.Schmidtchen, Volker (1977b), "Riesengeschütze des 15. Jahrhunderts. Technische Höchstleistungen ihrer Zeit", ''Technikgeschichte'' '''44''' (3): 213–237 (226–228)

Another weapon invented in the Islamic world, fashioned for killing infantry, was the first known autocannon. It was invented in the 16th century, by Fathullah Shirazi, a Persian-Indian polymath and mechanical engineer, who worked for Akbar the Great in the Mughal Empire. As opposed to the polybolos and repeating crossbows used earlier in Ancient Greece and China, respectively, Shirazi's rapid-firing machine had multiple gun barrels that fired hand cannon.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f8411db69348f1b12910ad97982f272e" name="Great_Turkish_Bombard_at_Fort_Nelson" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/f8411db69348f1b12910ad97982f272e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>