<document id="22ef5d9468d7aa2f806d865b88a27a52-2.6.2" name="Cannon" cat="29">
<text>
Autocannon have an automatic firing mode, similar to that of a machine gun. They have mechanisms to automatically load their ammunition, and therefore have a faster rate of fire than artillery, often approaching — and, in the case of Gatling guns, surpassing — that of a machine gun. While there is no minimum bore for autocannon, they are usually larger than machine guns, typically 20 mm or greater since World War II.

Most nations use these rapid-fire cannon on their light vehicles, replacing a more powerful, but heavier, tank gun. A typical autocannon is the 25 mm "Bushmaster" chain gun, mounted on the LAV-25 and M2 Bradley armored vehicles.


Autocannon are often found in aircraft, augmenting or replacing machine guns, while providing greater firepower. The first airborne cannon appeared in World War II, but each airplane could carry only one or two, as large bore cannon and their ammunition are generally heavier than machine guns, the standard armament. They were variously mounted, often in the wings, but also high on the forward fuselage, where they would fire through the propeller, or even through the propeller hub. Due both to the low number of cannon per aircraft and the lower rate of fire of cannon, machine guns continued to be used widely early in the war, as there was a greater probability of hitting enemy aircraft. However, as large cannon were more effective against more heavily armored bomber aircraft, they were eventually integrated into newer fighters, which usually carried between two and four autocannon. The Hispano-Suiza HS.404, Oerlikon 20 mm cannon, MG FF, and their numerous variants became among the most widely used autocannon in the war. Nearly all modern fighter aircraft are armed with an autocannon, and most are derived from their counterparts from the Second World War. The largest, heaviest, and most powerful airborne cannon used by the military of the United States is the GAU-8/A Avenger Gatling-type rotary cannon; it is surpassed only by the specialized artillery pieces carried on the AC-130 gunship.

Cannon are in principle capable of a very high rate of fire, but the ammunition is heavy, limiting the amount that can be carried by vehicles or aircraft. For this reason, both the 25 mm Bushmaster and the 30 mm RARDEN are deliberately designed with relatively slow rates of fire, so that they can operate for longer with a limited supply of ammunition. The typical rate of fire of modern autocannon ranges from 90 to 1,800 rounds per minute. Systems with multiple barrels — gatling guns — can have rates of fire of several thousand rounds per minute; the fastest of these is the GSh-6-30K, which has a rate of fire of over 6,000 rounds per minute.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7a5b7833b38167e5e5da8c7c65ba69b1" name="GAU-8_in_A-10" sectnum="2.6.2#1">../img/7a5b7833b38167e5e5da8c7c65ba69b1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>