<document id="230899921affee3f12387edba09920d0-4.4" name="Fort_Ticonderoga" cat="1">
<text>
In 1775, Fort Ticonderoga, in disrepair, was still manned by a token force.  On May 10, 1775, less than one month after the American Revolutionary War was ignited with the battles of Lexington and Concord, the British garrison of 48 soldiers was surprised by a small force of Green Mountain Boys, along with militia volunteers from Massachusetts and Connecticut, led by Ethan Allen and  Benedict Arnold.Martin, pp. 70–72  Allen claims to have said, "Come out you old Rat!" to the fort's commander, Captain William Delaplace.Martin, p. 71  He also later said that he demanded that the British commander surrender the fort "In the name of the Great Jehovah and the Continental Congress!"; however, his surrender demand was made to Lieutenant Jocelyn Feltham and not the fort's commander, who did later appear and surrender his sword.  With the capture of the fort, the Patriot forces obtained a large supply of cannons and other armaments, much of which Henry Knox transported to Boston during the winter of 1775–1776.  Ticonderoga's cannons were instrumental in ending the Siege of Boston when they were used to fortify Dorchester Heights.Martin, p. 73  Arnold remained in control of the fort until 1,000 Connecticut troops under the command of Benjamin Hinman arrived in June 1775.  Because of a series of political maneuvers and miscommunications, Arnold was never notified that Hinman was to take command.  After a delegation from Massachusetts (which had issued Arnold's commission) arrived to clarify the matter, Arnold resigned his commission and departed, leaving the fort in Hinman's hands.Martin, pp. 80–97


Beginning in July 1775, Ticonderoga was used as a staging area for the invasion of Quebec to begin in September.  Under the leadership of generals Philip Schuyler and Richard Montgomery, men and materiel for the invasion accumulated there through July and August.Smith, Vol 1, pp. 252–270  On August 28, after receiving word that British forces at Fort Saint-Jean, not far from the New York–Quebec border, were nearing completion of boats to launch onto Lake Champlain, Montgomery launched the invasion, leading 1,200 troops down the lake.Smith (1907), Vol 1, p. 320  Ticonderoga  continued to serve as a staging base for the action in Quebec until  the battle and siege at Quebec City that resulted in Montgomery's death.These events are recounted in detail in Smith (1907), Vol 2.

In May 1776, British troops began to arrive at Quebec City, where they broke the Continental Army's siege.Smith (1907), Vol 2, p. 316  The British chased the American forces back to Ticonderoga in June, and, after several months of shipbuilding, moved down Lake Champlain under Guy Carleton in October. The British destroyed a small fleet of American gunboats in the Battle of Valcour Island in mid-October, but snow was already falling, so the British retreated to winter quarters in Quebec. About 1,700 troops from the Continental Army, under the command of Colonel Anthony Wayne, wintered at Ticonderoga.Hamilton, p. 165  The British offensive resumed the next year in the Saratoga campaign under General John Burgoyne.Lonergan (1959), p. 101
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7c533d802a9647af85888d526fe51b1d" name="Fort_Ticonderoga_1775" sectnum="4.4#1">../img/7c533d802a9647af85888d526fe51b1d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>