<document id="23648f8f4e0293ec6f157b2675a3efab-2.2" name="Belton_House" cat="1">
<text>
The plan of the rooms at Belton was passé for a grand house of its time. Following the Restoration and the influx of European ideas, it had become popular for large houses to follow the continental fashion of a suite of state rooms consisting of a withdrawing room, dressing room, and bedroom proceeding from either side of a central saloon or hall.Girouard, 126. These rooms were permanently reserved for use by a high ranking guest, such as a visiting monarch. While Belton does have a saloon at its centre, enfilades of state rooms of lessening grandeur do not flank it. The possible reason for this unusual layout is that, while the Brownlows possessed great wealth, their title was only a baronetcy, and their fortune was barely a century old. They would have been regarded as gentry, not aristocracy. As a result, building a suite of state rooms would have been in hope rather than anticipation of a royal guest. However, the lack of a fashionable and formal suite of state apartments coupled with the Brownlows' lack of social credentials did not prevent a visit from King William III to the newly completed house in 1695. The King occupied the "Best bedchamber", a large room with an adjoining closet, directly above the saloon, that led directly from the second floor Great Dining Chamber.The King was reported to have enjoyed his stay so much that he was too hung over to eat any of the food provided on his state visit to Lincoln the following day (Tinniswood (2006), 49).

This design followed the older style of having reception rooms and bedrooms scattered over the two main floors. The layout used followed Roger Pratt's theory that guest and family rooms should be quite separate.Jackson-Stops, 66. As a consequence of this philosophy, the family occupied the rooms on the first and second floors of the west and east wings, with the state rooms in the centre. The great staircase, designed to be grand and imposing, rose to the east side of the house, and formed part of the guest's state route from the Hall and Saloon on the first floor to the principal dining room and bedroom on the second.Tinniswood (1999), 13. This older concept is more clearly exemplified at the Elizabethan Hardwick Hall in neighbouring Derbyshire.

The principal entrance hall, reception and family bedrooms were placed on the first floor above a low semi-basement containing service rooms. The two principal entrances to the mansion in the centre of both the north and south facades were accessed by external staircases, originally a single broad flight on the north side and a double staircase on the south. These staircases have since been replaced by simpler designs.

Piano nobile of Belton House. 1:Marble Hall; 2:Great Staircase; 3:Bedchamber, now Blue Room; 4:Sweatmeat closet; 5:Back stairs & east entrance; 6:Chapel Drawing Room; 7:Chapel (double height); 8:Tyrconnel Room; 9:Saloon; 10:Red Drawing Room; 11:Little Parlour (now Tapestry Room); 12:School Room; 13:Closet; 14:Back stairs & west entrance; 15:Service Room (now Breakfast Room); 16:Upper storey of kitchen, (now Hondecoeter Room); '''''Please note''': This is an unscaled plan for illustrative purposes only.''

The second floor has a matching fenestration, with windows of equal value to those on the first floor below. The very latest innovation, sash windows, was used on both floors. The semi-basement and attic storey used the more old-fashioned mullioned and transomed windows, indicating the lower status of the occupants of these floors. It was clearly emphasised from without that the two main floors of the house were purely for state and family use, and the staff and service areas were confined to the semi-basement and attic floors. This concept of keeping staff and domestic matters out of sight (when not required) was relatively new and had first been employed by Pratt in the design of Coleshill House in Berkshire. The contemporary social commentator of the day Roger North lauded back stairs, of which Belton has two examples ('''5''' and '''14''' on plan), as one of the most important inventions of his day.Jackson-Stops, 60; Marsden, 23.

The principal room is the large Marble Hall ('''1''') at the centre of the south front; this hall is the beginning of a grand procession of rooms, and corresponds to the former Great Parlour or Saloon ('''9''') on the north front. The Marble Hall is flanked by the former Little Parlour ('''11''', now the Tapestry Room) and the Great Staircase ('''2'''), while the Saloon is flanked by two withdrawing rooms ('''8''', '''10'''). The bedrooms are arranged in individual suites on both floors of the two wings ('''3''', ''etc.'') that flank the state centre of the house. The main staircase, set to one side of the Marble Hall, is one of the few things at Belton which is asymmetrically placed. It has a robust plaster-work ceiling incorporating the Brownlow crest by the London plasterer Edward Goudge, "now looked on as ye best master in England in his profession," William Winde reported in 1690.Winde to Lady Mary Bridgeman, 8 February 1690, noted by Beard, 221 and Tinniswood (1999), 9. The other great plaster ceiling by Goudge is in the Chapel, Beard, fig. 41 and Tinniswood (1999), 12.

Bodily and spiritual needs were balanced symmetrically within the mansion: the kitchen ('''16''') and the chapel ('''7''') were both large two-storied halls, rising from the semi-basement to the first floor. This design not only provided a great and lofty space, but also allowed the servants to worship in the chapel without leaving the service floor, while their employers would worship from a private gallery, complete with fireplace, overlooking the chapel on the first floor.Marsden, 19–21.



One of the most Carolean features of the house is the balustrade and cupola surmounting the roof, another element introduced to English architecture by Roger Pratt. The cupola at Belton does not light a lofty domed hall, as is often the case in Europe, but houses a staircase which gives access to a large viewing platform on top of a lead roof, concealed from the ground by the balustrade which tops the more conventional and visible hipped roof. From this vantage point, the owners of Belton could admire the perfect symmetry of their avenues and formal gardens spreading from the house. This feature of the house was removed by the architect James Wyatt when he modernised the house in the 18th century.Tinniswood (1999), 21–22. It was restored to its original form in the 1870s by the 3rd Earl Brownlow.Tinniswood (1999), 30.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ee4e812cf03691bc621ff5a2e1a057b1" name="Belton_Roof" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/ee4e812cf03691bc621ff5a2e1a057b1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>