<document id="236dc12aab372dbe6ba91e86958cce95-1.6" name="J._R._R._Tolkien" cat="17">
<text>
Tolkien's first civilian job after World War I was at the ''Oxford English Dictionary'', where he worked mainly on the history and etymology of words of Germanic origin beginning with the letter ''W''. In 1920 he took up a post as Reader in English language at the University of Leeds, and in 1924 was made a professor there. While at Leeds he produced ''A Middle English Vocabulary'' and, with E. V. Gordon, a definitive edition of ''Sir Gawain and the Green Knight'', both becoming academic standard works for many decades. He also translated ''Sir Gawain and the Green Knight'', ''Pearl'' and ''Sir Orfeo''. In 1925 he returned to Oxford as Rawlinson and Bosworth Professor of Anglo-Saxon, with a fellowship at Pembroke College.

During his time at Pembroke, Tolkien wrote ''The Hobbit'' and the first two volumes of ''The Lord of the Rings'', largely at 20 Northmoor Road in North Oxford, where a blue plaque was placed in 2002. He also published a philological essay in 1932 on the name "Nodens", following Sir Mortimer Wheeler's unearthing of a Roman Asclepieion at Lydney Park, Gloucestershire, in 1928.See ''The Name Nodens'' (1932) in the bibliographical listing. For the etymology, see Nodens#Etymology.

Of Tolkien's academic publications, the 1936 lecture "Beowulf: the Monsters and the Critics" had a lasting influence on Beowulf research.''Biography'', page 143. Lewis E. Nicholson said that the article Tolkien wrote about Beowulf is "widely recognized as a turning point in Beowulfian criticism", noting that Tolkien established the primacy of the poetic nature of the work as opposed to the purely linguistic elements. At the time, the consensus of scholarship deprecated ''Beowulf'' for dealing with childish battles with monsters rather than realistic tribal warfare; Tolkien argued that the author of ''Beowulf'' was addressing human destiny in general, not as limited by particular tribal politics, and therefore the monsters were essential to the poem.Tolkien: ''Finn and Hengest''. Chiefly, p.4 in the Introduction by Alan Bliss Where ''Beowulf'' does deal with specific tribal struggles, as at Finnsburg, Tolkien argued firmly against reading in fantastic elements.Tolkien: ''Finn and Hengest'', the discussion of ''Eotena'', ''passim''. In the essay, Tolkien also revealed how highly he regarded Beowulf: "Beowulf is among my most valued sources," and this influence can be seen in ''The Lord of the Rings''.

In the run-up to World War II, Tolkien was earmarked as a codebreaker.''Letters'', no. 35 (see also editorial note). In January 1939, he was asked whether he would be prepared to serve in the cryptographical department of the Foreign Office in the event of national emergency. He replied in the affirmative, and beginning 27 March, took an instructional course at the London HQ of the Government Code and Cypher School. However, although he was "keen" to become a codebreaker, he was informed in October that his services would not be required for the present. Ultimately he never served as one. In 2009, ''The Daily Telegraph'' claimed Tolkien turned down a £500-a-year offer to become a full-time recruit for unknown reasons.

In 1945, Tolkien moved to Merton College, Oxford, becoming the Merton Professor of English Language and Literature, in which post he remained until his retirement in 1959. He served as an external examiner for the University College, Dublin for many years. In 1954 Tolkien received an honorary degree from the National University of Ireland (of which U.C.D. was a constituent college). Tolkien completed ''The Lord of the Rings'' in 1948, close to a decade after the first sketches.

Tolkien also helped to translate the ''Jerusalem Bible'', which was published in 1966.Rogerson, John. ''The Oxford Illustrated History of the Bible'', 2001.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0bff631bcec8aa8f56d89430f428073c" name="20_Northmoor_Road,_Oxford" sectnum="1.6#1">../img/0bff631bcec8aa8f56d89430f428073c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>