<document id="23f1c01b206b2e887b9935b64df18240-1" name="Alexandra_of_Denmark" cat="25">
<text>
'''Princess Alexandra Caroline Marie Charlotte Louise Julia''', or "'''Alix'''", as she was known within the family, was born at the Yellow Palace, an 18th-century town house at 18 Amaliegade, right next to the Amalienborg Palace complex in Copenhagen. Her father was Prince Christian of Schleswig-Holstein-Sonderburg-Glücksburg and her mother was Princess Louise of Hesse-Cassel.Montgomery-Massingberd, Hugh (ed.) (1977). ''Burke's Royal Families of the World'', Volume 1. (London: Burke's Peerage). ISBN 0 220 66222 3. pp. 69–70 Although she was of royal blood,Her mother and father were both great-grandchildren of King Frederick V of Denmark and great-great-grandchildren of King George II of Great Britain. her family lived a comparatively normal life. They did not possess great wealth; her father's income from an army commission was about £800 per year and their house was a rent-free grace and favour property.Duff, pp. 16–17 Occasionally, Hans Christian Andersen was invited to call and tell the children stories before bedtime.Duff, p. 18

In 1848, King Christian VIII of Denmark died and his only son, Frederick ascended the throne. Frederick was childless, had been through two unsuccessful marriages, and was assumed to be infertile. A succession crisis arose as Frederick ruled in both Denmark and Schleswig-Holstein, and the succession rules of each were different. In Holstein, the Salic law prevented inheritance through the female line, whereas no such restrictions applied in Denmark. Holstein, being predominantly German, proclaimed independence and called in the aid of Prussia. In 1852, the great powers called a conference in London to discuss the Danish succession. An uneasy peace was agreed, which included the provision that Prince Christian of Schleswig-Holstein-Sonderburg-Glücksburg would be Frederick's heir in all his dominions and the prior claims of others (who included Christian's own mother-in-law, brother-in-law and wife) were surrendered.Battiscombe, p. 8Maclagan, Michael; Louda, Jiří (1999). ''Lines of Succession'' (London: Little, Brown). ISBN 0 856 05469 1. p. 49

Prince Christian was given the title Prince of Denmark and his family moved into a new official residence, Bernstorff Palace. Although the family's status had risen, there was no or little increase in their income and they did not participate in court life at Copenhagen as they refused to meet Frederick's third wife and former mistress, Louise Rasmussen, who had an illegitimate child by a previous lover.Duff, pp. 19–20 Alexandra shared a draughty attic bedroom with her sister, Dagmar (later Empress Maria of Russia), made her own clothes and waited at table along with her sisters.Priestley, p. 17 At Bernstorff, Alexandra grew into a young woman; she was taught English by the English chaplain at Copenhagen and was confirmed in Christiansborg Palace.Duff, p. 21 Alexandra was devout throughout her life, and followed High Church beliefs.Battiscombe, pp. 125 and 176
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="57c9cb720e83af151bde9935427b9a56" name="Det_Gule_Palae_Copenhagen" sectnum="1#1">../img/57c9cb720e83af151bde9935427b9a56.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>