<document id="23f1c01b206b2e887b9935b64df18240-4.2" name="Alexandra_of_Denmark" cat="25">
<text>
She did not attend her son's coronation in 1911 since it was not customary for a crowned queen to attend the coronation of another king or queen, but otherwise continued the public side of her life, devoting time to her charitable causes. One such cause included Alexandra Rose Day, where artificial roses made by the disabled were sold in aid of hospitals by women volunteers.Duff, pp. 251–257 and 260The Alexandra Rose Day fund still exists; its patron is Princess Alexandra, The Honourable Lady Ogilvy, Alexandra's great-granddaughter. During the First World War, the custom of hanging the banners of foreign princes invested with Britain's highest order of knighthood, the Order of the Garter, in St. George's Chapel, Windsor Castle, came under criticism, as the German members of the Order were fighting against Britain. Alexandra joined calls to "have down those hateful German banners".Alexandra to King George V, quoted in Battiscombe, p. 285 Driven by public opinion, but against his own wishes, the King had the banners removed but to Alexandra's dismay he had down not only "those vile Prussian banners" but also those of her relations who were, in her opinion, "simply soldiers or vassals under that brutal German Emperor's orders". On 17 September 1916, she was at Sandringham during a Zeppelin air raid,Battiscombe, pp. 291–292 but far worse was to befall the royalty of Europe. In Russia, Tsar Nicholas II was overthrown and he, his wife and children were killed by revolutionaries. The Dowager Empress was rescued from Russia in 1919 by HMS ''Marlborough'' and brought to England where she lived for some time with her sister, Alexandra.Duff, pp. 285–286

Alexandra retained a youthful appearance into her senior years,e.g. Mary Gladstone and Lord Carrington, quoted in Battiscombe, p. 206; Margot Asquith, quoted in Battiscombe, pp. 216–217; Jackie Fisher, 1st Baron Fisher quoted in Battiscombe, p. 232 but during the war her age caught up with her.Alexandra herself and Queen Mary quoted by Battiscombe, p. 296 She took to wearing elaborate veils and heavy makeup, which was described by gossipy women as having her face "enamelled". She made no more trips abroad, and suffered increasing ill-health. In 1920, a blood vessel in her eye burst, leaving her partially blind temporarily.Battiscombe, p. 299 Towards the end of her life, her memory and speech became impaired.Battiscombe, pp. 301–302 She died on 20 November 1925 at Sandringham after suffering a heart attack and was buried in an elaborate tomb next to her husband in St. George's Chapel, Windsor Castle.Eilers, Marlene A. - ''Queen Victoria's Descendants'', p. 171
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="23f1c01b206b2e887b9935b64df18240" name="Alexandra_of_Denmark" sectnum="4.2#1">../img/23f1c01b206b2e887b9935b64df18240.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>