<document id="23f4f580f1f1ae1a351c246e100d2da7-1.1" name="Greater_Manchester" cat="11">
<text>
Although the modern county of Greater Manchester was not created until 1974, the history of its constituent settlements and parts goes back centuries. There is evidence of Iron Age inhabitation, particularly at Mellor,Nevell and Redhead (2005), p. 20. and Celtic activity in a settlement named Chochion, believed to have been an area of Wigan settled by the Brigantes. Retrieved on 10 July 2008. Stretford was also part of the land believed to have been occupied by the Celtic Brigantes tribe, and lay on their border with the Cornovii on the southern side of the River Mersey.Bayliss (1996), p. 6. The remains of 1st-century forts at Castlefield in Manchester, Retrieved on 29 December 2007. and Castleshaw Roman fort in Saddleworth, Retrieved on 29 December 2007. are evidence of Roman occupation. Much of the region was omitted from the Domesday Book of 1086; Redhead states that this was because only a partial survey was taken, rather than sparsity of population.Redhead, Norman, in: Hartwell, Hyde and Pevsner (2004), p. 18.

During the Middle Ages, much of what became Greater Manchester lay within the hundred of Salfordshire – an ancient division of the county of Lancashire. Salfordshire encompassed several parishes and townships, some of which, like Rochdale, were important market towns and centres of England's woollen trade. The development of what became Greater Manchester is attributed to a shared tradition of domestic flannel and fustian cloth production, which encouraged a system of cross-regional trade.Frangopulo (1977), p. ix.Frangopulo (1977), pp. 24–25.McNeil and Nevell (2000), pp. 1–3. The Industrial Revolution transformed the local domestic system, and much of Greater Manchester's heritage is related to textile manufacture during the Industrial Revolution and the infrastructure that grew up to support this sector. The townships in and around Manchester began expanding "at an astonishing rate" around the turn of the 19th century as part of a process of unplanned urbanisation brought on by a boom in textile processing.Aspin (1981), p. 3. Places such as Bury, Oldham and Bolton played a central economic role in the nation, and by the end of the 19th century had become some of the most important and productive mill towns in the world.Cowhig (1976), pp. 7–9. However, it was Manchester that was the most populous settlement, a major city and the world's largest marketplace for cotton goods.Kidd (2006), pp. 12, 15–24, 224. By 1835 "Manchester was without challenge the first and greatest industrial city in the world", and due to its commercial and socioeconomic success the need for local government and geo-administrative reform for the region in and around the city was proposed in as early as the 1910s.Frangopulo (1977), p. 226.

By the 18th century, traders from Germany had coined the name ''Manchesterthum'', meaning "Greater Manchester", and were using that as a name for the region in and around Manchester.Frangopulo (1977), p. 268. However, the English term "Greater Manchester" did not appear until the start of the 20th century. One of its first known recorded uses was in a 1914 report put forward in response to what was considered to have been the successful creation of the County of London in 1889. The report suggested that a county should be set up to recognise the "Manchester known in commerce", and referred to the areas that formed "a substantial part of South-Lancashire and part of Cheshire, comprising all municipal boroughs and minor authorities within a radius of eight or nine miles of Manchester".Swarbrick, J., (February 1914), ''Greater Manchester: The Future Municipal Government of Large Cities'', pp. 12–15. In his 1915 book ''Cities In Evolution'', innovative urban planner Sir Patrick Geddes wrote "far more than Lancashire realises, is growing up another Greater London".Frangopulo (1977), p. 229.

Conurbations in England tend to build-up at the historic county boundaries and Greater Manchester is no exception. Most of Greater Manchester lay within the ancient county boundaries of Lancashire; those areas south of the Mersey and Tame were in Cheshire. The Saddleworth area and a small part of Mossley are historically part of Yorkshire and in the south-east a small part in Derbyshire. The areas that were incorporated into Greater Manchester in 1974 previously formed parts of the administrative counties of Cheshire, Lancashire, the West Riding of Yorkshire and of eight independent county boroughs. By the early 1970s, this system of demarcation was described as "archaic" and "grossly inadequate to keep pace both with the impact of motor travel, and with the huge increases in local government responsibilities". 

The ''Manchester Evening Chronicle'' brought to the fore the issue of "regional unity" for the area in April 1935 under the headline "Greater Manchester – The Ratepayers' Salvation". It reported on the "increasing demands for the exploration of the possibilities of a greater merger of public services throughout Manchester and the surrounding municipalities".Frangopulo (1977), p. 227. The issue was frequently discussed by civic leaders in the area at that time, particularly those from Manchester and Salford. The Mayor of Salford pledged his support to the idea, stating that he looked forward to the day when "there would be a merging of the essential services of Manchester, Salford, and the surrounding districts constituting Greater Manchester." Proposals were halted by the Second World War, though in the decade after it, the pace of proposals for local government reform for the area quickened.Frangopulo (1977), p. 228. In 1947, Lancashire County Council proposed a three "ridings" system to meet the changing needs of the county of Lancashire, including those for Manchester and surrounding districts. Other proposals included the creation of a Manchester County Council, a directly elected regional body. In 1951, the census in the UK began reporting on South-East Lancashire as a homogeneous conurbation.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4a43e871931b2a1dac0f78e50e0a173a" name="Weavers'_cottages,_Wardle" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/4a43e871931b2a1dac0f78e50e0a173a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>