<document id="241f041e0600065ff18039e0cc4c2d32-4" name="Giovanni_Villani" cat="14">
<text>
Historian J.K. Hyde states that the ''Nuova Cronica'' of Villani is representative of the strong vernacular tradition in Florence, appealing to the people of the time as a narrative that was "easy to read, full of human interest and occasionally spiced with novella-type anecdotes." Hyde also notes that Villani's criticisms of the commune politics in Florence promoted a trend of personal expression amongst later chroniclers that defied official conformity.Hyde (1979), 124&ndash;125. The ''Cronica'' is also an incredibly rich historical record; its greatest value to modern historians is its descriptions of the people, data, and events experienced by Villani during his lifetime.Wicksteed (1906), xxxi. Historian Mark Phillips states that all subsequent Florentine accounts of the tyrannical regime of Walter VI of Brienne—including those by Leonardo Bruni and Niccolò Machiavelli—were based upon the primary source of Villani's ''Cronica''. Villani's written work on Dante Alighieri and the age in which he lived has provided insight into Dante's work, reasoning, and psyche.Wicksteed (1906), xxv&ndash;xlvi The reprinting of new editions of Villani's work in the early 20th century provided material for a resurgence in the study of Dante.Caesar (1989), 58&ndash;59. However, his descriptions of events which preceded him by centuries are riddled with inaccurate traditional accounts, popular legend, and hearsay. In regards to his own time, he provides modern historians with valuable details on Florentine social and living habits, such as the growing trend and craze of wealthy Florentines in building large country homes far outside of the city.Goldthwaite (1980), 13, 22. However, the early 20th century historian Philip Wicksteed stated of Villani, "When dealing with his own times, and with events immediately connected with Florence, he is a trustworthy witness, but minute accuracy is never his strong point; and in dealing with distant times and places he is hopelessly unreliable." For example, although Nicolai Rubinstein acknowledged that Villani's chronicles were much more matured and developed than earlier ones, Villani still relied on legend and hearsay to account for the origins of cities such as Fiesole.Rubinstein (1942), 209. On Villani's estimation that a third of Antwerp's population died off during the Great Famine of 1315-1317, the early 20th century historian Henry S. Lucas wrote, "not much faith can be placed in such statistics which are little better than guesses."Lucas (1930), 366. Louis Green notes Villani's limitation as a chronicler and not a full-fledged historian:


Recording as he did incidents in the order of their occurrence without any of the historian's pretensions to a thematic organization of his material, he could not feed back the lessons of a changing present into a reinterpreted past. Nor did his devotion to the justification and glorification of Florence permit him to see in the altered fortunes of his city a repetition of the pattern of decline he had illustrated in the histories of the great dynasties of his age.Green (1967), 168.
 

Louis Green asserts that Giovanni's ''Cronica'' expressed the outlook of the merchant community in Florence at the time, but also provided valuable indications of "how that outlook was modified in a direction away from characteristically medieval to embryonically modern attitudes."Green (1967), 161. Green writes that Villani's ''Cronica'' was one of three types of chronicles found in the 14th century, the type which was largely a universal history. Other types would be chronicles of particular historic episodes such as Dino Compagni's account of the White Guelphs and Black Guelphs or the more domestic chronicle that focused on the fortunes and events of one family, as written by Donato Velluti or Giovanni Morelli.Green (1967), 161&ndash;162.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f0da808f451c59a64c0b393eb10f89bd" name="Dante-alighieri" sectnum="4#1">../img/f0da808f451c59a64c0b393eb10f89bd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>