<document id="24875d87b0ec525e2ec6cb280ba26331-4" name="Anglo-Saxon_Chronicle" cat="17">
<text>
''': The Winchester Chronicle'''

The Winchester, or Parker, Chronicle, is the oldest manuscript of the Chronicle that survives.  It was begun at Old Minster, Winchester, towards the end of Alfred's reign.  The manuscript begins with a genealogy of Alfred, and the first chronicle entry is for the year 60 BC.  The first scribe stopped with the year 891, and the following entries were made at intervals throughout the 10th century by several scribes.  The manuscript becomes independent of the other recensions after the entry for 975.  The book, which also had a copy of the Laws of Alfred and Ine bound in after the entry for 924, was transferred to Canterbury some time in the early eleventh century.  The last entry in the vernacular is for 1070.  After this comes the Latin ''Acta Lanfranci'', which covers church events from 1070–1093.  This is followed by a list of popes and the Archbishops of Canterbury to whom they sent the pallium.  The manuscript was acquired by Matthew Parker, Archbishop of Canterbury 1559–1575  and master of Corpus Christi College, Cambridge, following the dissolution of the monasteries, and bequeathed to the college on his death. It now forms part of the Parker Library.

''' The Abingdon Chronicle I'''

 was written by a single scribe in the second half of the 10th century.  It begins with an entry for 60 BC and ends with the entry for 977.  A manuscript that is now separate (British Library MS. Cotton Tiberius Aiii, f. 178) was originally the introduction to this chronicle; it contains a genealogy, as does , but extends it to the late 10th century.  It is known that  was at Abingdon in the mid-11th century, because it was used in the composition of .  Shortly after this it went to Canterbury, where interpolations and corrections were made.  As with , it ends with a list of popes and the archbishops of Canterbury to whom they sent the pallium.

''' The Abingdon Chronicle II'''

 includes additional material from local annals at Abingdon, where it was composed.  It also includes an Old English translation of Orosius's world history, followed by a menologium and some verses of the laws of the natural world and of humanity.  There follows a copy of the chronicle, beginning with 60 BC; the first scribe copied up to the entry for 490, and a second scribe took over up to the entry for 1048.   and  are identical between 491 and 652, but differences thereafter make it clear that the second scribe was also using another copy of the Chronicle.  This scribe also inserted, after the annal for 915, the Mercian Register, which covers the years 902–924, and which focuses on Aethelflaed.  The manuscript continues to 1066 and stops in the middle of the description of the Battle of Stamford Bridge.  In the 12th century a few lines were added to complete the account.

''' The Worcester Chronicle'''

 appears to have been written in the middle of the 11th century.  After 1033 it includes some records from Worcester, so it is generally thought to have been composed there.  Five different scribes can be identified for the entries up to 1054, after which it appears to have been worked on at intervals.  The text includes material from Bede's ''Ecclesiastical History'' and from a set of 8th-century Northumbrian annals.  It is thought that some of the entries may have been composed by Archbishop Wulfstan.   contains more information than other manuscripts on northern and Scottish affairs, and it has been speculated that it was a copy intended for the Anglicised Scottish court.  From 972 to 1016 the sees of York and Worcester were both held by the same person—Oswald from 972, Ealdwulf from 992, and Wulfstan from 1003, and this may explain why a northern recension was to be found at Worcester. By the 16th century, parts of the manuscript were lost; eighteen pages were inserted containing substitute entries from other sources.  These pages were probably written by John Joscelyn, who was secretary to Matthew Parker.

''' The Peterborough Chronicle'''

In 1116 a fire at the monastery at Peterborough destroyed most of the buildings. The copy of the Chronicle kept there may have been lost at that time or later, but in either case shortly thereafter a fresh copy was made, apparently copied from a Kentish version—most likely to have been from Canterbury. The manuscript was written at one time and by a single scribe, down to the annal for 1121. The scribe added material relating to Peterborough Abbey which is not in other versions. The Canterbury original which he copied was similar, but not identical, to : the Mercian Register does not appear, and a poem about the Battle of Brunanburh in 937, which appears in most of the other surviving copies of the Chronicle, is not recorded. The same scribe then continued the annals through to 1131; these entries were made at intervals, and thus are presumably contemporary records.  Finally, a second scribe, in 1154, wrote an account of the years 1132–1154; but his dating is known to be unreliable. This last entry is in Middle English, rather than Old English.  was once owned by William Laud, Archbishop of Canterbury 1633–1654, so is also known as the Laud Chronicle.

''' The Canterbury Bilingual Epitome'''

At about 1100 a copy of the Chronicle was written at Christ Church, Canterbury, probably by one of the scribes who made notes in .  This version is written in both Old English and Latin; each entry in Old English was followed by the Latin version. The version the scribe copied is similar to the version used by the scribe in Peterborough who wrote , though it seems to have been abridged.  It includes the same introductory material as  and, along with , is one of the two chronicles that does not include the "Battle of Brunanburh" poem. The manuscript has many annotations and interlineations, some made by the original scribe and some by later scribes.

'''/ Copy of the Winchester Chronicle'''

 was copied from  at Winchester.  The last annal copied was 1001, so the copy was made no earlier than that; and an episcopal list appended to  suggests that the copy was made by 1013.  This manuscript was almost completely destroyed in a fire at Ashburnham House in 1731, where the Cotton Library was housed. A few leaves remain.  However, a transcript had been made by Laurence Nowell, a 16th century antiquary, which was used by Abraham Wheloc in an edition of the Chronicle printed in 1643. Because of this, it is also sometimes known as , after Wheloc.

''' Cottonian Fragment'''

 consists of a single leaf, containing annals for 1113 and 1114.  In the entry for 1113 it includes the phrase "he came to Winchester"; hence it is thought likely that the manuscript was written at Winchester.  There is not enough of this manuscript for reliable relationships to other manuscripts to be established.

''' Easter Table Chronicle'''

Part of  was written by a scribe soon after 1073.  After 1085, the annals are in various hands and appear to have been written at Christ Church, Canterbury.  At one point this manuscript was at St Augustine's Abbey, Canterbury.  See Caligula A.15, under "Provenance", which gives a description of the manuscript and some of its history.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0cf1ed2b567be64a22c0b09b1248cd93" name="Anglo-Saxon_Chronicle_-_C_-_871" sectnum="4#1">../img/0cf1ed2b567be64a22c0b09b1248cd93.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>