<document id="24a8e59a16d5a7c087612cf148204f2e-3.3" name="Operation_Wrath_of_God" cat="29">
<text>
The Mossad continued to search for Ali Hassan Salameh, nicknamed the Red Prince, who was the head of Force 17 and the Black September operative believed by Israel to be the mastermind behind the Munich massacre.  This belief has since been challenged by accounts of senior Black September officials, who say that while he was involved in many attacks in Europe, Salameh was not at all connected with the events in Munich.Klein, 219.



Almost a full year after Munich, the Mossad believed they had finally located Salameh in the small Norwegian town Lillehammer.  On July 21, 1973, in what would become known as the Lillehammer affair, a team of Mossad agents killed Ahmed Bouchiki, a Moroccan waiter unrelated to the Munich attack and Black September, after an informant mistakenly identified Bouchiki as Salameh.  Six Mossad agents, including two women, were captured by the Norwegian authorities, while others, including the leader Mike Harari, managed to escape back to Israel.  Five of the captured were convicted of the killing and imprisoned, but were released and returned to Israel in 1975.  Victor Ostrovsky claims that Salameh was instrumental in leading the Mossad off course by giving the Mossad false information about his whereabouts.Ostrovsky, 206.

In the aftermath of the affair, international outrage over the mistaken murder forced Golda Meir to order the suspension of Operation Wrath of God.Reeve, 199. The ensuing Norwegian investigation and revelations by the captured agents compromised Mossad assets across Europe, including safe houses, agents, and operational methods.Black, 276–7. Yet five years later it was decided to recommence the operation under new Prime Minister Menachem Begin, and find those on the list still at large.Reeve, 203.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6d39c588a4b3c394ad1dbd7b427d0110" name="Alihassansalameh" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/6d39c588a4b3c394ad1dbd7b427d0110.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>