<document id="24d5235e2ecb0c65bba650d63f3a0f56-3" name="Reception_history_of_Jane_Austen" cat="17">
<text>
Austen had many admiring readers during the nineteenth century, who, according to critic Ian Watt, appreciated her " to ordinary social experience".Watt, 2. However, Austen's novels did not conform to certain strong Romantic and Victorian British preferences, which required that "powerful emotion  authenticated by an egregious display of sound and color in the writing".Duffy, 98–99; see also MacDonagh, 146; Watt, 3–4. Victorian critics and audiences were drawn to the work of authors such as Charles Dickens and George Eliot; by comparison, Austen's novels seemed provincial and quiet.Southam, "Introduction", Vol. 1, 2; Southam, "Introduction", Vol. 2, 1. Although Austen's works were republished beginning in late 1832 or early 1833 by Richard Bentley in the ''Standard Novels'' series, and remained in print continuously thereafter, they were not bestsellers.Johnson, 211. Southam describes her "reading public between 1821 and 1870" as "minute beside the known audience for Dickens and his contemporaries".Southam, "Introduction", Vol. 1, 20.

Those who did read Austen saw themselves as discriminating readers—they were a cultured few. This became a common theme of Austen criticism during the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.Duffy, 98–99. Philosopher and literary critic George Henry Lewes articulated this theme in a series of enthusiastic articles in the 1840s and 1850s. In "The Novels of Jane Austen", published anonymously in ''Blackwood's Magazine'' in 1859, Lewes praised Austen's novels for "the economy of  easy adaptation of means to ends, with no aid from superfluous elements" and compared her to Shakespeare.Southam, "Introduction", Vol. 1, 152; see also, Southam, "Introduction", Vol. 2, 20–21. Arguing that Austen lacked the ability to construct a plot, he still celebrated her dramatisations: "The reader's pulse never throbs, his curiosity is never intense; but his interest never wanes for a moment. The action begins; the people speak, feel, and act; everything that is said, felt, or done tends towards the entanglement or disentanglement of the plot; and we are almost made actors as well as spectators of the little drama."Lewes, 158.

Reacting against Lewes's essays and his personal communications with her, novelist Charlotte Brontë admired Austen's fidelity to everyday life but described her as "only shrewd and observant" and criticised the absence of visible passion in her work.Brontë, 128. To Brontë, Austen's work appeared formal and constrained, "a carefully fenced, highly cultivated garden, with neat borders and delicate flowers; but no glance of bright vivid physiognomy, no open country, no fresh air, no blue hill, no bonny beck".Brontë, 126.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c18833b0d09c84f00806bbe631f0a344" name="GHLewes1876" sectnum="3#1">../img/c18833b0d09c84f00806bbe631f0a344.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>