<document id="24d5235e2ecb0c65bba650d63f3a0f56-5.1" name="Reception_history_of_Jane_Austen" cat="17">
<text>
For decades, Scott's and Whately's opinions dominated the reception of Austen's works and few people read her novels. In 1870, this changed with the publication of the first significant Austen biography, ''A Memoir of Jane Austen'', which was written by Jane Austen's nephew, James Edward Austen-Leigh.The ''Memoir'' was published in December 1869 and dated 1870. With its release, Austen's popularity and critical standing increased dramatically.The ''Memoir'' was written by Austen-Leigh with the assistance and cooperation of his older sister, Anna, and his younger sister, Caroline, both of whom had known Austen and contributed written reminiscences. Le Faye, "Memoirs and biographies", 52–54; Southam, "Introduction", Vol. 2, 1–2. Readers of the ''Memoir'' were presented with the myth of the amateur novelist who wrote masterpieces: the ''Memoir'' fixed in the public mind a sentimental picture of Austen as a quiet, middle-aged maiden aunt and reassured them that her work was suitable for a respectable Victorian family. The publication of the ''Memoir'' spurred a major reissue of Austen's novels. The first popular editions were released in 1883—a cheap sixpenny series published by Routledge. This was followed by a proliferation of elaborate illustrated editions, collectors' sets, and scholarly editions.Southam, "Introduction", Vol. 2, 58–62. However, contemporary critics continued to assert that her works were sophisticated and only appropriate for those who could truly plumb their depths.Southam, "Criticism, 1870–1940", 102–03; see also Watt, 6; Johnson, 211; Trott, 92–94. Yet, after the publication of the ''Memoir'', more criticism was published on Austen's novels in two years than had appeared in the previous fifty.Southam, "Introduction", Vol. 1, 1.

In 1913, William Austen-Leigh and Richard Arthur Austen-Leigh, descendants of the Austen family, published the definitive family biography, ''Jane Austen: Her Life and Letters—A Family Record''. Based primarily on family papers and letters, it is described by Austen biographer Park Honan as "accurate, staid, reliable, and at times vivid and suggestive".Honan, "Biographies", 19. Although the authors moved away from the sentimental tone of the ''Memoir'', they made little effort to go beyond the family records and traditions immediately available to them. Their book therefore offers bare facts and little in the way of interpretation.Southam, "Criticism, 1870–1940", 106; Le Faye, "Memoirs and biographies", 55; Southam, "Introduction", Vol. 2, 82. For an updated and revised version of this biography, see Deirdre Le Faye, ''Jane Austen: A Family Record'', 2nd ed., (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press), 2003.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="219066d5232e3da1b98e4d3454134bb8" name="Jane_Austen,_from_A_Memoir_of_Jane_Austen_(1870)" sectnum="5.1#1">../img/219066d5232e3da1b98e4d3454134bb8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>