<document id="24d5235e2ecb0c65bba650d63f3a0f56-5.2" name="Reception_history_of_Jane_Austen" cat="17">
<text>
During the last quarter of the nineteenth century, the first books of critical analysis regarding Austen's works were published. In 1890 Godwin Smith published the ''Life of Jane Austen'', initiating a "fresh phase in the critical heritage", in which Austen reviewers became critics. This launched the beginning of "formal criticism", that is, a focus on Austen as a writer and an analysis of the techniques that made her writing unique.Southam, "Introduction", Vol. 2, 34, 45; Trott, 92–93. According to Southam, while Austen criticism increased in amount and, to some degree, in quality after 1870, "a certain uniformity" pervaded it:

We see the novels praised for their elegance of form and their surface 'finish'; for the realism of their fictional world, the variety and vitality of their characters; for their pervasive humour; and for their gentle and undogmatic morality and its unsermonising delivery. The novels are prized for their 'perfection'. Yet it is seen to be a narrow perfection, achieved within the bounds of domestic comedy.Southam, "Introduction", Vol. 2, 13–14.

Among the most astute of these critics were Richard Simpson, Margaret Oliphant, and Leslie Stephen. In a review of the ''Memoir'', Simpson described Austen as a serious yet ironic critic of English society. He introduced two interpretative themes which later became the basis for modern literary criticism of Austen's works: humour as social critique and irony as a means of moral evaluation. Continuing Lewes's comparison to Shakespeare, Simpson wrote that Austen:

began by being an ironical critic; she manifested her  by direct censure, but by the indirect method of imitating and exaggerating the faults of her , humour, irony, the judgment not of one that gives sentence but of the mimic who quizzes while he mocks, are her characteristics.Qtd. in Watt, 5–6.


Simpson's essay was not well-known and did not become influential until Lionel Trilling quoted it in 1957.Southam, "Introduction", Vol. 2, 17. Another prominent writer whose Austen criticism was ignored, novelist Margaret Oliphant, described Austen in almost proto-feminist terms, as "armed with a 'fine vein of feminine cynicism,' 'full of subtle power, keenness, finesse, and self-restraint,' blessed with an 'exquisite sense' of the 'ridiculous,' 'a fine stinging yet soft-voiced contempt,' whose novels are 'so calm and cold and keen'".Qtd. in Southam, "Criticism, 1870–1940", 102–03. This line of criticism would not be fully explored until the 1970s with the rise of feminist literary criticism.

Although Austen's novels had been published in the United States since 1832, albeit in bowdlerised editions, it was not until after 1870 that there was a distinctive American response to Austen.Southam, "Introduction", Vol. 2, 49–50. As Southam explains, "for American literary nationalists Jane Austen's cultivated scene was too pallid, too constrained, too refined, too downright unheroic".Southam, "Introduction", Vol. 2, 52. Austen was not democratic enough for American tastes and her canvas did not explore the frontier themes that had come to define American literature. By the turn of the century, the American response was represented by the debate between the American novelist and critic William Dean Howells and the writer and humorist Mark Twain. In a series of essays, Howells helped make Austen into a canonical figure for the populace whereas Twain used Austen to argue against the Anglophile tradition in America. That is, Twain argued for the distinctiveness of American literature by attacking English literature.Southam, "Introduction", Vol. 2, 74. In his book ''Following the Equator'', Twain described the library on his ship: "Jane Austen's  absent from this library. Just that one omission alone would make a fairly good library out of a library that hadn't a book in it."Twain, 232.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a047e5a24c7ebf07a11d5e38fd0820c5" name="Twain1909" sectnum="5.2#1">../img/a047e5a24c7ebf07a11d5e38fd0820c5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>