<document id="254505d8f78808ba3bd75c96f7f717ac-6.11" name="Primate" cat="3">
<text>
Only humans are recognized as persons and protected in law by the United Nations Universal Declaration of Human Rights.  The legal status of non-human primates (NHPs), on the other hand, is the subject of much debate, with organizations such as the Great Ape Project (GAP) campaigning to award at least some of them legal rights. In June 2008, Spain became the first country in the world to recognize the rights of some NHPs when its parliament's cross-party environmental committee urged the country to comply with GAP's recommendations, which are that chimpanzees, bonobos, orangutans, and gorillas not be used for animal experiments.


Many species of NHP are kept as pets by humans. GAP estimates that around 3,000 NHPs live as exotic pets in the United States, while the Humane Society of the United States puts the figure much higher, at around 15,000. The expanding Chinese middle class has increased demand for NHPs as exotic pets in recent years. Although NHP import for the pet trade was banned in the U.S. in 1975, smuggling still occurs along the United States – Mexico border, with prices ranging from US$3000 for monkeys to $30,000 for apes.

Primates are used as model organisms in laboratories and have been used in space missions.  They serve as service animals for disabled humans. Capuchin monkeys can be trained to assist quadriplegic humans; their intelligence, memory, and manual dexterity make them ideal helpers.

NHPs are kept in zoos around the globe. Historically, zoos were primarily a form of entertainment, but more recently have shifted their focus to conservation, education and research. Many zoos now feature naturalistic exhibits and educational material for the public; in the United States many participate in the Species Survival Plan (SSP), developed by the Association of Zoos and Aquariums (AZA), to maximize genetic diversity through captive breeding. Zoos and other animal welfare supporters generally oppose animal rights initiatives and the GAP's insistence that all NHPs be released from captivity for two primary reasons. First, captive-born primates lack the knowledge and experience to survive in the wild if released. Second, zoos provide living space for primates and other animals threatened with extinction in the wild.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="382aa4feb91a84d20cb61446455af656" name="Cebus_albifrons_edit" sectnum="6.11#1">../img/382aa4feb91a84d20cb61446455af656.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>