<document id="26014846a9bf8d6f8d62e0c74cb3a70b-1" name="Military_history_of_Puerto_Rico" cat="29">
<text>
Christopher Columbus arrived in the island of Puerto Rico on November 19, 1493 during his second voyage to the so-called "New World".  The island was inhabited by the Arawak group of indigenous peoples known as Tainos, who called the island "Borikén" or "Borinquen". Columbus named the island ''San Juan Bautista'' in honor of Saint John the Baptist. The main port was named ''Puerto Rico (Rich Port)'' (eventually the island was renamed Puerto Rico and the port which was to evolve into the capital of the island was renamed San Juan). The conquistador Juan Ponce de León accompanied Columbus on this trip.


When Ponce de León arrived in Puerto Rico, he was well received by the ''Cacique'' (Tribal chief) Agüeybaná (The Great Sun), chieftain of the island Taino tribes. Besides the conquistadors, some of the first colonists were farmers and miners in search of gold. In 1508, Ponce de León became the first appointed governor of Puerto Rico, founding the first settlement of Caparra between the modern-day cities of Bayamón and San Juan. After being named Governor, de León and the conquistadors forced the Tainos to work in the mines and to build fortifications; many Tainos died as a result of cruel treatment during their labor. In 1510, upon Agüeybaná's death, his brother Agüeybaná II (The Brave) and a group of Tainos led Diego Salcedo, a Spaniard, to a river and drowned him, proving to his people that the white men were not gods. Upon realizing this, Agüeybaná II led his people in the Taino rebellion of 1511, the first rebellion in the island against the better armed Spanish forces. Guarionex, cacique of Utuado, attacked the village of Sotomayor (present day Aguada) and killed eighty of its inhabitants. Cacique Guarionex died during the attack which was considered a Taino victory., Retrieved April 26, 2009 

After the Taino victory the colonists formed a citizens' militia to defend themselves against the attacks. Juan Ponce de León and one of his top commanders, Diego de Salazar led the Spaniards in a series of offensives which included a massacre of the Taino forces in the domain of Agüeybaná II. The Spanish offensive culminated in the Battle of Yagüecas against Cacique Mabodomoca.  Agüeybaná II was shot and killed, ending the first recorded military action in Puerto Rico. ''Naraciones historicas by Cayetano Coll y Toste, Pub. Editorial Cultural 1976 Pg.57 ISBN 84-399-5350-X. After the failed rebellion, the Tainos were forced to give up their customs and traditions by order of a Royal decree, approved by King Ferdinand II, which required that they adopt and practice the values, religion and language of their conquerors.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7f3b6a8918e5db34f00910df197b8644" name="Agueybana" sectnum="1#1">../img/7f3b6a8918e5db34f00910df197b8644.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>