<document id="26014846a9bf8d6f8d62e0c74cb3a70b-2.1" name="Military_history_of_Puerto_Rico" cat="29">
<text>
Puerto Rico was considered the "Key to the Antilles" by the Spanish because of its location as a way station and port for Spanish vessels. In 1540, with revenue from Mexican mines, the Spanish settlers began the construction of Fort San Felipe del Morro ("the promontory") in San Juan. With the completion of the initial phase of the construction in 1589 ''El Morro'' became the island's main military fortification, guarded by professional soldiers. The rest of Puerto Rico, which had been reorganized in 1580 as a captaincy general, had to rely on only a handful of soldiers and the local volunteer militia to defend the island against militant and pirate attacks.

The main enemies of Spain at the time were the British and the Dutch. They, however were not the only enemies that Spain faced in the Caribbean during this period. On October 11, 1528, the French sacked and burned the settlement of San Germán during an attempt to capture the island, destroying many of the island's first settlements&mdash;including Guánica, Sotomayor, Daguao and Loiza&mdash;before the local militia forced them to retreat. The only settlement that remained was San Juan.

In 1585, war broke out between England and Spain. The Anglo-Spanish War was not limited to Europe—extending to Spanish and English territories in the Americas. On November 22, 1595, Sir Francis Drake, the vice-admiral in command of the Royal Navy that overcame the Spanish Armada, and Sir John Hawkins attempted an invasion of the island with 26 vessels. Unable to take the island, Drake set San Juan on fire. In 1596, Drake died of dysentery after another unsuccessful attack on San Juan. On June 15, 1598, the British fleet, led by George Clifford, landed in Santurce and held the island for several months. He was forced to abandon the island upon an outbreak of bacillary dysentery among his troops. In 1599, 400 additional soldiers and 46 cannons were sent to the island along with a new governor, Alonso de Mercado, to rebuild the city.'' Colle y Toste (1918)and Dr. Oscar Costa-Mandry (1935)
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a2a74a9e108d51460708ef33c41874fd" name="CastilloElNorro" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/a2a74a9e108d51460708ef33c41874fd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>