<document id="26924e9fc0036fbe1e0fa59a964269d8-5.8" name="Le_Père_Goriot" cat="17">
<text>
The relations between family members follow two patterns: the bonds of marriage serve mostly as Machiavellian means to financial ends, while the obligations of the older generation to the young take the form of sacrifice and deprivation. Delphine is trapped in a loveless marriage to Baron de Nucingen, a money-savvy banker. He is aware of her extramarital affairs, and uses them as a means to extort money from her. Anastasie, meanwhile, is married to the Comte de Restaud, who cares less about the illegitimate children she has than the jewels she sells to provide for her lover – who is conning her in a scheme that Rastignac had heard was popular in Paris. This depiction of marriage as a tool of power reflects the harsh reality of the unstable social structures of the time.Kanes, pp. 46–49; Auerbach, p. 285; Bellos, pp. 46–51. 



Parents, meanwhile, give endlessly to their children; Goriot sacrifices everything for his daughters. Balzac refers to him in the novel as the "Christ of paternity" for his constant suffering on behalf of his children.Kanes, p. 47; Bellos, pp. 81–82. That they abandon him, lost in their pursuit of social status, only adds to his misery. The end of the book contrasts Goriot's deathbed moments with a festive ball hosted by Madame de Beauséant – attended by his daughters, as well as Rastignac – suggesting a fundamental schism between society and the family.Petrey, p. 337.

The betrayal of Goriot's daughters is often compared to that of the characters in Shakespeare's ''King Lear'';Hunt, pp. 87–89; Robb, p. 257; Bellos, pp. 34–35. Balzac was even accused of plagiarism when the novel was first published. Discussing these similarities, critic George Saintsbury claims that Goriot's daughters are "as surely murderesses of their father as  Goneril and Regan".Saintsbury, p. x. As Herbert J. Hunt points out in his book ''Balzac's Comédie humaine'', however, Goriot's tale is in some ways more tragic, since "he has a Regan and a Goneril, but no Cordelia".Hunt, p. 87.

Rastignac's family also sacrifices extensively for him. Convinced that he cannot achieve a decent status in Paris without a considerable display of wealth, he writes to his family and asks them to send him money: "Sell some of your old jewelry, my kind mother; I will give you other jewels very soon."Balzac (1901), p. 85. They do send him the money he requests, and – although it is not described directly in the novel – endure significant hardship for themselves as a result. His family, absent while he is in Paris, becomes even more distant despite this sacrifice. Although Goriot and Vautrin offer themselves as father figures to him, by the end of the novel they are gone and he is alone.Barbéris, pp. 310–314.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9e2b1e1f1da5eaba165c08472f486164" name="Goneril_and_Regan_from_King_Lear" sectnum="5.8#1">../img/9e2b1e1f1da5eaba165c08472f486164.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>