<document id="26ac7d591dacc94faaf50eda76daea7b-4" name="USS_Constitution" cat="29">
<text>
''Constitution'' was recommissioned in December with Captain John Rodgers again taking command to oversee a major refitting. She was overhauled at a cost just under $100,000; however, Rodgers inexplicably ignored her copper sheathing, later leading him to declare her a "slow sailer". She spent most of the following two years on training runs and ordinary duty. When Isaac Hull took command in June 1810, he immediately recognized the necessity to have her hull bottom cleaned, removing a noted "ten waggon loads" of barnacles and seaweed.Martin 1997, pp. 128, 130, 131 Hull then prepared for a voyage to France, carrying the new Ambassador to France Joel Barlow and his family, departing on 5 August 1811 and arriving on 1 September. Remaining near France and Holland through the winter months, Hull continually held sail and gun drills to keep the crew ready for possible hostilities with the British. After the events of the Little Belt Affair the previous May, tensions were high between the United States and Britain, resulting in ''Constitution'' being shadowed by British frigates while awaiting dispatches from Barlow to carry back to the United States, where she arrived on 18 February 1812.Martin 1997, pp. 134–139

War was declared on 18 June and Hull put to sea on 12 July, attempting to join the five ships of a squadron under the command of Rodgers in . Hull sighted five ships off Egg Harbor, New Jersey on 17 July and at first believed them to be Rodgers' squadron, but by the following morning the lookouts had determined they were a British squadron (, , ,  and ) out of Halifax that had sighted ''Constitution'' and were giving chase.Roosevelt 1882, Chapter III Finding themselves becalmed, Hull, from a suggestion given by Charles Morris, instructed the crew to put boats over the side to tow their ship out of range, using kedge anchors to draw the ship forward, and wetting the sails down to take advantage of every breath of wind. The British ships soon imitated the tactic of kedging and remained in pursuit. The resulting 57 hour chase in the July heat saw the crew of ''Constitution'' employ a myriad of methods to outrun the squadron, finally pumping overboard  of drinking water.Jennings 1966, p. 211 Cannon fire was exchanged several times, though the British attempts fell short or over their mark, including an attempted broadside from ''Belvidera''. On 19 July ''Constitution'' pulled far enough ahead of the British squadron that they abandoned the pursuit.Toll 2006, p. 344 She arrived in Boston on 27 July and remained there just long enough to replenish her supplies; Hull sailed without orders on 2 August to avoid being blockaded in port.Jennings 1966, p. 216 Heading on a northeast route towards the British shipping lanes near Halifax and the Gulf of Saint Lawrence, she captured three British merchantmen, which Hull ordered burned rather than risk taking them back to an American port. On 16 August Hull was informed of the presence of a British frigate  to the south and sailed in pursuit.Abbot 1896, Volume I, Part II, Chapter IV
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3e6338b24f6746dd556b4fbb29a43781" name="Chase_of_the_Constitution,_July_1812" sectnum="4#1">../img/3e6338b24f6746dd556b4fbb29a43781.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>