<document id="26ac7d591dacc94faaf50eda76daea7b-5" name="USS_Constitution" cat="29">
<text>
Built in an era when a wooden ship had an expected service life of ten to fifteen years,Martin 1980, p. 193 ''Constitution'' was now thirty-one years old. A routine order for surveys of ships held in ordinary was requested by the Secretary of the Navy John Branch; the commandant of the Charlestown Navy Yard, Charles Morris, estimated a repair cost of over $157,000.Martin 1997, p. 233 On 14 September 1830, an article appeared in the Boston ''Advertiser'' that erroneously claimed the Navy intended to scrap ''Constitution''.The ''Advertiser'' reported that the Secretary of the Navy ordered her to be sold or broken up. Martin presents a valid argument, and explanation of Navy procedures for aging ships, as to why this was not true and misreported Two days later, Oliver Wendell Holmes' poem "Old Ironsides" was published in the same paper and later all over the country, igniting public indignation and inciting efforts to save "Old Ironsides" from the scrap yard. Secretary Branch approved the costs, and she began a leisurely repair period while awaiting completion of the dry dock then under construction at the yard.Martin 1997, pp. 234, 235 In contrast to the efforts to save ''Constitution'', another round of surveys in 1834 would find ''Congress'' unfit for repair; she was unceremoniously broken up in 1835.Toll 2006, p. 474

On 24 June 1833 ''Constitution'' entered dry dock in company of a crowd of observers, among them Vice President Martin Van Buren, Levi Woodbury, Lewis Cass and Levi Lincoln. Captain Jesse Elliott, the new commander of the Navy yard, would oversee her reconstruction. With  of hog in her keel, ''Constitution'' remained in dry dock until 21 June 1834. This would be the first of many times that souvenirs would be made from her old planking; Isaac Hull ordered walking canes, picture frames and even a phaeton that was presented to President Andrew Jackson.Martin 1997, pp. 237, 238 Meanwhile, Elliot directed the installation of a new figurehead of President Jackson under the bowsprit, which became a subject of much controversy due to Jackson's political unpopularity in Boston at the time.Jennings 1966, p. 253 Elliot, a Jacksonian Democrat,Jennings 1966, p. 252 received death threats. Rumors circulated about the citizens of Boston storming the Navy yard to remove the figurehead themselves.

A merchant captain named Samuel Dewey accepted a small wager that he could complete the task of removal. Elliot had posted guards on ''Constitution'' to ensure safety of the figurehead, but—using the noise of thunderstorms to mask his movements—Dewey crossed the Charles River in a small boat and managed to saw off Jackson's head. The severed head made rounds between taverns and meeting houses in Boston until Dewey personally returned it to Secretary of the Navy Mahlon Dickerson; it remained on Dickerson's library shelf for many years. An 1855 letter to the editor of ''The New York Times'' reported the story again. Retrieved on 1 September 2009. The addition of busts to her stern depicting Isaac Hull, William Bainbridge and Charles Stewart escaped controversy of any kind and the busts would remain in place for the next forty years.Martin 1997, p. 240
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d8da4f78294a61a92ced0d147fbcf040" name="General_Jackson_-_Harpers_Weekly,_news_media_image_(1875c)" sectnum="5#1">../img/d8da4f78294a61a92ced0d147fbcf040.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>