<document id="26ac7d591dacc94faaf50eda76daea7b-3.2" name="USS_Constitution" cat="29">
<text>
On 31 October , under the command of William Bainbridge, ran aground off Tripoli while pursuing a Tripoline vessel. The crew were taken prisoner and ''Philadelphia'' was refloated by the Tripolines and brought into their harbor. Preble planned to scuttle ''Philadelphia'' using the captured ship ''Mastico''.Abbot 1896, Volume I, Part I, Chapter XVI She was renamed  and under the command of Stephen Decatur entered Tripoli Harbor on 16 February 1804, quickly overpowering the Tripoline crew and then setting ''Philadelphia'' ablaze.

Withdrawing the squadron to Syracuse, Sicily, Preble began planning for a summer attack on Tripoli, procuring a number of smaller gunboats that could move in closer to Tripoli than was feasible with ''Constitution''s deep draft.Martin 1997, p. 99 Arriving the morning of 3 August, ''Constitution'', , , , , the six gunboats and two bomb ketches began operations. Twenty-two Tripoline gunboats met them in the harbor and, in a series of attacks in the coming month, ''Constitution'' and her squadron severely damaged or destroyed several gunboats, taking their crews prisoner.Abbot 1896, Volume I, Part I, Chapter XVII Yusuf Karamanli remained firm in his demand for ransom and tribute. On the evening of 3 September, Richard Somers assumed command of ''Intrepid'', which had been fitted out as a "floating volcano" with  of gunpowder, and was to sail into Tripoli harbor and blow up in the midst of the corsair fleet close under the walls of the city. That night, she got underway into the harbor, but exploded prematurely, killing Somers and his entire crew of thirteen volunteers.

''Constellation'' and ''President'' arrived on 9 September with Samuel Barron in command, and Preble was forced to relinquish his command of the squadron to Barron, who was senior in rank. ''Constitution'' was ordered to Malta on the 11th for repairs, and while en route captured two Greek vessels attempting to deliver wheat into Tripoli. On 12 October a collision with ''President'' severely damaged ''Constitution''s bow area including her figurehead of Hercules. The collision was attributed to an "Act of God" from a sudden change in wind direction.Martin 1997, pp. 115, 116
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4d23ae13ae0e7dc56c11b13c773e0066" name="burning_of_the_uss_philadelphia" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/4d23ae13ae0e7dc56c11b13c773e0066.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>