<document id="26ac7d591dacc94faaf50eda76daea7b-4.4" name="USS_Constitution" cat="29">
<text>
A frigate sighted on 19 August was determined to be , with the words "Not The Little Belt"In reference to the incident where ''President'' had fired on HMS ''Little Belt'' the year prior, mistaking her for ''Guerriere''. painted on one of her topsails.Toll 2006, p. 348 ''Guerriere'' opened fire upon entering range of ''Constitution'', but Hull held his ship's guns in check until the two warships were a mere  apart, at which point he ordered a full double-loaded broadside of grape and round shot.Jennings 1966, p. 224 Over the course of the engagement, the ships collided, and at one point they rotated together counter-clockwise while ''Constitution'' continued firing broadsides. ''Guerriere''s bowsprit became entangled in ''Constitution''s rigging. When the two ships pulled apart, the force of the extracting bowsprit sent shockwaves through ''Guerriere''s rigging. Her foremast soon collapsed and it took the mainmast down with it shortly afterward.Hill 1905, p. 160 ''Guerriere'' was now a dismasted hulk, so badly damaged that she was not worth towing to port, and Hull ordered her burned the next morning. Using his heavier broadsides and his ship's sailing ability, Hull had managed to surprise the British and to their astonishment, their shot seemed to rebound harmlessly off ''Constitution''s hull. A sailor reportedly exclaimed "Huzzah! her sides are made of iron!"Sources differ on whether this was an English or an American sailor, however, the cheer "Huzzah" was historically used in a celebratory manner. and ''Constitution'' acquired the nickname "Old Ironsides". Arriving back in Boston on 30 August, Hull and his crew found that news of their victory had spread like wildfire, and they were hailed as heroes.Toll 2006, p. 354
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="db4ac1eb07684a70055832e3c7c61bd0" name="Constguncrew" sectnum="4.4#1">../img/db4ac1eb07684a70055832e3c7c61bd0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>