<document id="26ac7d591dacc94faaf50eda76daea7b-5.12" name="USS_Constitution" cat="29">
<text>
The last sailing frigate of the US Navy, , had been launched in 1855, and as steamships began service with the US Navy in growing numbers during the 1850s, many sail powered ships were assigned to training duty. Since the formation of the United States Naval Academy in 1845, there had been a growing need for quarters in which to house the students. In 1857, ''Constitution'' was moved to dry dock at the Portsmouth Navy Yard for conversion into a training ship. Some of the earliest known photographs of her were taken during this refitting, which added classrooms on her spar and gun decks. Reduced in armament to only 16 guns, her rating was changed to a "2nd rate ship". She was recommissioned on 1 August 1860 and moved from Portsmouth to the Naval Academy.Martin 1997, p. 312

At the outbreak of the Civil War in April 1861, ''Constitution'' was ordered to relocate farther north after threats had been made against her by Confederate sympathizers.Martin 1997, p. 314 Several companies of Massachusetts volunteer soldiers were stationed aboard for her protection.Abbot 1896, Volume II, Part III, Chapter II  towed her to New York City, where she arrived on 29 April. She was subsequently relocated, along with the Naval Academy, to Fort Adams near Newport, Rhode Island, for the duration of the war. Her sister ship ''United States'' was abandoned by the Union and then captured by Confederate forces at the Gosport Shipyard in Norfolk, leaving ''Constitution'' the only remaining frigate of the original six frigates.

During the war, to honor ''Constitution''s tradition of service, the US Navy bestowed the name  on an ironclad that was launched on 10 May 1862 as part of the South Atlantic Blockading Squadron and participated in the bombardment of Fort Sumter on 7 April 1863.  Unfortunately, ''New Ironsides''' naval career was short-lived; she was destroyed by fire on 16 December 1865 while in ordinary at the Philadelphia Navy Yard. In August 1865 ''Constitution'' moved back to Annapolis, along with the rest of the Naval Academy. During the voyage she was allowed to drop her tow lines from the tug and continue alone under sail. Despite her age, she was recorded running at  and arrived at Hampton Roads ten hours ahead of the  tug.

Settling in again at the Academy, a series of upgrades were installed that included steam pipes and radiators to supply heat from shore along with gas lighting. From June to August each year she would depart with midshipman for their summer training cruise and then return to operate for the rest of the year as a classroom. In June 1867 her last known plank owner, William Bryant, died in Maine. George Dewey assumed command in November and served as her commanding officer until 1870. In 1871 her condition had deteriorated to the point where she was retired as a training ship and towed to the Philadelphia Navy Yard where she was placed in ordinary on 26 September.Martin 1997, pp. 319–322
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9b4be82b38575636ddb8fd431fc40550" name="USS_Constitution_ready_for_launch" sectnum="5.12#1">../img/9b4be82b38575636ddb8fd431fc40550.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>