<document id="26ac7d591dacc94faaf50eda76daea7b-6.18" name="USS_Constitution" cat="29">
<text>
''Constitution''s mission is to promote understanding of the Navy’s role in war and peace through active participation in public events and education through  outreach programs, public access and historic demonstration. Her crew of 60 officers and sailors participate in ceremonies, educational programs, and special events while keeping the ship open to visitors year-round and providing free tours. The crew are all active-duty US Navy personnel and the assignment is considered special duty in the Navy. ''Constitution'' is the oldest commissioned vessel afloat in the world.

The Naval History & Heritage Command Detachment Boston is responsible for planning and performing her maintenance, repair and restoration, keeping her as close to her 1812 configuration as possible. She is berthed at Pier 1 of the former Charlestown Navy Yard, at one end of Boston's Freedom Trail. She is open to the public year round. The privately run USS Constitution Museum is nearby, located in a restored shipyard building at the foot of Pier 2. ''Constitution'' normally makes one "turnaround cruise" each year and is towed out into Boston Harbor to perform underway demonstrations, including gun drill, and then is returned to her dock where she is berthed in the opposite direction to ensure that she weathers evenly. The "turnaround cruise" is open to the general public based on a "lottery draw" of interested persons each year.

In 2003 the special effects crew from the production of ''Master and Commander: The Far Side of the World'' spent several days using ''Constitution'' as a computer model for the fictional French frigate ''Acheron'', using stem to stern digital image scans of "Old Ironsides". Retrieved on 25 August 2009.

In 2007, her commanding officer, Commander Thomas C. Graves, was relieved of command and reassigned after being accused of abusing his subordinates. The charges were settled at a private U.S. Navy hearing on 26 October 2007. Retrieved on 28 August 2009.

Also in October 2007, she entered a period of repair expected to last until September 2010. During this time the entire spar deck will be stripped down to the support beams and the current Douglas fir decking will be restored to the original white oak and yellow pine. The maintenance will restore the original curvature to the deck which will allow water to drain overboard and not remain standing on the deck area. ''Constitution'' will remain open for visitors but there will be no public "turnaround cruise". Lieutenant Commander John Scivier of the Royal Navy, commanding officer of HMS ''Victory'', paid a visit to ''Constitution'' in November, touring the local facilities with Commander William A. Bullard III, the 70th commanding officer of "Old Ironsides".
They discussed arranging an exchange program between the two ships. Bullard is scheduled to turn command of ''Constitution'' over to Commander Tim Cooper in July 2009.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1e9cb5ff1a03b6a9c850402ed709fcc8" name="USS_Constitution_under_repair_2009" sectnum="6.18#1">../img/1e9cb5ff1a03b6a9c850402ed709fcc8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>