<document id="2748a5cd290c2c660f84875646bc6e05-4" name="Turkey_Vulture" cat="3">
<text>
The Turkey Vulture is sometimes accused of carrying anthrax or hog cholera, both livestock diseases, on its feet or bill by cattle ranchers and is therefore occasionally perceived as a threat.Kirk, D. A., and M. J. Mossman. 1998. Turkey Vulture (Cathartes aura). In The Birds of North America, No. 339 (A. Poole and F. Gill, eds.). The Birds of North America, Inc., Philadelphia, PA. However, the virus that causes hog cholera is destroyed when it passes through the Turkey Vulture's digestive tract. This species also may be perceived as a threat by farmers due to the similar Black Vulture's tendency to attack and kill newborn cattle. The Turkey Vulture does not kill live animals but will mix with flocks of Black Vultures and will scavenge what they leave behind. Nonetheless, its appearance at a location where a calf has been killed gives the incorrect impression that the Turkey Vulture represents a danger to calves. The droppings produced by Turkey Vultures and other vultures can harm or kill trees and other vegetation. The Turkey Vulture can be held in captivity, though the Migratory Bird Treaty Act prevents this in the case of animals which are not injured or able to return to the wild. In captivity, it can be fed fresh meat, and younger birds will gorge themselves if given the opportunity.


The Turkey Vulture species receives special legal protections under the Migratory Bird Treaty Act of 1918 in the United States, by the Convention for the Protection of Migratory Birds in Canada, and by the Convention for the Protection of Migratory Birds and Game Mammals in Mexico. In the USA it is illegal to take, kill, or possess Turkey Vultures, and violation of the law is punishable by a fine of up to 15,000 US dollars and imprisonment of up to six months. It is listed as a species of Least Concern by the IUCN Red List. Populations appear to remain stable, and it has not reached the threshold of inclusion as a threatened species, which requires a decline of more than 30 percent in ten years or three generations.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c65258d39b37ae531e820d410d8b9c61" name="Cathartes_aura_cranium" sectnum="4#1">../img/c65258d39b37ae531e820d410d8b9c61.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>