<document id="27b9dd875888f006b6927962f5874ed8-5.3" name="Thescelosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
In 2000, a skeleton of this genus informally known as "Willo", now on display at the North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences, was described as including the remnants of a four-chambered heart and an aorta. It had been originally unearthed in 1993 in northwestern South Dakota. The authors had found the internal detail through computed tomography imagery.  They suggested that the heart had been saponified (turned to grave wax) under  airless burial conditions, and then changed to goethite, an iron mineral, by replacement of the original material. The authors interpreted the structure of the heart as indicating an elevated metabolic rate for ''Thescelosaurus'', not reptilian cold-bloodedness.

Their conclusions have been disputed; other researchers published a paper where they assert that the heart is really a concretion. As they note, the anatomy given for the object is incorrect (for example, the "aorta" narrows coming into the "heart" and lacks arteries coming from it), it partially engulfs one of the ribs and has an internal structure of concentric layers in some places, and another concretion is preserved behind the right leg. The original authors defended their position; they agreed that it was a type of concretion, but one that had formed around and partially preserved the more muscular portions of the heart and aorta. The question of how this find reflects on metabolic rate and dinosaur internal anatomy may be moot, though, regardless of the object's identity. Both modern crocodilians and birds, the closest living relatives of dinosaurs, have four-chambered hearts (albeit modified in crocodilians), so dinosaurs probably had them as well; the structure is not necessarily tied to metabolic rate.Chinsamy, Anusuya; and Hillenius, Willem J. (2004). "Physiology of nonavian dinosaurs". ''The Dinosauria'', 2nd. 643–659.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="68731ea3abff0396a25b84c58cb1b1bb" name="Willoheart" sectnum="5.3#1">../img/68731ea3abff0396a25b84c58cb1b1bb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>