<document id="27cb0eab7f04704337b59ed22d6d5458-1.1" name="Backmasking" cat="20">
<text>
In 1877 Thomas Edison invented the phonograph, a device that allowed sound to be recorded and reproduced on a rotating cylinder with a stylus (or "needle") attached to a diaphragm mounted at the narrow end of a horn. Emile Berliner invented the familiar lateral-cut disc phonograph record in 1888. His design overtook the Edison phonograph in the 1920s, since Berliner's patent expired in 1918, and others were then free to utilize his invention.

In addition to recreating recorded sounds by placing the stylus on the cylinder or disc and rotating it in the same direction as during the recording, one could hear different sounds by rotating the cylinder or disc backwards. In 1878 Edison noted that, when played backwards, "the song is still melodious in many cases, and some of the strains are sweet and novel, but altogether different from the song reproduced in the right way".Blecha, 48 The backwards playing of records was advised as training for magicians by occultist Aleister Crowley, who suggested in his 1913 book ''Magick (Book 4)'' that an adept "train himself to think backwards by external means", one of which was to "listen to phonograph records, reversed."



The 1950s saw the development of ''musique concrète'', an avant-garde form of electronic music which involves editing together fragments of natural and industrial sounds, and the concurrent spread of the use of tape recorders in recording studios. These two trends led to tape music compositions, composed on tape using techniques including reverse tape effects.

The Beatles, who incorporated the techniques of ''concrète'' into their recordings, were responsible for popularizing the concept of backmasking. Singer John Lennon and producer George Martin both claim they discovered the backward recording technique during the recording of 1966's ''Revolver''; specifically the album tracks "Tomorrow Never Knows" and "I'm Only Sleeping," and the single "Rain". Lennon stated that, while under the influence of marijuana, he accidentally played the tapes for "Rain" in reverse, and enjoyed the sound. The following day he shared the results with the other Beatles, and the effect was used first in the guitar solo for "Tomorrow Never Knows", and later in the coda of "Rain". According to Martin, the band had been experimenting with changing the speeds of and reversing the "Tomorrow Never Knows" tapes, and Martin got the idea of reversing Lennon's vocals and guitar, which he did with a clip from "Rain". Lennon then liked the effect and kept it. Regardless, "Rain" was the first song to feature a backmasked message: "Sunshine … Rain … When the rain comes, they run and hide their heads" (; the last line is the reversed first verse of the song).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1dae2d53ac2a9880ef5140c588c3a819" name="Reel-to-reel_recorder_tc-630" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/1dae2d53ac2a9880ef5140c588c3a819.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>