<document id="28209adff593e056a38cb7f1fde08178-3.9" name="Amazing_Stories" cat="17">
<text>
Cele Goldsmith's tenure as editor began with the opportunity to showcase two very well-established writers: E.E. Smith and Isaac Asimov.  Smith's ''The Galaxy Primes'' began serialization in March 1959.  Asimov's first published story, "Marooned Off Vesta", had appeared in the March 1939 issue of ''Amazing'', and Goldsmith reprinted it in March 1959 along with a sequel and Asimov's comments on the story.  She soon began to publish some of the better new writers.  Cordwainer Smith's "Golden the Ship Was&mdash;Oh! Oh! Oh!" appeared in April; and by the middle of the following year she had managed to attract stories from Robert Sheckley, Alan E. Nourse, Fritz Leiber, Gordon R. Dickson, Robert Bloch, and James Blish.  The changes she made were enough to bring Robert Heinlein back as a subscriber; Heinlein read a copy of the June 1961 issue which, he said, "caused me to think I had been missing something".Ashley, ''Transformations'', pp. 222&ndash;223.  The quote is from an unpublished letter from Heinlein to Goldsmith, quoted by Ashley.


In September 1960 ''Amazing'' began to carry Sam Moskowitz's series of author profiles, which had begun in ''Fantastic'', the sister magazine.  The following month the cover and logo were redesigned.  In April 1961, the 35th anniversary of the first issue, Goldsmith ran several reprints, including stories by Ray Bradbury and Edgar Rice Burroughs.  Goldsmith had little previous experience with science fiction, and bought what she liked, rather than trying to conform to a notion of what science fiction should be.  The result was the debut of more significant writers in her magazines than anywhere else at that time.  She published the first stories of Ursula K. Le Guin, Roger Zelazny, Piers Anthony and Thomas M. Disch, among many others.  Award-winning stories published during Goldsmith's editorship include Zelazny's "He Who Shapes", a story about the use of dream therapy to cure phobias.  It was serialized in the January and February 1965 issues, and won a Nebula Award, an annual award voted on by science fiction writers.  Goldsmith often wrote long, helpful letters to her authors: Zelazny commented in a letter to her that "Most of anything I have learned was stimulated by those first sales, and then I learned, and possibly even learned more, from some of the later rejections". Disch and Le Guin have also acknowledged the influence Goldsmith had on their early careers.Ashley, ''Transformations'', pp. 224&ndash;225.  The quote from Zelazny is from a personal letter from Zelazny to Cele Lalli (Goldsmith), dated March 20, 1965, quoted in Ashley p. 225.

The cover art for ''Amazing'' had been largely supplied by Ed Valigursky during the late fifties, but during the early sixties a much wider variety of artists appeared, including Alex Schomburg, Leo Summers and Ed Emshwiller.  Frank Paul, who had painted all the covers for the first few years of ''Amazing'', contributed a wraparound cover for the April 1961 35th anniversary issue; this was his last cover art for a science fiction magazine.

Goldsmith's open-minded approach meant that ''Amazing'' and ''Fantastic'' published some writers who did not fit into the other magazines.  Philip K. Dick's sales to magazines had dropped, but his work began to appear in ''Amazing'', and Goldsmith also regularly published David R. Bunch's stories of Moderan, a world whose inhabitants were part human and part metal.  Bunch, whose stories were "bewildering, exotic word pictures" according to Mike Ashley, had been unable to sell regularly elsewhere.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="794f6bc78782147cbbb411709815d4e2" name="amazing_stories_196103" sectnum="3.9#1">../img/794f6bc78782147cbbb411709815d4e2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>