<document id="28209adff593e056a38cb7f1fde08178-3.7" name="Amazing_Stories" cat="17">
<text>
Gernsback's editorial in the first issue asserted that "Not only do these amazing tales make tremendously interesting reading&mdash;they are also always instructive".Quoted in Ashley, ''Time Machines'', p. 50.  He had always believed that "scientifiction", as he called these stories, had educational power, but he now understood that the fiction had to entertain as well as to instruct.Ashley, ''Time Machines'', p. 50.  His continued belief in the instructional value of science fiction was not in keeping with the general attitude of the public towards pulp magazines, which was that they were "trash".Carter, ''Creation of Tomorrow'', p. 3.

The first issue of ''Amazing'' contained only reprints, beginning with a serialization of ''Off on a Comet'', by Jules Verne.  In keeping with Gernsback's new approach, this was one of Verne's least scientifically plausible novels.  Also included were H. G. Wells's "The New Accelerator", and Edgar Allan Poe's "The Facts in the Case of M. Valdemar"; Gernsback put the names of all three authors on the cover.  He also reprinted three more recent stories.  Two came from his own magazine, ''Science and Invention''; these were "The Man from the Atom" by G. Peyton Wertenbacker and "The Thing from&mdash;'Outside'" by George Allan England.  The third was Austin Hall's "The Man Who Saved the Earth", which had appeared in ''All-Story Weekly''.Ashley, ''Time Machines'', p. 50&ndash;51.

In the June 1926 issue Gernsback announced a competition to write a short story around a cover drawn by illustrator Frank R. Paul, with a first prize of $250.  The competition drew over 360 entries, seven of which were eventually printed in ''Amazing''.  The winner was Cyril G. Wates, who sold three more stories to Gernsback in the late 1920s.  Two other entrants went on to become successful writers: one was Clare Winger Harris, whose story, "The Fate of the Poseidonia", took third place in the competition, and was published in the June 1927 issue as by "Mrs. F.C. Harris".  The other notable entrant was A. Hyatt Verrill, with "The Voice from the Inner World", which appeared in July 1927.

A letter column, titled "Discussions", soon appeared, and became a regular feature with the January 1927 issue.  Many science fiction readers were isolated in small communities, knowing nobody else who liked the same fiction.  Gernsback's habit of publishing the full address of all his correspondents meant that the letter column allowed fans to correspond with each other directly.  Science fiction fandom traces its beginnings to the letter column in ''Amazing'' and its competitors, and one historian of the field, author Lester del Rey, has commented that the introduction of this letter column "may have been one of the most important events in the history of science fiction".del Rey, ''World of Science Fiction'', p. 45.


An example of one fan of the genre reaching out to others is a 1929 letter by Earl Hess of McIntyre, FL.  An excerpt reads: “...my plea is for help in getting together an independent experimental station, your part to be the putting into the public view of my desire to get in touch with chaps who are of my caliber, who want the opportunity to follow their own inclinations undisturbed, and live healthily and well while doing so.”
Letter in ''Amazing Stories'', June 1928, Vol. 3, No.3, pg. 279



For the first year, ''Amazing'' contained primarily reprinted material.  It was proving difficult to attract new, high-quality material, and Gernsback's slowness at paying his authors did not help.  Writers such as H.P. Lovecraft, H.G. Wells, and Murray Leinster all avoided ''Amazing'' because Gernsback took so long to pay for the stories he printed.  The slow payments were probably known to many of the other active pulp writers, which would have further limited the volume of submissions.  New writers did appear, but the quality of their stories was often weak.Ashley, ''Time Machines'', p. 54&ndash;56.

Gernsback discovered that the audience he had attracted was less interested in scientific invention stories than in fantastical adventures.  A. Merritt's ''The Moon Pool'', which began serialization in May 1927, was an early success; there was little or no scientific basis to the story, but it was very popular with ''Amazing'''s readers.  The covers, all of which were painted by Paul, were garish and juvenile, leading some readers to complain.  Raymond Palmer, later to become an editor of the magazine, wrote that a friend of his was forced to stop buying ''Amazing'' "by reason of his parents' dislike of the cover illustrations"."Discussions", ''Amazing Stories'', October 1928, p. 662; quoted in Ashley, ''Time Machines'', p. 56.  Gernsback experimented with a more sober cover for the September 1928 issue, but it sold poorly, and so the lurid covers continued.  The combination of poor quality fiction with garish artwork has led some critics to comment that Gernsback created a "ghetto" for science fiction,Ashley, ''Time Machines'', p. 58. though it has also been argued that the creation of a specialized market allowed science fiction to develop and mature as a genre.del Rey, ''World of Science Fiction'', p. 80.

Among the regular writers for ''Amazing'' by the end of the 1920s were several who were influential and popular at the time, such as David H. Keller and Stanton Coblentz, and some who would continue to be successful for much longer, most notably Edward E. Smith and Jack Williamson.  Smith's ''The Skylark of Space'', which had been written between 1915 and 1920, was a seminal space opera which found no ready market when ''Argosy'' stopped printing science fiction.Ashley, ''Time Machines'', p. 60.  When Smith saw a copy of the April 1927 issue of ''Amazing'', he submitted it to Sloane, and it appeared in the August&ndash;October 1928 issues.Sanders, ''Smith'', pp. 1 & 9; Moskowitz, ''Seekers'', p. 15.  It was such a success that Sloane requested a sequel before the second installment had been published.Moskowitz, ''Seekers'', p. 15.  It was also in the August 1928 issue that "Armageddon &ndash; 2419 AD", by Philip Francis Nowlan, appeared; this was the first appearance of Buck Rogers in print.Ashley, ''Time Machines'', p. 61-62.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e6f4ebea145d1b4379dd4a76ca6639ee" name="Amazing_stories_192809" sectnum="3.7#1">../img/e6f4ebea145d1b4379dd4a76ca6639ee.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>