<document id="2871d9c0be319d4b8ff139a1fed8a12c-4.8" name="Chew_Stoke" cat="11">
<text>
As with many cities and towns in the United Kingdom, the age of a number of the buildings in Chew Stoke, including the church, school, and several houses, reflects the long history of the village. For example, Chew Stoke School has approximately 170 pupils between 4 and 11 years old. After the age of 11, most pupils attend Chew Valley School. These two buildings were constructed in 1858 by Samuel Burleigh Gabriel on the site of a former charity school founded in 1718. Additional classrooms were built in 1926, and further alterations and extensions were carried out in 1970.

An obelisk on Breach Hill Lane, dating from the early to mid-19th century, is said to have been built as a waterworks marker. It has a square limestone plinth about  high. The obelisk is about  high with a pyramidal top and small opening at the top on two sides.


The importance of farming is reflected in the age of many of the farmhouses. Manor Farm, on Scot Lane (not to be confused with at least two other Manor Farms in the locality) is thought to date from 1495 and, as such, is probably the oldest building in the village. Presently (2007) occupied by Mr and Mrs Slater; the building has recently (2002) undergone a sympathetic extension to incorporate an old semi-derelict barn onto the main house for use as a garage and workshop. Mr Slater, a qualified engineer, is interested in bringing the art of clock making back to the village. Rookery Farmhouse, in Breach Hill Lane, is dated at 1720, with later 18th-century additions to either side of the central rear wing. 
An attached stable,  northeast of the farmhouse, is also a Grade II listed building. 
School Farmhouse, in School Lane, dates from the late 17th century and has a studded oak door in the side of the house. 
Wallis Farmhouse, farther along School Lane, is dated at 1782. 
Yew Tree Farmhouse, one of the oldest buildings in the area, dates to the 15th century but has had extensive alterations since then. 
North Hill Farmhouse also has 15th century origins. 
Paganshill Farmhouse dates from the 17th century. 
Fairseat Farmhouse is from the 18th century and includes a plaque recording that John Wesley preached at the house on 10 September 1790. In August of that year, Fairseat Farmhouse was "registered among the records of this County as a House set apart for the worship of God and religious exercise for Protestant Dissenters." At that time the house belonged to Anna Maria Griffon. In the garden is a large evergreen oak (''Ilex'') which measured  across until half of it broke away in a gale in 1976.

The Methodist Chapel was built in 1815/16 after religious services had been established at Fairseat Farm, and the chapel was rebuilt in the late 19th century with limestone walls with stone dressings and a slate hipped roof with brick eaves stacks and crestings. 

In the hamlet of Stoke Villice, which is south of the main village, there is a 19th-century milestone inscribed "8 miles to Bristol" that also has listed status.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a759696d4e82f61e34bf4ce2ab4a72c1" name="Fairseats" sectnum="4.8#1">../img/a759696d4e82f61e34bf4ce2ab4a72c1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>