<document id="2871d9c0be319d4b8ff139a1fed8a12c-3" name="Chew_Stoke" cat="11">
<text>
The area of Chew Stoke is surrounded by arable land and dairy  farms on the floor of the Chew Valley. It is located along the Strode Brook tributary of the River Chew, on the northwest side of the Chew Valley Lake. While much of the area has been cleared for farming, trees line the tributary and many of the roads. The village is built along the main thoroughfare, Bristol Road, which runs northeast to southwest. An older centre is located along Pilgrims Way, which loops onto Bristol Road and features an old stone packhorse bridge&mdash;now pedestrianised&mdash;and a 1950s Irish bridge, used as a ford in winter. Houses line both of these roads, with residential cul-de-sacs and lanes extending from them.

Chew Stoke is approximately  south of Bristol,  from Bath, and  from Keynsham. It is  south of Chew Magna on the B3130 road that joins the A37 and A38. The A368 crosses the valley west of the lake. The "Chew Valley Explorer" bus route 672/674, running from Bristol Bus Station to Cheddar, provides public transport access. This service is operated by Eurotaxis and subsidised by Bath and North East Somerset council. In 2002, a  cycle route, the Chew Lake West Green Route, was opened around the western part of the lake from Chew Stoke. It forms part of the Padstow to Bristol West Country Way, National Cycle Network Route 3. It has all-weather surfacing, providing a smooth off-road facility for ramblers, mobility-challenged visitors, and cyclists of all abilities. Funding was provided by Bath and North East Somerset Council, with the support of Sustrans and the Chew Valley Recreational Trail Association. The minor roads around the lake are also frequently used by cyclists. Bristol International Airport is approximately  away, and the nearest train stations are Keynsham, Bath Spa, and Bristol Temple Meads.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e0415ed8154443ed6bcfbbc3e26a6593" name="ChewStokeMap" sectnum="3#1">../img/e0415ed8154443ed6bcfbbc3e26a6593.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>