<document id="287b5f52e0e4c9acb350dbf700d2a42d-3" name="Chew_Valley_Lake" cat="11">
<text>
The area the lake covers was once rich farmland. Several farms and houses had to be removed before the land was flooded, and old roads, hedgerows and tree stumps can reappear when dry summers cause the level of the lake to drop. Prior to the flooding of the reservoir, archaeological excavations were carried out by Philip Rahtz and Ernest Greenfield employed by the Ministry of Works, from 1953 to 1955. The excavations found evidence of people belonging to the consecutive periods known as Upper Palaeolithic, Mesolithic and Neolithic (Old, Middle and New Stone Age), Bronze Age and Iron Age, including implements such as stone knives, flint blades and the head of a mace, along with buildings and graves. The artefacts from this period are held at Bristol City Museum and Art Gallery. Further evidence of Neolithic and Bronze Age occupation is provided by the archaeological survey of the Mendip Hills Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty. 
Excavations have also uncovered Roman remains, indicating agricultural and industrial activity from the second half of the first century to third century AD.  These finds included a moderately large villa, at Chew Park where wooden writing tablets (the first in the UK) with ink writing were found.  The tablets were sent to the British Museum, but other Roman material is on display at the Bristol City Museum and Art Gallery with the lake's other historical artefacts.

Further excavations around the village of Moreton, which has now been totally submerged, found evidence of a thriving community in medieval times and possibly the remains of the Nunnery of Santa Cruz. During the Middle Ages farming was the most important activity supported in the area covered by the lake, supported by four flour mills powered by the River Chew. Stratford Mill was demolished and re-erected in the grounds of Blaise Castle Museum, in north-west Bristol. The largest settlement was Moreton, which is listed in the Domesday Book and survived until the flooding of the lake, when the remains of the Moreton Cross were moved to Chew Stoke Parish Church. There is also evidence of lime kilns, which were used in the production of mortar for the construction of local churches. Farming, both arable and dairy, continued until the flooding of the lake, with most households also keeping pigs. There were many orchards for fruit production, including apples, pears and plums. In recent years there have been sightings of a ghostly young girl who has been seen by several local people crossing the B3114 walking towards the lake.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d4616937aa5b8079c425cd2d6dbf252a" name="Chewvalleylakeplaque" sectnum="3#1">../img/d4616937aa5b8079c425cd2d6dbf252a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>