<document id="28d565d33524329ba765a963b6e2db66-2.2" name="Battle_of_Bicocca" cat="29">
<text>
The overall command of the Swiss assault was given to Anne de Montmorency.  As the Swiss columns advanced towards the park, he ordered them to pause and wait for the French artillery to bombard the Imperial defences, but the Swiss refused to obey.Oman, ''Art of War'', 180; Taylor, ''Art of War'', 126.  Perhaps the Swiss captains doubted that the artillery would have any effect on the earthworks; historian Charles Oman suggests that it is more likely they were "inspired by blind pugnacity and self-confidence".Oman, ''Art of War'', 180.  Oman notes that this theory was popular among the French observers of the battle.  In any case, the Swiss moved rapidly towards Colonna's position, leaving the artillery behind.  There was apparently some rivalry between the two columns, as one, commanded by Arnold Winkelried of Unterwalden, was composed of men from the rural cantons, while the other, under Albert von Stein, consisted of the contingents from Bern and the urban cantons.Oman, ''Art of War'', 180.  The advancing Swiss quickly came into range of the Imperial artillery.  Unable to take cover on the level fields, they began to take substantial casualties; as many as a thousand Swiss may have been killed by the time the columns reached the Imperial lines.Oman, ''Art of War'', 180–181.



The Swiss came to a sudden halt as the columns reached the sunken road in front of the park; the depth of the road and the height of the rampart behind it—together higher than the length of the Swiss pikes—effectively blocked their advance.  Moving down into the road, the Swiss suffered massive casualties from the fire of d'Avalos's arquebusiers.Hall, ''Weapons and Warfare'', 175; Oman, ''Art of War'', 181.  Oman relates "that all the standards went down, and that the three or four first ranks perished wholesale."  Nevertheless, the Swiss made a series of desperate attempts to breach the Imperial line.  Some parties managed to reach the top of the rampart, only to be met by the landsknechts, who had come up from behind the arquebusiers.  One of the Swiss captains was apparently killed by Frundsberg in single combat; and the Swiss, unable to form up atop the earthworks, were pushed back down into the sunken road.Hall, ''Weapons and Warfare'', 175; Oman, ''Art of War'', 182.  Arnold Winkelried and Albert von Stein are each named as Frundsberg's opponent in contemporary sources.  Oman suggests that Winkelried's actions here may have caused his name to appear in the legend of Arnold Winkelried of Sempach.  After attempting to move forward for about half an hour, the remnants of the Swiss columns retreated back towards the main French line.  In the fields which they had crossed and before the rampart, they left more than 3,000 dead; among these were twenty-two captains, including both Winkelried and Albert von Stein.Hackett, ''Francis the First'', 250; Oman, ''Art of War'', 182.  Of the French nobles who had accompanied the Swiss assault, only Montmorency survived.Oman, ''Art of War'', 182.  Montmorency was badly wounded and had to be carried out of the sunken road.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f53180d714d1b9a4b2bbc5bfd204e7ab" name="Anne_de_Montmorency_(1530)" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/f53180d714d1b9a4b2bbc5bfd204e7ab.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>