<document id="28ecda472f12317d5cadd92f6d3925f1-4" name="French_Texas" cat="14">
<text>
La Salle's mission had remained secret until 1686 when former expedition member Denis Thomas, who had deserted in Santo Domingo, was arrested for piracy. In an attempt to gain a lesser punishment, Thomas informed his Spanish jailers of La Salle's plan to found a colony and eventually conquer Spanish silver mines. Despite his confession, Thomas was hanged.Bruseth and Turner (2005), pp. 7&ndash;8.

The Spanish government felt the French colony would be a threat to their mines and shipping routes, and Carlos II's Council of War thought that "Spain needed swift action 'to remove this thorn which has been thrust into the heart of America. The greater the delay the greater the difficulty of attainment.'" The Spanish had no idea where to find La Salle, and in 1686 they sent a sea expedition and two land expeditions to try to locate his colony. Although the expeditions were unable to find La Salle, they did narrow the search to the area between the Rio Grande and the Mississippi.Weber (1992), p. 151. Four additional Spanish expeditions the following year failed to find La Salle, but helped Spain to better understand the geography of the Gulf Coast region.

In 1688, the Spanish sent three more expeditions, two by sea and one by land. The land expedition, led by Alonso De Le贸n, discovered Jean Gery, who had deserted the French colony and was living in Southern Texas with the Coahuiltecans.Weber (1992), pp. 151&ndash;152. Using Gery as a translator and guide, De Le贸n finally found the French fort in late April 1689. The fort and the five crude houses surrounding it were in ruins. Several months before, the Karankawa had attacked the settlement. The Native Americans left a great deal of destruction and the bodies of three people, including a woman who had been shot in the back. A Spanish priest who had accompanied De Le贸n conducted funeral services for the three victims.Chipman (1992), p. 83. The chronicler of the expedition, Juan Bautista Chapa, wrote that the devastation was God's punishment for opposing the Pope, as Pope Alexander VI had granted the Indies exclusively to the Spanish.Weber (1992), p. 152. The remains of the fort were destroyed by the Spanish, who also buried the French cannons left behind.Weber (1992), p. 153. The Spanish later built a fort on the same location.Weber (1992), p. 168.

In early 1689, Spanish authorities received a plea, written in French. Jumano scouts had received these papers from the Caddo, who asked that they be delivered to the Spanish. The papers included a parchment painting of a ship, as well as a written message from Jean L'Archeveque.  The message read: 

De Le贸n later rescued L'Archeveque and his companion Jacques Grollet.  On interrogation, the men maintained that over 100 of the French settlers had died of smallpox, and the others had been killed by Native Americans. The only people known to have survived the final attack were the Talon children, who had been adopted by the Karankawa.Calloway (2003), p. 256. According to the children, they had been attacked around Christmas of 1688 and all the remaining settlers had been killed.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="89fccca5082aaa1c33652b50d1705c37" name="Matagorda_Bay_Texas_1689" sectnum="4#1">../img/89fccca5082aaa1c33652b50d1705c37.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>