<document id="28ecda472f12317d5cadd92f6d3925f1-1" name="French_Texas" cat="14">
<text>
By the late 17th century, much of North America had been claimed by European countries. Spain had claimed Florida as well as modern-day Mexico and much of the southwestern part of the continent.  The northern Atlantic coast was claimed by Britain, and New France comprised much of what is now Canada as well as the central Illinois Country.  The French feared that their territory was vulnerable to the expansionist aims of its neighbors.  In 1681, French nobleman Robert de La Salle launched an expedition down the Mississippi River from New France, at first believing he would find a path to the Pacific Ocean.Bannon (1997), p. 94.  Instead, La Salle found a route to the Gulf of Mexico.  Although Hernando De Soto had explored and claimed this area for Spain 140 years before,Weber (1992), p. 148. on April 9, 1682 La Salle claimed the Mississippi River valley for French king Louis XIV, naming the territory Louisiana in his honor.Chipman (1992), p. 72. 

Without a French presence at the base of the Mississippi, Spain would have an opportunity to control the entire Gulf of Mexico and potentially pose a threat to New France's southern borders.Chipman (1992), p. 73.  La Salle believed that the Mississippi River was near the eastern edge of New Spain, and on his return to France in 1683, he proposed establishing a colony at the mouth of the river. The colony could provide a base for promoting Christianity among the native peoples as well as a convenient location for attacking the Spanish province of Nueva Vizcaya and gaining control of its lucrative silver mines.Calloway (2003), p. 250.  He argued that a small number of Frenchmen could successfully invade New Spain by allying themselves with over 15,000 Native Americans who were angry over Spanish enslavement. After Spain declared war on France in October 1683, Louis agreed to support La Salle's plan; his official duties now included "confirming the Indians' allegiance to the crown, leading them to the true faith, and maintaining intertribal peace".

La Salle originally planned to sail to New France, journey overland to the Illinois Country, and then traverse the Mississippi River to its mouth.Bruseth and Turner (2005), p. 76. However, to spite Spain Louis insisted La Salle sail through the Gulf of Mexico, which Spain considered its exclusive property.Bruseth and Turner (2005), p. 19. Although La Salle had requested only one ship, on July 24, 1684 he left La Rochelle, France with four: the 36-gun man of war ''Le Joly'', the 300-ton storeship ''L'Aimable'', the barque ''La Belle'', and the ketch ''St. François''.Weddle (1991), p. 13.Chipman (1992), p. 74.  Although Louis XIV had provided both ''Le Joly'' and ''La Belle'', La Salle desired more cargo space and leased ''L'Aimable'' and ''St. François'' from French merchants.  Louis also provided 100 soldiers and full crews for the ships, as well as funds to hire skilled workers to join the expedition. However, La Salle was forced to purchase goods to trade with the Native Americans himself.Bruseth and Turner (2005), p. 20.

The ships carried almost 300 people, including soldiers, artisans and craftsmen, six missionaries, eight merchants, and over a dozen women and children.Weddle (1991), p. 16.  Shortly after their departure, France and Spain ceased hostilities, and Louis was no longer interested in sending La Salle further assistance.Weber (1992), p. 149. Details of the voyage were kept secret so that Spain would not be aware of its purpose, and La Salle's naval commander, the Sieur de Beaujeu, resented the fact that La Salle did not inform him of their destination until the party was well underway. The discord between the two intensified when they reached Santo Domingo and quarreled over where to anchor. Beaujeu sailed to another part of the island, allowing Spanish privateers to capture the ''St. François'', which had been fully loaded with supplies, provisions, and tools for the colony. 

During the 58-day voyage, two people died of illness and one woman gave birth to a child. The voyage to Santo Domingo had lasted longer than expected, and provisions ran low, especially after the loss of the ''St. François''. La Salle had little money with which to replenish supplies, and finally two of the merchants aboard the expedition sold some of their trade goods to the islanders, and lent their profits to La Salle. To fill the gaps left after several men deserted, La Salle recruited a few islanders to join the expedition.Weddle (1991), p. 17.

In late November 1684, when La Salle had fully recovered from a severe illness, the three remaining ships continued their search for the Mississippi River delta. Chipman (1992), p. 75. Before they left Santo Domingo, local sailors warned that strong Gulf currents flowed east and would tug the ships toward the Florida straits unless they corrected for it. On December 18, the ships reached the Gulf of Mexico and entered waters that Spain claimed as its territory.Weddle (1991), p. 19. None of the members of the expedition had ever been in the Gulf of Mexico or knew how to navigate it.Weddle (1991), p. 20. Due to a combination of inaccurate maps, La Salle's previous miscalculation of the latitude of the mouth of the Mississippi River, and overcorrection for the currents, the expedition failed to find the Mississippi.Chipman (1992), p. 76. Instead, they landed at Matagorda Bay in early 1685,  west of the Mississippi.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d3e9058f654af34601410d597e57d346" name="Claude_Bernou_Carte_de_lAmerique_septentrionale" sectnum="1#1">../img/d3e9058f654af34601410d597e57d346.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>