<document id="28ecda472f12317d5cadd92f6d3925f1-3" name="French_Texas" cat="14">
<text>
For several months after the permanent camp was established, the colonists took short trips to  explore their surroundings. At the end of October 1685, La Salle decided to undertake a longer expedition and reloaded the ''Belle'' with many of the remaining supplies. He took 50 men, plus the ''Belle's'' crew of 27 sailors, leaving behind 34 men, women, and children. The bulk of the men traveled with La Salle in canoes, while the ''Belle'' followed further off the coast. After three days of travel, they learned of hostile Native Americans in the area.  Twenty of the Frenchmen attacked the Native American village, where they found Spanish artifacts.Weddle (1991), p. 29. Several of the men died on this expedition from eating prickly pear, and the Karankawa killed a small group of the men who had camped on shore, including the captain of the ''Belle''.Weddle (1991), p. 30.

From January until March 1686, La Salle and most of his men searched overland for the Mississippi River, traveling towards the Rio Grande, possibly as far west as modern-day Langtry. The men questioned the local Native American tribes, asking for information on the locations of the Spaniards and the Spanish mines, offering gifts, and telling stories that portrayed the Spanish as cruel and the French as benevolent. When the group returned, they were unable to find the ''Belle'' where they had left her and were forced to walk back to the fort. 

The following month they traveled east, hoping to locate the Mississippi and return to Canada. During their travels, the group encountered the Caddo, who gave the Frenchmen a map depicting their territory, that of their neighbors, and the location of the Mississippi River.  The Caddo often made friendship pacts with neighboring peoples and extended their policy of peaceful negotiation to the French.Calloway (2003), p. 252. While visiting the Caddo, the French met Jumano traders, who reported on the activities of the Spanish in New Mexico. These traders later informed Spanish officials of the Frenchmen they had seen.Calloway (2003), p. 253.  

Four of the men deserted when they reached the Neches River, and La Salle and one of his nephews became very ill, forcing the group to halt for two months. While the men recovered, the group ran low on food and gunpowder.Weddle (1991), p. 34. In August, the eight surviving members of the expedition returned to Fort Saint Louis, having never left East Texas.Chipman (1992), p. 84.  


While La Salle was gone, six of those who had remained on the ''Belle'' finally arrived at Fort Saint Louis. According to them, the new captain of the ''Belle'' was always drunk. Many of the sailors did not know how to sail, and they grounded the boat on Matagorda Peninsula. The survivors took a canoe to the fort, leaving the ship behind.Weddle (1991), p. 31. The destruction of their last ship left the settlers stranded on the Texas coast, with no hope of gaining assistance from the French colonies in the Caribbean Sea.Chipman (1992), p. 77. 

By early January 1687, fewer than 45 of the original 180 people remained in the colony, which was beset by internal strife.Weddle (1991), p. 35. La Salle believed that their only hope of survival lay in trekking overland to request assistance from New France, and sometime that month he led a final expedition to attempt to reach the Illinois Territory. Fewer than 20 people remained at Fort Saint Louis, primarily women, children, and those deemed unfit, as well as seven soldiers and three missionaries with whom La Salle was unhappy. Seventeen men were included on the expedition, including La Salle, his brother, and two of his nephews.  While camping near present-day Navasota on March 18, several of the men quarreled over the division of buffalo meat. That night, one of La Salle's nephews and two other men were killed in their sleep by another expedition member. The following day La Salle was killed while approaching the camp to investigate his nephew's disappearance. Infighting led to the deaths of two other expedition members within a short time.Weddle (1991), p. 38.  Two of the surviving members, including Jean L'Archeveque, joined the Caddo. The remaining six men made their way to Illinois Country.  During their journey through Illinois to Canada, the men did not tell anyone that La Salle was dead.  They reached France in the summer of 1688 and informed King Louis of La Salle's death and the horrible conditions in the colony.  Louis did not send aid.Bannon (1997), p. 97.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f7f5e04eefd2549133b1d99716a043f0" name="Cavelier_de_la_salle" sectnum="3#1">../img/f7f5e04eefd2549133b1d99716a043f0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>