<document id="29b55b84322492cd3e4dd9530c2cb4ac-3.4" name="Axis_naval_activity_in_Australian_waters" cat="29">
<text>
The bombing of Darwin on 19 February 1942, was the heaviest single attack mounted by the Imperial Japanese Navy against mainland Australia. On 19 February four Japanese aircraft carriers (''Akagi'', ''Kaga'', ''Hiryū'' and ''Sōryū'') launched a total of 188 aircraft from a position in the Timor Sea. The four carriers were escorted by four cruisers and nine destroyers.Tom Lewis (2003). ''A War at Home. A Comprehensive guide to the first Japanese attacks on Darwin''. Tall Stories, Darwin. Page 16. These 188 naval aircraft inflicted heavy damage on Darwin and sank nine ships. A raid conducted by 54 land based bombers later the same day resulted in further damage to the town and RAAF Base Darwin and the destruction of 20 Allied military aircraft. Allied casualties were 251 killed and between 300 and 400 wounded, the majority of whom were non-Australian Allied sailors. Only four Japanese aircraft were confirmed to have been destroyed by Darwin's defenders.David Jenkins (1992), ''Battle Surface! Japan's Submarine War Against Australia 1942–44''. Random House Australia, Sydney. Pages 118–120 and Lewis (2003). Pages 63–71. The four Japanese aircraft carriers involved in the attack on Darwin were sunk during the Battle of Midway in June 1942.

The bombing of Darwin was the first of many Japanese naval aviation attacks against targets in Australia. The three aircraft carriers (''Shōhō'', ''Shōkaku''  and ''Zuikaku'') which escorted the invasion force dispatched against Port Moresby in May 1942 had the secondary role of attacking Allied bases in northern Queensland once Port Moresby was secured.Samuel Eliot Morison (1949 (2001 reprint)). ''Coral Sea, Midway and Submarine Actions, May 1942–August 1942'', Volume 4 of History of United States Naval Operations in World War II. University of Illinois Press, Champaign. Pages 12–13. These attacks did not occur, however, as the landings at Port Moresby were cancelled when the Japanese carrier force was mauled in the Battle of the Coral Sea. 

Japanese aircraft made almost 100 raids, most of them small, against northern Australia during 1942 and 1943. Land-based IJN aircraft took part in many of the 63 raids on Darwin which took place after the initial attack. The town of Broome, Western Australia experienced a devastating attack by IJN fighter planes on March 3, 1942, in which at least 88 people were killed. Long-range seaplanes operating from bases in the Solomon Islands made a number of small attacks on towns in Queensland.Jenkins (1992). Pages 261–262. 

Japanese naval aircraft operating from land bases also harassed coastal shipping in Australia's northern waters during 1942 and 1943. On 15 December 1942 four sailors were killed when the merchant ship ''Period'' was attacked off Cape Wessel. The small general purpose vessel HMAS ''Patricia Cam'' was sunk by a Japanese naval floatplane near the Wessel Islands on 22 January 1943 with the loss of nine sailors and civilians. Another civilian sailor was killed when the merchant ship ''Islander'' was attacked by a floatplane during May 1943.Gill (1968). Pages 264–266.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8c291f552f6f037c742a6774ca66eb80" name="Darwin_Harbour_(AWM_027334)" sectnum="3.4#1">../img/8c291f552f6f037c742a6774ca66eb80.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>