<document id="29b55b84322492cd3e4dd9530c2cb4ac-5.11" name="Axis_naval_activity_in_Australian_waters" cat="29">
<text>
In February 1944, the Japanese Combined Fleet withdrew from its base at Truk and was divided between Palau and Singapore. The appearance of a powerful Japanese squadron at Singapore concerned the Allies, as it was feared that this force could potentially conduct raids in the Indian Ocean and against Western Australia.Odgers (1968). Pages 134–135.

On 1 March 1944 a Japanese squadron consisting of the heavy cruisers ''Aoba'' (flagship), ''Tone'' and ''Chikuma'', under Vice Adm. Naomasa Sakonju, sortied from Sunda Strait to attack Allied shipping sailing on the main route between Aden and Fremantle. The only Allied ship this squadron encountered was the British steamer ''Behar'', which was sunk midway between Ceylon and Fremantle on 9 March 1944. Following this attack the squadron broke off its mission and returned to Batavia as it was feared that Allied ships responding to ''Behar's'' distress signal posed an unacceptable risk. While 102 survivors  from ''Behar'' were rescued by ''Tone'', 82 of these prisoners were murdered after the cruiser arrived in Batavia on 16 March. Following the war Vice Adm. Sakonju was executed for war crimes which included the killing of these prisoners, while the former commander of ''Tone'', Capt. Haruo Mayazumi, was sentenced to seven years imprisonment. Children & Families of Far East Prisoners of War. . Accessed 16 September 2006. The sortie mounted by ''Aoba'', ''Tone'' and ''Chikuma'' was the last raid mounted by Axis surface ships against the Allied lines of communication in the Indian Ocean, or elsewhere, during World War II.Gill (1968). Page 390

While the Japanese raid into the Indian Ocean was not successful, associated Japanese shipping movements provoked a major Allied response. In early March 1944 Allied intelligence reported that two battleships escorted by destroyers had left Singapore in the direction of Surabaya and a U.S. submarine made radar contact with two large Japanese ships in the Lombok Strait. The Australian Chiefs of Staff Committee reported to the Government on 8 March that there was a possibility that these ships could have entered the Indian Ocean to attack Fremantle. In response to this report, all ground and naval defences at Fremantle were fully manned, all shipping was ordered to leave Fremantle and several RAAF squadrons were redeployed to bases in Western Australia.Odgers (1968). Pages 136–139.

This alert proved to be a false alarm, however. The Japanese ships detected in the Lombok Strait were actually the light cruisers ''Kinu'' and ''Oi'' which were covering the return of the surface raiding force from the central Indian Ocean. The alert was lifted at Fremantle on 13 March and the RAAF squadrons began returning to their bases in eastern and northern Australia on 20 March.Gill (1968). Pages 390–391.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ffe3d6fd8f0e638b68b3938d74869937" name="HIJMS_Chikuma" sectnum="5.11#1">../img/ffe3d6fd8f0e638b68b3938d74869937.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>