<document id="29b55b84322492cd3e4dd9530c2cb4ac-4.7" name="Axis_naval_activity_in_Australian_waters" cat="29">
<text>
Japanese submarine operations against Australia in 1943 began when ''I-10'' and ''I-21'' sailed from Rabaul on 7 January to reconnoitre Allied forces around Nouméa and Sydney respectively. ''I-21'' arrived off the coast of New South Wales just over a week later. ''I-21'' operated off the east coast until late February and sank six ships during this period, making it the most successful submarine patrol conducted in Australian waters during World War II.Stevens (2005). Pages 218–220. In addition to these sinkings, ''I-21'''s floatplane conducted a successful reconnaissance of Sydney Harbour on 19 February 1943.Jenkins (1992). Pages 268–272.

In March, ''I-6'' and ''I-26'' entered Australian waters. While ''I-6'' laid nine German-supplied acoustic mines in the approaches to Brisbane this minefield was discovered by HMAS ''Swan'' and neutralised before any ships were sunk.Stevens (2005). Pages 223–224. Although ''I-6'' returned to Rabaul after laying her mines, the Japanese submarine force in Australian waters was expanded in April when the four submarines of Submarine Squadron 3 (''I-11'', ''I-177'', ''I-178'' and ''I-180'') arrived off the east coast and joined ''I-26''. This force had the goal of attacking reinforcement and supply convoys travelling between Australia and New Guinea.Jenkins (1992). Pages 272–273. 

As the Japanese force was too small to cut off all traffic between Australia and New Guinea, the Squadron commander widely dispersed his submarines between the Torres Strait and Wilson's Promontory with the goal of tying down as many Allied ships and aircraft as possible. This offensive continued until June and the five Japanese submarines sank nine ships and damaged several others.Stevens (2005). Pages 230–231. In contrast to 1942, five of the ships sunk off the Australian east coast were travelling in escorted convoys at the time they were attacked. The convoy escorts were not successful in detecting any submarines before they launched their attacks or counter-attacking these submarines.Gill (1968). Pages 253–262. The last attack by a Japanese submarine off the east coast of Australia was made by ''I-174'' on 16 June 1943 when she sank the merchant ship ''Portmar'' and damaged U.S. Landing Ship Tank ''LST 469'' as they were travelling in Convoy GP55 off the New South Wales north coast.Gill (1968). Pages 261–262. 


The single greatest loss of life resulting from a submarine attack in Australian waters occurred in the early hours of 14 May 1943 when ''I-177'' torpedoed and sank Australian Hospital Ship ''Centaur'' off Point Lookout, Queensland. After being hit by a single torpedo ''Centaur'' sank in less than three minutes with the loss of 268 lives. While hospital ships such as ''Centaur'' were legally protected against attack under the terms of the Geneva Conventions it is unclear whether Commander Hajime Nakagawa of ''I-177'' was aware that ''Centaur'' was a hospital ship. While she was clearly marked with a red cross and was fully illuminated, the light conditions at the time may have resulted in Nakagawa not being aware of '' Centaur'''s status, making her sinking a tragic accident. However, as Nakagawa had a poor record as a submarine captain and was later convicted of machine gunning the survivors of a British merchant ship in the Indian Ocean, it is probable that the sinking of ''Centaur'' was due to either Nakagawa's incompetence or indifference to the laws of warfare.Jenkins (1992). Pages 277–285. The attack on ''Centaur'' sparked widespread public outrage in Australia.Tom Frame (2004), ''No Pleasure Cruise: The Story of the Royal Australian Navy''. Allen & Unwin, Sydney. Pages 186–187.

The Japanese submarine offensive against Australia was broken off in July 1943 when the submarines were redeployed to counter Allied offensives elsewhere in the Pacific. The last two Japanese submarines to be dispatched against the Australian east coast, ''I-177'' and ''I-180'', were redirected to the central Solomon Islands shortly before they would have arrived off Australia in July.Stevens (2005). Page 246. The Australian Naval authorities were concerned about a resumption of attacks, however, and maintained the coastal convoy system until late 1943 when it was clear that the threat had passed. Coastal convoys in waters south of Newcastle ceased on 7 December and convoys off the north-east coast and between Australia and New Guinea were abolished in February and March 1944 respectively.Stevens (2005). Pages 246–248.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="76542c434bda6ed59db1687265e75a51" name="Centaur_(AWM_043235)" sectnum="4.7#1">../img/76542c434bda6ed59db1687265e75a51.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>