<document id="29b55b84322492cd3e4dd9530c2cb4ac-2.1" name="Axis_naval_activity_in_Australian_waters" cat="29">
<text>
While German surface raiders operated in the western Indian Ocean in 1939 and early 1940, they did not enter Australian waters until the second half of 1940. The first Axis ships in Australian waters were the unarmed Italian ocean liners ''Remo'' and ''Romolo'', which were in Australian waters when Fascist Italy entered the war on 11 June 1940, Eastern Australian Time. While ''Remo'' was docked at Fremantle and was easily captured, ''Romolo'' proved harder to catch, as she had left Brisbane on 5 June bound for Italy. Following an air and sea search, ''Romolo'' was intercepted by HMAS ''Manoora'' near Nauru on 12 June and was scuttled by her captain to avoid capture.Gill (1957). Pages 118–124.

The German surface raider HSK ''Orion'' was the first Axis warship to operate in Australian waters during World War II. After operating off the northern tip of New Zealand and the South Pacific, ''Orion'' entered Australian waters in the Coral Sea in August 1940 and closed to within  north-east of Brisbane on 11 August.Gill (1957). Page 261. Following this, ''Orion'' headed east and operated off New Caledonia before proceeding south into the Tasman Sea, sinking the merchant ship ''Notou'' south-west of Noumea on 16 August and the British merchant ship ''Turakina'' in the Tasman Sea four days later. ''Orion'' sailed south-west after sinking ''Turakina'', passing south of Tasmania, and operated without success in the Great Australian Bight in early September. While ''Orion'' laid four dummy mines off Albany, Western Australia on 2 September, she departed to the south-west after being spotted by an Australian aircraft the next day. After unsuccessfully patrolling in the Southern Ocean, ''Orion'' sailed for the Marshall Islands to refuel, arriving there on 10 October.Gill (1957). Page 262.

German attacks in Western Pacific, 12/1940 - 01/1941
HSK ''Pinguin'' was the next raider to enter Australian waters. ''Pinguin'' entered the Indian Ocean from the South Atlantic in August 1940 and arrived off Western Australia in October. ''Pinguin'' captured the Norwegian 8,998 ton tanker ''Storstad''Warsailors.com:  off North West Cape on 7 October and proceeded east with the captured ship. ''Pinguin'' laid mines between Sydney and Newcastle on 28 October, and ''Storstad'' laid mines off the Victorian coast on the nights of 29–31 October. ''Pinguin'' also laid further mines off Adelaide in early November. The two ships then sailed west for the Indian Ocean. ''Pinguin'' and ''Storstad'' were not detected during their operations off Australia's eastern and southern coasts, and succeeded in sinking three ships. Mines laid by ''Storstad'' sank two ships off Wilson's Promontory in early November, and the mines laid off Sydney by ''Pinguin'' sank one ship and a further merchant ship was damaged after striking a mine off Adelaide. ''Pinguin'' added to her tally of successes in Australian waters by sinking three merchant ships in the Indian Ocean during November.Gill (1957). Pages 270–275.

On 7 December 1940 the German raiders ''Orion'' and ''Komet'' arrived off the Australian protectorate of Nauru. During the next 48 hours the two ships sank four merchant ships off the undefended island.Gill (1957). Pages 276–279. Heavily loaded with survivors from their victims, the raiders departed for Emirau Island where they unloaded their prisoners. After an unsuccessful attempt to lay mines off Rabaul on 24 December, ''Komet'' made a second attack on Nauru on 27 December and shelled the island's phosphate plant and dock facilities.Gill (1957). Page 281. This attack was the last Axis naval attack in Australian waters until November 1941.Gill (1957). Page 410.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="39b76f064004239ab397ef91b4b61a7d" name="Romolo_(AWM_044621)" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/39b76f064004239ab397ef91b4b61a7d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>