<document id="29b55b84322492cd3e4dd9530c2cb4ac-5.12" name="Axis_naval_activity_in_Australian_waters" cat="29">
<text>
On 14 September 1944, the commander of the ''Kriegsmarine'', Grand Admiral Karl Dönitz, approved a proposal to send two Type IXD U-Boats into Australian waters with the objective of tying down Allied anti-submarine assets in a secondary theatre. The U-Boats involved was drawn from the ''Monsun Gruppe'' ("Monsoon Group"), and the two selected for this operation were ''U-168'' and ''U-862''.Stevens (2005). Page 262. An additional submarine, ''U-537'', was added to this force at the end of September.David Stevens (1997), ''U-Boat Far from Home''. Allen & Unwin, Sydney. Page 119.


Due to the difficulty of maintaining German submarines in Japanese bases, the German force was not ready to depart from its bases in Penang and Batavia (Jakarta) until early October. By this time, the Allies had intercepted and decoded German and Japanese messages describing the operation and were able to vector Allied submarines onto the German boats. The Dutch submarine ''Zwaardvisch'' sank ''U-168'' on 6 October near SurabayaPaul Kemp (1997), ''U-Boats Destroyed. German Submarine Losses in the World Wars''. Arms and Armour, London. Page 221. and the USS ''Flounder'' sank ''U-537'' on 10 November near the northern end of the Lombok Strait.Kemp (1997). Page 224. Due to the priority accorded to the Australian operation, ''U-196'' was ordered to replace ''U-168''.Stevens (1997). Page 124. However, ''U-196'' disappeared in the Sunda Strait some time after departing from Penang on November 30. The cause of ''U-196's'' loss is not known, though it was probably due to an accident or mechanical fault.Kemp (1997). Page 225. Kemp suggests that ''U-196'' may have been lost in a diving accident or due to a fault in the boat's locally constructed snorkel.

The only surviving submarine of the force assigned to attack Australia, ''U-862'', under ''Korvettenkapitän'' Heinrich Timm, departed Batavia on 18 November 1944, and arrived off the south west tip of Western Australia on 26 November. The submarine had great difficulty finding targets as the Australian naval authorities, warned of ''U-862'''s approach, had directed shipping away from the routes normally used. ''U-862'' unsuccessfully attacked the Greek freighter ''Ilissos'' off the South Australian coast on December 9, with bad weather spoiling both the attack and subsequent Australian efforts to locate the submarine.Stevens (1997). Pages 147–151.

Following her attack on ''Ilissos'', ''U-862'' continued east along the Australian coastline, becoming the only German submarine to operate in the Pacific Ocean during World War II.Uboat.net . Accessed 5 August 2006. After entering the Pacific ''U-862'' scored her first success on this patrol when she attacked the US-registered Liberty Ship ''Robert J. Walker'' off the south coast of New South Wales on 24 December 1944. The ship sank the following day. Following this attack, ''U-862'' evaded an intensive search by Australian aircraft and warships and departed for New Zealand.Stevens (1997). Pages 159–173.

As ''U-862'' did not find any worthwhile targets off New Zealand, the submarine's commander  planned to return to Australian waters in January 1945 and operate to the north of Sydney. ''U-862'' was ordered to break off her mission in mid-January, however, and return to Jakarta.Stevens (2005). Page 278. On her return voyage, the submarine sank another U.S. Liberty Ship, ''Peter Silvester'', approximately 1,520 kilometres (820 nautical miles) southwest of Fremantle on 6 February 1945. ''Peter Silvester'' was the last Allied ship to be sunk by the Axis in the Indian Ocean during the war.Gill (1968). Page 557. ''U-862'' arrived in Jakarta in mid February 1945 and is the only Axis ship known to have operated in Australian waters during 1945. Following Germany's surrender ''U-862'' became the Japanese submarine ''I-502'' but was not used operationally.Stevens (1997). Page 222.

While Allied naval authorities were aware of the approach of the German strike force and were successful in sinking two of the four submarines dispatched, efforts to locate and sink ''U-862'' once she reached Australian waters were continually hampered by a lack of suitable ships and aircraft and a lack of personnel trained and experienced in anti-submarine warfare.Stevens (2005). Page 258. As the southern coast of Australia was thousands of kilometres behind the active combat front in South-East Asia and had not been raided for several years it should not be considered surprising that few anti-submarine assets were available in this area in late 1944 and early 1945.Stevens (1997). Pages 164–165.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="21b1ab9ad3f3af1e2f5aebb985e49d9d" name="U-505chicago" sectnum="5.12#1">../img/21b1ab9ad3f3af1e2f5aebb985e49d9d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>