<document id="29b55b84322492cd3e4dd9530c2cb4ac-3.3" name="Axis_naval_activity_in_Australian_waters" cat="29">
<text>
The first Japanese submarines to enter Australian waters were ''I-121'', ''I-122'', ''I-123'' and ''I-124'', from the Imperial Japanese Navy's (IJN's) Submarine Squadron 6. Acting in support of the Japanese offensive in the Netherlands East Indies these boats laid minefields in the approaches to Darwin and the Torres Strait between 12 and 18 January 1942. These mines did not sink or damage any Allied ships.Stevens (2005). Page 183.

After completing their mine laying missions the four Japanese boats took station off Darwin to provide the Japanese fleet with warning of Allied naval movements. On 20 January 1942 the Australian Bathurst class corvettes HMAS ''Deloraine'', HMAS ''Katoomba'' and HMAS ''Lithgow'' sank ''I-124'' near Darwin. This was the only full-sized submarine sunk by the Royal Australian Navy in Australian waters during World War II.Stevens (2005). Pages 183–184. The only other Axis submarines sunk in Australian waters were two of the three midget submarines which entered Sydney Harbour in May 1942.


Following the conquest of the western Pacific the Japanese mounted a number of reconnaissance patrols into Australian waters. Three submarines (''I-1'', ''I-2'' and ''I-3'') operated off Western Australia in March 1942, sinking the merchant ships ''Parigi'' and ''Siantar'' on 1 and 3 March respectively. In addition, ''I-25'' conducted a reconnaissance patrol down the Australian east coast in February and March. During this patrol Nobuo Fujita from the ''I-25'' flew a Yokosuka E14Y floatplane over Sydney (17 February), Melbourne (26 February) and Hobart (1 March).Stevens (2005). Pages 185–186. Following these reconnaissances, ''I-25'' sailed for New Zealand and conducted overflights of Wellington and Auckland on 8 March and 13 March respectively.Sydney David Waters (1956), . Historical Publications Branch, Wellington. Pages 214–215.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7ece40100f17a3b95d91fabf7f9b2d1a" name="I-25" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/7ece40100f17a3b95d91fabf7f9b2d1a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>