<document id="2a2a1ea79f558bbe82c678dfe622524c-1.5" name="Kannada_literature_in_the_Vijayanagara_Empire" cat="17">
<text>
Although most of the writings that have survived from this period are religious in nature, there is sufficient literary evidence that secular writing was also popular in the imperial court. Some of these writings carry useful information on urban life, grandeur of the imperial and provincial courts, royal weddings and ceremonies. Other works refer the general town planning, fortifications and ordnance details at Vijayanagara and other important cities, irrigation reservoirs, merchants and shops dealing in a variety of commodities. On occasion, authors dwell on mythical cities that reflect their idealised views on contemporary life.Sinopoli (2003), p. 130 Commonly found in these works are description of artists and professionals and their relationship with the court. These included poets, bards, composers, painters, sculptors, dancers, theatrical performers and even wrestlers. Others who find mention are political leaders, ambassadors, concubines, accountants, goldsmiths, moneylenders and even servants and door keepers.Sinopoli (2003), pp. 130–133

Writings in various literary genres such as romance, fiction, erotica, folk songs and musical compositions were popular. A wealth of literature dealing in subjects such as astronomy, meteorology, veterinary science and medicine, astrology, grammar, philosophy, poetry, prosody, biography, history and lexicon, as well as dictionaries and encyclopedias, were written in this era.Narasimhacharya (1988), pp. 61–64

In 1360, Manjaraja I wrote a book on medicine called ''Khagendra Mani Darpana'', basing it on the 5th century writings of Pujyapada.Rice E.P. (1921), p. 45 Padmananka (1385) wrote a biography of his ancestor Kereya Padmarasa, a Hoysala minister and poet, in a work titled ''Padmaraja Purana''. The writing provides details about the Hoysala empire and notable personalities such as the poets Harihara and Raghavanka.Sahitya Akademi (1992), p. 4003 Chandrashekara (or Chrakavi), a court poet of Deva Raya II, wrote an account on the Virupaksha temple, its precincts and settlements at Pampapura (modern Hampi) in the ''Pampasthana Varnanam'' in 1430.Kotraiah in Sinopoli (2003), p. 131 Mangaraja II authored a lexicon called ''Mangaraja Nighantu'' in 1398, while Abhinava Chandra gave an account on veterinary science in his book called ''Asva Vaidya'' in the 14th century. Kavi Malla wrote on erotics in the ''Manmathavijaya'' in the 14th century. In the 15th century, Madhava translated an earlier Sanskrit poem by Dandi and called it ''Madhavalankara'', and Isvara Kavi (also called Bana Kavi) wrote a prosody called ''Kavijihva Bandhana''.Narasimhacharya (1988), pp. 62–64

Deparaja, a member of the royal family, authored ''Amaruka'' and a collection of romantic stories called the ''Sobagina Sone'' (1410), written in the form of a narration by the author to his wife.Sahitya Akademi (1992), p. 4003Sastri (1955), p. 363 However, according to Kotraiah, ''Sobagina Sone'' was actually written by King Deva Raya II. The writing contains interesting details on the king's hunting expeditions and on the professional hunters who accompanied him.Kotraiah in Sinopoli (2003), pp. 130, 134 In 1525, Nanjunda Kavi, a feudatory prince wrote on local history, published a eulogy of prince Ramanatha (also called Kumara Rama) titled ''Ramanatha Charite'' (or ''Kumara Rama Sangatya'') in the ''sangatya'' metre. The poem is about the prince of Kampili and his heroics at the dawn of the Muslim invasion into southern India. This work combines folk and epic literature. The protagonist rejects the advances of his stepmother, only to be condemned to death. He is rescued by a minister, but eventually achieves martyrdom fighting Muslim invaders at the capital.Sahitya Akademi (1988), p. 1182

In 1567, Jain ascetic Srutakirti of Mysore translated from Sanskrit a biographic poem of a Hoysala lady Vijayakumari in ''Vijayakumari Charite''. The writing goes into detail about a city (believed to be Vijayanagara, the royal capital), discussing its shops, guilds and businesses. The text describes the rigid caste-based human settlements and notes that people involved in mundane duties such as washing, barbering, pot-making and carpentry lived outside the fort walls in streets constructed specifically for them.Kotraiah in Sinopoli (2003), pp. 133–134 Salva (1550) authored two poems called ''Rasa Ratnakar'' and ''Sharada Vilas''. The former is about ''rasa'' (poetical sentiment or flavour) and the latter, only portions of which have been recovered, is about the ''dhvani'' (suggested meaning) in poems. Thimma's ''Navarasalankara'' of 16th century also discusses poetical flavour.Narasimhacharya (1988), p. 62 In the 16th century, lexicons were written by Lingamantri (''Kabbigarakaipidi'') and Devottama (''Nanaratha Ratnakara''). At the turn of the 17th century, Bhattakalanka Deva wrote comprehensively on old Kannada grammar. His ''Karnataka Sabdanusasanam'' is modelled on the lines of Sanskrit grammar and is considered an exhaustive work.Sahitya Akademi (1987), p. 476
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b13df53649a2ba2d1fc606dd685192c4" name="Shravanabelagola_Vindyagiri_14thc_Kannada_inscription" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/b13df53649a2ba2d1fc606dd685192c4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>