<document id="2a2a1ea79f558bbe82c678dfe622524c-1.3" name="Kannada_literature_in_the_Vijayanagara_Empire" cat="17">
<text>
The Veerashaiva writers were devotees of the Hindu God Shiva, his 25 forms, and the expositions of Shaivism. An important development in their literature during this period was the recasting the saints of the 12th century Veerashaiva movement (Basavanna, Allama Prabhu and others) as the protagonists of their writings.Nagaraj (2003), p. 355

Bhima Kavi paved the way for the ''shatpadi'' metre tradition in his work ''Basavapurana'' (c.1369), a form first experimented with by the 12th century Hoysala poet Raghavanka. Bhima Kavi's work, a biography of Basavanna, is an important Veerashaiva ''purana''. It was inspired by earlier biographies of Basavanna by the Hoysala poet Harihara (the author of the first biographical narrative poem of the protagonist's life called ''Basavaraja Ragale'') and the Telugu writings of Palkuriki Somanatha of 13th century. Bhima Kavi humbly acknowledges and eulogises his predecessors in a writing full of well-known personalities.Sahitya Akademi (1987), p. 512

The author starts with Basavanna's birth and weaves episodes of other famous ''sharanas'' (devotees of Hindu God Shiva)—such as Allama Prabhu—into his life history. Basavanna is depicted as a saintly person, a great devotee of Shiva, an incarnation of Nandi, a man of miracles and one with a mission, sent to re-establish the Veerashaiva faith on earth. The work is arranged into eight ''aswasas'' (divisions) containing sixty-one ''sandhis'' (chapters) and 3,621 verses. The narration includes stories of devotees of Shiva who overcame their egos. Apart from a few variations, the writings of Bhima Kavi and his predecessors are complementary. Two lost works of Bhima Kavi are the ''Bhimakaviswara Ragale'' and the ''Bhringidandaka''.Sahitya Akademi (1987), p. 513Sastri (1955), pp. 362–363

Chamarasa, Lakkanna Dandesa and Jakkanarya flourished under the patronage of King Deva Raya II.Rice E.P. (1921), pp. 68, 70 Chamarasa, champion of the Veerashaiva faith, was a rival of Kumara Vyasa in the court of King Deva Raya II. His ''magnum opus'', the ''Prabhulinga Lile'' (1430) was a eulogy of 12th century saint Allama Prabhu; it was translated into Telugu and Tamil language at the behest of his patron king, and later into the Sanskrit and Marathi languages.Sahitya Akademi (1987), p. 617 In the story, the saint is considered an incarnation of Hindu God Ganapathi while Parvati took the form of a princess of Banavasi.Sastri (1955), p. 363 In stark contrast to Kumara Vyasa's war-torn epic, Chamarasa delivered a writing full of spirituality. A remark made by the poet in the writing, that his story is "not about ordinary mortals", implied that the Vaishnava epics the Ramayana and the Mahabharata were about mortals; this was evidence of rivalry between the two faiths.Sahitya Akademi (1987), p. 617

Lakkanna Dandesa, the king's prime minister and provincial governor, wrote an encyclopaedia on the beliefs and rites of the Veerashaiva faith titled ''Sivatattva Chintamani''. This work is an account of the life of Basavanna, the progenitor of the faith, and hundreds of his followers, making it valuable material for students of the Lingayat movement.Sahitya Akademi (1996), p. 4003 Numerous references are made in this work to the capital city of Vijayanagara and its suburbs. Jakkanarya, a minister in the court, not only wrote ''Nurondusthala'' (one hundred and one stories) but also was patron to Kumarabanka Natha and Mahalinga Deva, poet-saints who wrote ''vachana'' poems and books on the Shaiva philosophy (called ''shatsthala'').Sastri (1955), p. 363Rice E.P. (1921), p. 70 Other writers of the 15th century worthy of mention are Kavi Linga (1490), court poet of King Saluva Narasimha I, Adrisappa (''Praudaraya Charitra''),Rice B.L. (1895), p. 501 Bommarasa (''Soundara Purana''), Kallarasa (''Janavasya''), Chaturmukha Bommarasa (''Revanasiddhesvara Purana''), Suranga Kavi (''Trisashti Puratanara Charitre''), and Nilakanthacharya (''Aradhya Charitra''), court poet of the Ummattur chieftain Virananjendra.Narasimhacharya (1988), pp. 22, 69

In 1500, inspired by Palkuriki Somanatha (a bilingual poet in Kannada and Telugu), Singiraja synthesised an account on the life of Basavanna titled ''Maha Basavaraja Charitra'' (or ''Singiraja Purana''), using the protagonist's ''vachana'' poems and giving details of his 88 famous deeds, as well as information about his opponents in the court of Southern Kalachuri King Bijjala II.Rice E.P. (1921), p. 67 An eminent poet of this time was Guru Basava, known for his authorship of seven famous classics (''Sapta Kavya''), all but one being written in the ''shatpadi'' metre. He expounded on religious teachings in the form of formal discussions between the guru and disciple. His ''kavyas'' (classical poems) deal with spiritualism and extrasensory perception.Sahitya akademi (1992), p. 4003

Mallanarya of Gubbi, a poet bilingual in Kannada and Sanskrit, enjoyed the patronage of King Krishnadeva Raya. His important writings in Kannada in the ''shatpadi'' metre are the ''Bhava Chintaratna'' (also called ''Satyendra Chole Kathe'', 1513) and the ''Virasaivamrita Purana'' (1530). The former was based on a 7th-century Tamil work and about a Chola King in the context of the Shaiva faith; the latter is a writing of encyclopedic proportions that goes beyond philosophical content, describing the various forms (or sports, called ''lila'') of God Shiva and the lives of famous Shaiva saints.''Bhava Chintaratna'' is said to be based on a work by Nanasambandar (Sastri 1955, p. 364)Rice E.P. (1921), p. 71

In 1584, Virupaksha Pandita, the head priest at the Virupaksha Temple in Vijayanagara, wrote an account on the life and deeds of the 12th century saint and ''vachana'' poet Chennabasava. The writing, titled ''Chenna Basava Purana'', regards the protagonist as an incarnation of God Shiva and describes the glory of Shiva and his famous devotees. The book gives valuable information, including dates, about early Veerashaiva saints and ''vachanakaras'' (''vachana'' poets).Rice E.P. (1921), p. 68 In addition to religious content, the writing provides useful insights about the former capital Vijayanagara, its royal palace, its market places and merchants, its military encampments, specialisations and divisions and the guilds of workers who served the military in various capacities.Sinopoli (2003), p. 134 Other authors from the 16th century were Chermanka (''Chermanka Kavya''), Virabhadraraja (''Virabhadra Vijaya''), Chennabasavanka (''Mahadevi Akkanna Purana''), Nanjunda of Ikkeri (''Bhairavaesvara Kavya'') and Sadasiva Yogi (''Ramanatha Vilasa'').
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fe1d4e3855d8dafca32a10f81894eda1" name="Kudala_Sangama" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/fe1d4e3855d8dafca32a10f81894eda1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>