<document id="2a2a1ea79f558bbe82c678dfe622524c-2.7" name="Kannada_literature_in_the_Vijayanagara_Empire" cat="17">
<text>
''Vachana'' poetry, developed in reaction to the rigid caste-based Hindu society, attained its peak in popularity among the under-privileged during the 12th century. The Veerashaivas, who wrote this poetry, had risen to influential positions by the Vijayanagara period.Shiva Prakash (1997), p. 188 Following the Muslim invasions in early 14th century, Brahmin scholars methodically consolidated writings of Hindu lore. This inspired several Veerashaiva anthologists of the 15th and 16th centuries to collect Shaiva writings and ''vachana'' poems, originally written on palm leaf manuscripts. Because of the cryptic nature of the poems, the anthologists added commentaries to them, thereby providing their hidden meaning and esoteric significance.Sahitya Akademi (1987), p. 761 An interesting aspect of this anthological work was the translation of the Shaiva canon into Sanskrit, bringing it into the sphere of the Sanskritic cultural order.Nagraj (2003), p. 368

Well-known among these anthologies are ''Ganabhasita Ratnamale'' by Kallumathada Prabhudeva (1430), ''Visesanubhava Satsthala'' by Channaviracharya (16th century) and ''Bedagina Vachanagalu'' by Siddha Basavaraja (1600). The unique ''Shunyasampadane'' (the 'mystical zero') was compiled in four versions.Sahitya Akademi (1987), pp. 191, 199–200 The first among them was anthologised by Shivaganaprasadi Mahadevaiah (1400), who set the pattern for the other three to follow. The poems in this anthology are essentially in the form of dialogues between patron saint Allama Prabhu and famous ''Sharanas'' (devotees), and was meant to rekindle the revolutionary spirit of the 12th century. Halage Arya (1500–1530), Gummalapura Siddhalinga Yati (1560) and Gulur Siddaveeranodaya (1570) produced the later versions.Shiva Prakash (1997), p. 189

Though the writing of ''vachana'' poems went into decline after the passing of the Basavanna era in late 12th century, latter day ''vachanakaras'' such as Tontada Siddhesavara (or Siddhalinga Yati), a noted Shaiva saint and guru of King Virupaksha Raya II, started a revival. He wrote ''Shatsthala Jnanamrita'' (1540), a collection of 700 poems.Sastri (1955), p. 362 In 1560, Virakta Tontadarya made the life of Tontada Siddhesavara the central theme in his writing ''Siddhesvara Purana''.Rice (1921), p. 71 Virakta Tontadarya, Gummalapura Siddhalinga, Swatantra Siddhalingeshwara (1560) and Ghanalingideva (1560) are some well-known ''vachana'' poets who tried to recreate the glory days of the early poets, though the socio-political expediency did not exist.

Mystic literature had a resurgence towards the beginning of 15th century, in an attempt to synthesise the Veerashaiva and advaitha (monistic) philosophies; this trend continued into the 19th century.Sahitya Akademi (1987), p. 200 Prominent among these mystics was Nijaguna Shivayogi, by tradition a petty chieftain near the Kollegal region (modern Mysore district) turned Shaiva saint, who composed devotional songs collectively known as ''Kaivalya sahitya'' (or ''Tattva Padagalu'', literally "songs of the pathway to emancipation"). Shivayogi's songs were reflective, philosophical and concerned with Yoga. They were written in almost all the native metres of Kannada language with the exception of ''shatpadi'' metre.

Shivayogi's other writings include a scientific encyclopaedia called ''Vivekachintamani'', so well regarded that it was translated into Marathi language in 1604 and Sanskrit language in 1652 and again in the 18th century. The writing categorises 1,500 topics based on subject and covers a wide array such as poetics, dance and drama, musicology and erotics.Sahitya Akademi (1988), p. 1165 His translation of the ''Shiva Yoga Pradipika'' from Sanskrit was done to elucidate the Shaiva philosophy and benefit those ignorant of the original language.Rice E.P. (1921), p. 71

In the post-Vijayanagara era, the ''Kaivalya'' tradition branched three ways. The first consisted of followers of the Nijaguna Shivayogi school, the second was more elitist and brahminical in nature and followed the writings of Mahalingaranga (1675), while the third was the branch that kept the ''vachana'' tradition alive.Shiva Prakash (1997), p. 191 Well-known poet-saints from this ''vachana'' tradition were Shivayogi's contemporary Muppina Sadakshari, whose collection of songs are called the ''Subodhasara''; Chidananda Avadhuta of the 17th century; and Sarpabhushana Shivayogi of the 18th century. So vast is this body of literature that much of it still needs to be studied.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f10a3a4d5af3c0fbd7756488c8968a1c" name="Akkamahadevi_Udathadi1" sectnum="2.7#1">../img/f10a3a4d5af3c0fbd7756488c8968a1c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>