<document id="2a2a1ea79f558bbe82c678dfe622524c-1.2" name="Kannada_literature_in_the_Vijayanagara_Empire" cat="17">
<text>
Vaishnava authors wrote treatments of the Hindu epics, the Ramayana, the Mahabharata and the Bhagavata, as well as the Vedanta and other subjects from the Hindu puranic traditions.Narasimhacharya (1988), p. 61
This was the age of Kumara Vyasa, an influential Vaishnava poet and a doyen of medieval Kannada epic poetry. Historians have drawn parallels between Adikavi Pampa (c. 941) and Kumaraya Vyasa, while identifying fundamental differences in their style. Both are considered masters of their respective periods; while Pampa is identified as a stylist of the classical age, Kumara Vyasa is considered a generalist of the medieval age. Unlike Pampa, a product of the ''marga'' (Sanskritic-mainstream) period of Kannada literature, Kumara Vyasa successfully wielded the flexibility of the ''desi'' (native) ''shatpadi'' metre, which used a range of language that included metaphors, similes, humour and even vulgarity.Shiva Prakash (1997), pp. 208–209

Kumara Vyasa wrote ''Gadugina Bharata'' in 1430 in the Vyasa tradition. The title of the work is a reference to ''Gadagu'' (modern Gadag), where the author lived. The writing is based on the first ten chapters of the Hindu epic Mahabharata and is also alternatively titled ''Karnata Bharata Kathamanjari'' or ''Kumaravyasa Bharata''. It is a dedication to the deity of Gadag and emphasises the divinity and grace of the Hindu God Krishna. Unlike Pampa, who adhered to a strictly Jain interpretation of the epic in his ''Vikramarjuna Vijaya'' (941), eulogising Pandava Arjuna as the hero, making Draupadi solely Arjuna's wife and casting the Kaurava prince Duryodhana and his loyal companion Karna as lofty individuals, Kumara Vyasa portrays all characters with the exception of Krishna as deeply human with foibles. His depiction of the secondary characters, such as the cunning Keechaka and the coward Uttara Kumara, is also noteworthy.Rice E.P. (1921), p. 31Sahitya Akademi (1987), p. 37 An interesting aspect of the work is the sense of humour exhibited by the poet and his hero, Krishna. This work marks the transition in Kannada literature from old to modern.Sastri (1955), p. 364 Particularly known for his use of sophisticated metaphors, Kumara Vyasa earned the title ''Rupaka Samrajya Chakravarti'' ("Emperor of the land of Metaphors"). The remaining chapters of the epic were translated by Timmanna Kavi (1510) of the court of King Krishnadevaraya. The poet named his work ''Krishnaraya Bharata'' after his patron king.Narasimhacharya (1988), p. 69Kamath (2001), p. 182 ''Airavata'' (1430) by Kumara Vyasa recounts an episode from the Mahabharata and is a story of the elephant ridden by God Indra.

Inspired by Kumara Vyasa, the first complete brahminical adaptation of the epic Ramayana was written by Kumara Valmiki (a pseudonym of Narahari, 1500) and is called ''Torave Ramayana'' after the village Torave, where it was composed. As with the Mahabharata, this adaptation veers away from the Jain version by Nagachandra (1105). Nagachandra had used the ''champu'' metre popular in Sanskrit works and sought to portray Ravana as a tragic hero. In a departure from the original version (by Valmiki), the Jain epic ends with Rama's asceticism and ''nirvana''.Sastri (1955), p. 357–358 Kumara Valmiki's account, written in the Valmiki tradition, is in the ''shatpadi'' metre and is steeped in the author's devotion for God Rama, an incarnation of God Vishnu. According to the author, the epic he wrote was actually a recounting of Shiva's conversation with his consort Parvati. In this version of the epic, King Ravana, the villain, is one of the suitors at Sita's Swayamvara (''lit'' a ceremony of "choice of a husband"). His failure in winning the bride's hand results in jealousy towards Rama, the eventual bridegroom. As the story progresses, Hanuman, for all his services, is heaped with encomium and is exalted to the status of "the next creator". At the end of the story, during the war with Rama, Ravana realises that Rama is none other than the God Vishnu and hastens to die at his hands to achieve salvation. The chapter narrating the war (''Yuddhakanda'') is given prominence over all other chapters. The writing has remained popular for centuries and inspired folk theatre such as the Yakshagana, which draws from episodes of ''Torave Ramayana'' for enactment.Sahitya Akademi (1987), p. 38 The influence of the Puranic tradition and that of Madhavacharya are visible in this lively yet religious narration that uses every opportunity to glorify its hero, Rama. However, the author has been criticised for dwelling in abstractions and for not reaching the graceful poetic level of his predecessor Kumara Vyasa.Sahitya Akademi (1987), p. 39

The early Bhagavata writings in Sanskrit by well-known ''acharyas'' (gurus) were solely meant to have a proselytising effect on the masses, encouraging them to a theistic way of life and belief in God Krishna. Chatu Vitthalanatha, who flourished as a court poet of King Krishnadeva Raya and his successor King Achyuta Raya, was the first to translate the Bhagavata into Kannada in a voluminous writing comprising 12,247 stanzas divided into 280 sections. The work covered the entire original version in ''shatpadi'' metre. Two other names appear in the colophons, Sadananda Yati and Nityatma Sukayogi, prompting some scholars to attribute the work to the group while others consider them alternate names of the same writer.Sahitya Akademi (1987), p. 36 The work covers all ten avatars of God Vishnu, though it is essentially centred on the depiction of Krishna as the supreme Lord. The purana covers stories of Vishnu's famous devotees such as Prahlad and Dhruva in detail, as well as stories of demons Vritasura, Hiranyakasipu and others who sought to attain salvation by dying at the hands of Vishnu. Most noteworthy is the epic's influence on the compositions of the Haridasas. Though the writing is not considered as important as the other two epics of the period, its significance to religiously minded people is well accepted. Chatu Vitthalanatha wrote a fuller version of portions of the epic Mahabharata as well.Sastri (1955), p. 365 Other notable writers of the 16th century were Tirumala Bhatta (''Siva Gite'') and Ramendra (''Saundarya Katharatna'', using ''tripadi'' metre).Narasimhacharya (1988), pp. 21–23
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="89d7a71acd19232e7ac871d56ad6ff37" name="Vijayanagara" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/89d7a71acd19232e7ac871d56ad6ff37.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>