<document id="2a42de3e93b81cb042806391a1ce1500-1.4" name="Ayumi_Hamasaki" cat="20">
<text>
In 2003, Hamasaki released three singles, "&", "Forgiveness", and "No Way to Say". To celebrate the release of her thirtieth single ("Forgiveness"), Hamasaki held the ''A Museum'' concert at the Yoyogi National Gymnasium.  Her mini-album ''Memorial Address'' (December 2003) was her first album to be released in CD+DVD format in addition to the regular CD-only format, a decision that came from her increased interest in the direction of her music videos. Like her previous albums, ''Memorial Address'' topped the Oricon chart and sold over a million copies.  Sales of Hamasaki's singles began to wane. Although all three of the album's singles topped the Oricon charts, "&" was Hamasaki's last single to sell over 500,000 copies. 

By the end of her ''Arena Tour 2003–2004'', Hamasaki had grown dissatisfied with her position in Avex: she felt that the company was treating her as a product instead of a person.  Along with her dissatisfaction over her last two studio albums (which she thought had been rushed), this led her to begin work on ''My Story'' (December 2004) early. In contrast with her previous albums, ''My Story'' had no set theme, nor did Hamasaki attempt to write "something good" or even "something that would give people hope"; rather, she simply wrote freely and honestly.Original text from ''Oricon Style'': "今回、正直にとか自由にっていうことはずっと頭の中にありましたね。だから、いいことを書 こうとか感動してもらおうとか、希望を持ってもらおうっていうようをことは一切意誠していなくて。単純に、ただ正直に書いていこうというだけでした。" As a result, the album contained mostly autobiographical lyrics about her emotions and reminiscences of her career. She approached the composition of the music with the same freedom per the lyrics. Because she liked rock music, the album had notable rock overtones.  She was so pleased with the result that she declared ''My Story'' the first album she felt satisfied with. ''My Story'' and its singles, "Moments", "Inspire", and "Carols", all topped the weekly Oricon charts; moreover, ''My Story'' became another million-seller.   From January to April 2005, Hamasaki held the nationwide ''My Story'' arena tour, her first album-based tour.

''(Miss)understood'' (January 2006), Hamasaki's seventh studio album, showed new musical directions. Wanting to sing a tune like those of the group Sweetbox, Hamasaki obtained the permission of Sweetbox composer Roberto "Geo" Rosan to use demo songs he had intended to use in Sweetbox's upcoming album. She edited the songs to fit her personal vision, rewriting the lyrics and rearranging some of the songs.  The result was more musically diverse than the previous album; ''(Miss)understood'' included ballads, funk, dance-pop, R&B, and rock songs. All of ''(Miss)understood'''s singles reached the top of the Oricon; "Bold & Delicious" became Hamasaki's twenty-fifth number-one single, tying her with Seiko Matsuda for the record of most number-one singles by a solo female artist. Though ''(Miss)understood'' also reached the top of the charts, Oricon stated that it sold fewer than a million copies—Hamasaki's first studio album to do so. ''(Miss)understood'' is listed as a million-seller by the RIAJ, but the RIAJ's certification is based on the number of albums shipped to retailers; Oricon gathers its tallies from the retailers themselves. In support of the album, Hamasaki held the ''(Miss)understood'' arena tour, which spanned three months with thirty concerts, from Saitama on March 11, 2006 to  Yoyogi on June 11, 2006. 

"Secrets" was, appropriately, the theme of Hamasaki's eighth studio album, ''Secret'' (November 2006). The album also explored strong female figures, love, and sadness; songs depicted the artist's struggles and were written to encourage females. Literally "cheer songs for girls". Original text from ''Vivi'': "'Secret'。 その中には、女のコのチアソングとも言える" Although ''Secret'' was originally intended to be a mini-album, Hamasaki "began brimming with things to say" while producing the album and wrote five more songs.Original text from ''Vivi'': "今回のアルバムは、はじめはミニアルバムのはずだったのを急フルアルバムに變更
したもの。傳えたいにことか、ある日を境にふねーっと溢れてきて、これは歌にして傳えなきゃ思って、詞は1日に3曲、きた1日に2曲つてハイペスで書き上げたの。" The album consisted mostly of rock songs and ballads; to complement these, Hamasaki experimented with new vocal techniques.  Both of the album's singles, "Startin'" and "Blue Bird", continued her streak of number-one singles: "Startin'" became her twenty-sixth, setting a new record for most number-one singles held by a solo female artist.  The album also topped the Oricon weekly charts, making Hamasaki the only artist to have eight consecutive number-one studio albums.  Her sales, however, continued to decline: according to both Oricon and the RIAJ, ''Secret'' failed to sell a million copies.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b04eb9e4d0add8629d88f445b624ecc3" name="Ayumi_Hamasaki_-_Arena_Tour_2006" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/b04eb9e4d0add8629d88f445b624ecc3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>