<document id="2a42de3e93b81cb042806391a1ce1500-1.5" name="Ayumi_Hamasaki" cat="20">
<text>
On February 28, 2007, Hamasaki released ''A Best 2'', a pair of compilation albums containing songs from ''I Am...'' to ''(Miss)understood''. The two versions, ''White'' and ''Black'', debuted at the first and second positions on the Oricon weekly charts, making Hamasaki the first female artist in thirty-six years to hold the top two positions on any Oricon album chart.  At the end of 2007, the pair became Japan's fifth and seventh best-selling albums of the year respectively. 

In support of ''A Best 2'' and ''Secret'', Hamasaki held the four-month-long ''Tour of Secret'' from March to the end of June. It was her first international tour, and aside from Japan, she performed in Taipei, Shanghai, and Hong Kong.  Her foreign fanbase highly anticipated the concerts, and tickets for the Taipei and Hong Kong performances sold out in less than three hours.  

Unlike its predecessors, the writing of Hamasaki's ninth studio album, ''Guilty'' (January 2008), was not an emotional experience for her, nor did it have a set theme. However, she said later that the album's tracks appeared to tell a story. Most of the songs were dark; the album had a notable rock tinge. It contained some upbeat dance tracks and ballads, though the latter also had rock overtones. ''Guilty'' peaked at the number-two position on the weekly Oricon charts, making it Hamasaki's first studio album not to reach the top. However, Hamasaki's first digital-only single, "Together When...", and the singles "Glitter / Fated" and "Talkin' 2 Myself", reached the top of their respective charts.    A short film, ''Distance Love'', was used as the music video for "Glitter" and "Fated". The film, shot in Hong Kong, co-starred Hong Kong actor Shawn Yue as Hamasaki's romantic interest.  ''Guilty'' was later released as a digital album in twenty-six countries outside Japan, nineteen of them Western nations. That, along with Hamasaki's decision to employ western DJs such as Armand van Helden for her 2008 remix albums ''Ayu-mi-x 6: Gold'' and ''Ayu-mi-x 6: Silver'', has been interpreted as her first step into the global market. 
 	
In April 2008, to commemorate her tenth anniversary in Avex, Hamasaki released the single "Mirrorcle World"; it topped the Oricon, making Hamasaki the only female solo artist to have a number-one single every year for ten consecutive years.  Hamasaki also held her second tour of Asia, ''Asia Tour 2008: 10th Anniversary'', to celebrate her tenth anniversary. From April until June, she toured Japan, holding seventeen concerts. Taiwan, Hong Kong, and Shanghai were again the foreign stops after the domestic performances. 
* 
* 
*  On September 10, 2008, Hamasaki released ''A Complete: All Singles'', a compilation album that includes the A-sides of all her singles along with previously unreleased footage from her A-nation concerts. 

Her tenth studio album, ''Next Level'', was released on March 25, 2009 in several formats: CD, CD+DVD, 2CD+DVD and a two-gigabyte USB flash drive.   The flash drive edition is expected to be priced at ¥6800 (approximately USD$75).  The first single, "Days/Green" (December 2008), became another number-one single for Hamasaki. The second single, "Rule/Sparkle", was released on February 25, 2009;  "Rule" is used as the international theme song for the film ''Dragonball Evolution''. ''Next Level'' reached the top of the Oricon charts, making Hamasaki the only artist to have a number-one album every year for eleven years in a row. However, the album was only certified double platinum, making it Hamasaki's lowest-selling studio album.  On August 12, 2009, Hamasaki released her forty-sixth single, "Sunrise/Sunset (Love Is All)". "Sunrise (Love Is All)", one of the A-sides, will be used as the opening theme song for the Japanese television drama ''Dandy Daddy?''. Hamasaki's third single of the year, You Were... / Ballad, is scheduled for release on December 16, 2009. http://www.avexnet.or.jp/ayu/jp/news/091022a.html | 【リリース情報】2009/12/16（水）発売「You were... / BALLAD」発売決定！
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4780809e00e915a61c883d45ed2a51a5" name="Ayumi_Hamasaki_in_concert,_April_2007" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/4780809e00e915a61c883d45ed2a51a5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>