<document id="2ba08a28cc5505e2eb2ab9c04fb4f2b6-1" name="Central_Coast_Mariners_FC" cat="26">
<text>
The Central Coast Mariners' bid for a franchise in the Football Federation Australia's (FFA) new A-League competition aimed to fill the one spot for a regional team that was designated by the FFA. Media speculation prior to announcement of the franchises in the new league suggested that the Mariners bid may be favourable due to its new blood. Backing from former Australian national team player and club technical director Alex Tobin, as well as Clean Up Australia personality Ian Kiernan - who would act as  inaugural club chairman - also strengthened their proposal. As the only regional bidder, the Mariners were expected to make it in to the league by default. Following a reported signed deal with the FFA, the club signed former Northern Spirit coach Lawrie McKinna as manager and Ian Ferguson, a former Rangers and Northern Spirit player as coach. To aid the FFA's goals of building the profile of the sport, the Mariners created formal links with local state league team Central Coast United. After much expectation, the club was announced as one of eight teams to become part of Football Australia's domestic competition, the Hyundai A-League on 1 November 2004.

At the time of the formation of the new league in 2004, the club was owned by Spirits Sports and Leisure Group. The club announced early on its search for a star player under the leagues' allowance for one star player outside of the $1.5 million salary cap, insisting that the player should not look at the position as a retirement fund. Coach Lawrie McKinna sought interest from Australia national football team players Ante Milicic and Simon Colosimo, and also announced that he may sign more than the three required under-20 players. Early concerns for the club centred around the concerns over financial stability, but after forming a partnership with technology giants Toshiba and a cash injection from local businessman John Singleton, the clubs financial worries were eased. McKinna was keen to sign local player Damien Brown of Bateau Bay, formerly of the Newcastle Jets. In a decision which prompted the player to declare that he was "over the moon", Brown became the first player to sign with the club. Club chairman Lyall Gorman was pleased that a local had become a "foundation player" and part of Brown's role would be to assist with selection of younger players from the local area. By early December 2004, the club had created a steady foundation of player signings and began negotiations with former Perth Glory striker Nik Mrdja, signing him later in the month as their star striker. Mrjda was one of the most prominent players in the last season of the National Soccer League, shooting the final goal to secure Perth Glory's finals win. The club management were reluctant to sign a star player outside of the $1.5 million salary cap, stipulating that they "would have to contribute on the pitch and get people to come to the ground." 


The Mariners' inaugural season was considered a resounding success by many, with the team reaching the A-League grand final after finishing third during the regular season.  They were defeated by Sydney FC 1&ndash;0 in the grand final, playing in front of a crowd of 41,689 - a competition record at the time. The Mariners also won the 2005 Pre-Season Cup, defeating Perth Glory in the final 1&ndash;0.

The Mariners developed a strong rivalry with Newcastle Jets throughout their first season, often referred to as the ''"F3 derby"''. The naming is a reference to the unofficial designation of the Sydney-Newcastle Freeway, the major motorway which joins the two clubs.

Prior to the 2006&ndash;07 season, the Mariners secured the services of then Australian international Tony Vidmar from NAC Breda for two years. This was the Mariners' first marquee signing, following the lead of Sydney FC (Dwight Yorke) and Adelaide United (Qu Shengqing). The Coast again reached the grand final of the Pre-Season Cup, losing to Adelaide United 5-4 on penalties after scores were tied 1&ndash;1 after extra time. Central Coast then participated in the 2006&ndash;07 A-League season, however were unable to gain a spot in the final series, finishing sixth after the regular season.

Club captain Noel Spencer was released by the mariners then signed to participate in the Asian Champions League by Sydney FC after the 2006&ndash;07 season, and Alex Wilkinson was appointed the new captain. Only 22 years of age at the time, Wilkinson had played every competitive match for the Mariners up to his appointment.

Goalkeeper Danny Vukovic was suspended from both domestic and international competition for striking referee Mark Shield in the A-League Grand Final in February, 2008. Despite appeals, the ban was eventually confirmed by FIFA in June, to include banning the young keeper from competing at the 2008 Olympic Games. The ban involves games at all levels up till October 6, 2008.

Due to Central Coast losing their first choice keeper for the first couple months of the season, the Mariners have signed high profile former Manchester United and Socceroos keeper, Mark Bosnich, on a seven week contract. This is the first time Mark has played professional football since a disappointing departure from the game back in 2002.

In February of this year, the Central Coast Mariners signed an arrangement with English Football League Championship side Sheffield United. The partnership between the Mariners, The Blades and other partner clubs including Ferencváros of Hungary, Chengdu Blades of China, São Paulo of Brazil and White Star Woluwé of Belgium will benefit the club in being able to provide an opportunity for the youth programme of the club to develop by touring the world and develop their footballing background, whilst in reverse, the Mariners will be able to share in having some of Sheffield United’s Youth Academy or reserve team prospects available to play. Current Western Sydney triallist Gregor Pac is leading the way out of the many fine Youth Academy players that could take advantage of this overseas link.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fd202b5092b845a644329e9911721a90" name="CC_Mariners_2005_PSC" sectnum="1#1">../img/fd202b5092b845a644329e9911721a90.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>