<document id="2bb0867f05a5c48a19f08457a5ed9771-2.1" name="Harry_McNish" cat="14">
<text>
The aim of the Imperial Trans-Antarctic Expedition was to be the first to cross the Antarctic continent from one side to the other. McNish was apparently attracted by Shackleton's advertisement for the expedition (although there are doubts as to whether the advertisement ever appeared):




McNish, at 40, was one of the oldest members of the crew of the ''Endurance'' (Shackleton though was seven months older). He suffered from piles and rheumatism in his legs, and was regarded as somewhat odd and unrefined, but also highly respected as a carpenter — Frank Worsley, the captain of the ''Endurance'', refers to him as a "splendid shipwright". The pipe-smoking Scot was, however, the only man of the crew that Shackleton was "not dead certain of". His Scots accent was described as rasping like "frayed cable wire".

During the initial stage of the voyage to Antarctica from Buenos Aires, he was kept busy with a number of routine tasks. He worked on the pram dinghy ''Nancy Endurance''; made a small chest of drawers for Shackleton; specimen shelves for the biologist, Robert Clark; instrument cases for Leonard Hussey, the meteorologist; and put up wind screens to protect the helmsman. He constructed a false deck, extending from the poop-deck to the chart-room to cover the extra coal that the ship had taken on board. He also acted as the ship's barber. As the ship pushed into the pack ice in the Weddell Sea it became increasingly difficult to navigate. McNish constructed a six-foot wooden semaphore on the bridge to enable the navigating officer to give the helmsman directions, and built a small stage over the stern to allow the propeller to be watched in order to keep it clear of the heavy ice.

When the ship became trapped in pack ice his duties expanded to constructing makeshift housing, and, once it became clear that the ship was doomed, to altering the sledges for the journey over the ice to open water. He built the quarters where the crew took their meals (nicknamed ''The Ritz'') and cubicles where the men could sleep. These were all christened as well; McNish shared ''The Sailors’ Rest'' with Alfred Cheetham, the Third Officer. Assisted by the crew, he constructed kennels for the dogs on the upper deck. Once ''Endurance'' became trapped, and the crew were spending the days on the ice, McNish erected goalposts and football became a daily fixture for the men. To pass the time in the evening, McNish joined Frank Wild, Tom Crean, James McIlroy, Worsley and Shackleton playing poker in the wardroom.

The pressure from the ice caused ''Endurance'' to start to take on water. To prevent the ship from flooding McNish built a cofferdam, caulking it with strips of blankets and nailing strips over the seams, standing for hours up to his waist in freezing water as he worked. He could not prevent the pressure from the ice crushing the ship though and was experienced enough to know when to stop trying. Once the ship had been destroyed he was put in charge of rescuing the stores from what had been ''The Ritz''. With McNish in charge it took only a couple of hours to open the deck far enough to retrieve a good quantity of provisions.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="585006305db68a8fb57994abeb3b1004" name="Endurance3" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/585006305db68a8fb57994abeb3b1004.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>