<document id="2bb0867f05a5c48a19f08457a5ed9771-4" name="Harry_McNish" cat="14">
<text>
After the expedition McNish returned to the Merchant Navy, working on various ships. He often complained that his bones permanently ached due to the conditions during the journey in the ''James Caird''; he would reportedly sometimes refuse to shake hands because of the pain. He divorced Lizzie Littlejohn on 2 March 1918, by which time he had already met his new partner, Agnes Martindale. McNish had a son named Tom and Martindale had a daughter named Nancy.  Although she is mentioned frequently in his diary, it appears McNish was not Nancy's father. He spent 23 years in the Navy in total during his life, but eventually secured a job with the New Zealand Shipping Company. After making five trips to New Zealand he moved there in 1925, leaving behind his wife and all of his carpentry tools. He worked on the waterfront in Wellington until his career was ended by an injury. Destitute, he would sleep in the wharf sheds under a tarpaulin and relied on monthly collections from the dockworkers. He was found a place in the Ohiro Benevolent Home, but his health continued to deteriorate and he died on 24 September 1930 in Wellington Hospital. He was buried in Karori Cemetery, Wellington, on 26 September 1930, with full naval honours; ''HMS Dunedin'' (which happened to be in port at the time) provided twelve men for the firing party and eight bearers.  However, his grave remained unmarked for almost thirty years; the New Zealand Antarctic Society (NZAC) erected a headstone on 10 May 1959. In 2001, it was reported that the grave was untended and surrounded by weeds, but in 2004, the grave was tidied and a life size bronze sculpture of McNish’s beloved cat, Mrs. Chippy, was placed on his grave by NZAC. His grandson, Tom, believes this tribute would have meant more to him than receiving the Polar Medal.

In 1958 the British Antarctic Survey named a small island in his honour, "McNeish Island", which lies in the approaches to King Haakon Bay, South Georgia. The island was renamed "McNish Island" in 1998 after his birth certificate was presented to the United Kingdom Antarctic Place-Names Committee. On 18 October 2006, a small, oval wall plaque commemorating his achievements was unveiled at the Port Glasgow Library in his home town, and earlier in the same year he was the subject of an exhibition at the McLean Museum and Art Gallery, Greenock. His journals are held in the Alexander Turnbull Library in Wellington, New Zealand.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="861da606e5fe1518ed184636a7ce7931" name="Mcnishb" sectnum="4#1">../img/861da606e5fe1518ed184636a7ce7931.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>