<document id="2bdf0a587f682a930d5a8767e4089c17-1.1" name="History_of_Miami" cat="14">
<text>
In 1513, Juan Ponce de León was the first European man to see the Miami area by sailing into Biscayne Bay. He wrote in his journal that he reached ''Chequescha'', which was Miami's first recorded name.Parks, p 13 It is unknown whether or not he came ashore and made contact with the natives. Pedro Menéndez de Avilés and his men made the first recorded landing when they visited the Tequesta settlement in 1566 while looking for Avilés' missing son, who was shipwrecked a year earlier.Parks, p 14 Spanish soldiers led by Father Francisco Villareal built a Jesuit mission at the mouth of the Miami River a year later but it was short-lived. By 1570, the Jesuits decided to look for more willing subjects outside of Florida. After the Spaniards left, the Tequesta Indians were left to fend themselves from European-introduced diseases like smallpox. Wars with other tribes greatly weakened their population, and they were easily defeated by the Creek Indians in battles. By 1711, the Tequesta sent a couple of local chiefs to Havana, Cuba to ask if they could migrate there. The Cubans sent two ships to help them, but Spanish illnesses struck and most of the Indians died.Parks, p 14-16 The Spaniards sent another mission to Biscayne Bay in 1743, where they built a fort and church. The missionary priests proposed a permanent settlement, where the Spanish settlers would raise food for the soldiers and American Indians. However, the proposal was rejected as impractical and the mission was withdrawn before the end of the year.Sturtevant, William C. (1978) The Last of the South Florida Aborigines, in Jerald Milanich and Samuel Proctor, Eds., ''Tacachale: Essays on the Indians of Florida and Southeastern Georgia during the Historic Period.'' Gainesville, Florida, The University Presses of Florida.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c413bc643ef352665eb996166040b00c" name="Juan_Ponce_de_León" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/c413bc643ef352665eb996166040b00c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>