<document id="2bdf0a587f682a930d5a8767e4089c17-2.7.4" name="History_of_Miami" cat="14">
<text>
In the 1980s, Miami became one of the United States' largest transshipment point for cocaine from Colombia, Bolivia, and Peru. Miami-New Times (2005), by Rebecca Wakefield, retrieved August 7, 2006. The drug industry brought billions of dollars into Miami, which were quickly funneled through front organizations into the local economy. Luxury car dealerships, five-star hotels, condominium developments, swanky nightclubs, major commercial developments and other signs of prosperity began rising all over the city. As the money arrived, so did a violent crime wave that lasted through the early 1990s. The popular television program ''Miami Vice'', which dealt with counter-narcotics agents in an idyllic upper-class rendition of Miami, spread the city's image as one of America's most glamorous subtropical paradises.
 
During the 1980s and early 1990s, many noted people visited Miami. Pope John Paul II visited in November 1987, and held an open-air mass for 150,000 people in Tamiami Park. (2005), by Ana Rodriguez-Soto, retrieved February 1, 2006. Queen Elizabeth II and three United States presidents also visited Miami. Among them was Ronald Reagan, who had a street named after him in Little Havana.Parks, p 202 Nelson Mandela's 1989 visit to the city was marked by ethnic tensions. Mandela had praised Cuban leader Fidel Castro for his anti-apartheid support on ABC News' ''Nightline''. Because of this, the city withdrew its official greeting and no high-ranking official welcomed him. That led to a boycott by the local African American community of all Miami tourist and convention facilities until Mandela received an official greeting. However, all efforts to resolve it failed for months, resulting in an estimated loss of over $10 million.Dunn, p 347
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e72b6cc4c4c10dc65135a518aaee1f9b" name="Wachoviatowerside" sectnum="2.7.4#1">../img/e72b6cc4c4c10dc65135a518aaee1f9b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>