<document id="2c7c7cfc6fda13471aba25999f4d9088-1.4" name="Albatross" cat="3">
<text>
The albatross diet is predominantly cephalopods, fish, crustaceans and offal, although they will also scavenge carrion and feed on other zooplankton. It should be noted that for most species, a comprehensive understanding of diet is only known for the breeding season, when the albatrosses regularly return to land and study is possible. The importance of each of these food sources varies from species to species, and even from population to population; some concentrate on squid alone, others take more krill or fish. Of the two albatross species found in Hawaii, one, the Black-footed Albatross, takes mostly fish while the Laysan feeds on squid.


The use of dataloggers at sea that record ingestion of water against time (providing a likely time of feeding) suggest that albatross predominantly feed during the day. Analysis of the squid beaks regurgitated by albatrosses has shown that many of the squid eaten are too large to have been caught alive,Croxall, J.P. & Prince, P.A. (1994). "Dead or alive, night or day: how do albatrosses catch squid?" ''Antarctic Science'' '''6''': 155–162. and include mid-water species likely to be beyond the reach of albatross, suggesting that, for some species (like the Wandering Albatross), scavenged squid may be an important part of the diet. The source of these dead squid is a matter of debate; some certainly comes from squid fisheries, but in nature it primarily comes from the die-off that occurs after squid spawning and the vomit of squid-eating whales (sperm whales, pilot whales and Southern Bottlenose Whales). The diet of other species, like the Black-browed Albatross or the Grey-headed Albatross, is rich with smaller species of squid that tend to sink after death, and scavenging is not assumed to play a large role in their diet. Also, some species such as the Black-browed Albatross and the Waved Albatross practice kleptoparasitism from boobies, Phalacrocorax or shearwaters.

Until recently it was thought that albatross were predominantly surface feeders, swimming at the surface and snapping up squid and fish pushed to the surface by currents, predators or death. The deployment of capillary depth recorders, which record the maximum dive depth undertaken by a bird (between attaching it to a bird and recovering it when it returns to land), has shown that while some species, like the Wandering Albatross, do not dive deeper than a metre, some species, like the Light-mantled Albatross, have a mean diving depth of almost 5 m and can dive as deep as 12.5 m.Prince, P.A., Huin, N., Weimerskirch, H., (1994) "Diving depths of albatrosses" ''Antarctic Science'' '''6''': (''3'') 353–354. In addition to surface feeding and diving, they have now also been observed plunge diving from the air to snatch prey.Cobley, N.D., (1996) "An observation of live prey capture by a Black-browed Albatross ''Diomedea melanophrys'' " ''Marine Ornithology'' '''24''': 45–46.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="92a3899ce6f18b9b5e29e7e48d122205" name="Light_sooty_albatross_flying" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/92a3899ce6f18b9b5e29e7e48d122205.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>