<document id="2c8c4a9769e370c19143ea9e0d58a32d-2.3" name="Battle_of_Midway" cat="29">
<text>
In order to do battle with an enemy force anticipated to muster four or five carriers, Admiral Chester W. Nimitz (Commander in Chief, Pacific Ocean Areas) needed every available U.S. flight deck. He already had Vice Admiral William Halsey's two-carrier (''Enterprise'' and ''Hornet'') task force at hand, though Halsey was stricken with psoriasis and had to be replaced by Rear Admiral Raymond A. Spruance (Halsey's escort commander).Prange, ''Miracle at Midway'', pp. 80–81; Cressman ''et al.'', ''A Glorious Page in Our History,'' p. 37. Nimitz also hurriedly called back Rear Admiral Frank Jack Fletcher's task force from the South West Pacific Area. He reached Pearl Harbor just in time to provision and sail.

''Yorktown'' had been severely damaged at the Battle of the Coral Sea. Despite estimates that she would require several months of repairs at Puget Sound Naval Shipyard, her elevators were intact, and her flight deck largely so.Willmott, ''Barrier and the Javelin'', p.337. The Pearl Harbor Naval Shipyard worked around the clock and in 72 hours, she was restored to a battle-ready state,Cressman ''et al.'', ''A Glorious Page in Our History'', pp.37–45; Lord, ''Incredible Victory'', pp.37–39. judged good enough for two or three weeks of operations, as Nimitz required.Willmott, ''Barrier and the Javelin'', p.338. Her flight deck was patched, whole sections of internal frames cut out and replaced, and several new squadrons were drawn from ''Saratoga''; they did not, however, get time to train.Willmott, ''Barrier and the Javelin''; p.337-40? Nimitz disregarded established procedure in getting his third and last available carrier ready for battle. Just three days after putting into dry dock at Pearl Harbor, ''Yorktown'' was again under way. Repairs continued even as she sortied, with work crews from the repair ship USS ''Vestal'', herself damaged in the attack on Pearl Harbor six months earlier, still aboard.Lord, ''Incredible Victory'', p.39; Willmott, ''Barrier and the Javelin'', p.340.

On Midway Island, the USAAF stationed four squadrons of B-17 Flying Fortresses, along with several B-26 Marauders. The Marine Corps had nineteen SBD Dauntless dive bombers, seven F4F-3 Wildcats, seventeen Vought SBU-3 Vindicators, twenty-one Brewster F2A-3s, and six Grumman TBF-1 Avenger torpedo bombers, the latter a detachment of VT-8 from ''Hornet''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d08ddd5c4f9b3da64096cdc8260b667f" name="G13065_USS_Yorktown_Pearl_Harbor_May_1942" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/d08ddd5c4f9b3da64096cdc8260b667f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>