<document id="2c8c4a9769e370c19143ea9e0d58a32d-1.1" name="Battle_of_Midway" cat="29">
<text>
Typical of Japanese naval planning during World War II, Yamamoto's battle plan was exceedingly complex.Prange, ''Miracle at Midway,'' pp. 375–379, Willmott, ''Barrier and the Javelin'', pp. 110–117; Parshall and Tully, ''Shattered Sword'', p. 52. Additionally, his design was predicated on optimistic intelligence suggesting USS ''Enterprise'' and USS ''Hornet'', forming Task Force 16, were the only carriers available to the U.S. Pacific Fleet at the time. USS ''Lexington'' had been sunk and USS ''Yorktown'' severely damaged (and believed by the Japanese to have been sunk) at the Battle of the Coral Sea just a month earlier. The Japanese were also aware that USS ''Saratoga'' was undergoing repairs on the West Coast after suffering torpedo damage from a submarine.

However, more important was Yamamoto's belief the Americans had been demoralized by their frequent defeats during the preceding six months. Yamamoto felt deception would be required to lure the U.S. fleet into a fatally compromised situation.Parshall and Tully, ''Shattered Sword'', p. 53, derived from Japanese War History Series (''Senshi Sōshō''), Volume 43 ('Midowei Kaisen'), p. 118. To this end, he dispersed his forces so that their full extent (particularly his battleships) would be unlikely to be discovered by the Americans prior to battle. Critically, Yamamoto's supporting battleships and cruisers would trail Vice-Admiral Nagumo Chūichi's carrier striking force by several hundred miles. Japan's heavy surface forces were intended to destroy whatever part of the U.S. fleet might come to Midway's relief, once Nagumo's carriers had weakened them sufficiently for a daylight gun duel;Parshall and Tully, ''Shattered Sword'', pp. 51, 55. this was typical of the battle doctrine of most major navies.Parshall and Tully, ''Shattered Sword'', pp. 43–45, derived from ''Senshi Sōshō'', p. 196.

Unbeknownst to Yamamoto, the United States had broken the main Japanese naval code (dubbed JN-25 by the Americans). Yamamoto's emphasis on dispersal also meant that none of his formations could support each other. For instance, the only significant warships larger than destroyers that screened Nagumo's fleet were two battleships and three cruisers, despite his carriers being expected to carry out the strikes and bear the brunt of American counterattacks. By contrast, the flotillas of Yamamoto and Kondo had between them two light carriers, five battleships, and six cruisers, none of which would see any action at Midway. Their distance from Nagumo's carriers would also have grave implications during the battle, since the larger warships in Yamamoto and Kondo's forces carried scout planes, an invaluable reconnaissance capability denied to Nagumo.Willmott, ''Barrier and the Javelin''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4910519bb1f16cf9f11ea241afdd893d" name="Midway_Atoll" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/4910519bb1f16cf9f11ea241afdd893d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>