<document id="2c8c4a9769e370c19143ea9e0d58a32d-2.4" name="Battle_of_Midway" cat="29">
<text>
Meanwhile, as a result of her participation in the Battle of the Coral Sea, the Japanese carrier ''Zuikaku'' was in port in Kure, awaiting a replacement air group. That there were none immediately available was a failure of the IJN crew training program, which already showed signs of being unable to replace losses.Willmott, ''Barrier and the Javelin'', p.101. Instructors from the Yokosuka Air Corps were employed in an effort to make up the shortfall. The heavily damaged ''Shōkaku'' had suffered three bomb hits at Coral Sea, and required months of repair in drydock. Despite the likely availability of sufficient aircraft between the two ships to re-equip ''Zuikaku'' with a composite air group, the Japanese made no serious attempt to get her into the forthcoming battle.Parshall and Tully, ''Shattered Sword'', pp. 65–67. Consequently, Admiral Nagumo would only have four fleet carriers: ''Kaga'' and ''Akagi'' forming Carrier Division 1; ''Hiryū'' and ''Sōryū'' as Carrier Division 2. At least part of this was a product of fatigue; Japanese carriers had been constantly on operations since 7 December, 1941, including raids on Darwin and Colombo.

The main Japanese strike aircraft to be used were the Aichi D3A1 dive bomber and the Nakajima B5N2, which was capable of being used either as a torpedo bomber or as a level attack bomber. The main carrier fighter was the fast and highly maneuverable Mitsubishi A6M2 Zero.Note: The code names "Val", "Kate" and "Zeke", which are often applied to these aircraft, were not introduced until late 1943 by the Allied forces. The D3A was normally referred to as Type 99 navy dive bomber, the B5N as the Type 97 navy torpedo bomber and the A6M as the Type 0 navy fighter; it was also known as the "Zero". Parshall and Tully ''Shattered Sword'' pp.78-80. However, the carriers of the ''Kido Butai'' were suffering from a shortage of frontline aircraft. For various reasons, production of the D3A had been drastically reduced, while that of the B5N had been stopped completely. As a consequence, there were none available to replace losses. This also meant that many of the aircraft being used during the June 1942 operations had been operational since late November 1941; although well maintained, they were almost worn out and had become increasingly unreliable. These factors meant that all carriers had less than their normal aircraft complement and few spare aircraft.Parshall and Tulley ''Shattered Sword'' pp. 89-91.

Japanese strategic scouting arrangements prior to the battle were also in disarray. A picket line of Japanese submarines was late getting into position (partly because of Yamamoto's haste), which let the American carriers reach their assembly point northeast of Midway (known as "Point Luck") without being detected.Willmott, ''Barrier and the Javelin,'' p. 351; Parshall and Tully, ''Shattered Sword'', pp. 98–99. A second attempt at reconnaissance, using four-engine Kawanishi H8K flying boats to scout Pearl Harbor prior to the battle (and thereby detect the absence or presence of the American carriers), part of Operation K, was also thwarted when Japanese submarines assigned to refuel the search aircraft discovered that the intended refueling point—a hitherto deserted bay off French Frigate Shoals—was occupied by American warships (because the Japanese had carried out an identical mission in March).Lord, ''Incredible Victory'', pp. 37–39; Parshall and Tully, ''Shattered Sword'', p. 99; Holmes, ''Double-Edged Secrets''. Thus, Japan was deprived of any knowledge concerning the movements of the American carriers immediately before the battle.

Japanese radio intercepts did notice an increase in both American submarine activity and message traffic. This information was in Yamamoto's hands prior to the battle. However, Japanese plans were not changed; Yamamoto, at sea on ''Yamato'', did not dare inform Nagumo for fear of exposing his position and assumed that Nagumo had received the same signal from Tokyo.Parshall and Tully, ''Shattered Sword'', pp. 102–104; Willmott, ''Barrier and the Javelin''. Nagumo's radio antennae, however, were unable to receive such long-wave transmissions, and he was left unaware of any American ship movements.Isom, ''Midway Inquest: Why the Japanese Lost the Battle of Midway'', pp.95-99
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6d2007b61e8ed58fccb98dc00c68a763" name="AkagiDeckApril42" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/6d2007b61e8ed58fccb98dc00c68a763.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>