<document id="2cb9f65d01c4221b75953e5be0ed2ff8-1.3" name="Beagle" cat="3">
<text>
Reverend Phillip Honeywood established a Beagle pack in Essex in the 1830s and it is believed that this pack formed the basis for the modern Beagle breed.
Although details of the pack's lineage are not recorded it is thought that North Country Beagles and Southern Hounds were strongly represented; William Youatt suspected that Harriers formed a good majority of the Beagles bloodline, but the origin of the Harrier is itself obscure.Youatt. p.110 Honeywood's Beagles were small, standing at about  at the shoulder, and pure white according to John Mills (writing in ''The Sportsman's Library'' in 1845). Prince Albert and Lord Winterton also had Beagle packs around this time, and Royal favour no doubt led to some revival of interest in the breed, but Honeywood's pack was regarded as the finest of the three.Mills p.172

Although credited with the development of the modern breed, Honeywood concentrated on producing dogs for hunting and it was left to Thomas Johnson to refine the breeding to produce dogs that were both attractive and capable hunters. Two strains were developed: the rough- and smooth-coated varieties. The rough-coated Beagle survived until the beginning of the 20th century, and there were even records of one making an appearance at a dog show as late as 1969, but this variety is now extinct having probably been absorbed into the standard Beagle bloodline.Kraeuter p.7

In the 1840s, a standard Beagle type was beginning to develop: the distinction between the North Country Beagle and Southern Hound had been lost, but there was still a large variation in size, character, and reliability among the emerging packs.Scott pp.75–8 In 1856, "Stonehenge" (the pseudonym of John Henry Walsh, editor of ''The Field''), writing in the ''Manual of British Rural Sports'' was still dividing Beagles into four varieties: the medium Beagle; the dwarf or lapdog Beagle; the fox Beagle (a smaller, slower version of the Foxhound); and the rough-coated or terrier Beagle, which he classified as a cross between any of the other varieties and one of the Scottish terrier breeds.Stonehenge pp.98–9 Stonehenge also gives the start of a standard description:



By 1887 the threat of extinction was on the wane: there were 18 Beagle packs in England.Krauter p.9 The Beagle Club was formed in 1890 and the first standard drawn up at the same time.Arnold p.12 The following year the Association of Masters of Harriers and Beagles was formed. Both organisations aimed to further the best interests of the breed, and both were keen to produce a standard type of Beagle.Daglish p.9 By 1902 the number of packs had risen to 44.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c2f2bbcce8942de44cfcf9618f45144d" name="4-beagles" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/c2f2bbcce8942de44cfcf9618f45144d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>