<document id="2ce6e785b25db1fa3a3a26800e8d4cb7-6.1" name="Elizabeth_I_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
Elizabeth often received offers of marriage, but she only seriously considered three or four suitors for any length of time. Of these, her childhood friend Lord Robert Dudley probably came closest. Early in 1559, Elizabeth's friendship with the married Dudley turned to love. Their intimacy soon was talk in court and country and abroad.Wilson, 95, 114; Doran ''Monarchy'', 72 It was also said that Amy Robsart, his wife, was suffering from a "malady in one of her breasts",Wilson, 95 and half a year later, that Lord Robert and the Queen had a "secret understanding" to marry after Amy would at last have been "sent into eternity".Gristwood, 129 Yet this was not a welcome idea: "There is not a man who does not cry out on him and her with indignation...she will marry none but the favoured Robert", the Spanish ambassador described the situation at the beginning of 1560.Chamberlin, 118 Accordingly, when Dudley's wife died in September of the same year from a fall from a flight of stairs, a great scandal arose.It is now presumed that Amy Dudley had cancer. At the time, it was widely believed that Dudley had done away with her in order to marry the queen. Somerset, 166–167. For a time, Elizabeth seriously considered marrying Dudley; but William Cecil, Nicholas Throckmorton, and other politicians were very alarmed and made their disapproval unmistakably clear.Wilson, 126&ndash;128 The opposition was so overwhelming, that there were even rumours that the nobility would rise if the marriage took place.Doran ''Monarchy'', 45



Despite several other marriage projects, Dudley was regarded as a serious candidate for nearly another decade.Doran ''Monarchy'', 212 Elizabeth encouraged him in his suit, remaining extremely jealous of his affections, even in case she never meant to marry him herself."...and after all, she will either not marry or else marry Robert, to  whom she has always been so much attached...the Queen is in love with Robert" (Philip II of Spain in October 1565): Haynes, 47; Hume, 90&ndash;104; Adams, 384, 146 Finally, after Dudley, whom she had created Earl of Leicester in 1564, had remarried in 1578, the queen reacted with repeated scenes of displeasure towards him for having done so.Jenkins, 245, 247; Leicester still wrote in 1585: "She  doth take every occasion by my marriage to withdraw any good from me.": Hammer, 46 His wife had to cope with the queen's lifelong hatred.Hammer, 34 Nevertheless, Dudley retained a special place in her heart. After Elizabeth's death, a note from him, who had died in 1588 shortly after the Armada, was found among her most personal belongings, marked "his last letter" in her handwriting.Wilson, 303
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="55dac85a7856c66c30ab786d802477b1" name="Elizabeth_I_Steven_Van_Der_Meulen" sectnum="6.1#1">../img/55dac85a7856c66c30ab786d802477b1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>