<document id="2d32ea24e2995aec9f052f1387150b71-1.2" name="George_Moore_(novelist)" cat="17">
<text>
In 1868, Moore's father was again elected MP for Mayo and the family moved to London the following year. Here, Moore senior tried, unsuccessfully, to have his son follow a career in the military though, prior to this, he attended the School of Art in the South Kensington Museum where his achievements were no better. He was freed from any burden of education when his father died in 1870. Moore, though still a minor, inherited the family estate that was valued at £3,596. He handed it over to his brother Maurice to manage and in 1873, on attaining his majority, moved to Paris to study art. It took him several attempts to find an artist who would accept him as a pupil. Monsieur Jullian, who had previously been a shepherd and circus masked man, took him on for 40 francs a month.Frazier (2000), pp. 28–29. At Académie Jullian he met Lewis Weldon Hawkins who became Moore's flat-mate and whose trait, as a failed artist, show up in Moore's own characters. He met many of the key artists and writers of the time, including Pissarro, Degas, Renoir, Monet, Daudet, Mallarmé, Turgenev and, above all, Zola, who was to prove an influential figure in Moore's subsequent development as a writer.

While still in Paris his first book, a collection of lyric poems called '' The Flowers of Passion'', was self-published in 1877. The poems were derivative, maliciously reviewed by the critics who were offended by some of the depravities in store for moralistic readers and was withdrawn by Moore.Farrow (1978), p. 22.Jeffares (1965), pp. 8–9. He was forced to return to Ireland in 1880 to raise £3,000 to pay debts incurred on the family estate due to his tenants refusing to pay their rent and the drop in agricultural prices. During his time back in Mayo, he gained a reputation as a fair landlord, continuing the family tradition of not evicting tenants and refusing to carry firearms when travelling round the estate. While in Ireland, he decided to abandon art and move to London to become a professional writer. There he published his second poetry collection, ''Pagan Poems'', in 1881. These early poems reflect his interest in French symbolism and are now almost entirely neglected. In 1886 Moore published ''Confessions of a Young Man'', a lively and energetic memoir about his 20s spent in Paris and London among bohemian artists.Arnold Bennett. ''Fame and fiction''. G. Richards, 1901.  It contains a substantial amount of literary criticism for which it has received a fair amount of praise, for instance The Modern Library chose it in 1917 to be included in the series as "one of the most significant documents of the passionate revolt of English literature against the Victorian tradition."Quote by Flyod Dell in "Introduction" to ''Confessions of a Young Man'' by George Moore. The Modern Library, 1917.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9dbb10099a9de2755b54c1e10f4eef00" name="Gmoore" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/9dbb10099a9de2755b54c1e10f4eef00.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>