<document id="2d32ea24e2995aec9f052f1387150b71-1.3" name="George_Moore_(novelist)" cat="17">
<text>
During the 1880s, Moore began work on a series of novels in a realist style. His first novel, ''A Modern Lover'' (1883) was a three-volume work, as preferred by the circulating libraries, and deals with the art scene of the 1870s and 1880s in which many characters are identifiably real.Farrow (1978), p. 31. The circulating libraries in England banned the book because of its explicit portrayal of the amorous pursuits of its hero. At this time the British circulating libraries, such as Mudie's Select Library, controlled the market for fiction and the public, who paid fees to borrow their books, expected them to guarantee the morality of the novels available.Frazier (2000), pp. 48–49. His next book, ''A Mummers Wife'' (1885) is widely recognised as the first major English language novel in the realist style. This too was regarded as unsuitable by Mudie's and W H Smith refused to stock it on their news-stalls. Despite this, during its first year of publication the book was in its fourteenth edition mainly due to the publicity garnered by its opponents.Peck (1898), pp. 90–95. As with ''A Modern Lover'', his two next novels, ''A Mummers Wife'' and ''A Drama in Muslin'', were banned by Mudie's and Smith's. In response Moore declared war on the circulating libraries by publishing two provocative pamphlets; ''Literature at Nurse'' and ''Circulating Morals''. In these, he complained that the libraries profit from salacious popular fiction while refusing to stock serious literary fiction. 

Moore's publisher Henry Vizetelly began to issue unabridged mass-market translations of French realist novels that endangered the moral and commercial influence of the circulating libraries around this time. In 1888, the circulating libraries fought back by encouraging the House of Commons to implement laws to stop 'the rapid spread of demoralising literature in this country'. However, Vizetelly was brought to court by the National Vigilance Association (NVA) for 'obscene libel'. The charge arose due to the publication of the English translation of Zola's ''La Terre''. A second case was brought the following year in order to force implementation of the original judgement and to remove all of Zola's works. This led to the 70-year-old publisher becoming a cause célèbre for the literary cause.Sloan (2003), pp. 92–93. Throughout Moore stayed loyal to Zola's publisher, and on 22 September 1888, about a month before the trial, wrote a letter that appeared in the ''St. James Gazette''. In it Moore suggested it was improper that Vizetelly's fate be determined by a jury of ''twelve tradesmen'', explaining it would be preferable to be judged by three novelists. Moore pointed out that the NVA could make the same claims against such books as ''Madame Bovary'' and Gautier's ''Mademoiselle de Maupin'', as their morals are equivalent to Zola's, though their literary merits might differ.Frazier (2000), pp. 173–174.

Because of his willingness to tackle such issues as prostitution, extramarital sex and lesbianism, Moore's novels were initially met with disapprobation. However, as the public's taste for realist fiction grew, this subsided. Moore began to find success as an art critic with the publication of books such as ''Impressions and Opinions'' (1891) and ''Modern Painting'' (1893)&mdash;which was the first significant attempt to introduce the Impressionists to an English audience. By this time Moore was first able to live from the proceeds of his literary work.

Other realist novels by Moore from this period include ''A Drama in Muslin'' (1886), a satiric story of the marriage trade in Anglo-Irish society that hints at same-sex relationships among the unmarried daughters of the gentry, and ''Esther Waters'' (1894), the story of an unmarried housemaid who becomes pregnant and is abandoned by her footman lover. Both of these books have remained almost constantly in print since their first publication. His 1887 novel ''A Mere Accident'' is an attempt to merge his symbolist and realist influences. He also published a collection of short stories: ''Celibates'' (1895).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f5674167b1bd3feb9a35c0fd2e8866c2" name="George_Moore_-_Project_Gutenberg_eText_19028" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/f5674167b1bd3feb9a35c0fd2e8866c2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>