<document id="2d62e212e80cd97d781296c2d1fa7227-5.2" name="Raccoon" cat="3">
<text>
The most important sense for the raccoon is its sense of touch.Bartussek, p. 13; Hohmann, p. 55; Zeveloff, p. 70 The "hyper sensitive"Hohmann, p. 55 front paws are protected by a thin horny layer which becomes pliable when wet.Hohmann, pp. 56–59; MacClintock, p. 15 The five digits of the paws have no webbing between them, which is unusual for a carnivoran.Zeveloff, p. 69 Almost two-thirds of the area responsible for sensory perception in the raccoon's cerebral cortex is specialised for the interpretation of tactile impulses, more than in any other studied animal.Hohmann, p. 56 They are able to identify objects before touching them with vibrissae located above their sharp, non-retractable claws.Hohmann, p. 57; Zeveloff, p. 70 The raccoon's paws lack an opposable thumb and thus it does not have the agility of the hands of primates.MacClintock, p. 15; Zeveloff, p. 70 It is not known why there is no observed negative effect on tactile perception when a raccoon stands in water below  for hours.Hohmann, pp. 60–62

Raccoons are thought to be color-blind or at least poorly able to distinguish color, though their eyes are well-adapted for sensing green light.Hohmann, p. 63; MacClintock, p. 18; Zeveloff, p. 66 Although their accommodation of 11 dioptre is comparable to that of humans and they see well in twilight due to the tapetum lucidum behind the retina, visual perception is of subordinate importance to raccoons because of their poor long-distance vision.Hohmann, pp. 63–65; MacClintock, pp. 18–21; Zeveloff, pp. 66–67 In addition to being useful for orientation in the dark, their sense of smell is important for intraspecific communication. Glandular secretions (usually from their anal glands), urine and feces are used for marking.Hohmann, pp. 67–70; MacClintock, p. 17; Zeveloff, pp. 68–69 With their broad auditory range, they can perceive tones up to 50–85 kHz as well as quiet noises like those produced by earthworms underground.Hohmann, pp. 66, 72; Zeveloff, p. 68
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="900de75a92e14d723288aa8c39435886" name="Mm_Hand" sectnum="5.2#1">../img/900de75a92e14d723288aa8c39435886.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>