<document id="2d62e212e80cd97d781296c2d1fa7227-9.13" name="Raccoon" cat="3">
<text>
The increasing number of raccoons in urban areas has resulted in diverse reactions in humans, ranging from outrage at their presence to deliberate feeding.Hohmann, pp. 103–106 Some wildlife experts and most public authorities caution against feeding wild animals because they might become increasingly obtrusive and dependent on humans as a food source.Bartussek, p. 34 Other experts challenge such arguments and give advice on feeding raccoons and other wildlife in their books.Holmgren, pp. 117–121 Raccoons without a fear of humans are a concern to those who attribute this trait to rabies, but scientists point out that this behavior is much more likely to be a behavioral adjustment to living in habitats with regular contact to humans for many generations.Bartussek, p. 24; Hohmann, p. 182Although serious attacks on humans by groups of non-rabid raccoons are extremely rare, at least one such attack has been documented.
  Raccoons usually do not prey on domestic cats and dogs, but individual cases of killings have been reported.

While overturned waste containers and raided fruit trees are just a nuisance to homeowners, it can cost several thousand dollars to repair damage caused by the use of attic space as dens. (Diploma thesis at the University of Halle-Wittenberg) Relocating or killing raccoons without a permit is forbidden in many urban areas on grounds of animal welfare. These methods usually only solve problems with particularly wild or aggressive individuals, since adequate dens are either known to several raccoons or will quickly be rediscovered.Bartussek, p. 32; Hohmann, pp. 142–144, 169 Loud noises, flashing lights and unpleasant odors have proven particularly effective in driving away a mother and her kits before they would normally leave the nesting place (when the kits are about eight weeks old).Bartussek, p. 40 Typically, though, only precautionary measures to restrict access to food waste and denning sites are effective in the long term.Bartussek, pp. 36–40; Hohmann, p. 169

Amongst all fruits and crops cultivated in agricultural areas, sweet corn in its milk stage is particularly popular among raccoons.Hohmann, pp. 87–88; MacClintock, p 49–50 In a two-year study by Purdue University researchers, published in 2004, raccoons were responsible for 87% of the damage to corn plants. Like other predators, raccoons searching for food can break into poultry houses to feed on chickens, ducks, their eggs or feed.Hohmann, p. 82; MacClintock, p. 47–48 Since they may enter tents and try to open locked containers on camping grounds, campers are advised to not keep food or toothpaste inside a tent.

Since raccoons are able to increase their rate of reproduction up to a certain limit, extensive hunting often does not solve problems with raccoon populations. Older males also claim larger home ranges than younger ones, resulting in a lower population density. The costs of large-scale measures to eradicate raccoons from a given area for a certain time are usually many times higher than the costs of the damage done by the raccoons.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="68ec40f25b699d68029ec31adbd0b5b8" name="Urban_raccoon_and_skunk" sectnum="9.13#1">../img/68ec40f25b699d68029ec31adbd0b5b8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>