<document id="2de1be2cdc7d6a0a469fc59a5d1a5588-6" name="Red-billed_Chough" cat="3">
<text>
In Greek mythology, the Red-billed Chough, also known as 'sea-crow', was considered sacred to the Titan Cronus and dwelt on Calypso's 'Blessed Island', where "The birds of broadest wing their mansions form/The chough, the sea-mew, the loquacious crow,"

The Red-billed Chough has a long association with Cornwall, and appears on the Cornish Coat of Arms.  A legend from the county says that King Arthur did not die but was transformed into a Red-billed Chough, and hence killing this bird was unlucky.

Up to the eighteenth century, the Red-billed Chough was associated with fire-raising, and was described by William Camden as ''incendaria avis'', "oftentime  it secretly conveieth fire sticks, setting their houses afire". Daniel Defoe was also familiar with this story:
It is counted little better than a kite, for it is of ravenous quality, and is very mischievous; it will steal and carry away any thing it finds about the house, that is not too heavy, tho' not fit for its food; as knives, forks, spoons and linnen cloths, or whatever it can fly away with, sometimes they say it has stolen bits of firebrands, or lighted candles, and lodged them in the stacks of corn, and the thatch of barns and houses, and set them on fire; but this I only had by oral tradition.

Not all mentions of "chough" refer to this species.  Because  of the origins of its  name, when Shakespeare writes of "the crows and choughs that wing the midway air"  or Henry VIII's Vermin Act of 1532 is "ordeyned to dystroye Choughes, Crowes and Rookes", they are clearly referring to the Jackdaw.

In  heraldry, Choughs are  known  as "beckits" and three were depicted on the coat of arms of Archbishop Thomas Becket. Due to its connection to the saint, the city of Canterbury also has Red-billed Choughs on its coats of arms. This species has  been depicted on the stamps of Bhutan, The Gambia, the Isle of Man, Turkmenistan and Yugoslavia. Retrieved 4 June 2009
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f0d66315d46b4952c1c9f7bcd20d72b3" name="Becket-arms" sectnum="6#1">../img/f0d66315d46b4952c1c9f7bcd20d72b3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>