<document id="2de1be2cdc7d6a0a469fc59a5d1a5588-4.2" name="Red-billed_Chough" cat="3">
<text>
The Red-billed Chough breeds from three years of age, and normally raises only one brood a year, although the age at first breeding is greater in large populations. A pair exhibits strong mate and site fidelity once a bond is established.  The bulky nest is  composed of roots and stems of heather, furze or other plants, and is lined with wool or hair; in  central Asia, the hair may be taken from live  Himalayan Tahr. The nest is constructed in a cave or similar fissure in a crag or cliff face. Old buildings may be used, and in Tibet working monasteries provide sites, as occasionally do modern buildings in Mongolian towns, including Ulan Bator. The Red-billed Chough will utilise other artificial sites sites such as quarries and mineshafts for nesting where they are available.

The Chough lays three to five eggs 3.9 x 2.8 centimetres (1.5 x 1.1 in) in size and weighing 15.7 grammes (0.55 oz), of which 6% is shell. They are spotted, not always densely, in various shades of brown and grey on a creamy or slightly tinted ground.
The egg size is independent of the clutch size and the nest site, but may vary between different females. The female incubates for 17–18 days before the altricial downy chicks are hatched, and is fed at the nest by the male. The female broods the newly hatched chicks for around ten days,Laiolo, P.; Bignal, E.M. & I.J. Patterson (1998). " The dynamics of parental care in Choughs(''Pyrrhocorax pyrrhocorax'')" ''Journal of Ornithology'' '''139''' (3): 297-305 and then both parents share feeding and nest sanitation duties. The chicks fledge 31–41 days after hatching..

Juveniles have a 43% chance of surviving their first year, and the annual survival rate of adults is about 80%. Choughs generally have a lifespan of about seven years, although an age of 17 years has been recorded.Roberts, P. J. (1985) The choughs of Bardsey, ''British Birds'' '''78'''(5): 217–32. The temperature and rainfall in the months preceding breeding correlates  with the number of young fledging each year and their survival rate. Chicks fledging under good conditions are more likely to survive to breeding age, and have longer breeding lives than those fledging under poor conditions.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0ba563583875cff92566a50a683d5ec8" name="South_Stack3" sectnum="4.2#1">../img/0ba563583875cff92566a50a683d5ec8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>