<document id="2de1be2cdc7d6a0a469fc59a5d1a5588-1.1" name="Red-billed_Chough" cat="3">
<text>
There are eight extant subspecies, although differences between them are slight.
* ''P. p. pyrrhocorax'', the nominate subspecies and smallest form, is endemic to the British Isles, where it is restricted to Ireland, the Isle of Man, and the far west of Wales and Scotland, although it has recently recolonised Cornwall after an absence of many years.
* ''P. p. erythropthalmus'', described by Louis Jean Pierre Vieillot in 1817 as ''Coracia erythrorhamphos'',  occurs in the Red-billed Chough's continental European range, excluding Greece. It is larger and slightly greener than the nominate race.
* ''P. p. barbarus'', described by Charles Vaurie under its current name in 1954, is resident in North Africa and on La Palma in the Canary Islands. Compared to ''P. p. erythropthalmus'', it is larger, has a longer tail and wings, and its plumage has a greener gloss. It is the longest-billed form, both absolutely and relatively.
* ''P. p. baileyi'' described by Austin Loomer Rand and Charles Vaurie under its current name in 1955, is a dull-plumaged subspecies endemic to Ethiopia, where it occurs in two separate areas. The two populations could possibly represent different subspecies.
* ''P. p. docilis'', described by Johann Friedrich Gmelin as ''Corvus docilis'' in 1774,  breeds from Greece to Afghanistan. It is larger than the African subspecies, but it has a smaller bill and its plumage is very green-tinted, with little gloss.

* ''P. p. himalayanus'', described by John Gould in 1862 as ''Fregilus himalayanus'', is found from the Himalayas to western China, but intergrades with  ''P. p. docilis'' in the west of its range. It is the largest subspecies, long-tailed, and with blue or purple-blue glossed feathers.
* ''P. p. centralis'', described by Erwin Stresemann in 1928 under its current name,   breeds in central Asia. It is smaller and less strongly blue than ''P. p. himalayanus'', but its distinctness from the next subspecies has been questioned.
* ''P. p. brachypus'', described by Robert Swinhoe in 1871 as ''Fregilus graculus  var. brachypus'', breeds in central and northern China, Mongolia and southern Siberia. It is similar to ''P. p. centralis'' but with a weaker bill.

There is one known prehistoric form of the Red-billed Chough. ''P. p. primigenius'', a subspecies that lived in Europe during the last ice age, which was described in 1875 by Alphonse Milne-Edwards from finds in southwest France. 

Detailed analysis of call similarity suggests that the Asiatic and Ethiopian races diverged from the western subspecies early in evolutionary history, and that Italian Red-billed Choughs are more closely allied to the North African subspecies than to those of the rest of Europe.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5db34a8a926b0b97a1791b7fd59fd437" name="Red-billed_Chough_I_IMG_7083" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/5db34a8a926b0b97a1791b7fd59fd437.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>