<document id="2e4489966c79adaa91cee52f59a7c50b-2.2" name="Actions_along_the_Matanikau" cat="29">
<text>
The 930 men of Puller's battalion marched west from the Lunga perimeter early on the morning of September 23.  Later that morning, Puller's troops chased away two Japanese patrols that were reconnoitering the Marine Lunga defenses.  Puller's battalion then camped for the night and prepared to climb Mount Austen the next day.Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 205.

At 17:00 on September 24, as Puller's men hiked up the northeast slope of Mount Austen, they surprised and killed a bivouac of 16 Japanese soldiers.  The noise from the skirmish alerted several companies of Oka's Maizuru Battalion, who were emplaced nearby.  The Maizuru troops quickly attacked Puller's Marines, who took cover and returned fire.  Acting on Oka's orders, the Japanese slowly disengaged while withdrawing towards the Matanikau River, and the engagement was over by nightfall.  The Marines counted 30 dead Japanese and had suffered 13 dead and 25 wounded.  Puller radioed headquarters and requested help to evacuate the wounded.  Vandegrift replied that he would send the 2nd Battalion, 5th Marine Regiment (2/5) as reinforcements the next day.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 270, Zimmerman, ''The Guadalcanal Campaign'', p. 97, Hough, ''Pearl Harbor to Guadalcanal'', p. 315, and Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 206.

2/5, under Lieutenant Colonel David McDougal, rendezvoused with Puller's unit early on September 25.  Puller sent his casualties back to the Lunga perimeter with three companies of his battalion and continued on with the mission with his remaining company (Company C), his headquarters staff, and 2/5, and they bivouacked for the night between Mount Austen and the Matanikau River.Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 208, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', pp. 270–271 and Zimmerman, ''The Guadalcanal Campaign'', p. 97.

On the morning of September 26, Puller and McDougal's troops reached the Matanikau River and attempted to cross over a bridge previously built by the Japanese that was called the "one-log bridge." Because of resistance by about 100 Japanese defenders around the bridge, the Marines instead proceeded north along the east bank of the Matanikau to the sand spit on the coast at the mouth of the river.  Oka's troops repulsed a Marine attempt to cross the Matanikau at the sand spit as well as another attempt to cross the one-log bridge later in the afternoon.  In the meantime, Griffith's Raider battalion along with Merritt A. Edson, commander of the 5th Marine Regiment, joined Puller and McDougal's troops at the mouth of the Matanikau.Zimmerman, ''The Guadalcanal Campaign'', pp. 97–99, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 271 and Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 208.  Approximately 100 Japanese from the 12th Company, 4th Regiment, were defending the one-log bridge (Alexander, p. 206).

Edson brought with him a "hastily devised" plan of attack, primarily written by Lieutenant Colonel Merrill B. Twining, a member of Vandegrift's division staff, that called for Griffiths Raiders, along with Puller's Company C, to cross the one-log bridge and then outflank the Japanese at the river mouth/sand spit from the south.  At the same time, McDougal's battalion was to attack across the sand spit.  If the attacks were successful, the rest of Puller's battalion would land by boat west of Point Cruz to take the Japanese by surprise from the rear.  Aircraft from Henderson Field as well as Marine 75 mm and 105 mm artillery would provide support for the operation.  The Marine offensive would begin the next day, on September 27.Hough, ''Pearl Harbor to Guadalcanal'', p. 315, Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 208 and Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', pp. 271–272.

The Marine attack on the morning of September 27 did not make much headway.  Griffith's Raiders were unable to advance at the one-log bridge over the Matanikau, suffering several casualties, including the death of Major Kenneth D. Bailey and the wounding of Griffith.  A flanking attempt by the Raiders further upstream also failed.  The Japanese, who had reinforced their units at the mouth of the Matanikau during the night with additional companies from the 124th Infantry Regiment, repulsed the attacks by McDougal's men.Alexander, pp. 208–210, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 272, Jersey, ''Hell's Islands'', p. 239, Zimmerman, ''The Guadalcanal Campaign'', pp. 97–99, and Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', pp. 208–209.  Griffith was shot through the shoulder which damaged his brachial plexus but refused to be evacuated until later that night (Alexander, p. 210).

As a result of "garbled" messages from Griffith because of a Japanese air raid on Henderson Field that disrupted the Marine communication's net, Vandegrift and Edson believed that the Raiders had succeeded in crossing the Matanikau.  Therefore, Puller's battalion was ordered to proceed with the planned landing west of Point Cruz.  Three companies of Puller's battalion, under Major Otho Rogers, landed from nine landing craft just west of Point Cruz at 13:00.  Rogers' Marines pushed inland and occupied a ridge, called Hill 84, about  from the landing area.  Oka, recognizing the seriousness of this landing, ordered his forces to close on Rogers' Marines from both the west and east.Alexander, p. 209, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 273, Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 210 and Zimmerman, Jersey, ''Hell's Islands'', p. 242, ''The Guadalcanal Campaign'', pp. 97–99.  Oka's units that attacked Puller's men on the ridge included the 2nd Battalion, 124th Infantry's headquarters unit, a regimental machinegun platoon, and the 3rd Battalion's Infantry Gun Unit plus the 1st Company and elements of the 1st Battalion's Machinegun Unit.

Soon after occupying the ridge, Rogers' men came under heavy fire from two directions from Oka's forces.  Major Rogers was hit by a mortar shell that blew him in half, killing him instantly.  Captain Charles Kelley, commander of one of the companies, took command and deployed the Marines in a perimeter defense around the ridge to fight back.Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 209 and Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', pp. 272–273.  The Marines on Hill 84 were without radio communication and thus could not call for help.  The Marines improvised by using white undershirts to spell out the word "H-E-L-P" on the ridge.  A Cactus Air Force (the name for the Allied aircraft operating out of Henderson Field) SBD Dauntless supporting the operation spotted the undershirt message and relayed the message to Edson by radio.Zimmerman, ''The Guadalcanal Campaign'', pp. 99–100, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 273 and Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 210.

Edson received a message from the Raider Battalion reporting their failure to cross the Matanikau.  Edson, speaking to those around him, stated, "I guess we better call them off.  They can't seem to cross the river."  Puller angrily replied, "You're not going to throw these men away!" apparently in reference to his men trapped on the west side of the Matanikau, and "stormed" off toward the beach where, with the help of his personal signalman, Puller was able to hail the Navy destroyer USS ''Monssen'' that was supporting the operation.  Once aboard ''Monssen'', Puller and the destroyer led ten landing craft towards Point Cruz and established communications with Kelly on the ridge by signal flag.Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 210, Hough, ''Pearl Harbor to Guadalcanal'', pp. 316–317, and Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 273.

By this time, Oka's troops had moved into position to completely cut-off the Marines on Hill 84 from the coast.  Therefore, ''Monssen'', coordinated by Puller, began to blast a path between the ridge and the beach.  After about 30 minutes of firing by the destroyer, the way was clear for the Marines to escape to the beach. Despite taking some casualties from their own artillery fire, most of the Marines made it to the beach near Point Cruz by 16:30.  Oka's troops put heavy fire on the Marines at the beach in effort to keep them from successfully evacuating, and the U.S. Coast Guard crews manning the U.S. landing craft responded with their own heavy fire to cover the Marines' withdrawal.  Under fire, the Marines boarded the landing craft and successfully returned to the Lunga perimeter, ending the action.  U.S. Coast Guard Signalman First Class Douglas Albert Munro was killed while providing covering fire from his landing craft for the Marines as they evacuated the beach and was posthumously awarded the Medal of Honor, to date the only member of the Coast Guard to receive the decoration.
Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 273, Zimmerman, ''The Guadalcanal Campaign'', pp. 100–101, and Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', pp. 212–213.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b46709a3a70fb3877a7c33285c0d5ba2" name="PullerGuadalcanal" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/b46709a3a70fb3877a7c33285c0d5ba2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>