<document id="2ef56eabe062fd860c81a0e44ee15549-2.9" name="Alfred_Russel_Wallace" cat="3">
<text>
In 1864, Wallace published a paper, "The Origin of Human Races and the Antiquity of Man Deduced from the Theory of 'Natural Selection'", applying the theory to humankind. Darwin had not yet publicly addressed the subject, although Thomas Huxley had in ''Evidence as to Man's Place in Nature''.

Shortly afterwards, Wallace became a spiritualist. At about the same time, he began to maintain that natural selection cannot account for mathematical, artistic, or musical genius, as well as metaphysical musings, and wit and humour. He eventually said that something in "the unseen universe of Spirit" had interceded at least three times in history. The first was the creation of life from inorganic matter. The second was the introduction of consciousness in the higher animals. And the third was the generation of the higher mental faculties in mankind. He also believed that the raison d'être of the universe was the development of the human spirit.Wallace Darwinism p. 477. These views greatly disturbed Darwin, who argued that spiritual appeals were not necessary and that sexual selection could easily explain apparently non-adaptive mental phenomena. While some historians have concluded that Wallace's belief that natural selection was insufficient to explain the development of consciousness and the human mind was directly caused by his adoption of spiritualism, other Wallace scholars have disagreed, and some maintain that Wallace never believed natural selection applied to those areas.Shermer pp. 157–160. Reaction to Wallace's ideas on this topic among leading naturalists at the time varied. Charles Lyell endorsed Wallace's views on human evolution rather than Darwin's.Larson p. 100.Shermer p. 160. However, many, including Huxley, Hooker, and Darwin himself, were critical of Wallace.Slotten pp. 280–96. As one historian of science has pointed out, Wallace's views in this area were at odds with two major tenets of the emerging Darwinian philosophy, which were that evolution was not teleological and that it was not anthropocentric.Shermer pp. 208–09.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2cbe0d05d3bef34aa4562cd08a9dc399" name="Wallace_chimp" sectnum="2.9#1">../img/2cbe0d05d3bef34aa4562cd08a9dc399.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>