<document id="2ef56eabe062fd860c81a0e44ee15549-1.1" name="Alfred_Russel_Wallace" cat="3">
<text>
Wallace was born in the Welsh village of Llanbadoc, near Usk, Monmouthshire.Wilson ''The Forgotten Naturalist'' p. 1. He was the eighth of nine children of Thomas Vere Wallace and Mary Anne Greenell. His mother was from a respectable middle-class English family from Hertford. Thomas Wallace was of Scottish ancestry. His family, like many Scottish Wallaces, claimed a connection to William Wallace, a Scottish leader during the Wars of Scottish Independence in the 13th century. Thomas Wallace received a law degree, but never actually practiced law. He inherited some income-generating property, but bad investments and failed business ventures resulted in a steady deterioration of the family's financial position.

When Wallace was five years old, his family moved to Hertford, north of London. There he attended Hertford Grammar School until financial difficulties forced his family to withdraw him in 1836.Wilson pp. 6–10. Wallace then moved to London to live and work with his older brother John, a 19-year-old apprentice builder. (In 1979, a plaque was placed at 44 St. Peter's Road in Croydon commemorating the fact that he lived there at one point during this period.) This was a stopgap measure until William, his oldest brother, was ready to take him on as an apprentice surveyor. While there, he attended lectures and read books at the London Mechanics' Institute, where he was exposed to the radical political ideas of the Welsh social reformer Robert Owen and Thomas Paine. He left London in 1837 to live with William and work as his apprentice for six years. At the end of 1839, they moved to Kington, Hereford, near the Welsh border before eventually settling at Neath in Glamorgan in Wales. Between 1840 and 1843, Wallace did surveying work in the countryside of the west of England and Wales.Raby ''Bright Paradise'' pp. 77–78.Slotten ''The Heretic in Darwin's Court'' pp. 11–14. By the end of 1843, William's business had declined due to difficult economic conditions. Wallace left in January, aged 20. One result of Wallace's early travels has been a modern controversy about his nationality. Since Wallace was born in Gwent (then called Monmouthshire), Wales, some sources have considered him to be Welsh. However some historians have questioned this because neither of his parents were Welsh, his family only briefly lived in Monmouthshire, the Welsh people Wallace knew in his childhood considered him to be English, and because Wallace himself consistently referred to himself as English rather than Welsh (even when writing about his time in Wales). One Wallace scholar has stated that because of these facts the most reasonable interpretation was that he was an Englishman born in Wales. 

After a brief period of unemployment, he was hired as a master at the Collegiate School in Leicester to teach drawing, mapmaking, and surveying. Wallace spent a lot of time at the Leicester library where he read ''An Essay on the Principle of Population'' by Thomas Malthus and where one evening he met the entomologist Henry Bates. Bates was only 19 years old, but had already published a paper on beetles in the journal ''Zoologist''. He befriended Wallace and started him collecting insects.Shermer ''In Darwin's Shadow'' p. 53.Slotten pp. 22–26. William died in March 1845, and Wallace left his teaching position to assume control of his brother's firm in Neath, but he and his brother John were unable to make the business work. After a couple of months, Wallace found work as a civil engineer for a nearby firm that was working on a survey for a proposed railway in the Vale of Neath. Wallace's work on the survey involved spending a lot of time outdoors in the countryside, allowing him to indulge his new passion for collecting insects. Wallace was able to persuade his brother John to join him in starting another architecture and civil engineering firm, which carried out a number of projects, including the design of a building for the Mechanics' Institute of Neath. William Jevons, the founder of that institute, was impressed by Wallace and persuaded him to give lectures there on science and engineering. In the autumn of 1846, he, aged 23, and John were able to purchase a cottage near Neath, where they lived with their mother and sister Fanny (his father had died in 1843).Slotten pp. 26–29.Wilson pp. 19–20. During this period, he read avidly, exchanging letters with Bates about the anonymous evolutionary treatise ''Vestiges of the Natural History of Creation'', Charles Darwin's ''Journal'', and Charles Lyell's ''Principles of Geology''.Raby ''Bright Paradise'' p. 78.Wallace ''My Life'' pp. ,
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="222b058220504cbfe9ad8ab1889b2204" name="Wallace_Mechanics_Institute" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/222b058220504cbfe9ad8ab1889b2204.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>