<document id="2f0c85c03d5688756a28d56d9db7657a-1.5" name="Peter_Jennings" cat="19">
<text>
As he did in 2000, on January 22, 2004, Jennings moderated the Democratic primary debate in New Hampshire. He was noted for questioning General Wesley Clark over Clark's silence over controversial comments made by liberal filmmaker Michael Moore, a supporter of Clark. Moore called then-President George W. Bush a "deserter".

By late 2004, Brokaw had retired from his anchoring duties at NBC, ceding the reins to Brian Williams; Rather planned to step down in March 2005. Jennings and ABC saw an opportunity to gain viewers, and initiated a publicity blitz touting the anchor's foreign reporting experience. However, despite having almost always reported from the scene of any major news story, Jennings was sidelined by an upper respiratory infection in late December 2004; he was forced to anchor from New York during the aftermath of the Asian tsunami, while his competitors traveled to the region. For Jennings, the situation was agonizing.Steinberg, Jacques (January 10, 2005). "". ''The New York Times'', p. E1. Retrieved on April 27, 2008.

In late March, viewers started noticing that Jennings' voice sounded uncharacteristically gravelly and unhealthy during evening newscasts. On April 1, 2005, he anchored ''World News Tonight'' for the last time; his poor health also prevented him from covering the death and funeral of Pope John Paul II. On April 5, 2005, Jennings informed viewers through a taped message on ''World News Tonight'' that he had been diagnosed with lung cancer, and was starting chemotherapy treatment the following week. "As some of you now know, I have learned in the last couple of days that I have lung cancer," he said. "Yes, I was a smoker until about 20 years ago, and I was weak and I smoked over 9/11. But whatever the reason, the news does slow you down a bit."Stanley, Alessandra (April 6, 2005). "". ''The New York Times'', p. A6. Retrieved on January 12, 2007. Although he stated his intention to continue anchoring whenever possible, the message was to be his last appearance on television.

Throughout the summer, Charles Gibson, co-host of ''Good Morning America'', and Elizabeth Vargas, co-host of ''20/20'', served as temporary anchors. On April 29, 2005 Jennings posted a letter on ABCNews.com with an update of his status and expressing thanks to those who had offered him their good wishes and prayers.Jennings, Peter (April 29, 2005). "". ''ABC News''. Retrieved on January 12, 2007.  In June, Jennings visited the ABC News headquarters, and addressed staff members in an emotional speech; he thanked Gibson for closing each broadcast with the phrase, "for Peter Jennings and all of us at ABC News."
He posted another short letter of thanks on July 29, 2005, his 67th birthday.Jennings, Peter (July 29, 2005). "". ''ABC News''. Retrieved on January 12, 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ba7313d0aa963569ccdbaccaf5dd9769" name="Abc_wnt_jennings2_050405_t" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/ba7313d0aa963569ccdbaccaf5dd9769.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>