<document id="2f0c85c03d5688756a28d56d9db7657a-1.2" name="Peter_Jennings" cat="19">
<text>
Jennings started reporting for ABC at its New York news bureau. At the time, ABC lagged behind the more established news divisions of NBC and CBS, and the network was trying to attract younger viewers. On February 1, 1965, ABC plucked the fresh-faced Canadian from the field and placed him at the anchor desk of ''Peter Jennings With the News'', then a 15-minute nightly newscast. He replaced Ron Cochran, a fellow Canadian. At 26, Jennings was, and remains, the youngest-ever U.S. network news anchor.Glass, Charles (August 9, 2005). "". ''The Independent'', p. 32. Retrieved on November 30, 2006. "ABC was in bad shape at the time," Jennings said. "They were willing to try anything, and, to demonstrate the point, they tried me."Dawidziak, Mark (August 9, 2005). "" (fee required). ''The Cleveland Plain Dealer'' through '''', p. E1. Retrieved on November 30, 2006. 

An inexperienced Jennings had a hard time keeping up with his rivals at the other networks, and he could not compete with the venerable newscasts of Walter Cronkite at CBS and Chet Huntley and David Brinkley at NBC. American audiences disliked Jennings' Canadian accent. He pronounced lieutenant as "leftenant", mangled the pronunciation of "Appomattox," and misidentified the Marines' Hymn as Anchors Aweigh at Lyndon Johnson's presidential inauguration; his general ignorance of American affairs and culture led critics to deride Jennings as a "glamorcaster". "It was a little ridiculous when you think about it," he later reflected. "A 26-year-old trying to compete with Cronkite, Huntley and Brinkley. I was simply unqualified."CTV.ca News Staff (August 8, 2005). "". ''CTV''. Retrieved on November 30, 2006. After three rocky years at the anchor desk, Jennings called it quits and became a foreign correspondent.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7a183762acbeea02f6e3e8895abfc7d3" name="1965JenningsPromo" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/7a183762acbeea02f6e3e8895abfc7d3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>