<document id="2f9f3af9fa657285fb5c6d019d60b131-3.4" name="Edward_Low" cat="14">
<text>
The new fleet captured many more sloops, including one Low kept, naming it the ''Fortune''. During a trial on 10 July 1723 for a number of Low's crew, a sailor on board the ''Fortune'' named John Welland recalled how Low stripped his boat, including gold to the value of £150, then beat him and cut off his ear with a cutlass. - recount of the trial of many of Low's men, including verdict and witness statements, and Low's articles.

Following this, Low's fleet captured a Portuguese ship called the ''Nostra Signiora de Victoria'' on 25 January 1723. The ''Victoria's'' Portuguese captain allowed a bag containing approximately 11,000 gold moidores (worth at the time around £15,000) to fall into the sea rather than see it captured. One of Low's most noted episodes of cruelty followed: in his rage, he slashed off the Portuguese captain's lips with a cutlass, broiled them, and forced the victim to eat them while still hot. He then murdered the remaining crew. Low's own men described him as "a maniac and a brute".

A story describes Low burning a French cook alive, saying he was a "greasy fellow who would fry well", and another tells he once killed 53 Spanish captives with his cutlass. Some historians, including David Cordingly, believe this was deliberately done to cultivate a ferocious image. Historian Edward Leslie described Low as a psychopath with a history filled with "mutilations, disembowelings, decapitations, and slaughter". Low, like other pirates of the time, tried to intimidate his victims into surrendering, by threatening to kill or torture them. The crew of the targeted ship would hinder the officers from defending the ship, so afraid were they of reprisals. Some content available at Google Books:  First chapter available at Beacon.org:  One failed torture session led to one of Low's crew members accidentally cutting him in the mouth. Botched surgery left Low scarred.

A snow called the ''Unity'' was added to the fleet, and used as a tender, but was abandoned during an encounter with a man of war named the ''Mermaid''. As Low's success increased in the Caribbean, so did his notoriety. Eventually, a bounty was placed on his head, and Low set out for the Azores, again teaming up with Charles Harris. As they terrorised the Azores, the pressure increased from the authorities, who by then had taken special notice of Edward Low, despite the hordes of pirates in operation at the time.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4f980b7c10d1674cdb1c83126f6eb3a9" name="The_Cruelties_practised_by_Captain_Low" sectnum="3.4#1">../img/4f980b7c10d1674cdb1c83126f6eb3a9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>