<document id="303f963884bb2fd0173ac553c5b14e7e-2" name="Through_the_Looking_Glass_(Lost)" cat="19">
<text>
The title is an allusion to Lewis Carroll's novel ''Through the Looking-Glass, and What Alice Found There''Lindelof, Damon & Cuse, Carlton, (May 21, 2007) "", ''ABC''.  Retrieved on July 3, 2007. and a reference to the fictitious Dharma Initiative station found in the previous episode. Shooting began on April 13, 2007Perez, Mario, (May 24, 2007) "", ''ABC Medianet''.  Retrieved on July 7, 2007. and ended on May 7, 2007.Lindelof, Damon & Cuse, Carlton, (May 11, 2007) "", ''ABC''.  Retrieved on July 7, 2007.  The writers were so far behind schedule that parts of the episode were shot while later parts were still being written.Cuse, Carlton & Lilly, Evangeline & Holloway, Josh, "I Do".  ''Lost: The Complete Third Season – The Unexplored Experience'', Buena Vista Home Entertainment.  Audio commentary, disc 2.  Released on December 11, 2007.  Filming mostly took place on Oahu, Hawaii, with additional scenes shot in Los Angeles."", ''Lost Virtual Tour''.  Retrieved on July 7, 2007.  The hospital scenes were filmed on the same sets used for the ABC show ''Grey's Anatomy''.Lachonis, Jon, (July 4, 2007) "", ''BuddyTV''.  Retrieved on July 7, 2007.

Despite not being mentioned in the official press release, then 15 year old Malcolm David Kelley returned to reprise his role as 10 year old Walt Lloyd,Abrams, J.J. (writer/director) & Lindelof, Damon (writer) & Lieber, Jeffrey (writer).  "Pilot". ''Lost'', ABC.  Episode 2, season 1.  Aired on September 29, 2004. and received credit as a "special guest star".Entertainment Yahoo! TV Beta, "", ''Yahoo!''.  Retrieved on July 8, 2007.  Kelley’s character had left the island in the second season finale,Lindelof, Damon (writer) & Cuse, Carlton (writer) & Bender, Jack (director).  "Live Together, Die Alone".  ''Lost'', ABC.  Episode 24, season 2.  Aired on May 24, 2007. only 26 days prior to the events of "Through the Looking Glass", however, Kelley had not filmed an episode in over a year.  In his single scene, Walt has visibly aged, appears taller and has a deeper voice.''BuddyTV'', (May 25, 2007) "".  Retrieved on July 8, 2007.  The producers had hoped that Harold Perrineau, who plays Walt's father Michael Dawson, would return in this episode, but he was busy filming the pilot for CBS' ''Demons''.Bruno, Mike, (August 6, 2007) "", ''Entertainment Weekly''.  Retrieved on August 7, 2007.   Perrineau instead returned to ''Lost'' in season 4.McPherson, Stephen, (July 25, 2007) "", ''American Broadcasting Company''. Retrieved on August 7, 2007.  Rob McElhenney's character—the Other Aldo, who had previously appeared in "Not in Portland"—is killed in the finale; however McElhenney does not appear because he was busy with FX's ''It's Always Sunny in Philadelphia''.Ausiello, Michael, (August 29, 2007) "", ''TV Guide''.  Retrieved on January 22, 2008.  Damon Lindelof and Carlton Cuse lent their voices for the unseen roles of the flight captain and newscaster, respectively.Lindelof, Damon & Cuse, Carlton, (May 4, 2007) "", ''ABC''.  Retrieved on July 7, 2007.



This episode concluded the story arc about Charlie's death, which began earlier in the season when Desmond prophesied Charlie's death.Lindelof, Damon (writer) & Goddard, Drew (writer) & Bender, Jack (director).  "Flashes Before Your Eyes".  ''Lost'', ABC.  Episode 8, season 3.  Aired on February 14, 2007.  Throughout the season, Charlie escaped death;Kim, Christina M. (writer) & Rosenberg, Jordan (writer) & Edwards, Paul (director).  "Par Avion".  ''Lost'', ABC.  Episode 12, season 3.  Aired on March 14, 2007. however, Desmond told Charlie that he had to die in order for his girlfriend, Claire Littleton, to get rescued from the island.  The storyline of Charlie's death was conceived while producing the latter part of the second season,Ausiello, Michael, (May 23, 2007) "", ''TV Guide''.  Retrieved on July 6, 2007. after the storyline of Charlie's drug addiction finished.Kitsis, Edward (writer) & Adam Horowitz (writer) & Williams, Stephen (director).  "Three Minutes".  ''Lost'', ABC.  Episode 22, season 2.  Aired on May 17, 2006.  The news of his character's death was broken to Monaghan two episodes in advance,Snierson, Dan, (May 24, 2007) "", ''Entertainment Weekly''.  Retrieved on July 7, 2007. to which Monaghan felt "relief" for knowing the future of his job on the show.Snierson, Dan, (May 18, 2007) "", ''Entertainment Weekly''.  Retrieved on July 7, 2007.  On the night of Monaghan's second to last day on set, he was presented with a canoe paddle that had been made by the cast and crew.Snierson, Dan, (May 24, 2007) "", ''Entertainment Weekly''.  Retrieved on July 7, 2007.  Monaghan hoped to return to ''Lost'' as a guest star in flashbacks or dreams.Malcolm, Shawna, (May 24, 2007) "", ''TV Guide''.   Retrieved on July 7, 2007.

Jack Bender stated that Matthew Fox "really commits body and soul into the story he's telling" and Fox questioned whether he had ever been more tired than while shooting the double episode."Lost: On Location – Through the Looking Glass".  ''Lost: The Complete Third Season – The Unexplored Experience'', Buena Vista Home Entertainment.  Featurette, disc 7.  Released on December 11, 2007.  Like the other ''Lost'' season finales, the final cliffhanger scene was given a codename—"The Rattlesnake in the Mailbox"—and kept top secret.Jensen, Jeff, (May 2007) "", ''Entertainment Weekly''.  Retrieved on August 3, 2007.  After Lindelof and Cuse wrote the scene, only Fox, Lilly, Bender and co-executive producer Jean Higgins were given copies of the script.  The scene was shot with a green screen in an abandoned Honolulu parking lot with the airport edited in.Malcolm, Shawna, (October 15, 2007) "", ''TV Guide''.  Retrieved on October 15, 2007.  Despite the security measures, a complete and detailed episode synopsis was uploaded online over a week before the episode aired.Lachonis, Jon, (May 20, 2007) "", ''BuddyTV''.  Retrieved on July 9, 2007.  Disney investigated the leak.Ausiello, Michael, (May 30, 2007) "", ''TV Guide''.  Retrieved on July 7, 2007.  The leak prompted Lindelof and Cuse to enter "radio silence", which was temporarily broken at Comic-Con International 2007.Lachonis, Jon, (May 31, 2007) "", ''BuddyTV''.  Retrieved on July 7, 2007.  The funeral parlor that Jack visits is called "Hoffs/Drawlar", which is an anagram of "flashforward".Hines, Ree, (June 4, 2007) "", ''MSNBC''.  Retrieved on July 7, 2007. The idea of flashforwards was conceived by creators Lindelof and Abrams during the show's conception.Veitch, Kristin, (May 23, 2007) "", ''E!''.  Retrieved on July 6, 2007.  However, Cuse and Lindelof only started fleshing out the idea at the end of the first season, after they realized that flashbacks would eventually stop being revelatory and knew that they would eventually have to switch to flashforwards.Lindelof, Damon & Cuse, Carlton, (July 26, 2007) "", ''Comic-Con International''.  Retrieved on July 31, 2007.  With the announcement that the series would conclude 48 episodes after "Through the Looking Glass",''ABC Medianet'', (May 7, 2007) "".  Retrieved on July 31, 2007. they felt comfortable playing flashforwards as early as the third season finale.

Post-production wrapped on May 21, 2007, only two days before it aired on television.  The score was composed by series musician Michael Giacchino, while popular music was also featured throughout the episode.  As Jack drives to the funeral parlor, he listens to "Scentless Apprentice" by Nirvana.  The code that Charlie uses to disable the jamming in the Looking Glass is to the tune of "Good Vibrations" by The Beach Boys.Disney (November 11, 2007) "", ''ABC''.  Retrieved on November 22, 2007.  Charlie also sings a song in the episode that was written by Dominic Monaghan, who plays him.Met/Hodder, "Through the Looking Glass" (enhanced).  Aired on January 30, 2007.  A ''Lost'' season finale is approximately twice as long the average ''Lost'' episode.  Due to the episode's length, it was split into two parts in some countries and when released on DVD.'','' (September 25, 2007) Buena Vista Home Entertainment. Unlike most episodes, this episode did not feature a "previously on ''Lost''…" recap at the start of the episode when it first aired; however, it was originally preceded by a clip-show titled "Lost: The Answers", which recapped the third season.''ABC Medianet'', (May 7, 2007) "".  Retrieved on July 31, 2007.  Cuse said that he and Lindelof think the finale is "very cool  we're very proud of it."  Stephen McPherson, the president of ABC Entertainment, called "Through the Looking Glass" "one of the best episodes" of the series.Veitch, Kristin, (May 15, 2007) "", ''E!''.  Retrieved on July 7, 2007.  Buena Vista Home Entertainment released "Through the Looking Glass" on the season's DVD and Blu-ray Disc sets on December 11, 2007 in Region 1.Snugglefish Media, (August 31, 2007) "", ''High-Def Digest''.  Retrieved on September 9, 2007.  A featurette called "''Lost'': On Location" features cast and crew discussing production of select episodes, including "Through the Looking Glass".  The episode was rerun for the first time on January 30, 2008 with on-screen text in the lower third of the screen, similar to VH1's ''Pop-up Video''.''ABC Medianet'', (January 24, 2008) "".  Retrieved on January 26, 2008.  These pop-ups were not written by ''Lost'''s writers due to the 2007–2008 Writers Guild of America strike; they were written by the marketing company Met/Hodder.Carter, Bill, (January 30, 2008) "", ''The New York Times''.  Retrieved on January 30, 2008.  This enhanced edition was viewed by almost 9 million Americans.Mitovich, Matt Webb, (January 31) "", ''TV Guide''.  Retrieved on January 31, 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="016b914f907313868898aa565f48fb19" name="Lost_chair" sectnum="2#1">../img/016b914f907313868898aa565f48fb19.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>