<document id="304d970e181469f7c726636b88a532d0-2.4" name="Halloween_II" cat="19">
<text>
John Carpenter refused to direct the sequel and originally approached Tommy Lee Wallace, the art director from the original ''Halloween'', to take the helm. Carpenter told one interviewer, "I had made that film once and I really didn't want to do it again."John Carpenter interview, ''Famous Monsters'' magazine, quoted at ; last accessed April 19, 2006 After Wallace declined, Carpenter chose Rick Rosenthal, a relatively unknown and inexperienced director whose previous credits included episodes of the television series ''Secrets of Midland Heights'' (1980–1981). In an interview with ''Twilight Zone Magazine'', Carpenter explains that Rosenthal was chosen because "he did a terrific short called ''Toyer''. It was full of suspense and tension and terrific performances."Behind the Scenes, ''Halloween II'', at ; last accessed April 19, 2006.



Stylistically, Rosenthal attempted to recreate the elements and themes of the original film. The opening title features a jack-o'-lantern that splits in half to reveal a human skull. In the original, the camera zoomed in on the jack-o'-lantern's left eye.  The first scene of the film is presented through a first-person camera format in which a voyeuristic Michael Myers enters an elderly couple's home and steals a knife from the kitchen. Rosenthal attempts to reproduce the "jump" scenes present in ''Halloween'', but does not film Myers on the periphery, which is where he appeared in many of the scenes of the original. Under Rosenthal's direction, Myers is the central feature of a majority of the scenes.Review of ''Halloween II'' at ; last accessed April 19, 2006. In an interview with Luke Ford, Rosenthal explains, ''The first movie I ever did '''' was a sequel, but it was supposed to be a direct continuation. It started one minute after the first movie ended. You have to try hard to maintain the style of the first movie. I wanted it to feel like a two-parter. You have the responsibility and the restraints of the style that's been set. It was the same crew. My philosophy was to do more of a thriller than a slasher movie.''

The decision to include more gore and nudity in the sequel was not made by Rosenthal, who contends that it was Carpenter who chose to make the film much bloodier than the original.Bill Chambers, review of ''Halloween II'' at ; last accessed April 19, 2006. According to the film's official website, "Carpenter came in and directed a few sequences to clean up some of Rosenthal's work." One reviewer of the film notes that "Carpenter, concerned that the picture would be deemed too 'tame' by the slasher audience, re-filmed several death scenes with more gore."James Berardinelli, review of ''Halloween II'' at ; last accessed April 19, 2006. When asked about his role in the directing process, Carpenter told an interviewer: ''That's a long, long story. That was a project I got involved in as a result of several different kinds of pressure. I had no influence over the direction of the film. I had an influence in the post-production. I saw a rough cut of ''Halloween II'', and it wasn't scary. It was about as scary as ''Quincy''. So we had to do some post-production work to bring it at least up to par with the competition.''

Rosenthal was not pleased with Carpenter's changes. He reportedly complained that Carpenter "ruined  carefully paced film."Justin Kerswell, "Slash with Panache?", review of ''Halloween II'' at ; last accessed April 19, 2006. Regardless, many of the graphic scenes contained elements not seen before in film. Roger Ebert claims, "This movie has the first close-up I can remember of a hypodermic needle being inserted into an eyeball." The film is often categorized as a splatter film rather than a slasher film due to the elevated level of gore. Film critic John McCarty writes of splatter films: " aim not to scare their audiences, necessarily, nor to drive them to the edge of their seats in suspense, but to mortify them with scenes of explicit gore. In splatter movies, mutilation is indeed the message ...."John McCarty, ''The Official Splatter Movie Guide'' (New York: St. Martin's Press, 1989), ISBN 0-312-02958-6, quoted at ; last accessed April 19, 2006. Rosenthal later directed the eighth film in the ''Halloween'' series, ''Halloween: Resurrection'' (2002).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="535648cb81944995adf1e0d29ed76586" name="HalloweenII_title" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/535648cb81944995adf1e0d29ed76586.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>