<document id="30a1a549da537191bea69768396b7621-3" name="Celine_Dion" cat="20">
<text>
Dion became an entrepreneur with the establishment of her franchise restaurant ''"Nickels"'' in 1990. She has since divested her interests in the chain and is no longer affiliated with ''Nickels'' as of 1997. She also has a range of eyewear and a line of perfume, manufactured by Coty, Inc.Barron, Lee. "'Elizabeth Hurley Is More Than a Model': Stars and Career Diversification in Contemporary Media." ''Journal of Popular Culture''. Vol. 39. Issue No. 4. ISSN: 00223840 (2006): pg 523.Fass, Allison. "Business Scents." ''Forbes Magazine''. September 19, 2005. pp 064a.Barnes, Rachel. "Coty set to add two fragrances to men's range." ''Marketing''. February 19, 2004. pg4. In October 2004, Canada's national air carrier Air Canada hired Dion as part of the new promotional campaign as the airline unveiled new in-flight service products and new aircraft livery. "You and I", the theme song sung by Dion, was written by advertising executives working for Air Canada.Alberts, Sheldon. "A Canadian liftoff; Dion 'flattered' her Air Canada ad chosen as Clinton's campaign song." ''National Post''. June 20, 2007. pg A3. In 2003, Dion signed a deal with Coty to release ''Celine Dion Parfums''.Davis, Mari (2003-04-16) "". Fashion Windows. Retrieved 2009-08-12] In April 2009, Dion also released her sixth fragrance, ''Chic''.&mdash; (2009-02-23) "". ''New York Magazine''. Retrieved 2009-08-12 Since its creation in 2003, ''Celine Dion Parfums'' have made over $500 million in retail sales.. celinedion.com. Retrieved 2008-04-09.

Dion has actively supported many charity organizations worldwide. She has promoted the Canadian Cystic Fibrosis Foundation (CCFF) since 1982 and became the foundation's National Celebrity Patron in 1993.McLellan, Stephanie Simpson. "Celebrating the Mother-Child Bond." ''Today's Parent'', p. 32. May 1, 2004. She has an emotional attachment to the foundation; her niece Karine succumbed to the disease at the age of sixteen. In 2003, Dion joined a number of other celebrities, athletes and politicians, including Josh Groban and Yolanda Adams, to support "World Children's Day", a global fundraising effort sponsored by McDonald's. The effort raised money from more than 100 countries and benefited many orphanages and children's health organizations. Dion has also been a major supporter of the T.J. Martell Foundation, the Diana Princess of Wales Memorial Fund, and many health and education campaigns. She also donated $1 million to the victims of Hurricane Katrina, and held a fund-raising event for the victims of the 2004 Asian Tsunami, raising more than $1 million.  After the 2008 Sichuan earthquake, Celine Dion donated $100,000 to China Children & Teenagers' Fund and sent a letter to show her consolation and support.Celine Dion . Retrieved 2009-10-15

In January 2004, Celine Dion received a star on the Hollywood Walk of Fame.&mdash; (2004-01-08) "". ''CBConline''. Retrieved 2009-10-15 She dedicated her star to her father, who died the month prior. In 2007, Celine Dion was ranked by ''Forbes Magazine'' as the 5th richest woman in entertainment with an estimated net worth of US$250 million. She also received France's highest award, the Légion d'honneur, in May 2008. In August 2008, she received an honorary doctorate in music from the Université Laval in Quebec City.. Canada.com. Retrieved on September 7, 2008
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="292763bc1d76ce50566ff61d3795ce51" name="Star_Celine" sectnum="3#1">../img/292763bc1d76ce50566ff61d3795ce51.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>