<document id="30a1a549da537191bea69768396b7621-1.6" name="Celine_Dion" cat="20">
<text>
Dion's aptly titled ''A New Day Has Come'', released in March 2002, ended her three-year break from the music industry. The album was Dion's most personal yet, and established a more mature side of Dion with the songs "A New Day Has Come", "I'm Alive", and "Goodbye's (The Saddest Word)", a change that resulted from her new-found maternal responsibilities, because, in her own words, "becoming a mother makes you a grown-up." She stated, "''A New Day Has Come'', for Rene, for me, is the baby. It has everything to do with the baby...That song "A New Day Has Come" represents very well the mood I'm feeling right now. It represents the whole album."Celine Dion. "Interview with Celine Dion." Peter Nansbridge. ''The National.'' With Alison Smith. CBC-TV''. March 28, 2002. Transcript. ''A New Day Has Come'' debuted at number one on the Billboard 200 &mdash; Dion's firstBasham, David. (2002-04-05). . Retrieved 2009-10-14&mdash; and was eventually certified 3x Platinum in the U.S.. ''Billboard Magazine''. Retrieved 2008-12-30. 

While the album was commercially successful, critical reviews suggested that it was "forgettable" and the lyrics were "lifeless".Tyrangiel, Josh. "Heart, No Soul." ''Time''; Canadian edition. April 8, 2002. pg. 61 Both Rob Sheffield of ''Rolling Stone'' magazine, and Ken Tucker of ''Entertainment Weekly'', stated that Dion's music had not matured during her break, and classed her music as trite and mediocre.. "Album Review: ''A New Day Has Come''." March 22, 2002. Retrieved May 17, 2007. Sal Cinquemani of ''Slant'' magazine called the album "a lengthy collection of drippy, gooey pop fluffer-nutter." The first single off the album, ''A New Day Has Come'' peaked at #22 on the Billboard Hot 100 charts, being an airplay-only release. On the Hot Adult Contemporary Tracks, however the song spent 21 consecutive weeks at number 1, breaking the record for the longest span at the top."". ''yahoo.com''. Retrieved 2009-10-14. The previous record holders were Phil Collins' ''You'll Be in My Heart'' and Dion's own ''Because You Loved Me,'' both of which lasted nineteen weeks at number 1. During 2002, she performed for many benefit concerts, the famous VH1 Divas Live, a concert to benefit the VH1 Save The Music Foundation, alongside Cher, Anastacia, Dixie Chicks, Mary J. Blige, Whitney Houston, Cyndi Lauper, and Stevie Nicks.

Drawing inspiration from personal experiences, Dion released ''One Heart'' (2003), an album that represented her appreciation for life.Flick, Larry. ''One Heart''. Billboard'' magazine. New York: March 29, 2003. Vol.115, Iss. 13; pg. 30, 1 pgs The album largely consisted of dance music—a deviation from the soaring, melodramatic ballads, for which she had once been given mixed reception. Although the album achieved moderate success, ''One Heart'' was met with mixed criticism, and words such as "predictable" and "banal" appeared even in the most lenient reviews.Durchholz, Daniel. ''One Heart:Céline's a Diva Who Still Goes On and On''. ''St.Louis Post'' - Dispatch. St. Louis, Mo.: April 24, 2003. pg. F.3 A cover of the 1989 Cyndi Lauper hit "I Drove All Night", released to launch her new advertising campaign with Chrysler,Stein, Jason. "Celine Dion sings flat for Chrysler." ''Automotive News''. November 24, 2003. Volume 78. incorporated dance-pop and rock and roll. The advertising deal itself, however was met with mixed criticism, with some stating that Dion was trying to please her sponsors.Murray, Sonia. ''Céline Dion's latest takes easy, well-worn route''. The Atlanta Journal–Constitution. Atlanta, Georgia: March 25, 2003. pg. C.1. However, people like Bonita Stewart, who was the director of Chrysler Group Marketing Communications stated that "Chrysler was taken by how her appeal crossed ethnic lines." She also added, "She brings sophistication, refinement, romance and passion to the brand."Kiley, David. (2003-6-8) "". ''USA Today''. Retrieved 2009-10-14.

After ''One Heart'', Dion released her next English Language studio album, ''Miracle'' (2004). ''Miracle'' was a multimedia project conceived by Dion and photographer Anne Geddes, and had a theme centering on babies and motherhood. The album was filled with lullabies and other songs of maternal love and inspiration, the two most popular being covers of Louis Armstrong's "What a Wonderful World" and John Lennon's "Beautiful Boy". The reviews for ''Miracle'' were mixed.. Allmusic. Retrieved 2009-10-14 Stephen Thomas Erlewine of Allmusic.com gave the album three of out five stars, stating, "The worst you can say about the record is that there are no surprises, but the audience for this record doesn't want surprises; they want comfort, whether it arrives in polished music or artsy photos of newborns, and Miracle provides both, which makes it appealing for those expectant or new mothers in Dion's audience.Allmusic Chuck Taylor of ''Billboard'' magazine wrote that the single "Beautiful Boy" was "an unexpected gem" and called Dion "a timeless, enormously versatile artist",Taylor, Chuck. ''Céline Dion: "Beautiful Boy"''. ''Billboard''. New York: October 16, 2004. Vol.116, Iss. 42; pg. 33, 1 pgs Chuck Arnold of ''People'' Magazine, however, labeled the album as excessively sentimental,Arnold, Chuck. "Review: Celine Dion, Miracle." ''People Magazine.'' November 22, 2004. pg, 48. while Nancy Miller of ''Entertainment Weekly'' opined that "the whole earth-mama act is just opportunism, reborn". ''Miracle'' debuted at number four on the ''Billboard'' 200 chart and number one in Canada , and was eventually certified platinum by the RIAA.

The Francophone album ''1 fille & 4 types'' (''1 Girl & 4 Guys'', 2003), fared better than her first two comebacks, and showed Dion trying to distance herself from the "diva" image. She recruited Jean-Jacques Goldman, Gildas Arzel, Eric Benzi, and Jacques Veneruso, with whom she had previously worked on two of her best selling French albums ''S'il suffisait d'aimer'' and ''D'eux''. Labeled "the album of pleasure" by Dion herself, the cover showed Dion in a simple and relaxed manner, contrary to the choreographed poses usually found on her album covers. The album achieved widespread commercial success in France, Canada, and Belgium where it reached No. 1. In France, the album debuted at number one and was later certified 2x platinum after selling over 700,000 copies. Reviewer Stephen Erlwine of ''Allmusic'' wrote that Dion was "getting back to pop basics and performing at a level unheard in a while."

Though her albums were commercially successful, they did not achieve the sales or the reception of her previous works. Albums like ''The Collector's Series, Volume One'' (2000), and ''One Heart'' (2003) did not perform as well critically.. Her songs received less airplay as radio became less embracing of balladeers like Dion, Carey, and Houston, and was focused on more up-tempo, Urban/Hip-hop songs.Gardner, Elysa. . ''USA Today''. November 28, 2002. Retrieved August 19, 2005. However, by 2004, Dion had accumulated sales of more than 175 million albums worldwide, and received the Chopard Diamond Award from the World Music Awards for her achievements.Canadian Press. (2004-09-14) "". ''CTV News''. Retrieved 2009-10-14 According to the official World Music Awards website, the award is rare; it's not even "presented every year" and an artist can only be presented with the award for selling "over 100 million albums during their career.". ''World Music Awards''. Retrieved July 30, 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bebb650b47ac034955bd8f1c099f5b8b" name="Céline_Dion-AFR" sectnum="1.6#1">../img/bebb650b47ac034955bd8f1c099f5b8b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>