<document id="30ad99bdc962780e9fab9002f9a93241-1" name="S._A._Andrée's_Arctic_balloon_expedition_of_1897" cat="14">
<text>
The second half of the 19th century has often been called the Heroic Age of polar exploration.For instance, in the title of John Maxtone-Graham's popularized narrative ''Safe Return Doubtful: The Heroic Age of Polar Exploration'', which has a chapter on the Andrée expedition. The inhospitable and dangerous Arctic and Antarctic regions spoke powerfully to the imagination of the age, not as lands with their own ecologies and cultures, but as challenges to technological ingenuity and manly daring.

The Swede Salomon August Andrée shared these enthusiasms, and proposed a plan for letting the wind propel a hydrogen balloon from Svalbard across the Arctic Sea to the Bering Strait, to fetch up in Alaska, Canada, or Russia, and passing near or even right over the North Pole on the way. Andrée was an engineer at the patent office in Stockholm, with a passion for ballooning. He bought his own balloon, the ''Svea'', in 1893 and made nine journeys with it, starting from Gothenburg or Stockholm and travelling a combined distance of 1,500 kilometers (900 miles).The most complete account of the ''Svea'' voyages is at . In the prevailing westerly winds, the ''Svea'' flights had a strong tendency to carry him uncontrollably out to the Baltic Sea and drag his basket perilously along the surface of the water and/or slam it into one of the many rocky islets in the Stockholm archipelago (see artist's impression, right). On one occasion he was blown clear across the Baltic to Finland. His longest trip was due east from Gothenburg, across the breadth of Sweden and out over the Baltic to Gotland. Even though he actually saw a lighthouse and heard breakers off Öland, he remained convinced that he was travelling over land and merely seeing lakes.

During a couple of the ''Svea'' flights, Andrée tested and tried out the drag-rope steering technique that he had invented and wanted to use on his projected North Pole expedition. Drag ropes, which hang from the balloon basket and drag part of their length on the ground, are designed to counteract the tendency of lighter-than-air craft to travel at the same speed as the wind, a situation that makes steering by sails impossible. The friction of the ropes was intended to slow the balloon to the point where the sails would have an effect (beyond that of making the balloon rotate on its axis). Andrée claimed that, with the drag rope/sails steering, his ''Svea'' had essentially become a dirigible, but this notion is rejected by modern balloonists. The Swedish Ballooning Association ascribes Andrée's conviction entirely to wishful thinking, capricious winds, and the fact that much of the time Andrée was inside clouds and had little idea where he was or which way he was moving.. Moreover, his drag ropes would persistently snap, fall off, become entangled with each other, or get stuck to the ground, which could result in pulling the often low-flying balloon down into a dangerous bounce. No modern Andrée researcher has expressed any faith in drag ropes as a balloon steering technique.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="386938a1b8c457b45f08cbab1c0d09b7" name="Andree.Svea" sectnum="1#1">../img/386938a1b8c457b45f08cbab1c0d09b7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>