<document id="31ba7682b7bbc35134b31c697db33ece-8" name="Darjeeling" cat="11">
<text>
Darjeeling urban agglomeration (which includes Pattabong Tea Garden), with an area of 12.77 km² (4.93 mi²) has a population of 109,163, while the municipal area has a population of 107,530. The town has an additional average diurnal floating population of 20,500 &ndash; 30,000, mainly consisting of the tourists. The population density of the municipal area is 10,173 per km².  The sex ratio is 1,017 females per 1,000 males &mdash; which is higher than the national average. The women make a significant contribution as earning members of households and the workforce.A consequence of heavy immigration. The major religion is Hinduism, followed by Buddhism. Christians and Muslims form sizable minorities. The population's ethnic composition is closely linked with that of Bengal,Nepal,Bhutan and Sikkim. The majority of the populace is of ethnic Nepali background. Indigenous ethnic groups include the Tamangs, Lepchas, Bhutias, Sherpas, Rais, Yamloos, Damais, Kamais, Newars and Limbus. Other communities that inhabit Darjeeling include the Marwaris, Anglo-Indians, Chinese, Biharis,Tibetans and Bengali . The most commonly spoken language is Nepali,Hindi and English are also used.

Darjeeling has seen significant growth in its population during the last century, especially since the 1970s. Annual growth rates reached as high as 45% in the 1990s, far above the national, state, and district averages. Now available in the Internet Archive in this  (accessed on 7 June 2006) The colonial town had been designed for a mere population of 10,000, and subsequent growth has created extensive infrastructual and environmental problems. The region is relatively new in geological terms and unstable in nature, suffering from a host of environmental problems. Environmental degradation, including  denudation of the surrounding hills has adversely affected Darjeeling's appeal as a tourist destination.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="afe2b4a63afd78440a69ec9d08c4b8e1" name="Darjeelinghillhouses" sectnum="8#1">../img/afe2b4a63afd78440a69ec9d08c4b8e1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>