<document id="31ed719daa37b297341a98fdf3bf31ae-2.2" name="Battle_of_Vimy_Ridge" cat="29">
<text>
In January 1917, three Canadian Corps officers accompanied other British and Dominion officers attending a series of lectures hosted by the French Army regarding their experiences during the Battle of Verdun. The French counter offensive devised by General Robert Nivelle was one of the limited Allied successes of 1916.  Following extensive rehearsal, eight French divisions assaulted German positions in two waves along a  front. Supported by exceedingly strong artillery, the French recovered lost ground and inflicted heavy casualties on five German divisions.Nicholson p. 227


On their return, the Canadian Corps staff officers produced a tactical analysis of the Verdun battles and delivered a series of corps and divisional-level lectures to promote the primacy of artillery and stress the importance of harassing fire and company and platoon flexibility. The report of 1st Canadian Division commander Arthur Currie in particular highlighted lessons he believed the Canadian Corps could learn from the experiences of the French.Humphries p. 67 The assault plan ultimately drafted for the assault on Vimy Ridge drew heavily on the experiences and tactical analysis of the officers who attended the Verdun lectures. First Army commander General Henry Horne approved the plan on 5 March 1917.

The plan divided the Canadian Corps advance into four coloured objective lines. The attack would be made on a front of , the centre being opposite the village of Vimy, which lay to the east side of the ridge. The Black Line, the first objective, involved the seizure of the German forward defensive line.Granatstein p. 113 The final objective of the northern flank was the Red Line, which involved the taking of the highest point on the ridge, the fortified knoll known as "The Pimple" (), the Folie Farm, the Zwischen-Stellung trench and the hamlet of Les Tilleuls. The southern two divisions had to achieve two additional objectives: the Blue Line encompassing the town of Thélus and the woods outside the town of Vimy, and the Brown Line, which involved capturing the Zwölfer-Graben trench and the German second line.Nicholson p. 254 The infantry would proceed close behind a creeping barrage placed down by light field guns, advancing in timed  increments. The medium and heavy howitzers would establish a series of standing barrages further ahead of the infantry against known defensive systems.Nicholson p. 249

The plan called for units to leapfrog over one another as the advance progressed in order to maintain momentum during the attack. The initial wave would capture and consolidate the Black Line and then push forward to the Red Line. The barrage would pause, to enable reserve units to move up, and then move forward with the units pushing beyond the Red Line to the Blue Line. Once the corps secured the Blue Line, advancing units would once again leapfrog established ones and capture of the Brown Line. Conducted properly, the plan would leave the Germans forces little time to exit the security of their deep dugouts and defend their positions against the infantry advance.Turner p. 38 If the corps maintained its schedule, the troops would advance as much as  and have the majority of the ridge under control by 1:00 pm of the first day.Nicholson p. 248
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0a86ad019a196fe01df703e5db3ceef0" name="Plan_of_Attack_Vimy_Ridge" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/0a86ad019a196fe01df703e5db3ceef0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>