<document id="31ed719daa37b297341a98fdf3bf31ae-3.9" name="Battle_of_Vimy_Ridge" cat="29">
<text>
German Sixth Army commander General Ludwig von Falkenhausen was responsible for the Cambrai–Lille sector and commanded 20 divisions (plus reserves).Nicholson p. 246 Vimy Ridge itself was principally defended by the ad hoc  formation based under I Bavarian Reserve Corps commander  Karl Ritter von Fasbender.Williams p. 149 However, a division of , under VIII Reserve Corps General Georg Karl Wichura, was  involved in the frontline defence along the northernmost portion of the ridge.Godefroy (2007b) pp. 228&ndash;229

Three divisions were ultimately responsible for manning the frontline defences opposite the Canadian Corps. The 16th Bavarian Infantry Division was located opposite the town of Souchez and responsible for the defence of the northernmost section of the ridge. The division was created in January 1917 through the amalgamation of existing Bavarian formations and had so far only opposed the Canadian Corps. The 79th Reserve Division was responsible for the defence of the vast central section including the highest point of the ridge, Hill 145.Hopkins p. 157 The 79th Reserve Division fought for two years on the Eastern Front before being transferred to the Vimy sector at the end of February 1917. The 1st Bavarian Reserve Division had been in the Arras area since October 1914 and was holding the towns of Thélus, Bailleul and the southern slope of the ridge.

Canadian Corps commander Lieutenant-General Sir Julian Byng commanded four attacking divisions, one division of reserves and numerous support units. He was supported to the north by the 24th British Division of I Corps, which advanced north of the Souchez river and by the advancing XVII Corps to the south. The 4th Canadian Division was responsible for the northern portion of the advance that included the capture of the highest point of the ridge followed by the heavily defended "Pimple" just west of the town of Givenchy-en-Gohelle. The 3rd Canadian Division was responsible for the narrow central section of the ridge, including the capture of La Folie Farm. The 2nd Canadian Division, which later included an additional brigade from the 5th British Division, was directly south of 3rd Canadian Division and entrusted with the capture of the town of Thélus. The 1st Canadian Division was responsible for the broad southern sector of the corps advance and expected to make the greatest advance in terms distance. Byng  planned for a healthy reserve for contingencies that included the relief of forward troops, help in consolidating positions and aiding the 4th Canadian Division with the capture of the "Pimple". As a result, the 9th Canadian Brigade, 15th British Brigade and 95th British Brigade were kept in corps-level reserve.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bb41253b451677edf8e79c33e9c68ff9" name="Defender_and_Attackers_-_Vimy_Ridge" sectnum="3.9#1">../img/bb41253b451677edf8e79c33e9c68ff9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>