<document id="31ed719daa37b297341a98fdf3bf31ae-2.4" name="Battle_of_Vimy_Ridge" cat="29">
<text>
The British made twenty-four brigade artillery groups consisting of four hundred eighty 18 pounder field guns, one hundred thirty-eight 4.5 inch howitzers, ninety-six 2 inch trench mortars, twenty-four 9.45 inch mortars, supported by 245 corps-level siege guns and heavy mortars available to the Canadian Corps.Nicholson p. 225Cook (2007) p. 113 This firepower gave a density of one heavy gun for every  and one field gun for every  of Canadian Corps frontage, representing a considerable average increase, including three times the heavy guns, over the distribution of artillery at the Battle of the Somme a year earlier.Sheffield pp. 191, 194 Brigadier-General Edward Morrison developed and subsequently issued a 35 page multi-phased fire support plan called ''Canadian Corps Artillery Instruction No. 1 for the Capture of Vimy Ridge'' to support the efforts of the infantry.WO 106/399 Canadian Corps Artillery Instruction No. 1 for the Capture of Vimy Ridge (1917) For its operations, the Canadian Corps received three times the artillery normally assigned to a corps for regular operations.Brennan pp. 98&ndash;99 To manage the logistics associated with the increased artillery, Royal Artillery staff officer Major Alan Brooke developed coordinated communication and transport plans to work in conjunction with the complex barrage plans.

A 1.6 million shell allotment allowed the artillery along the Canadian Corps front to maintain a high sustained rate of fire. Improvements in the quality of the shells compared to those used earlier in the war  ensured fewer duds.Sheffield p. 191 The introduction of the instantaneous No. 106 fuse  greatly improved the effectiveness of the artillery since this fuse burst reliably with the slightest of contact, unlike older timed fuses, making it especially effective at cutting barbed wire before the advance.Cook (2007) 113 To maintain communications during the battle, particularly with the artillery, field units laid over  of telegraph and field telephone cabling, normally at a depth of .Turner p. 39 In addition, the corps conducted coordinated counter-battery initiatives before the battle. Utilizing flash spotting, sound ranging and aerial reconnaissance from No. 16 Squadron and  Balloon Company of the Royal Flying Corps in the week before the battle, the counter battery artillery under command of Lieutenant-Colonel Andrew McNaughton fired 125,900 shells, harassing an estimated 83% of the German gun positions.Cook (2007) p. 117
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3afec757470658a84fe7082946982080" name="Vimy_Ridge_1917-barrage_map" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/3afec757470658a84fe7082946982080.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>