<document id="31ed719daa37b297341a98fdf3bf31ae-3.10" name="Battle_of_Vimy_Ridge" cat="29">
<text>
German foreign intelligence gathering, large-scale Allied trench raids and observed troop concentrations west of Arras made it clear to the Germans that a spring offensive near Arras was being planned.Sheldon pp. 229&ndash;237 In February 1917, a German-born Canadian soldier deserted to the German side and helped confirm many of the suspicions held by the Germans, providing them with a great deal of useful information. By March 1917, the German forces were aware that a major attack was imminent and would include operations aimed at capturing Vimy Ridge.Hopkins pp. 157&ndash;158Sheldon p. 251  Ernst August Marx von Bachmeister, commanding the German 79th Reserve Division, reported in late-March that he believed the Canadian Corps was moving into an echelon formation and were preparing for a major attack.Godefroy (2007b) p. 230Sheldon p. 259 The Germans quickly developed plans to launch a pre-emptive operation, following the adage that the best defence is a good offense, intent on capturing the northern section of the Zouave Valley along the northernmost portion of the Canadian front.Sheldon pp. 248&ndash;249The attack was code named Operation Munich Heavy Canadian Corps artillery fire ultimately prevented the Germans from executing their pre-emptive attack.Sheldon p. 263

The preliminary phase of the Canadian Corps artillery bombardment began on 20 March 1917, with a systematic two-week bombardment of German batteries, trenches and strong points.Barris p. 58 The Canadian Corps paid particular attention to eliminating German barbed wire, a task made easier with the introduction of the No. 106 instantaneous fuse. In addition, only half of the available artillery was committed at any one point in time with the intensity of the barrage expressly varied as to confuse the Germans and preserve some level of secrecy. Phase two lasted the entire week beginning 2 April 1917 and employed the entire artillery arsenal at the disposal of the Canadian Corps, massing the equivalent of one heavy gun for every  and one field gun for every . The German soldiers came to refer to the week before the attack as 'the week of suffering'.Nicholson p. 251 By the Germans' own account, their trenches and defensive works were almost completely demolished.Sheldon p. 273 Furthermore, German health and morale suffered from the stress of remaining at the ready for eleven straight days under extremely heavy artillery bombardment.Sheldon pp. 270&ndash;272 Compounding German difficulties was the inability of ration parties to bring food supplies to the front lines. On 3 April, General von Falkenhausen ordered his reserve divisions to prepare to relieve frontline divisions over the course of a long drawn-out defensive battle, in a manner similar to the Battle of the Somme. However, the divisions were kept  from the battlefield to avoid being shelled.Godefroy (2007a) p. 231
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bfd42a5b6315b2462e9f036bbbb595e4" name="Naval_gun_firing_over_Vimy_Ridge" sectnum="3.10#1">../img/bfd42a5b6315b2462e9f036bbbb595e4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>