<document id="320900763d954fed0bd83182584a34b5-5" name="Krill" cat="3">
<text>
Most krill are swarming animals; the sizes and densities of such swarms vary greatly depending on the species and the region. For ''Euphausia superba'', there have been reports of swarms of up to 10,000 to 60,000 individuals per cubic metre. deleted from Wikisource--> Swarming is a defensive mechanism, confusing smaller predators that would like to pick out single individuals. This behavior has given rise to the plural classification, a plague of krill.

Krill typically follow a diurnal vertical migration. They spend the day at greater depths and rise during the night towards the surface. The deeper they go, the more they reduce their activity, apparently to reduce encounters with predators and to conserve energy. Some species (e.g., ''Euphausia superba'', ''E. pacifica'', ''E. hanseni'', ''Pseudeuphausia latifrons'', and ''Thysanoessa spinifera'') also form surface swarms during the day for feeding and reproductive purposes even though such behaviour is dangerous because it makes them extremely vulnerable to predators.


Dense swarms may elicit a feeding frenzy among fish, birds and mammal predators, especially near the surface. When disturbed, a swarm scatters, and some individuals have even been observed to moult instantaneously, leaving the exuvia behind as a decoy.

Krill normally swim at pace of a few centimetres per second (0.2–10 body lengths per second), using their swimmerets for propulsion. Their larger migrations are subject to the currents in the ocean. When in danger, they show an escape reaction called lobstering — flicking their caudal structures, the telson and the uropods, they move backwards through the water relatively quickly, achieving speeds in the range of 10 to 27 body lengths per second, which for large krill such as ''E. superba'' means around . Their swimming performance has led many researchers to classify adult krill as micro-nektonic life-forms, i.e., small animals capable of individual motion against (weak) currents. Larval forms of krill are generally considered zooplankton.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7cf021746cde94f18b3817cec0892c8e" name="Pleopods_euphausia_superba" sectnum="5#1">../img/7cf021746cde94f18b3817cec0892c8e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>