<document id="320900763d954fed0bd83182584a34b5-6" name="Krill" cat="3">
<text>
Krill are an important element of the food chain. Antarctic krill feed directly on phytoplankton, converting the primary production energy into a form suitable for consumption by larger animals that cannot feed directly on the minuscule algae. Some species like the Northern krill have a relatively small filtering basket and actively hunt for copepods and larger zooplankton. Many animals feed on krill, ranging from smaller animals like fish or penguins to larger ones like seals and even baleen whales.

Disturbances of an ecosystem resulting in a decline in the krill population can have far-reaching effects. During a coccolithophore bloom in the Bering Sea in 1998, for instance, the diatom concentration dropped in the affected area. Krill cannot feed on the smaller coccolithophores, and consequently the krill population (mainly ''E. pacifica'') in that region declined sharply. This in turn affected other species: the shearwater population dropped, and the incident was even thought to have been a reason for salmon not returning to the rivers of western Alaska that season.

Other factors besides predation and food availability can influence the mortality rate in krill populations. As temperatures have risen over the past couple decades, Antarctic sea ice has melted. In this way, climate change poses a threat to krill populations as they feed on algae beneath the ice. There are several single-celled endoparasitoidic ciliates of the genus ''Collinia'' that can infect different species of krill and cause massive decline in affected populations. Such diseases have been reported for ''Thysanoessa inermis'' in the Bering Sea and also for ''E. pacifica'', ''Thysanoessa spinifera'', and ''T. gregaria'' off the North American Pacific coast.. See also the base article:  There are also some ectoparasites of the family Dajidae (epicaridean isopods) that afflict krill (and also shrimp and mysids); one such parasite is ''Oculophryxus bicaulis'', which has been found on the krill ''Stylocheiron affine'' and ''S. longicorne''. It attaches itself to the eyestalk of the animal and sucks blood from its head; it is believed that it inhibits the reproduction of its host, as none of the afflicted animals found reached maturity.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fd88f697e57bc541edd5e60ee73acf89" name="Coccolithophore_bloom" sectnum="6#1">../img/fd88f697e57bc541edd5e60ee73acf89.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>