<document id="320900763d954fed0bd83182584a34b5-7" name="Krill" cat="3">
<text>
Krill has been harvested as a food source for humans (''okiami'') and domesticated animals since the 19th century, in Japan maybe even earlier. Large-scale fishing developed only in the late 1960s and early 1970s, and now occurs only in Antarctic waters and in the seas around Japan. Historically, the largest krill fishery nations were Japan and the Soviet Union, or, after the latter's dissolution, Russia and Ukraine. A peak in krill harvest had been reached in 1983 with more than 528,000 tonnes in the Southern Ocean alone (of which the Soviet Union produced 93%). In 1993, two events led to a drastic decline in krill production: first, Russia abandoned its operations, and second, the Commission for the Conservation of Antarctic Marine Living Resources (CCAMLR) defined maximum catch quotas for a sustainable exploitation of Antarctic krill. The annual catch in Antarctic waters seems to have stabilised around 100,000 tonnes of krill, which is roughly one fiftieth of the CCAMLR catch quota. The main limiting factor is probably the high cost associated with Antarctic operations, although there are some political and legal issues as well. The fishery around Japan appears to have saturated at some 70,000 tonnes.

Experimental small-scale harvesting is being carried out in other areas, for example, fishing for ''Euphausia pacifica'' off British Columbia and harvesting ''Meganyctiphanes norvegica'', ''Thysanoessa raschii'' and ''Thysanoessa inermis'' in the Gulf of St. Lawrence. These experimental operations produce only a few hundred tonnes of krill per year. Nicol & Foster consider it unlikely that any large-scale harvesting operations in these areas will be started due to opposition from local fishing industries and conservation groups.

Krill tastes salty and somewhat stronger than shrimp. For mass-consumption and commercially prepared products they must be peeled, because their exoskeleton contains fluorides, which are toxic in high concentrations. Excessive intake of ''okiami'' may cause diarrhea.

Krill oil is said to be a good source of the omega 3 oils DHA and EPA. There is a small but growing market for krill oil as a dietary supplement ingredient. Two clinical trials have been published: Bunea R. Alternative Med Rev 2004;9:420-438 and Deutsch L. J Am Coll Nutr 2007;26:39-48. Tests included lipid lowering, arthritis pain and function, and C-reactive protein.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6de367cac2d22b19723944c7e1080d25" name="Krillmeatkils" sectnum="7#1">../img/6de367cac2d22b19723944c7e1080d25.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>