<document id="325dc920b2a0491e91aba4c256504c4f-3.5" name="Kevin_Pietersen" cat="26">
<text>
In May 2006, Pietersen matched his highest Test score of 158 in the first match against Sri Lanka,McGlashan, Andrew. "", Cricinfo, 2006-05-12. Retrieved on 2007-05-27. and followed it with 142 in the second Test.McGlashan, Andrew. "", Cricinfo, 2006-05-26. Retrieved on 2007-05-27. This took him past the milestone of 1,000 Test runs, in his 12th Test match, and he became the first batsman since Graham Gooch in 1990 to score a century in three successive Test innings on English soil.Kumar, Manish. "", cricketzone.com, 2007-03-08. Retrieved on 2007-05-27. This performance moved Pietersen into the top ten of the ICC cricket ratings, as he was named the England (Test Match) Player of the Series., Cricketarchive. Retrieved 28 May 2007."", BBC Sport, 2006-05-29. Retrieved on 2007-05-27.
On the first day of the third Test against Pakistan, Pietersen reached his fifth Test century with an overnight score of 104. Although Pietersen retired hurt shortly after reaching three figures, due to cramp, he returned to the crease the next morning and went on to top score in England's first innings total of 515 with 135 runs from 169 balls.McGlashan, Andrew. "", Cricinfo, 2006-08-05. Retrieved on 2007-05-27.
 
Pietersen bowled his first delivery in Test match cricket on 4 June, against Sri Lanka., Cricinfo. Retrieved on 2007-05-28. His first Test wicket came against Pakistan later in the summer when Kamran Akmal got a thin edge through to Geraint Jones.McGlashan, Andrew. "", Cricinfo, 2006-07-15. Retrieved on 2007-05-28.

Later in June, Pietersen scored 17 in the Twenty20 International as England lost by 2 runs to Sri Lanka., Cricketarchive, 2006-06-15. Retrieved on 2007-05-28. The twenty over match against Pakistan was no better, Pietersen being bowled by Mohammad Asif for a golden duck as Pakistan helped themselves to a five-wicket victory., Cricketarchive, 2006-08-28. Retrieved on 2007-05-28.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="017803ba7a477526d2db11c71998f127" name="Kevin_pietersen_bowl" sectnum="3.5#1">../img/017803ba7a477526d2db11c71998f127.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>