<document id="327b5e0aa5d999fca176cbc5f2d1cd04-5" name="House_Martin" cat="3">
<text>
The House Martin has a large range, with an estimated global extent of 10 million square kilometres. Its European population is estimated to be 20–48 million individuals. Global population trends have not been quantified, although there is evidence of population fluctuations.  For these reasons, the species is evaluated as "least concern" on the 2007 IUCN Red List, and has no special status under the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (CITES) which regulates international trade in specimens of wild animals and plants. In Europe and Britain however, population numbers indicate a declining trend, and leading conservation groups in Britain have updated the conservations status to amber indicating medium conservation concern there.


This is a species which has greatly benefited historically from forest clearance creating the open habitats it prefers, and from human habitation which have both given it an abundance of safe man-made nest sites. However, populations can fluctuate locally for a number of reasons. New housing has created more nest sites, and clean air legislation has enabled breeding in the centre of major cities like London. The population of House Martins in Sheffield, central UK, has been estimated at 12,353 individuals. doi:10.1111/j.1472-4642.2008.00537.x Conversely, poor weather, poisoning by agricultural pesticides, lack of mud for nest building and competition with House Sparrows can reduce numbers. Widespread declines in House Martin numbers have been reported from central and northern Europe since 1970. As an attractive bird which feeds on flying insects, the House Martin has usually been tolerated by humans when it shares their buildings for nesting, although the accumulation of droppings below breeding birds can be a nuisance leading to some destruction of nests.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f31a9e96f387873af93a3d15b59f16c9" name="Hirundo_rustica_(Adrian_Benko)" sectnum="5#1">../img/f31a9e96f387873af93a3d15b59f16c9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>