<document id="32858813e360308c6fab954ea09c91b8-4.1" name="Soviet_invasion_of_Poland" cat="14">
<text>
Of the 13.5 million civilians living in the newly annexed territories, Poles were the largest single ethnic group; but Belarusians and Ukrainians together made up over 50% of the population. The annexation did not give the Soviet Union control of all the areas where Belarusians or Ukrainians lived, some of which fell west of the new German–Soviet border. Nonetheless, it united the vast majority of the two peoples within the expanded Soviet Belorussian and Ukrainian republics.

On 26 October 1939, "elections" to Belorussian and Ukrainian assemblies were held,See Elections to the People's Assemblies of Western Ukraine and Western Belarus to give the annexation an appearance of validity. The Belarusians and Ukrainians in Poland had been increasingly alienated by the Polonization policies of the Polish government and its repression of their separatist movements, so they felt little loyalty towards the Polish state.Norman Davies, ''Boże Igrzysko'' (God's Playground), vol 2, pp. 512–513. Not all Belarusians and Ukrainians, however, trusted the Soviet regime, which was responsible for the Ukrainian Famine of 1932–33. In practice, the poor generally welcomed the Soviets, and the elites tended to join the opposition, despite supporting the reunification itself. Marek Wierzbicki, . "Białoruskie Zeszyty Historyczne", Biełaruski histaryczny zbornik, 20 (2003), p. 186-188. Retrieved 16 July 2007.Andrzej Nowak, , Sarmatian Review, January 1997, Volume XVII, Number 1. Retrieved 16 July 2007.

The Soviets quickly introduced Sovietization policies in Western Belorussia and Western Ukraine, including compulsory collectivization of the whole region. In the process, they ruthlessly broke up political parties and public associations and imprisoned or executed their leaders as "enemies of the people". The Soviet authorities also suppressed the anti-Polish Organization of Ukrainian Nationalists, which had actively resisted the Polish regime since the 1920s; aiming for an independent, undivided Ukrainian state.Miner, pp. 41–2. The unifications of 1939 were nevertheless a decisive event in the history of Ukraine and Belarus, because they produced two republics which eventually achieved independence in 1991 after the fall of the Soviet Union.Wilson, p. 17.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bdc245251cfd7a0b8861610b1f2c8b5d" name="Sssr_polsha_1939_plakat" sectnum="4.1#1">../img/bdc245251cfd7a0b8861610b1f2c8b5d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>