<document id="330a0587022a69563f92be75f2e7515b-5" name="History_of_a_Six_Weeks'_Tour" cat="17">
<text>
''History of a Six Weeks' Tour'' is part of a liberal reaction to recent history: its trajectory begins with a survey of the devastation of the Napoleonic Wars and ends by celebrating the sublime in nature. William Wordsworth’s 1850 ''The Prelude''  and the third canto of Byron’s ''Childe Harold's Pilgrimage'' follow a similar course.Moskal, “Travel writing”, 246. As Moskal explains, "nature is troped as the repository of a sublimity, once incarnated in Napoleon, that will re-emerge in politics".Moskal, “Travel writing, 246. The book is therefore not only a liberal political statement but also a Romantic celebration of nature.Bennett, 28.

The journal begins with, as Moskal describes, a "view of Napoleon’s shattered political power". He had just been exiled to Elba a few months before the Shelleys arrived in Europe. Surveying the devastation caused by the Napoleonic Wars, Mary Shelley worries about how the British will handle Paris and grieves over the "ruin" brought to the small French town of Nogent by the Cossacks. Between the two journeys recorded in the text, Napoleon returned to power in the so-called Hundred Days and was defeated at the Battle of Waterloo in 1815. The four letters from Geneva reflect obliquely on this event. As Moskal argues, "the Shelleys focus on the forms of sublimity and power that outlast Napoleon: the literary genius of Rousseau and the natural sublimity of Lake Geneva and Mont Blanc". Both Shelleys use their works in ''History of a Six Weeks’ Tour'' to assess and evaluate the French Revolution, making it a highly political travel narrative.Bennett, 25. In Letter II, Mary Shelley writes:

Mary Shelley also includes positive portrayals of the French people. As Mary Shelley scholar Betty T. Bennett explains, "politically pointed, these accolades underscore the link between the 1814 defeated enemy of Britain and the pre-Napoleon democratic spirit of the 1789 Revolution, a spirit the Shelleys wished to reactivate".

Lives of people interested Mary Shelley and she recorded them, but she also recorded a great deal of the travellers’ own feelings, suggesting to the reader the appropriate reaction.Nitchie, 38; Bennett, 26.  For example, she wrote of the French town Nogent:
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a3530dafc539bccf814560b6eb6470b8" name="Napoleon4" sectnum="5#1">../img/a3530dafc539bccf814560b6eb6470b8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>