<document id="330a0587022a69563f92be75f2e7515b-6" name="History_of_a_Six_Weeks'_Tour" cat="17">
<text>
''History of a Six Weeks' Tour'' received three major reviews, mostly favourable. However, the book did not sell well. Percy Shelley discovered in April or May 1820 that there were no profits to pay the printer and when Charles Ollier, the co-publisher, went out of business in 1823, his inventory included 92 copies of the work.Moskal, “Introductory note”, 4. Still, Mary Shelley believed the work was successful, and when she proposed another travel narrative, ''Rambles in Germany and Italy'', to publisher Edward Moxon in 1843, she wrote "my 6 weeks tour brought me many compliments". Her comments may have been self-interested, however.

The first review of ''History of a Six Weeks' Tour'' was published by ''The Eclectic Review'' in May 1818, which reviewed the book along with publisher Thomas Hookham's account of a Swiss tour, ''A Walk through Switzerland in September 1816''.Colbert, 25. Although both works share the same fascination with Rousseau and his liberal ideas, only Hookham is attacked; as scholar Benjamin Colbert explains, "Shelley tends to remain on more neutral territory", such as the cult of sensibility and the novel ''Julie''. However, the reviewer questions the authenticity of the work: "To us...the value of the book is considerably lessened by a strong suspicion that the dramatis personae are fictitious, and that the little adventures introduced for the purpose of giving life and interest to the narration, are the mere invention of the Author."Qtd. in Colbert, 26. He identifies passages that remind him of similar travel narratives by Patrick Brydone, Ann Radcliffe, and John Carr, effectively identifying the generic tradition in which the Shelleys were writing.Colbert, 26.

The second and most positive review was published by ''Blackwood’s Edinburgh Magazine'' in July 1818.Colbert, 27. The reviewer was most impressed with the journal section, particularly its informality and concision: "the perusal of it rather produces the same effect as a smart walk before breakfast, in company with a lively friend who hates long stories".Qtd. in Colbert, 28. Covertly comparing the work to bluestocking Lady Morgan’s recent ''France'' (1817), the reviewer found the female writer of ''History of a Six Weeks' Tour'' much more favourable: "The writer of this little volume, too, is a Lady, and writes like one, with ease, gracefulness, and vivacity. Above all, there is something truly delightful in the colour of her stockings; they are of the purest white, and much more becoming than the brightest blue."Qtd. in Moskal, “Introductory note”, 4. The ''Monthly Review'' published a short review in January 1819; they found the first journey “hurried” but the second one better described.Colbert, 28.

For most of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, Mary Shelley was known as the author of ''Frankenstein'' and the wife of famous Romantic poet Percy Bysshe Shelley. It was not until the 1970s, with the rise of feminist literary criticism, that scholars began to pay attention to her other works. In fact, with the exception of ''Frankenstein'' and ''The Last Man'',  until the 1990s almost all of Mary Shelley's writings had gone out of print or only been available in expensive, scholarly editions."Introduction", ''The Other Mary Shelley'', 7. It was not until the publication of scholarship by Mary Poovey and Anne K. Mellor in the 1980s that Mary Shelley's "other" works—her short stories, essays, reviews, dramas, biographies, travel narratives, and other novels—began to be recognised as literary achievements."Introduction", ''The Other Mary Shelley'', 3–9.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d45dfad7db2dd0bdb25f5404b2935323" name="LadyMorgan" sectnum="6#1">../img/d45dfad7db2dd0bdb25f5404b2935323.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>