<document id="33c2f77203851dab64c1554433ac09a9-2.2" name="Catherine_de'_Medici's_building_projects" cat="1">
<text>
Several of the monuments built for the Valois chapel have survived. These include the tomb of Catherine and Henry—in Zerner's view, "the last and most brilliant of the royal tombs of the Renaissance".Zerner, 379. Primaticcio himself designed its structure, which eliminated the traditional bas-reliefs and kept ornamentation to a minimum. The sculptor Germain Pilon, who had provided statues for the tomb of Francis I, carved the tomb’s two sets of effigies, which represented death below and eternal life above."With the rise of naturalistic representations beginning in the fifteenth century, the afterlife was imagined as an exact replica of earthly existence. As a result, the tombs of the mighty often insinuated an ambiguous conflation of the glorious Life Eternal with a glorification of their earthly lives." Zerner, 380. The king and queen, cast in bronze, kneel in prayer (''priants'') on a marble canopy supported by twelve marble columns. Their poses echo those on the nearby tombs of Louis XII and Francis I. Pilon’s feel for the material, however, invests his statues with a greater sense of movement.Blunt, ''Art and Architecture in France'', 94. Blunt believes that Benvenuto Cellini's Fontainebleau ''nymph'' may have influenced their carving. 

The cadavers (''gisants'') of the king and queen lie in the mortuary chamber below.Zerner 383–84. Girolamo della Robbia was originally commissioned to carve the queen’s corpse, but his effort, in which Catherine looks emaciated, was left unfinished in 1566 and is now in the Louvre. Catherine's corpse suggests sleep rather than death, while Henry is posed strikingly, with his head thrown back.Zerner, 379; Blunt, ''Art and Architecture in France'', 95. From 1583, Pilon also sculpted two later ''gisants'' of Catherine and Henry wearing their crowns and coronation robes.Zerner suggests that these two, apparently superfluous, recumbent effigies, as rigid as those from the thirteenth century, might have been a "call to order". In the context of the wars of religion, they may have represented a pulling back from the sensuality of the tomb, which "was bound to appear somewhat pagan". Zerner, 382–83. In this case, he portrays Catherine realistically, with a double chin. These two statues were intended to flank the altar of the chapel.Knecht, 226–27. Pilon's four bronze statues of the cardinal virtues stand at the corners of the tomb. Pilon also carved the reliefs round the base that recall Bontemps' work on the monument for the heart of Francis I.Blunt, ''Art and Architecture in France'', 94.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4be18e8b1e646b95e593f9b0a1658d50" name="Basilica_di_saint_Denis_tomba_enrico_II_e_caterina_de'_Medici_03" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/4be18e8b1e646b95e593f9b0a1658d50.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>