<document id="33e0307938bc295eb72af56bae3270cf-6" name="Mendip_Hills" cat="11">
<text>
The western end of the Mendip Hills have, since 1972, been designated an Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty (AONB) under the National Parks and Access to the Countryside Act 1949. The Mendip Society, which was formed in 1965, works to raise awareness of this designation and protect the area. The society now has 700 members and runs a programme of guided walks and educational presentations. The society also has a small grants fund to assist communities with the conservation and enhancement of the landscape and to encourage its enjoyment and celebration.

As they share similar landscape quality, AONBs may be compared to the national parks of England and Wales. AONBs are created under the same legislation as the national parks, the National Parks and Access to the Countryside Act 1949. Unlike AONBs, national parks have their own authorities and have legal power to prevent unsympathetic development. By contrast, there are very limited statutory duties imposed on local authorities within an AONB. However, further regulation and protection of AONBs was added by the Countryside and Rights of Way Act 2000.

In 2009 proposals were being prepared by the Mendip AONB in an attempt to get the Mendips designated as a Geopark which is defined by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) in its ''UNESCO Geopark''s International Network of Geoparks programme as ''A territory encompassing one or more sites of scientific importance, not only for geological reasons but also by virtue of its archaeological, ecological or cultural value.'' 

The Mendip Hills Partnership, which performs an administrative role, includes the five local authorities that cover the AONB, statutory bodies such as the Countryside Agency and English Nature, together with parish councils and other organisations and groups that have an interest in the conservation and care of the area. The Mendip Hills AONB Service is the staff unit of the partnership, and is based at the Charterhouse Centre in the heart of the AONB. The AONB Service consists of six staff, a manager, development officer, planning liaison officer, two wardens and a support officer. They are supported by 50 volunteer rangers who give approximately 3,000 volunteer hours each year.
In 2005 a proposal was submitted to the Countryside Agency to extend the Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty to Steep Holm and Brean Down in the west and towards Frome in the east.

Many of the villages on the Mendips have their own parish councils, which have some responsibility for local issues. They elect councillors to district councils, such as Mendip or Sedgemoor, to Somerset County Council, and to unitary authorities, such as Bath and North East Somerset. Each of the villages is also part of a parliamentary constituency: Wells, Weston-super-Mare, or Wansdyke (which will become North East Somerset). The area is also part of the South West England European Parliament consituency. Avon and Somerset Constabulary provides police services to the area.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4333738c89caab3def0cbf240bf9dee9" name="Mendiphillsaonb3" sectnum="6#1">../img/4333738c89caab3def0cbf240bf9dee9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>