<document id="33e0307938bc295eb72af56bae3270cf-8" name="Mendip_Hills" cat="11">
<text>
In the middle of the first century, ancient tracks across the hills were superseded by the Roman Fosse Way, from Bath to Ilchester, a branch of which served the Charterhouse lead mines.  Stratton-on-the-Fosse and Lydford-on-Fosse, two villages of the Mendips, reflect the arrival of this new road.  Much of the high plateau, however, remained uncultivated and unenclosed until the eighteenth century, resulting in many roads remaining as narrow winding lanes between high banks and hedges or stone walls.  Where the tracks had their origins as drovers roads, they typically become open roads with wide verges. The roads tend to follow the line of gorges and valleys, as at Cheddar Gorge.

More major roads often started as turnpikes in the 16th century and are found avoiding the highest areas. To the north of the western part of the Mendips, the A368 separates the hills from the Chew Valley, while on the southern edge the A371 similarly runs along the bottom of the scarp slope between the hills and the Somerset Levels. The western end of the hills is crossed by the M5 motorway and A38. Further east, and running almost north to south, are the A37 and A39.

During the late nineteenth and early twentieth century the Bristol and North Somerset Railway ran roughly parallel to the A37.  Further south and west, the Cheddar Valley line and Wrington Vale Light Railway, branches of the Bristol and Exeter Railway, served towns and villages from Cheddar to Wells. In the east, the Somerset and Dorset Joint Railway ran south from Bath into Dorset, and also served Wells. These have all now closed, although Mendip Rail has freight lines to carry limestone from the quarries of the Mendip Hills. The Somerset Coal Canal reached some of the pits of the Somerset coalfield in the eastern end of the Mendips.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="60241d3863b2a979066ccf5f09c95d4a" name="Pensfordviaduct" sectnum="8#1">../img/60241d3863b2a979066ccf5f09c95d4a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>