<document id="33e7dfcc437ce3c9f97af96223c409b7-2.2" name="Smallville_(season_1)" cat="19">
<text>
Production was set up in Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada, because the creators were looking for a "Middle America landscape", and Vancouver was a good substitute for Kansas.Simpson, Paul, pp.8–17 David Nutter, the director of the pilot, was given 16 days for main unit filming, twice that of the normal timeframe. Despite the extended schedule, it was still a short amount of time, and he shot the pilot primarily from storyboards created by Adrien Van Viersen.Simpson, Paul, pp.20–23

Millar developed most of the look for ''Smallville'' with the idea that Smallville should be the epitome of "Smalltown, USA". Millar's design required existing buildings to be painted, built, and remodeled. The Kent farm is the home of the Andalini family, and their barn was used for the pilot before a new barn was built. The new barn was one of the major additions to the sets of the episode "Metamorphosis". Production designer Doug Higgins and his crew built a fully functioning, three-story barn for the Kent farm on a converted soundstage in Burnaby. For the pilot, the crew built only a loft, with a set of stairs leading up to it, inside the existing barn on the Andalini's property.Simpson, Paul, pp.24–27 To resemble the Andalini's barn as closely as possible, Higgins had his crew locate 100-year-old wood to match the look of the Andalini's barn. The episode "Hourglass" called for several scenes to take place at the White House. Instead of building their own set, the ''Smallville'' producers called John Wells, producer of the political drama television series ''The West Wing'', and obtained permission to use the ''West Wing'' set to film the vision of Lex's future.

When the ''Smallville'' crew was not filming on one of the constructed sets, or on a sound stage, they were shooting on location at the surrounding Vancouver sites. During the filming of "Metamorphosis", Vancouver was holding a farmers' market, which proved beneficial to the ''Smallville'' crew, as "Metamorphosis" called for a similar event to take place in the episode. The market was on the verge of ending, so the filmmakers shot what wide-angle scenes they could at the time, and filmed a close up conversation between Whitney and Clark at the Andalini's farm, weeks after the initial market shooting. Other filming locations include Vancouver's Pacific National Exhibition and Burnaby's Swangard Stadium. The Pacific National Exhibit provided a storage silo for a scene in "Hourglass", which involved Harry Bollston (Eric Christian Olsen) attacking Martha Kent (O'Toole) in the Kents' corn silo. "Hothead" director Greg Beeman, who had previously worked with Gough and Millar on ''The Strip'' and ''Martial Law'', used Swangard Stadium, as a substitution for Smallville High Stadium, for the opening football scene that took place at night.Simpson, Paul, pp.28–31

When filming fell behind schedule, another director came in to assist the main unit director in finishing the episode. Greg Beeman assisted director Chris Long for the two "visceral visions of the future" that appeared in the episode "Hourglass". "Jitters" was an episode with so many changes that its initial scheduling as the second episode of the season was pushed back to the eighth spot. By the time filming for "Jitters" was completed, three directors had worked on the project: Greg Beeman, Phil Sgriccia, and Michael Watkins; however, Watkins was given sole directing credit for the episode.Simpson, Paul, pp.48–51
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="895d1fae11f1178102f53307ba17a614" name="Swangard_stadium_Burnaby" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/895d1fae11f1178102f53307ba17a614.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>