<document id="34667bafda20d49f51b2d910604d324c-3.3" name="Lake_Burley_Griffin" cat="11">
<text>
The excavation of Lake Burley Griffin began in 1960 with the clearing of vegetation from the floodplain of the Molonglo River. The trees on the golf course and along the river were pulled up, along with the various sports grounds and houses.Sparke, pp. 136–138.

During major earthworks, at least  of topsoil was excavated.Sparke, p. 138. It was collected for use at several public parks and gardens, including the future Commonwealth Park on the northern shore. It was also used to create the six artificial islands including Springbank Island. The island was named after the former Springbank Farm that was situated there. Land excavated to create a sailing course at Yarralumla was used for the thematically named Spinnaker Island to its north, while excavated stone was moved beside the Kings Avenue Bridge at the eastern edge of the central basin from Aspen Island.Andrews, p. 94.

Care was taken to excavate the entire lake floor to a depth of at least  to provide sufficient clearance for boat keels. Another reason given for this was that mosquitoes would not breed nor would weeds grow at such a depth. A soil conservation program was launched in the catchment and bed load traps were installed to minimise loss of earth. The traps have been used as a source of sand and gravel for building sites. Drainage blankets were used to prevent the loss of groundwater beneath the lake.

During the following phase of work, four types of lake margin were constructed. On the southern side of the Central Basin, low reinforced concrete retaining walls were used, while on the eastern side, grouted rock wall can be seen near Commonwealth Park, as well as much of the East Basin. Sand and gravel beaches were built to cater for lakeside recreational pursuits. These are mostly prevalent on the western half of the lake complex. Rocky outcrops, steeply sloping stable shores with water vegetation such as bullrushes were also used. This treatment is evident in the West Lake in Yarralumla. William Holford and Partners were responsible for the foreshore landscaping, and over 55,000 trees were planted in accordance with a detailed scheme.Minty, p. 809. Eucalypts were preferred so as to maintain the natural colour of the city landscape.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="653cc1875e741a88e820c1b061ac7858" name="Kings_ave_bridge" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/653cc1875e741a88e820c1b061ac7858.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>