<document id="3468a166bbcc1993a9b90a60c0024f2c-3" name="Battle_of_Tory_Island" cat="29">
<text>
During the night, Bompart attempted to decoy the British by sending the schooner ''Biche'' with orders for the frigate ''Résolue'', commanding Captain Jean-Pierre Bargeau to beach his ship and fire flares in the hope of distracting Warren from his pursuit. For unknown reasons this order was never carried out, and in the morning Warren was still hard behind Bompart, whose ships were now sailing in two uneven lines.James, p. 128 Warren's force was even more dispersed, with HMS ''Robust'' and HMS ''Magnanime''  astern of the French and gaining fast, ''Amelia'' and ''Melampus'' shortly behind them and flagship HMS ''Canada'' with HMS ''Foudroyant''  from the enemy. The other British ships were scattered throughout this formation except ''Anson'', which was wallowing to the rear, far out of sight.

Realising that he could not escape and would have to fight his way past the British, Bompart formed his squadron into a battleline and turned westwards, waiting for Warren's signal for the attack.Brooks, p. 626 Due to the dispersed nature of his squadron, Warren did not issue this signal until 07:00, when he ordered ''Robust'' to steer for the French line and attack ''Hoche'' directly.James, p. 129 Captain Edward Thornbrough of ''Robust'' obeyed immediately and closed with the French, firing into the frigates ''Embuscade'' and ''Coquille'' as he passed, before closing with ''Hoche'' and, at 08:50, beginning a bitter close-range artillery duel.Clowes, p. 347 Minutes later ''Magnanime'' joined the action, firing on the rear frigates and engaging the French van of ''Immortalité'', ''Loire'' and ''Bellone'', which had worn out of the line in an attempt to rake her. The next three British ships into action, ''Ethalion'', ''Melampus'' and ''Amelia'', all raked the isolated ''Hoche'' as they passed, before pressing on sail to pursue the French frigates, now making distance to the south-west.Tracy, p. 286, ''The Biographical Memoir of Sir John Borlase Warren, Bart, K.B.''  ''Canada'' and the subsequent British ships all ignored ''Hoche'' except to fire a few distant shots. By the time they passed, she was clearly a wreck, having been pounded repeatedly by ''Robust'' and ''Magnanime''. Bompart finally surrendered at 10:50 with 270 of his crew and passengers killed or wounded.

''Embuscade'' was the next to surrender, having been battered in the opening exchanges by ''Magnanime'', and further damaged by long-range fire from ''Foudroyant'' during the pursuit. Overhauled by several larger British ships,  Captain de la Ronciére surrendered at 11:30 rather than allow his ship to be destroyed.James, p. 130 ''Magnanime'', suffering the effects of her engagement with ''Hoche'', took possession of ''Embuscade'' and continued to follow slowly behind the rest of the fleet, while ''Robust'', which had suffered severely in her duel with ''Hoche'', remained alongside her erstwhile opponent to take possession. The direction of the French squadron's flight, following the direction of the wind, took them across the path of the straggling British ships, beginning with the ''Foudroyant''. Most of the frigates were able outrun this ponderous enemy, but ''Bellone'' was less fortunate and a speculative shot from the battleship detonated a case of grenades in one of her topmasts. This began a disastrous fire which was eventually brought under control, but at a significant cost in speed. She was soon closely attacked by ''Melampus'' and suffered further damage. Nearby, the struggling ''Coquille'' surrendered after being outrun by the approaching ''Canada''; Warren ordered the slowly following ''Magnanime'' to take possession.

''Ethalion'' took over pursuit of ''Bellone'' from ''Melampus'', and for two hours maintained continuous fire with her bow-chasers on the French ship. ''Ethalion'' was faster than her quarry, and she slowly pulled parallel with ''Bellone'' during the afternoon, but could not get close enough for a decisive blow. It took another two hours of pursuit before the battered ''Bellone'' eventually surrendered.James, p. 131 ''Hoche'' apart, ''Bellone'' had suffered more casualties than any other ship present. To the south of this conflict, the struggling ''Anson'' discovered herself in danger when the surviving frigates of the French vanguard swept towards her en masse. Captain Durham was initially confused by their approach as he had been too distant to witness the action and the French ships flew false British ensigns, but he rapidly realised their true identity and at 16:00 opened fire on ''Loire''. The damaged ''Anson'' was severely hampered by her inability to manoeuvre, and so could do nothing when the French ships pulled back and sailed away, except to continue to fire until they were out of range. During the evening, the surviving French frigates gradually pulled away from their pursuers and disappeared into the gathering night, leaving behind four of their squadron, including their flagship, as captives.Gardiner, p. 114
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="97d614bd1fe235b50adbe7e5ac5d0eeb" name="Admiral_Warren_Oateborl" sectnum="3#1">../img/97d614bd1fe235b50adbe7e5ac5d0eeb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>