<document id="3489e558c0c2c4c9e47b2291d67582d6-3.6.5" name="SMS_Von_der_Tann" cat="29">
<text>
''Von der Tann'' participated in the Battle of Jutland, as part of Hipper's First Scouting Group. ''Von der Tann'' was the rearmost of five battlecruisers in Hipper's line. Bennett, p. 183 Shortly before 16:00 CETIt should be noted that the times mentioned in this section are in CET, which is congruent with the German perspective. This is one hour ahead of UTC, the time zone commonly used in British works., Hipper's force encountered Vice Admiral Beatty's battlecruiser squadron. The German ships were the first to open fire, at a range of approximately 15,000 yd (14,000 m). At 16:49, ''Von der Tann'' fired her first shot at . Fourteen minutes of firing later,Hough, xiv ''Von der Tann'' had scored five hits on ''Indefatigable'' out of 52 heavy shells fired, one of which caused ''Indefatigable'' to explode and sink. An observer on the battlecruiser , which was directly ahead of ''Indefatigable'', later remarked that he saw "the ''Indefatigable'' hit by two shells from the ''Von der Tann'', one on the fore turret. Both appeared to explode on impact. After an interval of thirty seconds, the ship blew up. Sheets of flame were followed by dense smoke which obscured her from view." Bennett, p. 184–5

Following the destruction of ''Indefatigable'', Beatty turned his force away, while the British 5th Battle Squadron closed in on the German battlecruisers, opening fire from approximately 19,000 yd (17,000 m). Bennett, p. 185 ''Von der Tann'' and ''Moltke'', the two rearmost of Hipper's squadron, came under fire from the three lead British battleships of the 5th BS: , , and . Massie, p. 594 The German battlecruisers began zig-zagging to avoid the gunfire from the British ships. At 17:09, six minutes after sinking ''Indefatigable'', ''Von der Tann'' was hit by one 15 in (38 cm) shell from ''Barham'', which struck beneath the waterline and dislodged a section of the belt armour, causing ''Von der Tann'' to take in 600 tons of water. This hit temporarily damaged the ship's steering gear, and combined with ''Von der Tann''s zig-zagging cause her to fall out of line to port. The German Official History commented that "the greatest calamity of a complete breakdown of the steering gear was averted, otherwise, ''Von der Tann'' would have been delivered into the hands of the oncoming battleships as in the case of ''Blücher'' during the Dogger Bank action." Tarrant, p. 97

At 17:20, a 13.5 in (34 cm) shell from the battlecruiser  struck the barbette of ''Von der Tann''s A turret. A chunk of armour plate was dislodged from inside the turret, and struck the turret training gear, which jammed the turret at 120 degrees. This put the turret out of action for the duration of the engagement. Tarrant, p. 99 At 17:23, the ship was hit again by a 13.5 in (34 cm) shell from ''Tiger'', which struck near the C turret and killed 6 men. The shell holed the deck and created enough wreckage that the turret was unable to traverse, and the starboard rudder engine room was damaged. The C turret was out of action until the wreckage could be cut away. Smoke from a fire caused by burning practice targets that had been stowed below the turret obscured the ship. Sections of the torpedo nets were knocked loose and trailed behind the ship. However, they were cut loose before they could catch in the propellers. Tarrant, p. 100 ''New Zealand'', which had been engaging ''Von der Tann'' following ''Indefatigable''s destruction, lost sight of her target and shifted fire to ''Moltke''.Brooks, p. 244 At 17:18, the range to ''Von der Tann'' from ''Barham'' had closed to 17,500 yd (16,000 m), at which point ''Von der Tann'' opened fire on the British battleship. Shortly thereafter, at 17:23, ''Von der Tann'' registered a hit on ''Barham'' which caused serious damage. Brooks, p. 246 However, after firing only 24 shells, ''Von der Tann'' had to return to her earlier target, ''New Zealand'', because her fore and aft turrets had since been disabled, and her amidships turrets were no longer able to target ''Barham''.Tarrant, p. 102

At 18:15, the guns of the last active turret jammed in their mountings, leaving ''Von der Tann'' without any working main armament.Tarrant, p. 119 Regardless, she remained in the battle line to distract the British gunners. Because she was no longer firing her main guns, ''Von der Tann'' was able to manoeuvre in an erratic manner, such that she could avoid British gunfire. By 18:53, the ship's speed fell from 26 kn (48 km/h) to 23 kn (43 km/h). Over an hour and a half after having failed due to mechanical difficulties, D turret was repaired and again ready for action. ''Von der Tann'' sustained her fourth and final heavy shell hit at 20:19, when one 15 in (38 cm) shell from  struck the aft conning tower. Shell splinters penetrated the conning tower, killing the Third Gunnery Officer and both rangefinder operators and wounding every other crewman in the tower. Shell fragments and other debris fell through the ventilating shaft and onto the condenser, which put all of the lights in the ship out.Tarrant, p. 179 Eleven minutes later, at 20:30, B turret was again clear for action, and by 21:00, C turret was also in working order. However, both of the amidships turrets suffered further mechanical difficulties that put them out of action later during the battle. Tarrant, p. 188

At approximately 22:15, Hipper, with his flag now in ''Moltke'', ordered his battlecruisers to increase speed to 20 knots, and to fall into the rear of the main German line. Neither ''Derfflinger'', due to battle damage, nor ''Von der Tann'', due to the dirtiness of her boiler fires, could steam at more than 18 knots.Tarrant, p. 205 ''Derfflinger'' and ''Von der Tann'' took up positions astern of the II Squadron, and were later joined by the old pre-dreadnoughts  and  at 00:05.Tarrant, p. 240 At 03:37, the British destroyer ''Moresby'' fired a torpedo at the rear of the German line; this passed closely across ''Von der Tann''s bow, and forced the ship to turn sharply to starboard to avoid being hit.Tarrant, p. 244 Close to the end of the battle, at 03:55, Hipper transmitted a report to Admiral Scheer, informing him of the tremendous damage his ships had suffered. By that time, ''Derfflinger'' and ''Von der Tann'' each had only two guns in operation, ''Moltke'' was flooded with 1,000 tons of water, and ''Seydlitz'' was severely damaged. Hipper reported: "I Scouting Group was therefore no longer of any value for a serious engagement, and was consequently directed to return to harbour by the Commander-in-Chief, while he himself determined to await developments off Horns Reef with the battlefleet." Tarrant, p. 255

During the course of the battle, two of ''Von der Tann''s main turrets were knocked out by British gunfire, while her other two turrets suffered mechanical failures.Gardiner and Gray, p. 152 The ship was firing so fast that several of the main guns in the amidships turrets became overheated and jammed in their recoil slides, and could not be returned to working order.Massie, p. 604''Von der Tann'' was without her main battery for 11 hours, although three turrets were restored to working order before the end of the battle; Staff, p. 10–11 D turret only after much cutting away of bent metal with oxyacetylene torches—afterwards the guns could be worked only by hand. Her casualties amounted to 11 dead and 35 wounded. During the battle ''Von der Tann'' fired 170 heavy shells and 98 secondary calibre shells.Tarrant, p. 292
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9a2d7f8904b1570259f7835c9d5698b9" name="HMS_Indefatigable_sinking" sectnum="3.6.5#1">../img/9a2d7f8904b1570259f7835c9d5698b9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>