<document id="34caf65800d4f1d7b4ca594003f950bc-1.5" name="R.E.M." cat="20">
<text>
In April 1997, the band convened at Buck's Kauai holiday home to record demos of material intended for the next album. The band sought to reinvent its sound and intended to incorporate drum loops and percussion experiments.Longino, Miriam. "R.E.M.: To a different beat the famed Athens band becomes a threesome as drummer Bill Berry leaves to 'sit back and reflect'". ''Atlanta Journal-Constitution''. October 31, 1997. Just as the sessions were due to begin in October, Berry decided, after months of contemplation and discussions with Downs and Mills, to tell the rest of the band that he was quitting.Buckley, p. 276 Berry told his band mates that he would not quit if they would break up as a result, so Stipe, Mills, and Buck agreed to carry on as a three-piece with his blessing.Buckley, p. 280 Berry publicly announced his departure three weeks later in October 1997. Berry told the press, "I'm just not as enthusiastic as I have been in the past about doing this anymore . . . I have the best job in the world. But I'm kind of ready to sit back and reflect and maybe not be a pop star anymore." Stipe admitted that the band would be different without a major contributor: "For me, Mike, and Peter, as R.E.M., are we still R.E.M.? I guess a three-legged dog is still a dog. It just has to learn to run differently."

The band canceled its scheduled recording sessions as a result of Berry's departure. "Without Bill it was different, confusing", Mills later said. "We didn't know exactly what to do. We couldn't rehearse without a drummer."Black, p. 232 The remaining members of R.E.M. resumed work on the album in February 1998 at Toast Studios in San Francisco.Black, p. 233 The band ended its decade-long collaboration with Scott Litt and hired Pat McCarthy to produce the record. Nigel Godrich was taken on as assistant producer, and drafted in ex-Screaming Trees member Barrett Martin and Beck's touring drummer Joey Waronker. The recording process was plagued with tension, and the group came close to disbanding. Bertis Downs called an emergency meeting where the band members sorted out their problems and agreed to continue as a group.Buckley, p. 286 Led off by the single "Daysleeper", ''Up'' (1998) debuted in the top ten in the US and UK. However, the album was a relative failure, selling 900,000 copies in the US by mid-1999 and eventually selling just over two million copies worldwide. While R.E.M.'s American sales were declining, the group's commercial base was shifting to the UK, where more R.E.M. records were sold per capita than any other country and the band's singles regularly entered the Top 20.Buckley, p. 292

A year after ''Up'''s release, R.E.M. wrote the instrumental score to the Andy Kaufman biopic ''Man on the Moon'', a first for the group. The film took its title from the ''Automatic for the People'' song of the same name. The song "The Great Beyond" was released as a single from the ''Man on the Moon'' soundtrack album. "The Great Beyond" only reached number 57 on the American pop charts, but was the band's highest-charting single ever in the UK, reaching number three in 2000.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="348d640d29ff24224578fac2ae33ef9f" name="Michael_Stipe_at_Glastonbury" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/348d640d29ff24224578fac2ae33ef9f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>