<document id="34e2222d33d1c4535ce0672ed0575b93-3" name="Cochineal" cat="3">
<text>
There are two methods of farming cochineal: traditional and controlled. Cochineals are farmed in the traditional method by planting infected cactus pads or infecting existing cacti with cochineals and harvesting the insects by hand. The controlled method uses small baskets called ''Zapotec nests'' placed on host cacti. The baskets contain clean, fertile females that leave the nests and settle on the cactus to await insemination by the males. In both cases the cochineals have to be protected from predators, cold, and rain. The complete cycle lasts 3 months during which the cacti are kept at a constant temperature of . Once the cochineals have finished the cycle, the new cochineals are ready to begin the cycle again or to be dried for dye production.


To produce dye from cochineals, the insects are collected when they are approximately ninety days old. Harvesting the insects is labour-intensive, as they must be individually knocked, brushed, or picked from the cacti and placed into bags. The insects are gathered by small groups of collectors who sell them to local processors or exporters. 

Several natural enemies can reduce the population of the insect on its cacti hosts. Of all the predators, insects seem to be the most important group. Insects and their larvae such as pyralid moths (order Lepidoptera), which destroy the cactus, and predators such as lady bugs (Coleoptera), various Diptera (such as Syrphidae and Chamaemyiidae), lacewings (Neuroptera), and ants (Hymenoptera) have been identified, as well as numerous parasitic wasps. Many birds, human-commensal rodents (especially rats) and reptiles also prey on cochineal insects. In regions dependent on cochineal production, pest control measures have to be taken seriously. For small-scale cultivation, manual methods of control have proved to be the most effective and safe. For large-scale cultivation, advanced pest control methods have to be developed, including alternative bioinsecticides or traps with pheromones.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="25afdcfabce1a90cfeb99619509f534f" name="Cochinel_Zapotec_nests" sectnum="3#1">../img/25afdcfabce1a90cfeb99619509f534f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>