<document id="35c5f60ea04deea79f6107fee80af0c0-7" name="Westgate-on-Sea" cat="11">
<text>
The town has sandy beaches at both St Mildred's Bay and West Bay. The larger of the beaches is at St Mildred's Bay, where it is possible to hire beach huts, deck chairs and jet-skis. The beach is a short distance from tennis courts and a golf putting course. At West Bay, there are many small rock pools, which are popular with children. Each beach has nearby cafés, restaurants and public houses, and a European Blue Flag Award is shared between them due to their cleanliness and safety.


The town centre has several Victorian canopied shops, a library and the three-screen Carlton Cinema. In addition to the theatre, the Westgate Pavilion is a venue for discos, yoga, indoor bowls and dance classes. 

Formed in 1896, Westgate and Birchington Golf Club has an 18-hole  course on the cliff tops between Westgate and Birchington. Based at Hawtreys Field, Westgate-on-Sea Cricket Club runs two Saturday teams and two Sunday teams. As of the 2007 season, both Saturday teams played in the Kent Cricket Feeder League East; the Saturday 1st XI team in Division 1C and the Saturday 2nd XI in Division 2C. The Sunday teams do not play in competitive matches. In 2006, Thanet Council opened a free skatepark at the Lymington Road recreation ground. Designed by local young people, the park caters for skateboarders and in line skaters of all ages and skill levels.

There are four local weekly newspapers providing news on the Thanet district area. ''Isle Of Thanet KM Extra'' is owned by the KM Group, and the ''Isle of Thanet Gazette'', ''Thanet Adscene'' and ''Thanet Times'' are owned by Trinity Mirror. ''Isle Of Thanet KM Extra'' and ''Thanet Adscene'' are free newspapers, whereas the other two are paid-for. KMFM Thanet is a radio station on frequency 107.2FM, owned by the KM Group and previously known as TLR (Thanet Local Radio).  KOS publish newspapers covering this area.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e1a22f2e3c69588a1692fa65cabf3899" name="Westgate-on-Sea_Cricket_Club" sectnum="7#1">../img/e1a22f2e3c69588a1692fa65cabf3899.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>