<document id="361961d900d8171b305cb8f79b1aabc2-6" name="Chennai" cat="11">
<text>
A resident of Chennai is called a ''Chennaiite''. As of 2001, Chennai city had a population of 4.34 million, while the total metropolitan population was 7.04 million. The population density for Chennai city and the metropolitan area have been calculated using the population figures and the total area of the respective regions, mentioned in the Second Master Plan. The conversion rate of  = 1.609 km. has been used to compute the density per sq. mile. The estimated metropolitan population in 2006 is 4.5  million. In 2001, the population density in the city was 24,682 per km² (63,926 per mi²), while the population density of the metropolitan area was 5,922 per km² (15,337 per mi²), making it one of the most densely populated cities in the world. In terms of population density, Chennai was ranked 51st among all urban agglomerations in the world with over 500,000 people. The sex ratio is 951 females for every 1,000 males, slightly higher than the national average of 944. The average literacy rate is 80.14%, much higher than the national average of 64.5%. The city has the fourth highest population of slum dwellers among major cities in India, with about 820,000 people (18.6% of its population) living in slum conditions. This number represents about 5% of the total slum population of India. In 2005, the crime rate in the city was 313.3 per 100,000 people, accounting for 6.2% of all crimes reported in major cities in India. The number of crimes in the city showed a significant increase of 61.8% from 2004.

The majority of the population in Chennai are Tamilians. Tamil is the primary language spoken in Chennai. English is  widely spoken especially in business, education and white collar professions. Sizeable Telugu and Malayalee communities live in the city.  Chennai also has a large migrant population, who come from other parts of Tamil Nadu and the rest of the country. As of 2001, out of the 937,000 migrants (21.57% of its population) in the city, 74.5% were from other parts of the state, 23.8% were from rest of India and 1.7% were from outside the country.

According to the 2001 census, Hindus constitute about 82.27% of the city's population, and Muslims (8.37%), Christians (7.63%) and Jains (1.05%) are other major religious groups.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="caf0f6152e512a7b093435b6810b6cd1" name="Chennai_Shopping" sectnum="6#1">../img/caf0f6152e512a7b093435b6810b6cd1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>