<document id="361fcdbbab8779dedc0dd32afb70a48c-3.8" name="Sarah_Churchill,_Duchess_of_Marlborough" cat="25">
<text>
Sarah's last attempt to re-establish her friendship with Anne came in 1710, when they had their final meeting. An account written by  Sarah shortly afterwards shows that she pleaded to be given an explanation of why their friendship was at an end, but Anne was unmoved. After hearing this, the Duke of Marlborough, realising that Anne intended to dismiss them, begged her to keep them in their offices for nine months, until the campaign was over, so that they could retire honourably. However, Anne told Marlborough that “for her  honour” Sarah was to resign immediately and return her gold key&ndash;the symbol of her authority within the Royal household&ndash;within two days.Field, p. 287. Years of trying the Queen's patience had finally resulted in her dismissal. When told the news, Sarah, in a fit of pride, told Marlborough to return the key to the Queen immediately.Field, p. 287. 

In January 1711, Sarah was stripped of the offices of Mistress of the Robes and Groom of the Stole and replaced by Elizabeth Seymour, Duchess of Somerset. Abigail was made Keeper of the Privy Purse. This broke a promise Anne had made to distribute these court offices to Sarah's children.Add MS 61422 ''An Account of a Conversation with Her Majesty when it appear'd plainly that she did not intend to keep her promise to the Duchess of Marlborough in letting her resign her employments to her children''.

The Marlboroughs also lost state funding for Blenheim Palace, and the building came to a halt for the first time since it was begun in 1705. Now in disgrace, they left England and travelled Europe. As a result of his success in the War of the Spanish Succession, the Duke of Marlborough was a favourite among the German courts and with the Holy Roman Empire, and the family was received in those places with full honours. 

Sarah, however, did not like being away from England, and often complained that they were received with full honours in Europe, but were in disgrace at home. Sarah found life travelling the royal courts difficult, remarking that they were full of dull company.Field, p. 327. She took the waters at Aix-la-Chapelle in Germany on account of her ill health, corresponded with those in England who could supply her with political gossip, and indulged in her fascination with Catholicism.Field, p. 328.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9b1441e2664b3176d8dfe20bdd22580b" name="Kensington_Palace_from_the_south_by_Kip_(1724)" sectnum="3.8#1">../img/9b1441e2664b3176d8dfe20bdd22580b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>