<document id="361fcdbbab8779dedc0dd32afb70a48c-2" name="Sarah_Churchill,_Duchess_of_Marlborough" cat="25">
<text>
In 1702, King William III died, and Anne became Queen. Anne immediately offered John Churchill a dukedom, which Sarah initially refused. Sarah was concerned that a dukedom would strain the family's finances; a ducal family at the time was expected to show off its rank through lavish entertainments.Field, pp. 106-107. Anne countered by offering the Marlboroughs a pension of £5000 a year, for life, from Parliament, as well as an extra £2000 a year from the Privy Purse, and they accepted the Dukedom. Sarah was promptly created Mistress of the Robes&ndash;the highest office in the royal court that could be held by a woman&ndash;Groom of the Stole, Keeper of the Privy Purse, and Ranger of Windsor Great Park. The Duke accepted the Order of the Garter, as well as the office of Captain-General of the army.Field, pp. 99 (Captain General and Order of the Garter); 107 (dukedom).

During much of Anne’s reign, the Duke of Marlborough was abroad fighting the War of the Spanish Succession, while Sarah remained in England. Despite being the most powerful woman in England besides the Queen, she appeared at court only rarely 1705, preferring to oversee the construction of her new estate, Woodstock Manor (the site of the later Blenheim Palace), a gift from Queen Anne after the duke's victory at the Battle of Blenheim.Field, p. 145. Nevertheless, Anne sent her news of political developments in letters and consulted Sarah's advice in most matters.Gregg, ‘’. Retrieved 6 August 2007.

Sarah was famous for telling the Queen exactly what she thought, and did not offer her flattery.Hooke, p. 11. Anne and Sarah had invented petnames for themselves during their youths which they continued to use after Anne became queen: ''Mrs Freeman'' (Sarah) and ''Mrs Morley'' (Anne).Hooke, p. 14. Effectively a business manager, Sarah had control over the Queen's position, from her finances to people admitted to the royal presence.Field, p. 99
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="653a3e6b93e632ce207d74ad4fe4ad3b" name="Queen_Anne" sectnum="2#1">../img/653a3e6b93e632ce207d74ad4fe4ad3b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>