<document id="361fcdbbab8779dedc0dd32afb70a48c-3.7" name="Sarah_Churchill,_Duchess_of_Marlborough" cat="25">
<text>
In July 1708, the Duke of Marlborough, with his ally Prince Eugene of Savoy, won a great victory at the Battle of Oudenarde. On the way to the thanksgiving service at St Paul's Cathedral, Sarah engaged in a furious argument with Anne about the jewels Anne wore to the service, and showed her a letter from the Duke of Marlborough which expressed hope that the Queen would make good political use of the victory. The implication that she should publicly express her support for the Whigs offended her; and at the service, Sarah told the Queen to "be quiet" after Anne continued the argument, thus offending the Queen still further.Field, p. 211. Anne wrote to Marlborough encouraging him not to let her rift with Sarah become public knowledge; but he could not prevent his wife's indiscretion. Sarah continued vehemently supporting the Whigs in writing and speaking to Anne, with the support of Godolphin and the other Whig ministers. The news of the public's support for the Whigs reached Marlborough in letters from Sarah and Godolphin, which influenced his political advice to the Queen. Anne, already in ill health, felt used and harassed and was desperate for escape. She found refuge in the gentle and quiet comfort of Abigail Masham.Harris, Frances.  Retrieved 8 August 2007.

Anne had explained before that she did not wish the public to know that her relationship with Sarah was failing, because any sign that Sarah was out of favour would have a damaging impact on the duke of Marlborough's authority as Captain-General. Sarah was kept in all of her offices&ndash;purely for the sake of her husband's position as Captain-General of the army&ndash;and the tension between the two women lingered on until early in 1711.Field, p. 229, 251-5, 265, 344. This year was to see the end of their relationship for good.

Sarah had always been jealous of Anne's affection for Abigail Masham. Together with the Duke of Marlborough and most of the Whig party, she had tried to force Anne to dismiss her. All these attempts failed, even when Anne was threatened with an official parliamentary demand from the Whigs, who were suspicious of Abigail's Tory influence with Anne, for Abigail's dismissal.Field, p. 238. The whole scenario echoed Anne's refusal to give up Sarah during the reign of William and Mary; but the threat of Parliamentary interference exceeded anything tried against Anne in the 1690s.Gregg, . Retrieved 6 August 2007. Anne was ultimately triumphant; she conducted interviews with high ranking politicians of both political parties and begged them "with tears in her eyes" to oppose the motion.

The passion she showed for Abigail, and the stubborn refusal to dismiss her, angered Sarah to the point that she implied that a lesbian affair was taking place between the two women.Field, 191-192. During the mourning period for Anne's husband, Sarah was the only one who refused to wear suitable mourning clothes. This gave the impression that she did not consider Anne's grief over his death to be genuine.Field, pp. 219-220. Eventually, as a result of mass support for peace in the War of the Spanish Succession,See Treaty of Utrecht. Anne decided she no longer needed the Duke of Marlborough and took the opportunity to dismiss him on trumped-up charges of embezzlement.Field, pp. 308, 311-14, 317, 322-3.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="361fcdbbab8779dedc0dd32afb70a48c" name="Sarah_Churchill,_Duchess_of_Marlborough" sectnum="3.7#1">../img/361fcdbbab8779dedc0dd32afb70a48c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>