<document id="361fcdbbab8779dedc0dd32afb70a48c-1.3" name="Sarah_Churchill,_Duchess_of_Marlborough" cat="25">
<text>
Life for Sarah during the reign of William and Mary was difficult. Although the new King and Queen had awarded Sarah’s husband the title Earl of Marlborough, Sarah and John enjoyed considerably less favour than they had during the reign of James II.Hattendorf, ‘’. Retrieved on 6 August 2007. The new Earl of Marlborough had supported the now exiled James; and by this time Sarah’s influence on Anne, and her cultivation of high members of the government to promote Anne’s interests, was widely known. Mary II responded to this by demanding that Anne dismiss Sarah. However, Anne refused. This created a rift between Mary and Anne that never healed.Field, pp. 69, 70, 80-81, 85.

Other problems also emerged. In 1689, Anne's supporters (including the Marlboroughs and the Duke of Somerset) demanded that she be granted a parliamentary annuity of £50 000, a sum that would end her dependence on William and Mary.Field, p. 60. Sarah was seen as the driving force behind this bill, creating further ill-feeling towards her at court. William responded to the demand by offering the same sum from the Privy Purse, to keep Anne dependent on his generosity. However, Anne, through Sarah, refused, pointing out that a parliamentary grant would be more secure than charity from the Privy Purse.Field, p. 60. Eventually Anne received the grant from parliament, and felt she owed this to Sarah's efforts.Field, p. 60

Sarah's success as a leader of the opposition only intensified Queen Mary's animosity towards the Marlboroughs. Although she could not dismiss Sarah from Anne's service, Mary responded by evicting Sarah from her court lodgings at the Palace of Whitehall. Anne responded by leaving the court as well, and Sarah and she went to stay with their friends Charles Seymour, the sixth Duke of Somerset, and Elizabeth, the Duchess of Somerset at Syon House. Anne continued to defy the Queen’s demand for Sarah’s dismissal, even though an incriminating document signed by the Earl of Marlborough supporting the recently exiled James II and his supporters had been discovered. This document is likely to have been forged by Robert Young, a known forger and disciple of Titus Oates; Oates was famous for stirring a strongly anti-Catholic atmosphere in England between 1679 and the early 1680s.Field, pp. 79-80. The Earl was imprisoned in the Tower of London.Field, p. 79. The loneliness Sarah suffered during these events drew her and Anne closer together.Field, pp. 79, 80.

Following the death of Mary II from smallpox in 1694, William III restored Anne’s honours, in an effort to increase his popularity with the English, and provided her with apartments at St. James's Palace. He also restored the Earl of Marlborough to all his offices and honours, and exonerated him from any past accusations. However, fearing Sarah’s powerful influence, William kept Anne out of government affairs, and he did not make her regent in his absences.Gregg, Anne (1665–1714); ''William alone, 1694 &ndash; 1702''.This was uncommon; an heir to the throne is often appointed to act as regent if the sovereign is out of the country.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1fd9dac6a793ff21689f2ec22d53cc09" name="SidneyGodolphinEarlGodolphin" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/1fd9dac6a793ff21689f2ec22d53cc09.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>