<document id="361fcdbbab8779dedc0dd32afb70a48c-2.5" name="Sarah_Churchill,_Duchess_of_Marlborough" cat="25">
<text>
Sarah's frankness and indifference for rank, so admired by Anne earlier in their friendship, was now seen to be intrusive. Unlike most women of the time&ndash;many of whom did not have influence with their own husbands&ndash;Sarah had a powerful intimacy with the two most powerful men in the country, Marlborough and Godolphin. Godolphin, though a great friend of Sarah's, had even considered refusing high office after Anne's accession, preferring to live quietly and away from the political side of Sarah, who was bossy, interfering, and presumed to tell him what to do when Marlborough was away.Hibbert, p. 95 Sarah, although a woman in a man's world of national and international politics, was always ready to give her advice; express her opinions; antagonize with outspoken censure; and insist on having her say on every possible occasion.Hibbert, p. 312 However, she had a charm and vivaciousness which was admired by many; and she could easily delight those she met with her wit.Hibbert, p. 312 

Anne's apparent withdrawal of genuine affection occurred for a number of reasons. She was frustrated by Sarah's long absences from Court, and despite numerous letters from Anne to Sarah on this subject, Sarah rarely attended, and wrote her excuses in letters to Anne. There was also a political difference between them: Anne was a Tory (the party known as the "Church party", religion being one of Anne's chief concerns), and Sarah was a Whig (the party known to support Marlborough's wars). The Queen did not want this difference to come between them; but Sarah, always thinking of her husband, wanted Anne to give more support to the Whigs, which she was not prepared to do.Field, pp. 111, 112.

Sarah was called to Cambridge in 1703, where her only surviving son, John, Marquess of Blandford, was taken ill with Smallpox. The Duke of Marlborough was recalled from the war and was at his bedside when he died on 20 February 1703.Hattendorf, . Retrieved on 8 August 2007. Sarah was heartbroken over the loss of her son and became reclusive for a period, expressing her grief by closing herself off from Anne and either not answering her letters or doing so in a cold and formal manner.Field, pp. 122-123. However, Sarah did not allow Anne to shut her out when Anne suffered bereavement. After the death of Anne's husband, Prince George of Denmark in 1708, Sarah arrived uninvited at Kensington Palace to find Anne with the prince's body. She pressed the heartbroken Queen to move from Kensington to St James's Palace in London, which Anne bluntly refused, and instead commanded Sarah to call Abigail Masham to attend her. Aware that Abigail was gaining more influence with Anne, Sarah disobeyed her, and instead scolded her for grieving over Prince George's death. Although Anne eventually submitted and allowed herself to be taken to St James's Palace, Sarah's insensitivity greatly offended her and added to the already significant strain on the relationship.Field, pp. 218, 219.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="686059554284916b7aa3835d27720bc9" name="Sarah_Churchill_and_Lady_Fitzharding" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/686059554284916b7aa3835d27720bc9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>