<document id="367ff337b6c9f07b9c1e8d9e32aed8d4-2.9" name="Rachel_Carson" cat="17">
<text>
A variety of groups ranging from government institutions to environmental and conservation organizations to scholarly societies have celebrated Carson's life and work since her death.  Perhaps most significantly, on June 9, 1980 Carson was awarded the Presidential Medal of Freedom, the highest civilian honor in the United States, archived 2007-10-18, retrieved 2009-08-01.  A U.S. postage stamp was issued in her honor the following year; several other countries have since issued Carson postage as well.. Retrieved September 26, 2007-->


Carson's birthplace and childhood home in Springdale, Pennsylvania—now known as the Rachel Carson Homestead—became a National Register of Historic Places site, and the nonprofit Rachel Carson Homestead Association was created in 1975 to manage it.. Retrieved September 7, 2007.  Her home in Colesville, Maryland where she wrote ''Silent Spring'' was named a National Historic Landmark in 1991.  Near Pittsburgh, a  hiking trail, maintained by the Rachel Carson Trails Conservancy, was dedicated to Carson in 1975.. Retrieved September 26, 2007.  A Pittsburgh bridge was also renamed in Carson's honor as the Rachel Carson Bridge.Jerome L. Sherman, , ''Pittsburgh Post-Gazette'', April 23, 2006. Retrieved September 23, 2007. The Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection State Office Building in Harrisburg is named in her honor. An elementary school in Gaithersburg, Montgomery County, MD, built in 1990, was named in her honor,. Retrieved February 22, 2008. as was a middle school in Herndon, VA.. Retrieved February 28, 2008. 

The ceremonial auditorium on the third floor of U.S. EPA's main headquarters, the Ariel Rios Building, is named after Rachel Carson. The Rachel Carson room is just a few feet away from the EPA administrator's office and has been the site of numerous important announcements, including the Clean Air Interstate Rule, since the Agency moved to Ariel Rios in 2001.. REtrieved August 18, 2009.

A number of conservation areas have been named for Carson as well.  Between 1964 and 1990,  near Brookeville in Montgomery County, Maryland were acquired and set aside as the Rachel Carson Conservation Park, administered by the Maryland-National Capital Park and Planning Commission.. Retrieved August 26, 2007.  In 1969, the Coastal Maine National Wildlife Refuge became the Rachel Carson National Wildlife Refuge; expansions will bring the size of the refuge to about .. Retrieved September 11, 2007. In 1985, North Carolina renamed one of its estuarine reserves in honor of Carson, in Beaufort.. Retrieved October 12, 2007.

Carson is also a frequent namesake for prizes awarded by philanthropic, educational and scholarly institutions.  The Rachel Carson Prize, founded in Stavanger, Norway in 1991, is awarded to women who have made a contribution in the field of environmental protection.. Retrieved September 11, 2007.((dead link}}-->  The American Society for Environmental History has awarded the Rachel Carson Prize for Best Dissertation since 1993.. Retrieved September 11, 2007.  Since 1998, the Society for Social Studies of Science has awarded an annual Rachel Carson Book Prize for "a book length work of social or political relevance in the area of science and technology studies.". Retrieved September 11, 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="96eb12b5bbd830224adb1d2295f90d37" name="HAER_PBG_9thStreet_361504pv" sectnum="2.9#1">../img/96eb12b5bbd830224adb1d2295f90d37.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>