<document id="36db9d44ace3462d9cc2fff06ad36ed8-1.4.2" name="Pyotr_Ilyich_Tchaikovsky" cat="20">
<text>
In 1868, Tchaikovsky met the Belgian soprano Désirée Artôt, then on a tour of Russia.  They became infatuated, and were engaged to be married.Brown, ''Early Years'', 156–157; Warrack, ''Tchaikovsky'', 53. He dedicated his ''Romance in F minor'' for piano, Op. 5, to her. However, on September 15, 1869, without any communication with Tchaikovsky, Artôt married a member of her company, the Spanish baritone Mariano Padilla y Ramos. The general view has been that Tchaikovsky got over the affair fairly quickly. It has, however, been postulated that he coded her name into the Piano Concerto No. 1 in B-flat minor and the tone-poem ''Fatum''.Brown, ''Early Years'', 197–200. They met on a handful of later occasions, and in October 1888 he wrote ''Six French Songs'', Op. 65, for her, in response to her request for a single song. Tchaikovsky later claimed she was the only woman he ever loved.

In April 1877 Tchaikovsky's favorite pupil, Vladimir Shilovsky, had married suddenly.Poznansky, 204. Poznansky also asserts that Shilovsky was homosexual, and that he and Tchaikovsky had shared a mutual bond of affection for just over a decade. (Poznansky, 95, 126).Tchaikovsky, M.I., ''Zhizn' Petra Il'icha Chaikovskoyo'' , 3 vols. (Moscow and Leipzig, 1900–1902), 1:258–259. Shilovsky's wedding may in turn have spurred Tchaikovsky to consider such a step himself.Poznansky, 204. He declared his intention to marry in a letter to his brother.Letter to Modest Tchaikovsky, August 31, 1876. As quoted in Holden, 113. There followed Tchaikovsky's ill-starred marriage to one of his former composition students, Antonina Miliukova. The brief time with his wife drove him to an emotional crisis, which was followed by a stay in Clarens, Switzerland, for rest and recovery.Holden, 126, 145, 148, 150. They remained legally married but never lived together again nor had any children, though she later gave birth to three children by another man.Brown, ''Man and Music'', 230, 232; Holden, 209.

Tchaikovsky's marital débâcle may have forced him to face the full truth concerning his sexuality.Holden, 172. He apparently never again considered matrimony as a camouflage or escape, nor considered himself capable of loving women in the same manner as men. He wrote to his brother Anatoly from Florence, Italy on February 19, 1878,

Thanks to the regularity of my life, to the sometimes tedious but always inviolable calm, and above all, thanks to time which heals all wounds, I have completely recovered from my ''insanity''. There's no doubt that for some months on end I was a bit ''insane'', and only now, when I'm completely recovered, have I learned to relate ''objectively'' to everything which I did during my brief insanity. That man who in May took it into his head to marry Antonina Ivanova, who during June wrote a whole opera as though nothing had happened, who in July married, who in September fled from his wife, who in November railed at Rome and so on—that man wasn't I, but another Pyotr Ilyich.As quoted in Brown, ''Crisis Years'', 254.

A few days later, in another letter to Anatoly, he added that there was "nothing more futile than wanting to be anything other than what I am by nature."Letter to Anatoly Tchaikovsky, February 25, 1878. As quoted in Holden, 172

It has been commonly held that the strain of the marriage and Tchaikovsky's emotional state immediately preceding it may have actually enhanced Tchaikovsky's creativity. To some extent, this may have been the case. While the Fourth Symphony was begun some months before Tchaikovsky married Antonina,Brown, ''Crisis Years'', 159. both the symphony and the opera ''Eugene Onegin'', arguably two of his finest compositions, are held up as proof of this enhanced creativity. He finished both these works in the six months between his engagement and the completion of the rest cure following his marriage breakdown. While in Clarens he also composed his Violin Concerto, with the technical assistance of one of his former students, violinist Yosif Kotek. Kotek later helped establish contact between Tchaikovsky and Nadezhda von Meck, the widow of a railway magnate, who became the composer's patron and confidante.Steinberg, ''Concerto'', 484–85.

Like the First Piano Concerto, the Violin Concerto was rejected initially by its intended dedicatee, in this case the noted virtuoso and pedagogue Leopold Auer. It was premiered by another soloist (Adolph Brodsky), and while the work would eventually enjoy public success, the audience hissed at its premiere in Vienna,Steinberg, ''Concerto'', 487. and it was denigrated by music critic Eduard Hanslick:

The Russian composer Tchaikovsky is surely no ordinary talent, but rather, an inflated one, obsessed with posturing as a man of genius, and lacking all discrimination and taste ... the same can be said for his new, long, and ambitious Violin Concerto. For a while it proceeds soberly, musically, and not mindlessly, but soon vulgarity gains the upper hand and dominates until the end of the first movement. The violin is no longer played: it is tugged about, torn, beaten black and blue ... The Adagio is well on the way to reconciling us and winning us over when, all too soon, it breaks off to make way for a finale that transports us to the brutal and wretched jollity of a Russian church festival. We see a host of gross and savage faces, hear crude curses, and smell the booze. In the course of a discussion of obscener illustrations, Friedrich Vischer once maintained that there were pictures whose stink one could see. Tchaikovsky's Violin Concerto confronts us for the first time with the hideous idea that there may be musical compositions whose stink one can hear.Hanslick, Eduard, ''Music Criticisms 1850–1900'', ed. and trans. Henry Pleasants (Baltimore: Penguin Books, 1963). As quoted in Steinberg, ''Concerto'', 487.

Auer belatedly accepted the concerto, and eventually played it to great public success. In future years he taught the work to his pupils, including Jascha Heifetz and Nathan Milstein. Auer later said that Hanslick's comment that "the last movement was redolent of vodka  did credit neither to his good judgment nor to his reputation as a critic."As quoted in Steinberg, ''Concerto'', 486.



The intensity of personal emotion now flowing through Tchaikovsky's works was entirely new to Russian music. It prompted some Russian commentators to place his name alongside that of novelist Fyodor Dostoyevsky. Like Dostoyevsky's characters, they felt the musical hero in Tchaikovsky's music persisted in exploring the meaning of life while trapped in a fatal love-death-faith triangle.Volkov, 115. The critic Osoovski wrote of Tchaikovsky and Dostoyevsky: "With a hidden passion they both stop at moments of horror, total spiritual collapse, and finding acute sweetness in the cold trepidation of the heart before the abyss, they both force the reader to experience those feelings, too."Osoovski, A.V., ''Muzykal'no-kritcvheskie stat'i, 1894–1912'' (Musical Criticism articles, 1894–1912) (Leningrad, 1971), 171. As quoted in Volkov, 116.

Tchaikovsky's fame among concert audiences began to expand outside Russia, and continued to grow within it. Hans von Bülow had become a fervent champion of the composer's work after hearing some of it in a Moscow concert during Lent of 1874. In a German newspaper later that year, he praised the First String Quartet, ''Romeo and Juliet'' and other works, and he would later take up many other Tchaikovsky works both as pianist and conductor. In France, Camille Benoit began introducing Tchaikovsky's music to readers of the ''Revue et gazette musicale de Paris''. The music also received significant exposure during the 1878 International Exhibition in Paris. While Tchaikovsky's reputation as a composer grew, a corresponding increase in performances of his works did not occur until he began conducting them himself, starting in the mid-1880s.Wiley, ''New Grove (2001)'', 25:161. Nevertheless, by 1880, all of the operas Tchaikovsky had completed up that point had been staged, and his orchestral works had been given performances that had been sympathetically received.Warrack, ''Tchaikovsky Symphonies and Concertos'', 28.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f675da035c30e1aeb7e348c3542ab3e5" name="Hans_von_buelow" sectnum="1.4.2#1">../img/f675da035c30e1aeb7e348c3542ab3e5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>