<document id="36e74fb63ee94b15d73472eadeb01a2d-2" name="Prince_Albert_Victor,_Duke_of_Clarence_and_Avondale" cat="25">
<text>
When Albert Victor was just short of seventeen months old, his brother, Prince George of Wales, was born on 3 June 1865. Given the closeness in age of the two royal brothers, they were educated together. In 1871, the Queen appointed John Neale Dalton as their tutor. The two princes were given a strict programme of study, which included games and military drills as well as academic subjects.Nicolson, pp. 7–9 Dalton complained that Albert Victor's mind was "abnormally dormant".Letter from Dalton in the Royal Archives, 6 April 1879, quoted in Cook, p. 52 Though he learned to speak Danish, progress in other languages and subjects was slow.Cook, pp. 52, 56–57 and Harrison, pp. 68–69 Albert Victor never excelled intellectually. Lady Geraldine Somerset blamed Dalton for Albert Victor's poor education,Quoted by Aronson, p. 74 but possible physical explanations for Albert Victor's inattention or indolence in class include his premature birth, which can be associated with learning difficulties, or ''petit mal'', a mild form of epilepsy manifested in childhood as periods of mental vacuity.Aronson, pp. 53–54 and Harrison, p. 35 Sir Henry Ponsonby thought that Albert Victor might have inherited his mother's deafness.Aronson, p. 54 and Harrison, p. 34

Separating the brothers for the remainder of their education was considered, but Dalton advised the Prince of Wales against splitting them up as "Prince Albert Victor requires the stimulus of Prince George's company to induce him to work at all."Nicolson, pp. 12–13 In 1877, the two boys were sent to the Royal Navy's training ship, HMS ''Britannia''. They began their studies there two months behind the other cadets as Albert Victor contracted typhoid fever, for which he was treated by Sir William Gull.Cook, p. 62 and Harrison, p. 37 Dalton accompanied them as chaplain to the ship. In 1879, after a great deal of discussion between the Queen, the Prince of Wales, their households and the Government, the royal brothers were sent as naval cadets on a three-year world tour aboard HMS ''Bacchante''.Cook, pp. 70–72 Albert Victor was rated midshipman on his sixteenth birthday.Cook, p. 79 They toured the British Empire, accompanied by Dalton, visiting the Americas, the Falkland Islands, South Africa, Australia, Fiji, the Far East, Singapore, Ceylon, Aden, Egypt, the Holy Land and Greece. They acquired tattoos in Japan. By the time they returned to the UK, Albert Victor was eighteen.Cook, pp. 79–94 and Harrison, pp. 41–56

The brothers were parted in 1883; George continued in the navy and Albert Victor attended Trinity College, Cambridge.Cook, p. 98 and Harrison, p. 72 James Kenneth Stephen was appointed as a tutor and lived partly at Sandringham during his tutorship, along with Dalton who was still in attendance both at Sandringham and at Trinity.Aronson, pp. 64–67 and Cook, pp. 101–104 Stephen was a misogynist and he may have felt emotionally attached to Albert Victor, but whether or not his feelings were overtly homosexual is open to question.Aronson, pp. 66–67 No details of Albert Victor's own sex life at Cambridge are known or even if he had one, but partners of either gender would have been available to him.Aronson, p. 73 Albert Victor showed little interest in the intellectual atmosphere and he was excused examinations, though he did become involved in undergraduate life. In August 1884, he spent some time at the University of Heidelberg studying German.Cook, pp. 104–111 Leaving Cambridge in 1885, where he had already served as a cadet in the 2nd Cambridge University Battalion, he was gazetted as an officer in the 10th Hussars.Cook, pp. 119–120



One of Albert Victor's instructors said he learnt by listening rather than reading or writing and had no difficulty remembering information,Major Miles quoted in Aronson, p. 81, Cook, p. 123 and Harrison, p. 92 but his uncle, Prince George, Duke of Cambridge, had a less favourable opinion of him, calling him "an inveterate and incurable dawdler".Harrison, p. 90 Much of Albert Victor's time at his post in Aldershot was spent drilling, which he disliked, though he did like to play polo.Pope-Hennessy, p. 192 He passed his examinations, and in March 1887, he was posted to Hounslow where he was promoted to captain. He was given more public engagements, visited Ireland and Gibraltar, and opened the Hammersmith suspension bridge.Cook, p. 135 Of his private life, a childhood friend of Albert Victor later recalled that it was uneventful: "his brother officers had said that they would like to make a man of the world of him. Into that world he refused to be initiated."Rev. William Rogers quoted in Bullock, Charles (1892). "Prince Edward: A Memory" p. 53 quoted by Aronson, pp. 80–81
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4f012d2ce459c797b41a08b22932128f" name="Albert_Victor_1875" sectnum="2#1">../img/4f012d2ce459c797b41a08b22932128f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>