<document id="374bb4d8045a454b7548419999879246-5.2" name="Banker_horse" cat="3">
<text>
Public Law 105-229, commonly referred to as the Shackleford Banks Wild Horses Protection Act, states that the Bankers on Shackleford Island are to be jointly managed by the National Park Service and another qualified nonprofit entity (currently the Foundation for Shackleford Horses). The herd is limited to 120–130 horses. Population management is achieved through adoption and by administering the contraceptive vaccine Porcine zona pellucida (PZP) to individual mares via dart. The island’s horse population is monitored by freeze branding numbers onto each animal’s left hindquarter. The identification of individuals allows the National Park Service to ensure correct gender ratios and to select which mares to inject with PZP. Since 2000, adoptions of Bankers from Shackleford have been managed by the Foundation for Shackleford Horses. As of 2007, 56 horses had found new homes, 10 resided with another herd on Cedar Island, and two had been moved to the Ocracoke herd.

On November 12, 1996, the Shackleford horses were rounded up by the North Carolina Department of Agriculture's Veterinary Division and tested for equine infectious anemia (EIA). EIA is a potentially lethal disease, a lentivirus transmitted by bodily fluids and insects. Seventy-six of the 184 captured horses tested positive. Those who tested negative were allowed to remain on the island and those with the disease were transported to a temporary quarantine facility. Finding a permanent, isolated area for such a large number of Bankers was a challenging task for the Foundation of Shackleford Horses; eight days later the state declared all proposed locations for the herd unsuitable and so the 76 infected horses were euthanized. Two more horses died in the process&mdash;one who was fatally injured during the roundup and an uninfected foal that slipped into the quarantined herd to be with its mother.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c0ca475b3a91fc9364faaab9142ce206" name="Branded_Shackleford_Pony" sectnum="5.2#1">../img/c0ca475b3a91fc9364faaab9142ce206.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>