<document id="375a3ab409560e9ffd3a97600e85a88c-1.2" name="Old_Dan_Tucker" cat="20">
<text>
The original "Old Dan Tucker" and most folk variants are not political in nature. However, as early as 1844, the Hutchinson Family Singers were performing "Get off the Track!" to its tune, billed as "A song for Emancipation"Crawford 257. One verse and the chorus say:

:Ho! the car Emancipation
:Rides majestic thro' our nation,
:Bearing on its train the story;
:Liberty! a nation's glory.

:Get out the way! Every station!
:Freedom's car, Emancipation!Hutchinson, Jesse (1845). "Get off the Track!". ''The Liberty Minstrel''. Leavitt & Alden.

That same year, supporters of Henry Clay at a Whig rally sang a version that makes references to Clay ("Ole Kentucky"), Martin Van Buren, and James Buchanan:

:The people's fav'rite, Henry Clay, is now the 'fashion' of the day;
:And let the track be dry or mucky, we'll stake our pile on Ole Kentucky.

:Get out of the way, he's swift and lucky; clear the track for Ole Kentucky!Quoted in Harland 137.

In 1856, supporters of John C. Frémont's run for the Republican Party nomination adopted the tune as his campaign song with the changed refrain "Get out the way, old Buchanan".May 74. William Jennings Bryan's campaign song for the 1900 Democratic National Convention in Kansas City, Missouri, changed the lyrics to say:Welsch 78–79.

:Voters, come and hear my ditty,
:What was done at Kansas City:
:David Hill, the New York lion,
:Nominated Billy Bryan.

:Get out of the way, you Grand Old Party,
:You're so old, you're getting warty.Quoted in Welsch 78–79

A version popular during the American Civil War adds references to Abraham Lincoln:

:Old Abe is coming down to fight,
:And put the Democrats to flight;
:He's coming with the wedge and maul
:And he will split 'em one and all.

:Get out the way, you little giant
:You can't come in, you're too short and pliant.Forcucci 131.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7984c23b4a87deec5f6e967ef38d7293" name="Get_off_the_Track_sheet_music" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/7984c23b4a87deec5f6e967ef38d7293.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>