<document id="375a3ab409560e9ffd3a97600e85a88c-4" name="Old_Dan_Tucker" cat="20">
<text>
In December 1842 and January 1843, Dan Emmett portrayed the character Old Dan Tucker in solo and duo performances; the playbills do not indicate whether he included the song in his act.Nathan 114. The Virginia Minstrels probably made "Old Dan Tucker" a regular part of their show beginning with their first performance at the Bowery Amphitheatre on February 6, 1843. Their minstrel show also included a comic scene loosely based on the song, "Dan Tucker on Horseback", about a black riding master. The piece starred Richard Pelham in the title role and Frank Brower as a black clown.Nathan 118–119. "Old Dan Tucker" did not appear on a Virginia Minstrels playbill until a March 7 and 8 performance at Boston's Masonic Temple. There, the playbill described it as "OLD DAN TUCKER, a Virginian Refrain, in which is described the ups and downs of Negro life."Quoted in Nathan 119. As early as February 15, Emmett billed himself as "Old Dan Emmett".''New York Herald'', 2/15/1843, p. 3.

By the end of March, "Old Dan Tucker" was a hit, and it quickly became the Virginia Minstrels' most popular song.Nathan 121. Robert Winans found the song on 49% of the minstrel playbills he surveyed from the 1843–1847 period (behind only "Miss Lucy Long"),Winans 148. and research by musicologist William J. Mahar suggests that it was behind only "Mary Blane" and "Lucy Long" in its frequency of publication in antebellum songsters. The next year, Dan Tucker returned in the popular "Ole Bull and Old Dan Tucker", which pits him against Ole Bull in a contest of skill.Mahar 22, 370 note 5. Sequels such as "De New Ole Dan Tucker" and "Old Dan Tucker's Wedding" followed.Lott 267, note 3. Other companies adopted Tucker for comedy sketches, such as burlesques of ''La sonnambula'' by Buckley's Serenaders in 1850 and Sanford's Opera Troupe in 1853.Mahar 107.

The song became so identified with Emmett and the Virginia Minstrels that it became part of their foundation myth. Billy Whitlock and George B. Wooldridge both claimed that the troupe members played "Old Dan Tucker" in their first impromptu performance together:. . . as if by accident, each one picked up his tools and joined in a chorus of "Old Dan Tucker," while Emmett was playing and singing. It went well, and they repeated it without saying a word. Each did his best, and such a rattling of the principal and original instruments in a minstrel band was never heard before.''New York Clipper'', April 13, 1878. Quoted in Nathan 116. Emmett repeated this story in the May 19, 1877, ''New York Clipper'', although other details changed.Nathan 117. The press began to refer to Emmett as "Ole Dan Tucker", and Emmett eventually adopted the nickname. The Virginia Minstrels sometimes went by "Ole Dan Tucker and Co."Lawrence 232 note 26. They were called "Old Dan Tucker & Co.," either by themselves or by the press, as early as February 16, 1843.''New York Herald'', 2/16/1843, p. 3.

The song's disdain for the customs of the upper classes hit a chord with working class audiences. On January 28, 1843, ''The New York Sporting Whip'' reported that the song had been adopted by a Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, street gang called the Hallow Guards. As their leader, Stovepipe Bill, led them against a military raid, he sang the verses followed by the gang singing the chorus.Cockrell 200 note 62. Two years later, ''The Knickerbocker'' remarked, "At this present moment, a certain ubiquitous person seems to be in the way of the whole people of these United States simultaneously."''The Knickerbocker'', 1845, quoted in ''The Black Perspective in Music'' (1975), p. 87–88; quoted in turn in Crawford 210 note 23. Nathanson claimed that "Old Dan Tucker" had "been sung, perhaps, oftener than any melody ever written."Quoted in Nathan 179 note 17.

In 1871, 28 years after its first published edition, ''Board and Trade'' listed editions of "Old Dan Tucker" in print from seven different publishers. The song had by default fallen into the public domain.Crawford 870–871 note 21. In later decades, "Old Dan Tucker" became a standard of bluegrass and country music,Cantwell 104.Malone 173. with recordings by such artists as Fiddlin' John Carson, Uncle Dave Macon, Pete Seeger, and Gid Tanner and his Skillet Lickers.Waltz and Engle. It is referred to in John Steinbeck's novel The Grapes of Wrath. More recently, rock musician Bruce Springsteen made a recording. Children's music collections frequently feature the song. In the 1935 novel ''Little House on the Prairie'' by Laura Ingalls Wilder, the character Mr. Edwards sings the song as his trademark; accordingly, the ''Little House on the Prairie'' television series from the 1970s and 1980s uses the song as a leitmotif for the character.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="274f31e93aba1b0969eed06d42260181" name="Virginia_Minstrels,_1843" sectnum="4#1">../img/274f31e93aba1b0969eed06d42260181.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>