<document id="375a3ab409560e9ffd3a97600e85a88c-3" name="Old_Dan_Tucker" cat="20">
<text>
The origin of the music of "Old Dan Tucker" has always been obscure, and no sheet music edition from 1843, its year of its first publication, names a composer. The first performance of the tune (but not lyrics) may have happened as early as 1841.Nathan 301. The music may in fact be from the oral tradition or may have been a product of collaboration.

Nevertheless, "Old Dan Tucker" has been credited to at least three different songwriters: Dan Emmett, J. R. Jenkins, and Henry Russell.Tracy 19. In his old age, Emmett related the traditional story to his biographer, H. Ogden Wintermute: "I composed ''Old Dan Tucker'' in 1830 or 1831, when I was fifteen or sixteen years old."Quoted in Chase 239. The biography claims that Emmett first played the song in public at a performance by a group of traveling entertainers. They lacked a fiddle player, and the local innkeeper suggested young Emmett to fill in. Emmett played "Old Dan Tucker" to the troupe manager's liking, and he debuted on the Mount Vernon, Ohio, village green in blackface to perform the song on the Fourth of July. Wintermute claims that the name Dan Tucker is a combination of Emmett's own name and that of his dog.Canebrake Minstrels.Knowles 233, note 13. However, there is no evidence for any of this.Rammel 91. Instead, Emmett may merely have written the words. Even these seem to partially derive from an earlier minstrel song called "Walk Along John" or "Oh, Come Along John", first published in various songsters in the early 1840s.Rammel 90. Some verses have clear echoes in versions of "Old Dan Tucker":

:Johnny law on de rail road track,
:He tied de engine on his back;
:He pair's his corn wid a rail road wheel,
:It gib 'em de tooth ache in de heel.Quoted in Rammel 90.

The Charles Keith company published "Old Dan Tucker" in Boston, Massachusetts, in 1843. The sheet music credits words to Dan Emmett but says that the song is from "Old Dan Emmit's Original Banjo Melodies".Quoted in Crawford 206. The lack of attribution of the melody may be another sign that Emmett did not write it.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="70dbf23639113674bda594d51986ecb9" name="Dan_Emmett_old" sectnum="3#1">../img/70dbf23639113674bda594d51986ecb9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>