<document id="38826bae32085a573f3584a00871e198-3" name="Battle_of_Edson's_Ridge" cat="29">
<text>
At 13:05 on September 14 Kawaguchi led the survivors of his shattered brigade away from the ridge and deeper into the jungle, where they rested and tended to their wounded all the next day.  Kawaguchi's units were then ordered to withdraw west to the Matanikau River valley to join with Oka's unit, a six-mile (10 km) march over difficult terrain.  Kawaguchi's troops began the march on the morning of September 16.Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 193.  Almost every soldier able to walk had to help carry the wounded.  As the march progressed, the exhausted and hungry soldiers, who had eaten their last rations on September 14, began to discard their heavy equipment and then their rifles.  By the time most of them reached Oka's positions at Kokumbona five days later, only half still carried their weapons.  The Kuma battalion's survivors, attempting to follow Kawaguchi's Center Body forces, became lost and wandered for three weeks in the jungle and almost starved to death before finally reaching Kawaguchi's camp.Griffith, ''Battle for Guadalcanal'', p. 146–147 and Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 245–246.

In total, Kawaguchi's forces lost about 830 killed in the attack, including 350 in Tamura's battalion, 200 in Kokusho's battalion, 120 in Oka's force, 100 in the Kuma battalion, and 60 in Watanabe's battalion.  A further but unknown number of wounded died during the withdrawal march to the Matanikau.  On and around the ridge, the Marines counted 500 Japanese dead, including 200 on the slopes of Hill 123.  The Marines suffered 80 killed between September 12 and September 14.Christ, p. 281, Griffith, ''Battle for Guadalcanal'', p. 144 and Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 184–185.  Only 86 Paramarines, out of the 240 originally deployed, walked off of the ridge the morning after the battle; the rest were all killed or seriously wounded.  Christ states that 53 Marines were killed on the ridge and 237 seriously wounded, and that the Japanese suffered 1,133 killed or wounded.  The Americans buried the Japanese bodies in mass graves or burned them.

On September 17 Vandegrift sent two companies from the 1st Battalion, 1st Marine Regiment (1/1) to pursue the retreating Japanese.  The Marines were ambushed by two Japanese companies acting as rear-guards for the withdrawal, and one Marine platoon was pinned down as the rest of the Marines retreated.  The Marine company commander requested permission to attempt to rescue his platoon but was denied by Vandegrift.  By nightfall, the Japanese overran and nearly annihilated the platoon, killing 24 Marines with only a few wounded members of the platoon surviving.  On September 20, a patrol from Edson's Raiders encountered stragglers from Kawaguchi's retreating column and called in artillery fire that killed 19 of them.Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 193–194.  The Marine company commander of the annihilated platoon was Captain Charles Brush, who had led the patrol that ambushed a patrol from Ichiki's First Echelon during the Battle of the Tenaru.

As the Japanese regrouped west of the Matanikau, the U.S. forces concentrated on shoring up and strengthening their Lunga defenses.  On September 14, Vandegrift moved another battalion, the 3rd Battalion, 2nd Marine Regiment (3/2), from Tulagi to Guadalcanal.  On September 18, an Allied naval convoy delivered 4,157 men from the 3rd Provisional Marine Brigade (the U.S. 7th Marine Regiment augmented by additional support units) to Guadalcanal.  These reinforcements allowed Vandegrift, beginning on September 19, to establish an unbroken line of defense completely around the Lunga perimeter.  Vandegrift's forces' next significant clashes with the Japanese occurred along the Matanikau River from September 23 to 27 and October 6 to 9.Griffith, ''Battle for Guadalcanal'', p. 156 and Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 198–200.  The transport ships that had delivered the 7th Marines departed with the approximately 100 survivors of the originally 361-strong 1st Parachute Battalion (Hoffman, ''Silk Chutes'').
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="36952ef5503f0e1092bfde36fa209190" name="GuadEdsonRidgeDeadJapaneseSoldiers" sectnum="3#1">../img/36952ef5503f0e1092bfde36fa209190.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>