<document id="38826bae32085a573f3584a00871e198-4" name="Battle_of_Edson's_Ridge" cat="29">
<text>
On September 15 General Hyakutake at Rabaul learned of Kawaguchi's defeat, the Imperial Japanese Army's first defeat involving a unit of this size in the war.  The general forwarded the news to the Imperial General Headquarters in Japan.  In an emergency session, the top Japanese army and navy command staffs concluded that, "Guadalcanal might develop into the decisive battle of the war."  The results of the battle began to have a telling strategic impact on Japanese operations in other areas of the Pacific.  Hyakutake realized that, in order to send sufficient troops and materiel to defeat the Allied forces on Guadalcanal, he could no longer support the major Japanese offensive on the Kokoda Track in New Guinea.  Hyakutake, with the concurrence of the General Headquarters, ordered his troops on New Guinea, who were within  of their objective of Port Moresby, to withdraw until the Guadalcanal matter was resolved.  The Japanese were never able to restart their drive towards Port Moresby; the defeat at Edson's Ridge contributed not only to Japan's defeat in the Guadalcanal campaign, but also to Japan's ultimate defeat throughout the South Pacific.Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 197–198.

After delivering more forces during the next month the Japanese mounted a major ground offensive on Guadalcanal, led by Hyakutake, in late October 1942 at the Battle for Henderson Field, but it resulted in an even more decisive defeat for the Japanese.  Vandegrift later stated that Kawaguchi's assault on the ridge in September was the only time during the entire campaign he had doubts about the outcome and that had it succeeded, "we would have been in a pretty bad condition."Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 190–191.  Historian Richard B. Frank adds, "The Japanese never came closer to victory on the island itself than in September 1942, on a ridge thrusting up from the jungle just south of the critical airfield, best known ever after as Bloody Ridge."Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. vii.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4ab71ae754363bc31d76dc23c3756d50" name="EdsonsWatercolor" sectnum="4#1">../img/4ab71ae754363bc31d76dc23c3756d50.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>