<document id="38826bae32085a573f3584a00871e198-1.2" name="Battle_of_Edson's_Ridge" cat="29">
<text>
On August 28, 600 of Kawaguchi's troops were loaded onto the destroyers ''Asagiri'', ''Amagiri'', ''Yugiri'', and ''Shirakumo'', designated Destroyer Division 20 (DD20).  Because of a shortage of fuel, DD20 could not make the entire round trip to Guadalcanal at high speed in one night, but had to start the trip earlier in the day so that they could complete the trip by the next morning at a slower speed which conserved fuel.  At 18:05 that day 11 U.S. dive bombers from VMSB-232 under the command of Lt. Col. Richard Mangrum,Hulbert and DeChant, ''Flying Leathernecks'', p. 49. flew from Henderson Field and located and attacked DD20 about 110 kilometers (70 mi) north of Guadalcanal, sinking ''Asagiri'' and heavily damaging ''Yugiri'' and ''Shirakumo''.  ''Amagiri'' took ''Shirakumo'' in tow and the three destroyers returned to the Shortlands without completing their mission.  The attack on DD20 killed 62 of Kawaguchi's soldiers and 94 crew members.Griffith, ''Battle for Guadalcanal'', p. 114, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 199–200, and Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 98.

Subsequent "Express" runs were more successful.  Between August 29 and September 4, various Japanese light cruisers, destroyers, and patrol boats were able to land almost 5,000 troops at Taivu Point, including all of the 35th Infantry Brigade, one battalion of the Aoba Regiment, and the rest of Ichiki's regiment.  General Kawaguchi, who landed at Taivu Point on the August 31 Express run, was placed in command of all the Japanese troops on Guadalcanal.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 201–203, Griffith, ''Battle for Guadalcanal'', p. 116–124, and Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 87–112.  On the night of September 4&ndash;5, as three of the Express destroyers&mdash;''Yudachi'', ''Hatsuyuki'', and ''Murakumo''&mdash;prepared to shell Henderson Field after landing their troops, they detected and sank two U.S. ships in the vicinity, the small, old destroyer transports (called "APDs" by the U.S. Marines) USS ''Little'' and USS ''Gregory'' that were used to shuttle Allied troops around the Guadalcanal/Tulagi area.Frank, '' Guadalcanal'', p. 211–212, Peatross, ''Bless 'em All'', p. 91–92, and Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 118–the 121.

In spite of the successes of the destroyer runs, Kawaguchi insisted that as many soldiers of his brigade as possible be delivered to Guadalcanal by slow barges.  Therefore, a convoy carrying 1,100 of Kawaguchi's troops and heavy equipment in 61 barges, mainly from the 2nd Battalion, 124th Infantry Regiment under the command of Colonel Akinosuka Oka, departed the northern coast of Santa Isabel Island on September 2.  On September 4 and 5, aircraft from Henderson Field attacked the barge convoy, killing about 90 of the soldiers in the barges and destroying much of the unit's heavy equipment.  Most of the remaining 1,000 troops were able to land near Kamimbo (), west of the Lunga perimeter over the next few days.Alexander, p. 138–139, Griffith, ''Battle for Guadalcanal'', p. 116–124, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 213, and Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 106–109.  Griffith says 400 troops were killed, Frank and Smith say 90 were killed.  Oka commanded the entire 124th Regiment so his command section was attached to the 2nd Battalion at this time.  The 2nd Battalion's commander, Major Takamatsu, was killed during the air attacks on the barge convoy.  By September 7, Kawaguchi had 5,200 troops at Taivu Point and 1,000 west of the Lunga perimeter.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 219.  Kawaguchi was confident enough that he could defeat the Allied forces facing him that he declined an offer from the 17th Army for delivery of one more infantry battalion to augment his forces.  Kawaguchi believed that there were only about 2,000 U.S. Marines on Guadalcanal.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 218.


During this time, Vandegrift continued to direct efforts to strengthen and improve the defenses of the Lunga perimeter.  Between August 21 and September 3, he relocated three Marine battalions, including the 1st Raider Battalion, under U.S. Lieutenant Colonel Merritt A. Edson (Edson's Raiders), and the 1st Parachute Battalion from Tulagi and Gavutu to Guadalcanal.  These units added about 1,500 troops to Vandegrift's original 11,000 men defending Henderson Field.Peatross, ''Bless 'em All'', p. 91, Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 15 and Hough, ''Pearl Harbor to Guadalcanal'', p. 298.  U.S. transport destroyer ''Colhoun'' was sunk by Japanese aircraft off Guadalcanal on August 30, after delivering Company D of the 1st Raiders, with 51 of her crew killed.  The 1st Parachute battalion, which had suffered heavy casualties in the Battle of Tulagi and Gavutu-Tanambogo in August, was placed under Edson's command.Christ, p. 176, Smith, ''Bloody Ridge'', p. 103.  The Parachutists were delivered to Guadalcanal on September 2.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="916ca5b29a867ab53c7aff5964da940d" name="GuadAoba" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/916ca5b29a867ab53c7aff5964da940d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>