<document id="396fd1a668d97e3699cbe3b4c9cd76d1-2.2" name="Diocletian" cat="25">
<text>
After his accession, Diocletian and Lucius Caesonius BassusFully, L. Caesonius Ovinius Manlius Rufinianus Bassus. were named as consuls.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 5; Bowman, "Diocletian and the First Tetrarchy" (CAH), 69; Potter, 280; Southern, 134. They assumed the ''fasces'' in place of Carinus and Numerianus. Bassus was a member of a Campanian senatorial family, a former consul and a proconsul of Africa. He had been chosen by Probus for signal distinction. He was a man skilled in areas of government where Diocletian, presumably, had no experience. Diocletian's elevation of Bassus as consul symbolized his rejection of Carinus' government in Rome, his refusal to accept second-tier status to any other emperor, and his willingness to continue the long-standing collaboration between the empire's senatorial and military aristocracies. It also tied his success to that of the Senate, whose support he would need in an advance on Rome.

Diocletian was not the only challenger to Carinus' rule; the usurper M. Aurelius Julianus, Carinus' ''corrector Venetiae'', took control of northern Italy and Pannonia after Diocletian's accession.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 5; Bowman, "Diocletian and the First Tetrarchy" (CAH), 69; Leadbetter, "Carinus"; Southern, 134&ndash;35; Williams, 38. See also Banchich. He minted coins from the mint at Siscia (Sisak, Croatia) declaring himself as emperor and promising freedom. It was all good press for Diocletian, and aided in his portrayal of Carinus as a cruel and oppressive tyrant.Southern, 134&ndash;5; Williams, 38. Julianus' forces were weak, however, and were handily dispersed when Carinus' armies moved from Britain to northern Italy. As leader of the united East, Diocletian was clearly the greater threat.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 5; Bowman, "Diocletian and the First Tetrarchy" (CAH), 69; Leadbetter, "Carinus." Over the winter of 284&ndash;85, Diocletian advanced west across the Balkans. In the spring, some time before the end of May,Bowman, "Diocletian and the First Tetrarchy" (CAH), 69; Potter, 280. his armies met Carinus' across the river Margus (Great Morava) in Moesia. In modern accounts, the site has been located between the Mons Aureus (Seone, west of Smederevo) and Viminacium,Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 5. near modern Belgrade, Serbia.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 5; Odahl, 40; Southern, 135. 

Despite having the stronger army, Carinus held the weaker position. His rule was unpopular; it was subsequently alleged that Carinus had mistreated the Senate and seduced the wives of his officers.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 5; Williams, 37&ndash;38. It is possible that Flavius Constantius, the governor of Dalmatia and Diocletian's associate in the household guard, had already defected to Diocletian in the early spring.Potter, 280; Williams, 37. When the Battle of the Margus began, Carinus' prefect Aristobulus also defected. In the course of the battle, Carinus was killed by his own men. Following Diocletian's victory, both the western and the eastern armies acclaimed him emperor.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 5; Bowman, "Diocletian and the First Tetrarchy" (CAH), 69; Odahl, 40; Williams, 38. Diocletian exacted an oath of allegiance from the defeated army and departed for Italy.Southern, 135; Williams, 38.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4bc66a7eb7efd1a771d955b608c7bc34" name="Montemartini_-_Carino_1030439" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/4bc66a7eb7efd1a771d955b608c7bc34.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>