<document id="396fd1a668d97e3699cbe3b4c9cd76d1-4.6" name="Diocletian" cat="25">
<text>
Some time after his return, and before 293, Diocletian transferred command of the war against Carausius from Maximian to Flavius Constantius. Constantius was a former governor of Dalmatia and a man of military experience stretching back to Aurelian's campaigns against Zenobia (272&ndash;73). He was Maximian's praetorian prefect in Gaul, and the husband to Maximian's daughter, Theodora. On March 1, 293 at Milan, Maximian gave Constantius the office of Caesar.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 8&ndash;9; Barnes, ''New Empire'', 4, 36&ndash;37; Potter, 288; Southern, 146; Williams, 64&ndash;65. In the spring of 293, in either Philippopolis (Plovdiv, Bulgaria) or Sirmium, Diocletian would do the same for Galerius, husband to Diocletian's daughter Valeria, and perhaps Diocletian's praetorian prefect. Constantius was assigned Gaul and Britain. Galerius was assigned Syria, Palestine, Egypt, and responsibility for the eastern borderlands.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 8&ndash;9; Williams, 67.

This arrangement is called the Tetrarchy, from a Greek term meaning "rulership by four".Southern, 145. The Tetrarchic emperors were more or less sovereign in their own lands, and they travelled with their own imperial courts, administrators, secretaries, and armies.Corcoran, "Before Constantine", 45&ndash;46; Williams, 67. They were joined by blood and marriage; Diocletian and Maximian now styled themselves as brothers. The senior co-emperors formally adopted Galerius and Constantius as sons in 293. These relationships implied a line of succession. Galerius and Constantius would become Augusti after Diocletian and Maximian's departure. Maximian's son Maxentius, and Constantius' son Constantine would then become Caesars. In preparation for their future roles, Constantine and Maxentius were taken to Diocletian's court in Nicomedia.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 8&ndash;9.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c924a35e1f1a45712a1cdc60c1ed1eae" name="Sbeitla_10" sectnum="4.6#1">../img/c924a35e1f1a45712a1cdc60c1ed1eae.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>