<document id="396fd1a668d97e3699cbe3b4c9cd76d1-6.11" name="Diocletian" cat="25">
<text>
Diocletian entered the city of Rome in the early winter of 303. On November 20, he celebrated, with Maximian, the twentieth anniversary of his reign (''vicennalia''), the tenth anniversary of the Tetrarchy (''decennalia''), and a triumph for the war with Persia. Diocletian soon grew impatient with the city, as the Romans acted towards him with what Edward Gibbon, following Lactantius, calls "licentious familiarity"Gibbon, ''Decline and Fall'', I, 153 and 712, note 92. The Roman people did not give enough deference to his supreme authority; it expected him to act the part of an aristocratic ruler, not a monarchic one. On December 20, 303,Potter, 341. Diocletian cut short his stay in Rome and left for the north. He did not even perform the ceremonies investing him with his ninth consulate; he did them in Ravenna on January 1, 304 instead.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 24&ndash;25. There are suggestions in the ''Panegyrici Latini'' and Lactantius' account that Diocletian arranged plans for his and Maximian's future retirement of power in Rome. Maximian, according to these accounts, swore to uphold Diocletian's plan in a ceremony in the temple of Jupiter.''Panegyrici Latini'' 7(6)15.16; Lactantius, ''De Mortibus Persecutorum'' 20.4; Southern, 152, 336.

From Ravenna, Diocletian left for the Danube. There, possibly in Galerius' company, he took part in a campaign against the Carpi. He contracted a minor illness while on campaign, but his condition quickly worsened and he chose to travel in a litter. In the late summer he left for Nicomedia. On November 20, he appeared in public to dedicate the opening of the circus beside his palace. He collapsed soon after the ceremonies. Over the winter of 304&ndash;5 he kept within his palace at all times. Rumors alleging that Diocletian's death was merely being kept secret until Galerius could come to assume power spread through the city. On December 13, he seemed to have finally died. The city was sent into a mourning from which it was only retrieved by public declarations of his survival. When Diocletian reappeared in public on March 1, 305, he was emaciated and barely recognizable.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 25; Southern, 152.

Galerius arrived in the city later in March. According to Lactantius, he came armed with plans to reconstitute the Tetrarchy, force Diocletian to step down, and fill the imperial office with men compliant to his will. Through coercion and threats, he eventually convinced Diocletian to comply with his plan. Lactantius also claims that he had done the same to Maximian at Sirmium.Lactantius, ''De Mortibus Persecutorum'' 18.1&ndash;7; Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 25; Southern, 152. On May 1, 305, Diocletian called an assembly of his generals, traditional companion troops, and representatives from distant legions. They met at the same hill,  out of Nicomedia, where Diocletian had been proclaimed emperor. In front of a statue of Jupiter, his patron deity, Diocletian addressed the crowd. With tears in his eyes, he told them of his weakness, his need for rest, and his will to resign. He declared that he needed to pass the duty of empire on to someone stronger. He thus became the first Roman emperor to voluntarily abdicate his title.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 25&ndash;27; Lenski, "Reign of Constantine," 60; Odahl, 69&ndash;72; Potter, 341&ndash;42.

Most in the crowd believed they knew what would follow; Constantine and Maxentius, the only adult sons of a reigning emperor, men who had long been preparing to succeed their fathers, would be granted the title of Caesar. Constantine had traveled through Palestine at the right hand of Diocletian, and was present at the palace in Nicomedia in 303 and 305. It is likely that Maxentius received the same treatment.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 25&ndash;26. In Lactantius' account, when Diocletian announced that he was to resign, the entire crowd turned to face Constantine.Lactantius, ''De Mortibus Persecutorum'' 19.2&ndash;6; Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 26; Potter, 342. It was not to be: Severus and Maximin were declared Caesars. Maximin appeared and took Diocletian's robes. On the same day, Severus received his robes from Maximian in Milan. Constantius succeeded Maximian as Augustus of the West, but Constantine and Maxentius were entirely ignored in the transition of power. This did not bode well for the future security of the Tetrarchic system.Lenski, "Reign of Constantine," 60&ndash;61; Odahl, 72&ndash;74; Southern, 152&ndash;53.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="79199a7a1037e34a349b8eeef7628d5f" name="SPLIT-Hebrard_overall_color_restitution" sectnum="6.11#1">../img/79199a7a1037e34a349b8eeef7628d5f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>