<document id="396fd1a668d97e3699cbe3b4c9cd76d1-7.17.4" name="Diocletian" cat="25">
<text>
By the early 280s, market forces had created a stable exchange rate between gold and the copper ''antoninianus'', more or less stabilizing commodity prices. The ''antoninianus'', which had become the standard medium, however, remained a serious issue:Southern, 160. In spite of attempts to wean the nation off metal currency by converting governmental taxes and salaries to annonary payments in kind, metal currency remained in wide circulation.Cascio, "The New State of Diocletian and Constantine" (CAH), 176. In the wake of a brief period of re-inflation, Diocletian began a more comprehensive reform of the currency in 293.Potter, 392. The new system consisted of five coins: the ''aureus''/''solidus'', a gold coin weighing, like its predecessors, one-sixtieth of a pound; the ''argenteus'', a coin weighing one ninety-sixth of a pound and containing ninety-five percent pure silver; the ''follis'', sometimes referred to as the ''laureatus'' A, which is a copper coin with added silver struck at the rate of thirty-two to the pound; the ''radiatus'', a small copper coin struck at the rate of 108 to the pound, with no added silver; and a coin known today as the ''laureatus'' B, a smaller copper coin struck at the rate of 192 to the pound.Potter, 392&ndash;93. Since the nominal values of these new issues were lower than their intrinsic worth as metals, the state was minting these coins at a loss. This practice could be sustained only by requisitioning precious metals from private citizens in exchange for state-minted coin (of a far lower value than the price of the precious metals requisitioned).

By 301, however, the system was in trouble, strained by a new bout of inflation. Diocletian therefore issued his ''Edict on Coinage'', an act re-tariffing all debts so that the ''nummi'', the most common coin in circulation, would be worth half as much.Potter, 334, 393; Southern, 160. In the edict, preserved in an inscription from the city of Aphrodisias in Caria (near Geyre, Turkey), it was declared that all debts contracted before September 1, 301 would be repaid at the old standards, while all debts contracted after September 1 would be repaid at the new standards.Potter, 334&ndash;35. It appears that the edict was made in an attempt to preserve the current price of gold and to keep the empire's coinage on silver, Rome's traditional metal currency.Potter, 393. This edict risked giving further momentum to inflationary trends, as had happened after Aurelian's currency reforms. Soon the Tetrarchic government could see no better solution to its monetary woes than a series of price freezes.Cascio, "The New State of Diocletian and Constantine" (CAH), 176&ndash;77.

The ''Edict on Maximum Prices'' (''Edictum De Pretiis Rerum Venalium'') was issued two to three months after the coinage edict, somewhere between November 20 and December 10, 301. The best-preserved Latin inscription surviving from the Greek East,Potter, 336. the edict survives in many versions, on materials as varied as wood, papyrus, and stone.Southern, 160, 339.  In the edict, Diocletian declared that the current pricing crisis resulted from the unchecked greed of merchants, and had resulted in turmoil for the mass of common citizens. The language of the edict calls on the people's memory of their benevolent leaders, and exhorts them to enforce the provisions of the edict, and thereby restore perfection to the world. The edict goes on to list in detail over one thousand goods and accompanying retail prices not to be exceeded. Penalties are laid out for various pricing transgressions.Cascio, "The New State of Diocletian and Constantine" (CAH), 177&ndash;78; Potter, 335; Southern, 161.

In the most basic terms, the edict was ignorant of the law of supply and demand: it ignored the fact that prices might vary from region to region according to product availability, and it ignored the impact of transportation costs in the retail price of goods. In the judgment of the historian David Potter, the edict was "an act of economic lunacy".Potter, 335. Inflation, speculation, and monetary instability continued, and a black market arose to trade in goods forced out of official markets.Cascio, "The New State of Diocletian and Constantine" (CAH), 178. The edict's penalties were applied unevenly across the empire (some scholars believe they were applied only in Diocletian's domainsCascio, "The New State of Diocletian and Constantine" (CAH), 177.), widely resisted, and eventually dropped, perhaps within a year of the edict's issue.Potter, 336; Southern, 161. Lactantius has written of the perverse accompaniments to the edict; of goods withdrawn from the market, of brawls over minute variations in price, of the deaths that came when its provisions were enforced. His account may be true, but it seems to modern historians exaggerated and hyperbolic,Lactantius, ''De Mortibus Persecutorum'' 7.6&ndash;7, cited in Cascio, "The New State of Diocletian and Constantine" (CAH), 178, and Southern, 161. and the impact of the law is recorded in no other ancient source.Potter, 336; Williams, 131&ndash;32.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="307ea9f1d71aa535bc35bdd34d43d0af" name="Edict_on_Maximum_Prices_Diocletian_piece_in_Berlin" sectnum="7.17.4#1">../img/307ea9f1d71aa535bc35bdd34d43d0af.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>