<document id="396fd1a668d97e3699cbe3b4c9cd76d1-7.15" name="Diocletian" cat="25">
<text>
As with most emperors, much of Diocletian's daily routine rotated around legal affairs&mdash;responding to appeals and petitions, and delivering decisions on disputed matters. Rescripts, authoritative interpretations issued by the emperor in response to demands from disputants in both public and private cases, were a common duty of second- and third-century emperors. Diocletian was awash in paperwork, and was nearly incapable of delegating his duties. It would have been seen as a dereliction of duty to ignore them. Diocletian's praetorian prefects&mdash;Afranius Hannibalianus, Julius Asclepiodotus, and Flavius Constantius&mdash;aided in regulating the flow and presentation of such paperwork, but the deep legalism of Roman culture kept the workload heavy.Williams, 53&ndash;54, 142&ndash;43. Emperors in the forty years preceding Diocletian's reign had not managed these duties so effectively, and their output in attested rescripts is low. Diocletian, by contrast, was prodigious in his affairs: there are around 1,200 rescripts in his name still surviving, and these probably represent only a small portion of the total issue.Johnston, "Epiclassical Law" (CAH), 201; Williams, ''Diocletian''. 143. The sharp increase in the number of edicts and rescripts produced under Diocletian's rule has been read as evidence of a thoroughgoing effort to realign the whole empire on terms dictated by the imperial center.Potter, 296, 652.

Under the governance of the jurists Gregorius, Aurelius Arcadius Charisius, and Hermogenianus, the imperial government began issuing official books of precedent, collecting and listing all the rescripts that had been issued from the reign of Hadrian (r. 117&ndash;38) to the reign of Diocletian.Harries, 14&ndash;15; Potter, 295&ndash;96. The ''Codex Gregorianus'' includes rescripts up to 292, which the ''Codex Hermogenianus'' updated with a comprehensive collection of rescripts issued by Diocletian in 293 and 294. Although the very act of codification was a radical innovation, given the decentralized nature of the Roman legal system,Potter, 295&ndash;96. the jurists themselves were generally conservative, and constantly looked to past Roman practice and theory for guidance.Harries, 21, 29&ndash;30; Potter, 295&ndash;96. They were probably given more free rein over their codes than the compilers of the ''Codex Theodosianus'' (438) and ''Codex Justinianus'' (529) would have. Gregorius and Hermogenianus' codices lack the rigid structuring of later codes,Harries, 21&ndash;22. and were not published in the name of the emperor, but in the names of their compilers.Harries, 63&ndash;64.

After Diocletian's reform of the provinces, governors were called ''iudex'', or judge. The governor became responsible for his decisions first to his immediate superiors, as well as to the more distant office of the emperor.Harries, 162. It was most likely at this time that judicial records became verbatim accounts of what was said in trial, making it easier to determine bias or improper conduct on the part of the governor. With these records and the empire's universal right of appeal, imperial authorities probably had a great deal of power to enforce behavior standards for their judges.Harries, 167. In spite of Diocletian's attempts at reform, the provincial restructuring was far from clear, especially when citizens appealed the decisions of their governors. Proconsuls, for example, were often both judges of first instance and appeal, and the governors of some provinces took appellant cases from their neighbors. It soon became impossible to avoid taking some cases to the emperor for arbitration and judgment.Harries, 55. Diocletian's reign marks the end of the classical period of Roman law. Where Diocletian's system of rescripts shows an adherence to classical tradition, Constantine's law is full of Greek and eastern influences.Johnston, "Epiclassical Law" (CAH), 207.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0b6e8d76d94dfcbf16cc38218a66b7fa" name="Digesto_02" sectnum="7.15#1">../img/0b6e8d76d94dfcbf16cc38218a66b7fa.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>