<document id="3a1acd1fe8b9c3dad8fa395a7ed61d08-1.9" name="Bette_Davis" cat="19">
<text>
In the early 1970s, Davis was invited to appear in New York, in a stage presentation, ''Great Ladies of the American Cinema.'' Over five successive nights, a different female star discussed her career and answered questions from the audience; Myrna Loy, Rosalind Russell, Lana Turner and Joan Crawford were the other participants. Davis was well received and was invited to tour Australia with the similarly themed, ''Bette Davis in Person and on Film,'' and its success allowed her to take the production to the United Kingdom.Chandler (2006), pp 258–59

In 1972, she played the lead role in two television films that were each intended as pilots for upcoming series for NBC, ''Madame Sin'' with Robert Wagner, and  ''The Judge and Jake Wyler,'' with Joan Van Ark, but in each case, NBC decided against producing a series. 

In the U.S., she appeared in the stage production, ''Miss Moffat,'' a musical adaptation of ''The Corn is Green,'' but after the show was panned by the Philadelphia critics during its pre-Broadway run, she cited a back injury and abandoned the show, which closed immediately. She played supporting roles in ''Burnt Offerings'' (1976) and ''The Disappearance of Aimee'' (1976), but she clashed with Karen Black and Faye Dunaway, respectively the stars of the two productions, because she felt that neither extended her an appropriate degree of respect, and that their behavior on the film sets was unprofessional.Spada (1993), pp 414 (Karen Black), 416 (Faye Dunaway)

In 1977, Davis became the first woman to receive the American Film Institute's Lifetime Achievement Award. The televised event included comments from several of Davis's colleagues including William Wyler who joked that given the chance Davis would still like to refilm a scene from ''The Letter'' to which Davis nodded. Jane Fonda, Henry Fonda, Natalie Wood and Olivia de Havilland were among the actors who paid tribute, with de Havilland commenting that Davis "got the roles I always wanted".Spada (1993), p 424

Following the telecast she found herself in demand again, often having to choose between several offers. She accepted roles in the television miniseries ''The Dark Secret of Harvest Home'' (1978) and the theatrical film ''Death on the Nile'' (1978), an Agatha Christie murder mystery. The bulk of her remaining work was for television. She won an Emmy Award for ''Strangers: The Story of a Mother and Daughter'' (1979) with Gena Rowlands, and was nominated for her performances in ''White Mama'' (1980) and ''Little Gloria... Happy at Last'' (1982). She also played supporting roles in two Disney films, ''Return from Witch Mountain'' (1978) and ''The Watcher in the Woods'' (1980).

Davis's name became well-known to a younger audience when Kim Carnes's song "Bette Davis Eyes" became a worldwide hit and the best-selling record of 1981 in the U.S., where it stayed at number one on the music charts for more than two months. Davis's grandson was impressed that she was the subject of a hit song and Davis considered it a compliment, writing to both Carnes and the songwriters, and accepting the gift of gold and platinum records from Carnes, and hanging them on her wall.Davis (1987), p 112

She continued acting for television, appearing in ''Family Reunion'' (1981) opposite her grandson J. Ashley Hyman, ''A Piano for Mrs. Cimino'' (1982) and ''Right of Way'' (1983) with James Stewart.

In 1985, Davis donated 59 scrapbooks to Boston University library. Upon examination, the library's staff found a photograph of Joan Crawford with all her teeth blacked out.Robertson, Patrick. ''The Guinness Book of Almost Everything You Didn't Need to Know About the Movies''. Great Britain: Guinness Superlatives Ltd., Enfield, Middlesex, 1986. ISBN 0-85112-481-X, p. 139
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9ca6ae30b9b01b8869fcf8a10305def1" name="DavisTaylor" sectnum="1.9#1">../img/9ca6ae30b9b01b8869fcf8a10305def1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>