<document id="3a1acd1fe8b9c3dad8fa395a7ed61d08-1.8" name="Bette_Davis" cat="19">
<text>
In 1961, Davis opened in the Broadway production ''The Night of the Iguana'' to mostly mediocre reviews, and left the production after four months due to "chronic illness". She then joined Glenn Ford and Ann-Margret for the Frank Capra film ''A Pocketful of Miracles'' (1961) (a remake of Capra's ''Lady for a Day'' (1933)), based on a story by Damon Runyon. She accepted her next role, in the Grand Guignol horror film ''What Ever Happened to Baby Jane?'' (1962) after reading the script and believing it could appeal to the same audience that had recently made Alfred Hitchcock's ''Psycho'' (1960) a success. She negotiated a deal that would pay her 10 percent of the worldwide gross profits, in addition to her salary. The film became one of the year's biggest successes.Spada (1993), pp 353–55

Davis and Joan Crawford played two aging sisters, former actresses forced by circumstance to share a decaying Hollywood mansion. The director, Robert Aldrich, explained that Davis and Crawford were each aware of how important the film was to their respective careers and commented, "It's proper to say that they really detested each other, but they behaved absolutely perfectly."Guiles (1995), p 186 After filming was completed, their public comments against each other allowed the tension to develop into a lifelong feud, and when Davis was nominated for an Academy Award, Crawford campaigned against her. Davis also received her only BAFTA Award nomination for this performance.

Daughter B.D. played a small role in the film and when she and Davis visited the Cannes Film Festival to promote it, she met Jeremy Hyman, an executive for Seven Arts Productions. After a short courtship, she married Hyman at the age of 16, with Davis's permission.

In September 1962, Davis placed an advertisement in ''Variety'' under the heading of "Situations wanted - women artists", which read, "Mother of three—10, 11 & 15—divorcee. American. Thirty years experience as an actress in Motion Pictures. Mobile still and more affable than rumor would have it. Wants steady employment in Hollywood. (Has had Broadway)." Davis said that she intended it as a joke, and she sustained her comeback over the course of several years. ''Dead Ringer'' (1964) was a crime drama in which she played twin sisters and ''Where Love Has Gone'' (1964) was a romantic drama based on a Harold Robbins novel. Davis played the mother of Susan Hayward but filming was hampered by heated arguments between Davis and Hayward.Spada (1993), p 376 ''Hush... Hush, Sweet Charlotte'' (1964) was Robert Aldrich's follow-up to ''What Ever Happened to Baby Jane?'', in which he planned to reunite Davis and Crawford, but when Crawford withdrew allegedly due to illness soon after filming began, she was replaced by Olivia de Havilland. The film was a considerable success and brought renewed attention to its veteran cast, which also included Joseph Cotten, Mary Astor and Agnes Moorehead.

In 1964 Davis was cast as the lead in an Aaron Spelling sitcom, ''The Decorator''.  A pilot episode was filmed, but was not shown, and the project was terminated.  By the end of the decade, Davis had appeared in the British films ''The Nanny'' (1965), ''The Anniversary'' (1968), and ''Connecting Rooms'' (1970), but her career again stalled.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9f09274d5e08102dd1dd9ec846a53bb8" name="Bette_Davis_and_Joan_Crawford_in_Whatever_Happened_to_Baby_Jane_trailer" sectnum="1.8#1">../img/9f09274d5e08102dd1dd9ec846a53bb8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>