<document id="3a8aad3f81b9e8585d9a9b6cb074931f-3" name="Henry_James" cat="17">
<text>
James never married, and after settling in London proclaimed himself "a bachelor" and regularly rejected suggestions that he marry. After his death, critics speculated on the cause of his bachelorhood. F. W. Dupee, in several well-regarded volumes on the James family, originated the theory that James had been in love with his cousin Mary ("Minnie") Temple, but that a neurotic fear of sex kept him from admitting such affections: "James's invalidism . . . was itself the symptom of some fear of or scruple against sexual love on his part." Dupee used an episode from James's memoir ''A Small Boy and Others,'' recounting a dream of a Napoleonic images in the Louvre, to exemplify James's romanticism about Europe, a Napoleonic fantasy into which he fled.See Dupee (1949) and (1951), collecting earlier papers. This analysis seemed to support literary critics like Van Wyck Brooks and Vernon Parrington who had condemned James's expatriation, and who criticized his work as effeminate and deracinated. Leon Edel used it as the premise of his own masterly biography, which held the field for many years. Dupee had not been given access to the James family papers, however, and had worked principally from James's published memoir of his older brother, and the limited collection of letters edited by Percy Lubbock, which was heavily weighted toward James's last years. Dupee's account, perhaps as a result, portrayed James as a man moving directly from childhood, when he trailed after his older brother, to an elderly invalidism. 

As more material became available to scholars, including the diaries of contemporaries and hundreds of affectionate and sometimes erotic letters written by James to younger men, the picture of neurotic celibacy gave way to a portrait of a closeted homosexual. As author Terry Eagleton has stated, "...gay critics debate exactly how repressed his (probable) homosexuality was...""The asperity papers" (June 24, 2006) by Terry Eagleton, a review of ''The Year of Henry James: The Story of a Novel'' by David Lodge in . James's letters to expatriate American sculptor Hendrik Christian Andersen have attracted particular attention. James met the 27-year-old Andersen in Rome in 1899, when James was 56, and wrote letters to Andersen that are intensely emotional: "I hold you, dearest boy, in my innermost love, & count on your feeling me—in every throb of your soul". In a letter of May 6, 1904 to his brother William, James referred to himself as "always your hopelessly celibate even though sexagenarian Henry".''The Correspondence of William James: Volume 3, William and Henry'' edited by Ignas Skrupskelis and Elizabeth Bradley (1994) p. 271. How accurate that description might have been is the subject of contention among James's biographers,See volume four of Edel's referenced biography, p.306–316, for a particularly long and inconclusive discussion on the subject. See also Bradley (1999) and (2000). but the letters to Andersen were occasionally quasi-erotic: "I put, my dear boy, my arm around you, & feel the pulsation, thereby, as it were, of our excellent future & your admirable endowment." Mamoli Zorzi, Rosella (Ed.) ''Beloved Boy: Letters to Hendrik C. Andersen, 1899–1915'' ISBN 0-8139-2270-4 To his homosexual friend Howard Sturgis, James could write: "I repeat, almost to indiscretion, that I could live with you. Meanwhile I can only try to live without you,"Gunter, Susan E; Jobe, Steven ''Dearly Beloved Friends: Henry James's Letters to Younger Men'' (2001) ISBN 0-472-11009-8 and it is only in letters to young gay men that James refers to himself as their "lover". James wrote to young men who are now thought to have been homosexual or bisexual, who made up a large fraction of his close male friends. In a letter to Howard Sturgis, following a long visit, James refers jocularly to their "happy little congress of two".Gunter and Jobe (2001) p.125 In letters to Hugh Walpole, James pursues involved jokes and puns about their relationship, referring to himself as an elephant who "paws you oh so benevolently" and winds about Walpole his "well meaning old trunk".Gunter and Jobe p.179 The privately printed letters to Walter Berry have long been celebrated for their lightly veiled eroticism.Black Sun Press (1927) 

However, James wrote to fellow-novelist Lucy Clifford: "Dearest Lucy! What shall I say? when I love you so very, very much, and see you nine times for once that I see Others! Therefore I think that—if you want it made clear to the meanest intelligence—I love you more than I love Others."''Bravest of Women and Finest of Friends: Henry James's Letters to Lucy Clifford'', edited by Marysa Demoor and Monty Chisholm, University of Victoria (1999), p.79 ISBN 0-920604-67-6 In another example he wrote to his New York friend Mary Cadwalader Jones:



His long friendship with American novelist Constance Fenimore Woolson, in whose house he lived for a number of weeks in Italy in 1887, and his shock and grief over her suicide in 1894, are discussed in detail in Leon Edel's biography and play a central role in a study by Lyndall Gordon. Edel conjectured that Woolson was in love with James and killed herself in part because of his coldness. Gordon builds on Edel's account and adds her own speculation that James felt guilt at having sabotaged Woolson's work. Woolson's biographers have strongly objected to Edel's account, however,,See e.g. Cheryl Torsney, ''Constance Fenimore Woolson: The Grief of Artistry'' (1989)("Edel's text. . . a convention-laden male fantasy"). and have generally portrayed James as a friend who advanced Woolson's career. Novick in his more recent account argues that the available evidence shows that James suffered strong emotions prompted by the apparent suicide of a friend and colleague, but that there is no evidence Woolson was in love with him or that he was the cause of her death.Novick (2007)pp. 202-204
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ec7074532667bc1faa6233a671a5be9c" name="HenryJamesatage16" sectnum="3#1">../img/ec7074532667bc1faa6233a671a5be9c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>