<document id="3a8aad3f81b9e8585d9a9b6cb074931f-8" name="Henry_James" cat="17">
<text>
James's work has remained steadily popular with the limited audience of educated readers to whom he spoke during his lifetime, and remained firmly in the British canon, but after his death American critics, such as Van Wyck Brooks, expressed hostility towards James's long expatriation and eventual naturalization as a British citizen.''The Pilgrimage of Henry James'' by Van Wyck Brooks (1925) develops this thesis at length. Other critics like E.M. Forster complained about what they saw as James's squeamishness in the treatment of sex and other possibly controversial material, or dismissed his style as difficult and obscure, relying heavily on extremely long sentences and excessively latinate language.''Aspects of the Novel'' by E.M. Forster p.153–163, (1956) ISBN 0-674-38780-5 Vernon Parrington, composing a canon of American literature, condemned James for having cut himself off from America. Although these criticisms have by no means abated completely, James is now widely valued for his psychological and moral realism, his masterful creation of character, his low-key but playful humor, and his assured command of the language. In his 1983 book, ''The Novels of Henry James'', Edward Wagenknecht offers an assessment that echoes Theodora Bosanquet's:



Early biographies of James echoed the unflattering picture of him drawn in early criticism. F.W. Dupee, as noted above, characterized James as neurotically withdrawn and fearful, and although Dupee lacked access to primary materials his view has remained persuasive in academic circles, partly because Leon Edel's massive five-volume work, published from 1953 to 1972, seemed to butress it with extensive documentation. Michael Anesko, Fred Kaplan, and Sheldon Novick, working from primary materials have disputed the factual basis of Dupee's and Edel's accounts. Other critics and biographers have disputed Edel's interpretations and conclusions. James has also figured in at least a half-dozen novels. Colm Tóibín used an extensive list of biographies of Henry James and his family for his widely admired 2004 novel, ''The Master'', which is a third person narrative with James as the central character, and deals with specific episodes from his life during the period between 1895 and 1899. ''Author, Author'', a novel by David Lodge published in the same year, was based on James's efforts to conquer the stage in the 1890s. In 2002 Emma Tennant published ''Felony: The Private History of The Aspern Papers'', a novel that fictionalized the relationship between James and American novelist Constance Fenimore Woolson and the possible effects of that relationship on ''The Aspern Papers''.

The published criticism of James's work has reached enormous proportions. The volume of criticism of ''The Turn of the Screw'' alone has become extremely large for such a brief work. ''The Henry James Review'', published three times a year, offers criticism of James's entire range of writings, and many other articles and book-length studies appear regularly. Some guides to this extensive literature can be found on the external sites listed below.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3e9f57bc8923643c4f6acf5270f9ed4a" name="LambHouseInterior" sectnum="8#1">../img/3e9f57bc8923643c4f6acf5270f9ed4a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>