<document id="3a8aad3f81b9e8585d9a9b6cb074931f-4" name="Henry_James" cat="17">
<text>
James is one of the major figures of trans-Atlantic literature. His works frequently juxtapose characters from the Old World (Europe), embodying a feudal civilization that is beautiful, often corrupt, and alluring, and from the New World (United States), where people are often brash, open, and assertive and embody the virtues — freedom and a more highly evolved moral character — of the new American society. James explores this clash of personalities and cultures, in stories of personal relationships in which power is exercised well or badly. His protagonists were often young American women facing oppression or abuse, and as his secretary Theodora Bosanquet remarked in her monograph ''Henry James at Work'':

 

Critics have jokingly described three phases in the development of James's prose: "James the First, James the Second, and The Old Pretender" and observers do often group his works of fiction into three periods. In his apprentice years, culminating with the masterwork ''The Portrait of a Lady,'' his style was simple and direct (by the standards of Victorian magazine writing) and he experimented widely with forms and methods, generally narrating from a conventionally omniscient point of view. Plots generally concern romance, except for the three big novels of social commentary that conclude this period. In the second period, as noted above, he abandoned the serialized novel and from 1890 to about 1897, he wrote short stories and plays. Finally, in his third and last period he returned to the long, serialized novel. Beginning in the second period, but most noticeably in the third, he increasingly abandoned direct statement in favor of frequent double negatives, and complex descriptive imagery. Single paragraphs began to run for page after page, in which an initial noun would be succeeded by pronouns surrounded by clouds of adjectives and prepositional clauses, far from their original referents, and verbs would be deferred and then preceded by a series of adverbs. The overall effect could be a vivid evocation of a scene as perceived by a sensitive observer. In its intense focus on the consciousness of his major characters, James's later work foreshadows extensive developments in 20th century fiction.See James's prefaces, Horne's study of his revisions for ''The New York Edition,'' Edward Wagenknecht's ''The Novels of Henry James'' (1983) among many discussions of the changes in James's narrative technique and style over the course of his career. Then and later many readers find the late style difficult and unnecessary; his friend Edith Wharton, who admired him greatly, said that there were passages in his work that were all but incomprehensible.''The Writing of Fiction'' by Edith Wharton, p.90–91 (1925) H.G. Wells harshly portrayed James as a hippopotamus laboriously attempting to pick up a pea that has got into a corner of its cage.H.G. Wells, Boon, The Mind of the Race, The Wild Asses of the Devil, and The Last Trump. London: T. Fisher Unwin (1915) p. 101. Some critics have claimed that the more elaborate manner was a result of James taking up the practice of dictating to a secretary. He was afflicted with a stutter and compensated by speaking slowly and deliberately. The late style does become more difficult in the years when he dictates, but James also was able to revise typewritten drafts more extensively, and his few surviving drafts show that the later works are more heavily revised and redrafted. In some cases this leads critics to prefer the earlier, unrevised versions of some works because the older style is thought to be closer to the original conception and spirit of the work, ''Daisy Miller'' being a case in point: most of the current reprints of this novel contain the unrevised text. On the other hand, the late revision of the early novel ''The Portrait of a Lady'' is generally much preferred to the first edition, even by those who dislike the late style, because of the power of the imagery and the depth of characterization, while his shorter late fiction, such as ''The Turn of the Screw'', is considered highly accessible and remains popular with readers.

More important for his work overall may have been his position as an expatriate, and in other ways an outsider, living in Europe. While he came from middle-class and provincial belongings (seen from the perspective of European polite society) he worked very hard to gain access to all levels of society, and the settings of his fiction range from working class to aristocratic, and often describe the efforts of middle-class Americans to make their way in European capitals. He confessed he got some of his best story ideas from gossip at the dinner table or at country house weekends.James's prefaces to the ''New York Edition'' of his fiction often discuss such origins for his stories. See, for instance, the preface to ''The Spoils of Poynton''. He worked for a living, however, and lacked the experiences of select schools, university, and army service, the common bonds of masculine society. He was furthermore a man whose tastes and interests were, according to the prevailing standards of Victorian era Anglo-American culture, rather feminine, and who was shadowed by the cloud of prejudice that then and later accompanied suspicions of his homosexuality.James himself noted his "outsider" status. In a letter of October 2, 1901 to W. Morton Fullerton, James talked of the "essential loneliness of my life" as "the deepest thing" about him (''Henry James Letters'' edited by Leon Edel, volume 4, p.170 (1984) ISBN 0-674-38780-5) Edmund Wilson famously compared James's objectivity to Shakespeare's:



It is also possible to see many of James's stories as psychological thought-experiments. ''The Portrait of a Lady'' may be an experiment to see what happens when an idealistic young woman suddenly becomes very rich. In many of his tales, characters seem to exemplify alternate futures and possibilities, as most markedly in "The Jolly Corner", in which the protagonist and a ghost-doppelganger live alternate American and European lives; and in others, like ''The Ambassadors,'' an older James seems fondly to regard his own younger self facing a crucial moment.Millicent Bell explores such themes in her monograph ''Meaning in Henry James''
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="923c82bb57d137da3b34709a274c7630" name="Portrait_of_Henry_James_1913" sectnum="4#1">../img/923c82bb57d137da3b34709a274c7630.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>