<document id="3a8aad3f81b9e8585d9a9b6cb074931f-7" name="Henry_James" cat="17">
<text>
Beyond his fiction, James was one of the more important literary critics in the history of the novel. In his classic essay ''The Art of Fiction'' (1884), he argued against rigid proscriptions on the novelist's choice of subject and method of treatment. He maintained that the widest possible freedom in content and approach would help ensure narrative fiction's continued vitality. James wrote many valuable critical articles on other novelists; typical is his insightful book-length study of his American predecessor Nathaniel Hawthorne. When he assembled the ''New York Edition'' of his fiction in his final years, James wrote a series of prefaces that subjected his own work to the same searching, occasionally harsh criticism.See the referenced editions of James's criticism and the related articles in the "Literary criticism" part of the "Notable works by James" section for further discussion of his critical essays.

For most of his life James harbored ambitions for success as a playwright. He converted his novel ''The American'' into a play that enjoyed modest returns in the early 1890s. In all he wrote about a dozen plays, most of which went unproduced. His costume drama ''Guy Domville'' failed disastrously on its opening night in 1895. James then largely abandoned his efforts to conquer the stage and returned to his fiction. In his ''Notebooks'' he maintained that his theatrical experiment benefited his novels and tales by helping him dramatize his characters' thoughts and emotions. James produced a small but valuable amount of theatrical criticism, including perceptive appreciations of Henrik Ibsen.''Henry James: The Scenic Art, Notes on Acting and the Drama 1872–1901'' edited by Allan Wade, p.243–260 (1948). For a general discussion of James's efforts as a playwright, see Edel's referenced edition of his plays.

With his wide-ranging artistic interests, James occasionally wrote on the visual arts. Perhaps his most valuable contribution was his favorable assessment of fellow expatriate John Singer Sargent, a painter whose critical status has improved markedly in recent decades. James also wrote sometimes charming, sometimes brooding articles about various places he visited and lived in. His most famous books of travel writing include ''Italian Hours'' (an example of the charming approach) and ''The American Scene'' (most definitely on the brooding side).Further information about these works can be found in the related articles in the "Travel writings" and "Visual arts criticism" parts of the "Notable works by James" section and in the referenced editions of James's travel writings.

James was one of the great letter-writers of any era. More than ten thousand of his personal letters are extant, and over three thousand have been published in a large number of collections. A complete edition of James's letters began publication in 2006 with two volumes covering the 1855–1872 period, edited by Pierre Walker and Greg Zacharias. James's correspondents included celebrated contemporaries like Robert Louis Stevenson, Edith Wharton and Joseph Conrad, along with many others in his wide circle of friends and acquaintances. The letters range from the "mere twaddle of graciousness"''Henry James Letters'' edited by Leon Edel, volume 4 p.208 (1983). Further information on James's letters can be found at . For more information on the complete edition of James's letters, see ''The Henry James Scholar's Guide to Web Sites'' in the "External links" section. to serious discussions of artistic, social and personal issues. Very late in life James began a series of autobiographical works: ''A Small Boy and Others'', ''Notes of a Son and Brother'', and the unfinished ''The Middle Years''. These books portray the development of a classic observer who was passionately interested in artistic creation but was somewhat reticent about participating fully in the life around him.See the referenced edition of James's autobiographical books by F.W. Dupee, which includes a critical introduction, an extensive index, and notes.

Henry James was only twenty-two when he wrote ''The Noble School of Fiction'' for ''The Nation'''s first issue in 1865. He wrote, in all, over two hundred essays and book, art and theater reviews for the magazine.Katrina Vanden Heuvel ''The Nation 1865-1990'', p. 5, Thunder's Mouth Press, 1990 ISBN 1-56025-001-1
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="23bf90c14d5b1702c4c8d21656011894" name="HenryJames1897" sectnum="7#1">../img/23bf90c14d5b1702c4c8d21656011894.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>