<document id="3ab1ef3067dc08e67d0dcd4273754f0f-8" name="Hong_Kong_action_cinema" cat="19">
<text>
The Hong Kong film industry has been in a severe slump since the mid-1990s.  The number of local films produced, and their box office takings, are dramatically reduced; American imports now dominate in a way they had not for decades, or perhaps ever.  This crisis and increased contact with Western cinema have probably been the biggest recent influences on Hong Kong action cinema.MovieMaker magazine issue 49:  by Patrick J Gorman (URL accessed 1 April 2006)

Luring local and regional youth audiences away from Hollywood is a constant concern.  Action movies are now generally headlined by babyfaced Cantonese pop music idols, such as Ekin Cheng and Nicholas Tse, enhanced with wires and digital effects - a trend also driven by the waning of a previous generation of martial arts-trained stars.  The late 1990s witnessed a fad for Cantopop stars in high-tech, more American-styled action pictures such as ''Downtown Torpedoes'' (1997), ''Gen-X Cops'' and ''Purple Storm'' (both 1999).  

Andrew Lau's wuxia comic-book adaptation ''The Storm Riders'' (1998) earned a record-breaking gross and ushered in an era of computer-generated imagery, previously little used in Hong Kong film.  Tsui Hark's lavish CGI-enhanced efforts ''Time and Tide'' (2000) and ''The Legend of Zu'' (2001), however, were surprisingly unsuccessful.  Comedy megastar and director Stephen Chow used digital effects to push his typical affectionate parody of martial arts conventions to cartoonish levels in ''Shaolin Soccer'' (2001) and ''Kung Fu Hustle'' (2004), each of which also set a new box office record.

Striking a different note were a series of crime films more restrained and actor-driven than the earlier, John Woo-inspired examples.  The Milkyway Image production company was at the vanguard with examples like Patrick Yau's ''Expect the Unexpected'' (1998), Johnnie To's  ''The Mission'' (1999) and ''Running Out of Time'' (2000).  Andrew Lau and Alan Mak's blockbuster ''Infernal Affairs'' trilogy (2002–2003) has set off a mini-trend of brooding police thrillers.

Collaboration with other industries, particularly that of Mainland China, is another increasingly common survival and recovery strategy.  Hong Kong stars and other personnel have been involved in international wuxia successes like ''Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon'' (Taiwan, 2000) and ''Hero'' (China, 2002).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ef3727bb78de14e2b242f6c31e75d938" name="TwinsEffect_Poster" sectnum="8#1">../img/ef3727bb78de14e2b242f6c31e75d938.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>