<document id="3b4204788b4bc9cdbdb7b55237c38f84-1.3" name="Honoré_de_Balzac" cat="17">
<text>
Balzac's first project was a libretto for a comic opera called ''Le Corsaire'', based on Lord Byron's  The Corsair. Realizing he would have trouble finding a composer, however, he turned to other pursuits.

In 1820, he completed the five-act verse tragedy ''Cromwell''. Although it pales in comparison to later works, some critics consider it a quality text.Robb, 59.Rogers, 19 When he finished, Balzac went to Villeparisis and read the entire work to his family; they were unimpressed.Robb, 60. He followed this effort by starting (but never finishing) three novels: ''Sténie'', ''Falthurne'', and ''Corsino''.

In 1821 Balzac met the enterprising Auguste Lepoitevin, who convinced the author to write short stories, which Lepoitevin would then sell to publishers. Balzac then quickly turned to longer works, and by 1826 he had written nine novels, all published under pseudonyms and often produced in collaboration with other writers.Saintsbury, EB, 298.  For example, the scandalous novel ''Vicaire des Ardennes'' (1822) – banned for its depiction of nearly-incestuous relations and,  more egregiously, of a married priest – was attributed to a 'Horace de Saint-Aubin'.Robb, 103. These books were potboiler novels, designed to sell quickly and titillate audiences. In Saintsbury's view, "They are curiously, interestingly, almost enthrallingly bad."Saintsbury, "Honoré de Balzac", xv. He indicates that Robert Louis Stevenson tried to dissuade him from reading these early works of Balzac's.Saintsbury, "Honoré de Balzac", xiv. American critic Samuel Rogers, however, notes that "without the training they gave Balzac, as he groped his way to his mature conception of the novel, and without the habit he formed as a young man of writing under pressure, one can hardly imagine his producing ''La Comédie Humaine''."Rogers, 23. Biographer Graham Robb suggests that as he discovered the Novel, Balzac discovered himself.Robb, 63.

Also during this time, Balzac wrote two pamphlets in support of primogeniture and the Society of Jesus. The latter, regarding the Jesuit order, illustrated his life-long admiration for the Catholic Church. Later, in a preface to ''La Comédie Humaine'', he wrote: "Christianity, and especially Catholicism, being a complete repression of man's depraved tendencies, is the greatest element in Social Order."Rogers, 15.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3a1107ba9f6556028ea73a270f861295" name="Laure_Junot" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/3a1107ba9f6556028ea73a270f861295.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>