<document id="3b4204788b4bc9cdbdb7b55237c38f84-1.6" name="Honoré_de_Balzac" cat="17">
<text>
Balzac's work habits are legendary – he did not work quickly, but toiled with an incredible focus and dedication. His preferred method was to eat a light meal at five or six in the afternoon, then sleep until midnight. He then rose and wrote for many hours, fueled by innumerable cups of black coffee. He would often work for fifteen hours or more at a stretch; he claimed to have once worked for 48 hours with only three hours of rest in the middle.Saintsbury, "Honoré de Balzac", xxvi.



He revised obsessively, covering printer's proofs with changes and additions to be reset. Balzac sometimes repeated this process during the publication of a book, causing significant expense for both himself and the publisher.Saintsbury, "Honoré de Balzac", xxvii. As a result, the finished product was frequently quite different from the original book. While some of his books never reached a finished state, some of those – such as ''Les employés'' (''The Government Clerks'', 1841) – are nonetheless noted by critics.Robb, 106. 

Although Balzac was "by turns a hermit and a vagrant",Saintsbury, EB, 299 he managed to stay connected to the social world which nourished his writing. He was friends with Théophile Gautier and Pierre-Marie-Charles de Bernard du Grail de la Villette, and he knew Victor Hugo. Nevertheless, he did not spend as much time in ''salons'' and clubs as did many of his characters. "In the first place he was too busy", explains Saintsbury, "in the second he would not have been at home there…. e felt it was his business not to frequent society but to create it."Saintsbury, "Honoré de Balzac", xxviii. He would, however, often spend long periods staying at Château de Saché, near Tours, the home of his friend Jean de Margonne, his mother's lover and father to her youngest child. Many of Balzac's tormented characters were conceived in the small second-floor bedroom.  Today the Château is a museum dedicated to the author's life.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5786ccac1ab93784d7ae045c8d177b3f" name="Balzac_Beatrix_Proof" sectnum="1.6#1">../img/5786ccac1ab93784d7ae045c8d177b3f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>