<document id="3bcbbf276cf890d669b99a1636581999-3" name="James_Robert_Baker" cat="17">
<text>
Baker's work received mixed reviews. His only two books not specifically gay themed (though containing gay characters and a somewhat gay sensibility), ''Boy Wonder'' and ''Fuel-Injected Dreams'', were better received by critics, and more popular with readers, though he was never a bestselling novelist.Schiff, Stephen.   ''New York Times'', September 4, 1988. Retrieved on 2006-08-12. ''awfulagent.com''.  Retrieved on 2006-08-12. Press release of clippings from Baker's agent. Baker himself estimated that his books sold approximately 25,000 copies each. His following book, however, ''Tim and Pete'', met with hostile reviews, primarily for its advocacy of political assassination and terror tactics in combating AIDS discrimination. Baker himself was ambivalent on the subject. "I think assassination does change things ... But I'm not really calling for violence," he said. "It's a novel, not a position paper."

In a 1993 interview, however, Baker stated: 

I think a strong case can be made that political assassination actually does change things. If you look at the assassinations in this country in the 1960s you can certainly see how it affected history in a very profound way. So if you killed right wing figures, you'd also be altering the course of history, and eliminating people who might very well be president in 1996 and those who are making bashing gays their number one issue right now. On the one hand, I'm not advocating PWA's turn themselves into human bombs, but on the other hand I have to admit that if I clicked on CNN and heard somebody had blown Patrick Buchanan's head clean off, I'd be elated, and to say otherwise would be a lie.



There were also charges of racism, due to his portrayals of blacks and Hispanics. Baker denied those charges, and pointed out that the protagonist later realized that the blacks were also gay and the Latina "was just a sweet old woman putting up with a lot of (stuff) that I couldn't even imagine." He went on to say, "I just wanted to explore the conflicts between gays and Latinos and gays and blacks ... the real feelings  misapprehensions of each other. I realized it wouldn't all be nice and politically correct. If blacks (and Latinos) want my respect, they have to deal with their own homophobia. I'm not playing guilty liberal anymore".

The book caused a great deal of controversy among critics, with some calling it "irresponsible", and saying it was "determined to give offense" and "appears to endorse violence".Welt, Bernard. "Love and Death in the Gay Novel". ''Book World'', October 14, 1993, p. X7  One critic of the book wrote, "The work rapidly becomes an apology for political terrorism and effectively advocates the assassination of the entire American New Right. While the reasons for such a vengeance motif are perhaps evident, can it really be countenanced? Are we still justified in referring to this as art? And even if we are, is there a point at which such invective (and such suggestions) become simply counterproductive?"Pegrum, Mark. "A Big Disease with a Little Name: Responses to AIDS in Contemporary Culture"; ''Mots Pluriels''; Vol.1. no 3. 1997 
Another critic, however, called it "a masterful creation" and wrote: 
"In coming years Baker will be seen as having understood the implications of this period in our history while the rest of us were simply living it".Lowenthal, Michael. "Tim and Pete"; ''Lambda Book Report'', April 30, 1993, Vol.3; No.9; Pg.14 It polarized the reading public as well, with letters to the editor of major newspapers both supporting and opposing Baker's ideology. ''Los Angeles Times'', April 19, 1993, Monday, Home Edition, View; Part E; Page 2; Column 1. Baker himself was aware that the book would be controversial, and deliberately provoked much of the reaction he received. He said: 
"''Tim and Pete'' tries to convey in print what people really think rather than what they should think or what's P.C. My fantasy was to leave readers so infuriated they'd throw down the book and march right out to a gun store because they wanted to see the finale so bad they realize the only way it'd happen is if they make it happen in real life!"Grzesiak, Rich.  ''axiongrafix.com''.  Retrieved on 2006-10-30.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="371de9122836ebe47b5dec8689b11495" name="tim-pete2" sectnum="3#1">../img/371de9122836ebe47b5dec8689b11495.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>