<document id="3be2f628b5328e9ec52377dea610f0b2-2" name="Peregrine_Falcon" cat="3">
<text>
This species was first described by Marmaduke Tunstall in his 1771 ''Ornithologia Britannica'' under its current binomial name.  The scientific name ''Falco peregrinus'', means "wandering falcon" in Latin. Indeed, the species' common name refers to its wide-ranging flights in most European languages.e.g. French ''faucon pèlerin'', German ''Wanderfalke'', Italian ''falco pellegrino'', Polish ''sokół wędrowny'', Slovak ''sokol sťahovavý'', Swedish ''pilgrimsfalk'' The Latin term for falcon, ''falco'', is related to ''falx'', the Latin word meaning sickle, in reference to the silhouette of the falcon's long, pointed wings in flight. 

The Peregrine Falcon belongs to a genus whose lineage includes the hierofalcons''Contra'' Helbig ''et al.'' (1994), Wink ''et al.'' (1998). The supposed basal position of the hierofalcons was due to them having a cytochrome ''b'' numt: see Wink & Sauer-Gürth (2000) and the Prairie Falcon  (''F. mexicanus''). This lineage probably diverged from other falcons towards the end of the Late Miocene or in the Early Pliocene, about 8–5 million years ago (mya). As the Peregrine-hierofalcon group includes both Old World and North American species, it is likely that the lineage originated in western Eurasia or Africa. Its relationship to other falcons is not clear; the issue is complicated by widespread hybridization confounding mtDNA sequence analyses; for example a genetic lineage of the Saker Falcon (''F. cherrug'') is knownHelbig ''et al.'' (1994), Wink ''et al.'' (1998) which originated from a male Saker producing fertile young with a female Peregrine ancestor some 100,000 years ago. 

Today, Peregrines are regularly hybridized in captivity with other species such as the Lanner Falcon (''F. biarmicus'') to produce the "perilanner", a somewhat popular bird in falconry as it combines the Peregrine's hunting skill with the Lanner's hardiness, or the Gyrfalcon to produce large, strikingly colored birds for the use of falconers. As can be seen, the Peregrine is still genetically close to the hierofalcons, though their lineages diverged in the Late Pliocene (maybe some 2.5–2 mya in the Gelasian).Helbig ''et al.'' (1994), Wink ''et al.'' (1998), Griffiths (1999), Wink & Sauer-Gürth (2000), Groombridge ''et al.'' (2002), Griffiths ''et al.'' (2004), Nittinger ''et al.'' (2005)
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="525f603f9f5ea8535ef8b333f9ab000e" name="Peregrine_Falcon_in_flight" sectnum="2#1">../img/525f603f9f5ea8535ef8b333f9ab000e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>