<document id="3be2f628b5328e9ec52377dea610f0b2-3.2" name="Peregrine_Falcon" cat="3">
<text>
The Peregrine Falcon feeds almost exclusively on medium sized birds such as doves, waterfowl, songbirds, waders and pigeons. Worldwide, it is estimated that between 1,500 and 2,000 bird species (up to roughly a fifth of the world's bird species) are predated by these falcons. In North America, prey has varied in size from 3-g hummingbirds to a 3.1-kg Sandhill Crane (killed by a peregrine in a swoop).http://bna.birds.cornell.edu/bna/species/660/articles/foodhabits Other than bats taken at night, it rarely hunts small mammals, but will on occasion take rats, voles, hares, mice and squirrels; the coastal populations of the large subspecies ''pealei'' feed almost exclusively on seabirds. In the Brazilian mangrove swamp of Cubatão, a wintering falcon of the subspecies ''tundrius'' was observed while successfully hunting a juvenile Scarlet Ibis. Insects and reptiles make up a small proportion of the diet, which varies greatly depending on what prey is available. In urban areas, the main item of the Peregrine's diet is the Rock or Feral Pigeon, which comprise 80% or more of the dietary intake for peregrines in some cities. Other common city birds are also taken regularly, such as Mourning Doves, Common Swifts, Northern Flickers, Common Starlings, American Robins and various corvids. 

The Peregrine Falcon hunts at dawn and dusk, when prey are most active, but in cities  also nocturnally, particularly during migration periods when hunting at night may become prevalent. Nocturnal  migrants taken by Peregrines include species as diverse as Yellow-billed Cuckoo, Black-necked Grebe, Virginia Rail and Common Quail. It requires open space in order to hunt, and therefore often hunts over open water, marshes, valleys, fields and tundra. It searches for prey either from a high perch or from the air. Once prey is spotted, it begins its stoop, folding back the tail and wings, with feet tucked. The air pressure from a  dive could possibly damage a bird's lungs, but small bony tubercles in a falcon's nostrils guide the shock waves of the air entering the nostrils (compare intake ramps and inlet cones of jet engines), enabling the bird to breathe more easily while diving by reducing the change in air pressure. To protect their eyes, the falcons use their nictitating membranes (third eyelids) to spread tears and clear debris from their eyes while maintaining vision. Prey is struck and captured in mid-air; the Peregrine Falcon strikes its prey with a clenched foot, stunning or killing it, then turns to catch it in mid-air. The Peregrine will drop it to the ground and eat it there if it is too heavy to carry. Prey is plucked before consumption. Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9424dba81f2f00bf8eb31c8f7d0bed25" name="Falco_peregrinus_on_ship_USFWS" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/9424dba81f2f00bf8eb31c8f7d0bed25.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>