<document id="3c97d0a6679175df9f01dfbe2e7280e0-4.8" name="Ancient_Egyptian_literature" cat="17">
<text>
The funerary stone slab stela was first produced during the early Old Kingdom. Usually found in mastaba tombs, they combined raised-relief artwork with inscriptions bearing the name of the deceased, their official titles (if any), and invocations..

Funerary poems were thought to preserve a monarch's soul in death. The Pyramid Texts are the earliest surviving religious literature incorporating poetic verse. These texts do not appear in tombs or pyramids originating before the reign of Unas (r. 2375–2345 BC), who had the Pyramid of Unas built at Saqqara.; ; . The Pyramid Texts are chiefly concerned with the function of preserving and nurturing the soul of the sovereign in the afterlife. This aim eventually included safeguarding both the sovereign and his subjects in the afterlife.. A variety of textual traditions evolved from the original Pyramid Texts: the Coffin Texts of the Middle Kingdom,. the so-called ''Book of the Dead'', ''Litany of Ra'', and ''Amduat'' written on papyri from the New Kingdom until the end of Ancient Egyptian civilization..

Poems were also written to celebrate kingship. For example, at the Precinct of Amun-Re at Karnak, Thutmose III (r. 1479–1425 BC) of the Eighteenth dynasty erected a stela commemorating his military victories in which the gods bless Thutmose in poetic verse and ensure for him victories over his enemies.. In addition to stone stelas, poems have been found on wooden writing boards used by schoolboys.. Besides the glorification of kings,. poems were written to honor various deities, and even the Nile..

A blind harpist, from a mural of the Eighteenth dynasty of Egypt, 15th century BC

Surviving hymns and songs from the Old Kingdom include the morning greeting hymns to the gods in their respective temples.. A cycle of Middle-Kingdom songs dedicated to Senusret III (r. 1878–1839 BC) have been discovered at El-Lahun. Erman considers these to be secular songs used to greet the pharaoh at Memphis,. while Simpson considers them to be religious in nature but affirms that the division between religious and secular songs is not very sharp.; . The Harper's Song, the lyrics found on a tombstone of the Middle Kingdom and on Papyrus Harris 500 from the New Kingdom, was to be performed for dinner guests at formal banquets.; .

During the reign of Akhenaten (r. 1353–1336 BC), the Great Hymn to the Aten—preserved in tombs of Amarna, including the tomb of Ay—was written to the Aten, the sun-disk deity given exclusive patronage during his reign.; . Simpson compares this composition's wording and sequence of ideas to those of Psalm 104..

Only a single poetic hymn in the Demotic script has been preserved.. However, there are many surviving examples of Late-Period Egyptian religious hymns written in hieroglyphs on temple walls..

No Egyptian love song has been dated from before the New Kingdom, these being written in Late Egyptian, although it is speculated that they existed in previous times.; ; see also . Erman compares the love songs to the Song of Songs, citing the labels "sister" and "brother" that lovers used to address each other..
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="79547ba09b266efc35a661ac51d07ecc" name="BD_Hunefer" sectnum="4.8#1">../img/79547ba09b266efc35a661ac51d07ecc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>