<document id="3c97d0a6679175df9f01dfbe2e7280e0-1.3" name="Ancient_Egyptian_literature" cat="17">
<text>
Underground Egyptian tombs built in the desert provide possibly the most protective environment for the preservation of papyrus documents. For example, there are many well-preserved ''Book of the Dead'' funerary papyri placed in tombs to act as afterlife guides for the souls of the deceased tomb occupants. However, it was only customary during the late Middle Kingdom and first half of the New Kingdom to place non-religious papyri in burial chambers. Thus, the majority of well-preserved literary papyri are dated to this period..

Most settlements in ancient Egypt were situated on the alluvium of the Nile floodplain. This moist environment was unfavorable for long-term preservation of papyrus documents. Archaeologists have discovered a larger quantity of papyrus documents in desert settlements on land elevated above the floodplain,; . and in settlements that lacked irrigation works, such as Elephantine, El-Lahun, and El-Hiba..


Stones with inscriptions were frequently re-used as building materials, while ceramic ostraca require a dry environment to ensure the preservation of the ink on their surfaces.

Papyrus rolls and packets were usually stored in boxes for safekeeping, while ostraca were routinely discarded in waste pits; one such pit was discovered by chance at the Ramesside-era village of Deir el-Medina, and has yielded the majority of known private letters on ostraca.. Penelope Wilson discusses the range of documents, including letters, hymns, fictional narratives, recipes, business receipts, and wills and testaments, found at Deir el-Medina.. She describes the archaeological find as the equivalent of sifting through a modern landfill or waste container. She notes that the inhabitants of Deir el-Medina were incredibly literate by ancient Egyptian standards, and cautions that such finds only come "...in rarefied circumstances and in particular conditions".; see also .

John W. Tait stresses that "Egyptian material survives in a very uneven fashion ... the unevenness of survival comprises both time and space." For instance, there is a dearth of written material from all periods from the Nile Delta but an abundance at western Thebes, dating from its heyday.. He notes that while some texts were copied numerous times, others survive from a single copy; for example, there is only one complete surviving copy of the ''Tale of the shipwrecked sailor'' from the Middle Kingdom.; see also . However, ''Tale of the shipwrecked sailor'' also appears in fragments of texts on ostraca from the New Kingdom.. Many other literary works survive only in fragments or through incomplete copies of lost originals.; .
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b43eadcadc1d311f437988204e0a93fd" name="Egyptian_harvest" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/b43eadcadc1d311f437988204e0a93fd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>