<document id="3cdd7f212d77dd690991abe3df14eb0e-3.2" name="Krulak_Mendenhall_mission" cat="29">
<text>
The meeting became confrontational when Krulak interrupted Phillips, asserting that American military advisers on the ground rejected the USOM officer's assessments. Phillips conceded that although the overall military situation had improved, this was not the case in the crucial delta areas. Phillips noted that the provincial military adviser in Long An Province adjacent to Saigon, had reported that the Viet Cong had overrun 200 Strategic Hamlets in the previous week, forcing the villagers to dismantle the settlement. McNamara shook his head at the radically divergent reports. When Krulak derided Phillips, Assistant Secretary of State Averell Harriman could no longer restrain himself and called the general "a damn fool". Phillips diplomatically took over from Harriman and asserted that it was a battle for hearts and minds rather than pure military metrics.Jones, p. 359. 

Mecklin generated more disquiet by advocating the use of American combat troops to unseat the Diem regime and win the war. He asserted that "the time had come for the US to apply direct pressure to bring about a change of government, however distasteful". Mecklin asserted that there would be a backlash if aid was simply cut, so US troops would have to directly fix the problem. Mecklin later wrote to USIS head Edward R. Murrow to insist that US troops would welcome combat in the case of a communist escalation. On the journey back to the United States, he had asserted that the use of American combat forces would encourage the coup and lift morale against the Viet Cong. He also called for the engineering of a coup. He called for the US to show more intent.Jones, p, 360. 

The pessimism expressed by Phillips and Mecklin surprised Frederick Nolting, who preceded Lodge as the US ambassador in Saigon. Nolting said that Phillips' account "surprised the hell out of me. I couldn't believe my ears." Nolting asserted that Mecklin was psychologically vulnerable to being brainwashed because he had recently split with his wife. At the time, Mecklin was living with journalists David Halberstam and Neil Sheehan of ''The New York Times'' and UPI respectively. Halberstam and Sheehan both won Pulitzer Prizes and were strident critics of Diem.Jacobs, p. 130.Karnow, p. 312.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2b4065b0afe4bad94bdf710a7488001d" name="Lbj_diem_nolting" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/2b4065b0afe4bad94bdf710a7488001d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>