<document id="3d788317ceb201ae2a325091b2c7b1c1-4" name="Palazzo_Pitti" cat="1">
<text>
The Palazzo Pitti is characterized by a severe and simple architecture. One continual architectural theme used throughout four centuries has produced massive but impressive elevations and façades which belie the long evolution and history of the structure. The architecture commands attention by virtue of size, strength and the reflection of the sun on the glass and stone, coupled with the repetitive, almost monotonous theme. Ornament and elegance of design take second place to the vast and solid mass of rusticated stonework relieved solely by the arcade-like frequency of the arched window embrasures.  As with many Italian palazzi one has to enter the building in order to fully appreciate its 

Control of the palazzo, today transformed from royal palace to museum, is in the hands of the Italian state through the "Polo Museale Fiorentino", an institution which administers twenty museums, including the Uffizi Gallery, and has ultimate responsibility for 250,000 catalogued works of art. In spite of its metamorphosis from royal residence to a state-owned public building, the palazzo, sitting on its elevated site overlooking Florence, still retains the air and atmosphere of a private collection in a grand house.  This is to a great extent due to the "Amici di Palazzo Pitti" (Friends of the Palazzo Pitti), an organisation of volunteers and patrons founded in 1996, which raises funds and makes suggestions for the ongoing maintenance of the palazzo and the collections, and for the continuing improvement of their visual display.

Florence receives more than five million visitors each year, and for many of them the Palazzo Pitti is an essential stop.  Thus the palazzo still impresses visitors with the splendours of Florence, the purpose for which it was originally built.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="880f7cfcdee1258713cb0459c1038a60" name="BoboliEntrance" sectnum="4#1">../img/880f7cfcdee1258713cb0459c1038a60.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>