<document id="3d788317ceb201ae2a325091b2c7b1c1-3.6" name="Palazzo_Pitti" cat="1">
<text>
This gallery originates from the remodeling of the Florentine academy in 1748, when a gallery of Modern Art was established.Chiarini, p. 77  The gallery was intended to hold those art works which were prize-winners in the academy's competitions. The Palazzo Pitti was being redecorated on a grand scale at this time and the new works of art were being collected to adorn the newly decorated salons. By the mid-19th century so numerous were the Grand Ducal paintings of modern art that many were transferred to the Palazzo Croncetta, which became the first home of the newly formed "Modern Art Museum".



Following the Risorgimento and the expulsion of the Grand Ducal family from the palazzo, all the Grand Ducal modern art works were brought together under one roof in the newly titled "Modern gallery of the Academy".  The collection continued to expand, particularly so under the patronage of Vittorio Emanuele II. However it was not until 1922 that this gallery was moved to the Palazzo Pitti where it was complemented by further modern works of art in the ownership of both the state and the municipality of Florence.  The collection was housed in apartments recently vacated by members of the Italian Royal family.Chiarini, p. 78 The gallery was first opened to public viewing in 1928.

Today, further enlarged and spread over 30 rooms, this large collection includes works by artists of the Macchiaioli movement and other modern Italian  schools of the late 19th and early 20th centuries.  The pictures by the Macchiaioli artists are of particular note, as this school of 19th-century Tuscan painters led by Giovanni Fattori were early pioneers and the founders of the impressionist movement.Broude, Norma (1987). ''The Macchiaioli: Italian Painters of the Nineteenth Century''. New Haven and London: Yale University Press. ISBN 0-300-03547-0  The title "gallery of modern art" to some may sound incorrect, as the art in the gallery covers the period from 1700 to early 1900. No examples of later art are included in the collection since In Italy, "modern art" refers to the period before World War II; what has followed is generally known as "contemporary art" (''arte contemporanea'').  In Tuscany this art can be found at the Centro per l'arte contemporanea Luigi Pecci at Prato, a city about  from Florence.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="599cfdbd863d105d3b4a8751c74a4b3f" name="Fattori_painting" sectnum="3.6#1">../img/599cfdbd863d105d3b4a8751c74a4b3f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>