<document id="3de4f35d8a989025d7611f8e57f2ea4a-3.4" name="Witold_Pilecki" cat="14">
<text>
On May 8, 1947, he was arrested by the communist security service (Urząd Bezpieczeństwa). Prior to trial, he was repeatedly tortured. The investigation on Pilecki’s activities was carried out by Colonel Roman Romkowski. He was interrogated by lieutenants: S. Łyszkowski, W. Krawczyński, J. Kroszel, T. Słowianek, E. Chimczak, and S. Alaborski – men who were especially famous for their savagery. But Pilecki sought to protect other prisoners and revealed no sensitive information.

On March 3, 1948, a show trial took place The Times 1948. Testimony against him was presented by a future Polish prime minister, Józef Cyrankiewicz, himself an Auschwitz survivor. Pilecki was accused of illegal crossing of the borders, use of forged documents, not enlisting with the military, carrying illegal arms, espionage for general Władysław Anders (head of the military of the Polish Government-in-Exile) and preparing an assassination on several officials from the Ministry of Public Security of Poland.   Pilecki denied the assassination charges, as well as espionage (although he admitted to passing information to the II Polish Corps of whom he considered himself an officer and thus claimed that he was not breaking any laws); he pleaded guilty to the other charges.  On May 15, with three of his comrades, he was sentenced to death.  Ten days later, on May 25, 1948, he was executed at Warsaw's Mokotów Prison on ''ulica Rakowiecka'' (Rakowiecka Street) almost certainly by Staff Sergeant Piotr Smietanski, the prison's executioner.

Pilecki's conviction was part of a prosecution of Home Army members and others connected with the Polish Government-in-Exile in London.  In 2003, the prosecutor, Czesław Łapiński, and several others involved in the trial were charged with complicity in Pilecki's murder. Cyrankiewicz escaped similar proceedings, having died; Łapiński died in 2004, before the trial was concluded.

After Poland regained its independence, Witold Pilecki and all others sentenced in the staged trial were rehabilitated on October 1, 1990. In 1995, he received posthumously the Order of Polonia Restituta.  In 2006, he received the Order of the White Eagle, the highest Polish decoration. Gazeta Wyborcza, PAP, "60 lat temu zginął rotmistrz Witold Pilecki" (Sixty years ago Captain Witold Pilecki died), 2008-05-23,  His place of burial has never been found.  He is thought to have been buried in an unmarked grave near Warsaw's Powązki Cemetery's garbage dump.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9363e5aaa5d28105e543fd760bbf93b4" name="Pilecki_photo_1947" sectnum="3.4#1">../img/9363e5aaa5d28105e543fd760bbf93b4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>