<document id="3e294a7f42a4bc3dc5782022de7b2ddc-2.3" name="Blue_Whale" cat="3">
<text>
Mating starts in late autumn and continues to the end of winter. Little is known about mating behaviour or breeding grounds. Females typically give birth once every two to three years at the start of the winter after a gestation period of ten to twelve months. The calf weighs about  and is around  in length. Blue Whale calves drink 380&ndash;570 litres (100&ndash;150 U.S. gallons) of milk a day. Weaning takes place for about six months, by which time the calf has doubled in length. Sexual maturity is typically reached at eight to ten years, by which time males are at least  long (or more in the Southern Hemisphere). Females are larger still, reaching sexual maturity at around the age of five, by which they are about  long.

Scientists estimate that Blue Whales can live for at least 80 years; however, since individual records do not date back into the whaling era, this will not be known with certainty for many years. The longest recorded study of a single individual is 34 years, in the north-east Pacific. The whales' only natural predator is the Orca. Studies report that as many as 25% of mature Blue Whales have scars resulting from Orca attacks. The mortality rate of such attacks is unknown.

Blue Whale strandings are extremely uncommon, and, because of the species' social structure, mass strandings are unheard of.William Perrin and Joseph Geraci. "Stranding" pp 1192–1197 in ''Encyclopedia of Marine Mammals'' (Perrin, Wursig and Thewissen eds) However, when strandings do occur, they can become the focus of public interest. In 1920, a Blue Whale washed up near Bragar on the Isle of Lewis in the Outer Hebrides of Scotland. It had been shot in the head by whalers, but the harpoon had failed to explode. As with other mammals, the fundamental instinct of the whale was to try to carry on breathing at all costs, even though this meant beaching to prevent itself from drowning. Two of the whale's bones were erected just off a main road on Lewis and remain a tourist attraction.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="47e501c367b5e6cb0ef1a40a47bd9e58" name="BlueWhaleWithCalf" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/47e501c367b5e6cb0ef1a40a47bd9e58.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>