<document id="3e5bcd062df2a216eefb2011a4c29d3a-2" name="La_Peau_de_chagrin" cat="17">
<text>
The title ''La Peau de chagrin'' first appeared in print on 9 December 1830, as a passing mention in an article Balzac wrote for ''La Caricature'' under the pseudonym Alfred Coudreux. His scrapbook includes the following note, probably written at the same time: "L'invention d'une peau qui représente la vie. Conte oriental." ("The invention of a skin that represents life. Oriental story.")Millott, p. 68. One week later, he published a story fragment called "Le Dernier Napoléon" in ''La Caricature'', under the name "Henri B...". In it, a young man loses his last Napoleon coin at a Parisian gambling house, then proceeds to the Pont Royal to drown himself. During this early stage, Balzac did not think much of the project. He referred to it as "a piece of thorough nonsense in the literary sense, but in which  has sought to introduce certain of the situations in this hard life through which men of genius have passed before achieving anything".Quoted in Maurois, p. 174. Before long, though, his opinion of the story improved.

By January 1831 Balzac had generated enough interest in his idea to secure a contract with publishers Charles Gosselin and Urbain Canel. They agreed on 750 copies of an octavo edition, with a fee of 1,125 francs paid to the author upon receipt of the manuscript – no later than mid-February. Balzac delivered the novel in July.Millott, pp. 68–69; Robb, p. 179; Gerson, p. 103; Maurois, p. 175. The exact amount of the fee is disputed: Millott and Robb list 1,125 francs; Maurois lists 1,135; and Gerson writes: "Canel paid him an advance royalty of two thousand francs for the work".



During the intervening months, however, he provided glimpses of his erratic progress. Two additional fragments appeared in May, part of a scheme to promote the book before its publication. "Une Débauche", published in the ''Revue des deux mondes'', describes an orgiastic feast that features constant bantering and discussion from its bourgeois participants. The other fragment, "Le Suicide d'un poète", was printed in the ''Revue de Paris''; it concerns the difficulties of a would-be poet as he tries to compensate for his lack of funds. Although the three fragments were not connected into a coherent narrative, Balzac was excerpting characters and scenes from his novel-in-progress.Millott, pp. 69–71.

The novel's delayed publication was a result of Balzac's active social life. He spent many nights dining at the homes of friends, including novelist Eugène Sue and his mistress Olympe Pélissier, as well as the feminist writer George Sand and her lover Jules Sandeau. Balzac and Pélissier had a brief affair, and she became the first lover with whom he appeared in public. Eventually he removed himself from Paris by staying with friends in the suburbs, where he committed himself to finishing the work. In late spring he allowed Sand to read a nearly-finished manuscript; she enjoyed it and predicted it would do well.Gerson, pp. 103–104; Maurois, pp. 175–176.

Finally, in August 1831, ''La Peau de chagrin: Conte philosophique'' was published in two volumes. It was a commercial success, and Balzac used his connections in the world of Parisian periodicals to have it reviewed widely. The book sold quickly, and by the end of the month another contract had been signed: Balzac would receive 4,000 francs to publish 1,200 additional copies. This second edition included a series of twelve other stories with fantastic elements, and was released under the title ''Romans et contes philosophiques'' (''Philosophical Novels and Stories''). A third edition, rearranged to fill four volumes, appeared in March 1833.Millott, pp. 70–71; Maurois, pp. 180–181.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="674b254cafd381cd7c7049af16d9ea4f" name="Caricature1830Ad" sectnum="2#1">../img/674b254cafd381cd7c7049af16d9ea4f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>