<document id="3e5bcd062df2a216eefb2011a4c29d3a-6.6" name="La_Peau_de_chagrin" cat="17">
<text>
The popularity of the novel extended to Ukraine, where a baroness named Ewelina Hańska read about Balzac's novels in newspapers she received from Paris. Intrigued, she ordered copies of his work, and she read them with her cousins and friends in the region of Volhynia. They were impressed by the understanding he showed toward women in ''La Physiologie du mariage'', but felt that ''La Peau de chagrin'' portrayed them in a cruel and unforgiving light. Hańska wrote a letter to Balzac, signed it as ''L'Étrangère'' ("The Stranger"), and mailed it from Odessa on 28 February 1832.Robb. pp. 223–224; Gerson, pp. 154–155. Hańska's signature ''L'Étrangere'' is sometimes translated as "The Unknown" or "The Foreigner".

With no return address, Balzac was left to reply in the ''Gazette de France'', with the hope that she would see the notice. She did not, but wrote again in November: "Your soul embraces centuries, monsieur; its philosophical concepts appear to be the fruit of long study matured by time; yet I am told you are still young. I would like to know you, but feel I have no need to do so. I know you through my own spiritual instinct; I picture you in my own way, and feel that if I were to actually set eyes upon you, I should instantly exclaim, 'That is he!'"Quoted in Gerson, p. 155, and Maurois, p. 218.

Eventually she revealed herself to him, and they began a correspondence that lasted for fifteen years. Although she remained faithful to her husband Wacław, Mme. Hańska and Balzac enjoyed an emotional intimacy through their letters. When the baron died in 1841, the French author began to pursue the relationship outside the written page. They wed in the town of Berdychiv on 14 March 1850, five months before he died.Robb, pp. 223–230 and 403.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5e99f9d208307cb4f05f17e99e2198ba" name="Hanska_Holz_Sowgen_1825" sectnum="6.6#1">../img/5e99f9d208307cb4f05f17e99e2198ba.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>