<document id="3e8dbc9c7700b34acdf3a0a80c48ae10-2" name="History_of_Tamil_Nadu" cat="14">
<text>
Ancient Tamil Nadu contained three monarchical states, headed by kings called ''Ventar'' and several tribal chieftaincies, headed by the chiefs called by the general denomination ''Vel'' or ''Velir''.K.A.N. Sastri, A History of South India, pp 109–112 Still lower at the local level there were clan chiefs called ''kizar'' or ''mannar''.'There were three levels of redistribution corresponding to the three categories of chieftains, namely: the Ventar, Velir and Kilar in descending order. Ventar were the chieftains of the three major lineages, viz Cera, Cola and Pandya. Velir were mostly hill chieftains, while Kilar were the headmen of settlements...' — During the third century BCE, the Deccan was part of the Mauryan kingdom, and from the middle of the first century BCE to second century CE the same area was ruled by the Satavahana dynasty. The Tamil area had an independent existence outside the control of these northern empires. The Tamil kings and chiefs were always in conflict with each other mostly over property. The royal courts were mostly places of social gathering rather than places of dispensation of authority; they were centres for distribution of resources. Gradually the rulers came under the spell of north Indian influence and Vedic ideology, which encouraged performance of sacrifices to enhance the status of the ruler.K.A.N. Sastri, ''A History of South India'', p 129

The names of the three dynasties, Cholas, Pandyas, and Cheras  are mentioned in the Pillars of Ashoka (inscribed 273&ndash;232 BCE) inscriptions, among the kingdoms, which though not subject to Ashoka, were on friendly terms with him.'Everywhere within Beloved-of-the-Gods, King Piyadasi's domain, and among the people beyond the borders, the Cholas, the Pandyas, the Satyaputras, the Keralaputras, as far as Tamraparni...' —K.A.N. Sastri, ''The CōĻas'', 1935 p 20 The king of Kalinga, Kharavela, who ruled around 150 BCE, mentioned in the famous Hathigumpha inscription of the confederacy of the Tamil kingdoms that had existed for over 100 years.

Karikala Chola was the most famous early Chola. He is mentioned in a number of poems in the Sangam poetry.''Pattinappaalai'', ''Porunaraatruppadai'' and a number of individual poems in ''Akananuru'' and ''Purananuru'' have been the main source for the information we attribute now to Karikala. See also K.A.N. Sastri, ''The Colas'', 1935 In later times Karikala was the subject of many legends found in the ''Cilappatikaram'' and in inscriptions and literary works of the eleventh and twelfth centuries. They attribute to him the conquest of the whole of India up to the Himalayas and the construction of the flood banks of the river Kaveri with the aid of his feudatories.''Cilappatikaram'' (c. sixth century C.E.) which attributes northern campaigns and conquests to all the three monarchs of the Tamil country, gives a glorious account of the northern expeditions of Karikala, which took him as far north as the Himalayas and gained for him the alliance and subjugation of the kings of Vajra, Magadha and Avanti countries. There is no contemporary evidence either in Sangam literature or from the north Indian source for such an expedition. These legends however are conspicuous by their absence in the Sangam poetry. Kocengannan was another famous early Chola king who has been extolled in a number of poems of the Sangam period. He was even made a Saiva saint during the medieval period.


Pandyas ruled initially from Korkai, a sea port on the southernmost tip of the Indian peninsula, and in later times moved to Madurai. Pandyas are also mentioned in Sangam Literature, as well as by Greek and Roman sources during this period. Megasthenes in his ''Indika'' mentions the Pandyan kingdom.In Megasthenes' account (350 BCE – 290 BCE), the Pandya kingdom is ruled by Pandaia, a daughter of Herakles —K.A.N. Sastri, ''A History of South India'', p 23 The Pandyas controlled the present districts of Madurai, Tirunelveli, and parts of south Kerala. They had trading contacts with Greece and Rome. With the other kingdoms of Tamilakam, they maintained trading contacts and maritial relationships with Tamil merchants from Eelam. Various Pandya kings find mention in a number of poems in the Sangam literature. Among them Nedunjeliyan, 'the victor of Talaiyalanganam', yet another Nedunjeliyan 'the conqueror of the Aryan army' and Mudukudimi Peruvaludi 'of several sacrifices' deserve special mention. Besides several short poems found in the ''Akananuru'' and the ''Purananuru'' collections, there are two major works—''Mathuraikkanci'' and the ''Netunalvatai'' (in the collection of ''Pattupattu'') that give a glimpse into the society and commercial activities in the Pandyan kingdom during the Sangam age. The early Pandyas went into obscurity at the end of the third century CE during the incursion of the Kalabhras.

The kingdom of the Cheras comprised the modern state of Kerala, along the western or Malabar Coast of southern India. Their proximity to the sea favoured trade with Africa.'Archaeologists from UCLA and the University of Delaware have unearthed the most extensive remains to date from sea trade between India and Egypt during the Roman Empire, adding to mounting evidence that spices and other exotic cargo travelled into Europe over sea as well as land.' Archaeological evidence for the maritime contact between the Sangam age Cheras and the Roman empire has been found at Karur near Tiruchi. —R. Nagasami, ''Roman Karur'' The people of the current Indian state of Kerala, which constitutes the ancient territories of the Cheras spoke the same language and had extensive interaction with the rest of the Tamil country. It was only towards the ninth or the tenth centuries CE, Due to Aryan's Sanskrit influence in Tamil their individual identity change then a new language began to evolve."Malayalam" Manipravalam or Mani+Pavazham Mani=Sanskrit Pavazham= Tamil,.manipravalam called Malayalam . first appeared in writing in the vazhappalli inscription which dates from about 830 AD. 


These early kingdoms sponsored the growth of some of the oldest extant literature in Tamil. The classical Tamil literature, referred to as Sangam literature is attributed to the period between 200 BCE and 300 CE.Kamil Veith Zvelebil, ''Companion Studies to the History of Tamil Literature'', p 12K.A.N. Sastri, ''A History of South India'', OUP (1955) p 105 The poems of Sangam literature, which deal with emotional and material topics, were categorised and collected into various anthologies during the medieval period. These Sangam poems paint the picture of a fertile land and of a people who were organised into various occupational groups. The governance of the land was through hereditary monarchies, although the sphere of the state's activities and the extent of the ruler's powers were limited through the adherence to the established order (''dharma'').K.A.N. Sastri, ''A History of South India'', OUP (1955) pp 118, 119 The people were loyal to their kings and roving bards and musicians and danseuse gathered at the royal courts of the generous kings. The arts of music and dancing were highly developed and popular. Musical instruments of various types find mention in the Sangam poems. The amalgamation of the southern and the northern styles of dancing started during this period and is reflected fully in the epic ''Cilappatikaram''.K.A.N. Sastri, ''A History of South India'', OUP (1955) p 124

Internal and external trade was well organised and active. Evidence from both archaeology and literature speaks of a flourishing foreign trade with the ''yavanas''. The port city of Puhar on the east coast and Muziris on the west coast of south India were emporia of foreign trade, where huge ships moored, offloading precious merchandise.'The vast quantities of gold and silver coins struck by Roman emperors up to Nero (54–68CE) found all over Tamil Nadu testify the extent of the trade, the presence of Roman settlers in the Tamil country'. K.A.N. Sastri, ''A History of South India'', OUP (1955) pp 125–127 This trade started to decline after the second century CE and the direct contact between the Roman empire and the ancient Tamil country was replaced by trade with the Arabs and the Auxumites of East Africa. Internal trade was also brisk and goods were sold and bartered. Agriculture was the main profession of a vast majority of the populace and ''Vellalars'', the hereditary agriculturalists, owned the bulk of the land.K.A.N. Sastri, ''A History of South India'', OUP (1955) p 128
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f355c05db42f89cc47ec828aaefd4d5e" name="HathiGumphaInscription" sectnum="2#1">../img/f355c05db42f89cc47ec828aaefd4d5e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>