<document id="3e8dbc9c7700b34acdf3a0a80c48ae10-4.4" name="History_of_Tamil_Nadu" cat="14">
<text>
The seventh century Tamil Nadu saw the rise of the Pallavas under Mahendravarman I and his son ''Mamalla''  Narasimhavarman I. The Pallavas were not a recognised political power before the second century. K.A.N. Sastri, ''A History of South India'' pp 91–92 It has been widely accepted by scholars that they were originally executive officers under the Satavahana kings. Durga Prasad, ''History of the Andhras up to 1565 A. D''., pp 68 After the fall of the Satavahanas, they began to get control over parts of Andhra and the Tamil country. Later they had marital ties with the Vishnukundina who ruled over the Deccan. It was around 550 AD under King Simhavishnu that the Pallavas emerged into prominence. They subjugated the Cholas and reigned as far south as the Kaveri River.
The Pallavas were at their finest during the reigns of Narasimhavarman I and ''Pallavamalla'' Nandivarman II. Pallavas ruled a large portion of South India with Kanchipuram as their capital. Dravidian architecture reached its peak during the Pallava rule.http://www.tamilnation.org/culture/architecture/temple.htm Narasimhavarman II built the Shore Temple which is a UNESCO World Heritage Site. Many sources describe Bodhidharma, the founder of the Zen school of Buddhism in China, as a prince of the Pallava dynasty.Kamil V. Zvelebil (1987). "The Sound of the One Hand", ''Journal of the American Oriental Society'', Vol. 107, No. 1, p. 125-126.Graeme Lyall. ''''.

During the sixth and the seventh centuries, the western Deccan saw the rise of the Chalukyas based in Vatapi. Pulakesi II (c.610–642) invaded the Pallava kingdom in the reign of Mahendravarman I. Narasimhavarman who succeeded Mahendravarman mounted a counter invasion of the Chalukya country and took Vatapi. The rivalry between the Chalukyas and the Pallavas continued for another 100 years until the demise of the Chalukyas around 750. The Chalukyas and Pallavas fought numerous battles and the Pallava capital Kanchipuram was occupied by Vikramaditya II during the reign of Nandivarman II. K.A.N. Sastri, ''A History of South India'' pp 140 Nandivarman II had a very long reign (732–796). He led an expedition to the Ganga kingdom (south Mysore) in 760. Pallavas were also in constant conflict with the Pandyas and their frontier shifted along the river Kaveri. The Pallavas had the more difficult existence of the two as they had to fight on two fronts—against the Pandyas as wells as the Chalukyas.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a0b8e4f8640ece3dcdae48ca011ea70e" name="Mamallapuram1a" sectnum="4.4#1">../img/a0b8e4f8640ece3dcdae48ca011ea70e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>