<document id="3f7c4c1408eb0f354e63f6a5073cd683-1.3" name="Chicago_Bears" cat="26">
<text>
Lovie Smith, hired on January 15, 2004, is the third and current (as of 2009) post-Ditka head coach. Joining the Bears as a rookie head coach, Smith brought the highly successful Tampa 2 defensive scheme with him to Chicago. Before his second season with the Bears, the team rehired their former offensive coordinator and then Illinois head coach Ron Turner to improve the Bears' struggling offense. In , the Bears won their division and reached the playoffs for the first time in four years. Their previous playoff berth was earned by winning the NFC Central in . The Bears improved upon their success the following season, by clinching their second consecutive NFC North title during week thirteen of the  season, winning their first playoff game since 1995, and earning a trip to Super Bowl XLI. However, they fell short of the championship, losing 29–17 to the Indianapolis Colts. Following the 2006 season, the club decided to give Lovie Smith a contract extension through 2011, at roughly $5 million per year. This comes a season after being the lowest paid head coach in the National Football League.

The club has played in over a thousand games since becoming a charter member of the NFL in . Through the 2008 season, they lead the NFL in overall franchise wins with 702 and have an overall record of 702–515–42 (going 686–498–42 during the regular season and 16–17 in the playoffs)..  On December 7, 2008 the Bears recorded franchise win number 700 in a win against the Jacksonville Jaguars.

On April 2, 2009, the Bears made one of the biggest trades in franchise history, acquiring Pro Bowl quarterback Jay Cutler and a 5th round selection in the 2009 NFL Draft from the Denver Broncos in exchange for quarterback Kyle Orton, the Bears' 1st and 3rd round selections in the 2009 NFL Draft and the Bears' 1st round selection in the 2010 NFL Draft.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="25357e49ceea7ae81afbfbdc971f286b" name="Packvbears" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/25357e49ceea7ae81afbfbdc971f286b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>