<document id="3fe124971ff0da2b395d4dcda6a1d1ca-6" name="The_Adventures_of_Tintin" cat="17">
<text>
The earliest stories in ''The Adventures of Tintin'' have been criticised for racist, violent, colonialist, animal cruelty and even fascist leanings, including caricatured portrayals of non-Europeans. The Tintin series originated as a comic strip in the "''Le Petit Vingtième''" journal, with the result that the first published story described Tintin as a reporter sent abroad by this very newspaper. Whilst the Hergé Foundation has presented such criticism as naïveté, and scholars of Hergé such as Harry Thompson have claimed that "Hergé did what he was told by the Abbé Wallez", Hergé himself felt that his background made it impossible to avoid prejudice: "I was fed the prejudices of the bourgeois society that surrounded me."

In ''Tintin in the Land of the Soviets'', the Bolsheviks were presented without exception as villains. Hergé drew on ''Moscow Unveiled'', a work given to him by Wallez and authored by Joseph Douillet, the former Belgian consul in Russia, that is highly critical of the Soviet regime, although Hergé contextualised this by noting that in Belgium, at the time a devout Catholic nation, "Anything Bolshevik was atheist". In the story, Bolshevik leaders are motivated only by personal greed and by a desire to deceive the world. Tintin discovers, buried, "the hideout where Lenin, Trotsky, and Stalin have collected together wealth stolen from the people". Hergé later dismissed the failings of this first story as "a transgression of my youth". By 1999, some part of this presentation was being noted as far more reasonable, ''The Economist'' declaring: "In retrospect, however, the land of hunger and tyranny painted by Hergé was uncannily accurate"."Moreover: Great blistering barnacles" ''The Economist'' (London); 30 January 1999; p. 79

''Tintin in the Congo'' has been criticised as presenting the Africans as naïve and primitive. In the original work, Tintin is shown at a blackboard addressing a class of African children. "Mes chers amis," he says, "je vais vous parler aujourd'hui de votre patrie: La Belgique" ("My dear friends, I am going to talk to you today about your fatherland: Belgium"). Hergé redrew this in 1946 to show a lesson in mathematics. Hergé later admitted the flaws in the original story, excusing it by noting: "I portrayed these Africans according to ... this purely paternalistic spirit of the time". The perceived problems with this book were summarised by Sue Buswell in 1988''Mail on Sunday'' Associated Newspapers 27.11.1988 as being "all to do with rubbery lips and heaps of dead animals" although Thompson noted this quote may have been "taken out of context". "Dead animals" refers to the fashion for big game hunting at the time of the work's original publication. Drawing on André Maurois' ''Les Silences du colonel Bramble'', Hergé presents Tintin as a big-game hunter, bagging 15 antelope as opposed to the one needed for the evening meal. However, concerns over the number of dead animals did lead the Scandinavian publishers of Tintin's adventures to request changes. A page which presented Tintin killing a rhinoceros by drilling a hole in the animal's back and inserting a stick of dynamite was deemed excessive, and Hergé substituted a page in which the rhino accidentally discharges Tintin's rifle whilst the erstwhile hunter snoozes under a tree.Michael Farr ''Tintin: The Complete Companion'', John Murray (2001) ISBN 0-7195-5522-1 In 2007 the UK's Commission for Racial Equality called for the book to be pulled from the shelves after a complaint, stating that "it beggars belief that in this day and age that any shop would think it acceptable to sell and display 'Tintin In The Congo'." In August 2007, a complaint was filed in Brussels, Belgium, by a Congolese student, claiming the book was an insult to the Congolese people. Public prosecutors are investigating, the Centre for Equal Opportunities and Opposition to Racism warned against political over-correctness.



Some of the early albums were altered by Hergé in subsequent editions, usually at the demand of publishers. For example, at the instigation of his American publishers, many of the black characters in ''Tintin in America'' were re-coloured to make their race white or ambiguous. ''The Shooting Star'' album originally had an American villain with the Jewish surname of "Blumenstein". This proved to be controversial, as the character looked very stereotypically Jewish. "Blumenstein" was changed to an American with a less ethnically specific name, Mr. Bohlwinkel, in later editions and subsequently to a South American of a fictional country - São Rico. Hergé later discovered that 'Bohlwinkel' was also a Jewish name.

Nazi  collaborator SS officer Léon Degrelle published a book insisting that he was Hergé's model for the character Tintin (See: Tintin, inspiration).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="55fe67ec22b859e66e435cf956a4ed90" name="Bohlwinkel" sectnum="6#1">../img/55fe67ec22b859e66e435cf956a4ed90.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>