<document id="3ff4a5fb4f787be0a3de2cc6ce99a42f-3" name="Made_in_the_Dark" cat="20">
<text>
Taylor stated in an interview with ''The Sun'' that he was "so proud of  lyrically" and thought the song "Made in the Dark" contained the best lyrics he had ever written. Taylor explained that it was "very easy" for him to focus on the "more serious lyrics, like a love song very dear to  heart" but stated that "Wrestlers" was "equally as important and feels like a very different style of music than we have ever got down on record before." He discussed "Wrestlers" in the band's interview with ''The Sun'', explaining that the song is "musically and lyrically quite direct" because "it doesn’t have thousands of layers", in contrast to the song "Bendable Poseable". The concept of the song "Wrestlers", originates from a text message from James Murphy of LCD Soundsystem. After Doyle toured with Murphy, Murphy sent a text message that said, "Sorry you can't have Al back, I'll wrestle you for him. And I'll beat you because I'm bigger and stronger than you." Goddard explained that "the words in that song are about wrestling", and the band "have no doubt" that Murphy would defeat them in a wrestling fight.

The song "Ready for the Floor" contains an allusion to the 1989 film, ''Batman'', with the line, "You're my number one guy". In an interview with ''The Fader'' magazine, Taylor said the reference was a result of thinking about the Batman film, which has many things that Taylor is fond of, such as the Prince soundtrack. He commented that sometimes those items "seep into what we're writing about" and said that he likes to reference "in an oblique way". He conjectured that he had included the line to say something to "everyone in the band, particularly to Joe , 'You're my number one guy, why is there any problems between any of us?' "

"Shake a Fist" was written by Taylor after Goddard took a legal herbal substance during the Glastonbury Festival which produced feelings akin to teleportation. Goddard said, "it was a brilliant time" and told Alexis to write down words to go with his experience. The song features a voice sample from Todd Rundgren.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="309db8877c48b845549ae6f2da8d841a" name="Alexi_Taylor_of_Hot_Chip" sectnum="3#1">../img/309db8877c48b845549ae6f2da8d841a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>