<document id="3ff4a5fb4f787be0a3de2cc6ce99a42f-1" name="Made_in_the_Dark" cat="20">
<text>
Hot Chip often records their music in a bedroom. However, the band took a different approach in recording ''Made in the Dark'' to make it sound "not quite so homemade". Recording took place in a variety of locations, including in-studio and live venues, to make "different acoustic spaces to be obvious to the listener". Lead vocalist Alexis Taylor said there was tension between the band's members, as the band didn't want to continue creating music in the same way, but also didn't want to "throw away a songwriting and production partnership that has worked before." Taylor and vocalist Joe Goddard worked on some of the songs together. Several songs were overdubbed with parts of the rest of the band playing.

In regards to editing, Taylor said that Hot Chip have "never really been too good at bothering to get rid of little imperfections in the music"; he felt they added personality and said that "it's good not to be too dogmatic about it if that's what suits the song". Hot Chip used a variety of vocal structures, including layered vocals, where two takes of the same vocals were added together, changed by idiosyncrasies from the way it had been sung, and the doubling of a single performance, shifted out of beat.

Drummer Felix Martin said ''Made in the Dark'' was a "true group effort". The process began with Taylor and Goddard creating lyrics, then Goddard would produce parts of tracks, which Alexis would then add "lyrical content and melodies and so on that he’s thought of while he’s on the bus or in the bath or wherever he happened to be". The other three members of Hot Chip, Owen Clarke, Al Doyle, and Felix Martin would then "have some influence on the way the songs are put together."

Some equipment used to create the album remained the same as previous albums—Goddard used Steinberg Cubase SX3 on his laptop and Doyle and Martin worked on songs using Apple Logic in their studio. To create the chorus for "Ready for the Floor", Goddard used plug-ins from Arturia, such as Moog Modular. He used two sound channels to control noise and melody, and placed the noise channel in Cubase and had it follow the melody, to make it "punchier". With "Bendable Poseable", Goddard recorded live percussion parts with a Shure Beta 57A mic going directly into Cubase and "fashioned them into a jittery, three-minute loop". This was emailed to Taylor, who then recorded the main vocals for the song. To create the beat in "Shake a Fist" Martin used the Elektron Machinedrum.

Hot Chip enjoy being a live band and have said it is "something  always tried to do". As the group contains "a lot of different types of musicianship", the band "have to be spontaneous whenever  can." Doyle, the guitarist, stated that Hot Chip change the original recordings when playing their music live. At the London-based studio called the Strongroom, "One Pure Thought", "Hold On" and "Shake a Fist" were recorded live, instead of on multitrack, and were subsequently pieced together. This was the first occasion that Hot Chip had recorded music in a studio environment.

Taylor described ''Made in the Dark'' as "a real mix of different things" and said that Hot Chip was "learning how to be a different kind of band" while making the album:
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="dc779c3ced297d8e527ad8e3cc0ea351" name="Al_Doyle_by_Fred_Benenson_(cropped)" sectnum="1#1">../img/dc779c3ced297d8e527ad8e3cc0ea351.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>