<document id="402bcc8b7037bcc6c252de4b597d38dc-3.2" name="Confederate_government_of_Kentucky" cat="14">
<text>
Prior to abandoning Bowling Green, Governor Johnson requested that Richard Hawes come to the city and help with the administration of the government, but Hawes was delayed due to a bout with typhoid fever.Rose, pp. 90&ndash;91 Following Johnson's death, the provisional government elected Hawes, who was still recovering from his illness, as governor.Harrison in ''Kentucky Governors'', pp. 85&ndash;88 Following his recovery, Hawes joined the government in Corinth, Mississippi, and took the oath of office on May 31.Brown, p. 93

During the summer of 1862, word began to spread through the Army of Tennessee that Generals Bragg and Edmund Kirby Smith were planning an invasion of Kentucky. The legislative council voted to endorse the invasion plan, and on August 27, Governor Hawes was dispatched to Richmond to favorably recommend it to President Davis. Davis was non-committal, but Bragg and Smith proceeded, nonetheless. 

On August 30, Smith commanded one of the most complete Confederate victories of the war against an inexperienced Union force at the Battle of Richmond.Kleber, pp. 772&ndash;773 Bragg also won a decisive victory at the September 13 Battle of Munfordville, but the delay there cost him the larger prize of Louisville, which Don Carlos Buell moved to occupy on September 25.Harrison in ''The Civil War in Kentucky'', p. 46 Having lost Louisville, Bragg spread his troops into defensive postures in the central Kentucky cities of Bardstown, Shelbyville and Danville and waited for something to happen, a move that historian Kenneth Noe called a "stupendously illogical decision."Harrison in ''The Civil War in Kentucky'', p. 48Noe, p. 124

Meanwhile, the leaders of Kentucky's Confederate government had remained in Chattanooga, Tennessee, awaiting Governor Hawes' return. They finally departed on September 18, and caught up with Bragg and Smith in Lexington, Kentucky on October 2.Rose, pp. 90&ndash;91 Bragg had been disappointed with the number of soldiers volunteering for Confederate service in Kentucky; wagon loads of weapons that had been shipped to the Commonwealth to arm the expected enlistees remained unissued.Harrison in ''The Civil War in Kentucky'', p. 47''Encyclopedia Americana'', p. 407 Desiring to enforce the Confederate Conscription Act to boost recruitment, Bragg decided to install the provisional government in the recently-captured state capital of Frankfort. On October 4, 1862, Hawes was inaugurated as governor by the Confederate legislative council. In the celebratory atmosphere of the inauguration ceremony, however, the Confederate forces let their guard down, and were ambushed and forced to retreat by Buell's artillery.Powell, p. 115''Encyclopedia Americana, p. 707
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9c972a2cdd1cc4e5d3e0f0c3b67b4572" name="Richard-Hawes" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/9c972a2cdd1cc4e5d3e0f0c3b67b4572.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>