<document id="40392225f4fa686724dfe50fb84fd125-3.10" name="Tool_(band)" cat="20">
<text>
Following their first tours in the early nineties, Tool has performed as a headline act in world tours and major festivals such as Lollapalooza (1997 and 2009), Coachella (1999 and 2006), Download Festival (2006),  Roskilde (2001 and 2006), Big Day Out (2007), Bonnaroo (2007), All Points West Music & Arts Festival (2009), and Epicenter (2009). They have been joined on stage by numerous artists such as Buzz Osborne and Scott Reeder on several occasions; Tom Morello and Zack de la Rocha during their 1991 tour; Tricky, Robert Fripp, Mike Patton, Dave Lombardo, Brann Dailor of Mastodon, and experimental arts duo Osseus Labyrint  during their 2001–02 ''Lateralus'' tour; and Kirk Hammett, Phil Campbell, Serj Tankian, and Tom Morello during their 2006–07 tour. They have covered songs by Led Zeppelin, Ted Nugent,Akhtar, D9. Peach, Kyuss, and the Ramones.

Live shows on Tool's headline tour incorporate an unorthodox stage setting and video display. Singer Maynard James Keenan lines up in the back with himself and drummer Danny Carey on elevated platforms, while guitarist Adam Jones and bassist Justin Chancellor stand in the front toward the side edges of the stage. Keenan, despite being the vocalist, often faces the backdrop or the sides of the stage rather than the audience. No followspots or live cameras are used; instead, the band employs extensive backlighting to direct the focus away from the band members and toward large screens in the back and the crowd. Breckinridge Haggerty, the band's live video director, explains that the resulting dark spaces on stage "are... for Maynard. A lot of the songs are a personal journey for him... and he feels more comfortable in the shadows."
The big screens are used to play back "looped clips that aren’t tracked to a song like a music video. The band has never used any sort of timecode. They’ve always made sure the video can change on-the-fly, in a way that can be improvised... The show is never the same twice." During the ''10,000 Days'' tour, the video material consisted of over six hours of material, created by Adam Jones, his wife Camella Grace, Chet Zar, Meats Meier and Breckinridge Haggerty. Some of the material created by Chet Zar has been released on his DVD ''Disturb the Normal''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="aa9c07cf31846389a4c09d987c48a788" name="Tool_live_mannheim_2006" sectnum="3.10#1">../img/aa9c07cf31846389a4c09d987c48a788.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>