<document id="40392225f4fa686724dfe50fb84fd125-1.4" name="Tool_(band)" cat="20">
<text>
In January 2001, Tool announced a new album, ''Systema Encéphale'', along with a 12-song tracklist containing titles such as "Riverchrist", "Numbereft", "Encephatalis", "Musick", and "Coeliacus". File-sharing networks such as Napster were flooded with bogus files bearing the titles' names. At the time, Tool members were outspokenly critical of file-sharing networks in general due to the negative impact on artists that are dependent on success in record sales to continue their career. Keenan had this to say during an interview with ''NY Rock'' in 2000, "I think there are a lot of other industries out there that might deserve being destroyed. The ones who get hurt by MP3s are not so much companies or the business, but the artists, people who are trying to write songs."



A month later, the band revealed that the new album was actually titled ''Lateralus'' and that the name ''Systema Encéphale'' and the tracklist had been a ruse. ''Lateralus'' and the corresponding tours would take Tool a step further toward Art rock and progressive rockDeRogatis, p. 562. territory.  ''Rolling Stone'' wrote in an attempt to summarize the album that "Drums, bass and guitars move in jarring cycles of hyperhowl and near-silent death march... The prolonged running times of most of ''Lateralus''' thirteen tracks are misleading; the entire album rolls and stomps with suitelike purpose." Joshua Klein of ''The A.V. Club'' in turn expressed his opinion that ''Lateralus'', with its 79 minutes and relatively complex and long songs—topped by the ten-and-a-half minute music video for "Parabola"—posed a challenge to fans and music programming alike.

The album became a worldwide success, reaching #1 on the U.S. ''Billboard'' 200 albums chart in its debut week. Tool received their second Grammy Award for the best metal performance of 2001 for the song "Schism". During the band's acceptance speech, drummer Carey stated that he would like to thank his parents (for putting up with him) and Satan, and bassist Chancellor concluded: "I want to thank my dad for doing my mom."

Extensive touring throughout 2001 and 2002 supported ''Lateralus'' and included a personal highlight for the band: a 10-show joint mini-tour with King Crimson in August 2001. Comparisons between the two were made, MTV describing the bands as "the once and future kings of progressive rock". Keenan stated of the minitour: "For me, being on stage with King Crimson is like Lenny Kravitz playing with Led Zeppelin, or Britney Spears onstage with Debbie Gibson." 



Although the end of the tour in November 2002 seemed to signal the start of another dormancy for the band, they did not become completely inactive. While Keenan recorded and toured with A Perfect Circle, the other band members released an interview and a recording of new material, both exclusive to the fan club. On April 1, 2005, the official Tool website announced that "Maynard has found Jesus" and would be abandoning the recording of the new Tool album temporarily and possibly permanently. Kurt Loder of MTV contacted Keenan via email to ask for a confirmation and received a nonchalant confirmation. When Loder asked again, Keenan's response was simply "heh heh." However, on April 7 the official site explained, "Good news, April fools fans. The writing and recording is back under way."

The writing and recording proceeded for the follow-up to ''Lateralus''; meanwhile, a ''Lateralus'' vinyl edition and two DVD singles were released, and the band's official website received a new splash intro by artist Joshua Davis. The "double vinyl four-picture disc" edition of ''Lateralus'' was first released as a limited autographed edition exclusively available to fan club members and publicly released on August 23, 2005. On December 20, 2005, the two DVDs were released, one containing the single "Schism" and the other "Parabola", a remix by Lustmord, and the music video with a dual-commentary by David Yow and Jello Biafra, respectively.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e8d6d9d209c81f4bbf3cf41184b95d82" name="Adam_jones_tool_roskilde_festival_2006" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/e8d6d9d209c81f4bbf3cf41184b95d82.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>