<document id="404aeccc9289e35bb82049711bb73aeb-6" name="Pham_Ngoc_Thao" cat="29">
<text>
Between January and February, Thao began plotting his own counter-coup, using the contacts he had cultivated over the past decades. One source says that Thao had already begun plotting while in Washington. Thao consulted Ky&mdash;who wanted to seize power for himself&mdash;before the plot, and exhorted him to join the coup, but the air force chief claimed that he was remaining neutral. Thao thus believed that Ky would not intervene against him. Shortly before noon on 19 February, he used around fifty tanks, their crew and a mixture of infantry battalions with whom he had prior connections to seize control of the military headquarters, the post office and the radio station of Saigon. He surrounded the home of General Khanh and Gia Long Palace, the residence of head of state Phan Khac Suu. The country was still trying to find stability, with Phan Huy Quat being appointed prime minister just three days earlier.Moyar, p. 363. Khanh managed to escape and flee to Vung Tau. His plane lifted off from Tan Son Nhut Air Base, the country's military headquarters, just as rebel tanks were rolling in, attempting to block the runway.Tang, p. 363. Thao made a radio announcement stating that the sole objective of his military operation was to get rid of Khanh, whom he described as a "dictator". He said that he intended to recall Khiem to Saigon to lead the Armed Forces Council in place of Khanh, but would retain the civilian cabinet that answered to the generals. Thao did this in league with General Lam Van Phat, who was supposed to seize the Bien Hoa Air Base to prevent air force chief Ky from mobilising air power against them. Due to his religion, Thao was able to recruit Catholic Diem loyalists like Phat.VanDeMark, p. 80.

The attempt to seize Bien Hoa failed, and Ky circled Tan Son Nhut, threatening to bomb the rebels. Most of the forces of the III and IV Corps surrounding the capital disliked both Khanh and the rebels, and took no action.Moyar, pp. 363&ndash;364. At 20:00, Phat and Thao met Ky in a meeting organised by the Americans, and insisted that Khanh be removed from power. The coup collapsed when, around midnight, loyal ARVN forces swept into the city from the south and some loyal to Ky from Bien Hoa in the north. Whether the rebels were defeated or a deal was struck with Ky to end the revolt in exchange for Khanh's removal is disputed.Moyar, p. 364.VanDeMark, p. 82. Before fleeing, Thao managed to broadcast a "final message to the nation" on radio, stating that the coup had been effective in removing Khanh. This was not the case, but the chaos led the Armed Forces Council to adopt a vote of no confidence in Khanh, and Ky assumed control.Shaplen, pp. 310&ndash;312.Langguth, pp. 346&ndash;347.

While in hiding, Thao expressed his willingness to surrender and cooperate with the government of Quat, if he and approximately fifty officers involved in the coup were granted amnesty. He also offered to go into exile in the United States, where his family had moved when he was sent there for training in 1964.Shaplen, pp. 321&ndash;322. In May 1965, a military tribunal sentenced both Thao and Phat to death ''in absentia''. The death sentence was attributed to the influence of General Nguyen Chanh Thi, who was a rival of Thao and had assigned hit squads to look for him. After the conclusion of the trial, it was announced that the Armed Forces Council would disband and give the civilians more control in running the government. Thi was believed to have agreed to the transfer of power to a civilian government in return for Thao's death. As a result, Thao had little choice but to attempt to seize power in order to save himself and he and Thi began to manoeuvre against one another. 

On 20 May, a half dozen officers and around forty civilians, predominantly Catholic, were arrested on the charges of attempting to assassinate Quat and kidnap Thi and Ky. Several of the arrested were known supporters of Thao and believed to be abetting him in evading the authorities. Despite this, Thao himself managed to escape, even as a USD 30,000 bounty was put on him by the ''junta''. In July 1965, he was reported dead in unclear circumstances; an official report claimed that he died of injuries while on a helicopter ''en route'' to Saigon, after being captured north of the city. However, it is generally assumed that he was murdered or tortured to death on the orders of some military officials.Shaplen, pp. 338&ndash;344. One report holds that a Catholic priest betrayed Thao, while another claims that General Nguyen Van Thieu caught him. In his memoirs, Ky claimed that Thao was jailed and "probably  from a beating".Ky, p. 116. After the Fall of Saigon in 1975, a conspiracy theory emerged, maintaining that Thao went underground and worked in counterintelligence for the Central Office of South Vietnam, helping to hunt down Vietcong cadres.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6fdb25c5e976ff0e1fb4b1a82083e00b" name="NguyenCaoKy" sectnum="6#1">../img/6fdb25c5e976ff0e1fb4b1a82083e00b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>