<document id="405bb63965c183867d9e4bb78aeb5a3b-6" name="Mysore" cat="11">
<text>
Before the advent of the English system of education in Mysore, ''agraharas'' imparted the Vedic system of education to Hindus and ''madrasas'' served as centres of learning for Muslims.Hayavadana Rao (1929), p459 Modern education saw its beginning in Mysore when a free English school was established in 1833. In 1854, the East India Company promulgated the ''Halifax Dispatch'' which looked at organising education based on the Western model within the princely state of Mysore.Hayavadana Rao (1929), p494 The first college to be set up for higher education in Mysore was the ''Maharajas College'', which was founded in 1864. In 1868, the Mysore state decided to establish ''hobli schools'' to extend education to the masses.Hayavadana Rao (1929), p497 Under this scheme, a school was established in each ''hobli'' (a locality within the city) and the education was free. This led to the establishment of a ''normal school'' in Mysore which imparted coaching to teachers who were meant to teach in the ''hobli schools''. In 1881, a high school exclusively for girls was established and this was later converted into the ''Maharanis Women's College''. In 1892, the ''Industrial School'', the first institute to impart technical education in the city was started and this was followed by the Chamarajendra Technical Institute in 1913.Hayavadana Rao (1929), p601 While the modern system of education was making inroads in the city, colleges such as the ''Mysore Sanskrit college'', which was established in 1876, continued to provide Vedic education.Hayavadana Rao (1929), p595

The education system in Mysore received further impetus when the University of Mysore was established in 1916. This was the sixth university to be established in India and first in Karnataka. It was named  ''Manasagangotri'' (literally meaning "fountainhead of the Ganges of the mind") by the poet laureate, Kuvempu. The university caters to the districts of Mysore, Mandya, Hassan and Chamarajanagar in Karnataka. About 127 colleges (having a total student population of 53,000) are affiliated with the university. Mysore University is the only university in the state of Karnataka to get a grade of A+ from the National Assessment and Accreditation Council of India.

Education in the field of engineering was started in Mysore with the establishment of the National Institute of Engineering in 1946 the Second Oldest Engineering College in the State. Medical education started in 1930 when the Mysore Medical College was transferred from Bangalore to Mysore. Other institutes in the city include the Central Food and Technological Research Institute, the Central Institute of Indian Languages and the All India Institute of Speech and Hearing.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="64b6c459ae1e25c7144b2126c9c92cc1" name="Mysore_university_building" sectnum="6#1">../img/64b6c459ae1e25c7144b2126c9c92cc1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>