<document id="4062a15c6c2f4b43904cb50d25b6cc78-5" name="USS_Iowa_(BB-61)" cat="29">
<text>
As part of President Ronald Reagan’s and  Secretary of the Navy John F. Lehman’s effort to create an expanded 600-ship Navy, ''Iowa'' was reactivated and moved under tow to Avondale Shipyard near New Orleans, Louisiana, for refitting and equipment modernization in advance of her planned recommissioning. During the refit, ''Iowa'' had all of her remaining Oerlikon 20 mm and Bofors 40 mm anti-aircraft guns removed, due to their ineffectiveness against modern fighter jets and anti-ship missiles. Additionally, the two  gun mounts located at mid-ship and in the aft on the port and starboard sides of the battleship were removed.

''Iowa'' was then towed to Ingalls Shipbuilding, Pascagoula, Mississippi, where over the next several months the battleship was upgraded with the most advanced weaponry available. Among the new weapons systems installed were four MK 141 quad cell launchers for 16 AGM-84 Harpoon anti-ship missiles, eight Armored Box Launcher (ABL) mounts for 32 BGM-109 Tomahawk missiles, and a quartet of Phalanx Close In Weapon System (CIWS) gatling guns for defense against enemy anti-ship missiles and enemy aircraft. ''Iowa'' was the first battleship to receive the RQ-2 Pioneer Unmanned Aerial Vehicle. She could carry up to eight of the remotely controlled drones, which replaced the helicopters previously used to spot for her nine /50 cal Mark 7 guns. Also included in her modernization were upgrades to radar and fire-control systems for her guns and missiles, and improved electronic warfare capabilities. Armed as such, ''Iowa'' was formally recommissioned on 28 April 1984, ahead of schedule, within her budget at a cost of $500 million, and under the command of Captain Gerald E. Gneckow. In order to expedite the schedule, many necessary repairs to ''Iowa'' engines and guns were not completed and the mandatory US Navy Board of Inspection and Survey (InSurv) inspection was skipped.Thompson, p. 26. Although ''Iowa'' was refurbished within budget, the final price tag was $50 million above the originally projected cost, mainly because of overtime pay for the ship's contractors.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="15fa4e48d6ded0cf848e294437f4dcf6" name="Iowa_Modernization" sectnum="5#1">../img/15fa4e48d6ded0cf848e294437f4dcf6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>