<document id="4062a15c6c2f4b43904cb50d25b6cc78-6" name="USS_Iowa_(BB-61)" cat="29">
<text>
A flag hoist lies on the deck near the bow of ''Iowa'' following the ship's decommissioning ceremony at Norfolk, Virginia

With the collapse of the Soviet Union in the early 1990s and the lack of a perceived threat against the United States came drastic cuts to the defense budget, and the high cost of maintaining battleships as part of the active fleet became uneconomical; as a result, ''Iowa'' was decommissioned again on 26 October 1990. She was the first of the reactivated battleships to be decommissioned, and this was done earlier than originally planned as a result of the damaged turret. ''Iowa'' was berthed at the Naval Education and Training Center in Newport from 24 September 1998-8 March 2001, when the ship began her journey under tow to California. The ship arrived in Suisun Bay near San Francisco on 21 April 2001 and is part of the reserve fleet there, where she remained in reserve until struck from the Naval Vessel Register in January 1995.

Section 1011 of the National Defense Authorization Act of 1996 required the United States Navy to reinstate to the Naval Vessel Register two of the ''Iowa''-class battleships that had been struck by the Navy in 1995; these ships were to be maintained in the United States Navy reserve fleets (or "mothball fleet"). The Navy was to ensure that both of the reinstated battleships were in good condition and could be reactivated for use in the Marine Corps' amphibious operations. Due to ''Iowa''’s damaged turret, the Navy selected ''New Jersey'' for placement into the mothball fleet, even though the training mechanisms on ''New Jersey'''s  guns had been welded down. The cost to fix ''New Jersey'' was considered less than the cost to fix ''Iowa''; as a result, ''New Jersey'' and ''Wisconsin'' were reinstated to the Naval Vessel Register and placed back in the reserve fleet.

''New Jersey'' remained there until the Strom Thurmond National Defense Authorization Act of 1999 required the United States Secretary of the Navy to list and maintain ''Iowa'' and ''Wisconsin'' on the Naval Vessel Register. The Act also required the Secretary of the Navy to strike ''New Jersey'' from the Naval Vessel Register and transfer the battleship to a not-for-profit entity in accordance with section 7306 of Title 10, United States Code. It also required the transferee to locate the battleship in the State of New Jersey. The Navy made the switch in January 1999, allowing ''New Jersey'' to open as a museum ship in her namesake state.

For several years, plans had been underway to berth ''Iowa'' in San Francisco as a museum ship, but in 2005 the city council—citing opposition to the Iraq War and the military's policies regarding homosexuals—voted 8–3 against maintaining ''Iowa'' in the city, paving the way for other California communities to bid for the battleship. Vallejo, site of the former Mare Island Naval Shipyard, and Stockton submitted proposals. The Historic Ships Memorial at Pacific Square (HSMPS) organization, which had attempted to place the ship in San Francisco, supported the Mare Island—Vallejo site. Ultimately, the Navy decided in the winter of 2007–2008 to side with the HSMPS bid, and ruled that the Vallejo site would be the candidate to acquire ''Iowa''.

 

On 17 March 2006, the Secretary of the Navy exercised his authority to strike ''Iowa'' and ''Wisconsin'' from the NVR, which has cleared the way for both ships to be donated for use as museum ships, but the United States Congress remains "deeply concerned" over the loss of the naval surface gunfire support that the battleships provided, and has noted that "navy efforts to improve upon, much less replace, this capability have been highly problematic". As a partial consequence, Congress passed Pub.L. 109-163, the National Defense Authorization Act 2006, requiring that the battleships be kept and maintained in a state of readiness should they ever be needed again. Congress has ordered that the following measures be implemented to ensure that, if need be, ''Iowa'' can be returned to active duty:
#''Iowa'' must not be altered in any way that would impair her military utility;
#The battleship must be preserved in her present condition through the continued use of cathodic protection, dehumidification systems, and any other preservation methods as needed;
#Spare parts and unique equipment such as the  gun barrels and projectiles be preserved in adequate numbers to support ''Iowa'', if reactivated;
#The Navy must prepare plans for the rapid reactivation of ''Iowa'' should she be returned to the Navy in the event of a national emergency.

These four conditions closely mirror the original three conditions that the Nation Defense Authorization Act of 1996 laid out for the maintenance of ''Iowa'' while she was in the "mothball fleet". 

''Iowa'' earned nine battle stars for World War II service and two for Korean War service.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c2c681301b8adce53f0bf1c4f40827a1" name="Iowa-26-03-2006" sectnum="6#1">../img/c2c681301b8adce53f0bf1c4f40827a1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>