<document id="4062a15c6c2f4b43904cb50d25b6cc78-5.6" name="USS_Iowa_(BB-61)" cat="29">
<text>
At 0955 on 19 April 1989, an explosion ripped through the Number Two  gun turret, killing 47 crewmen. A gunner in the powder magazine room quickly flooded the #2 powder magazine, likely preventing catastrophic damage to the ship. At first, Naval Criminal Investigative Service investigators theorized that one of the dead crewman, Clayton Hartwig, had detonated an explosive device in a suicide attempt after the end of an alleged homosexual affair with another sailor. To support this claim, naval officials pointed to several different factors, including Hartwig's life insurance policy, which named Kendall Truitt as the sole beneficiary in the event of his death, the presence of unexplained materials inside Turret II, and his mental state, which was alleged to be unstable.

Although the Navy was satisfied with the investigation and its results, others were unimpressed, and in October 1991, amid increasing criticism, Congress forced the Navy to reopen the investigation. This second investigation, handled by independent investigators, was hampered by the fact that most of original debris from ''Iowa'' had been cleaned up or otherwise disposed of by the Navy before and after the first investigation, but it did manage to uncover evidence pointing to an accidental powder explosion rather than an intentional act of sabotage.

While ''Iowa'' was undergoing modernization, her sister ship  had been dispatched to Lebanon to aid the peacekeeping forces by providing offshore fire support. At the time, ''New Jersey'' was the only commissioned battleship anywhere in the world, and it was found that, in an effort to get another battleship commissioned to relieve ''New Jersey'', the modernization of ''Iowa'' was stepped up, leaving her in poor condition when she recommissioned in 1984. It was also determined that Captain Fred Moosally was more concerned with the maintenance of the missiles than the training and manning of guns.  In addition, the Navy had improperly stored the gunpowder used aboard the battleship; it had been placed aboard a barge where sunlight and other elemental factors contributed to its degradation.

Powder from the same lot as the one under investigation was tested at the Naval Surface Warfare Center Dahlgren Division. Spontaneous combustion was achieved with the powder, which had been originally milled in the 1930s and improperly stored in a barge at the Navy's Yorktown, Virginia Naval Weapons Station during a 1988 dry-docking of ''Iowa''. As it degrades, gunpowder gives off ether gas, which is highly flammable and could be ignited by a spark. This revelation resulted in a shift in the Navy's position on the incident, and Admiral Frank Kelso, the Chief of Naval Operations at the time, publicly apologized to the Hartwig family, concluding that there was no real evidence to support the claim that he had intentionally killed the other sailors.At the same time, he also pointed out that there was not enough evidence to exonerate Hartwig of the alleged charges, either. In time this would lead the Hartwig family to file a $12 million lawsuit against the Navy.  ''Iowa'' captain Fred Moosally was severely criticized for his handling of the matter, and as a result of the incident the Navy changed the powder-handling procedures for its battleships. The incident remains the surface Navy's worst loss of life during peace time operations, surpassing the loss of life incurred from the attack of an Iraqi Air Force jet on the ''Oliver Hazard Perry''-class guided missile frigate .Although the worst loss of life in peace time, the turret explosion aboard ''Iowa'' in 1989 is tied with the 1942 explosion in the #2 turret aboard the battleship , which also claimed 47 lives.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4157557e1496b5f08fb4b5223db9992d" name="USS_Iowa_BB61_Iowa_Explosion_1989" sectnum="5.6#1">../img/4157557e1496b5f08fb4b5223db9992d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>