<document id="408c93f6dacd70528b842ca93b659344-5" name="Superb_Fairywren" cat="3">
<text>
Like all fairywrens, the Superb Fairywren is an active and restless feeder, particularly on open ground near shelter, but also through the lower foliage. Movement is a series of jaunty hops and bounces,Rowley & Russell, p. 42 with its balance assisted by a proportionally large tail, which is usually held upright, and rarely still. The short, rounded wings provide good initial lift and are useful for short flights, though not for extended jaunts.Rowley & Russell, p. 41 During spring and summer, birds are active in bursts through the day and accompany their foraging with song. Insects are numerous and easy to catch, which allows the birds to rest between forays. The group often shelters and rests together during the heat of the day. Food is harder to find during winter and they are required to spend the day foraging continuously.Rowley & Russell, p. 61–62   

The Superb Fairywren is a cooperative breeding species, with pairs or groups of 3–5 birds maintaining and defending small territories year-round. The group consists of a social pair with one or more male or female helper birds that were hatched in the territory, though they may not necessarily be the offspring of the main pair. These birds assist in defending the territory and feeding and rearing the young.Rowley & Russell, p. 99 Birds in a group roost side-by-side in dense cover as well as engaging in mutual preening.

Major nest predators include Australian Magpies ''(Gymnorhina tibicen)'', butcherbirds (''Cracticus'' spp.), Laughing Kookaburra ''(Dacelo novaeguineae)'', currawongs (''Strepera'' spp.), crows and ravens (''Corvus'' spp.), shrike-thrushes (''Colluricincla'' spp.) as well as introduced mammals such as the Red Fox (''Vulpes vulpes''), cat and Black Rat ''(Rattus rattus)''.Rowley & Russell, p. 121 Superb Fairywrens may utilise a 'Rodent-run' display to distract predators from nests with young birds. The head, neck and tail are lowered, wings held out and feathers fluffed as the bird runs rapidly and voices a continuous alarm call.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="780575e76e6c14c448a05bef304d4c63" name="Superb_wren" sectnum="5#1">../img/780575e76e6c14c448a05bef304d4c63.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>