<document id="40a7e794398bcbc755d379273793eca8-1.1" name="Hare_coursing" cat="26">
<text>
Whether for sporting or hunting purposes, hare coursing was in Europe historically restricted to landowners and the nobility, who used sighthounds, the ownership of which was at certain historic times prohibited among the lower social classes. The oldest documented description of hare coursing is the work ''Kynegetikos'' (Greek), otherwise known as ''Cynegeticus'' (Latin), which was written by Arrian circa 180 AD. This work, known from its first complete English translation as ''On Coursing'' 1831, by William Dansey, was considered by its original author as a necessary addition to the classic work of the same name ''Cynegeticus'' (''On Hunting''), scent hunting, by Xenophon. Arrian felt compelled to describe the sight hunt and sighthounds because the Ancient Greeks only knew the scent hunt. It is from Arrian that the most famous quote on the sporting fairness of coursing originates "... true huntsmen do not take out their hounds to catch the creature, but for a trial of speed and a race, and they are satisfied if the hare manages to find something that will rescue her". 
The competitive version of hare coursing was given definitive form in the UKsee page 246 Turbervile "A short observation  ... concerning coursing" http://www.archive.org/details/turbervilesbooke00turb when the first complete set of English rules was drawn up in the reign of Elizabeth I by Thomas Duke of Norfolk,  providing for a pursuit of no more than two hounds, a headstart termed "Law" to be given to the hare for a fair run, and for the manner of awarding points on "Speed", "Go-bye", "Turn", "Wrench", "Kill" & "Trip", to judge the dogs' performance. The first modern coursing club was established at Swaffham in 1776, and the National Coursing Club was founded to regulate the sport in 1858. During the 1800s, coursing crossed the class divide, and reached its peak of popularity, with more than 150 coursing clubs in Britain, some attracting up to 80,000 people. By the late 19th century, hare coursing had become a predominantly working class sport. 

Coursing declined during the 20th century, notably due to the development of urban greyhound racing in the 1920s, and there were less than 30 coursing clubs in the UK by 2000.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5428000956fe293e97545553614531cf" name="Coursing_the_Hare" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/5428000956fe293e97545553614531cf.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>