<document id="40f5c1a3e3e260961b03312b908e5f0a-1" name="Rhinemaidens" cat="20">
<text>
Water-sprites (German: ''Nixen'') appear in many European myths and legends, often but not invariably in a form of disguised malevolence. Wagner drew widely and loosely from those legends when compiling his ''Ring'' narrative, and the probable origin of his Rhine Maidens is in the German ''Nibelungenlied''.Cooke (1979), p. 139 In one part of the ''Nibelungenlied'' narrative Hagen and Gunther encounter certain "wise women" (thereafter described as water-sprites), bathing and refreshing themselves in the waters of the Danube. Hagen creeps softly towards them, but her is seen, whereupon the sprites retreat and mock him from a distance. Hagen then steals their clothes. To obtain the return of these, one of the sprites, Hadeburg, promises falsely that Hagen and Gunther will find honor and glory when they enter Etzel's kingdom. After their clothes are returned, another sprite, Sigelinde (a name Wagner would adopt again for use elsewhere), tells Hagen that her sister has lied. If they go to Etzel’s land, they will die there.Mowat translation, stanzas 1528–54, pp. 142–43

This story, itself unrelated to the ''Ring'' drama, is echoed by Wagner both in the opening ''Das Rheingold'' scene and in the first scene in Act III of ''Götterdämmerung''. Wagner first adapted the story for use in his early libretto of ''Siegfried's Death'' (which eventually became ''Götterdämmerung''), introducing three unnamed water-maids (''Wasserjungfrauen''),The number of sprites in the ''Nibelungenlied'' plot is not specified. Two are named, and the text suggests the possibility of a third. and locating them in the Rhine, where they warn Siegfried of his impending death.Cooke, p. 139 Later these water-maids became Rhine Maidens (''Rheintöchter''), and were given individual names: Flosshilde, Wellgunde, and Bronnlinde.Newman, p. 464 As Wagner continued working on his reverse chronology from Siegfried's death, he arrived at what he determined was the initial act of the drama — Alberich's theft of the Rhine gold. Believing that a simple abduction of the unguarded gold would lack dramatic force, Wagner made the Rhine Maidens the guardians of the gold, and he introduced the "renunciation of love" condition.Cooke, p. 139 Bronnlinde became Woglinde, probably to avoid confusion with Brünnhilde.Newman, p. 464

Wagner may also have been influenced by the Rhine River-based German legend of Lorelei, the lovelorn young maiden who drowns herself in the river and becomes a siren, luring fishermen onto the rocks by her singing.Cooke, p. 138 Further possible sources lie in Greek mythology and literature. Similarities exist between the maiden guardians in the Hesperides myth and the Rhine Maidens of ''Das Rheingold''; three females guard a highly desired golden treasure that is stolen in the telling of each tale.Cooke, p. 140 Wagner was an enthusiastic reader of Aeschylus, including his ''Prometheus Bound'' which has a chorus of Oceanids or water nymphs. One author, Rudolph Sabor, sees a link between the Oceanids' treatment of Prometheus and the Rhine Maidens' initial tolerance of Alberich.Sabor pp. 91–2 Just as in Greek myth the Oceanids are the daughters of the titan sea god Oceanus, in Norse mythology—specifically the ''Poetic Edda''—the jötunn (similar to a giant) sea god Ægir has nine daughters. The name of one of these means "wave" (''Welle'' in German) and is a possible source for Wellgunde's name.

Wagner's operas do not reveal where the Rhine Maidens came from, or whether they have any connection to other characters. Whereas most of the characters in the cycle are inter-related, through birth, marriage, or sometimes both,Exceptions are Fasolt and Fafner who are only related to each other, and the Woodbird who is alone. the Rhine Maidens are seemingly independent. The identity of their father who entrusted them with the guardianship of the gold"Father  ordered us cleverly to guard the bright treasure…": Flosshilde in ''Das Rheingold'', Scene 1 (p. 26) is not given in the text. Some Wagnerean scholars have suggested that he may be a "Supreme Being" who is the father of Wotan and all the gods—indeed, of all creation.Holman, p. 174 Others take the German ''Rheintöchter'' literally and say that they are the daughters of the Rhine River.Spencer p. 31 Whatever is surmised, the Rhine Maidens are in a different category from Wotan and the other gods, who are destroyed by fire at the end of ''Götterdämmerung'', while the Rhine Maidens swim happily away in the river, bearing their recovered treasure.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="dfa33c6d7657a169a23a50c1113da87b" name="Ring4" sectnum="1#1">../img/dfa33c6d7657a169a23a50c1113da87b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>