<document id="40f5c1a3e3e260961b03312b908e5f0a-2" name="Rhinemaidens" cat="20">
<text>
The Rhine Maidens act essentially as a unity, with a composite yet elusive personality.Holman, p.174 Apart from Flosshilde’s implied seniority,Holman, p. 174 demonstrated by occasional light rebukes and illustrated musically by awarding the role to a deeper-voiced contralto or mezzo, their characters are undifferentiated. In ''The Perfect Wagnerite'', his 1886 analysis of the ''Ring'' drama as political allegory, George Bernard Shaw describes the Rhine Maidens as "thoughtless, elemental, only half-real things, very much like modern young ladies".Shaw, p. 11 The attributes most apparent initially are charm and playfulness, combined with a natural innocence; their joy in the gold they guard derives from its beauty alone, even though they know its latent power.Holman, p. 175 However, this veneer of child-like simplicity is misleading; aside from proving themselves irresponsible as guardians, they are also provocative, sarcastic and cruel in their interaction with Alberich.''Das Rheingold'', Scene I When the demigod Loge reports that the Rhine Maidens need Wotan's help to regain the gold, Fricka, the goddess of marriage, calls them a "watery brood" (''Wassergezücht'') and complains about the many men they have lured away with their "treacherous bathing".Mann, ''Das Rheingold'' p. 44 They are beguiling and flirtatious with Siegfried,''Götterdämmerung'', Act III Scene I but finally wise as revealed by the undisclosed counsel which they give to Brünnhilde.''Götterdämmerung'', Act III Scene III Sabor sees the personality of the Rhine Maidens as a blend of the "good hearted nature" of the Oceanids and the "austerity" (including the willingness to drown people) of the daughters of Ægir.

The first lines sung by Woglinde in the ''Ring'' are dominated by wordless vocalisations. ''Weia! Waga! ... Wagala weia! Wallala weiala weia!'' This attracted comment both at the 1869 premiere of ''Rheingold'' and the 1876 premiere of the entire ''Ring'', with Wagner's work being dismissed as "Wigalaweia-Musik". In a letter to Nietzsche dated 12 June 1872, Wagner explained that he had derived ''Weiawaga'' from old German and that it was related to ''Weihwasser'', meaning holy water. Other words were intended as parallels to those found in nursery lullabies. Thus Woglinde's lines portray both the childish innocence of the Rhine Maidens and the holiness of Nature.

The Rhine Maidens' sorrow in the loss of the gold is deep and heartfelt. As the gods are crossing the rainbow bridge into Valhalla at the end of ''Das Rheingold'', Loge ironically suggests that, in the absence of the gold, the maidens should "bask in the gods’ new-found radiance". Cooke (1979), p. 244 The maidens' lament then becomes a stern reproof: ''"Tender and true are only the depths"'', they sing; ''"False and cowardly is all that rejoices up there"''.Mann, ''Das Rheingold'', p. 85 In the final ''Götterdämmerung'' scene they show ruthlessness as, having recovered the ring, they drag the hapless Hagen down into the waters of the Rhine.''Götterdämmerung'', Act III Scene III finale

They are the only prominent characters seen definitely alive at the end of the drama; the fates of a few others are ambiguous, but most have certainly perished.Holman, pp. 399–402 Despite the relative brevity of their roles in the context of the four-opera cycle, they are key figures, whose provocation of Alberich to the theft of the gold is responsible for all that follows. Since the titular ring was made from the stolen gold, only its return to the Rhine Maidens' care in the waters of the Rhine will lift the curse on it. Hence, the return of the stolen property provides a unifying thematic consistency to Wagner's complex story.Holman, p, 174
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b3aaf2415742923f9478a0cb7e4a8819" name="Ring17" sectnum="2#1">../img/b3aaf2415742923f9478a0cb7e4a8819.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>