<document id="4116d95272961024c1b3800365a19042-1.5" name="Janet_Jackson" cat="20">
<text>
In May 1993, Jackson's fifth studio album ''janet.'' (pronounced "Janet, period."), was released by Virgin Records and debuted at number one on the ''Billboard'' 200. She commented, "ertain people feel I'm just riding on my last name ... That's why I just put my first name on ''janet.'' and why I never asked my brothers to write or produce music for me." ''Billboard'' magazine's Larry Flick noted she "also broadens her musical scope on 'janet.' by layering deep house, swing jazz, hip-hop, rock, and Caribbean elements on top of a radio-minded jack/funk foundation." ''Rolling Stone'' wrote: "As princess of America's black royal family, everything Janet Jackson does is important. Whether proclaiming herself in charge of her life, as she did on Control (1986), or commander in chief of a rhythm army dancing to fight society's problems (Rhythm Nation 1814, from 1989), she's influential. And when she announces her sexual maturity, as she does on her new album, Janet., it's a cultural moment." ''The New Rolling Stone Album Guide'' (2004) commented that the album's number one hit single "That's the Way Love Goes"—winner of the 1994 Grammy Award for Best R&B Song—and the top 10 singles "If", "Because of Love", "You Want This", and "Any Time, Any Place", all contained "grown-up desires". Robert Johnson of ''San Antonio Express-News'' wrote that the album ranges from "dreamy and sensual" to "downright erotic", and although " isn't perfect ... it should be enough to make her the Queen of Pop." Conversely, David Browne of ''Entertainment Weekly'' gave it a moderate rating, asserting "her wispy voice is often smothered by her two male producers", and regarded ''janet.'' as a "blatant rip-off of the club-beat style of Madonna's ''Erotica''." ''janet.'' was certified six times platinum by the RIAA, with worldwide sales exceeding twenty million copies.

In July 1993, Jackson made her film debut in ''Poetic Justice''. ''Rolling Stone'' described her performance as "a beguiling film debut" despite her inexperience, while ''The Washington Post'' considered her "believably eccentric". Several reviews were also negative, as Owen Gleiberman of ''Entertainment Weekly'' noted she "isn't an inept actress, yet there are no more edges to her personality than there are to her plastic Kewpie-doll visage." Jackson's ballad "Again" was featured on the film's soundtrack, and garnered a nomination for the Academy Award for Best Original Song. In September 1993, Jackson appeared topless on the cover of ''Rolling Stone'' magazine with the hands of her then-husband René Elizondo, Jr. covering her breasts. The photograph is the original full-length version of the cropped image used on the cover of the ''janet.'' album, shot by Patrick Demarchelier. Sonia Murray of ''The Vancouver Sun'' later reported, "Jackson, 27, remains clearly established as both role model and sex symbol; the Rolling Stone photo of Jackson ... became one of the most recognizable, and most lampooned, magazine covers of the year." Jackson expressed, "... sex has been an important part of me for several years. But it just hasn't blossomed publicly until now." David Ritz likened her transformation to Marvin Gaye, stating "ust as Gaye moved from What's Going On to Let's Get It On, from the austere to the ecstatic, Janet, every bit as serious-minded as Marvin, moved from Rhythm Nation to janet., her statement of sexual liberation." Her second world tour—the janet. Tour—garnered critical acclaim as Michael Snyder of the ''San Francisco Chronicle'' described Jackson's stage performance as erasing the line between "stadium-size pop music concerts and full-scale theatrical extravaganzas."

During this time period, Jackson's brother Michael was immersed in a child sex abuse scandal, of which he denied any wrongdoing. She gave moral support to her brother, and denied allegations made by her sister La Toya Jackson in her book ''La Toya: Growing up in the Jackson Family'' (1991) that their parents had abused her and her siblings as children. In an interview with Lynn Norment of ''Ebony'', she commented on her sister's then-estrangement from the family, stating, "her tegory:Living people]]
Category:1966 births
Category:A&M Records artists
Category:Actors from California
Category:Actors from Indiana
Category:African American singer-songwriters
Category:African American television actors
Category:American child actors
Category:American child singers
Category:American film actors
Category:American dance musicians
Category:American dancers
Category:American female singers
Category:American mezzo-sopranos
Category:American pop singers
Category:American record producers
Category:American rhythm and blues singer-songwriters
Category:American soul singers
Category:American television actors
Category:Emmy Award winners
Category:English-language singers
Category:Female rock singers
Category:Former Jehovah's Witnesses
Category:Grammy Award winners
Category:Jackson family
Category:LGBT rights activists from the United States
Category:MTV Video Vanguard Award winners
Category:Musicians from California
Category:Musicians from Indiana
Category:People from Gary, Indiana
Category:People from Los Angeles, California
Category:Virgin Records artists
Category:Universal Music Group artists
Category:MTV Europe Music Awards winners


az:Canet Cekson
bar:Janet Jackson
bg:Джанет Джаксън
cs:Janet Jackson
cy:Janet Jackson
da:Janet Jackson
de:Janet Jackson
et:Janet Jackson
el:Τζάνετ Τζάκσον
es:Janet Jackson
fa:جنت جکسون
fr:Janet Jackson
ga:Janet Jackson
ko:자넷 잭슨
id:Janet Jackson
it:Janet Jackson
he:ג'נט ג'קסון
la:Janet Jackson
lv:Dženeta Džeksone
hu:Janet Jackson
nl:Janet Jackson
ja:ジャネット・ジャクソン
no:Janet Jackson
pl:Janet Jackson
pt:Janet Jackson
ro:Janet Jackson
ru:Джексон, Джанет
simple:Janet Jackson
sk:Janet Jacksonová
sl:Janet Jackson
sh:Janet Jackson
fi:Janet Jackson
sv:Janet Jackson
th:เจเน็ต แจ็กสัน
tr:Janet Jackson
vi:Janet Jackson
yi:זשענעט זשעקסאן
yo:Janet Jackson
zh:珍妮特·杰克逊
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c2d4b8a4c32aed1e3bfaadb7f0e231fc" name="Janetrollingstonecover" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/c2d4b8a4c32aed1e3bfaadb7f0e231fc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>