<document id="4143d621e742074887b0ecba0011d1da-2.5" name="Action_potential" cat="3">
<text>
As described in the section Ions and the forces driving their motion, equilibrium or reversal potential of an ion is the value of transmembrane voltage at which the electric force generated by diffusional movement of the ion down its concentration gradient becomes equal to the molecular force of that diffusion. The equilibrium potential for any ion can be calculated using the Nernst equation.Purves ''et al.'', pp. 28–32; Bullock, Orkand, and Grinnell, pp. 133–134; Schmidt-Nielsen, pp. 478–480, 596–597; Junge, pp. 33–35 For example, reversal potential for potassium ions will be as follows

:  E_{eq,K^+} = \frac{RT}{zF} \ln \frac{_{o}}{_{i}} , 

where
*''E''eq,K+ is the equilibrium potential for potassium, measured in volts
*''R'' is the universal gas constant, equal to 8.314 joules·K-1·mol-1
*''T'' is the absolute temperature, measured in kelvins (= K = degrees Celsius + 273.15)
*''z'' is the number of elementary charges of the ion in question involved in the reaction
*''F'' is the Faraday constant, equal to 96,485 coulombs·mol-1 or J·V-1·mol-1
*o is the extracellular concentration of potassium, measured in mol·m-3 or mmol·l-1
*i is the intracellular concentration of potassium

Even if two different ions have the same charge (ie. K+ and Na+), they can still have very different equilibrium potentials, provided their outside and/or inside concentrations differ. Take, for example, the equilibrium potentials of potassium and sodium in neurons. The potassium equilibrium potential ''E''K is -84 mV with 5 mM potassium outside and 140 mM inside. The sodium equilibrium potential, on the other hand,  ''E''Na is approximately +40mV with 1-2 mM sodium inside and 120 mM outside.Membrane potentials are defined relative to the exterior of the cell; thus, a potential of −70 mV implies that the interior of the cell is negative relative to the exterior. 

However, there is an equilibrium membrane potential ''E''''m'' at which the ''net'' flow of all ions across the membrane is zero. This potential is calculated by the Goldman equationPurves ''et al.'', pp. 32–33; Bullock, Orkand, and Grinnell, pp. 138–140; Schmidt-Nielsen, pp. 480; Junge, pp. 35–37  It is essentially the Nernst equation, in that it is based on the charges of the ions in question, as well as the difference between their inside and outside concentrations. However, it also takes into consideration the relative permeability of the plasma membrane to each ion in question. 

:
E_{m} = \frac{RT}{F} \ln{ \left( \frac{ P_{\mathrm{K}}_\mathrm{out} + P_{\mathrm{Na}}_\mathrm{out} + P_{\mathrm{Cl}}_\mathrm{in}}{ P_{\mathrm{K}}_\mathrm{in} + P_{\mathrm{Na}}_\mathrm{in} + P_{\mathrm{Cl}}_\mathrm{out}} \right) }


for the three monovalent ions most important to action potentials: potassium (K+), sodium (Na+), and chloride (Cl−). Being an anion, the chloride terms are treated differently than the cation terms; the inside concentration is in the numerator, and the outside concentration is in the denominator, which is reversed from the cation terms. ''P''i stands for the permeability of the ion type i.  If calcium ions are also considered, which are critically important for action potentials in muscles, the formula for the equilibrium potential becomes more complicated.

Generation of resting membrane potential is explicitly explained by the Goldman equation. The resting plasma membrane of most animal cells is much more permeable to K+, which results in the resting potential ''V''rest to be close to the potassium equilibrium potential.Purves ''et al.'', p. 34; Bullock, Orkand, and Grinnell, p. 134; Schmidt-Nielsen, pp. 478–480.Purves ''et al.'', pp. 33–36; Bullock, Orkand, and Grinnell, p. 131. 

It is important to realize, that ionic and water permeability of a pure lipid bilayer is very small, and it is similarly negligible for ions of comparable size, such as Na+ and K+. The cell membranes, however, contain a large number of ion channels, water channels (aquaporins), and various ionic pumps, exchangers, and transporters, which dramatically and selectively increase permeability of the membrane for different ions. The relatively high membrane permeability for potassium ions at resting potential results from Inward-rectifier potassium ion channels which are open at negative voltages, and so called leak potassium conductances such as open rectifier K+ channel (ORK+) which are locked in open state. These potassium channels should not be confused with voltage-activated K+ channels responsible for membrane repolarization during action potential.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8a42e56a8d5f99c2f33f7f4ca4fbaa87" name="Neurons_big1" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/8a42e56a8d5f99c2f33f7f4ca4fbaa87.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>