<document id="4143d621e742074887b0ecba0011d1da-5" name="Action_potential" cat="3">
<text>
The action potential generated at the axon hillock propagates as a wave along the axon.Bullock, Orkland, and Grinnell, pp. 160–64. The currents flowing inwards at a point on the axon during an action potential spread out along the axon, and depolarize the adjacent sections of its membrane. If sufficiently strong, this depolarization provokes a similar action potential at the neighboring membrane patches. This basic mechanism was demonstrated by Alan Lloyd Hodgkin in 1937. After crushing or cooling nerve segments and thus blocking the action potentials, he showed that an action potential arriving on one side of the block could provoke another action potential on the other, provided that the blocked segment was sufficiently short.* 

Once an action potential has occurred at a patch of membrane, the membrane patch needs time to recover before it can fire again.  At the molecular level, this ''absolute refractory period'' corresponds to the time required for the voltage-activated sodium channels to recover from inactivation, i.e. to return to their closed state.Stevens, pp. 19–20. There are many types of voltage-activated potassium channels in neurons, some of them inactivate fast (A-type currents) and some of them inactivate slowly or not inactivate at all; this variability guarantees that there will be always an available source of current for repolarization, even if some of the potassium channels are inactivated because of preceding depolarization. On the other hand, all neuronal voltage-activated sodium channels inactivate within several millisecond during strong depolarization, thus making following depolarization impossible until a substantial fraction of sodium channels is not returned to their closed state. Although it limits the frequency of firing,Stevens, pp. 21–23. the absolute refractory period ensures that the action potential moves in only one direction along an axon.  The currents flowing in due to an action potential spread out in both directions along the axon.Bullock, Orkand, and Grinnell, pp. 161–164.  However, only the unfired part of the axon can respond with an action potential; the part that has just fired is unresponsive until the action potential is safely out of range and cannot restimulate that part.  In the usual orthodromic conduction, the action potential propagates from the axon hillock towards the synaptic knobs (the axonal termini); propagation in the opposite direction—known as antidromic conduction—is very rare.Bullock, Orkand, and Grinnell, p. 509.  However, if a laboratory axon is stimulated in its middle, both halves of the axon are "fresh", i.e., unfired; then two action potentials will be generated, one traveling towards the axon hillock and the other traveling towards the synaptic knobs.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8af6b72f1671b241efd5d57706f2ab28" name="Neuron1" sectnum="5#1">../img/8af6b72f1671b241efd5d57706f2ab28.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>