<document id="4143d621e742074887b0ecba0011d1da-2.1" name="Action_potential" cat="3">
<text>
Electrical signals within biological organisms are generally driven by ions.Johnston and Wu, p. 9.  The most important cations for the action potential are sodium (Na+) and potassium (K+).Bullock, Orkand, and Grinnell, pp. 140–41. Both of these are ''monovalent'' cations that carry a single positive charge.  Action potentials can also involve calcium (Ca2+),Bullock, Orkand, and Grinnell, pp. 153–54. which is a ''divalent'' cation that carries a double positive charge.  The chloride anion (Cl−) plays a major role in the action potentials of some algae, but plays a negligible role in the action potentials of most animals.Schmidt-Nielsen, p. 483.

Ions cross the cell membrane under two influences: diffusion and electric fields. Let's start off with a simple example whereby two solutions are separated by a porous barrier. Let us further call these two solutions A and B. In this case, diffusion will ensure that they will eventually mix into equal solutions. This mixing occurs because of the difference in their concentrations. The region with high concentration will diffuse out towards the region with low concentration. To further the example, let solution A have 30 sodium ions and 30 chloride ions. Also, let solution B have only 20 sodium ions and 20 chloride ions. Assuming the barrier allows both types of ions to travel through it, then a steady state will be reached whereby both solutions have 25 sodium ions and 25 chloride ions. If, however, the porous barrier is selective to which ions are let through, then diffusion alone will not determine the resulting solution. Returning to the previous example, lets now construct a barrier that is only permeable to sodium ions. Since solution B has a lower concentration of both sodium and chloride, it will attract both ions from solution A. However, only sodium will travel through the barrier. This will result in an accumulation of sodium in solution B. Since sodium has a positive charge, this accumulation will make solution B more positive relative to solution A. Positive sodium ions will be less likely to travel to the now more positive B solution. This constitutes the second factor controlling ion flow, namely electric fields. The point at which this electric field completely counteracts the force due to diffusion is called the equilibrium potential. At this point, the net flow of this specific ion (in this case sodium) is zero.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1026a3d9ef92494879bc194c3cf3a4a6" name="CellMembraneDrawing" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/1026a3d9ef92494879bc194c3cf3a4a6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>