<document id="4183c178ab71cc15dde125801caa4160-2" name="George_Calvert,_1st_Baron_Baltimore" cat="25">
<text>
Calvert named his son Cæcilius for Sir Robert Cecil,Browne, Page 4.Fiske, Page 255. spymaster to Queen Elizabeth, whom Calvert had met during an extended trip to Europe between 1601 and 1603,Browne, Page 3. after which he became known as a specialist in foreign affairs. Calvert carried a packet for Cecil from Paris, and so entered the service of the principal engineer of James VI of Scotland’s succession to the English throne in 1603.Krugler, Page 30. James was keen to reward Cecil, whom he made a privy councillor and secretary of state, earl of Salisbury in 1605, and in 1608 Lord High Treasurer, making him the most powerful man at the royal court.Krugler, Page 30. And as Cecil rose, Calvert rose with him. Calvert’s foreign languages, legal training, and discretion made him an invaluable aide to Cecil, who, no lover of Catholics,Krugler, Page 32. seems to have accepted Calvert’s conformity as beyond question. Working at the centre of court politics, Calvert exploited his influence by selling favours, an accepted practice for the times.Krugler, Page 31. One by one, Calvert accumulated a number of small offices, honours, and sinecures. In August 1605, he attended the king at Oxford, and received an honorary master-of-arts degree in an elaborate ceremony at which the Duke of Lennox, the Earls of Oxford and Northumberland, and Cecil received degrees.Browne, Page 4; Krugler, Page 32. Given the prestige of the other graduates, Calvert's was the last awarded, but his presence in such company signalled his growing stature.

In 1606, the king made Calvert clerk of the Crown and Assizes in Connaught, County Clare, Ireland, his first royal appointment,Krugler, Page 33. and in 1609, appointed him a clerk of the Signet office, a post which required the preparation of documents for the royal signature and brought Calvert into close contact with the king.Krugler, Page 32. Calvert also served in James’s first parliament as a member for the borough of Bossiney, Cornwall, installed there by Cecil to support his policies.Browne, Pages 3–4. In 1610, Calvert was appointed a clerk of the Privy Council.Krugler, Page 32. All these positions would have required an oath of allegiance.

With Cecil's support, Calvert came into his own as an advisor and supporter of King James. In 1610 and 1611, Calvert undertook missions to the continent on behalf of the king, visiting a number of embassies in Paris, Holland, and Cleves,Krugler, Page 35. and acting as an ambassador to the French court during the coronation of Louis XIII in 1610.Browne, Page 5. A correspondent from France reported that Calvert gave “everyone great contentment with his discreet conversation”.Krugler, Page 35. In 1615, James sent him to the Palatinate, whose impoverished elector, Frederick V, had married James’s daughter Elizabeth in 1613.Krugler, Page 39. One of Calvert’s tasks was to convey the king’s disapproval that Elizabeth, for lack of money, had given away expensive jewels to a gentlewoman leaving her employ. Frederick’s decision in 1619 to accept the throne of Bohemia triggered a war with the powerful Habsburgs which James attempted to end through a proposed alliance with Spain.Krugler, Page 40.

In 1611, James employed Calvert to research and transcribe his tract against the Dutch theologian Conrad Vorstius.Krugler, Page 36. The following year, Cecil died, and Calvert acted as one of the four executors of his will. The king’s favourite, Sir Robert Carr, Viscount Rochester, assumed the duties of secretary of state and recruited Calvert to assist with foreign policy, in particular the Latin and Spanish correspondence.Krugler, Page 37. Carr, soon raised to the earldom of Somerset, was not a success in the job, however, and fell from favour partly as a result of the murder of Thomas Overbury, to which Carr's wife, Frances, the former Countess of Essex, pleaded guilty in 1615. Carr's place as James’s principal favourite was now taken by the handsome George Villiers, with whom James was said to have been infatuated.Stewart, Page 265.



In 1613, the king commissioned Calvert to investigate Catholic grievances in Ireland, along with Sir Humphrey Wynch, Sir Charles Cornwallis, and Sir Roger Wilbraham. The commission spent almost four months in Ireland, and its final report, partly drafted by Calvert, concluded that conformity should be enforced more strictly in Ireland, Catholic schools be suppressed, and bad priests removed and punished.Krugler, Page 38. The king resolved not to reconvene an Irish parliament until the Catholics "shall be better disciplined".Krugler, Page 38. In 1616, James endowed Calvert with the manor of Danby Wiske in Yorkshire, which brought him into contact with Sir Thomas Wentworth, who became his closest friend and political ally.Krugler, Page 38 and Page 83. Calvert was now wealthy enough to buy the Kiplin estate in his home parish;Krugler, Page 39. and in 1617, his social status received a further boost when he was knighted.Krugler, Page 38.

In 1619, Calvert completed his rise to power when James appointed him as one of the two principal secretaries of state, after Sir Thomas Lake's dismissal following scandals, including his wife’s indiscretions with state secrets.Browne, Page 6. Calvert did not emerge as a candidate until the end of the selection process, his appointment coming as a surprise to most observers, including to Calvert himself. Assuming he owed his promotion to the king’s increasingly powerful favourite, George Villiers, he sent him a great jewel as a token of thanks. Villiers returned the jewel, however, saying he had had nothing to do with the matter.Krugler. Pages 41–42. Calvert's personal fortune was secured when he was additionally appointed a commissioner of the treasury with a £1,000 pension and a subsidy on imported raw silk which would later be converted to a further £1,000 pension.Browne, Page 8; Brugger, Page 4.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fa421645c85f7bba20e40b0ce35e5307" name="KiplinHallfront" sectnum="2#1">../img/fa421645c85f7bba20e40b0ce35e5307.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>