<document id="41d6793b4ba381f946ac84795946147a-1.4" name="Procellariidae" cat="3">
<text>
The diet of the procellariids is the most diverse of all the Procellariiformes, as are the methods employed to obtain it. With the exception of the giant petrels, all procellariids are exclusively marine, and the diet of all species is dominated by either fish, squid, crustaceans and carrion, or some combination thereof.

The majority of species are surface feeders, obtaining food that has been pushed to the surface by other predators or currents, or have floated in death. Among the surface feeders some, principally the gadfly petrels, can obtain food by dipping from flight, while most of the rest feed while sitting on the water. These surface feeders are dependent on their prey being close to the surface, and for this reason procellariids are often found in association with other predators or oceanic convergences. Studies have shown strong associations between many different kinds of seabirds, including Wedge-tailed Shearwaters, and dolphins and tuna, which push shoaling fish up towards the surface.Au, D.W.K. & Pitman, R.L. (1986) Seabird interactions with Dolphins and Tuna in the Eastern Tropical Pacific. ''Condor'',  '''88''': 304–317.  

The fulmarine petrels are generalists which for the most part take many species of fish and crustacea. The giant petrels, uniquely for Procellariiformes, will feed on land, eating the carrion of other seabirds and seals. They will also attack the chicks of other seabirds. The diet of the giant petrels varies according to sex, with the females taking more krill and the males more carrion.González-Solís, J., Croxall., J.  & Wood, A. (2000) "Foraging partitioning between giant petrels ''Macronectes'' spp. and its relationship with breeding population changes at Bird Island, South Georgia" ''Marine Ecology Progress Series'' '''204''': 279–288   All the fulmarine petrels readily feed on fisheries discards at sea, a habit that has been implicated in (but not proved to have caused) the expansion in range of the Northern Fulmar in the Atlantic.Thompson, P.M., (2004) "Identifying drivers of change; did fisheries play a role in the spread of North Atlantic fulmars?" in '' Management of marine ecosystems: monitoring change in upper trophic levels''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press    

Three of the six prion species have bills filled with lamellae which act as filters to sift zooplankton from the water.Cherel, Y., Bocher, P., De Broyer, C., Hobson, K.A., (2002) "Food and feeding ecology of the sympatric thin-billed ''Pachyptila belcheri'' and Antarctic ''P. desolata'' prions at Iles Kerguelen, Southern Indian Ocean" ''Marine Ecology Progress Series'' '''228''': 263–281   Water is forced through the lamellae and small prey items are collected. This technique is often used in conjunction with a method known as hydroplaning where the bird dips its bill beneath the surface and propels itself forward with wings and feet as if walking on the water.

Many of the shearwaters in the genus ''Puffinus'' are proficient divers. While it has long been known that they regularly dive from the surface to pursue prey, using both their wings and feet for propulsion, the depth that they are able to dive to was not appreciated (or anticipated) until scientists began to deploy maximum-depth recorders on foraging birds. Studies of both long-distance migrants such as the Sooty Shearwater and more sedentary species such as the Black-vented Shearwater have shown maximum diving depths of  and . Keitt, B.S., Croll, D.A. & Tershy, B.R. (2000) "Dive depth and diet of the Black-vented Shearwater (''Puffinus opisthomelas'')" ''Auk'' '''117''': 507–510  Tropical shearwaters, such as the Wedge-tailed Shearwater and the Audubon's Shearwater, also dive in order to hunt, making the shearwaters the only tropical seabirds capable of exploiting that ecological niche (all other tropical seabirds feed close to the surface).Burger, A. (2001) "Diving depths of Shearwaters" ''Auk'' '''118'''(3):755–759  Many other species of procellariid, from White-chinned Petrels to Slender-billed Prions, dive to a couple of metres below the surface, though not as proficiently or as frequently as the shearwaters. Chastel, O. & Breid, J. (1996) "Diving ability of the Blue Petrels and Thin-billed Prions" ''Condor'' '''98''': 621–629
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1a75cc69f60dc1182e60b60e9e406e18" name="Broad_billed_prion" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/1a75cc69f60dc1182e60b60e9e406e18.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>