<document id="41d6793b4ba381f946ac84795946147a-1.1" name="Procellariidae" cat="3">
<text>
According to the famous DNA hybridization study into avian phylogenetic relationships by Sibley and Ahlquist, the split of the Procellariiformes into the four families occurred around 30 million years ago; a fossil bone often attributed to the order, described as the genus ''Tytthostonyx'', has been found in rocks dating around the Cretaceous-Tertiary boundary (70-60 mya), but the remains are too incomplete for placement within the Procellariiformes to be certain.Dyke, G. & Van Tuinen, M., (2004) "The evolutionary radiation of modern birds (Neornithes): reconciling molecules, morphology, and the fossil record" ''Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society'', '''141'''(2): 153-177
The molecular evidence suggests that the storm-petrels were the first to diverge from the ancestral stock, and the albatrosses next, with the procellariids and diving petrels splitting most recently. Many taxonomists used to retain the diving petrels in this family also, but today their distinctiveness is considered well supported.

However, modern procellariid genera began to appear possibly just as early as the proposed splitting of the family, with a Rupelian (Early  Oligocene) fossil from Belgium tentatively attributed to the shearwater genus ''Puffinus'',''Puffinus raemdonkii'' (see ''Puffinus''). Whittow, G. C., 1997. Wedge-tailed Shearwater (''Puffinus pacificus''). In ''The Birds of North America, No. 305'' (A. Poole and F. Gill, eds.). The Academy of Natural Sciences, Philadelphia, PA, and The American Ornithologists’ Union, Washington, D.C.
and most modern genera were established by the Miocene. Thus, a basal radiation of the Procellariiformes in the Eocene at least (as with many modern orders of birds) seems likely, especially given that significant anomalies in molecular evolution rates and patterns have been discovered in the entire family  Rheindt, F. E. & Austin, J., (2005) "", ''Emu'' '''105''': 181–186Nunn, G & Stanley, S. (1998)" Body Size Effects and Rates of Cytochrome b Evolution in Tube-Nosed Seabirds" ''Molecular Biology and Evolution'' '''15''': 1360–1371   (''see also'' Leach's Storm-petrel), and molecular dates must be considered extremely tentative. Some genera (''Argyrodyptes'', ''Pterodromoides'') are only known from fossils. ''Eopuffinus'' from the Late Paleocene is sometimes placed in the Procellariidae, but even its placement in the Procellariiformes is quite doubtful.

Sibley and Ahlquist's taxonomy has included all the members of the Procellariiformes inside the Procellariidae and that family in an enlarged Ciconiiformes, but this change has not been widely accepted.

 The procellariid family is usually broken up into four fairly distinct groups; the fulmarine petrels, the gadfly petrels, the prions, and the shearwaters.

* The fulmarine petrels include the largest procellariids, the giant petrels, as well as the two fulmar species, the Snow Petrel, the Antarctic Petrel, and the Cape Petrel. The fulmarine petrels are a diverse group with differing habits and appearances, but are linked morphologically by their skull features, particularly the long prominent nasal tubes. 

* The gadfly petrels, so named due to their helter-skelter flight, are the 37 species in the genus ''Pterodroma'' and have traditionally included the two species in the genus ''Bulweria''. The species vary from small to medium sizes, , and are long winged with short hooked bills. The genus ''Pterodroma'' is now split into four sub genera, Imber, M.J., (1985) "Origins, phylogeny and taxonomy of the gadfly petrels ''Pterodroma spp''." ''Ibis'' 127: 197–229 and some species have been split out of the genus (see below).

* The prions comprise six species of true prion in the genus ''Pachyptila'' and the closely related Blue Petrel. Often known in the past as whalebirds, three species have large bills filled with lamellae that they use to filter plankton somewhat as baleen whales do, though the old name derives from their association with whales, not their bills (though "prions" does, deriving from Ancient Greek for "saw"). They are small procellariids, , with grey, patterned plumage, all inhabiting the Southern Ocean. 

* The shearwaters are adapted for diving after prey instead of foraging on the ocean's surface; one species has been recorded diving as deep as . The shearwaters are also well known for the long trans-equatorial migrations undertaken by many species. The shearwaters include the 20 or so species of the genus ''Puffinus'', as well as the five large ''Procellaria'' species and the three ''Calonectris'' species. While all these three genera are known collectively as shearwaters, the ''Procellaria'' are called petrels in their common names. A recent study splits the shearwater genus ''Puffinus'' into two separate clades or subgroups, Puffinus and Neonectris. Puffinus are the 'smaller' ''Puffinus'' shearwaters (Manx, Little and Audubon's Shearwaters, for example), and the Neonectris are the 'larger' ''Puffinus'' shearwaters (Sooty Shearwaters, for example); in 2004 it was proposed that Neonectris be split into its own genus, ''Ardenna''. Penhallurick, J. and Wink, M. (2004). "Analysis of the taxonomy and nomenclature of the Procellariformes based on complete nucleotide sequences of the mitochondrial cytochrome b gene." ''Emu'' '''104''': 125–147. This split into two clades is thought to have occurred soon after ''Puffinus'' split from the other procellariids, with the genus originating in the north Atlantic Ocean and the Neonectris clade evolving in the southern hemisphere.Austin, J., (1996) "Molecular Phylogenetics of ''Puffinus'' Shearwaters: Preliminary Evidence from Mitochondrial Cytochrome b Gene Sequences" ''Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution'' '''6''' (1): 77–88.  (HTML abstract)


The more traditional taxonomy of the family, particularly the split into four groups, has been challenged by recent research. A 1998 study by Gary Nunn and Scott Stanley showed that the fulmarine petrels were indeed a discrete group within the family, as were the gadfly petrels in the genus ''Pterodroma''. 
However the two petrels in the genus ''Bulweria'' are no longer considered close to the gadfly petrels, instead being moved closer to the shearwaters in the genus ''Procellaria''. Two genera, ''Pseudobulweria''  and ''Lugensa'', have been split from the gadfly petrel genus ''Pterodroma'', with ''Pseudobulweria'' being phylogenetically closer to the ''Puffinus'' shearwaters than the ''Pterodroma'' gadfly petrels,Bretagnolle, V., Attié, C., Pasquet, E., (1998) "Cytochrome-B evidence for validity and phylogenetic relationships of ''Pseudobulweria'' and ''Bulweria'' (Procellariidae)" ''Auk'' '''115'''(1):188–195 
and ''Lugensa'' (the Kerguelen Petrel) possibly being closely related to the shearwaters or the fulmars.Imber, 1985, thought that ''Lugensa'' belonged with the fulmarine petrels, Nunn and Stanley (1998) placed it nearer the larger (Neonectris) ''Puffinus'' shearwaters.
The prions, according to Nunn and Stanley, were amongst the larger shearwater group. The ''Calonectris'' shearwaters were placed close to the two ''Puffinus'' clades (closer to the Puffinus, or small, clade) and both were distant to the ''Procellaria'' shearwaters. The relationships between the genera and within the genera are still the subject of debate, with researchers lumping and splitting the species and genera within the family and arguing about the position of the genera within the family. Many of the confusing species are amongst the least known of all seabirds; some of them (like the Fiji Petrel) have not been seen more than 10 times since their discovery by science, and others' breeding grounds are unknown (like the Heinroth's Shearwater).

There are around 80 species of procellariid in 14 genera. For a complete list, and notes on different taxonomies, see  ''List of Procellariidae.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b02f09fbfc6f3f8804286b97dda92512" name="Bulwers_petrel" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/b02f09fbfc6f3f8804286b97dda92512.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>