<document id="41d6793b4ba381f946ac84795946147a-1.3" name="Procellariidae" cat="3">
<text>
The procellariids are present in all the world's oceans and most of the seas. They are absent from the Bay of Bengal and Hudson Bay, but are present year round or seasonally in the rest. The seas north of New Zealand are the centre of procellariid biodiversity, with the most species.Schreiber, Elizabeth A. & Burger, Joanne.(2001.) ''Biology of Marine Birds'', Boca Raton: CRC Press, ISBN 0-8493-9882-7 Among the four groups, the fulmarine petrels have a mostly polar distribution, with most species living around Antarctica and one, the Northern Fulmar ranging in the Northern Atlantic and Pacific Oceans. The prions are restricted to the Southern Ocean, and the gadfly petrels are found mostly in the tropics with some temperate species. The shearwaters are the most widespread group and breed in most temperate and tropical seas, although by a biogeographical quirk are absent as breeders from the North Pacific.


Many procellariids undertake long annual migrations in the non-breeding season. Southern species of shearwater such as the Sooty Shearwater and Short-tailed Shearwater, breeding on islands off Australia, New Zealand and Chile, undertake transequatorial migrations of millions of birds up to the waters off Alaska and back each year during the austral winter.Spear, L. & Ainley, D. (1999) "Migration Routes of Sooty Shearwaters in the Pacific Ocean" ''Condor'' '''101'''(2): 205–218 Manx Shearwaters from the North Atlantic also undertake transequatorial migrations from Western Europe and North America to the waters off Brazil in the South Atlantic.Hamner, K. (2003) ''Puffinus puffinus'' Manx Shearwater. ''BWP Update'' '''5'''(3): 203–213 The mechanisms of navigation are poorly understood, but displacement experiments where individuals were removed from colonies and flown to far-flung release sites have shown that they are able to home in on their colonies with remarkable precision. A Manx Shearwater released in Boston returned to its colony in Skomer, Wales within 13 days, a distance of 5,150 kilometres (3,200 mi). Matthews, G.V.T., (1953) "Navigation in the Manx Shearwater" '''30''' ''Journal of Experimental Biology''(3): 370–396
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f612e90c2c710466ad43218b427b946b" name="Shearwater_migrant_flock" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/f612e90c2c710466ad43218b427b946b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>