<document id="4260e4023c1bdab27b53fdc8b305daf4-2.2" name="Battle_of_Lissa_(1811)" cat="29">
<text>
Behind ''Volage'' and ''Danaé'', the Venetian ''Corona'' had engaged ''Cerberus'' in a close range duel, during which ''Cerberus'' took heavy damage but inflicted similar injuries on the Italian ship. This exchange continued until the arrival of ''Active'' caused the ''Danaé'', ''Corona'' and ''Carolina'' to sheer off and retreat to the east.James p. 355 To the rear, ''Amphion'', succeeded in closing with and raking ''Flore'', and caused such damage that within five minutes the French ship's officers threw the French colours overboard in surrender. Captain Péridier had been seriously wounded in the action, and took no part in ''Flore'''s later movements. ''Amphion'' then attacked ''Bellona'' and in an engagement that lasted until 12:00, forced the Italian ship's surrender.Woodman p. 255 During this combat, the small ship ''Principessa Augusta'' fired on ''Amphion'' from a distance, until the frigate was able to turn a gun on them and drive them off.Gardiner, p. 174 Hoste sent a punt to take possession of ''Bellona'' but due to the damage suffered was unable to launch a boat to seize ''Flore''. Realising ''Amphion's'' difficulty, the officers of ''Flore'', who had made hasty repairs during the conflict between ''Amphion'' and ''Bellona'', immediately set sail for the French harbour on Lesina, despite having already surrendered.Henderson, p. 116

''Active'', the only British ship still in fighting condition, took up pursuit of the retreating enemy and at 12:30 caught the ''Corona'' in the channel between Lissa and the small island of Spalmadon.Henderson, p. 117 The frigates manoeuvred around one another for the next hour; captains Gordon and Paschaligo each seeking the best position from which to engage. The frigates engaged in combat at 13.45, ''Active'' forcing ''Corona'''s surrender 45 minutes later after a fire broke out aboard the Italian ship.Adkins, p. 361 ''Active'' too had suffered severely and as the British squadron was not strong enough to continue the action by attacking the remaining squadron in its protected harbour on Lesina, the battle came to an end. The survivors of the Franco-Venetian squadron had all reached safety; ''Carolina'' and ''Danaé'' had used the conflict between ''Active'' and ''Corona'' to cover their escape while ''Flore'' had indicated to each British ship she passed that she had surrendered and was in British possession despite the absence of a British officer on board. Once ''Flore'' was clear of the British squadron she headed for safety, reaching the batteries of Lesina shortly after her ''Carolina'' and ''Danaé'' and ahead of the limping British pursuit. The smaller craft of the Franco-Venetian squadron scattered during the battle's final stages and reached Lesina independently.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b4595cea4c9e7a6b722ca676d96387c4" name="BattleofLissa1811(2)" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/b4595cea4c9e7a6b722ca676d96387c4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>