<document id="42dd5b575163e4a03fb16c58f7c7ce50-3.5" name="Grunge" cat="20">
<text>
Grunge bands had made inroads to the musical mainstream in the late 1980s. Soundgarden was the first grunge band to sign to a major label when they joined the roster of A&M Records in 1989. Soundgarden, along with other major label signings Alice in Chains and Screaming Trees, performed "okay" with their initial major label releases, according to Jack Endino. Nirvana, originally from Aberdeen, Washington, was also courted by major labels, finally signing with Geffen Records in 1990. In September 1991, the band released its major label debut, ''Nevermind''. The album was at best hoped to be a minor success on par with Sonic Youth's ''Goo'', which Geffen had released a year previous.Wice, Nathaniel. "How Nirvana Made It." ''Spin''. April 1992. It was the release of the album's first single "Smells Like Teen Spirit" that "marked the instigation of the grunge music phenomenon". Due to constant airplay of the song's music video on MTV, ''Nevermind'' was selling 400,000 copies a week by Christmas 1991.Lyons, p. 120 In January 1992, ''Nevermind'' replaced pop superstar Michael Jackson's ''Dangerous'' at number one on the ''Billboard'' 200."The ''Billboard'' 200." ''Billboard''. January 11, 1992.

The success of ''Nevermind'' surprised the music industry. ''Nevermind'' not only popularized grunge, but also established "the cultural and commercial viability of alternative rock in general." Michael Azerrad asserted that ''Nevermind'' symbolized "a sea-change in rock music" in which the glam metal that had dominated rock music at that time fell out of favor in the face of music that was authentic and culturally relevant.Azerrad (1994), p. 229-30 Other grunge bands subsequently replicated Nirvana's success. Pearl Jam, which featured former Mother Love Bone members Jeff Ament and Stone Gossard, had released its debut album ''Ten'' in August 1991, a month before ''Nevermind'', but album sales only picked up a year later. By the second half of 1992 ''Ten'' became a breakthrough success, being certified gold and reaching number two on the ''Billboard'' charts.Pearlman, Nina. "Black Days." ''Guitar World''. December 2002. Soundgarden's album ''Badmotorfinger'' and Alice in Chains' ''Dirt'', along with the ''Temple of the Dog'' album collaboration featuring members of Pearl Jam and Soundgarden, were also among the 100 top selling albums of 1992.Lyons, p. 136 The popular breakthrough of these grunge bands prompted ''Rolling Stone'' to nickname Seattle "the new Liverpool." Major record labels signed most of the prominent grunge bands in Seattle, while a second influx of bands moved to the city in hopes of success.Azerrad (2001), p. 452–53

The popularity of grunge resulted in a large interest in the Seattle music scene's perceived cultural traits. While the Seattle music scene in the late 1980s and early 1990s in actuality consisted of various styles and genres of music, its representation in the media "served to depict Seattle as a music 'community' in which the focus was upon the ongoing exploration of one musical idiom, namely grunge."Lyons, p. 122 The fashion industry marketed "grunge fashion" to consumers, charging premium prices for items such as knit ski hats. Critics asserted that advertising was co-opting elements of grunge and turning it into a fad. ''Entertainment Weekly'' commented in a 1993 article, "There hasn't been this kind of exploitation of a subculture since the media discovered hippies in the '60s" ''The New York Times'' compared the "grunging of America" to the mass-marketing of punk rock, disco, and hip hop in previous years. Ironically the ''New York Times'' was tricked into printing a fake list of slang terms that were supposedly used in the grunge scene; often referred to as the grunge speak hoax. This media hype surrounding grunge was documented in the 1996 documentary ''Hype!''.

A backlash against grunge began to develop in Seattle; in 1993 Bruce Pavitt said that in the city, "All things grunge are treated with the utmost cynicism and amusement  Because the whole thing is a fabricated movement and always has been." Many grunge artists were uncomfortable with their success and the resulting attention it brought. Nirvana's Kurt Cobain told Michael Azerrad, "Famous is the last thing I wanted to be."Azerrad, Michael. ''Come as You Are: The Story of Nirvana''. Doubleday, 1994. ISBN 0-385-47199-8, p. 254 Pearl Jam also felt the burden of success, with much of the attention falling on frontman Eddie Vedder. Nirvana's follow-up album ''In Utero'' (1993) was an intentionally abrasive album that Nirvana bassist Krist Novoselic described as a "wild aggressive sound, a true alternative record."DeRogatis, Jim. ''Milk It!: Collected Musings on the Alternative Music Explosion of the 90's''. Cambridge: Da Capo, 2003. ISBN 0-306-81271-1, p. 18 Nevertheless, upon its release in September 1993 ''In Utero'' topped the ''Billboard'' charts. Pearl Jam also continued to perform well commercially with its second album, ''Vs.'' (1993). The album sold a record 950,378 copies in its first week of release, topped the ''Billboard'' charts, and outperformed all other entries in the top ten that week combined.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d33cbeff8da654b7c27f6c3117871bf5" name="Nirvana_around_1992" sectnum="3.5#1">../img/d33cbeff8da654b7c27f6c3117871bf5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>