<document id="430e2856ee8488ce800bba5d1f4133de-2.5" name="John_Mayer" cat="20">
<text>
Mayer's latest album, entitled ''Continuum'', was released on September 12, 2006, and was produced by Mayer himself and Steve Jordan. Mayer suggested the album was intended to combine his signature pop music with the feel, sound, groove, and sensibilities of the blues. In that vein, two of the tracks from his trio release ''Try!''—the funky "Vultures" and the blues centerpiece "Gravity"—also were included on ''Continuum''.  Mayer has said that "Gravity" is the most important song he's ever written.Youtube video. '' (2006)''. .Online forum entry. ''''.

The first single from ''Continuum'' was "Waiting on the World to Change," which debuted on ''The Ron and Fez Show''. The song was the third most downloaded song of the week on the iTunes Music Store following its release on July 11, 2006, and debuted at #25 on the ''Billboard'' Hot 100 Chart. On August 23, 2006, Mayer debuted the entire album on the Los Angeles radio station Star 98.7, giving commentary on each track.Mayer, John (2006).  JohnMayer.com. Retrieved on June 8, 2007. A subsequent version was released the next day on the Clear Channel Music website as a streaming sneak preview. On September 21, 2006, Mayer appeared on ''CSI'', playing "Waiting on the World to Change" and "Slow Dancing in a Burning Room." The song "Gravity" was featured on the television series ''House'' in the episode "Cane & Able" and ''Numb3rs''. He recorded a session for the British program ''Live From Abbey Road'' at Abbey Road Studios on October 22, 2006.

On December 7, 2006, Mayer was nominated for five 2007 Grammys, including "Album of the Year." The John Mayer Trio also received a nomination for their album, ''Try!''. He won two: Best Pop Song with Vocal for "Waiting on the World to Change" and Best Pop Album for ''Continuum''. Mayer remixed an acoustic version of his single "Waiting on the World to Change" with vocal additions from fellow musician Ben Harper. In preparation for recording ''Continuum'', Mayer had booked the Village Recorder in Los Angeles to record five demo acoustic versions of his songs with veteran musician Robbie McIntosh. These recordings became ''The Village Sessions'', an EP released on December 12, 2006. As usual, Mayer oversaw the artwork of the release.No byline (2006).  JohnMayer.com. Retrieved on June 8, 2007.


Mayer was featured on the cover of ''Rolling Stone'' (#1020) in February 2007, along with John Frusciante and Derek Trucks. He was named as one of the "New Guitar Gods," and the cover nicknamed him "Slowhand, Jr.," a reference to Eric Clapton. Additionally, he was selected by the editors of ''Time'' magazine as one of the 100 Most Influential People of 2007 and was listed among artists and entertainers.Tyrangiel, Josh (May 14, 2007).  ''TIME'' '''169''' (20):140

On November 20, 2007, the re-issue of ''Continuum'' became available online and in stores. The release contains a bonus disc of six live songs from his 2007 tour: five from ''Continuum'' and a cover of the Ray Charles song "I Don't Need No Doctor."JohnMayer.org staff (November 14, 2007). ( JohnMayer.com Retrieved 2007-11-19 His new single, "Say," also became available through iTunes. On December 6, 2007, "Belief" was nominated for Best Male Pop Vocal for the 50th Annual Grammy Awards. He accompanied Alicia Keys on guitar on her song "No One" at the ceremony.

In February 2008, Mayer hosted a three-day Caribbean cruise event that included performances with various musicians including David Ryan Harris, Brett Dennen, and Colbie Caillat, among others. The event was called "The Mayercraft Carrier" and was held aboard the cruise ship known as the ''Carnival Victory''. A follow up cruise titled "Mayercraft Carrier 2" set sail from Long Beach, California on March 27-31, 2009 on the Carnival Splendor.

On July 1, 2008, Mayer released ''Where the Light Is'' a live concert film of Mayer's performance at the Nokia Theatre L.A. Live on December 8, 2007. The film was directed by Danny Clinch. It features an acoustic set and a set with the John Mayer Trio, followed by a set with John's band from the ''Continuum'' album. The DVD and Bluray bonus material includes footage of Mayer backstage and playing outside on Mulholland Drive.. ''Johnmayer.com''. July 1, 2008. Retrieved July 2, 2008.

CBS confirmed on January 14, 2009 that Mayer is in negotiations with the station for a variety show. The details of the deal and the nature of the show are yet unknown.Fernandez, Maria Elena (January 14, 2009), . ''The Los Angeles Times''. (accessed 2009-01-20)

Mayer has recently collaborated with Australian soul artist Guy Sebastian on three songs on his upcoming album "Like it Like That". . ''Undercover Music News''. (Retrieved 4 August 2009)   He also played guitar on the title track of Crosby Loggins's debut LP, ''Time to Move'', released on July 10, 2009.Newman-Bremang, Kathleen (May 12, 2009), . MTV.com. (accessed 2009-06-24) and 

On 7 July 2009, Mayer performed an instrumental guitar version of Michael Jackson's "Human Nature" at Jackson's memorial service.Powers, Ann; Martens, Todd (July 7, 2009)  LA Times (accessed 2009-07-08)
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f7e8899844567497ccb8b74c51469a8c" name="Rolling_Stone_-_The_New_Guitar_Gods" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/f7e8899844567497ccb8b74c51469a8c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>