<document id="4326505b6fed19a0464dfcc01ca17a1d-3" name="Battlefield_Earth_(film)" cat="19">
<text>
Travolta and his manager, Jonathan Krane, took the lead in hiring the on-set personnel. They initially approached Quentin Tarantino to direct the film. When Tarantino declined, Roger Christian, a protégé of George Lucas, was recruited as the director. Christian had most recently been the second unit director on Lucas' ''Star Wars Episode I: The Phantom Menace''. Patrick Tatopoulos was signed to develop the production design and costumes, including the design of the alien Psychlos, and Czech-American composer Elia Cmiral was signed to provide the film's score. Travolta and Krane also signed the cinematographer and most of the principal actors. Corey Mandell, a screenwriter who had previously worked with Ridley Scott on ''Blade Runner'', signed on to write the script for the film, which had previously gone through 10 revisions. Mandell stated in an interview, "I am not a Scientologist ... I came on board because John asked me to read the book and said, 'It's not a religious book. It's a science-fiction story. There's nothing sacred about the story, nothing of the religious philosophy.' I was given this to read purely as science fiction &mdash; to see whether it was intriguing as a movie. And it was."


The cast included Travolta, Barry Pepper, Forest Whitaker, Kim Coates, Richard Tyson, Sabine Karsenti, and Michael Byrne. Travolta's wife Kelly Preston also appeared in one scene, playing Terl's "baldish Psychlo girlfriend". Travolta originally saw himself in the role of Tyler, but by the time the movie was actually made, Travolta felt he was too old to play the role, and took the role of the main villain instead. Travolta's role in the film required what he described as an amazing physical transformation: "I wear a tall head apparatus with strange hair. I have amber eyes and talons for hands. It's quite remarkable ... I'm on 4-foot stilts." To star in the film, Travolta turned down the movie ''The Shipping News'' and postponed production on ''Standing Room Only''.

The movie was filmed in Canada, with principal filming taking place in Montreal and several other Quebec locations during the summer and autumn of 1999. In January 1999, Travolta flew his private Boeing 727 on a secret visit to Montreal to scout out locations for shooting. The film was reported to have been the most expensive production shot in Canada up to that point. It was also reported that the production costs would have been twice as high had the film been shot in the United States.

In an ominous sign for the film's prospects, it was "plagued by bad buzz" before release with the media speculating about the possible influence of Scientology and commenting on the production's tight security. As the film was entering post-production, the alternative newspaper ''Mean Magazine'' obtained a copy of the screenplay. ''Mean's'' staffers changed the script's title to "Dark Forces" by "Desmond Finch" and circulated it to readers at major Hollywood film production companies. The comments that came back were universally unfavorable: "a thoroughly silly plotline is made all the more ludicrous by its hamfisted  dialog and ridiculously shallow characterizations", "a completely predictable story that just isn't written well enough to make up for its lack of originality". One reviewer labeled the screenplay "as entertaining as watching a fly breathe".

''Battlefield Earth'' was released on May 12, 2000, three days after the 50th anniversary of the publication of Hubbard's book ''Dianetics: The Modern Science of Mental Health'', a date celebrated by Scientologists worldwide as a major Scientology holiday. Its premiere was held on May 10, 2000 at Mann's Chinese Theater on Hollywood Boulevard in Los Angeles.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b50fb383e09ab2909b4c8215d92de5b7" name="Battlefield_earth_screencap" sectnum="3#1">../img/b50fb383e09ab2909b4c8215d92de5b7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>