<document id="43cd981d95db24efb7e9a7ef4eb512ab-5.6" name="History_of_Minnesota" cat="14">
<text>
After the Civil War, Minnesota became an attractive region for European immigration and settlement as farmland.  Minnesota's population in 1870 was 439,000; this number tripled during the two subsequent decades.  The Homestead Act in 1862 facilitated land claims by settlers, who regarded the land as being cheap and fertile.  The railroad industry, led by the Northern Pacific Railway and Saint Paul and Pacific Railroad, advertised the many opportunities in the state and worked to get immigrants to settle in Minnesota.  James J. Hill, in particular, was instrumental in reorganizing the Saint Paul and Pacific Railroad and extending lines from the Minneapolis-Saint Paul area into the Red River Valley and to Winnipeg.  Hill was also responsible for building a new passenger depot in Minneapolis, served by the landmark Stone Arch Bridge which was completed in 1883.  During the 1880s, Hill continued building tracks through North Dakota and Montana.  In 1890, the railroad, now known as the Great Northern Railway, started building tracks through the mountains west to Seattle.  Other railroads, such as the Lake Superior and Mississippi Railroad and the Milwaukee Road, also played an important role in the early days of Minnesota's statehood.  Later railways, such as the Soo Line and Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway facilitated the sale of Minneapolis flour and other products, although they were not as involved in attracting settlers.

Oliver Hudson Kelley played an important role in farming as one of the founders of the National Grange, along with several other clerks in the United States Department of Agriculture.  The movement grew out of his interest in cooperative farm associations following the end of the Civil War, and he established local Grange chapters in Elk River and Saint Paul.  The organization worked to provide education on new farming methods, as well as to influence government and public opinion on matters important to farmers.  One of these areas of concern was the freight rates charged by the railroads and by the grain elevators.  Since there was little or no competition between railroads serving Minnesota farm communities, railroads could charge as much as the traffic would bear.  By 1871, the situation was so heated that both the Republican and Democratic candidates in state elections promised to regulate railroad rates.  The state established an office of railroad commissioner and imposed maximum charges for shipping.  Populist Ignatius L. Donnelly also served the Grange as an organizer.

Saint Anthony Falls, the only waterfall of its height on the Mississippi, played an important part in the development of Minneapolis.  The power of the waterfall first fueled sawmills, but later it was tapped to serve flour mills.  In 1870, only a small number of flour mills were in the Minneapolis area, but by 1900 Minnesota mills were grinding 14.1% of the nation's grain.  Advances in transportation, milling technology, and water power combined to give Minneapolis a dominance in the milling industry.  Spring wheat could be sown in the spring and harvested in late summer, but it posed special problems for milling.  To get around these problems, Minneapolis millers made use of new technology.  They invented the middlings purifier, a device that used jets of air to remove the husks from the flour early in the milling process.  They also started using roller mills, as opposed to grindstones.  A series of rollers gradually broke down the kernels and integrated the gluten with the starch.  These improvements led to the production of "patent" flour, which commanded almost double the price of "bakers" or "clear" flour, which it replaced. Pillsbury and the Washburn-Crosby Company (a forerunner of General Mills) became the leaders in the Minneapolis milling industry.  This leadership in milling later declined as milling was no longer dependent on water power, but the dominance of the mills contributed greatly to the economy of Minneapolis and Minnesota, attracting people and money to the region.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d051e36ccb236e96b99405876e13bbde" name="Mill_City_Museum" sectnum="5.6#1">../img/d051e36ccb236e96b99405876e13bbde.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>