<document id="43cd981d95db24efb7e9a7ef4eb512ab-6.12" name="History_of_Minnesota" cat="14">
<text>
Like other U.S. States, Minnesota made its contributions to the effort of World War II in wartime manufacturing and other areas. The United States Navy contracted with Cargill to build ships after seeing their success in building ships and barges used to haul grain.  Cargill built facilities in Savage, Minnesota on the south bank of the Minnesota River and turned out 18 refueling ships and four towboats in four years.  After the war, the Cargill facilities became a major grain shipping terminal. Honeywell built airplane control systems and periscope sights for submarines, and also developed a proximity fuse for anti-aircraft shells.  The United States government built the Twin Cities Ordnance Plant to produce munitions.  The plant employed 8,500 workers in 1941, and since there was a shortage of male workers during the war, more than half of the workers at the munitions plant were women.  The plant also employed nearly 1000 African American workers, as President Roosevelt had issued an executive order forbidding racial discrimination in defense industries.  Native American workers also found opportunities due to workforce shortages in wartime.

During the wartime years, Savage was also the home of Camp Savage, a school designed to improve the foreign language skills of Japanese-American soldiers and to train them in military intelligence gathering.  The school was originally established in San Francisco, but moved to Minnesota after the bombing of Pearl Harbor.  Eventually, the school outgrew its facilities in Savage and was moved to Fort Snelling.  Fort Snelling itself served a major role as a reception center for newly drafted recruits after the Selective Service Act was passed in 1940.  New recruits were given a physical exam and the Army General Qualification Test to determine their fitness for service in a particular branch.  The most intelligent recruits, about 37% of Minnesotans going through Fort Snelling, were assigned to the Army Air Corps.  Recruits were also issued uniforms and sent from the fort to other training centers.  Over 300,000 recruits were processed through Fort Snelling during the World War II years.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b76b53020cd87be7e20d7b4e2dcdd9b5" name="snellingbldgs" sectnum="6.12#1">../img/b76b53020cd87be7e20d7b4e2dcdd9b5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>