<document id="4417b11a49bee1dca8edee49d5d15fc3-1.4" name="Godsmack" cat="20">
<text>
In 2002, Erna was asked to write and perform a song for the soundtrack to ''The Scorpion King''. The motion picture was the third in the ''Mummy'' saga, and was a spin-off prequel of the ''Mummy'' series. The song Godsmack wrote and performed was titled "I Stand Alone" and became the number 1 single at Rock Radio and the most played Active Rock song in 2002 for 14 weeks straight. It was also used in the game Prince of Persia: Warrior Within.


With Shannon Larkin (ex Ugly Kid Joe, Souls at Zero, Wrathchild America, MF Pitbulls) replacing Tommy Stewart, who left due to personal differences for the second time, Godsmack went back into the studio to record a new album that was released in 2003. ''Faceless'' debuted at number one on the ''Billboard 200'', selling 269,000 copies in its first week, and the album would go on to sell over one million copies in the United States. ''Faceless'' managed to beat West Coast nu metal rival Linkin Park, with the release of their second studio album ''Meteora'', which dropped to number two on the ''Billboard 200''. ''Faceless'' also debuted at number nine on the Top Canadian Albums and at number one on the Top Internet Albums and remained at that position for two weeks. A massive Tour of America and Europe supporting Metallica followed.

The lead single "Straight Out of Line" received a Grammy Award nomination for "Best Hard Rock Performance." The award went to Evanescence's single, "Bring Me to Life".

The album got its name after a pool incident, retold by Larkin; "Sully and I were standing up for one more jump, we're both there buck-naked, and I look over to the left and there's some woman who had just opened the blinds standing there with her mouth wide open". Erna added, "She was just waking up, we go, 'Sorry', and then boom, right into the pool. The next thing we know the cops are banging on the door, and that's sort of the point of calling the record ''Faceless''". However in a later interview Merrill stated otherwise, making it unclear of how the album's title came to be, "It came from the band's feeling that, despite our radio and sales success, we still flew a bit under the radar".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="504073ac7608e0212806694c1d2ecffb" name="Shannon_Larkin_godsmack_drums" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/504073ac7608e0212806694c1d2ecffb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>