<document id="4417b11a49bee1dca8edee49d5d15fc3-2" name="Godsmack" cat="20">
<text>
The band's primary influences include Alice in Chains, Black Sabbath, Led Zeppelin, Aerosmith, Judas Priest, Pantera, Metallica and Rush according to Erna, Larkin, and Rombola. Erna has cited Staley as his primary influence. The overall sound of the band's first two albums sound similar to the sound of the Alice in Chains album, ''Dirt'', according to Subvulture.com. More recently, Godsmack has attempted to distance themselves from the Alice in Chains comparison with Erna stating in an interview with Matt Ashare, "I've just never really heard that in our music".

''Rolling Stone Magazine'' describes the band as "hard as nails and cranked to eleven," while Alternative Press praised the band for its "churning, riff-driven hybrid of all that is heavy, past and present."

The band's music is often compared to Alice in Chains, which the band cites as an influence. Adrien Begrand of ''Popmatters'' states, "Erna perfectly mimics the late Layne Staley's low, guttural, sinister singing and snarly, metal-inspired growls"-Erna's vocals also seem to be reminiscent of Metallica's James Hetfield-and, "The band's music is a faithful retread of Jerry Cantrell's churning, tuned-down hard rock". Katherine Turman of Amazon.com states the band has, "dark, swirling, commanding music". She also commented on the band's third album ''Faceless'', "mixes arena rock in the vein of an Alice in Chains" and, "riff-heavy, layered tunes and sharp, confident bridge-burning lyrics".

Erna's singing style has been stated as "the snarl of James Hetfield", and, "is composed of dark harmony that sounds a lot like Alice in Chains". Merrill's bass style has been described as "bulldozer bottom with occasional slap-bass reverb". Larkin's drumming is thought to "worship at the twin altars of Neil Peart and John Bonham". And Rombola's guitar playing style has been praised as, "guitars that sound like percussion instruments".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="832dabfed77cb87bbb892a665183f619" name="Sully_Erna" sectnum="2#1">../img/832dabfed77cb87bbb892a665183f619.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>