<document id="4442e4af0916f53a07fb8ca9a49b98ed-8" name="Australia" cat="11">
<text>
The Australian dollar is the currency of the Commonwealth of Australia, including Christmas Island, Cocos (Keeling) Islands, and Norfolk Island, as well as the independent Pacific Island states of Kiribati, Nauru, and Tuvalu. After the 2006 merger of the ''Australian Stock Exchange'' and the ''Sydney Futures Exchange'', the Australian Securities Exchange is now the 9th largest in the World.http://www.asx.com.au/about/pdf/asx_speech_eric_mayne_061106.pdf

Australia is one of the most laissez-faire free market economies, according to indices of economic freedom. Australia's per capita GDP is slightly higher than that of the UK, Germany, and France in terms of purchasing power parity. The country was ranked second in the United Nations 2009 Human Development Index, first in Legatum's 2008 Prosperity Index, and sixth in ''The Economist'' worldwide Quality-of-Life Index for 2005. All of Australia's major cities fare well in global comparative liveability surveys; (2004), ''The Age''. Retrieved on 31 January 2009. Melbourne reached 2nd place on ''The Economist'''s 2008 World's Most Livable Cities list, followed by Perth at 4th, Adelaide at 7th, and Sydney at 9th.". 

An emphasis on exporting commodities rather than manufactures has underpinned a significant increase in Australia's terms of trade during the rise in commodity prices since the start of the century. Australia has a balance of payments that is more than 7% of GDP negative, and has had persistently large current account deficits for more than 50 years. The Economist, 29 March 2007. Australia has grown at an average annual rate of 3.6% for over 15 years, a period in which the OECD annual average was 2.5%. Australia did not fall into a technical recession during the late 2000s recession that affected most other Western countries , BBC News, Wednesday, 3 June 2009.


Destination and value of Australian exports in 2006

The Hawke Government floated the Australian dollar in 1983 and partially deregulated the financial system.Macfarlane, I. J. (1998). . ''Reserve Bank of Australia Bulletin'', October. The Howard Government followed with a partial deregulation of the labour market and the further privatisation of state-owned businesses, most notably in the telecommunications industry.Parham, D. (2002). . ''Conference of Economists'', Adelaide, 1 October. The indirect tax system was substantially changed in July 2000 with the introduction of a 10% Goods and Services Tax (GST), which has slightly reduced the reliance on personal and company income tax that characterises Australia's tax system.

In January 2007, there were 10,033,480 people employed, with an unemployment rate of 4.6%.Australian Bureau of Statistics. Labour Force Australia. Cat#6202.0. Over the past decade, inflation has typically been 2–3% and the base interest rate 5–6%. The service sector of the economy, including tourism, education, and financial services, accounts for 69% of GDP.Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade (2003). ''Advancing the National Interest'', . Although agriculture and natural resources account for only 3% and 5% of GDP respectively, they contribute substantially to export performance. Australia's largest export markets are Japan, China, the US, South Korea, and New Zealand.Australian Bureau of Statistics. .
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="eb2c239a40ce2017308117ad5bac6365" name="Kalgoorlie_The_Big_Pit_DSC04498" sectnum="8#1">../img/eb2c239a40ce2017308117ad5bac6365.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>