<document id="4442e4af0916f53a07fb8ca9a49b98ed-1" name="Australia" cat="11">
<text>
The name ''Australia'' is derived from the Latin ''australis'', meaning "southern". Legends of an "unknown land of the south" (''terra australis incognita'') date back to Roman times and were commonplace in medieval geography but were not based on any documented knowledge of the continent. 

The first recorded use of the word ''Australia'' in English was in 1625, in "A note of Australia del Espíritu Santo, written by Master Hakluyt", published by Samuel Purchas in ''Hakluytus Posthumus''.Purchas, vol. iv, pp. 1422–32, 1625. This appears to be variation of the original Spanish "Austrialia" . A copy at the Library of Congress can be read online .
The Dutch adjectival form ''Australische'' was used by Dutch East India Company officials in Batavia to refer to the newly discovered land to the south in 1638. ''Australia'' was used in a 1693 translation of ''Les Aventures de Jacques Sadeur dans la Découverte et le Voyage de la Terre Australe'', a 1676 French novel by Gabriel de Foigny under the pen-name Jacques Sadeur.Sidney J. Baker, ''The Australian Language'', second edition, 1966.  Alexander Dalrymple then used it in ''An Historical Collection of Voyages and Discoveries in the South Pacific Ocean'' (1771), to refer to the entire South Pacific region. In 1793, George Shaw and Sir James Smith published ''Zoology and Botany of New Holland'', in which they wrote of "the vast island, or rather continent, of Australia, Australasia or New Holland". It also appeared on a 1799 chart by James Wilson.

The name ''Australia'' was popularised by Matthew Flinders, who, as early as 1804, pushed for the name to be formally adopted. When preparing his manuscript and charts for his 1814 ''A Voyage to Terra Australis'', he was persuaded by his patron Sir Joseph Banks to use the term ''Terra Australis'' as this was the name most familiar to the public. Flinders did so, but allowed himself the footnote:  This is the only occurrence of the word ''Australia'' in that text; but in Appendix III, Robert Brown's ''General remarks, geographical and systematical, on the botany of Terra Australis'', Brown makes use of the adjectival form ''Australian'' throughout, this being the first known use of that form. Despite popular conception, the book was not instrumental in the adoption of the name: the name came gradually to be accepted over the following ten years.Estensen p. 450. Lachlan Macquarie, a Governor of New South Wales, subsequently used the word in his dispatches to England, and on 12 December 1817 recommended to the Colonial Office that it be formally adopted.Weekend Australian, 30–31 December 2000, p. 16 In 1824, the Admiralty agreed that the continent should be known officially as ''Australia''.

The word ''Australia'' in Australian English is pronounced .Australian pronunciations: ''Macquarie Dictionary, Fourth Edition'' (2005). Melbourne, The Macquarie Library Pty Ltd. ISBN 1-876429-14-3. Since early in the 20th century, the country has been sometimes referred to locally and internationally as ''Oz''. ''Aussie'' (less frequently spelt ''Ozzie'', better representing the pronunciation) is common colloquially as an adjective, and as a noun referring to an Australian.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="625a11b5c86aa7dccec2215b65d96ae7" name="Flinders_View_of_Port_Jackson_taken_from_South_Head" sectnum="1#1">../img/625a11b5c86aa7dccec2215b65d96ae7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>