<document id="44b439ba9975f8e802b456777c54a854-7" name="Antarctica" cat="11">
<text>
Antarctica has no government and belongs to no country. Various countries claim areas of it but, while some have mutually recognized each other's claims, "Australia, New Zealand, France, Norway and the United Kingdom reciprocally recognize the validity of each other's claims." no other countries recognize such claims.

New claims on Antarctica have been suspended since 1959 and the continent is considered politically neutral. Its status is regulated by the 1959 Antarctic Treaty and other related agreements, collectively called the Antarctic Treaty System. Antarctica is defined as all land and ice shelves south of 60° S for the purposes of the Treaty System. The treaty was signed by twelve countries including the Soviet Union (and later Russia), the United Kingdom, Argentina, Chile, Australia, and the United States. It set aside Antarctica as a scientific preserve, established freedom of scientific investigation and environmental protection, and banned military activity on the continent. This was the first arms control agreement established during the Cold War. 

In 1983, the Antarctic Treaty Parties began negotiations on a convention to regulate mining in Antarctica.  A coalition of international organisations launched a public pressure campaign to prevent any minerals development in the region, led largely by Greenpeace International which established its own scientific station – World Park Base – in the Ross Sea region and conducted annual expeditions to document environmental effects of humans on the continent.  In 1988, the Convention on the Regulation of Antarctic Mineral Resources (CRAMRA) was adopted. The following year, however, Australia and France announced that they would not ratify the convention, rendering it dead for all intents and purposes. They proposed instead that a comprehensive regime to protect the Antarctic environment be negotiated in its place. The Protocol on Environmental Protection to the Antarctic Treaty (the ‘Madrid Protocol’) was negotiated as other countries followed suit and on 14 January 1998 it entered into force. The Madrid Protocol bans all mining in Antarctica, designating the continent as a ‘natural reserve devoted to peace and science’.

The Antarctic Treaty prohibits any military activity in Antarctica, including the establishment of military bases and fortifications, military manoeuvers, and weapons testing. Military personnel or equipment are permitted only for scientific research or other peaceful purposes. The only documented military land manoeuvre was Operation NINETY by the Argentine military.

The United States military issues the Antarctica Service Medal to military members or civilians who perform research duty in Antarctica. The medal includes a "wintered over" bar issued to those who remain on the continent for 2 six-month seasons.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3618bb7b2894f99ff7e08fff43794d34" name="HMS_Endurance,_Portsmouth" sectnum="7#1">../img/3618bb7b2894f99ff7e08fff43794d34.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>