<document id="44bef2ee415c62f0ce01fbe6c5566250-8" name="Kolkata" cat="11">
<text>
The KMC supplies potable water to the city, sourced from the River Hooghly. The water is purified and treated at Palta water pumping station located in North 24 Parganas. Almost all of Kolkata's daily refuse of 2500 tonnes is transported to the dumping grounds in Dhapa to the east of the town. Agriculture on this dumping ground is encouraged for natural recycling of garbage and sewer water.

 Parts of the city still lack sewage facilities leading to unsanitary methods of waste disposal.

 Electricity is supplied by the privately operated Calcutta Electric Supply Corporation (CESC) to the city region, and by the West Bengal State Electricity Board in the suburbs. Frequent interruption of power supply was a problem until the mid 1990s; however the situation has since improved immensely with seldom power cuts occurring presently. The city has 20 fire stations (under West Bengal Fire Service) that attend to 7,500 fire and rescue calls on average per year.



State-owned BSNL and private enterprises like Vodafone, Airtel, Reliance Communications, Aircel and Tata Indicom are the leading telephone and cell phone service providers in the city. Cellular coverage is extensive with both GSM and CDMA services being available. Virgin Mobile and MTS India are also offers CDMA based mobile services over city. Broadband internet penetration has steadily increased with BSNL, Tata Indicom, Airtel and Reliance being the leading service providers. Sify and Alliance also offers Broadband service in Kolkata.

Bengali language newspapers like ''Anandabazar Patrika'', ''Aajkaal'', ''Bartaman'', ''Sangbad Pratidin'' and ''Ganashakti'', Dainik Statesman are widely circulated. Regional and national English newspapers such as ''The Times of India'', ''Hindustan Times'', ''The Telegraph'', ''The Statesman'' and ''Asian Age'', are sold in large numbers. Some major periodicals are ''Desh'', ''Sananda'', ''Unish Kuri'', ''Kindle'', ''Anandalok'' and ''Anandamela''. Being the biggest trading market in Eastern India, Kolkata has a substantial readership of many financial dailies including Economic Times, Financial Express and Business Standard. Vernacular newspapers such as those in Hindi, Gujarati, Oriya, Urdu, Punjabi and Chinese are also read by a minority. All India Radio (AIR), the state-owned radio broadcaster, airs several AM radio stations in the city. Kolkata has 12 local FM radio stations, including two from AIR. The state-owned television broadcaster Doordarshan provides two free terrestrial channels, while four MSO provide a mix of Bengali, Hindi, English and other regional channels via cable. Bengali 24-hour television news channels include STAR Ananda, 24 Ghanta, Kolkata TV,Channel 10 and Tara Newz.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5f5d03605a5532203c2ab5e34f09f4f1" name="Kolkatavsnl" sectnum="8#1">../img/5f5d03605a5532203c2ab5e34f09f4f1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>