<document id="44db7fe40b3dc4854932bc1d8b36400e-6.6" name="Ernest_Shackleton" cat="14">
<text>
''Endurance''  departed from South Georgia for the Weddell Sea on 5 December, heading for Vahsel Bay. As the ship moved southward, early ice was encountered, which slowed progress. Deep in the Weddell Sea conditions gradually grew worse until, on 19 January 1915, ''Endurance'' became frozen fast in an ice floe.Shackleton (''South''), pp. 29&ndash;30 On 24 February, realising that she would be trapped until the following spring, Shackleton ordered the abandonment of ship's routine and her conversion to a winter station.Shackleton (''South''), p. 36 She drifted slowly northward with the ice through the following months.   When spring arrived in September the breaking of the ice and its later movements put extreme pressures on the ship's hull.Shackleton (''South''), pp. 63&ndash;66 

Until this point Shackleton had hoped that the ship, when she was released from the ice, could work her way back towards Vahsel Bay. On 24 October, however, water began pouring in. After a few days, with the position at 69°05'S, 51°30'W, Shackleton gave the order to abandon ship, saying, "She's going down!"; and men, provisions and equipment were transferred to camps on the ice.Shackleton (''South''), pp. 75&ndash;76  On 21 November 1915, the wreck finally slipped beneath the surface.Shackleton (''South''), p. 98

For almost two months Shackleton and his party camped on a large, flat floe, hoping that it would drift towards Paulet Island, approximately  away, where it was known that stores were cached.Shackleton (''South''), p. 100   After failed attempts to march across the ice to this island, Shackleton decided to set up another more permanent camp (Patience Camp) on another floe, and trust to the drift of the ice to take them towards a safe landing.Shackleton, p. 106 By 17 March their ice camp was within  of Paulet IslandFisher, p. 366 but, separated by impassable ice, they were unable to reach it. On 9 April their ice floe broke into two, and Shackleton ordered the crew into the lifeboats, to head for the nearest land.Shackleton (''South''), pp. 121&ndash;22  After five harrowing days at sea the exhausted men landed their three lifeboats at Elephant Island. This was the first time they had stood on solid ground for 497 days.Shackleton (''South''), p. 143 Shackleton's concern for his men was such that he gave his mittens to photographer Frank Hurley, who had lost his during the boat journey. Shackleton suffered frostbitten fingers as a result.Perkins, p, 36
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b97df31e9f2a2c947657139e523aa823" name="Shackletonold" sectnum="6.6#1">../img/b97df31e9f2a2c947657139e523aa823.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>