<document id="44db7fe40b3dc4854932bc1d8b36400e-6.7" name="Ernest_Shackleton" cat="14">
<text>
Elephant Island was an inhospitable place, far from any shipping routes. Consequently, Shackleton decided to risk an open-boat journey to the distant South Georgia whaling stations, where he knew help was available. The strongest of the lifeboats, christened  ''James Caird'' after the expedition's chief sponsor, was chosen for the trip. Ship's carpenter Harry McNish made various improvements, including raising the sides, strengthening the keel, building a makeshift deck of wood and canvas, and sealing the work with oil paint and seal blood. Shackleton chose five companions for the journey: Frank Worsley, ''Endurance'''s captain, who would be responsible for navigation; Tom Crean, who had "begged to go"; two strong sailors in John Vincent and Timothy McCarthy, and finally the carpenter McNish. Shackleton had clashed with McNish during the time when the party was stranded on the ice but, while he would not forgive the carpenter's earlier insubordination, Shackleton recognised his value for this particular job.For an account of McNish's "mutiny", see Huntford, pp. 475&ndash;76. Despite McNish's heroics during the ''James Caird'' voyage, Shackleton refused to recommend him for the award of a Polar Medal &ndash; Huntford, p. 656

Shackleton refused to pack supplies for more than four weeks, knowing that if they did not reach South Georgia within that time, the boat and its crew would be lost.Alexander, p. 137 The ''James Caird'' was launched on 24 April 1916; during the next fifteen days it sailed through the waters of the southern ocean, at the mercy of the stormy seas, in constant peril of capsizing. On 8 May, due to Worsley's navigational skills, the cliffs of South Georgia came into sight, but hurricane-force winds prevented the possibility of landing. The party were forced to ride out the storm offshore, in constant danger of being dashed against the rocks. They would later learn that the same hurricane had sunk a 500-ton steamer bound for South Georgia from Buenos Aires.Worsley, p. 162 On the following day they were able, finally, to land on the unoccupied southern shore.   After a period of rest and recuperation, rather than risk putting to sea again to reach the whaling stations on the northern coast, Shackleton decided to attempt a land crossing of the island. Although it is likely that Norwegian whalers had previously crossed at other points on ski, no one had attempted this particular route before.Huntford, p. 574 Leaving McNish, Vincent and McCarthy at the landing point on South Georgia, Shackleton travelled with Worsley and Crean over mountainous terrain for 36 hours to reach the whaling station at Stromness.Worsley, pp. 211&ndash;12
 
The next successful crossing of South Georgia was in October 1955, by the British explorer Duncan Carse, who travelled much of the same route as Shackleton's party. In tribute to their achievement he wrote: "I do not know how they did it, except that they had to&mdash;three men of the heroic age of Antarctic exploration with 50 feet of rope between them&mdash;and a carpenter's adze".Quoted in Fisher, p. 386
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="97a2d991202d5019dbf43b7e3705184d" name="LaunchingTheJamesCaird2" sectnum="6.7#1">../img/97a2d991202d5019dbf43b7e3705184d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>