<document id="44db7fe40b3dc4854932bc1d8b36400e-3" name="Ernest_Shackleton" cat="14">
<text>
After a period of convalescence in New Zealand, Shackleton returned to England via San Francisco and New York.Fisher, pp. 78&ndash;80 As the first significant person to return from the Antarctic he found that he was in demand; in particular, the Admiralty wished to consult him about their further proposals for the rescue of ''Discovery''.Huntford, pp. 119&ndash;20 With Sir Clements Markham's blessing he accepted a temporary post assisting the outfitting of the ''Terra Nova'' for the second ''Discovery'' relief operation but turned down the offer to sail with her as chief officer. He also assisted in the equipping of the Argentinian gunboat ''Uruguay'', which was being fitted out for the relief of the stranded  Swedish Antarctic Expedition under Nordenskiöld. In search of more permanent employment, Shackleton applied for a regular commission in the Royal Navy, via the back-door route of the Supplementary List,Huntford, p. 123 but despite the sponsorship of Markham and of the president of the Royal Society he was not successful.   Instead, he became a journalist, working for the ''Royal Magazine'', but found this unsatisfactory.Huntford, pp. 124&ndash;28 He was then offered, and accepted, the secretaryship of the Royal Scottish Geographical Society (RSGS), a post which he took up on 11 January 1904.

In 1905 Shackleton became a shareholder in a speculative company that aimed to make a fortune transporting Russian troops home from the Far East. Despite his assurances to Emily that "we are practically sure of the contract" nothing came of this scheme.Fisher, pp. 97&ndash;98 He also ventured into politics, unsuccessfully standing in the 1906 General Election as the Liberal Unionist Party's candidate for Dundee.He finished fourth of five candidates, with 3,865 votes to the victor's 9,276. Morrell, p. 32 Meantime he had taken a job with wealthy Clydeside industrialist William Beardmore (later Lord Invernairn), with a roving commission which involved interviewing prospective clients and entertaining Beardmore's business friends.Fisher, p. 99  Shackleton by this time, however, was making no secret of his ambition to return to Antarctica at the head of his own expedition. 

Beardmore was sufficiently impressed with Shackleton to offer financial support,Beardmore's help took the form of guaranteeing a loan at Clydesdale Bank, for £7,000 (2008 equivalent approx. £350,000), not through an outright gift. Riffenburgh, p. 106  but other donations proved hard to come by. Nevertheless, in February 1907 Shackleton presented his plans for an Antarctic expedition to the Royal Geographic Society, the details of which, under the name British Antarctic Expedition, were published in the Royal Society's newsletter, ''Geographic Journal''. The aim was the conquest of both the geographical South Pole and the South Magnetic Pole. Shackleton then worked hard to persuade others of his wealthy friends and acquaintances to contribute, including Sir Phillip Lee Brocklehurst, who subscribed £2,000 (2008 equivalent £150,000) to secure a place on the expedition,Riffenburgh, p. 108 author Campbell Mackellar, and Guinness baron Lord Iveagh whose contribution was secured less than two weeks before the departure of the expedition ship ''Nimrod''.Riffenburgh, p. 130
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="876a8ce607124a95cbc8d386cc061e8f" name="Emily_Dorman_(Lady_Shackelton)" sectnum="3#1">../img/876a8ce607124a95cbc8d386cc061e8f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>