<document id="44db7fe40b3dc4854932bc1d8b36400e-4" name="Ernest_Shackleton" cat="14">
<text>
On 1 January 1908, ''Nimrod'' sailed for the Antarctic from Lyttleton Harbour, New Zealand. Shackleton's original plans had envisaged using the old ''Discovery'' base in McMurdo Sound to launch his attempts on the South Pole and South Magnetic Pole.  However, before leaving England he had been pressured to give an undertaking to Scott that he would not base himself in the McMurdo area, which Scott was claiming as his own field of work. Shackleton reluctantly agreed to look for winter quarters either at the Barrier Inlet (which ''Discovery'' had briefly visited in 1902) or at King Edward VII Land.Riffenburgh, pp. 110&ndash;16 

To conserve coal, the ship was towed  by the steamer ''Koonya'' to the Antarctic ice, after Shackleton had persuaded the New Zealand government and the Union Steamship Company to share the cost.Riffenburgh, pp. 143&ndash;44 In accordance with Shackleton's promise to Scott the ship headed for the eastern sector of the Great Ice Barrier, arriving there on 21 January 1908. They found that the Barrier Inlet had expanded to form a large bay, in which were hundreds of whales, which led to the immediate christening of the area as the Bay of Whales.Riffenburgh, pp. 151&ndash;53 It was noted that ice conditions were unstable, precluding the establishment of a safe base there. An extended search for an anchorage at King Edward VII Land proved equally fruitless, so Shackleton was forced to break his undertaking to Scott and set sail for McMurdo Sound, a decision which, according to second officer Arthur Harbord, was "dictated by common sense" in view of the difficulties of ice pressure, coal shortage and the lack of any nearer known base.

''Nimrod'' arrived at McMurdo Sound on 29 January, but was stopped by ice  north of ''Discovery'''s old base at Hut Point.Riffenburgh, pp. 157&ndash;67 After considerable weather delays, Shackleton's base was eventually established at Cape Royds, about  north of Hut Point. The party was in high spirits, despite the difficult conditions; Shackleton's ability to communicate with each man kept the party happy and focused.Riffenburgh, pp. 185&ndash;86

The "Great Southern Journey",Mills, p. 72 as Frank Wild called it, began on 19 October 1908. On 9 January 1909 Shackleton and three companions (Wild, Eric Marshall and Jameson Adams) reached a new Farthest South latitude of 88°23'S, a point only  from the Pole.Shackleton: ''Heart of the Antarctic'', p. 210. The distance from the Pole is commonly given as 97 or 98 miles, this being the distance in nautical miles.  En route the South Pole party discovered the Beardmore Glacier, (named after Shackleton's patron),Mills, pp. 82&ndash;86 and became the first persons to see and travel on the South Polar Plateau.Mills, p. 90 Their return journey to McMurdo Sound was a race against starvation, on half-rations for much of the way. At one point Shackleton gave his one biscuit allotted for the day to the ailing Frank Wild, who wrote in his diary: "All the money that was ever minted would not have bought that biscuit and the remembrance of that sacrifice will never leave me". Mills, p. 108 They arrived at Hut Point just in time to catch the ship.

The expedition's other main accomplishments included the first ascent of Mount Erebus, and the discovery of the approximate location of the South Magnetic Pole, reached on 16 January 1909 by Edgeworth David, Douglas Mawson, and Alistair Mackay.Riffenburgh, p. 244   Shackleton returned to the United Kingdom as a hero, and soon afterwards published his expedition account, ''The Heart of the Antarctic''. Emily Shackleton later recorded: "The only comment he made to me about not reaching the Pole was "a live donkey is better than a dead lion, isn't it?" and I said "Yes darling, as far as I am concerned".Huntford, p. 300
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="25f103819cfa7fe88f776a103923aa9f" name="TheSouthernParty" sectnum="4#1">../img/25f103819cfa7fe88f776a103923aa9f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>