<document id="44ede2e7d638461432bfa297951762ea-4" name="History_of_Aston_Villa_F.C._(1961–present)" cat="26">
<text>
On 26 May 1982, just three months after being appointed manager, Barton guided Villa to a 1&ndash;0 victory over Bayern Munich in the European Cup final in Rotterdam. As of January 2008, Villa remain one of only four English teams to have won the European Cup, along with Liverpool, Manchester United and Nottingham Forest. They were the underdogs in the final and were expected to lose.Ward, Adam, p.124

The final was held in Feyenoord Stadium, Rotterdam, with an attendance of 39,776. Only nine minutes into the game, Villa lost their experienced goalkeeper Jimmy Rimmer to a shoulder injury. He was replaced by 23-year-old reserve goalkeeper Nigel Spink, who had only played one match for the club in five years since joining from Chelmsford. Spink went on to make one of his best performances for the clubWard, Adam, p.131, " produced the performance of a lifetime just when it was needed most" against the highly experienced Bayern strikeforce, which included Karl-Heinz Rummenigge. Other key players in this Villa side included Tony Morley, Gordon Cowans and Dennis Mortimer.Ward, Adam, p.133

The win was not followed with more success and the team performed badly in the following seasons. At the AGM in October 1982, it was revealed that the club were in £1.6 million of debt, mainly due to escalating wages and building costs, including the construction of the North Stand.Ward, Adam, p.135 At the end of November Ron and Donald Bendall resigned from the board to be replaced by Doug Ellis, who bought Ron Bendall's 42% shareholding.Ward, Adam, p.133 In January 1983, Villa beat Barcelona 3&ndash;1 on aggregate to win the 1982 UEFA Super Cup. Barton remained in charge for two seasons after the European Cup triumph, but was sacked at the end of the 1983&ndash;84 season despite Villa finishing 10th in the First Division and reaching the semi-finals of the League Cup. Shrewsbury Town manager Graham Turner was brought in as his successor. Turner was unable to reverse the decline, and in 1986 Villa narrowly avoided relegation to the Second Division. A lacklustre start to the following season saw Turner sacked halfway through September. Billy McNeill was hired in his place, but was unable to save Villa from relegation. They were relegated to the Second Division just five years after winning the European Cup. McNeill handed in his notice and moved to Celtic when the season ended. Chairman Ellis persuaded Watford manager Graham Taylor to take over the reins and set about rebuilding the team.Ward, Adam, p.149
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="161a2614bea487036334ae5a6a518009" name="Ligue_des_champions_NB" sectnum="4#1">../img/161a2614bea487036334ae5a6a518009.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>