<document id="45009b4a16ef03ba8bb5b15665ef4469-8" name="Minnesota" cat="11">
<text>
The people of Minnesota have a high rate of participation in outdoor activities; the state is ranked first in the percentage of residents who engage in regular exercise.  Minnesotans have the nation's lowest premature death rate, third-lowest infant mortality rate, and the second-longest life expectancies.  According to the U.S. Census Bureau, 91% of Minnesotans have health insurance, more than in any other state.  These and other measures have led two groups to rank Minnesota as the fourth-healthiest state in the nation. 

On October 1, 2007 Minnesota became the seventeenth state to enact a statewide smoking ban in restaurants and bars with the enactment of Freedom to Breathe Act.

Medical care is provided by a comprehensive network of hospitals and clinics, headed by two institutions with international reputations. The University of Minnesota Medical School is a highly rated teaching institution that has made a number of breakthroughs in treatment, and its research activities contribute significantly to the state's growing biotechnology industry. The Mayo Clinic, a world-renowned medical practice, is based in Rochester. Mayo and the University are partners in the Minnesota Partnership for Biotechnology and Medical Genomics, a state-funded program that conducts research into cancer, Alzheimer's disease, heart health, obesity, and other areas.

In March 2008, The American State Litter Scorecard, presented at the American Society for Public Administration national conference, rated Minnesota along with Vermont as topmost Best states for litter/debris removals from public properties (roadways, streams, trails), resulting in an overall healthy environmental quality status. S. Spacek, The American State Litter Scorecard, 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8469a917158e7ed3e9858cc952bace73" name="MayoMedicalCentersign2006-05-14" sectnum="8#1">../img/8469a917158e7ed3e9858cc952bace73.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>