<document id="45a9dfd227f1849d53d440a09113c1a3-6.10" name="To_Kill_a_Mockingbird" cat="17">
<text>
During the years immediately following the novel's publication, Lee enjoyed the attention its popularity garnered her, granting interviews, visiting schools, and attending events honoring the book. In 1961, when ''To Kill a Mockingbird'' was in its 41st week on the bestseller list, it was awarded the Pulitzer Prize, stunning Harper Lee.Shields, p.199–200. It also won the Brotherhood Award of the National Conference of Christians and Jews in the same year, and the Paperback of the Year award from ''Bestsellers'' magazine in 1962.Mancini, p. 15. Starting in 1964, Lee began to turn down interviews, complaining of monotonous questioning. She has declined ever since to talk with reporters about the book. She has also steadfastly refused to provide an introduction, writing in 1995: "Introductions inhibit pleasure, they kill the joy of anticipation, they frustrate curiosity. The only good thing about Introductions is that in some cases they delay the dose to come. ''Mockingbird'' still says what it has to say; it has managed to survive the years without preamble."

In 2001, Lee was inducted into the Alabama Academy of Honor. In the same year, Chicago mayor Richard M. Daley initiated a reading program throughout the city's libraries, and chose his favorite book, ''To Kill a Mockingbird'', as the first title of the One City, One Book program. Lee declared that "there is no greater honor the novel could receive". By 2004, the novel had been chosen by 25 communities for variations of the citywide reading program, more than any other novel.

In 2006, Lee was awarded an honorary doctorate from the University of Notre Dame. During the ceremony, the graduating class and audience gave Lee a standing ovation, and the entire graduating class held up copies of ''To Kill a Mockingbird'' to honor her.

Lee was awarded the Presidential Medal of Freedom on November 5, 2007 by President George W. Bush. In his remarks, Bush stated, "One reason ''To Kill a Mockingbird'' succeeded is the wise and kind heart of the author, which comes through on every page... ''To Kill a Mockingbird'' has influenced the character of our country for the better. It's been a gift to the entire world. As a model of good writing and humane sensibility, this book will be read and studied forever."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="64fbf40e55781b8120fcca588e1242e9" name="Harper_Lee_Medal" sectnum="6.10#1">../img/64fbf40e55781b8120fcca588e1242e9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>