<document id="45af5b1cface02ee25496df285e94ad5-1.2" name="Deconstructivism" cat="1">
<text>
The main channel from deconstructivist philosophy to architectural theory was through the philosopher Jacques Derrida's influence with  Peter Eisenman. Eisenman drew some philosophical bases from the literary movement Deconstruction, and collaborated directly with Derrida on projects including an entry for the Parc de la Villette competition, documented in ''Chora l Works''. Both Derrida and Eisenman, as well as Daniel LibeskindLibeskind, Daniel.  quote ''"This project develops the realm of the in between, the inter-est.... Pointing to that which is absent"''. Retrieved April, 2006 were concerned with the "metaphysics of presence," and this is the main subject of deconstructivist philosophy in architecture theory. The presupposition is that architecture is a language capable of communicating meaning and of receiving treatments by methods of linguistic philosophy.
 The dialectic of presence and absence, or solid and void occurs in much of Eisenman's  projects, both built and unbuilt. Both Derrida and Eisenman believe that the locus, or place of presence, is architecture, and the same dialectic of presence and absence is found in construction and deconstruction.Eisenman and Derrida, ''Chora l Works''

According to Derrida, readings of texts are best carried out when working with classical narrative structures. Any architectural ''de''construction requires the existence of a particular archetypal ''con''struction, a strongly-established conventional expectation to play flexibly against.Derrida, ''Of Grammatology'' The design of Frank Gehry’s own Santa Monica residence, (from 1978), has been cited as a prototypical deconstructivist building. His starting point was a prototypical suburban house embodied with a typical set of intended social meanings. Gehry altered its massing, spatial envelopes, planes and other expectations in a playful subversion, an act of "de"construction"Holloway, Robert (1994). Dissertation Exploring the work of Gordon Matta-Clark. Retrieved April, 2006.

In addition to Derrida's concepts of the metaphysics of presence and deconstruction, his notions of trace and erasure, embodied in his philosophy of writing and arche-writingDerrida, ''Of Grammatology'' (1967) found their way into deconstructivist memorials. Daniel Libeskind envisioned many of his early projects as a form of writing or discourse on writing and often works with a form of concrete poetry. He made architectural sculptures out of books and often coated the models in texts, openly making his architecture refer to writing. The notions of trace and erasure were taken up by Libeskind in essays and in his project for the Jewish Museum Berlin. The museum is conceived as a trace of the erasure of the Holocaust, intended to make its subject legible and poignant. Memorials such as Maya Lin's Vietnam Veterans Memorial and Peter Eisenman's Memorial to the Murdered Jews of Europe also reflect themes of trace and erasure.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d36cb073af9ea568181eb86199fdad1d" name="Turning_Torso_3" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/d36cb073af9ea568181eb86199fdad1d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>