<document id="45c76ba14e8668b3d4ee674f4c6e26d9-2" name="Splendid_Fairywren" cat="3">
<text>
The Splendid Fairywren is a small, long-tailed bird  long.  Exhibiting a high degree of sexual dimorphism, the breeding male is distinctive with a bright blue forehead and ear coverts, a violet throat and deeper rich blue back wings, chest and tail with a black bill, eye band and chest band. The blue breeding plumage of the male is often referred to as nuptial plumage. The non-breeding male is brown with blue in the wings and a bluish tail. The female resembles the non-breeding male but has a chestnut bill and eye-patch. Immature males will moult into breeding plumage the first breeding season after hatching, though this may be incomplete with residual brownish plumage and may take another year or two to perfect.Rowley & Russell, p. 45 Both sexes moult in autumn after breeding, with males assuming an eclipse non-breeding plumage. They will moult again into nuptial plumage in winter or spring.Rowley & Russell, p. 149 Some older males have remained blue all year, moulting directly from one year's nuptial plumage to the next. Breeding males' blue plumage, particularly the ear-coverts, is highly iridescent due to the flattened and twisted surface of the barbules.Rowley & Russell, p. 44 The blue plumage also reflects ultraviolet light strongly, and so may be even more prominent to other fairywrens, whose colour vision extends into this part of the spectrum. The call is described as a gushing reel; this is harsher and louder than other fairywrens and varies from individual to individual. A soft single ''trrt'' serves as a contact call within a foraging group, while the alarm call is a ''tsit''. Cuckoos and other intruders may be greeted with a threat posture and churring threat. Females emit a ''purr'' while brooding. Rowley & Russell, p. 151
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4cd5b260b04851aae0597d492d0d8117" name="Blue_wren_gnangarra" sectnum="2#1">../img/4cd5b260b04851aae0597d492d0d8117.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>