<document id="461a1a38011260404c8514de09399538-4" name="1994_Black_Hawk_shootdown_incident" cat="29">
<text>
On July 17, 1995, U.S. Senator William Roth, chairman of the Permanent Subcommittee on Investigations, authorized a Senate investigation into the incident, primarily in response to complaints from family members of the shootdown victims that it appeared that the U.S. military was not holding anyone seriously accountable for the shootdown.Verhovek, "Air Force Officer Is Acquitted In Downing of Army Aircraft", Diehl, ''Silent Knights'', p. 251, Piper, ''Chain of Events'', p. 224.  Also in response to complaints about the DoD's response to the incident, the U.S. House of Representatives' Armed Services Subcommittee on Military Personnel scheduled a hearing on the incident for August 3, 1995 to examine the accident investigation and the judicial actions that followed.  In addition, on July 24 the DoD ordered the USAF to reexamine the disciplinary and administrative actions for the personnel involved in the shootdown and for the Joint Chiefs of Staff to review the corrective actions taken against those involved and determine whether further action was necessary.  Widnall requested that the new USAF chief of staff, Ronald R. Fogleman begin his own review of accountability for the incident.Washington, "So, Who's to Blame?", Schmitt, "Chief of Air Force Grounds 5 Pilots",  Piper, ''Chain of Events'', p. 224, 231&ndash;232, Diehl, ''Silent Knights'', p. 251.

The House Committee on National Security hearing on August 3 was presided over by Congressman Bob Dornan and lasted one day.  At the hearing, Pilkington and Andrus explained how the USAF accident investigation was conducted and emphasized that Wickson and May violated the OPC rules of engagement by conducting a VID pass of the Black Hawks that was inadequate to determine the helicopter's national origin.  Andrus stated, "Sir, as a pilot, I would have made another pass.  You would never fire until you know what you are shooting at."  Retired USAF Colonel and pilot Jerry Cox expressed concern to the Committee with the F-15 pilots for not taking responsibility for their actions.Piper, ''Chain of Events'', p. 70&ndash;71, 233&ndash;236, Hall, ''Michael, My Son'', pp. 205–206.  Others testifying at the hearing included US Army Major General Stephan Silvasy, Jr. for the Joint Chiefs of Staff,  USAF Major General Nolan Sklute, USAF Judge Advocate General, US Navy Rear Admiral James Lair, Director of Operations for the US Navy in Europe, US Army Captain Michael Nye, an Eagle Flight pilot, retired USAF Colonel Jerry Cox, a former USAF pilot and journalist for the ''Military Times'', and Frank J. Spinner, Wang's attorney (Hall).

On August 10, 1995 Fogleman spoke at a press conference at the Pentagon in which he announced the conclusions reached by his review into the accountability of USAF personnel involved in the shootdown incident.  He stated that his investigation found that not all of the performance evaluations for the individuals involved in the shootdown reflected the fact that they had received administrative action related to the incident.Schmitt, "Chief of Air Force Grounds 5 Pilots",  GAO, "Operation Provide Comfort"  Fogleman stated, "The fact that the conduct of some individuals did not give rise to criminal prosecution or conviction should not end the inquiry into the appropriateness of their actions.  Air Force standards require that people display the extraordinary discipline, judgement, and training that their duties require and that the American people expect."Piper, ''Chain of Events'', p. 239&ndash;240.

Fogleman then announced that he had directed that Wickson, May, Wang, Halcli, and Wilson be disqualified from aviation service duties for at least three years.  Also, Fogleman wrote and placed "letters of evaluation" in the permanent personnel files of Wickson, May, Wang, Halcli, Wilson, Pilkington, and Emery that stated that each had failed "to meet Air Force standards in job knowledge, judgment and leadership".  In addition, a military decoration awarded to O'Brien for his service during OPC was rescinded.  A videotape in which Fogleman described his actions related to the incident and his views on standards and accountability was distributed throughout the USAF and all USAF officers, senior non-commissioned officers, and senior executive service civilians were ordered to view it.Arana-Barradas, "Black hawk incident 'tragic series of errors'", GAO, "Operation Provide Comfort", Schmitt, "Chief of Air Force Grounds 5 Pilots",  Piper, ''Chain of Events'', p. 240, Sklute, "DoD NewsBriefing".  Fogleman further stated that he had found that the military justice system had "worked as it was designed to work".Sklute, "DoD NewsBriefing".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3502aa13199f24f163a1b1807d431bab" name="Ronald_R._Fogleman" sectnum="4#1">../img/3502aa13199f24f163a1b1807d431bab.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>