<document id="461a1a38011260404c8514de09399538-3.2" name="1994_Black_Hawk_shootdown_incident" cat="29">
<text>
Wang's court-martial took place, beginning on June 2, 1995, at Tinker Air Force Base.  Wang was tried on three counts of dereliction of duty.  Most of the personnel involved in the incident, with the exception of May, were called to testify, including the AWACS crew members, Wickson, and Pilkington.  Most of the 40 witnesses testified with a grant of immunity.Arana-Barradas, "Black hawk incident "tragic series of errors", Chu Lin, "Friendly Fire Doesn’t Shoot Down Wang", Peterson, "Court-Martial Begins in 'Friendly Fire' Deaths in Iraq", Diehl, ''Silent Knights'', p. 247, Piper, ''Chain of Events'', p. 205&ndash;213, Verhovek, "Air Force Officer Is Acquitted In Downing of Army Aircraft".

During the trial, evidence was presented that Wang often had trouble staying awake during AWACS missions.  In fact, the problem was considered serious enough that the military had referred Wang to medical authorities to be checked for narcolepsy.  Wang had also previously failed two check rides.Piper, ''Chain of Events'', p. 161, 171.

Pilkington, an F-16 pilot, testified that as commander of OPC he had sent numerous aircrew members, the majority of them F-15 pilots, back to their home bases for violating OPC rules or procedures or for displaying a lack of good judgement.  In response to questions on the F-15 pilot's actions resulting in the shootdown, Pilkington stated, "I don't understand and I will probably never understand Wickson's mindset."  When asked if Wickson and May violated OPC rules of engagement in the incident, Pilkington responded, "Yes."  AWACS crew members added in their testimonies that once Wickson and May visually identified the helicopters as hostile, all responsibility for the shootdown passed to the F-15 pilots.Peterson, "Court-Martial Begins in 'Friendly Fire' Deaths in Iraq", Piper, ''Chain of Events'', p. 214&ndash;215.

Frank Spinner, Wang's civilian attorney, argued that USAF Chief of Staff General Merrill McPeak, a career fighter pilot, had made clear that he did not want Wickson and May punished for their actions in the shootdown.  Cited as evidence for this was a Los Angeles Times report, published also in the European ''Stars and Stripes'' newspaper on June 18, 1994 that stated that McPeak "strongly opposed" court-martial action for Wickson or May.  Pilkington stated that he had heard rumors that McPeak had said something to that effect, but could not confirm if they were true or not.Novak, "Past Fiasco dims General's new Third Star", reported in "Soldiers for Truth" and in Diehl, ''Silent Knights'', p. 252, Piper, ''Chain of Events'', p. 119.

On June 20, 1995 the USAF announced a "nullification" verdict by Wang's 10-member court-martial jury, effectively acquitting Wang of the charges.  Nullification is not a finding of innocence, but instead is a refusal to convict on the stated charges.  After the verdict, Wang stated, "I want to say the fight is nowhere near over for me.  I want a congressional hearing or investigation into why I was the only person charged."Verhovek, "Air Force Officer Is Acquitted In Downing of Army Aircraft", Piper, ''Chain of Events'', p. 220–221.  Major General Nolan Sklute, the USAF's top legal officer, stated, "An incident like this does not necessarily mean that the conduct of all those involved rises to the level of criminal culpability.  I'm satisfied with the handling of the case."Bacon, "DoD Press Briefing", Verhovek, "Air Force Officer Is Acquitted In Downing of Army Aircraft", Piper, ''Chain of Events'', p. 221.  Secretary of the Air Force Sheila Widnall added, "The Black Hawk helicopters were downed as a result of a tragic series of errors and unfortunate events involving numerous people.  The mishap was not the result of any one individual's actions; the conduct of numerous officers and the system itself contributed."Arana-Barradas, "Black hawk incident "tragic series of errors".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e3232b152ac7ed5d365c5b842af66365" name="Merrill_McPeak,_official_military_photo" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/e3232b152ac7ed5d365c5b842af66365.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>