<document id="462570d0fe2da2257700f7db3bc6b25c-4.10" name="Ruffed_lemur" cat="3">
<text>
Contrary to initial reports of monogamy, ruffed lemurs in the wild exhibit seasonal polygamous breeding behavior, with both males and females mating with more than one partner within a single season.  Mating is not restricted to just community members, but also involves members of neighboring communities.  Females mate primarily with males with whom they had affiliative relations prior to mating season, although some matings occurred with roaming males from other communities.

Shortly before mating season begins, females exhibit swelling of the sex skin, which reaches its peak around the middle of their 14.8 day estrous cycle. Male sexual physiology also undergoes its own change, with testicular volume increasing during mating season, peaking around the time of breeding. Aggression also increases during the mating season, both between members of the same sex and by females towards the male attempting to mate with her.  Females have been observed grappling, cuffing, and biting the male during copulation.  Either sex may approach the other when the female is in estrus.  Initially they may ''roar-shriek'' with each other. When a male approaches a female he often lowers his head and squeals, inspecting the female's genitalia by licking or sniffing, scent-marking, and offering a submissive chattering vocalization. When a female approaches a male, she may posture herself for mounting. Mating pairs often copulate many times during the course of a mating bout.

The mating season lasts from May through July, during the cold, rainy season, resulting in birth and peak lactation coinciding with the time that fruit is the most plentiful.  The gestation period of ruffed lemurs is the shortest of the family Lemuridae, averaging 102 days (with a range of 90 to 106 days).  Gestation in the wild last slightly longer than in captivity, averaging 106 days.  Just like the mating season, parturition is also seasonal, synchronized to the end of the cold, dry season and the start of the productive hot, rainy season.

In addition to an abnormally short gestation period, ruffed lemurs share another feature with small, nocturnal lemurs by producing the largest litters of the family Lemuridae.  Litters typical include two or three infants, although up to five have been reported.  Birth weights in captivity average between  and range from .  Ruffed lemur infants are altricial, and are born with their eyes open and a full coat of fur.



Ruffed lemurs are the only known primates to build arboreal nests, used exclusively for birth and for the first week or two of life.  Starting three weeks prior to birth, females begin constructing the nest from twigs, branches, leaves, and vines, locating it within her core area and  above ground.  The nests have only one apparent entry point, and are shallow and dish-shaped. During the first couple weeks, the mother is mostly solitary and does not travel far from the nest, spending as much as 70&ndash;90% of her time with the newborns (in captivity).  In order to find food, she will leave the infants alone in the nest or, after the first couple of weeks, will carry them in her mouth and stash them in concealed locations in the canopy while she forages.  Since this early developmental period corresponds with the end of the cold, dry season, which offers the least amount of fruit, energy is conserved for lactation while travel is limited.  As the hot, rainy season begins, fruit availability rises, lactation demands rise as well, and females increase their travel distance in search of food.

Unlike other diurnal primates, which usually carry their infants with them, ruffed lemur mothers will stash their young by concealing them in the canopy foliage, leaving them to rest and sit quietly for several hours while she forages and performs other activities.  Mothers continue to transport their offspring by mouth, moving them one at a time by grasping the infant's belly crosswise. This form of transports usually stops around 2.5 months of age when the infants become too heavy to carry.

Ruffed lemurs are cooperative breeders, with parental care being shared by all community members.  For example, mothers will stash their offspring with other mothers or leave them to be guarded by other community members, including non-breeding individuals of both genders.  While the mother is away, community members will not only care for and guard them, but also sound alarm calls if danger is detected or if leaving the infant alone.   They will also respond to alarm calls by others. These coordinated vigilance displays further involve communal transmission of the alarm call, with nearby community members repeating the alarm call, potentially summoning the mother back to her offspring.  Infant transport by other members of the community has also been recorded.  Females have been observed nursing infants of their close relatives, while close kin have adopted rejected infants, acting as foster parents.

Male care for infants has been documented in ruffed lemur societies. During early development, adult males may guard the nests of multiple core group females, as well as help care for the infants that were likely fathered by other males.  During the season when females practice infant stashing, males effectively lighten the reproductive burden of up to several mothers by guarding, huddling, grooming, travelling, playing with and feeding the young.

Female ruffed lemurs produce relatively rich milk compared to other lemurs, and consequently, their young develop faster than those of other lemurs.  Infants develop rapidly, attaining approximately 70&ndash;75% adult weight by the age of 4 months.  They begin climbing and clinging at one month of age, advancing to the point of independently following their mother and group members through the canopy at heights of  by 2 to 3 months.  Full adult mobility is attained at 3 to 4 months of age.  Socially, they begin exchanging contact calls with their mother at 3 weeks, and select mother as their play partner 75&ndash;80% of the time during the first 3 months. Participation in greeting displays and utilization of more extensive vocalizations commences around 4 months, while scent marking does not start until 6 months of age.  Infants begin testing solid food starting around 40 days to 2 months with weaning occurring between 4 to 6 months in the wild, although some individuals have continued to nurse until 7 to 8 months.

Infant mortality is often high among ruffed lemurs, but can also be highly variable. In some seasons, as many as 65% are unable to reach 3 months of age, possibly due to falls and related injuries, although in some seasons infant mortality is as low as 0%.  For those that do survive to adulthood, sexual maturity is attained at 18 to 20 months in females and 32 to 48 months in males.  Sexual maturity may take longer to reach in the wild compared to captivity. For females, the inter-birth interval, or time between successive offspring, is typically 1 year, and in captivity, females can remain reproductively active until the age of 23.  The life expectancy for both species of ruffed lemur is estimated at 36 years in captivity, although it is likely to be considerably less in the wild.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="51977b334a535c9e7cd1b3cf1761fe7e" name="Varecia_variegata_mammary_glands" sectnum="4.10#1">../img/51977b334a535c9e7cd1b3cf1761fe7e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>