<document id="462570d0fe2da2257700f7db3bc6b25c-3.4" name="Ruffed_lemur" cat="3">
<text>
Like all lemurs, this genus is found only on the island of Madagascar off the southeastern coast of Africa. Confined to the island's seasonal eastern tropical rainforests, it is uncommon to rare throughout its range, which historically ran from the Masoala Peninsula in the northeast to the Mananara River in the south.  Today, the Black-and-white Ruffed Lemur has a much larger, though very patchy, range than the Red Ruffed Lemur, extending from slightly northwest of Maroantsetra, on Antongil Bay, in the north down the coast to the Mananara River near Vangaindrano in the south.  Additionally, a concentrated population of Black-and-white Ruffed Lemurs, of the subspecies ''Varecia variegata subcincta'', can also be found on the island reserve of Nosy Mangabe in Antongil Bay. It is suspected that this population was introduced to the island in the 1930s.  The Red Ruffed Lemur, on the other hand, has a very restricted range on the Masoala Peninsula.

Historically, the confluence of the Vohimara and Antainambalana Rivers may have been a zone of hybridization between these two species, although no conclusive results have indicated current interbreeding. In general, the Antainambalana River appears to isolate the Red Ruffed Lemurs from the neighboring subspecies of Black-and-white Ruffed Lemur, ''V. v. subcincta''. The subspecies ''V. v. variegata'' can be found further south, and ''V. v. editorum'' is the southernmost subspecies. The ranges of these two southern subspecies overlap and intermediate forms are reported to exist, although this has not been confirmed.

The rainforests in which these animals live are seasonal, with two primary seasons: the hot, wet season (November through April), the cool, dry season (May through October).  The primary habitat for both species, at any season, is in the crowns of trees, where they spend the majority of their time  above ground. With the seasonal availability of resources being similar regardless of location, there is little to no difference in tree usage between species. From September through April, more fruit is available, so females prefer the lianas in the crowns of trees. Both sexes utilize the lower, major branches during the hot, rainy season. The tree crowns are predominantly used from May through August, when young leaves and flowers are in abundance.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ba7c52e0f4e8196a92a4562330071434" name="Maki_vari_roux_Amiens" sectnum="3.4#1">../img/ba7c52e0f4e8196a92a4562330071434.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>