<document id="462570d0fe2da2257700f7db3bc6b25c-4.7" name="Ruffed_lemur" cat="3">
<text>
The social organization of ruffed lemurs is widely variable in both group organization and group composition, although no notable difference can be seen between the two species. Ruffed lemurs are typically described as multi-male/multi-female groups with a fission-fusion social structure, although this can vary by season and locality.

In a study done at Masoala Peninsula on Red ruffed lemurs three levels of organization were identified and defined: communities, core groups, and subgroups. Communities are individuals that affiliated regularly with each other, but rarely with conspecifics outside of the community.  Although the entire multi-male/multi-female community lives within a discrete home range, all individuals are never seen in the same location at the same time. Instead, individuals form dispersed social networks, known as core groups, within the community.  Core groups are individuals that shared the same core area within a community territory throughout the year.  Core groups typically consist of two reproductive females, as well as reproductive males and subadults, ranging in size from 2 individuals to 9.  Females within the groups are cooperative, but male encounters are often agonistic. Subgroups, on the other hand, vary daily in size, composition, and duration, and consist of associated individuals from either the same core group or different core groups, depending on the season.  It is from the consistent, daily changes in these subgroups that occur throughout the year, as well as the seasonal formations of core groups in core areas, that demonstrate the fission-fusion nature of ruffed lemur social structure.



In another study done at Nosy Mangabe on Black-and-white Ruffed Lemurs a fourth level or organization was defined: affiliates. Affiliates were individuals with more persistent social bonds and more frequent interactions, usually within a core group, but sometimes also between core groups within a subgroup. Adult females typically had many affiliates, whereas adult males rarely interacted with conspecifics, living a more solitary existence.

Past studies have reported other social organizations in ruffed lemurs including monogamous pair bonding. This may have been due to the use of short-term, seasonal field studies instead of yearlong studies that take into consideration the effects that changing seasons have on ruffed lemur communities. For instance, during the cold, rainy season, which corresponds with the breeding season, interactions between core groups within a community are significantly reduced. During this time small subgroups form consisting of a mature female, a mature male, and sometimes offspring. This can be misinterpreted as monogamous pair bonding.

Not only group composition, but ranging behavior can also exhibit seasonal variability. During the hot, wet season females range widely, either alone or in groups of up to 6 individuals. In the cool, dry season, smaller core groups stabilize in order to occupy concentrated areas.  Therefore, during seasons when fruit is abundant subgroups are larger while scarcity is met with more solitary behavior.  This suggests that although their feeding ecology is inflexible, being tied to widely distributed, patchy, and sometimes scarce fruit, ruffed lemurs instead adapt the social system in order to survive.

In terms of dominance the ruffed lemur's social structure is not as clear-cut as other lemur societies where female dominance is the norm. Although it is historically reported that "males were subordinate to females," especially with captive and free-ranging ruffed lemur populations demonstrating this, wild populations cannot be definitively labeled as matriarchal due to inter-group variation.

There are also social difference between males and females. Females typically have many affiliates and bond strongly with other females both within and outside their core areas, but do not affiliate with individuals outside the community range, except during mating season.  Males, on the other hand, are more solitary, interact with only a couple of conspecifics, have weak social bonds with other males, and rarely associate with others outside their core group. Furthermore, field studies suggests that only females play a role in communal home range defense. Males may scent-mark and remain relatively silent, but otherwise show little involvement during disputes.

Community range or territory size can vary widely, from  while group size can range from a single pair to 31 individuals.  Population density is also noticeably variable. These wide ranges can be attributed to differing levels of protection and degree of environmental degradation, with better protection and a less degraded environment resulting in higher population density and more moderately sized community ranges.  (The duration and seasonality of the studies involved may also have contributed to low group size estimates and community ranges. A study at the Betampona Reserve, for instance, observed monogamous pairs with two to five infants maintaining ranges of .) Core areas at Ambatonakolahy constituted approximately 10% of the overall community range and showed a close relationship with the location of the largest fruiting trees.

The average daily traveling distance for ruffed lemurs varies between , averaging  per day.  Activity patterns within the community range vary by gender and season. Males generally stay within a core area all year, whereas females only confine themselves to a core area during the cold, wet season, then expand their range throughout the community range during the hot, rainy season.  Females expand their traveling range slightly after giving birth, still staying within the core area, but gradually range further in December when they begin stashing their infants with other community members while they look for food. Females range the furthest later during the hot, rainy season.  Both activity level and reproductive activity can be summarized in the following table.



Although males demonstrate little involvement in territorial disputes between neighboring communities, and ruffed lemur communities lack cohesiveness, females communally defend the community range against females of other communities. These disputes occur mostly during the hot, rainy season, when resources are more abundant and occur near the boundaries of community ranges.  Spacing is maintained by scent marking and vocal communication. Ruffed lemurs are known for their loud, raucous calls that are answered by neighboring communities and subgroups within the same community.

During agonistic encounters between communities, chasing, scent-marking, calling, and occasional physical contact can be seen. Other social behaviors appear to vary between wild and captive ruffed lemurs, as illustrated by the following table.



Some affiliative behaviors are seasonal or gender-specific, such as the male squeal approach and anogenital inspections performed during the mating season.  Another example is the female greeting behavior, where two females will use their anogenital scent glands to mark each other's backs, jump over one another, writhe together, and emit squealing vocalizations. This behavior is not seen during the end of the cool, dry season or around gestation.  The frequency of other affiliative behaviors can be affected by age. All ruffed lemurs over 5 months of age allogroom, and, in captivity, subadults participate in play more frequently than adults.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b3b72c7526957e387f0e54d994855a45" name="Varecia_variegata_sunning_posture1" sectnum="4.7#1">../img/b3b72c7526957e387f0e54d994855a45.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>