<document id="46557d9c44e732a65c24f05183e57ec9-5.4" name="Music_of_Minnesota" cat="20">
<text>
In the mid-1970s, the local music scene in the Minneapolis area began producing popular and innovative acts. Many signed to major record labels, and by the mid 1980s, had achieved national prominence. The first may have been Lipps Inc, who gained some popularity in the late 1970s during the disco era with the global hit "Funkytown" (though the song itself was not in the rock genre).  The Suburbs also formed around the same time. They were the first group to be released under the local Twin/Tone Records label in 1978. Largely only known locally, the group developed a New Wave sound in the 1980s and opened for national acts such as Iggy Pop and The B-52's.






Originally based out of Jay's Longhorn Bar, the Minneapolis hardcore punk scene grew slowly.  The Suicide Commandos were perhaps first, and they were quickly followed by Hüsker Dü and The Replacements, who started as hardcore punk bands and became pivotal in the development of alternative rock. The Replacements eventually achieved some limited mainstream success, while Hüsker Dü became the first hardcore outfit to sign to a major label. Soul Asylum was originally a Minneapolis hardcore band called Loud Fast Rules, which played with bands like Man Sized Action, Rifle Sport and Breaking Circus who mixed funk, thrash metal and other influences.Blush, pg. 224 The Twin Cities rock scene had fully come to national prominence by 1984, when the ''Village Voice'''s renowned critics poll, Pazz and Jop, named three Minneapolis recordings among the top ten of the year: Prince's ''Purple Rain'', The Replacements' ''Let It Be'', and Hüsker Dü's ''Zen Arcade''. ''Purple Rain'' was at #2, ''Let It Be'' was at #4 and ''Zen Arcade'' at #8.''

The late 1980s saw new sounds coming out of the state, when Information Society came to the attention of nightclubs and record labels in New York City. The group had formed in 1982 at Macalester College in St. Paul and made an initial release on the local Wide Angle Records label two years later.  "What's on Your Mind (Pure Energy)" became a huge hit in 1988, and they continued to make music through most of the 1990s. Beginning in 1986, The Jayhawks began recording, achieving critical acclaim with a modern folk-rock sound.

Another group to form around the same time was Babes in Toyland, an early riot grrl band that saw moderate popularity through the 1990s as well. They toured with Lollapalooza in 1993. Many groups of the 1980s and 1990s eventually split up, and a number of other bands formed from the remnants.  Bob Mould left Hüsker Dü to head Sugar and do solo projects.  Trip Shakespeare eventually transformed into Semisonic, who gained popularity in the late 1990s. A former member of Semisonic met up with another from Trip Shakespeare to form The Flops. Other prominent, recent rock acts from Minnesota include slowcore band Low, indie rockers Tapes 'n Tapes, punk rock + rollers THE ViGNETTES, and progressive rock gurus The Plastic Constellations. Popular indie rock act The Hold Steady, while from New York, has numerous songs about the Twin Cities thanks to Edina native Craig Finn, their lead singer. Minneapolis is also home to a steady Hard Rock movement brought on by Classic Rock influenced bands such as SueCity, Cocaine, Castle, Minor League, The Infidels, and others. The most recent scene includes rockers such as the Ready Goes, Future Antiques, and Wanna Be Hasbeens.

2009 brings new bands who are furthering the Rock scene of Minnesota. These three rock bands boast very large play totals of their online music. +2Million plays Dropping Daylight, +300k plays Model 43, and +200k plays Down and Above.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9180dffd397a46890a095efa15851e5c" name="Paul_Westerberg" sectnum="5.4#1">../img/9180dffd397a46890a095efa15851e5c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>