<document id="467b9c0e460a05beed2a77aae07d8209-2" name="Mariah_Carey" cat="20">
<text>
Carey began to take professional acting lessons in 1997, and in the coming year, she was auditioning for film roles. She made her debut as an opera singer in the romantic comedy ''The Bachelor'' (1999), starring Chris O'Donnell and Renée Zellweger. CNN referred derisively to her casting as a talentless diva as "letter-perfect  the "can't act" part informs Carey's entire performance".Tatara, Paul. . CNN.com. November 9, 1999. Retrieved March 17, 2006.

Carey's first starring role was in ''Glitter'' (2001), in which she played a struggling musician in the 1980s who breaks into the music industry after meeting a disc jockey (Max Beesley). Though Roger Ebert said "'s acting ranges from dutiful flirtatiousness to intense sincerity",Ebert, Roger. . ''Chicago Sun-Times''. September 23, 2001. Retrieved from the Wayback Machine on March 17, 2006. most critics panned it: ''Halliwell's Film Guide'' called it a "vapid star vehicle for a pop singer with no visible acting ability",Walker, John. ''Halliwell's Film Guide 2004: 19th Edition'' (2003). pg. 338. UK: HarperCollins Publishers Inc. ISBN 0-06-055408-8. and ''The Village Voice'' observed: "When  tries for an emotion — any emotion — she looks as if she's lost her car keys."Atkinson, Michael. . ''The Village Voice''. September 26 — October 2, 2001. Retrieved March 17, 2006. ''Glitter'' was a box office failure, and Carey earned a Razzie Award for her role. She later said that the film "started out as a concept with substance, but it ended up being geared to 10-year-olds. It lost a lot of grit  I kind of got in over my head."

Carey, Mira Sorvino and Melora Walters co-starred as waitresses at a mobster-operated restaurant in the independent film ''WiseGirls'' (2002), which premiered at the Sundance Film Festival but went straight to cable in the U.S. Critics commended Carey for her efforts — ''The Hollywood Reporter'' predicted, "Those scathing notices for ''Glitter'' will be a forgotten memory for the singer once people warm up to Raychel",Honeycutt, Kirk. . ''The Hollywood Reporter''. January 15, 2002. Retrieved March 17, 2006. and Roger Friedman, referring to her as "a Thelma Ritter for the new millennium", said, "Her line delivery is sharp and she manages to get the right laughs".Friedman, Roger. . Fox News. January 14, 2002. Retrieved March 17, 2006. ''WiseGirls'' producer Anthony Esposito cast Carey in ''The Sweet Science'' (2006), a film about an unknown female boxer recruited by a boxing manager, but it never entered production.Moss, Corey. . MTV.com. February 20, 2002. Retrieved March 17, 2006.

Carey was one of several musicians who appeared in the independently produced Damon Dash films ''Death of a Dynasty'' (2003) and ''State Property 2'' (2005). Her television work has been limited to a January 2002 episode of ''Ally McBeal''. Carey had a cameo appearance in Adam Sandler's 2008 film ''You Don't Mess with the Zohan'', playing herself.Sampson, Mike. . JoBlo.com. June 11, 2007. Retrieved June 12, 2007.

In 2006, Carey joined the cast of the indie film ''Tennessee'' (2008), taking the role of an aspiring singer who flees her controlling husband and joins two brothers on a journey to find their long-lost father.. Retrieved December 26, 2008. The movie received mixed reviews, but most of them raved about Carey's performance and praised it as "understated and very effective." In 2009, she appeared as a social worker in ''Precious'', the movie adaptation of the 1996 novel ''Push'' by Sapphire. The film has garnered mostly positive reviews from critics, as has Carey's performance. ''Variety'' described her acting as "pitch-perfect". . ''New York Daily News''. September 22, 2008. --> So far Precious has won awards at both the Sundance Film Festival and the Toronto Film Festival, receiving top awards there.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bbde15d738083571737e9a51a2dccb01" name="Mariah_Carey_and_Robert_De_Niro_by_David_Shankbone" sectnum="2#1">../img/bbde15d738083571737e9a51a2dccb01.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>