<document id="4684821448f0ae2437312daece9d1cd9-1.2" name="U2" cat="20">
<text>
Island Records signed U2 in March 1980, and in May "11 O'Clock Tick Tock" was the band's first internationally released single.Stokes (1996), page 142 The band's debut album, ''Boy'', followed in October. It was produced by Steve Lillywhite and received generally positive reviews.; ; ;  Although Bono's lyrics were unfocused and seemingly improvised, a common theme was the dreams and frustrations of adolescence. The album included the band's first United Kingdom hit single, "I Will Follow". ''Boy'''s release was followed by U2's first tour of continental Europe and the United States.de la Parra (2003), pages 16,17 Despite being unpolished, these early live performances demonstrated U2's potential, as critics noted that Bono was a "charismatic" and "passionate" showman.

The band's second album, ''October,'' was released in 1981 and contained overtly spiritual themes. During the album's recording sessions, Bono and The Edge left the band due to spiritual conflicts, and U2 ceased to exist for a brief period of time. Bono, The Edge, and Mullen had joined a Christian group in Dublin called the 'Shalom Fellowship', which led them to question the relationship between the Christian faith and the rock and roll lifestyle.Flanagan (1995), pages 46–48 Ultimately, they left the group to continue with the band. Recording was further complicated when a briefcase containing lyrics for several working songs was stolen from backstage during the band's performance at a nightclub in Portland, Oregon. The album received mixed reviews and limited radio play. Low sales outside the UK put pressure on their contract with Island and focused the band on improvement.McCormick (2006), page 120



Resolving the doubts of the ''October'' period, U2 released ''War'' in 1983.Stokes (1996), page 36 A record where the band "turned pacifism itself into a crusade",Reynolds, Simon. ''Rip It Up and Start Again: Postpunk 1978–1984''. Penguin, 2005. p. 367. ISBN 0-14-303672-6 ''War'''s sincerity and "rugged" guitar was intentionally at odds with the "cooler" synthpop of the time.Graham (2004), page 14 The album included the politically-charged "Sunday Bloody Sunday", where Bono had lyrically tried to contrast the events of Bloody Sunday with Easter Sunday.McCormick (2006), page 135. ''Rolling Stone'' magazine wrote that the song showed the band was capable of deep and meaningful songwriting. ''War'' was U2's first album to feature the photography of Anton Corbijn, who remains U2's principal photographer and has had a major influence on their vision and public image.McCormick (2006), page 127 U2's first commercial success, ''War'' debuted at number one in the UK, and its first single, "New Year's Day", was the band's first hit outside Ireland or the UK."New Year's Day" reached number ten on the UK charts, and received extensive radio coverage in the US, almost breaking that country's Top 50. (McCormick (2006), page 139); 

On the subsequent War Tour, the band performed sold-out concerts in mainland Europe and the US. Bono, waving a white flag during performances of "Sunday Bloody Sunday", became the tour's iconic image. U2 recorded the ''Under a Blood Red Sky'' live album on this tour, as well as the ''Live at Red Rocks'' concert film, both of which received extensive play on the radio and MTV, expanding the band's audience and showcasing their live performance. Their generally unfavourable record deal with Island Records was coming to an end, and in 1984 U2 signed a highly lucrative extension. They negotiated the return of their copyrights (so that they owned the rights to their own songs), an increase in their royalty rate, and a general improvement in terms, at the expense of a larger initial payment.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="958b0df9b529d2576515cb6c3d435ad7" name="U2_21081983_01_800b" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/958b0df9b529d2576515cb6c3d435ad7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>