<document id="4684821448f0ae2437312daece9d1cd9-1.7" name="U2" cat="20">
<text>
Following the comparatively poor reception of ''Pop'', U2 declared they were "reapplying for the job ...  the best band in the world", and have since pursued a more conventional rock sound mixed with the influences of their 1990s musical explorations.McCormick (2006), pages 289, 296 ''All That You Can't Leave Behind'' was released in October 2000 and was produced by Brian Eno and Daniel Lanois. For many of those not won over by the band's 1990s music, it was considered a return to grace; Guardian.co.uk (27 October 2000). Retrieved on 31 October 2006 ''Rolling Stone'' called it U2's "third masterpiece" alongside ''The Joshua Tree'' and ''Achtung Baby''. The album debuted at number one in 22 countries therockradio.com. Retrieved 31 October 2006. and its worldwide hit single, "Beautiful Day" earned three Grammy Awards, as did the album's three other singles.


For the Elevation Tour, U2 performed in a scaled-down setting, returning to arenas after nearly a decade of stadium productions. A heart-shaped stage and ramp permitted greater proximity to the audience. Following the September 11 attacks, the new album gained added resonance,; McCormick (2006), pages 308–309 and in October, U2 performed at Madison Square Garden in New York City. Bono and the Edge later said these New York City shows were among their most memorable and emotional performances.; McCormick (2006), page 309 In early 2002, U2 performed during halftime of Super Bowl XXXVI,de la Parra (2003), page 268 which SI.com ranked as the best halftime show in Super Bowl history.


The band's next studio album, ''How to Dismantle an Atomic Bomb'', was released in November 2004. The band were looking for a harder-hitting rock sound than ''All That You Can't Leave Behind''. Thematically, Bono states that "A lot of the songs are paeans to naiveté, a rejection of knowingness." The first single, "Vertigo", was featured on a widely-aired television commercial for the Apple iPod, and a U2 iPod and an iTunes U2 box set was released. The album debuted at number one in the U.S. where first week sales doubled that of ''All That You Can't Leave Behind'' and set a record for the band. rockonthenet.com. Retrieved 31 October 2006. Claiming it as a contender as one of U2's three best albums, Bono said, "There are no weak songs. But as an album, the whole isn't greater than the sum of its parts, and it fucking annoys me." The Vertigo Tour featured a set list that varied more across dates than any U2 tour since the Lovetown Tour, and included songs not played since the early 1980s. Like the Elevation Tour, the Vertigo Tour was a commercial success.Waddell, Ray (13 December 2005).  ''Billboard''. Retrieved 31 October 2006. The album and its singles won Grammy Awards in all eight categories in which U2 were nominated. In 2005, Bruce Springsteen inducted U2 into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame. bbc.co.uk (15 March 2005). Retrieved 17 January 2007;  u2station.com. Retrieved 17 January 2007 A 3-D concert film, ''U2 3D'', filmed at nine concerts during the South America leg of the Vertigo Tour was released on 23 January 2008.

In August 2006, the band incorporated its publishing business in The Netherlands following the capping of Irish artists' tax exemption at €250,000. Dave Evans stated that businesses often seek to minimize their tax burdens. The move was criticised in the Irish parliament. The band said the criticism was unfair, stating that approximately 95% of their business took place outside of Ireland, that they were taxed globally because of this, and that they were all "personal investors and employers in the country".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1f7504a8f243fa5a25b4b12f0f2fb43e" name="U2_Super_Bowl" sectnum="1.7#1">../img/1f7504a8f243fa5a25b4b12f0f2fb43e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>