<document id="4684821448f0ae2437312daece9d1cd9-1.6" name="U2" cat="20">
<text>
In 1995, U2 released an experimental album called ''Original Soundtracks 1''. Brian Eno, producer of three previous U2 albums, contributed as a full partner, including writing and performing. For this reason, and due to the record's highly experimental nature, the band chose to release it under the moniker "Passengers" to distinguish it from U2's conventional albums. Mullen said of the album, "There's a thin line between interesting music and self-indulgence. We crossed it on the Passengers record." http://www.threechordsandthetruth.net/u2quotes/larry.htm It was commercially unnoticed by U2 standards and it received generally poor reviews. However, the single "Miss Sarajevo" featuring Luciano Pavarotti, which Bono cites as one of his favourite U2 songs,McCormick (2006), page 261–62 was a hit.



On 1997's ''Pop'', U2 continued experimenting; tape loops, programming, rhythm sequencing, and sampling provided much of the album with heavy, funky dance rhythms.Graham (2004), pages 62–63 Released in March, the album debuted at number one in 35 countries, and drew mainly positive reviews.;  ''Rolling Stone'', for example, stated that U2 had "defied the odds and made some of the greatest music of their lives". Others felt that the album was a major disappointment and sales were poor compared to previous U2 releases.; ;  The band was hurried into completing the album in time for the impending pre-booked tour, and Bono admitted that the album "didn't communicate the way it was intended to".

The subsequent tour, PopMart, commenced in April 1997. Like Zoo TV, it poked fun at pop culture and was intended to send a sarcastic message to those accusing U2 of commercialism. The stage included a  tall golden yellow arch (reminiscent of the McDonald's logo), a  long video screen, and a  tall mirrorball lemon. U2's "big shtick" failed, however, to satisfy many who were seemingly confused by the band's new kitsch image and elaborate sets.; Anderson, Kyle (4 October 2006).  spin.com. Retrieved on 29 December 2006;  ''Rolling Stone'', 18 December 1997. Retrieved 29 December 2006. The late delivery of ''Pop'' meant rehearsal time was severely reduced, and performances in early shows suffered.de la Parra (2003), pages 193–202 A highlight of the tour was a concert in Sarajevo where U2 were the first major group to perform following the Bosnian War. rockonthenet.com. Retrieved 31 October 2006 Mullen described the concert as "an experience I will never forget for the rest of my life, and if I had to spend 20 years in the band just to play that show, and have done that, I think it would have been worthwhile." msn.com. Retrieved 15 January 2007; Furthermore, Bono described the show as "one of the toughest and one of the sweetest nights of my life". ( ''The Independent'' (26 September 1997). Retrieved 15 January 2007) One month following the conclusion of the PopMart Tour, U2 appeared on the 200th episode of ''The Simpsons'', "Trash of the Titans", in which Homer Simpson disrupted the band on stage during a PopMart concert.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0f3546ca3780bba34c8996e7cfbdfaca" name="U2-LiveInReggioEmilia-19970920-BonoEdge" sectnum="1.6#1">../img/0f3546ca3780bba34c8996e7cfbdfaca.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>