<document id="4684821448f0ae2437312daece9d1cd9-1.3" name="U2" cat="20">
<text>
''The Unforgettable Fire'' was released in 1984. Ambient and abstract, it was at the time the band's most marked change in direction.Parra, Pimm Jal de la ''U2 Live: A Concert Documentary'', pages 52–55, 1996, Harper Collins Publishers, ISBN 0-7322-6036-1 The band feared that following the overt rock of the ''War'' album and tour, they were in danger of becoming another "shrill", "sloganeering arena-rock band". Thus, experimentation was soughtGraham (2004), page 21 as Adam Clayton recalls, "We were looking for something that was a bit more serious, more arty." The Edge admired the ambient and "weird works" of Brian Eno, who, along with his engineer Daniel Lanois, eventually agreed to produce the record.Island Records boss Chris Blackwell initially tried to discourage them from their choice of producers, believing that just when the band were about to achieve the highest levels of success, Eno would "bury them under a layer of avant-garde nonsense". (McCormick (2006), page 151)


''The Unforgettable Fire'' has a rich and orchestrated sound. Under Lanois' direction, Mullen's drumming became looser, funkier, and more subtle and Clayton's bass became more subliminal; the rhythm section no longer intruded, but flowed in support of the songs. Complementing the sonic atmospherics, the album's lyrics are open to many interpretations, providing what the band called a "very visual feel". Bono's recent immersion in fiction, philosophy, and poetry made him realise that his songwriting responsibility — about which he had always been reluctant — was a poetic one. Due to a tight recording schedule, however, Bono felt songs like "Bad" and "Pride (In the Name of Love)" were incomplete "sketches".McCormick (2006), page 151 "Pride (In the Name of Love)", about Martin Luther King, Jr., was the album's first single and became the band's biggest hit to that point, including being their first to enter the U.S. top 40.Graham, (2004), pages 23–24

Much of The Unforgettable Fire Tour moved into indoor arenas as U2 began to win their long battle to build their audience.de la Parra (1994), pages 62–63 The complex textures of the new studio-recorded tracks, such as "The Unforgettable Fire" and "Bad", were problematic to translate to live performance. One solution was programmed sequencers, which the band had previously been reluctant to use, but are now used in the majority of the band's performances. Songs on the album had been criticised as being "unfinished", "fuzzy", and "unfocused", but were better received by critics when played on stage.''Rolling Stone'', which was critical of the album version of "Bad", described its live performance as a 'show stopper'. 


U2 participated in the Live Aid concert for Ethiopian famine relief at Wembley Stadium in July 1985.Kaufman, Gil (29 Jun 2005).  MTV.com. Retrieved 31 October 2006. U2's performance was a pivotal point in the band's career.McCormick (2006), page 164 During the song "Bad", Bono leapt down off the stage to embrace and dance with a fan, showing a television audience of millions the personal connection that Bono could make with audiences.de la Parra (2003), pages 72–73 In 1985, ''Rolling Stone'' magazine called U2 the "Band of the 80s", saying that "for a growing number of rock-and-roll fans, U2 have become the band that matters most, maybe even the only band that matters".Peake, Steve.  about.com. Retrieved 31 January 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f32953f2e473b521bf34b767dec83512" name="Live_Aid_-_U2" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/f32953f2e473b521bf34b767dec83512.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>