<document id="4684821448f0ae2437312daece9d1cd9-1.5" name="U2" cat="20">
<text>
Stung by the criticism of ''Rattle and Hum'', the band made a calculated change in musical and thematic direction for their seventh studio album, ''Achtung Baby''; the change was their most dramatic since ''The Unforgettable Fire''.Flanagan (1995), pages 4–6; Graham (2004), page 43  The band began work on ''Achtung Baby'' in East Berlin in October 1990 with producers Daniel Lanois and Brian Eno, seeking inspiration and renewal on the eve of German reunification.Flanagan (1995), page 7 The sessions instead proved to be difficult, as conflict arose within the band over their musical direction and the quality of their material. While Clayton and Mullen preferred a sound similar to U2's previous work, Bono and Edge were inspired by alternative rock and European dance music and advocated a change. Weeks of slow progress, arguments, and tension subsided when the band rallied around a chord progression The Edge had written to improvise the song "One".Flanagan (1995), pages 6–11 The band completed the album in Dublin.



In November 1991, U2 released ''Achtung Baby''. Sonically, the album incorporated alternative rock, dance, and industrial influences of the time and the band referred to the album as the sound of "four men chopping down the Joshua Tree". Thematically, it was a more inward-looking and personal record; it was darker, yet at times more flippant, than the band's previous work. Commercially and critically, it has been one of the band's most successful albums and was a crucial part of the band's early 1990s reinvention.Graham (2004), page 44 Like ''The Joshua Tree'', it is cited by ''Rolling Stone'' as one of rock's greatest.



The Zoo TV Tour of 1992–1993 was a multimedia event, and showcased an extravagant but intentionally bewildering array of hundreds of video screens, upside-down flying Trabant cars, mock transmission towers, satellite TV links, subliminal messages, and Bono's over-the-top stage characters such as "The Fly", "Mirror-Ball Man", and "(Mister) MacPhisto". The extravagant shows were intentionally in contrast to the austere staging of previous U2 tours, and mocked the excesses of rock and roll by appearing to embrace these very excesses. The shows were, in part, U2's way to represent the pervasive nature of cable television and its blurring of news, entertainment, and home shopping.de la Parra (1994), pages 139–41; Flanagan (1995), pages 12,13, 58–61; Stokes (1996), pages 110–11 Prank phone calls were made to President Bush, the United Nations, and others. Live satellite uplinks to war-torn Sarajevo caused controversy.de la Parra (2003), pages 153, 166

Quickly recorded and released during a break in the Zoo TV tour in mid-1993, the ''Zooropa'' album continued many of the themes from ''Achtung Baby'' and the Zoo TV tour. Initially intended as an EP, the band expanded ''Zooropa'' into a full-length LP album. It was an even greater departure from the style of their earlier recordings, incorporating techno influences and other electronic effects.Graham (2004), page 51 Johnny Cash sang the vocal on the "The Wanderer". Most of the songs were played at least once during the 1993 leg of the tour, which extended through Europe, Australia, New Zealand and Japan; half the album's tracks became fixtures in the set.de la Parra (2003), pages 166–72
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8c852519c4de0573291e4db773721af5" name="Zoo_stage" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/8c852519c4de0573291e4db773721af5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>