<document id="469979eb5d434b2684b0c932f4454cae-1" name="Craters_of_the_Moon_National_Monument_and_Preserve" cat="11">
<text>
The Craters of the Moon Lava Field spreads across  and is the largest mostly Holocene-aged basaltic lava field in the lower 48 U.S. states. The Monument and Preserve contain more than 25 volcanic cones including outstanding examples of spatter cones. The 60 distinct lava flows that form the Craters of the Moon Lava Field range in age from 15,000 to just 2,000 years. The Kings Bowl and Wapi lava fields, both about 2,200 years old, are part of the National Preserve. 

Craters of the Moon Lava Field reaches southeastward from the Pioneer Mountains. This lava field is the largest of several large beds of lava that erupted from the  south-east to north-west trending Great Rift volcanic zone—a line of weakness in the Earth's crust created by Basin and Range rifting. Together with fields from other fissures they make up the Lava Beds of Idaho, which in turn are located within the much larger Snake River Plain volcanic province. The Great Rift almost extends across the entire Snake River Plain. 

The rugged landscape remains remote and undeveloped with only one paved road across the northern end. Craters of the Moon is located in south-central Idaho midway between Boise and Yellowstone National Park, and its elevation at the visitor center is  above sea level.NPS website Combined U.S. Highway 20-26-93 cuts through the northwestern part of the monument and provides access to it.

Total average precipitation in the Craters of the Moon area is between  per year.Lower elevation areas near the Snake River average only 10–11 inches of precipitation annually. Most of this is lost in cracks in the basalt, only to emerge later in springs and seeps in the walls of the Snake River Canyon. Older lava fields on the plain have been invaded by drought-resistant plants such as sagebrush, while younger fields, such as Craters of the Moon, only have a seasonal and very sparse cover of vegetation. In fact, from a distance this cover disappears almost entirely, giving an impression of utter black desolation. Repeated lava flows over the last 15,000 years have raised the land surface enough to expose it to the prevailing southwesterly winds, which help to keep the area dry. Together these conditions make life on the lava field difficult.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="db2fe1affbf31169c64e08825e6bdfac" name="Craters_of_the_Moon_within_Idaho" sectnum="1#1">../img/db2fe1affbf31169c64e08825e6bdfac.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>