<document id="469979eb5d434b2684b0c932f4454cae-2.4" name="Craters_of_the_Moon_National_Monument_and_Preserve" cat="11">
<text>
Robert Limbert, a sometime taxidermist, tanner, and furrier from Boise, explored the area, which he described as "practically unknown and unexplored ..." in the 1920s after hearing stories from fur trappers about "strange things they had seen while ranging the region". 



Limbert wrote: "I had made two trips into the northern end, covering practically the same region as that traversed by a Geological Survey party in 1901. My first was a hiking and camping trip with Ad Santel (the wrestler), Dr. Dresser, and Albert Jones; the second was with Wes Watson and Era Martin (ranchers living about four miles  from the northern edge). The peculiar features seen on those trips led me to take a third across the region in the hope that even more interesting phenomena might be encountered."http://kencole.bravehost.com/CRATERS1.HTML
Limbert set out on his third and most ambitious foray to the area in May 1920,http://www.nps.gov/archive/crmo/hcs4b.htm this time with Walter L. Colehttp://kencole.bravehost.com/CRATERS1.HTML and an Airedale Terrier to accompany him. Starting from Minidoka, Idaho, they explored what is now the monument area from south to north passing Two Point Butte, Echo Crater, Big Craters, North Crater Flow, and out of the lava field through the Yellowstone Park and Lincoln Highway (now known as the Old Arco-Carey Road). Taking the dog along was a mistake, Limbert wrote, "for after three days' travel his feet were worn and bleeding".  

A series of newspaper and magazine articles authored by Limbert were later published about this and previous treks, which increased public awareness of the area. The most famous of these was an article that appeared in a 1924 issue of ''National Geographic'' where he called the area "Craters of the Moon," helping to solidify the use of that name. In the article he had this to say about the cobalt blue of the Blue Dragon Flows: 
:"It is the play of light at sunset across this lava that charms the spectator. It becomes a twisted, wavy sea. In the moonlight its glazed surface has a silvery sheen. With changing conditions of light and air, it varies also, even while one stands and watches. It is a place of color and silence ..."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="08aac08eff9ede5b38a655a7c21f72ed" name="Craters_of_the_Moon_National_Monument-10" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/08aac08eff9ede5b38a655a7c21f72ed.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>