<document id="46a806af69758583647ce238463c9852-2.3.4" name="Pericles" cat="14">
<text>
The Samian War was one of the last significant military events before the Peloponnesian War. After Thucydides' ostracism, Pericles was re-elected yearly to the generalship, the only office he ever officially occupied, although his influence was so great as to make him the ''de facto'' ruler of the state. In 440 BC Samos was at war with Miletus over control of Priene, an ancient city of Ionia on the foot-hills of Mycale. Worsted in the war, the Milesians came to Athens to plead their case against the Samians.Thucydides, 1.115 When the Athenians ordered the two sides to stop fighting and submit the case to arbitration at Athens, the Samians refused.Plutarch, ''Pericles'', XXV In response, Pericles passed a decree dispatching an expedition to Samos, "alleging against its people that, although they were ordered to break off their war against the Milesians, they were not complying". In a naval battle the Athenians led by Pericles and the other nine generals defeated the forces of Samos and imposed on the island an administration pleasing to them. When the Samians revolted against Athenian rule, Pericles compelled the rebels to capitulate after a tough siege of eight months, which resulted in substantial discontent among the Athenian sailors.Plutarch, ''Pericles'', XXVIII Pericles then quelled a revolt in Byzantium and, when he returned to Athens, gave a funeral oration to honor the soldiers who died in the expedition.R. Sealey, ''A History of the Greek City States'', 310

Between 438-436 BC Pericles led Athens' fleet in Pontus and established friendly relations with the Greek cities of the region.C.J. Tuplin, ''Pontus and the Outside World'', 28 Pericles focused also on internal projects, such as the fortification of Athens (the building of the "middle wall" about 440 BC), and on the creation of new cleruchies, such as Andros, Naxos and Thurii (444 BC) as well as Amphipolis (437&ndash;436 BC).Plutarch, ''Pericles'', XI and Plato, ''Gorgias'',
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="90bd6595b88023b99c980c25f4d5a904" name="Pericles6" sectnum="2.3.4#1">../img/90bd6595b88023b99c980c25f4d5a904.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>