<document id="46a806af69758583647ce238463c9852-2.2" name="Pericles" cat="14">
<text>
Around 461 BC the leadership of the democratic party decided it was time to take aim at the Areopagus, a traditional council controlled by the Athenian aristocracy, which had once been the most powerful body in the state.Fornara-Samons, ''Athens from Cleisthenes to Pericles'',  The leader of the party and mentor of Pericles, Ephialtes, proposed a sharp reduction of the Areopagus' powers. The Ecclesia (the Athenian Assembly) adopted Ephialtes' proposal without strong opposition.Plutarch, ''Pericles'', IX This reform signalled the commencement of a new era of "radical democracy". The democratic party gradually became dominant in Athenian politics and Pericles seemed willing to follow a populist policy in order to cajole the public. According to Aristotle, Pericles' stance can be explained by the fact that his principal political opponent, Cimon, was rich and generous, and was able to secure public favor by lavishly bestowing his sizable personal fortune.Aristotle, ''Constitution of Athens'',  The historian Loren J. Samons II argues, however, that Pericles had enough resources to make a political mark by private means, had he so chosen. L.J. Samons, ''What's Wrong with Democracy?'', 80

In 461 BC, Pericles achieved the political elimination of this formidable opponent using the weapon of ostracism. The ostensible accusation was that Cimon betrayed his city by acting as a friend of Sparta.Plutarch, ''Cimon'',  

Even after Cimon's ostracism, Pericles continued to espouse and promote a populist social policy. He first proposed a decree that permitted the poor to watch theatrical plays without paying, with the state covering the cost of their admission. With other decrees he lowered the property requirement for the archonship in 458–457 BC and bestowed generous wages on all citizens who served as jurymen in the Heliaia (the supreme court of Athens) some time just after 454 BC.Fornara-Samons, ''Athens from Cleisthenes to Pericles'',  His most controversial measure, however, was a law of 451 BC limiting Athenian citizenship to those of Athenian parentage on both sides. R. Martin,  



Such measures impelled Pericles' critics to regard him as responsible for the gradual degeneration of the Athenian democracy. Constantine Paparrigopoulos, a major modern Greek historian, argues that Pericles sought for the expansion and stabilization of all democratic institutions.K. Paparrigopoulos, ''History of the Greek Nation'', Ab, 145 Hence, he enacted legislation granting the lower classes access to the political system and the public offices, from which they had previously been barred on account of limited means or humble birth.Aristotle, ''Constitution of Athens'',  and ''Politics'',  According to Samons, Pericles believed that it was necessary to raise the demos, in which he saw an untapped source of Athenian power and the crucial element of Athenian military dominance. L.J. Samons, ''What's Wrong with Democracy?'', 65 (The fleet, backbone of Athenian power since the days of Themistocles, was manned almost entirely by members of the lower classes.Fine, ''The Ancient Greeks'', 377–8)

Cimon, on the other hand, apparently believed that no further free space for democratic evolution existed. He was certain that democracy had reached its peak and Pericles' reforms were leading to the stalemate of populism. According to Paparrigopoulos, history vindicated Cimon, because Athens, after Pericles' death, sank into the abyss of political turmoil and demagogy. Paparrigopoulos maintains that an unprecedented regression descended upon the city, whose glory perished as a result of Pericles' populist policies. According to another historian, Justin Daniel King, radical democracy benefited people individually, but harmed the state.J.D. King, , 24–25 On the other hand, Donald Kagan asserts that the democratic measures Pericles put into effect provided the basis for an unassailable political strength.D. Kagan, ''The Outbreak of the Peloponnesian War'', 79 After all, Cimon finally accepted the new democracy and did not oppose the citizenship law, after he returned from exile in 451 BC.D. Kagan, ''The Outbreak of the Peloponnesian War'', 135–136
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="23e02f0f871cee198354ea1f98a3adcd" name="Cholargus" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/23e02f0f871cee198354ea1f98a3adcd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>