<document id="46da6fca4289383263ffaad66648281c-7.13" name="Youngstown,_Ohio" cat="11">
<text>
Youngstown's most popular resource is Mill Creek Park, a five-mile (8 km)-long stretch of landscaped woodland reminiscent of Rock Creek Park in Washington, D.C. Mill Creek Park is the oldest park district in Ohio, established as a township park in 1891. The park's highlights include the restored 19th century Lanterman's Mill, the rock formations of Bear's Den, scores of nature trails, the Fellows Riverside Gardens and Nature Center, the "Cinderella" iron link bridge, and two 18 hole Donald Ross golf courses.
 Mill Creek Park encompasses approximately ,  of drives and  of foot trails. Its attractions include gardens, streams, lakes, woodlands, meadows, and wildlife.

The Nature Center's popular lookout point offers visitors contrasting views of the area. From the south side, the canopied woodlands overlooking Lake Glacier are visible; from the north side, visitors are presented with a view of downtown Youngstown. The park features two 18-hole golf courses. The North Course is situated on rolling terrain, while the South Course features narrow, tree-lined fairways. Other features include playgrounds, athletic fields, and picnic areas. 

In 2005, Mill Creek Park was placed on the National Register of Historic Places.
 A plaque commemorating this event is located near a memorial statue of Volney Rogers, the Youngstown attorney who set aside land for the creation of Mill Creek Park. 
 
A smaller recreational area called Wick Park is located on the historic north side.  Wick Park's periphery is lined with early 20th-century mansions built by the city's industrialists, business leaders, and professionals during Youngstown's "boom" years.  Stambaugh Auditorium, a popular venue for concerts and other public events, is located near the park's southwestern edge.  Several cemeteries (notably historic Oak Hill Cemetery) and small recreational spaces are scattered throughout the city.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c4ba9547c17a3b890996e4239eaa33b0" name="cinderellabridge" sectnum="7.13#1">../img/c4ba9547c17a3b890996e4239eaa33b0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>