<document id="46da6fca4289383263ffaad66648281c-7.12" name="Youngstown,_Ohio" cat="11">
<text>
Youngstown's most widely known museum is the Butler Institute of American Art, which is located on the northeastern edge of the Youngstown State University campus. This institution was established by industrialist Joseph G. Butler, Jr., in 1919 as the first museum in the country dedicated to American art. Across the street from the Butler stands the McDonough Museum of Art, which is owned and operated by YSU. The McDonough, since its establishment in 1991, has showcased contemporary art and hosted programs for students on campus and throughout the surrounding area. The Clarence R. Smith Mineral Museum, also located on the YSU campus, is operated by the university's geology department and housed in a campus building.

To the immediate north of YSU is the Arms Family Museum of Local History. The museum, housed in a 1905 Arts & Crafts style mansion on the main artery of Wick Avenue, is managed by the Mahoning Valley Historical Society. Once the estate of a local industrialist, the museum maintains period rooms that showcase the original contents of the household, including furnishings, art objects, and personal artifacts. The museum mounts rotating exhibits on topics related to local history. Recently, the museum opened the "Anne Kilcawley Christman Hands-on History Room". The MVHS Archival Library operates in the estate's former carriage house, located near the back of the site.

Located just south of the YSU campus is the Youngstown Historical Center of Industry and Labor, which sits on a grade overlooking the downtown area. This museum, owned and operated by the Ohio Historical Society, focuses on the Mahoning Valley's history of steel production. Other museums include the Children's Museum of the Valley, an interactive educational center located in the downtown area, and the Davis Education and Recreation Center, a small museum that showcases the history of Youngstown's Mill Creek Park.
On the city's north side the Tod Engine Foundation is constructing the Tod Engine Heritage Park, featuring a collection of steel industry equipment and artifacts.  The main exhibit is a 1914 William Tod Co. rolling mill steam engine that was built in Youngstown and used at the Youngstown Sheet and Tube Brier Hill Works.  The Tod Engine is one of three remaining rolling mill engines in the United States and is a Mechanical and Materials Engineering Landmark.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ca1f42bb4f6f2d2842aa5dac003577f6" name="Youngstown_021" sectnum="7.12#1">../img/ca1f42bb4f6f2d2842aa5dac003577f6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>