<document id="474a2658885fa43f691eeb946e1f8805-1.2" name="New_South_Greenland" cat="14">
<text>
At 2 pm next day, 15 March, as ''Wasp'' cruised north-east in the sea that would later bear Weddell's name, Morrell records: "land was seen from the masthead, bearing west, distance 3 leagues" (about nine miles, 14 km). (pp. 69&ndash;70) His account continues: "At half past 4 pm we were close on with the body of land to which Captain Johnson had given the name of New South Greenland".(Map, p. 52) Robert Johnson, a former captain of the ''Wasp'', had made an exploratory voyage along the western coast of the Antarctic peninsula in 1821, calling it "New South Greenland".Johnson's name for this land was never adopted; in 1831 it was named Graham Land H R Mill, pp. 161&ndash;62. Morrell's casual reference to Johnson indicates that he assumed the land he was now seeing was the east coast of the peninsula, the geographical character and dimensions of which were not then known (his actual position was about 14° east of the peninsula).H R Mill, p. 109  Morrell describes seal hunting activities continuing along this putative coast during the remainder of the day. On the following morning  sealing resumed as the ship moved slowly southward, and continued until Morrell called a halt "because of shortage of water and season far advanced". Mountains of snow, he observed, could be discerned about  further south.

Morrell turned north from a position he calculated as 67°52'S, 48°11W. Three days later, on 19 March, the ship passed what he took to be the northern cape of the land, at 62°41'S, 47°21'W. "This land abounds with oceanic birds of every description", wrote Morrell.  He also records seeing 3,000 sea elephants. At 10 o'clock ''Wasp'' "bade farewell to the cheerless shores of New South Greenland"; there is no further mention of it in the long voyage account. ''Wasp'' sailed for Tierra del Fuego, then through the Magellan Strait into the Pacific Ocean, reaching  Valparaiso, Chile, on 26 July 1823.

From the first navigations of the Southern Ocean in the 16th century, lands which subsequently proved to be nonexistent had  from time to time been reported in these waters.See list of reported lands and islands in:  Polar historian Robert Headland of the Scott Polar Research Institute has suggested various reasons for these false sightings, ranging from "too much rum" to deliberate hoaxes designed to lure rival ships away from good sealing grounds. Some  may have been of large ice masses that were carrying rocks and other glacial debris&mdash;dirty ice can appear convincingly similar to land. It is also possible that some of these lands existed, but later became submerged after volcanic eruptions. Other sightings may have been of actual land, wrongly located through observational errors due to chronometer failure, adverse weather or simple incompetence.(p. 152, insert by Robert Headland: "Non-existent Antarctic Islands")
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="67a20a7eadc68fb9617497a50fddcd91" name="Morrell" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/67a20a7eadc68fb9617497a50fddcd91.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>