<document id="474a2658885fa43f691eeb946e1f8805-2" name="New_South_Greenland" cat="14">
<text>
Doubt was cast over the existence of New South Greenland when, in 1838, the French explorer Jules Dumont d'Urville sailed over the position of Morrell's "north cape", but saw no indication of land.Gould, pp. 266&ndash;67 This evidence, and the general nature of Morrell's account&mdash;its obvious errors, and his reputation as a braggart "as great  as any hero of autobiographical romance" in the words of British geographer Hugh Robert Mill, led many geographers thereafter to ignore his claims.H R Mill, pp. 104&ndash;05 This scepticism remained even after Sir James Clark Ross reported an appearance of land in 1843, not far from Morrell's alleged observation: Ross's sighting was occasionally proffered as supportive of Morrell's claim. There was no further penetration of the Weddell Sea until 1903, when William Speirs Bruce took ''Scotia'' to 74°1'S, but in a sector of the sea which did not bring him close to Morrell's or Ross's sightings.Speak, p. 92. Bruce reached his Farthest South at longitude 22°W.  Bruce was, however, generally well-disposed towards Morrell, writing that his claims should not be rejected until absolutely disproved.Gould, p. 271

The first determined search for New South Greenland came during the Second German Antarctic Expedition, 1911&ndash;13, under Wilhelm Filchner. The expedition's ship, ''Deutschland'', had become trapped in heavy sea ice while attempting to establish a shore base at Vahsel Bay. Her subsequent north-westerly drift had, by mid-June 1912, brought her to a position  east of Morrell's recorded sighting. Filchner left the ship on 23 June and, with two companions and sufficient provisions for three weeks, sledged westward across the sea ice in search of Morrell's land. Daylight was limited to two or three hours a day, and temperatures fell to -31 °F (-35 °C),  making travel difficult. In these conditions the group covered , taking frequent sightings. They found no signs of land; a lead weight dropped through the ice reached a depth of  before the line snapped, a depth which confirmed there was no land in the vicinity. Filchner concluded that what Morrell had seen had been a mirage.

On  17 August 1915 Sir Ernest Shackleton's ship ''Endurance'', trapped in the ice like ''Deutschland'' three years earlier, drifted to a point 10 miles west of Morrell's charted position. Here, a depth sounding recorded 1,676 fathoms (10,000 feet, 3,000 m), leading Shackleton to write: "I decided that Morrell Land must be added to the long list of Antarctic islands and continental coasts that have resolved themselves into icebergs". On 25 August a further sounding of 1,900 fathoms (11,400 feet, 3,500 m) gave Shackleton additional evidence of the non-existence of New South Greenland.Shackleton, pp. 60&ndash;61

Although Filchner's and Shackleton's investigations and observations were accepted as conclusive proof that New South Greenland was a myth, there remained the question of Sir James Ross's reported appearance of land in a position around 65°S, 47°W.Gould, p. 272 Ross's reputation was sufficient for this possibility to be taken seriously, and for his alleged sighting to be recorded on maps and Admiralty charts. p. 91 In 1922 Frank Wild, leading the Shackleton-Rowett Expedition aboard ''Quest'' after Shackleton's death early in the expedition, investigated the location of Ross's  sighting. Nothing was seen; prevented by ice conditions from reaching the exact spot, Wild took a sounding at 64°11'S, 46°4'W, which  revealed 2,331 fathoms of water (14,000 feet, 4,300 m). This showed that no land was near. p. 144
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="639af4a370fc4db11fa0df48b11b299e" name="1894_map_of_Antactica" sectnum="2#1">../img/639af4a370fc4db11fa0df48b11b299e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>