<document id="479ed3fd160aa5cc630a5ae4bab23ab3-4.4" name="Banksia_prionotes" cat="3">
<text>
Flowering begins in February and is usually finished by the end of June. The species has an unusually low rate of flowering: even at the peak of its flowering season, it averages less than seven inflorescences per plant flowering at any one time. Individual flowers open sequentially from bottom to top within each inflorescence, the rate varying with the time of day: more flowers open during the day than at night, with a peak rate of around two to three florets per hour during the first few hours of daylight, when honeyeater foraging is also at its peak.

The flowers are fed at by a range of nectarivorous birds: mainly honeyeaters, including the New Holland Honeyeater (''Phylidonyris novaehollandiae''), White-cheeked Honeyeater (''P. nigra''), Brown Honeyeater (''Lichmera indistincta''), Singing Honeyeater (''Lichenostomus virescens''), Tawny-crowned Honeyeater (''Gliciphila melanops'') and Red Wattlebird (''Anthochaera carunculata''). Lorikeets have also been observed feeding at the flowers, as have insects, including ants, bees, and aphids. Of these, evidence suggests that only birds are effective pollinators. Insects apparently play no role in pollination, since inflorescences do not form follicles when birds are excluded in pollinator exclusion experiments; and pollination by mammals has never been recorded in this species.

Honeyeaters prefer to forage at individual flowers which have only just opened, as these offer the most nectar. As they probe for nectar, honeyeaters end up with large quantities of pollen on their beaks, foreheads and throats, some of which they subsequently transfer to other flowers. This transfer is quite efficient: flowers typically lose nearly all their pollen within four hours of opening, and pollen is deposited on the majority of stigmata. Around 15% of these stigmata end up with pollen lodged in the stigmatic groove, a prerequisite to fertilisation.

The structure of the ''Banksia'' flower, with the style end functioning as a pollen presenter, suggests that autogamous self-fertilisation must be common. In many ''Banksia'' species, the risk of this occurring is reduced by protandry: a delay in a flower's receptivity to pollen until after its own pollen has lost its viability. There is dispute, however, over whether this occurs in ''B. prionotes'': one study claimed to have confirmed "protandrous development", yet recorded high levels of stigmatic receptivity immediately after anthesis, and long pollen viability, observations that are not consistent with protandry.

If it does occur, protandry does nothing to prevent geitonogamous self-pollination: that is, pollination with pollen from another flower on the same plant. In fact, when birds forage at ''B. prionotes'', only about a quarter of all movements from inflorescence to inflorescence involve a change of plant. Geitonogamous self-pollination must therefore occur more often in this species than cross-pollination. This does not imply high rates of self-fertilisation, however, as the species appears highly self-incompatible: although pollen grains will germinate on flowers of the self plant, they apparently fail to produce pollen tubes that penetrate the style. Even where cross-pollination does occur, fertilisation rate is fairly low. It is speculated that this is related to "a variety of chemical reactions at the pollen-stigma interface".

Cone production varies a great deal from year to year, but, as a result of its low flowering rate, is generally very low. However there are typically a very high number of follicles per cone, leading to relatively high seed counts. There is some seed predation, primarily from the curculionid weevil ''Cechides amoenus''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9f3a0da7c877ea670aaebb1d9870b857" name="Banksia_prionotes_4_gnangarra2" sectnum="4.4#1">../img/9f3a0da7c877ea670aaebb1d9870b857.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>