<document id="47fd10c0c4c4f33cf49c2763bdde607e-2" name="Shahbag" cat="11">
<text>
With an area of  and an estimated 2006 population of 112,000 Shabag lies within the monsoon climate zone at an elevation of 1.5 to 13 meters (5 to 43 ft) above mean sea level. Like rest of Dhaka city it has an annual average temperature of  and monthly means varying between  in January and  in August. Nearly 80% of the annual average rainfall of  occurs between May and September.

The Shahbag neighbourhood covers a large approximately rectangular area, extending on the east from Ramna Park to the Supreme Court of Bangladesh; on the west as far as Sonargaon Road; on the south as far as Fuller Road and from the University of Dhaka to the Suhrawardy Udyan (formerly, Ramna Racecourse); and on the north as far as Minto Road, Hotel Sheraton and the Diabetic Hospital.

Shahbag is home to the Dhaka Metropolitan Police (DMP) Control Room as well as a Dhaka Electric Supply Authority substation.  The mausoleums of three leaders—Bengali statesman A.K. Fazlul Huq (1873—1962), former Prime Minister of Pakistan, Huseyn Shaheed Suhrawardy (1892—1963), and former Prime Minister and Governor-General of Pakistan, Khwaja Nazimuddin (1894—1964)—are all located in Shahbag.  The major academic bodies around Shahbag Intersection and in Shahbag ''Thana'' area include: Dhaka University, Dhaka Medical College, BUET, Bangladesh Civil Service Administration Academy, Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujib Medical University (BSMMU), the only public medical university in the country, Institute of Fine Arts (formerly, Dhaka Art College), Institute of Cost & Management Accountants, IBA, Institute of Modern Languages, Udayan School, University Laboratory School, and the Engineering University School. Other public and educational institutions in the area include  the Bangladesh National Museum, the Central Public Library, and the Shishu Academy, the National Academy for Children.

The Shahbag Intersection, the nerve centre of the neighbourhood, is the location of many Dhaka landmarks.  Well-known ones include Hotel Sheraton (formerly Hotel Intercontinental, the second five-star hotel in Dhaka); the Dhaka Club, the oldest and largest club in Dhaka, established in 1911; the National Tennis Complex; Shishu Park, the oldest children's entertainment park in Dhaka, notable for admitting underprivileged children ''gratis'' on weekends; ''Sakura'', the first bar in Dhaka; and ''Peacock'', the first Dhaka bar with outdoor seating. The Shahbag Intersection is one of the major public transportation hubs in Dhaka, along with Farmgate, Gulistan, Mohakhali, and Moghbazar. 

The ''thana'' also contains a hospitals complex, which is a major destination for Bangladeshis seeking medical treatment. The Diabetic Association of Bangladesh (DAB) is located at the Shahbag Intersection, as are BIRDEM (Bangladesh Institute of Research and Rehabilitation in Diabetes, Endocrine and Metabolic Disorders) and the BIRDEM Hospital.  Flanking BIRDEM hospital is the Ibrahim Memorial Cardiac Hospital, named after Dr Muhammad Ibrahim, the founder of DAB and BIRDEM.  Other facilities in the area are BSMMU Hospital (at the Intersection) and the Dhaka Medical College Hospital at the southern end of Shahbag.

Located at the juncture of two major bus routes &ndash; Gulistan to Mirpur and Motijheel to Uttara &ndash; Shahbag Intersection serves as a public transport hubs in Dhaka, where the population commutes exclusively by the city bus services. The Intersection also has one of the few taxi stands in Dhaka. The thoroughfares of Shahbag has been made free of cycle-rickshaws, the traditional transport of Dhaka.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="342c9ef51fb63befd9eda01fc112f389" name="DSC03652" sectnum="2#1">../img/342c9ef51fb63befd9eda01fc112f389.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>