<document id="4825ef6733cf29c6343c5d27ab3dfd2b-3.4" name="Marcus_Trescothick" cat="26">
<text>
The 2004&ndash;5 tour of Zimbabwe caused several players to voice their concerns about the Robert Mugabe regime, the security issues in the country, and the standard of the Zimbabwean side."", Cricinfo, 2004-09-09. Retrieved on 2007-05-30. Steve Harmison was the first to boycott the tour for "political and sporting reasons","", Cricinfo, 2004-09-19. Retrieved on 2007-05-30. and Flintoff was reported to be considering taking a moral stand himself. The England Chairman of Selectors David Graveney denied that the selectors would leave out players unhappy with touring Zimbabwe and would put their absences down to injury."", Cricinfo, 2004-09-26. Retrieved on 2007-05-30. Flintoff and Trescothick were, however, "rested" allowing Kevin Pietersen to make his debut."", Cricinfo, 2004-09-28. Retrieved on 2007-05-30.

Trescothick used the time to prepare for the following series in South Africa, even took up yoga in attempt to bolster his performances abroad."", BBC Sport, 2004-12-09. Retrieved on 2007-08-08. In December 2004, he made 85 not out against an N.F. Oppenheimer XI in South Africa. A partnership of 152 with Strauss in the opening Test against South Africa was followed by a partnership of 273 in the second, in which they both scored over 130. This was a record opening partnership at Durban and England's first 200 opening stand since Gooch and Michael Atherton in 1991."", Cricinfo. Retrieved on 2007-08-08. Before this, the difference between his home and abroad average was over 20,"", BBC Sport, 2004-12-28. Retrieved on 2007-08-08. and his third overseas century went a long way to counter this. With regard to his touring difficulties, Trescothick stated "I wouldn't say I've put it to rest, but I've made a big step forward to putting it to rest. It's a mental battle for me, something I have to deal with and work hard to try to understand what is different. He made a further improvement with an even larger score of 180, as England won the fourth Test. After batting slowly with Ashley Giles, the fall of Hoggard's wicket soon afterwards spurred Trescothick to start "unleashing ferocious shots", setting up an unlikely victory with Steve Harmison partnering him.Agnew, Jonathan ", BBC Sport, 2005-01-17. Retrieved on 2007-08-08. In the matches preceding the 2005 Ashes series, England wrapped up two easy victories against Bangladesh. Trescothick scored 194 in the first Test, and 151 in the second."", BBC Sport, 2005-06-03. Retrieved on 2007-08-08. He also scored 100 not out against Bangladesh in his 100th ODI, surpassing Gooch's record of eight ODI centuries for England., Cricinfo. Retrieved on 2007-08-08.

Trescothick fared better in 2005 than in the previous Ashes series, becoming the second highest run scorer in the series (behind the prolific Kevin Pietersen)., Cricinfo. Retrieved on 2007-08-08. During the third Test, he became the fastest player to reach 5,000 runs in Test cricket,Lynch, Stephen "", Cricinfo, 2005-09-26. Retrieved on 2007-06-10. and also achieved the notable feat of scoring over 1,000 Test runs in a calendar year for the third consecutive year: 1,004 in 2003, 1,003 in 2004, and 1,323 in 2005. He also had the dubious honour of becoming both Glenn McGrath's 500th and Shane Warne's 600th Test wicket during the series."", BBC Sport, 2005-08-11. Retrieved on 2007-07-27."", BBC Sport, 2005-07-21. Retrieved on 2007-07-27. Trescothick was named as one of the five Wisden Cricketers of the Year for his achievements in 2005,'''', Cricinfo. Retrieved on 2007-10-15. and was awarded an MBE in the 2006 New Year honours list with the rest of the English team.'''', BBC Sport, 2005-12-31. Retrieved on 2007-10-14.

For the Test series against Pakistan, Trescothick was offered the captaincy once more due to an injury to Vaughan. He was unsure whether to accept but realised that as "unofficial second in command...I believe it was the right thing to step up. It is exciting to think I could be in charge for a few weeks...I know there is a chance I maybe won't be a one-match wonder this time - it could be the whole series, but being very close to Michael, I've seen the things it  does to you.", BBC Sport, 2005-11-11. Retrieved on 2007-08-08. As it transpired, Trescothick scored 193 in the first innings (although England lost the match), and Vaughan returned for the second Test. Trescothick had considered leaving the tour early when his father-in-law had a serious accident, but stayed in Pakistan as fellow opener Andrew Strauss returned home to attend the birth of his first child."", BBC Sport, 2005-11-18. Retrieved on 2007-08-08.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="16fd235b24eac3fc645f17e5e12ae1a4" name="Trescoshirt" sectnum="3.4#1">../img/16fd235b24eac3fc645f17e5e12ae1a4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>