<document id="4825ef6733cf29c6343c5d27ab3dfd2b-3.3" name="Marcus_Trescothick" cat="26">
<text>
Trescothick played well against a weak Zimbabwe side in the two-Test series in May-June 2003, and scored an unbeaten century in the three ODIs against Pakistan averaging over 100., CricketArchive. Retrieved on 2007-08-07. His form continued in the 2003 NatWest Series, with 114 not out against South Africa. The opening stand with Vikram Solanki of 200 runs was the highest first-wicket partnership for England and provided the first instance of both England openers scoring centuries in the same innings.Gupta, Rajneesh "", CricketArchive, 2003-06-28. Retrieved on 2007-08-07. Trescothick maintained his form in the South Africa Test matches; a career-best 219 at The Oval completed a successful series in which he averaged 60.87., Cricinfo. Retrieved on 2007-08-08.

In Bangladesh, scores in the nineties against both the President's XI and Bangladesh A were followed by a century in the first Test, and 60 in the second. He scored one half century in the three ODIs, although England only used five batsman in the comfortable victories. England played poorly against Sri Lanka,Miller, Andrew"", Cricinfo, 2003-12-21. Retrieved on 2007-10-22. with Trescothick finding it hard to build a large innings. He attempted to take control of the match with 70 at Colombo, as England tried to get something from the series, but was also criticised for his poor catching.Millar, Andrew "", Cricinfo, 2003-12-22. Retrieved on 2007-08-08."", BBC Sport, 2003-12-19. Retrieved on 2007-08-08.

His form in the tour to the West Indies in March and April 2004 was mixed. After several low scores in the Test series&mdash;Trescothick started with only 20 runs from his first five innings&mdash;he reached two half-centuries, but failed to make a substantial match-winning contribution. This poor touring form may have been the start of the troubles that would rule him out of international cricket in the future. Trescothick said, "The hardest thing for me has been the pitches. So far nets and the matches have been on average surfaces and runs have been hard work...In England you get used to good practice surfaces so the rhythm of batting comes pretty easy ."Cheese, Caroline "", BBC Sport, 2004-04-02. Retrieved on 2007-08-08. However, he topped the England batting averages in the 7-match one-day series, with 267 runs including 130 in the 5th ODI and 82 from 57 balls in the 7th., Cricinfo. Retrieved on 2007-08-08.

Back in England, Trescothick was called upon to captain England after Michael Vaughan sustained a knee injury. Although other England captains had seemed to suffer a lack of batting form, the extra authority did not affect Trescothick, and he forged a good partnership with debutant Andrew Strauss against New Zealand. This understanding developed in the second Test with a first-wicket partnership of 153; Trescothick went on to score 132, his sixth Test century."", BBC Sport, 2004-06-05. Retrieved on 2007-08-08. Trescothick's partnerships with Strauss were to average 52.35 in 52 innings."" Cricinfo. Retrieved on 2007-08-25. His first century against the West Indies followed in the second Test, and Trescothick became the first player to make centuries in both innings of a Test match at Edgbaston, and the ninth England player to score a century in each innings of a Test match."", BBC Sport, 2004-08-01. Retrieved on 2007-08-08., Cricinfo. Retrieved on 2007-07-14. Trescothick was again England's best One Day International batsman in the 2004 ICC Champions Trophy, scoring 261 runs in just four innings, including a century in the final; he also took his fourth ODI wicket.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c1349d77e02a608a655fb8079a54e8a3" name="marcus_trescothick" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/c1349d77e02a608a655fb8079a54e8a3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>