<document id="4825ef6733cf29c6343c5d27ab3dfd2b-2" name="Marcus_Trescothick" cat="26">
<text>
Trescothick's first full season at Somerset in 1994 was one of his best, where he scored a total of 925 runs, including two centuries and eight half-centuries at an impressive batting average of 48.63., CricketArchive. Retrieved on 2007-07-14. Having played for the English U-19 cricket team against the West Indies in 1993, and Sri Lanka and India in 1994, Trescothick was named captain for the two Under-19 series against West Indies and South Africa in 1995. His career aggregate of 1,032 runs for England U-19 is second only to John Crawley's 1,058., Cricketarchive. Retrieved on 2007-11-18., ecb.co.uk. Retrieved on 2007-07-12. 


Trescothick was not as successful in domestic cricket in 1995, although there were still some highlights including an innings of 151 against Northamptonshire (a third of his season's total), and a hat-trick, including the wicket of century-maker Adam Gilchrist, for Somerset against Young Australia., CricketArchive, 1995-07-07. Retrieved on 2007-06-10. Trescothick's England Under-19 form was still excellent, averaging 74.62 with the bat in six matches. His Under-19 team mates would often mock him for wearing an England blazer after his matches; Trescothick would reply by saying that "it might be the closest I get to playing for England".Kidd, Patrick. "", The Times, 2006-09-26. Retrieved on 2007-07-03.

The following five years were mixed for Trescothick. Averaging about 30 runs per innings, he was often criticised for a lack of foot movement. David Gower described Trescothick's technique by saying "he does not need to move a long way but needs to move enough. When he is playing well ... he is very good at transferring weight. When he is not playing well, his feet get stuck".Gower, David. ", Cricinfo, July 2006. Retrieved on 2007-07-14. However, Trescothick was awarded the NBC Denis Compton Award for Somerset's most promising young county player in the 1996 and 1997 seasons. In 1997, Somerset Second XI were set 612 to win by Warwickshire Second XI, and Trescothick scored 322 to bring the Seconds to 605.

In 1999, Trescothick impressed Glamorgan coach Duncan Fletcher in a county match at Taunton, by scoring 167 in a low-scoring match where the next-highest innings was 50.  When England opening batsman Nick Knight sustained a finger injury in 2000, Fletcher, who had been appointed England coach, called on Trescothick to make his England debut in the NatWest Series against Zimbabwe and the West Indies., Cricinfo, 2000-07-09. Retrieved on 2007-06-11. Trescothick's regular selection for England meant that he was rarely available for domestic selection between 2000 and 2006, often playing only a few matches for Somerset at the start of the season.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d8f9ed7afce3e40df493e4694ccc43aa" name="Tressyatsom" sectnum="2#1">../img/d8f9ed7afce3e40df493e4694ccc43aa.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>