<document id="4892fd2142a14e5ab807fd95d17eb4c2-12" name="Only_Fools_and_Horses" cat="19">
<text>
''Only Fools and Horses'' spawned many merchandising spin-offs. Several books have been published, most notably the officially sanctioned ''"The Only Fools and Horses Story"'' by Steve Clark (ISBN 0-563-38445-X) and ''"The Complete A-Z of Only Fools and Horses"'' by Richard Webber (ISBN 0-7528-6025-9), both of which detail the history of the series. The scripts have been published in a three-volume compendium, ''"The Bible of Peckham"''. The light-hearted ''"The Trotter Way to Millions"'' (ISBN 0-14-023956-1) and ''"The Trotter Way to Romance"'' (ISBN 0-297-81227-0), both written by John Haselden, see Del giving tips on how to achieve both wealth and love. 

It has been released on VHS, DVD and audio CD in several guises. A DVD collection containing every episode was issued, along with various other special edition box-sets, such as a tin based on their Reliant Regal. DVDs and videos of ''Only Fools and Horses'' continue to be among the BBC's biggest-selling items, having sold over 6 million VHS copies and 1 million DVDs in the UK. An Only Fools and Horses magazine was released in 2004, with each issue containing a DVD of the show. See the list of Only Fools And Horses DVD cuts for the differences between transmitted episodes and DVD episodes.

It also featured on a cavalcade of everyday items. These include a Monopoly-style board game, the ''"Trotters Trading Game"'', in which participants attempt to emulate the Trotters and become millionaires, and another game set in their local pub, entitled the ''"Nag's Head Game tin"''; a DVD board game which features clips and questions while trading hookie gear to other players, a CD-ROM for Windows 95 and Windows 98 which allows users to customise their PCs; a soundtrack of songs used during the show, including the theme tune, and replica die cast models of the Trotters' yellow Reliant Regal van, manufactured by Corgi. Replica money has been made by the 'Bank of Peckham', featuring 'altered' English pound notes with Cockney rhyming slang and Del Boy's head on it instead of the Queen. Other spin-off merchandise includes bottle openers, playing cards, wristwatches, beauty products, calendars and talking alarm clocks.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5f59e3fe460237ef9423b2e5c4e44e7e" name="Only_fools" sectnum="12#1">../img/5f59e3fe460237ef9423b2e5c4e44e7e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>