<document id="497dc4d5f42f6d8692f1297fd61b3321-1" name="Massospondylus" cat="3">
<text>
''Massospondylus'' was a mid-sized prosauropod that was around 4 meters (13 ft) in length and weighed approximately 135 kilograms (300 lb), although a few sources have estimated its length at up to 6 meters (20 ft).  Although long assumed to have been quadrupedal, a 2007 anatomical study of the forelimbs has questioned this, arguing that their range of motion precluded effective habitual quadrupedal gait. The study also ruled out the possibility of "knuckle-walking" and other forms of locomotion that would avoid the issue of the limited ability of ''Massospondylus'' to pronate its hands. Although its mass suggests a quadrupedal nature, it would have been restricted to its hind legs for locomotion.


''Massospondylus'' was a typical prosauropod in most other respects. It possessed a slender body and long neck, with around nine long cervical (neck) vertebrae, 13 dorsal (back) vertebrae, three sacral (hip) vertebrae, and at least 40 caudal (tail) vertebrae. The pubis faced forward, as with most saurischians. It had a slighter build than that of ''Plateosaurus'', an otherwise similar prosauropod dinosaur. A recent discovery shows that ''Massospondylus'' possessed well-developed clavicles, joined in a furcula-like arrangement, suggesting both that it had immobile shoulder blades and that clavicles were not rudimentary and nonfunctional in those dinosaurs that did not have true furculae.  This discovery also indicates that the furcula of birds is derived from clavicles.

Like ''Plateosaurus'', it had five digits on each foot, with a large thumb claw used for feeding or defense against predators. The fourth and fifth digits of the forepaws were tiny, giving the forepaws a lopsided look. The 2007 study indicated that ''Massospondylus'' held its manus (hands) in a semi-supinated ("prayer-like") orientation, with the palmar surfaces facing one another; the wrist was never found rotated in articulated (still-connected) fossil specimens.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5ce22d7ec470ac99f38c3f0f7bbe4c46" name="Massospondylus_1_NHM2" sectnum="1#1">../img/5ce22d7ec470ac99f38c3f0f7bbe4c46.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>