<document id="49892ced776b6ef3376a37b50a6c07fb-1.1" name="Action_of_13_January_1797" cat="29">
<text>
Morard de Galles was planning to sail his fleet from the French naval fortress of Brest under cover of darkness, on the night of 15–16 December. The British Channel Fleet normally maintained a squadron off Brest to blockade the port, but this force had withdrawn  off shore due to the severe Atlantic winter gales, its commander John Colpoys concerned that his ships might be wrecked on the Brittany coastline. The only British ships within sight of Brest were an inshore squadron of frigates under Sir Edward Pellew in , accompanied by , ,  and the lugger HMS ''Duke of York''. Pellew was already renowned, having been the first British officer of the war to capture a French frigate: the ''Cléopâtre'' in 1793. He later captured the frigates ''Pomone'' and ''Virginie'' in 1794 and 1796, and saved 500 lives following the shipwreck of the East Indiaman ''Dutton'' in January 1796. For these actions he had first been knighted and then raised to a baronetcy. ''Indefatigable'' was a razee, one of the largest frigates in the Royal Navy, originally constructed as a 64-gun third rate and cut down to 44-guns in 1795 to make her fast and powerful enough to catch and fight the largest of French frigates. Armed with 24-pounder cannons on the main decks and 42-pounder carronades on the quarter deck, she had a stronger armament than any equivalent French frigate.Woodman, p. 65.


Observing the French fleet's departure from the harbour at dusk, Pellew immediately dispatched ''Phoebe'' to Colpoys and ''Amazon'' to the main fleet at Portsmouth with warnings, before approaching the entrance to Brest in ''Indefatigable'' with the intention of disrupting French movements.Woodman, p. 84. Believing that the frigates in the bay must be the forerunners of a larger British force, Morard de Galles attempted to pass his fleet through the Raz de Sein. This channel was a narrow, rocky and dangerous passage, and de Galles used corvettes as temporary light ships that shone blue lights and fired fireworks to direct his main fleet through the channel.Henderson, p. 21. Pellew observed this, and sailed the ''Indefatigable'' right through the French fleet, launching rockets and shining lights at random. This confused the French officers, causing the ''Séduisant'' to strike the Grand Stevenent rock and sink with the loss of over 680 men from her complement of 1,300.James, p. 6. ''Séduisant'''s distress flares added to the confusion and delayed the fleet's passage until dawn. His task of observing the enemy completed, Pellew took his remaining squadron to Falmouth, sent a report to the Admiralty by semaphore telegraph, and refitted his ships.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f587d593209c0bf54e36806828fda7d9" name="Edward_Pellew" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/f587d593209c0bf54e36806828fda7d9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>