<document id="49892ced776b6ef3376a37b50a6c07fb-3" name="Action_of_13_January_1797" cat="29">
<text>
Pellew was aware that his frigate was heavily outclassed by his much larger opponent, and that ''Amazon'', which was  distant, was not large enough to redress the balance when she did arrive. He correctly assumed, however, that the ocean was too rough to allow Lacrosse to open his lower gunports without the risk that heavy waves would enter them and cause the ''Droits de l'Homme'' to founder.Gardiner, p. 159. In fact the French ship was totally unable to open her lower deck gunports during the action: an unusual design feature had the ports  lower than was normal and as a result the sea poured in at any attempt to open them, preventing any gunnery at all from the lower deck and halving the ship's firepower.James, p. 12 Although this reduced the number of available guns on the French vessel, Lacrosse still held the advantage in terms of size, weight of shot and manpower. The situation was worsened by the loss of the topmasts: this reduced the stability of the French ship, and caused her to roll so severely in the high winds that it was far more difficult to both steer the ship and aim the cannon than on the British vessels.

To the surprise of Lacrosse and his officers, ''Indefatigable'' did not retreat from the ship of the line, nor did she pass the ship of the line at long-range to leeward as expected. Instead, at 17:30, Pellew closed with the stern of the ''Droits de l'Homme'' and raked her. Lacrosse turned to meet the threat and opened fire with the guns on the upper deck accompanied by a heavy volley of musket fire from the soldiers on board. Pellew then attempted to pull ahead of ''Droits de l'Homme'' and rake her bow, to which Lacrosse responded by attempting to ram ''Indefatigable''. Neither manoeuvre was successful, as ''Droits de l'Homme'' raked the British ship but caused little damage as most of her shot scattered into the ocean.

''Indefatigable'' and ''Droits de l'Homme'' manoeuvred around one another, exchanging fire when possible until 18:45, when ''Amazon'' arrived. During this exchange, one of ''Droits de l'Homme'''s cannon burst, causing heavy casualties on her packed deck.Woodman, p. 88. Approaching the larger French ship with all sail spread, Reynolds closed to within pistol shot before raking the ''Droits de l'Homme''. Lacrosse responded to this new threat by manoeuvring to bring both British ships to face the westward side of his ship, avoiding becoming trapped in a crossfire.Henderson, p. 24. The battle continued until 19:30, when both ''Amazon'' and ''Indefatigable'' pulled away from their opponent to make hasty repairs.Clowes, p. 303. By 20:30 the frigates had returned to the much slower French ship and began weaving in front of the ''Droits de l'Homme'''s bow, repeatedly raking her.Henderson, p. 25. Lacrosse's increasingly desperate attempts to ram the British ships were all unsuccessful and what little cannon fire he did manage to deploy was ineffectual, as the rolling of the ship of the line prevented reliable aiming.

By 22:30, the ''Droits de l'Homme'' was in severe difficulties, with heavy casualties among her crew and passengers and the loss of her mizzenmast to British fire. Observing the battered state of their opponent, Pellew and Reynolds closed on the stern quarters of the French ship, maintaining a high rate of fire that was sporadically returned by ''Droits de l'Homme''.James, p. 13. Having exhausted the 4,000 cannon balls available, Lacrosse was forced to use shells against the frigates. In the high winds, these proved even less effective than solid shot but did drive the frigates to a further distance. With their opponent almost immobilised, the British frigates were able to remain outside her arc of fire, effect repairs when necessary and secure guns that had broken loose in the heavy seas.Woodman, p. 89. For the rest of the night the three battered ships remained locked in a close range duel, until suddenly, at 04:20, land was spotted just  to leeward by Lieutenant George Bell of the ''Indefatigable''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="65f2dbc7c1099471eefaccd9575c6ba0" name="Vaisseau-Droits-de-lHomme" sectnum="3#1">../img/65f2dbc7c1099471eefaccd9575c6ba0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>