<document id="4a25a85c4830bcdb6731ee6bf3b1ceb4-3.5" name="Demosthenes" cat="14">
<text>
:''For more details on this topic, see First Philippic and Olynthiacs''

Most of Demosthenes' major orations were directed against the growing power of King Philip II of Macedon. Since 357 BC, when Philip seized Amphipolis and Pydna, Athens had been formally at war with the Macedonians.D. Phillips, ''Athenian Political Oratory'', 69 In 352 BC, Demosthenes characterized Philip as the very worst enemy of his city; his speech presaged the fierce attacks that Demosthenes would launch against the Macedonian king over the ensuing years.Demosthenes, ''Against Aristocrates'',  A year later he criticized those dismissing Philip as a person of no account and warned that he was as dangerous as the King of Persia.Demosthenes, ''For the Liberty of the Rhodians'', 24 

In 352 BC, Athenian troops successfully opposed Philip at Thermopylae,Demosthenes, ''On the False Embassy'', 319 but the Macedonian victory over the Phocians at the Battle of Crocus Field shook Demosthenes. The theme of the ''First Philippic'' (351&ndash;350 BC) was preparedness and the reform of the theoric fund, a mainstay of Eubulus' policy. In his rousing call for resistance, Demosthenes asked his countrymen to take the necessary action and asserted that "for a free people there can be no greater compulsion than shame for their position".Demosthenes, ''First Philippic'', 10


From this moment until 341 BC, all of Demosthenes' speeches referred to the same issue, the struggle against Philip. In 349 BC, Philip attacked Olynthus, an ally of Athens. In the three ''Olynthiacs'', Demosthenes criticized his compatriots for being idle and urged Athens to help Olynthus.Demosthenes, ''Second Olynthiac'', 3Demosthenes, ''First Olynthiac'', 3 He also insulted Philip by calling him a "barbarian". Despite Demosthenes' warnings, the Athenians engaged in a useless war in Euboea and offered no military support to Olynthus.Demosthenes, ''On the Peace'', 5
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a42ad7d8cbd485b9b2ccbc36c7b8ecf0" name="Philip_II_of_Macedon_CdM" sectnum="3.5#1">../img/a42ad7d8cbd485b9b2ccbc36c7b8ecf0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>