<document id="4a25a85c4830bcdb6731ee6bf3b1ceb4-1.1" name="Demosthenes" cat="14">
<text>
Demosthenes was born in 384 BC, during the last year of the 98th Olympiad or the first year of the 99th Olympiad.H. Weil, ''Biography of Demosthenes'', 5&ndash;6 His father—also named Demosthenes—who belonged to the local tribe, Pandionis, and lived in the deme of PaeaniaAeschines, ''Against Ctesiphon'',  in the Athenian countryside, was a wealthy sword-maker.H. T. Peck,   Aeschines, Demosthenes' greatest political rival, maintained that his mother Kleoboule was a Scythian by bloodAeschines, ''Against Ctesiphon'', —an allegation disputed by some modern scholars. Demosthenes was orphaned at the age of seven. Although his father provided well for him, his legal guardians, Aphobus, Demophon and Therippides, mishandled his inheritance.O. Thomsen, ''The Looting of the Estate of the Elder Demosthenes'', 61 

As soon as Demosthenes came of age in 366 BC, he demanded they render an account of their management. According to Demosthenes, the account revealed the misappropriation of his property. Although his father left an estate of nearly fourteen talents,Demosthenes, ''Against Aphobus 1'',  (very  roughly  11,700 troy ounces in silver or 150,000 current United States dollars) Demosthenes asserted his guardians had left nothing "except the house, and fourteen slaves and thirty silver minae" (30 minae = ½ talent).Demosthenes, ''Against Aphobus 1'',  At the age of 20, Demosthenes sued his trustees in order to recover his patrimony and delivered five orations — three ''Against Aphobus'' during 363 BC and 362 BC and two ''Against Ontenor'' during 362 and 361 BC.  The courts fixed Demosthenes' damages at ten talents.Demosthenes, ''Against Aphobus 3'',  When all the trials came to an end, he only succeeded in retrieving a portion of his inheritance.

Between his coming of age in 366 BC and the trials that took place in 364 BC, Demosthenes and his guardians negotiated acrimoniously but were unable to reach an agreement, for neither side was willing to make concessions. At the same time, Demosthenes prepared himself for the trials and improved his oratory skill. As an adolescent, his curiosity had been noticed by the orator Callistratus, who was then at the height of his reputation, having just won a case of considerable importance.Plutarch, ''Demosthenes'', 5 According to Friedrich Nietzsche, a German philologist and philosopher, and Constantine Paparregopoulus, a major Greek historian, Demosthenes was a student of Isocrates;F. Nietzsche, ''Lessons of Rhetoric'', 233&ndash;235K. Paparregopoulus, Ab, 396&ndash;398 according to Cicero, Quintillian and the Roman biographer Hermippus, he was a student of Plato. Lucian, a Roman-Syrian rhetorician and satirist, lists the philosophers Aristotle, Theophrastus and Xenocrates among his teachers.Lucian, ''Demosthenes, An Encomium'', 12 These claims are nowadays disputed. According to Plutarch, Demosthenes employed Isaeus as his master in Rhetoric, even though Isocrates was then teaching this subject, either because he could not pay Isocrates the prescribed fee or because Demosthenes believed Isaeus' style better suited a vigorous and astute orator such as himself . Curtius, a German archaeologist and historian, likened the relation between Isaeus and Demosthenes to "an intellectual armed alliance".R. C. Jebb,  

It has also been said that Demosthenes paid Isaeus 10,000 drachmae (somewhat over 1.5 talents) on the condition that Isaeus should withdraw from a school of Rhetoric which he had opened, and should devote himself wholly to Demosthenes, his new pupil. Another version credits Isaeus with having taught Demosthenes without charge.Suda, article  According to Sir Richard C. Jebb, a British classical scholar, "the intercourse between Isaeus and Demosthenes as teacher and learner can scarcely have been either very intimate or of very long duration". Konstantinos Tsatsos, a Greek professor and academician, believes that Isaeus helped Demosthenes edit his initial judicial orations against his guardians.K. Tsatsos, ''Demosthenes'', 83 Demosthenes is also said to have admired the historian Thucydides. In the ''Illiterate Book-Fancier,'' Lucian mentions eight beautiful copies of Thucydides made by Demosthenes, all in Demosthenes' own handwriting.Lucian, ''The Illiterate Book-Fancier'', 4 These references hint at his respect for a historian he must have assiduously studied.H. Weil, ''Biography of Demothenes'', 10&ndash;11

According to Pseudo-Plutarch, Demosthenes was married once. The only information about his wife, whose name is unknown, is that she was the daughter of Heliodorus, a prominent citizen.Pseudo-Plutarch, ''Demosthenes'', 847c Demosthenes also had a daughter, "the only one who ever called him father", according to Aeschines' in a trenchant remark.Aeschines, ''Against Ctesiphon'',  His daughter died young and unmarried a few days before Philip's death.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="da96147d69c261b2bcd7d0b33eb27477" name="Demosthenes_bust-_r280_BC.2jpg" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/da96147d69c261b2bcd7d0b33eb27477.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>