<document id="4a25a85c4830bcdb6731ee6bf3b1ceb4-2.3" name="Demosthenes" cat="14">
<text>
Even before he turned 21-years-old in 363 BC, Demosthenes had already demonstrated an interest in politics. In 363, 359, and 357 BC, he assumed the office of the trierarch, being responsible for the outfitting and maintenance of a trireme.A.W. Pickard, ''Demosthenes and the Last Days of Greek Freedom'', xiv-xv In 348 BC, he became a choregos, paying the expenses of a theatrical production.S. Usher, ''Greek Oratory'', 226
 
Although Demosthenes said he never pleaded a single private case,Demosthenes, ''Against Zenothemis'',  it remains unclear when and if Demosthenes abandoned the profitable but not so prestigious profession of logography. According to Plutarch, when Demosthenes first addressed himself to the people, he was derided for his strange and uncouth style, "which was cumbered with long sentences and tortured with formal arguments to a most harsh and disagreeable excess".Plutarch, ''Demosthenes'', 6 

Some citizens however discerned his talent. When he first left the ecclesia (the Athenian Assembly) disheartened, an old man named Eunomus encouraged him, saying his diction was very much like that of Pericles. Another time, after the ecclesia had refused to hear him and he was going home dejected, an actor named Satyrus followed him and entered into a friendly conversation with him.Plutarch, ''Demosthenes'', 7

As a boy Demosthenes had a speech impediment — an inarticulate and stammering pronunciation. Aeschines taunted him and referred to him in his speeches by the nickname "Batalus", apparently invented by Demosthenes' pedagogues or by the little boys with whom he was playing.Aeschines, ''Against Timarchus'', Aeschines, ''The Speech on the Embassy'',  According to Plutarch, he had a weakness in his voice of "a perplexed and indistinct utterance and a shortness of breath, which, by breaking and disjointing his sentences much obscured the sense and meaning of what he spoke." Demosthenes soon undertook a disciplined program to overcome these shortcomings and improve his elocution. He worked on his diction, his voice and his gestures.Plutarch, ''Demosthenes'', 6&ndash;7 His zeal and perseverance have passed into proverb. It is however unknown whether these vignettes are factual accounts of events in Demosthenes' life or merely anecdotes used to illustrate his perseverance and determination.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1f4fb7c67eaa68b764f1e2cfd9ee94e6" name="DemosthPracticing" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/1f4fb7c67eaa68b764f1e2cfd9ee94e6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>