<document id="4a4566696cc81c6053ec708975767498-5" name="Batman" cat="17">
<text>
Batman's interactions with the characters around him, both heroes and villains, help to define the character. Commissioner James "Jim" Gordon, Batman's ally in the Gotham City police, debuted along with Batman in ''Detective Comics'' #27 and has been a consistent presence since then. Later on, Batman gained Alfred as his butler and Lucius Fox as his business manager and apparently unwitting armorer. However, the most important supporting role in the Batman mythos is filled by the hero's young sidekick Robin.Boichel, pg. 7 The first Robin, Dick Grayson, eventually leaves his mentor and becomes the hero Nightwing, though he would appear time to time to give him assistance. The second Robin, Jason Todd, is badly beaten by the Joker, then killed in an explosion set by the Joker but later returns as an adversary. Tim Drake, the third Robin, first appears in 1989 and has gone on to star in his own comic series. Alfred, Bruce Wayne's loyal butler, father figure, and one of the few to know his secret identity, " a homey touch to Batman's environs and  ever ready to provide a steadying and reassuring hand" to the hero and his sidekick.Boichel, pg. 8 

Batman is at times a member of superhero teams such as the Justice League of America and the Outsiders. Batman has often been paired in adventure with his Justice League teammate Superman, notably as the co-stars of ''World's Finest'' and ''Superman/Batman'' series. In pre-Crisis continuity, the two are depicted as close friends; however, in current continuity, they have a mutually respectful but uneasy relationship, with an emphasis on their differing views on crime fighting and justice.

Batman is involved romantically with many women throughout his various incarnations. These range from society women such as Julie Madison, Vicki Vale and Silver St. Cloud, to allies like Wonder Woman and Sasha Bordeaux, to even villainesses such as Catwoman and Talia al Ghul, with the latter of whom he sired a son, Damien, and with the former of whom sired a daughter, Helena. While these relationships tend to be short, Batman's attraction to Catwoman is present in nearly every version and medium in which the characters appear. Authors have gone back and forth over the years as to how Batman manages the 'playboy' aspect of Bruce Wayne's personality; at different times he embraces or flees from the women interested in attracting "Gotham's most eligible bachelor."

Other supporting characters in Batman's world include former Batgirl Barbara Gordon, Commissioner Gordon's daughter who, now using a wheelchair due to a gunshot wound inflicted by the Joker, serves the superhero community at large as the computer hacker Oracle; Azrael, a would-be assassin who replaces Bruce Wayne as Batman for a time; Cassandra Cain, an assassin's daughter who became the new Batgirl, Huntress, the sole surviving member of a mob family turned Gotham vigilante who has worked with Batman on occasion, Stephanie Brown, the daughter of a criminal who operated as the Spoiler and temporarily as Robin, Ace the Bat-Hound, Batman's Canine partner;Daniels (1995), pg. 138 and Bat-Mite, an extra-dimensional imp who idolizes Batman.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="891b28d6c845124f7ad24013177842c9" name="BatmanRobin" sectnum="5#1">../img/891b28d6c845124f7ad24013177842c9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>