<document id="4a4566696cc81c6053ec708975767498-6.12" name="Batman" cat="17">
<text>
The character of Batman has appeared in various media aside from comic books. The character has been developed as a vehicle for newspaper syndicated comic strips, books, radio dramas, television and several theatrical feature films. The first adaptation of Batman was as a daily newspaper comic strip which premiered on October 25, 1943.Daniels (1999), pg. 50 That same year the character was adapted in the 13-part serial ''Batman'', with Lewis Wilson becoming the first actor to portray Batman on screen. While Batman never had a radio series of his own, the character made occasional guest appearance in ''The Adventures of Superman'' starting in 1945 on occasions when Superman voice actor Bud Collyer needed time off.Daniels (1999), pg. 64 A second movie serial, ''Batman and Robin'', followed in 1949, with Robert Lowery taking over the role of Batman. The exposure provided by these adaptations during the 1940s "helped make  a household name for millions who never bought a comic book.".

In the 1964 publication of Donald Barthelme's collection of short stories "Come Back, Dr. Caligari", Barthelme wrote "The Joker's Greatest Triumph." Batman is portrayed for purposes of spoof as a pretentious French-speaking rich man.Olsen, Lance. "Linguistic Pratfalls in Barthelme", ''South Atlantic Review'', Vol. 51, No. 4 (Nov., 1986), pp. 69-77 (article consists of 9 pages). South Atlantic Modern Language Association. Stable URL: http://www.jstor.org/stable/3199757 


The ''Batman'' television series, starring Adam West, premiered in January 1966 on the ABC television network. Inflected with a camp sense of humor, the show became a pop culture phenomenon. In his memoir, ''Back to the Batcave'', West notes his dislike for the term 'camp' as it was applied to the 1960s series, opining that the show was instead a farce or lampoon, and a deliberate one, at that. The series ran for 120 episodes, ending in 1968. In between the first and second season of the ''Batman'' television series the cast and crew made the theatrical release ''Batman'' (1966). The popularity of the ''Batman'' TV series also resulted in the first animated adaptation of Batman in the series ''The Batman/Superman Hour'';Boichel, pg. 14 the Batman segments of the series were repackaged as ''Batman with Robin the Boy Wonder'' which produced thirty-three episodes between 1968 and 1977. From 1973 until 1986, Batman had a starring role in ABC's ''Super Friends'' series, which was animated by Hanna-Barbera. Olan Soule was the voice of Batman in all these series, but was eventually replaced during ''Super Friends'' by Adam West, who voiced the character in Filmation's 1977 series ''The New Adventures of Batman''.

In 1989, Batman returned to movie theaters in director Tim Burton's ''Batman'' starring Michael Keaton as the title character. The film was a huge success; not only was it the top-grossing film of the year, but at the time was the fifth highest-grossing film in history. The film spawned three sequels: ''Batman Returns'' (1992), ''Batman Forever'' (1995) and ''Batman & Robin'' (1997), the last two of which were directed by Joel Schumacher instead of Burton, and replaced Keaton as Batman with Val Kilmer and George Clooney, respectively. 


In 1992, Batman returned to television in ''Batman: The Animated Series'', which was produced by Warner Bros. and broadcast on the Fox television network. Author Les Daniels described the series as " as close as any artistic statement has to defining the look of Batman for the 1990s."Daniels (1999), pg. 178 The success of ''Batman: The Animated Series'' led to the animated spin-off film ''Batman: Mask of the Phantasm'' (1993), as well as various other animated series set in the same continuity, including ''The New Batman Adventures'', ''Batman Beyond'', and ''Justice League''. As with ''Batman: The Animated Series'', each of these productions featured Kevin Conroy as the voice of Batman. In 2004, a new animated series titled ''The Batman'' made its debut with Rino Romano as the title character. In 2008, this show was replaced by another animated series, ''Batman: The Brave and the Bold'', with Diedrich Bader as Batman.

In 2005, Christopher Nolan directed ''Batman Begins'', a reboot of the film franchise starring Christian Bale as Batman. Its sequel, ''The Dark Knight'' (2008), set the record for the highest grossing opening weekend of all time in the U.S., earning approximately $158 million, and became the fastest film to reach the $400 million mark in the history of American cinema (eighteenth day of release). These record breaking attendances saw ''The Dark Knight'' listed as the second-highest domestic grossing film of all time with $533 million, second only to ''Titanic''. An animated anthology feature set between the Nolan films, ''Batman: Gotham Knight'', was also released in 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="67c4677159c50a045a2bfe37bee3cc47" name="Batman_keaton_89" sectnum="6.12#1">../img/67c4677159c50a045a2bfe37bee3cc47.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>