<document id="4ad82ee1df8c0b5db4d1dcf60c32fb58-6.2" name="Blue_Iguana" cat="3">
<text>
The Blue Iguana is listed as critically endangered on the IUCN Red List. The population is restricted to the eastern interior of Grand Cayman, where it had been reduced to a critically low level, only three animals having been observed before the survey in 1988.
 The range of the Blue Iguana has contracted significantly over the past 25 years, with many sites once populated now showing no signs of iguanas. Surveys in 2003 indicated a total population in the range of 5–15 individuals. By 2005 the unmanaged wild population was considered to be functionally extinct. The species is one of the most endangered animals on Earth.
 A further blow to the dwindling population came in May 2008 when six individuals were found butchered in a nature preserve.

As the Blue Iguana consumes a variety of plant material, favoring fruits and flowers over leaves and stems when available, it is valuable on Grand Cayman as a seed disperser throughout its range. A study in 2000 by Dr Allison Alberts revealed that seeds passing through the digestive tracts of ''Cycluras'' germinate more rapidly than those that do not. These seeds in the fruits consumed by the Blue Iguana have an adaptive advantage by sprouting before the end of very short rainy seasons. The Blue Iguana is also an important means of distributing seeds to new areas and, as the largest native herbivore of Grand Cayman's ecosystems, it is essential for maintaining the delicate balance between climate and vegetation necessary to survive under harsh conditions.


Restored free-roaming subpopulations in the Queen Elizabeth II Botanic Park and the Salina Reserve numbered approximately 125 individuals in total after a release in December 2005. The restored subpopulation in the Queen Elizabeth II Botanic Park has been breeding since 2001, and the subpopulation in the Salina Reserve was deemed to be breeding in 2006 after a nest of three hatched eggs was discovered in the wild.
 As of April 2007, after another large-scale release, there are 299 Blue Iguanas living in the wild, with hundreds more being raised in captivity on Grand Cayman.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b1acf87820ea5988e16630f46c11a1f0" name="Blue_Iguana_in_tree" sectnum="6.2#1">../img/b1acf87820ea5988e16630f46c11a1f0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>