<document id="4ad82ee1df8c0b5db4d1dcf60c32fb58-6.4.1" name="Blue_Iguana" cat="3">
<text>
The Blue Iguana Recovery Programme grew from a small project started within the National Trust for the Cayman Islands in 1990. It is now a partnership, linking the Trust with the Cayman Islands Department of Environment, National Trust Cayman Islands, Queen Elizabeth II Botanic Park, Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust, International Reptile Conservation Foundation, IRCF, and the European Commission. This program operates under a special exemption from provisions in the Animals Law of the Cayman Islands which normally would make it illegal for anyone to kill, capture, or keep iguanas. BIRP's conservation strategy involves generating large numbers of genetically diverse hatchlings, head-starting'''Head-starting''' means raising the animals in captivity from the time they hatch until they are big enough not to fall prey to feral cats and rodents, thereby offsetting the juvenile mortality rate. them for two years where their chance of survival in the wild is high, and using these animals to rebuild a series of wild sub-populations in protected, managed natural areas.
 This is accompanied by field research, nest site protection, and monitoring of the released animals.


 A rapid numerical increase from a maximum possible number of founding stock is sought to minimize loss of genetic diversity caused by the "population bottleneck".

Restored sub-populations are already present in two non-contiguous areas—the Salina Reserve and the Queen Elizabeth II Botanic Park. Habitat protection is still vital, as the Salina Reserve has only  of dry shrubland, which is not enough to sustain the 1,000 Blue Iguanas that must be restored to the wild to remove this species from the Critically Endangered List. Additional separate sub-populations will be restored in one or more other areas. The overall captive population is likely to remain genetically fragmented in the long term. Individuals will be translocated between sub-populations to maintain gene flow so that the entire population remains a single genetic management unit. When the wild sub-populations have reached the carrying capacity of their respective protected areas, release of head-started animals will be phased out, and they will be left to reproduce naturally. In addition, guided by research and monitoring, control or eradication of non-native predators will be implemented to the degree necessary to allow young Blue Iguanas to survive to maturity in sufficient numbers to maintain these sub-populations.

Maintenance of Blue Iguanas in the wild requires active management into the indefinite future. To sustain this activity, a range of commercial activities generates the funding required, while an ongoing education and awareness effort ensures continued involvement and support by the local community.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7707ddfee90df8b55922e64166299479" name="BlueIguana-close" sectnum="6.4.1#1">../img/7707ddfee90df8b55922e64166299479.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>