<document id="4b055af79e05167b41460443de65e574-5" name="Ian_Johnson_(cricketer)" cat="26">
<text>
Unusually for an Australian, Johnson bowled off-spin rather than the wrist spin normally associated with countrymen of his day.  Johnson had an atypical bowling action, with a "rather staccato swing" of his bowling arm.Martin-Jenkins (1980), p. 193. He bowled with a high degree of flight, causing opposing batsmen difficulties in judging where the ball would land. Making intelligent use of the wind, Johnson was able to make his deliveries float away from the batsman, changing from his standard off-break. According to E. W. Swanton, Johnson was "probably the slowest bowler to achieve any measure of success in Test cricket".  His action was compared to a corkscrew; writer Ray Robinson saying that "to coax turn from firm Australian pitches he twisted the ball almost hard enough to screw a doorknob off".  There were doubts about the legality of his bowling action; his English rival, Trevor Bailey claimed Johnson threw every delivery.  Johnson was never no-balled for throwing, having played cricket in front of umpires from Australia, England, New Zealand, South Africa, the West Indies, India and Pakistan. 

Jack Pollard described Johnson as a "dour middle order batsman". He had a sound defence and when necessary could hit the ball with power. Bradman was full of praise for Johnson's batting after the ''Invincibles'' tour in 1948: "Splendid batsman&mdash;most valuable about number 7", also describing him as a "very good slip field".


As captain, Johnson was noted for his public relations skills and his gift for public speaking.Haigh (2006), p. 92.  He was optimistic by nature, with a belief in "guts and determination".Robinson (1996), p. 245. "With his slogan 'Guts and determination', Johnson had too much fire to lose heart, even when on the ropes."  However, he was seen as insensitive at times; Bill Johnston took offence when Johnson attempted to rouse him during a practise session: "Just cos you are one of the old blokes in the side doesn't mean you don't have to bloody well put in you know."Haigh (2006), p. 95. At times his optimism could appear artless and naive. Ian Craig&mdash;his successor as Australian captain&mdash;was critical of Johnson's attitude during the 1956 tour of England: "I don't think  was ever realistic about the situation.  I supposed he felt obliged to make rallying speeches, but the team knew what was going on." Pat Crawford felt "Johnson couldn't get anything out of the players, whereas the guys would have busted a gut for ".  He was seen by some of his team mates as "dictatorial" with  Benaud and Harvey particularly resenting Johnson's insistence on the entire touring party attending every lead-in match before 1956 Test series in England.  

Johnson was sportsmanlike; on one occasion in South Africa, when Eastern Province batsman Ray Connell was bowled after the ball deflected from his head, Johnson replaced the bails, allowing him to continue batting.Haigh (2006), p. 28.  During the Adelaide Test in 1950&ndash;51 he "walked", ensuring that the unlucky John Warr took at least one wicket for the series.   Johnson was not above some gamesmanship, resorting to time-wasting tactics to avoid defeat in the final Test of the 1956 series against England.  He was willing to have some fun on occasion; when in the West Indies he convinced a local pilot to allow him to fly the plane carrying the Australian team between Trinidad and nearby Tobago, to the later displeasure of the Australian Board of Control. 

Normally diplomatic, in a newspaper article in South Africa, Johnson was blunt with his hosts about race relations in the country: "I am certain that the average man-in-the-street avoids the problem too much for, at the moment, you're living in a fool's paradise".Haigh (2006), p. 17. Urbane, courteous and popular with opposition players and spectators, Colin Cowdrey described Johnson as "an astute leader and fine ambassador for cricket".Cowdrey (1986), p. 197.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c62102715614b3259b1ce2473b8a674b" name="JohnsontoHutton" sectnum="5#1">../img/c62102715614b3259b1ce2473b8a674b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>