<document id="4b055af79e05167b41460443de65e574-2.3" name="Ian_Johnson_(cricketer)" cat="26">
<text>
During the Test series in South Africa in 1949&ndash;50, Johnson took 18 wickets at an average of 24.22&mdash;only Bill Johnston, with 23, took more. Against a South African team weakened following the Second World War, the Australians started the series with a win in the First Test at Ellis Park at Johannesburg.  The Australians won the match by an innings and 83 runs; Johnson made 66 and took 3/37 and 3/54.  His best performance was in the Third Test at Kingsmead in Durban; 5/34 including the wicket of Dudley Nourse as South Africa was dismissed for 99. Australia, having made only 75 in their first innings, scored 336, including 151 not out by Neil Harvey, to win the match by five wickets.  Australia won the series&mdash;Lindsay Hassett's first as captain&mdash;four Tests to nil.


Freddie Brown and his English team toured Australia in 1950&ndash;51 to compete for the Ashes in a five Test series.  Australia won the series four Tests to one; however ''Wisden'' reports that while "Australia held a slight superiority ... the difference between the teams was markedly less than revealed by statistics".  Johnson had a "mediocre series", taking only seven wickets at an average of 44.42.  His best performance was in the Third Test, when he took three wickets in the England first innings. He followed this by scoring 77 runs in a 150 run partnership with Keith Miller, who went on to score 145 not out. Johnson took another wicket in the English second innings and Australia won the Test by an innings and 13 runs.  England's victory in the Fifth Test in Melbourne ended Australia's unbeaten run of 29 Tests since 1938.Pollard (1988), p. 388.

The next summer, the West Indian team visited Australia to play five Tests.  The series was billed as the "unofficial cricket championship of the world", following the West Indian victory against England in 1950. However, the Australians won the series comfortably, 4&ndash;0. Johnson had another lean series, taking only eight wickets at an average of 32.75.  

When the South Africans toured in 1952&ndash;53, Johnson was selected for Australia ahead of Queenslander Colin McCool. His selection was unpopular with a parochial Gabba crowd; when Gil Langley&mdash;who had replaced another Queenslander, Don Tallon&mdash;fumbled a stumping chance against John Watkins, they cheered loudly.Haigh (2006), p. 48. Johnson was omitted from the side for the remainder of the series and was not included in the Australian squad to tour England in 1953.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f263d665c972092f24c4d9b412a3e892" name="AusCricketTeam1950" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/f263d665c972092f24c4d9b412a3e892.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>