<document id="4b055af79e05167b41460443de65e574-3.4" name="Ian_Johnson_(cricketer)" cat="26">
<text>
While the Australian team lost the Ashes for the first time in twenty years, Johnson spent the winter of 1953 calling Australian rules football matches for local radio station 3AW and writing columns for ''The Argus newspaper.''Haigh (2006), pp. 83&ndash;85.  Later that year, the Victorian Cricket Association appointed him to succeed the retired Hassett as captain of Victoria.  In the middle of the season, at a mutual friend's New Year's Eve party, Hassett approached Johnson to discuss his form.  Taking a confrontational approach, Hassett said to Johnson, "The problem is that you are not getting stuck in.  You're not trying."  When Johnson protested, Hassett continued "If you have got any brains, you will start taking this game seriously.  Because if you do you will end up captaining Australia next year."

The other contender for the vacant national captaincy position was Keith Miller, the fast-bowling all-rounder and captain of New South Wales.  Miller had led his team to victory in the 1953&ndash;54 Sheffield Shield and was recognised as an intuitive captain.  Based solely on cricketing merit, Miller, a regular selection at international level, was seen as the superior candidate.Haigh (2006), p. 84. "On cricketing merits, Miller was vastly Johnson's superior."  However, inter-state rivalries and a perception that Miller would be a poor disciplinarian saw him passed over. This perception was partly based on a incident when Miller, as captain of New South Wales, allowed his team-mate Sid Barnes to serve drinks on the field dressed in a three-piece suit rather than standard cricket whites.  Johnson, on the other hand, was part of the cricket establishment: he was an alumnus of the exclusive Wesley College and the son of a former Test selector.  He had also returned to form, taking 37 wickets in the 1953&ndash;54 Sheffield Shield&mdash;more than any other player&mdash;at an average of 16.37.   In what cricket writer Dick Whitington speculated was a vote split between the New South Wales and Victorian factions, the Australian Board of Control appointed Johnson as Australian captain. His appointment was not universally applauded.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="14b6039c334a582e171f9f02a9db50c0" name="KeithMiller1954" sectnum="3.4#1">../img/14b6039c334a582e171f9f02a9db50c0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>