<document id="4b68493476c7b9b3e7a207677df788c6-2" name="Zodiac_(film)" cat="19">
<text>
*Jake Gyllenhaal as Robert Graysmith: a cartoonist for the ''San Francisco Chronicle''. While researching the film, Fincher considered Gyllenhaal to play Graysmith. According to the director, “I really liked him in ''Donnie Darko'' and I thought, ‘He’s an interesting double-sided coin. He can do that naive thing but he can also do possessed’”. To prepare for his role, Gyllenhaal met Graysmith and videotaped him in order to study his mannerisms and behavior.
*Mark Ruffalo as SFPD Inspector David Toschi: Initially, Ruffalo was not interested in the project but Fincher wanted him to play Toschi. He met with the actor and told him that he was rewriting the screenplay. “I loved what he was saying and loved where he was going with it,” the actor remembers. For research, he read every report on the case and read all the books on the subject. Ruffalo met Toschi and found out that he had “perfect recall of the details and what happened when, where, who was there, what he was wearing. He always knew what he was wearing. I think it is seared into who he is and it was a big deal for him”.
*Robert Downey Jr. as Paul Avery, a journalist at the ''San Francisco Chronicle'' who covered the Zodiac killer case.
*Anthony Edwards as SFPD Inspector William Armstrong: When casting the role, Fincher said he thought of Edwards because "I knew I needed the most decent person I could find, because he would be the balance of the movie. In a weird way, this movie wouldn’t exist without Bill Armstrong. Everything we know about the Zodiac case, we know because of his notes. So in casting the part, I wanted to get someone who is totally reliable".
*Brian Cox as Melvin Belli, a prominent defense attorney who received a letter from the Zodiac killer. Originally, Gary Oldman was to play him but "he went to a lot of trouble, they had appliances, but just physically it wasn't going to work, he just didn't have the girth," Graysmith remembers. Cox was cast instead.
*John Carroll Lynch as Arthur Leigh Allen, a prime suspect in the case. Allen was never charged with these crimes.
*Chloë Sevigny as Melanie Graysmith, Graysmith's wife.
*John Getz as Templeton Peck.
*Elias Koteas as Sgt. Jack Mulanax, a police detective from Vallejo.
*Dermot Mulroney as Captain Marty Lee, Armstrong's and Toschi's supervisor in the SFPD homicide division.
*Donal Logue as Ken Narlow, a police detective in Napa.
*Philip Baker Hall as Sherwood Morrill, a handwriting analyst.
*Adam Goldberg as Duffy Jennings, a real life journalist who replaced Avery at the ''San Francisco Chronicle'' when the latter went to the ''San Francisco Examiner''. He received a letter from the Zodiac in 1978.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9241d5e8d692774fabac749272e1fc69" name="Z-Approved-039R" sectnum="2#1">../img/9241d5e8d692774fabac749272e1fc69.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>