<document id="4b81674785998f48856b4680001df379-3.4" name="Funerary_Monument_to_Sir_John_Hawkwood" cat="1">
<text>
The choice of Paolo Uccello (born in Florence in 1397),The date of Uccello's birth is somewhat speculative. However it is known that he was born to Antonia di Giovanni and Dona di Paolo, a barber-surgeon. who had apprenticed for Lorenzo Ghiberti from June 1407, busying himself polishing the "Gates of Paradise", may have been an attempt to find a painter knowledgeable in bronze and statuary, which the fresco was to mimic.D'Ancona, 1960, p. 5.Paolieri, 1991, p. 12. For centuries, art historians have regarded Uccello as a less-prominent artist at the time of the Hawkwood commission: he is not mentioned in the preface of Alberti's ''De Pictura'', nor in Domenico Veneziano's 1438 letter to Piero di Cosimo de' Medici listing the major contemporary painters; nor have art historians even attempted to speculate that he studied the frescoes at the Brancacci Chapel.Paolieri, 1991, p. 7. The designation of an artist as having studied the Brancacci frescos&mdash;which is often not based on documentary evidence&mdash;is primarily of historigraphical importance, an indication that the artist is regarded as worthy of the trope of "genius". One difficulty for art historians attempting to gauge Uccello's reputation at the time of the ''Hawkwood'''s commissioning is the 10-year blind spot in the reconstruction of Uccello's career between 1415&mdash;when Uccello was made a member of the Guild of Doctors and Apothecaries (''Arte dei Medici e Speziali'')&mdash;and his trip to Venice in 1425.Some speculate that he stayed at Ghiberti's workshop. See Paolieri, 1991, p. 12. Similarly, all the works of Uccello's Venetian period are either missing or else of uncertain attribution: Uccello is thought to have made a no-longer-existing mosaic of St. Peter on the façade of St. Mark's Basilica, to have collaborated on the design of architectural structures for the mosaics in the Mascoli Chapel of St. Mark's by Michele Giambono, and possibly to have made some geometrical pattern decorations for the interior of St. Mark's.Paolieri, 1991, p. 12–13.

Uccello was known to have been in Venice in 1427 and to have returned to Florence by 1431, allowing a second window for historiographical speculation: some say he may have gone to Rome;Paolieri, 1991, p. 13. others say he went directly to Florence.Mode, 1972, p. 377. Uccello probably painted the ''Creation of the Animals and Creation of Adam'' (c. 1431) in the upper part of one of the bays of the Chiostro Verde (the "Green Cloister") in Santa Maria Novella, which&mdash;like the ''Hawkwood'', as specified in its commissionHudson, 2006, p. 17; Wegener, 1993, p. 134.&mdash;is in the "terra verde" grisaille manner.Paolieri, 1991, p. 13–15. Perhaps Uccello worked on the stories from the life of the Virgin and St. Stephen in the Chapel of Our Lady of the Assumption in the Prato Cathedral around 1435, although Pope-Hennessy, Pudelko, and SalmiSalmi, 1936, p. 106. all dispute this attribution.Paolieri, 1991, p. 15–16.

Thus, the Florence Cathedral is the repository of all the extant works of Uccello whose attribution is firmly rooted in contemporary documents: two murals&mdash;the ''Hawkwood'' and the ''Clock Face with Four Heads of Prophets or Evangelists'' (1443)&mdash;and two stained glass windows&mdash;''Resurrection'' (1443-1444) and ''Nativity'' (1443-1444).Hudson, 2006, p. 1. The ''Hawkwood'' is Uccello’s "earliest dated and fully authenticated extant work".Pudelko, 1934, p. 232.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="10e01f1ef744427799f89787716020f1" name="Florence-Duomo-Clock" sectnum="3.4#1">../img/10e01f1ef744427799f89787716020f1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>