<document id="4b81674785998f48856b4680001df379-3.1" name="Funerary_Monument_to_Sir_John_Hawkwood" cat="1">
<text>
On August 20, 1393&mdash;when the Signoria, at the suggestion of  Coluccio Salutati, voted to erect a marble statue of Hawkwood in the Duomo, "that brave men may know that the commune of Florence recompenses true service"&mdash;Hawkwood was liquidating his Tuscan properties and preparing to return to England.Caferro, 2006, p. 310–313. It was unprecedented for the Signoria to vote to erect a monument to a living person in the cathedral.Borsi, 1994, p. 302. The ambiguous plans of the Signoria&mdash;which likely was aware of Hawkwood's health status&mdash;might well have been for a tomb rather than a cenotaph; Hawkwood died soon after, on March 17, 1394.Caferro, 2006, p. 313. The Signoria went to great lengths (unsuccessfully) to entice Donnina to remain in the city—voting to transfer various sums of money to her (in exchange for Hawkwood's Tuscan fortress), despite "thorny legal issues" which required multiple acts of the city council&mdash;indicating to some extent the market value of Hawkwood’s symbolic capital.Caferro, 2006, p. 321–322. 

Hawkwood's March 20 funeral began in the Piazza della Signoria, continued to the Battistero di San Giovanni, where his body was placed on the baptismal font for public viewing, and culminated in the Cathedral, at a cost of 410 florins, not counting the substantial expenses of the Guilds.Caferro, 2006, p. 314–315; Hudson, 2006, p. 9; for comparison, the funeral of Coluccio Salutati, the humanist Chancellor of Florence, cost 250 florins. See Caferro, 2006, p. 315. 

The plans for Hawkwood's commemoration were modified on December 2, 1395, when it was decided to also rework the wooden monument of Pietro Farnese, the hero of the Pisan war, and to place marble tomb monuments to Farnese and Hawkwood on the north aisle, facing the high altar.Caferro, 2006, p. 317. Painters Agnolo Gaddi and Giuliano Arrighi were selected by a committee to sketch directly onto the Duomo wall models for the Hawkwood and Farnese tombs. Although neither tomb was realized, documentary evidence suggests that a painting of Hawkwood&mdash;with a figure of Hawkwood by Gaddi and a sarcophagus by Pesello&mdash;was completed by June 16, 1396.Caferro, 2006, p. 317–318. Other dates include 1395 (plans) and 1405 (execution). See Hatfield, 1965, p. 320. Historian Frances Stonor Saunders speculates that Uccello may have based his representation of Hawkwood on this early painting and that the earlier painting may have been based on a death mask of Hawkwood.Saunders, 2004, pp 313–315. The Hawkwood fresco is situated in the third bay of the northern wall, today flanked by paintings of Dante (c. 1455) and fellow mercenary Niccolò da Tolentino (c. 1465, by Andrea del Castagno); fictive tombs in fresco of two humanist ecclesiasts&mdash;Bishop Corsini (c. 1422, probably by Giovanni dal Ponte) and Fra Luigi de' Marsigli (c. 1439 by Bicci di Lorenzo), an Augustinian monk who founded a literary academy&mdash;are much smaller than those of the two ''condottieri''.Caferro, 2006, p. 318.Hudson, 2006, p. 8. The fresco probably came to replace the tomb (rather than serving as a place marker for it) for reasons of expedience and frugality, although on these points there is little documentary evidence.Hudson, 2006, p. 9.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bd34a04b65348610cf02288eaf3815a5" name="Firenze.Duomo.Tolentino" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/bd34a04b65348610cf02288eaf3815a5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>