<document id="4ba89b2fc68d6ab4f37feb53eae919d2-4.1" name="Western_Chalukya_Empire" cat="14">
<text>
The fall of the Rashtrakuta empire to the Western Chalukyas in the tenth century,  coinciding with the defeat of the Western Ganga Dynasty by the Cholas  in Gangavadi, was a setback to Jainism. The growth of Virashaivism in the Chalukya territory and Vaishnava Hinduism in the Hoysala region paralleled a general decreased interest in Jainism, although the succeeding kingdoms continued to be religiously tolerant.Kamath (2001), p112, p132 Two locations of Jain worship in the Hoysala territory continued to be patronaged, Shravanabelagola and Kambadahalli. The decline of Buddhism in South India had begun in the 8th century with the spread of Adi Shankara's Advaita philosophy.A 16th century Buddhist work by Lama Taranatha speaks disparagingly of Shankaracharya as close parallels in some beliefs of Shankaracharya with Buddhist philosophy was not viewed favourably by Buddhist writers (Thapar,  2003, pp 349–350, p397) The only places of Buddhist worship that remained during the Western Chalukya rule were at Dambal and Balligavi.An inscription dated 1095 CE of Vikramaditya VI mentions  grants to a ''Vihara'' of Buddha and Arya-Taradevi (Cousens 1926, p11) There is no mention of religious conflict in the writings and inscriptions of the time which suggest the religious transition was smooth.

Although the origin of the Virashaiva faith has been debated, the movement grew through its association with Basavanna in the twelfth century.It is said five earlier saints Renuka, Daruka, Ekorama, Panditharadhya and Vishwaradhya were the original founders of Virashaivism (Kamath 2001, p152)However it is argued that these saints were from the same period as Basavanna (Sastri 1955, p393) Basavanna and other Virashaiva saints preached of  a faith without a caste system. In his Vachanas (a form of poetry), Basavanna appealed to the masses in simple Kannada and wrote "work is worship" (Kayakave Kailasa). Also known as the Lingayats (worshipers of the ''Linga'', the universal symbol of Shiva), these Virashaivas questioned many of the established norms of society such as the belief in rituals and the theory of rebirth and supported the remarriage of widows and the  marriage of unwed older women.Thapar (2003), p399 This gave more social freedom to women but they were not accepted into the priesthood. Ramanujacharya, the head of the Vaishnava monastery in Srirangam, traveled to the Hoysala territory and preached the way of devotion (bhakti marga). He later wrote ''Sribhashya'', a commentary on Badarayana Brahmasutra, a critique on the Advaita philosophy of Adi Shankara.He criticised Adi Shankara as a "Buddhist in disguise" (Kamath 2001, p151) Ramanujacharya's stay in Melkote resulted in the Hoysala King Vishnuvardhana converting to Vaishnavism, a faith that his successors also followed.

The impact of these religious developments on the culture, literature, and architecture in South India was profound. Important works of metaphysics and poetry based on the teachings of these philosophers were written over the next centuries. Akka Mahadevi, Allama Prabhu, and a host of Basavanna's followers, including Chenna Basava, Prabhudeva, Siddharama, and Kondaguli Kesiraja wrote hundreds of poems called Vachanas in praise of Lord Shiva.Narasimhacharya (1988), p20 The esteemed scholars in the Hoysala court, Harihara and Raghavanka, were Virashaivas.Sastri (1955), p361&ndash;362 This tradition continued into the Vijayanagar empire with such well known scholars as Singiraja, Mallanarya, Lakkana Dandesa and other prolific writers of Virashaiva literature.Kamath (2001), p182Narasimhacharya (1988), p22 The Saluva, Tuluva and Aravidu dynasties of the Vijayanagar empire were followers of Vaishnavism and a Vaishnava temple with an image of Ramanujacharya exists today in the Vitthalapura area of Vijayanagara.Mack (2001), pp35–36 Scholars in the succeeding Mysore Kingdom wrote Vaishnavite works supporting the teachings of Ramanujacharya.Kamath (2001), p152 King Vishnuvardhana built many temples after his conversion from Jainism to Vaishnavism.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f044ee96a5fbe4236ba3e0a147bbd988" name="Basava_statue" sectnum="4.1#1">../img/f044ee96a5fbe4236ba3e0a147bbd988.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>