<document id="4ba89b2fc68d6ab4f37feb53eae919d2-3" name="Western_Chalukya_Empire" cat="14">
<text>
Agriculture was the empire's main source of income through taxes on land and produce. The  majority of the people lived in villages and worked farming the  staple crops of rice, pulses, and cotton in the dry areas and sugarcane in areas having sufficient rainfall, with  areca and betel being the chief cash crops.  The living conditions of the labourers who farmed the land must have been bearable as there are no records of revolts by the landless against wealthy landlords. If  peasants were disgruntled the common practice was to migrate in large numbers out of the jurisdiction of the ruler who was mistreating them, thereby depriving him of revenue from their labor.Thapar (2002), p373 

Taxes were levied on mining and forest products, and additional income was raised through tolls for the use of transportation facilities. The state also collected fees from customs, professional licenses, and judicial fines.Thapar (2002), p378 Records show horses and salt were taxed as well as commodities  (gold, textiles, perfumes) and agricultural produce  (black pepper, paddy, spices, betel leaves, palm leaves, coconuts and sugar). Land tax assessment was based on frequent surveys evaluating the quality of land and the type of produce. Chalukya records specifically mention black soil and red soil lands in addition to wetland, dry land and wasteland in determining taxation rates.Sastri (1955), p298

Key figures mentioned in inscriptions from rural areas were the Gavundas (officials) or Goudas.  The Gavundas belonged to two levels of economic strata, the ''Praja Gavunda'' (people's Gavunda) and the ''Prabhu Gavunda'' (lord of Gavundas). They served the dual purpose of representing  the people before the rulers as well as functioning as state appointees for tax collection and the raising of militias. They are mentioned in inscriptions related to land transactions, irrigation maintenance, village tax collection and  village council  duties.Thapar (2002), p379

The organisation of corporate enterprises became common in  the 11th century.Thapar (2002), p382 Almost all arts and crafts were organised into guilds and work was done on a corporate basis; records do not mention individual artists, sculptors and craftsman. Only in the regions ruled by the  Hoysala did individual sculptors etched their names below their creations.Sastri (1955), p299
Merchants organised themselves into powerful guilds that  transcended political divisions, allowing their operations to be largely unaffected by wars and revolutions. Their only threat  was the possibility of theft from brigands when their ships and caravans traveled to distant lands. Powerful South Indian merchant guilds  included the ''Manigramam'', the ''Nagarattar'' and the ''Anjuvannam''. Local guilds  were called ''nagaram'', while the ''Nanadesis''  were traders from neighbouring kingdoms who perhaps mixed business with pleasure. The wealthiest and most influential and celebrated of all South Indian merchant guilds was the self styled ''Ainnurruvar'', also known as the 500 ''Svamis'' of Ayyavolepura (Brahmins and ''Mahajanas'' of present day Aihole),Sastri (1955), p300Thapar (2002), p384  who conducted extensive land and sea trade and thereby  contributed significantly to the total foreign trade of the empire. It fiercely protected its trade obligations  (''Vira Bananjudharma'' or law of the noble merchants) and its members often recorded their achievements in inscriptions called ''Prasasti''. Five hundred such excavated ''Prasasti'' inscriptions, with their own flag and the bull as their emblem, record their pride in their business. 

Rich traders  contributed significantly to the king's treasury through paying import and export taxes. The edicts of the Aihole ''Svamis'' mention trade ties with foreign kingdoms such as Chera, Pandya, Maleya (Malayasia), Magadh, Kaushal, Saurashtra, Kurumba, Kambhoja (Cambodia), Lata (Gujarat), Parasa (Persia) and Nepal. Travelling both land and sea routes, these merchants traded mostly in precious stones, spices and perfumes, and other specialty items such as camphor. Business flourished in precious stones such as diamonds, lapis lazuli, onyx, topaz, carbuncles and emeralds. Commonly traded spices were cardamom, saffron, and cloves,  while perfumes included the by-products of sandalwood, bdellium, musk, civet and rose. These items were sold either in bulk or hawked on streets by local merchants in towns.Sastri (1955), 301 The Western Chalukyas controlled most of South India's west coast and by the 10th century they had established extensive trade ties with the Tang Empire of China, the empires of Southeast Asia and the Abbasid Caliphate in Bhagdad, and by the 12th century Chinese fleets were frequenting Indian ports. Exports to Song Dynasty China included textiles, spices, medicinal plants, jewels, ivory, rhino horn, ebony and camphor. The same products also reached ports in the west such as Dhofar and Aden. The final destinations for those trading with the west were Persia, Arabia and Egypt.Thapar (2002), 383  The thriving trade center of Siraf, a port on the eastern coast of the Persian Gulf, served an international clientele of merchants  including those from the Chalukya empire who were feasted by wealthy local merchants during business visits.   An indicator of the Indian merchants' importance in Siraf comes from  records describing  dining plates reserved for them.Sastri (1955), p302  In addition to this, Siraf received aloe wood, perfumes, sandalwood and condiments. The most expensive import to South India were Arabian horse shipments, this  trade being monopolised by Arabs and local Brahmin merchants. Thirteenth century traveler Marco Polo recorded that the breeding of horses never succeeded in India  due to differing climatic, soil and grassland conditions.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bc5e2f1e12ccbc13969bb433a861479d" name="Wall_Sculpture_at_Kedaresvara_Temple_in_Balligavi-cropped" sectnum="3#1">../img/bc5e2f1e12ccbc13969bb433a861479d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>