<document id="4ba89b2fc68d6ab4f37feb53eae919d2-2" name="Western_Chalukya_Empire" cat="14">
<text>
The Western Chalukya kingship was hereditary, passing to the king's brother if the king did not have a male heir. The administration was highly decentralised and  feudatory clans such as the Alupas, the Hoysalas, the Kakatiya, the Seuna, the southern Kalachuri and others were allowed to rule their autonomous provinces, paying an annual tribute to the Chalukya emperor.Kamath (2001), p110 Excavated inscriptions record titles such as ''Mahapradhana'' (Chief minister), ''Sandhivigrahika'', and ''Dharmadhikari'' (chief justice). Some positions such as ''Tadeyadandanayaka'' (commander of reserve army) were specialised in function while  all ministerial positions included the role of ''Dandanayaka'' (commander), showing that cabinet members were trained as army commanders as well as in general administrative skills.Kamath (2001), p109

The kingdom was divided into provinces such as ''Banavasi-12000'', ''Nolambavadi-32000'', ''Gangavadi-96000'', each name including the number of villages under its jurisdiction. The large provinces were divided into smaller provinces containing a lesser number of villages, as in ''Belavola-300''. The big provinces were called ''Mandala'' and under them were ''Nadu'' further divided into  ''Kampanas'' (groups of villages) and finally a ''Bada'' (village). A ''Mandala'' was under a member of the royal family, a trusted feudatory or a senior official. Tailapa II himself was in charge of Tardavadi province during the Rashtrakuta rule. Chiefs of ''Mandalas'' were transferable based on political developments. For example, an official named Bammanayya administered Banavasi-12000 under King Somesvara III but was later transferred to Halasige-12000. Women from the royal family also administered ''Nadus'' and ''Kampanas''. Army commanders were titled ''Mahamandaleshwaras'' and those who headed a ''Nadu'' were entitled ''Nadugouvnda''.There was flexibility to the terms used to designate territorial division (Dikshit G.S. in Kamath 2001, p110)

The Western Chalukyas minted punch-marked gold pagodas with Kannada and Nagari legendsCoins of Western Chalukyas with Kannada legends have been found (Kamath 2001, p12) which were large, thin gold coins with several varying punch marks on the obverse side. They usually carried multiple punches of symbols such as a stylised lion, ''Sri'' in Kannada, a spearhead, the king's title, a lotus and others. Jayasimha II used the legend ''Sri Jaya'', Somesvara I issued coins with ''Sri Tre lo ka malla'', Somesvara II used ''Bhuvaneka malla'', Lakshmideva's coin carried ''Sri Lasha'', and Jagadhekamalla II coinage had the legend ''Sri Jagade''. The Alupas, a feudatory, minted coins with the Kannada and ''Nagari'' legend ''Sri Pandya Dhanamjaya''. Lakkundi in Gadag district and Sudi in Dharwad district were the main mints (''Tankhashaley''). Their heaviest gold coin was Gadyanaka weighting 96 grains, Dramma weighted 65 grains, Kalanju 48 grains, Kasu 15 grains, Manjadi 2.5 grains, Akkam 1.25 grains and Pana 9.6 grain.Kamath (2001), p111
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c44f3e2efa068f6df33dfdabf9c69aa5" name="Mallikarjuna_group_of_temples_at_Badami" sectnum="2#1">../img/c44f3e2efa068f6df33dfdabf9c69aa5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>