<document id="4bec6023a71d057082ba2f1ff30bd9db-4" name="Platypus" cat="3">
<text>
The Platypus and other monotremes were very poorly understood and some of the 19th century myths that grew up around them—for example, that the monotremes were "inferior" or quasi-reptilian—still endure. In 1947, William King Gregory theorised that placental mammals and marsupials may have diverged earlier and a subsequent branching divided the monotremes and marsupials, but later research and fossil discoveries have suggested this is incorrect. In fact, modern monotremes are the survivors of an early branching of the mammal tree, and a later branching is thought to have led to the marsupial and placental groups. Molecular clock and fossil dating suggest platypuses split from echidna around 19–48 million years ago.Phillips  MJ, Bennett TH,  Lee MS. (2009). Molecules, morphology, and ecology indicate a recent, amphibious ancestry for echidnas. PNAS. 106:17089–17094.  

The oldest discovered fossil of the modern Platypus dates back to about 100,000 years ago, during the Quaternary period. The extinct monotremes ''Teinolophos'' and ''Steropodon'' were closely related to the modern Platypus. The fossilised ''Steropodon'' was discovered in New South Wales and is composed of an opalised lower jawbone with three molar teeth (whereas the adult contemporary Platypus is toothless). The molar teeth were initially thought to be tribosphenic, which would have supported a variation of Gregory's theory, but later research has suggested that, while they have three cusps, they evolved under a separate process. The fossil is thought to be about 110 million years old, which means that the Platypus-like animal was alive during the Cretaceous period, making it the oldest mammal fossil found in Australia. ''Monotrematum sudamericanum'', another fossil relative of the Platypus, has been found in Argentina, indicating that monotremes were present in the supercontinent of Gondwana when the continents of South America and Australia were joined via Antarctica (up to about 167 million years ago).

Because of the early divergence from the therian mammals and the low numbers of extant monotreme species, it is a frequent subject of research in evolutionary biology. In 2004, researchers at the Australian National University discovered the Platypus has ten sex chromosomes, compared with two (XY) in most other mammals (for instance, a male Platypus is always XYXYXYXYXY). Although given the XY designation of mammals, the sex chromosomes of the Platypus are more similar to the ZZ/ZW sex chromosomes found in birds. The platypus genome also has both reptilian and mammalian genes associated with egg fertilisation. Lacking the mammalian sex-determining gene SRY, the process of sex determination in the Platypus remains unknown. A draft version of the platypus genome sequence was published in ''Nature'' on 8 May 2008, revealing both reptilian and mammalian elements, as well as two genes found previously only in birds, amphibians and fish. More than 80% of the Platypus' genes are common to the other mammals whose genomes have been sequenced.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bfb69e3b0ab05597fd5d70ee3844b6d8" name="Platypus_skeleton_Pengo" sectnum="4#1">../img/bfb69e3b0ab05597fd5d70ee3844b6d8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>