<document id="4bec6023a71d057082ba2f1ff30bd9db-5" name="Platypus" cat="3">
<text>
Except for its loss from the state of South Australia, the Platypus occupies the same general distribution as it did prior to European settlement of Australia. However, local changes and fragmentation of distribution due to human modification of its habitat are documented. Its current and historical abundance, however, is less well-known and it has probably declined in numbers, although still being considered as common over most of its current range. The species was extensively hunted for its fur until the early years of the 20th century and, although protected throughout Australia in 1905, up until about 1950 it was still at risk of drowning in the nets of inland fisheries. The Platypus does not appear to be in immediate danger of extinction thanks to conservation measures, but it could be impacted by habitat disruption caused by dams, irrigation, pollution, netting and trapping. The IUCN lists the Platypus on its Red List as Least Concern.



Platypuses generally suffer from few diseases in the wild; however, there is widespread public concern in Tasmania about the potential impacts of a disease caused by the fungus ''Mucor amphibiorum''. The disease (termed ''Mucormycosis'') only affects Tasmanian platypuses, and has not been observed in platypuses in mainland Australia. Affected platypuses can develop ugly skin lesions or ulcers on various parts of the body, including their backs, tails and legs. Mucormycosis can kill platypuses, death arising from secondary infection and by affecting the animals' ability to maintain body temperature and forage efficiency. The Biodiversity Conservation Branch at the Department of Primary Industries and Water are collaborating with NRM north and University of Tasmania researchers to determine the impacts of the disease on Tasmanian Platypus, as well as the mechanism of transmission and current spread of the disease. Until recently, the introduced Red Fox (''Vulpes vulpes'') was confined to mainland Australia, but growing evidence now indicates that it is present in low numbers in Tasmania.http://www.dpiw.tas.gov.au/inter.nsf/ThemeNodes/LBUN-5K438G?open.

Much of the world was introduced to the Platypus in 1939 when ''National Geographic Magazine'' published an article on the Platypus and the efforts to study and raise it in captivity. This is a difficult task, and only a few young have been successfully raised since—notably at Healesville Sanctuary in Victoria. The leading figure in these efforts was David Fleay, who established a platypussary—a simulated stream in a tank—at the Healesville Sanctuary and had a successful breeding in 1943. In 1972, he found a dead baby of about 50 days old, which had presumably been born in captivity, at his wildlife park at Burleigh Heads on the Gold Coast, Queensland. Healesville repeated its success in 1998 and again in 2000 with a similar stream tank. Taronga Zoo in Sydney bred twins in 2003, and had another birth in 2006.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9c0b6fe90620e654df73e2fd08747966" name="platypus-plate" sectnum="5#1">../img/9c0b6fe90620e654df73e2fd08747966.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>