<document id="4c0470cfa08c6ca79cbd9b9b4cf5c8cf-7" name="Satyajit_Ray" cat="19">
<text>
Ray created two very popular characters in Bengali children's literature—Feluda, a sleuth, and Professor Shonku, a scientist. He was a prominent writer of science fiction in Bengali or any Indian language for that matter. He also wrote short stories which were published as volumes of 12 stories, always with names playing on the word twelve (for example ''Aker pitthe dui'', or literally "Two on top of one"). Ray's interest in puzzles and puns is reflected in his stories, Feluda often has to solve a puzzle to get to the bottom of a case. The Feluda stories are narrated by Topshe, his cousin, something of a Watson to Feluda's Holmes. The science fictions of Shonku are presented as a diary discovered after the scientist himself had mysteriously disappeared. Ray's short stories give full reign to his interest in the macabre, in suspense and other aspects that he avoided in film, making for an interesting psychological study. Most of his writings have now been translated into English, and are finding a new group of readers.

Most of his screenplays have also been published in Bengali in the literary journal ''Eksan''. Ray wrote his autobiography encompassing his childhood years, ''Jakhan Choto Chilam'' (1982) and essays on film: ''Our Films, Their Films'' (1976), along with ''Bishoy Chalachchitra'' (1976), ''Ekei Bole Shooting'' (1979). During the mid-1990s, Ray's film essays and an anthology of short stories were also published in the West. ''Our Films, Their Films'' is an anthology of film criticism by Ray. The book contains articles and personal journal excerpts. The book is presented in two sections—Ray first discusses Indian film, before turning his attention towards Hollywood and specific international filmmakers (Charlie Chaplin, Akira Kurosawa) and movements like Italian neorealism. His book ''Bishoy Chalachchitra'' was translated in 2006 as ''Speaking of Films'', and contains a compact description of his philosophy of different aspects of the cinema. Ray also wrote a collection of nonsense verse named ''Today Bandha Ghorar Dim'', which includes a translation of Lewis Carroll's "Jabberwocky". He also authored a collection of humorous stories of Mullah Nasiruddin in Bengali.

Satyajit Ray designed four typefaces for roman script named Ray Roman, Ray Bizarre, Daphnis, and Holiday Script, apart from numerous Bengali ones for the Sandesh magazine. Ray Roman and Ray Biazarre won an international competition in 1971. In certain circles of Kolkata, Ray continued to be known as an eminent graphic designer, well into his film career. Ray illustrated all his books and designed covers for them, as well as creating all publicity material for his films. He also designed covers of several books by other authors.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5994ff6692aa5d172d6a172ef1bf2c08" name="Ekerpithedui" sectnum="7#1">../img/5994ff6692aa5d172d6a172ef1bf2c08.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>