<document id="4c0470cfa08c6ca79cbd9b9b4cf5c8cf-9" name="Satyajit_Ray" cat="19">
<text>
Satyajit Ray is a cultural icon in India and in Bengali communities worldwide.  Following his death, the city of Kolkata came to a virtual standstill, as hundreds of thousands of people gathered around his house to pay him their last respects. Satyajit Ray's influence has been widespread and deep in Bengali cinema; a number of Bengali directors including Aparna Sen, Rituparno Ghosh and Gautam Ghose in India, Tareq Masud and Tanvir Mokammel in Bangladesh, and Aneel Ahmad in England, have been influenced by his film craft. Across the spectrum, filmmakers such as Budhdhadeb Dasgupta, Mrinal Sen
 and Adoor Gopalakrishnan have acknowledged his seminal contribution to Indian cinema. Beyond India, filmmakers such as Martin Scorsese,
 James Ivory,
 Abbas Kiarostami, Elia Kazan, François Truffaut, Carlos Saura, Isao Takahata and Danny Boyle have been influenced by his cinematic style, with many others such as Akira Kurosawa praising his work. Ira Sachs's 2005 work ''Forty Shades of Blue'' was a loose remake of ''Charulata'', and in Gregory Nava's 1995 film ''My Family'', the final scene is duplicated from the final scene of ''Apur Sansar''. Similar references to Ray films are found, for example, in recent works such as ''Sacred Evil'',
 the ''Elements trilogy'' of Deepa Mehta and even in films of Jean-Luc Godard.
 According to Michael Sragow of ''The Atlantic Monthly'', the "youthful coming-of-age dramas that have flooded art houses since the mid-fifties owe a tremendous debt to the Apu trilogy".

The character Apu Nahasapeemapetilon in the American animated television series '' The Simpsons'' was named in homage to Ray's popular character from ''The Apu Trilogy''. Ray along with Madhabi Mukherjee, was the first Indian film personality to feature in a foreign stamp (Dominica). Many literary works include references to Ray or his work, including Saul Bellow's ''Herzog'' and J. M. Coetzee's ''Youth''. Salman Rushdie's ''Haroun and the Sea of Stories'' contains fish characters named ''Goopy'' and ''Bagha'', a tribute to Ray's fantasy film. In 1993, UC Santa Cruz established the Satyajit Ray Film and Study collection, and in 1995, the Government of India set up Satyajit Ray Film and Television Institute for studies related to film. In 2007, British Broadcasting Corporation declared that two ''Feluda'' stories would be made into radio programs.
 During the London Film Festival, a regular "Satyajit Ray Award" is given to first-time feature director whose film best captures "the artistry, compassion and humanity of Ray's vision".
Wes Anderson has claimed Ray as an influence on his work; his most recent film, ''The Darjeeling Limited'', set in India, is dedicated to Ray.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="95d9ea2b68f1098748f66ad64f223086" name="Satyajit-ray-oscar-180" sectnum="9#1">../img/95d9ea2b68f1098748f66ad64f223086.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>