<document id="4c1c270666933dbd47ce3ac089c0d63a-4.3" name="Archaeopteryx" cat="3">
<text>
Today, the fossils are usually assigned to a single species ''A. lithographica'', but the taxonomic history is complicated. Dozens of names have been published for the handful of specimens, most of which are simply spelling errors (''lapsus'').  Originally, the name ''A. lithographica'' only referred to the single feather described by von Meyer. In 1960, Swinton proposed that the name ''Archaeopteryx lithographica'' be officially transferred from the feather to the London specimen. The ICZN did suppress the plethora of alternative names initially proposed for the first skeleton specimens, which mainly resulted from the acrimonious dispute between von Meyer and his opponent Johann Andreas Wagner (whose ''Griphosaurus problematicus''—"problematic riddle-lizard"—was a vitriolic sneer at von Meyer's ''Archaeopteryx''). In addition, descriptions of ''Archaeopteryx'' fossils as pterosaurs before their true nature was realized were also suppressed.

 
The relationships of the  specimens are problematic.  Most subsequent specimens have been given their own species at one point or another.  The Berlin specimen has been designated as ''Archaeornis siemensii'', the Eichstätt specimen as ''Jurapteryx recurva'', the Munich specimen as ''Archaeopteryx bavarica'' and the Solnhofen specimen was designated as ''Wellnhoferia grandis''. 

Recently, it has been argued that all the specimens belong to the same species. However, significant differences exist among the specimens. In particular, the Munich, Eichstätt, Solnhofen and Thermopolis specimens differ from the London, Berlin, and Haarlem specimens in being smaller or much larger, having different finger proportions, having more slender snouts, lined with forward-pointing teeth and possible presence of a sternum. These differences are as large as or larger than the differences seen today between adults of different bird species. However, it is also possible that these differences could be explained by different ages of the living birds.

Finally, it is worth noting that the feather, the first specimen of ''Archaeopteryx'' described, does not agree well with the flight-related feathers of ''Archaeopteryx''.  It certainly is a flight feather of a contemporary species, but its size and proportions indicate that it may belong to another, smaller species of feathered theropod, of which only this feather is so far known.  As the feather was the original type specimen, this has created significant nomenclatorial confusion.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="aaeba354857312d8c6e417cf0f77ab24" name="Solnhofen_Specimen" sectnum="4.3#1">../img/aaeba354857312d8c6e417cf0f77ab24.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>