<document id="4c54c163f43d0ac8512df032b3b07bff-8" name="Seattle" cat="11">
<text>
Of the city's population over the age of 25, 52.5 percent (vs. a national average of 24 percent) hold a bachelor's degree or higher, and 91.2 percent (vs. 80 percent nationally) have a high school diploma or equivalent.http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/STTable?_bm=y&-geo_id=16000US5363000&-qr_name=ACS_2007_3YR_G00_S1501&-ds_name=ACS_2007_3YR_G00_ A United States Census Bureau survey showed that Seattle had the highest percentage of college and university graduates of any major U.S. city. The city was listed as the most literate of the country's sixty-nine largest cities in 2005 and 2006 and second most literate in 2007, and tied for most literate again in 2008 in a study conducted by Central Connecticut State University.



Seattle Public Schools desegregated without a court order but continue to struggle to achieve racial balance in a somewhat ethnically divided city (the south part of town having more ethnic minorities than the north). In 2007, Seattle's racial tie-breaking system was struck down by the United States Supreme Court, but the ruling left the door open for desegregation formulae based on other indicators (e.g., income or socioeconomic class).

The public school system is supplemented by a moderate number of private schools: five of the private high schools are Catholic, one is Lutheran, and six are secular.

Seattle is home to one of the United States' most respected public research universities, the University of Washington, as well as its professional and continuing Education unit, University of Washington Educational Outreach. A study by ''Newsweek International'' in 2006 cited UW as the twenty-second best university in the world. Seattle also has a number of smaller private universities including Seattle University and Seattle Pacific University, both founded by religious groups; universities aimed at the working adult, like City University and Antioch University; and a number of arts colleges, such as Cornish College of the Arts and The Art Institute of Seattle. In 2001, ''Time'' magazine selected Seattle Central Community College as community college of the year, stating the school "pushes diverse students to work together in small teams".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="72c1fa4ca973d4baf8899867422b8685" name="Suzzallo_Library_Graduate_Reading_Room" sectnum="8#1">../img/72c1fa4ca973d4baf8899867422b8685.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>