<document id="4c54c163f43d0ac8512df032b3b07bff-1.3" name="Seattle" cat="11">
<text>
This boom was followed by the construction of a park system, designed by the Olmsted brothers' landscaping firm.

The second and most dramatic boom and bust resulted from the Klondike Gold Rush, which ended the depression that had begun with the Panic of 1893; in a short time, Seattle became a major transportation center. On July 14, 1897, the ''S.S. Portland'' docked with its famed "ton of gold", and Seattle became the main transport and supply point for the miners in Alaska and the Yukon. Those working men only found lasting wealth in a few cases, however; it was Seattle's business of clothing the miners and feeding them salmon that panned out in the long run. Everett, Tacoma, Port Townsend, Bremerton, Seattle, and Olympia became competitors for exchange, rather than mother-lodes for extraction, of precious metals. The boom lasted well into the early part of the 20th century and funded many new Seattle companies and products. In 1907, 19-year-old James E. Casey borrowed $100 from a friend and founded the American Messenger Company (later UPS). Other Seattle companies founded during this period include Nordstrom and Eddie Bauer. The Gold Rush era culminated in the Alaska-Yukon-Pacific Exposition of 1909, which is largely responsible for the layout of today's University of Washington campus.

A shipbuilding boom in the early part of the 20th century became massive during World War I, making Seattle somewhat of a company town; the subsequent retrenchment led to the Seattle General Strike of 1919, the first general strike in the country A 1912 city development plan by Virgil Bogue went largely unused. Seattle was mildly prosperous in the 1920s but was particularly hard hit in the Great Depression, experiencing some of the country's harshest labor strife in that era. Violence during the Maritime Strike of 1934 cost Seattle much of its maritime traffic, which was rerouted to the Port of Los Angeles.BOLA Architecture + Planning & Northwest Archaeological Associates, Inc., , Port of Seattle, April 5, 2005, p. 12-13 (which is p. 14-15 of the PDF). Accessed online July 25, 2008.

Seattle was also the home base of impressario Alexander Pantages who, starting in 1902, opened a number of theaters in the city exhibiting vaudeville acts and silent movies. Soon, however, his activities expanded and the thrifty Greek went on and became one of America's greatest theater and movie tycoons. Because of this connection Seattle was for a while something of Americas vaudeville mecca. Though the theaters Pantages built in Seattle were later demolished they are still extant in other cities of the USA.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2b8544857feae7f156fd66499634c309" name="SCL" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/2b8544857feae7f156fd66499634c309.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>