<document id="4c54c163f43d0ac8512df032b3b07bff-4.10" name="Seattle" cat="11">
<text>
Seattle has been a regional center for the performing arts for many years. The century-old Seattle Symphony Orchestra is among the world's most recorded and performs primarily at Benaroya Hall. The Seattle Opera and Pacific Northwest Ballet, which perform at McCaw Hall (opened 2003 on the site of the former Seattle Opera House at Seattle Center), are comparably distinguished, This press release from New York's Metropolitan Opera describes the Seattle Opera as "one of the leading opera companies in the United States… recognized internationally…" with the Opera being particularly known for its performances of the works of Richard Wagner and the PNB School (founded in 1974) ranking as one of the top three ballet training institutions in the United States. The Seattle Youth Symphony Orchestras (SYSO) is the largest symphonic youth organization in the United States. The city also boasts lauded summer and winter chamber music festivals organized by the Seattle Chamber Music Society.

The 5th Avenue Theatre, built in 1926, stages Broadway-style musical shows featuring both local talent and international stars.Examples of local talent are Billy Joe Huels (lead singer of the Dusty 45s starring in ''Buddy – The Buddy Holly Story'' and Sarah Rudinoff in ''Wonderful Town''. National-level stars include Stephen Lynch in ''The Wedding Singer'', which went on to Broadway and Cathy Rigby in ''Peter Pan''
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
 Seattle has "around 100" theatrical production companies "around 100 theater companies ... Twenty-eight have some sort of Actors' Equity contract ..." Lists 145 theatrical production companies in the Seattle metropolitan area, the majority of them in the city. The list is certainly not complete. and over two dozen live theatre venues, many of them associated with fringe theatre;(1)  This lists 23 distinct venues in Seattle hosting live theater (in the narrow sense) that week; it also lists 7 other venues hosting burlesque or cabaret, and three hosting improv. In any given week, some theaters are "dark".
(2)  This article mentions five fringe theater groups that were new at that time, each with a venue. Seattle is probably second only to New York for number of equity theaters (28 Seattle theater companies have some sort of Actors' Equity contract).
In addition, the 900-seat Romanesque Revival Town Hall on First Hill hosts numerous cultural events, especially lectures and recitals. 


Seattle is considered the home of grunge music because it was home to artists such as Nirvana, Pearl Jam, Soundgarden, Alice in Chains, and Mudhoney all of whom reached vast audiences in the early 1990s.  The city is also home to such varied musicians as avant-garde jazz musicians Bill Frisell and Wayne Horvitz, rapper Sir Mix-a-Lot, smooth jazz saxophonist Kenny G, Heart, heavy metal bands Queensrÿche, Nevermore and Sunn O))), as well as such poppier rock bands as Harvey Danger, Goodness, and The Presidents of the United States of America. Such musicians as Jimi Hendrix, Kurt Cobain, Duff McKagan, Nikki Sixx, and Quincy Jones spent their formative years in Seattle. 

Since the grunge era, the area has hosted a diverse and influential alternative music scene. The Seattle record label Sub Pop—the first to sign Nirvana and Soundgarden—has signed such non-grunge bands as Band of Horses, Modest Mouse, Murder City Devils, Sunny Day Real Estate, Death Cab for Cutie, The Postal Service and Flight of the Conchords.

Earlier Seattle-based popular music acts include the collegiate folk group The Brothers Four; The Wailers, a 1960s garage band; The Ventures, an instrumental rock band; pop Young Fresh Fellows and The Posies; pop-punk The Fastbacks; and the outright punk of The Fartz (later 10 Minute Warning), The Gits, and 7 Year Bitch.Seattle_Music, the best nightclub Seattle ever had was named Pier 70 Chowder House with the best disk jocky named David Prince

Seattle annually sends a team of spoken word slammers to the National Poetry Slam and considers itself home of some of the most talented performance poets in the world: Buddy Wakefield, two-time Individual World Poetry Slam Champ; Anis Mojgani, two-time National Poetry Slam Champ; and Danny Sherrard, 2007 National Poetry Slam Champ and 2008 Individual World Poetry Slam Champ. Seattle also hosted the 2001 national Poetry Slam Tournament. The Seattle Poetry Festival is a biennial poetry festival that (launched first as the Poetry Circus in 1997) has featured local, regional, national, and international names in poetry.

The city also has movie houses showing both Hollywood productions and works by independent filmmakers. Among these, the Seattle Cinerama stands out as one of only three movie theaters in the world still capable of showing three-panel Cinerama films.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="93be5c40c58d43a84b586fd6aebdfc10" name="Seattle_-_The_Moore_Theater_entrance_01" sectnum="4.10#1">../img/93be5c40c58d43a84b586fd6aebdfc10.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>