<document id="4c9ae308e2c96cf3d902ec8bd2aacfdc-3" name="History_of_Sheffield" cat="14">
<text>
Following the death of William de Lovetot, the manor of Hallamshire passed to his son Richard de Lovetot and then his son William de Lovetot before being passed by marriage to Gerard de Furnival in about 1204.Hunter, ''Hallamshire'', p. 26 The de Furnivals held the manor for the next 180 years.Hunter, ''Hallamshire'', p. 31 The fourth Furnival lord, Thomas de Furnival, supported Simon de Montfort in the Second Barons' War. As a result of this, in 1266 a party of barons, led by John de Eyvill, marching from north Lincolnshire to Derbyshire passed through Sheffield and destroyed the town, burning the church and castle. A new stone castle was constructed over the next four years and a new church was consecrated by William II Wickwane the Archbishop of York around 1280. In 1295 Thomas de Furnival's son (also Thomas) was the first lord of Hallamshire to be called to Parliament, thus taking the title Lord Furnivall. On 12 November 1296 Edward I granted a charter for a market to be held in Sheffield on Tuesday each week. This was followed on 10 August 1297 by a charter from Lord Furnival establishing Sheffield as a free borough.Hunter, ''Hallamshire'', pp. 38–39.Charter to the Town of Sheffield, 10 August 1297 The Sheffield Town Trust was established in the Charter to the Town of Sheffield, granted in 1297.  De Furnival, granted land to the freeholders of Sheffield in return for an annual payment, and a Common Burgery administrated them.  The Burgery originally consisted of public meetings of all the freeholders,Clyde Binfield et al., ''The History of the City of Sheffield 1843-1993: Volume I: Politics'' who elected a Town Collector.Sidney and Beatrice Webb, ''The Manor and the Borough'' Two more generations of Furnivals held Sheffield before it passed by marriage to Sir Thomas Nevil and then, in 1406, to John Talbot, the first Earl of Shrewsbury.


In 1430 the 1280 Sheffield parish church building was pulled down and replaced. Parts of this new church still stand today and it is now Sheffield city centre's oldest surviving building, forming the core of Sheffield Cathedral.Harman & Minnis, ''Sheffield'', pp.45–56 Other notable surviving buildings from this period include the Old Queen's Head pub in Pond Hill, which dates from around 1480, with its timber frame still intact, Bishops' House and Broom Hall, both built around 1500,Harman & Minnis, ''Sheffield'', pp. 4–7 and the Church of St. Mary, Ecclesfield.Simon Jenkins, England's Thousand Best Churches

The fourth Earl of Shrewsbury, George Talbot took up residence in Sheffield, building the Manor Lodge outside the town in about 1510 and adding a chapel to the Parish Church c1520 to hold the family vault.  Memorials to the fourth and sixth Earls of Shrewsbury can still be seen in the church.

In 1569 George Talbot, the sixth Earl of Shrewsbury, was given charge of Mary Queen of Scots. Mary was regarded as a threat by Elizabeth I, and had been held captive since her arrival in England in 1568. Talbot brought Mary to Sheffield in 1570, and she spent most of the next 14 years imprisoned in Sheffield Castle and its dependent buildings. The castle park extended beyond the present Manor Lane, where the remains of Manor Lodge are to be found. Beside them is the Turret House, an Elizabethan building, which may have been built to accommodate the captive queen. A room, believed to have been the queen's, has an elaborate plaster ceiling and overmantle, with heraldic decorations.

During the English Civil War, Sheffield changed hands several times, finally falling to the Parliamentarians, who demolished the Castle in 1648.

The Industrial Revolution brought large-scale steel making to Sheffield in the 18th century. Much of the mediaeval town was gradually replaced by a mix of Georgian and Victorian buildings.  Large areas of Sheffield's city centre have been rebuilt in recent years, but among the modern buildings, some old buildings have been retained.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9778097b367e63b5ba3e5c55445f4404" name="BishopsHouse01" sectnum="3#1">../img/9778097b367e63b5ba3e5c55445f4404.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>