<document id="4cb8d1c251d3436a4abbf1df9d300bde-3" name="2007_ACC_Championship_Game" cat="26">
<text>
The 2007 ACC Championship Game kicked off at 13:10 EST in Jacksonville, Florida. ESPN.com, December 1, 2007. Accessed December 10, 2007. At kickoff, the weather was partly cloudy, with winds from the northeast at . The air temperature was . (PDF). The Atlantic Coast Conference, December 1, 2007. Accessed December 10, 2007. The official attendance estimate was 53,212, but by most accounts the actual attendance was far lower. David Teel, The Daily Press, December 8, 2007. Accessed December 11, 2007. Virginia Tech fans made up most of the crowd, and fewer than 5,000 Boston College fans were present at the game. Mark Schlabach, ESPN.com, December 6, 2007. Accessed December 9, 2007. The Associated Press, December 1, 2007. Accessed December 10, 2007. The game was broadcast on ABC and netted a television rating of 4.1, placing it behind the SEC Championship Game and the Big 12 Championship Game, which earned ratings of 5.9 and 6.6, respectively. Andrew Krukowski, TVWeek.com. Accessed December 13, 2007.

The Marching Virginians, Virginia Tech's marching band, and the "Screaming Eagles", the Boston College Marching Band, played the national anthem before the game.See image. The pre-game coin toss involved two members of the Wounded Warrior Project, a program that assists the physical rehabilitation of wounded American combat veterans returning to the United States from fighting overseas. One soldier from Virginia and another from Massachusetts were chosen to throw the ceremonial coin that would determine the game's starting possession. The Atlantic Coast Conference, December 1, 2007. Accessed December 10, 2007. Supervising the coin toss was referee Jack Childress, who had also officiated the inaugural ACC Championship Game.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="002936036f27ce100608bfedda1042ac" name="07ACCCG_National_Anthem_Flag" sectnum="3#1">../img/002936036f27ce100608bfedda1042ac.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>