<document id="4cb8d1c251d3436a4abbf1df9d300bde-2.1" name="2007_ACC_Championship_Game" cat="26">
<text>
Following the 2006 ACC Championship Game, the Gator Bowl Association, which administered the ACC Championship Game during its first two years of existence, was awarded a one-year extension to its two-year contract to host the game.Frenette, Gene. "ACC Game staying, at least through '07". ''Jacksonville Times-Union'', February 7, 2007. Accessed February 10, 2008. The 2006 game suffered from poor attendance, resulting in over $1 million in losses for the Gator Bowl Association. In the off-season, the Gator Bowl Association declared that if sales did not improve for the 2007 ACC Championship game, the game's Jacksonville future would be in jeopardy. Gene Frenette, ''Jacksonville Times-Union'', December 1, 2007. Accessed December 10, 2007. Attendance for the 2006 game was low due to high travel costs stemming from Jacksonville's distance from the participating schools, and the 2007 participants—Boston College and Virginia Tech—faced the same problem.David Teel, "ACC Championship Might Move". ''The Daily Press'', Hampton Roads, Virginia. November 29, 2007. Accessed February 10, 2008. 

With Jacksonville's future as host in doubt, representatives from Charlotte, North Carolina, Tampa, Florida, and Jacksonville visited the ACC offices to lobby to host the 2008 game. Brian Landman, St. Petersburg Times, November 13, 2007. Accessed December 10, 2007. Orlando, Florida, which had been an early contender to host the 2008 game, was eliminated from consideration before the meetings took place. Robbi Pickeral, ACC Now, ''The News & Observer'', July 24, 2007. Accessed December 10, 2007. As kickoff drew closer, the Gator Bowl Association expressed displeasure with the poor ticket sales, saying that nearly 20,000 tickets remained unsold as of the week of the game and that if it was not a sellout, the game would likely not remain in Jacksonville.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3e1531c1f85abd739cce8e78761707b5" name="Cointoss" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/3e1531c1f85abd739cce8e78761707b5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>