<document id="4cda707678ec32361cca5881e085f7ca-2.1" name="Miranda_Otto" cat="19">
<text>
Otto's first post-graduation film role in 1991, as Nell Tiscowitz in ''The Girl Who Came Late'', was her breakthrough role, which brought her to the attention of the Australian film industry and the general public. In the film, directed by Kathy Mueller, she starred as a young woman who could communicate with horses. Her appearance garnered Otto her first Australian Film Institute nomination for "Best Actress" the following year.

Otto's next role was in the film ''The Last Days of Chez Nous'', which portrayed the complex relationships between the members of an Australian family. The film earned Otto her second Australian Film Institute nomination, this time for "Best Supporting Actress". In 1993, Otto co-starred with Noah Taylor in the sexually provocative comedy film ''The Nostradamus Kid'', which was based on the memories of author Bob Ellis during the 1960s. Otto was drawn to the film because she was "fascinated by the period and the people who came out of it."Bass, Matthew. . ''Cinema Papers''. October 1997. Retrieved 7 April 2007. A small role in the independent film ''Sex Is a Four Letter Word'' followed in 1995.


In 1995, Otto began to doubt her career choice as she failed to get the parts for which she auditioned. She fled to her home in Newcastle for almost a year, during which she painted her mother's house. In 1996, director Shirley Barrett cast Otto as a shy waitress in the film ''Love Serenade''. She played Dimity Hurley, a lonely young woman, who competes with her older sister Vicki-Ann for the attention of a famous DJ from Brisbane. The film was met with positive reviews and Otto's performance was praised: Steve Rhodes of Internet Reviews felt that Otto's performance was "the most interesting and funniest" of the film.Rhodes, Steve (1996), , Internet Reviews. Retrieved 7 April 2007.

Otto's first starring roles were in the 1997 films ''The Well'' and ''Doing Time for Patsy Cline''. When Otto received the film script for ''The Well'', she refused to read it, fearing that she would not get the part. Otto believed that she could not convincingly play the role of Katherine, who is supposed to be eighteen, as she was thirty years old at the time. The film, directed by Samantha Lang, starred Otto as a teenager involved in a claustrophobic relationship with a lonely older woman. ''The Well'' received mixed reviews; critic Paul Fisher wrote that Otto's performance was not "convincing" as she was  "playing another repetitious character about whom little is revealed", while Louise Keller stated that Otto had delivered "her best screen performance yet."Fisher, Paul and Louise Keller. . UrbanCinefile.com.au. 1997. Retrieved 7 April 2007. Otto earned her third Australian Film Institute nomination for the film. Later that year, she co-starred with Richard Roxburgh in the drama ''Doing Time for Patsy Cline''. The low-budget Australian film required Otto to perform country music standards and also received mixed reviews from film critics.. ''Rotten Tomatoes''. Retrieved 29 May 2007.

Soon after the release of ''The Well'' and ''Doing Time for Patsy Cline'', magazines and other media outlets were eager to profile the actress. In 1997, Otto began dating her ''Doing Time for Patsy Cline'' co-star Richard Roxburgh. Her involvement with Roxburgh made her a regular subject of Australian tabloid magazines and media at the time, a role to which she was unaccustomed.Scobie, Claire. . ''The Age''. 26 June 2005. Retrieved 8 April 2007.

Otto's next project was the romantic comedy ''Dead Letter Office'' (1998). The film was Otto's first with her father, Barry, who makes a brief appearance. ''In the Winter Dark'', directed by James Bogle, followed later that year. Otto played Ronnie, a pregnant woman recently abandoned by her boyfriend. The film was a critical success in Australia, and Otto was nominated for her fourth Australian Film Institute Award. A small role in the big-budget World War II film ''The Thin Red Line'', starring George Clooney and Sean Penn, led to further film roles outside of Australia,. Yahoo! Movies. Retrieved 9 April 2007. such as in Italy, where she co-starred as Ruth in the low-budget Italian film ''La volpe a tre zampe'' (''"The Three-legged Wolf"''), produced in 2001 and broadcasted for the first time on Italian television in March 2009.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e1b1a11f9fdc7ac6619caaff343185ae" name="Loveserenade-MirandaOtto" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/e1b1a11f9fdc7ac6619caaff343185ae.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>