<document id="4cda707678ec32361cca5881e085f7ca-2.2" name="Miranda_Otto" cat="19">
<text>
Otto's first Hollywood role was opposite Harrison Ford and Michelle Pfeiffer in the suspense thriller ''What Lies Beneath'' in 2000. She played Mary Feur, a mysterious next-door neighbor. The film was met with mixed reviews, but was an international success, grossing US $291 million.. Box Office Mojo. Retrieved 10 April 2007. In 2001, Otto was cast as a naturalist in the comedy ''Human Nature''. Writer Charlie Kaufman, impressed by her audition two years earlier for his film ''Being John Malkovich'', arranged for Otto to audition and meet with the film's director Michel Gondry.Landry, B. Jude (April 2002), . ''Venice: L.A.'s Arts and Entertainment Magazine''. Retrieved 11 April 2007. ''Human Nature'' was both a commercial and critical disappointment., Box Office Mojo. Retrieved 29 May 2007. Critic Jeffrey M. Anderson criticized Otto's French accent and wrote that she "doesn't seem to mesh with what's going on around her".Anderson, Jeffrey M. (April 2002), . CombustibleCelluloid.com. Retrieved 11 April 2007. That same year, she also appeared in the BBC adaptation of Anthony Trollope's ''The Way We Live Now'', as a strong-willed American Southerner determined to manipulate Cillian Murphy into marrying her.



In 1999, Otto was cast as Éowyn, a shieldmaiden of Rohan, in ''The Lord of the Rings'' film trilogy. Director Peter Jackson cast her immediately after viewing the audition video she had filmed in Australia.Nathan, Ian (January 2003), , ''Empire Mahazine''. Retrieved 11 April 2007. For the role, Otto spent six weeks learning stunt choreography and horseback riding.. LordOfTheRings.net. November 2003. Retrieved 11 April 2007. Otto's character was introduced in the trilogy's second film ''The Lord of the Rings: The Two Towers'' in 2002 and appeared in the third film, ''The Lord of the Rings: The Return of the King'', the following year. ''The Lord of the Rings'' trilogy was a critical and financial success, and the third film won the Academy Award for Best Picture in 2004.. BBC. 4 March 2004. Retrieved 29 May 2007. Otto's performance earned her an Academy of Science Fiction, Fantasy & Horror Films nomination for Best Supporting Actress.. IMDB.com. Retrieved 29 May 2007.

Otto's next project was the Australian television miniseries ''Through My Eyes: The Lindy Chamberlain Story'' (2004). The film is a drama that portrays the story of Lindy Chamberlain; in 1982 she was convicted of killing her baby daughter, Azaria, in one of Australia's most publicized murder trials. Otto was cast as Chamberlain after her husband, Peter O'Brien, had been cast as prosecutor Ian Barker. She was drawn to the role because it provided her with the "prospect of exploring an unconventional character."Enker, Debi. . ''The Age''. 18 November 2004. 12 April 2007. At the 2005 Logie Awards, Otto won "Most Outstanding Actress in a Drama Series" for her role.

Director Steven Spielberg, impressed by Otto's performance in ''The Lord of the Rings'', called her to ask if she would play opposite Tom Cruise in the big-budget science fiction film ''War of the Worlds'' (2005).  Otto, pregnant at the time, believed she would have to turn down the role, but the script was reworked to accommodate her. After the birth of her daughter in 2005, Otto took a rest from films to concentrate on motherhood and theatre roles in Australia.

In 2007, Otto starred as Cricket Stewart, the wife of a successful director, in the television miniseries ''The Starter Wife''.. USA Network. Retrieved 12 April 2007. That same year, she was cast in the American television series ''Cashmere Mafia''. In the series she plays Juliet Draper, a successful female executive who must rely on her friends to juggle the demands of a career and family in New York City.Andreeva, Nellie. . ''The Hollywood Reporter''. 9 January 2007. Retrieved 12 April 2007. Otto chose to star in the series because "American television at the moment is so interesting and, particularly, the characters for women are so fantastic" and she "liked the idea of having a character over a long period of time and developing it."Amatangelo, Amy. . ''Boston Herald''. 12 January 2008. Retrieved 20 January 2008. The series was cancelled in May 2008.. TVSeriesFinale.com. 12 May 2008. Retrieved 22 October 2009.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="09aa0a6982b94c035332472d479145ef" name="LOTRTT1" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/09aa0a6982b94c035332472d479145ef.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>