<document id="4d370bdadc7ebbf7b49c7075a7b3fcba-2.2" name="Love._Angel._Music._Baby." cat="20">
<text>
"What You Waiting For?", one of the first songs written for ''L.A.M.B.'', was chosen as the lead single as an "explanation for doing the record". The song discusses Stefani's fears of beginning a solo career, and an accompanying music video was made, in which Stefani regains her confidence after an experience inspired by Lewis Carroll's ''Alice's Adventures in Wonderland'' and ''Through the Looking-Glass''.Vineyard, Jennifer. . MTV News. November 10, 2004. Retrieved February 27, 2007. The song received positive reviews, noted as "one of the album's undeniable highs". Its single was successful, reaching the top ten in most countries.. αCharts.us. Retrieved July 27, 2007. The second single, "Rich Girl" charted equally well.. αCharts.us. Retrieved July 27, 2007. The song, a ragga adaptation of the ''Fiddler on the Roof'' song "If I Were a Rich Man", features rapper Eve, with whom Stefani had worked when featured on Eve's 2001 single "Let Me Blow Ya Mind".



"Hollaback Girl", the third track, became the album's best-selling and most popular single.. Allmusic. Retrieved July 27, 2007. It was written as a response to a derogatory comment that grunge musician Courtney Love made, referring to Stefani as a cheerleader,Rubenstein, Atoosa. "Courtney Love speaks about Gwen Stefani". ''Seventeen'' (August 2004): pg. 19. and its lyrics and music video feature a cheerleading theme. It received mixed reviews from music critics, several of whom criticized its repetitive use of the word ''shit'', but it became the first U.S. digital download to sell one million copies.Hiatt, Brian. . ''Rolling Stone''. January 19, 2006. Retrieved February 27, 2007. The fourth track "Cool" was well-received by critics,. ''Blender''. January/February 2006. Retrieved March 21, 2007. but its single charted moderately compared to its predecessors. The song chronicles Stefani's previous relationship with Tony Kanal, and in its music video, the relationship between Stefani and Kanal, played by Daniel González, is illustrated through a series of flashbacks. "Bubble Pop Electric", the fifth track, is an electro song featuring André 3000's alias Johnny Vulture. It tells of the two having sex at a drive-in movie, and it was generally well-received by critics, who drew comparisons to ''Grease'' and ''Grease 2''.McCroy, Winnie. . ''The Villager''. January 5–11, 2005: Volume 74, Number 35. Retrieved March 22, 2007.Linden, Amy. . ''The Village Voice''. December 13, 2004. Retrieved March 22, 2007.



"Luxurious", whose single features rapper Slim Thug, compares riches to love.Moss, Corey. . MTV News. November 1, 2005. Retrieved February 27, 2007. The song received mixed reviews from critics and was less successful than the other singles. The seventh track, "Harajuku Girls", is a pop song produced by Jimmy Jam and Terry Lewis. The song was panned by critics who found the track "bizarrely" and "weirdly homoerotic" and "teeth-gnashingly cutesy". The sixth single "Crash" was not originally planned as a single since Stefani was preparing to release ''The Sweet Escape''. While on tour, Stefani discovered that she was pregnant, so a live video accompanied the single,. MTV News. February 28, 2006. Retrieved February 27, 2007. which sold poorly and was unable to reach the top forty in any country.. αCharts.us. Retrieved July 27, 2007. "The Real Thing", the ninth track, is a synthpop collaboration between Stefani, Perry, Wendy and Lisa, and members of New Order. It received mixed reviews: ''Pitchfork'' disapproved of it, commenting, "anyone remotely involved ... should find a stray dog and let it bite him", while About.com called it "the album's finest moment".. About.com. November 23, 2004. Retrieved December 9, 2007.

"Serious", the tenth track, is another synthpop song, similar to Madonna's work during the early 1980s. A music video was produced for the song,. ''Spin''. October 16, 2006. Retrieved March 21, 2007. but no single or video were officially released. "Danger Zone", an electro/rock song, was well-received as one of the more well-crafted tracks similar to her work with No Doubt. In 2004, Stefani found out that her husband Gavin Rossdale had an illegitimate daughter, and the song was widely interpreted to be about the incident; however, it had been written before the discovery. The closing track, "Long Way to Go", is an outtake from André 3000's ''The Love Below'' (2003).Smirke, Richard. . PlayLouder. November 23, 2004. Retrieved March 22, 2007. The song discusses interracial dating and was criticized for its use of a sample of Martin Luther King's "I Have a Dream" speech.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a562118e99e9c01032b81d26c941fdd5" name="GwenStefaniTheRealThing" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/a562118e99e9c01032b81d26c941fdd5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>