<document id="4d370bdadc7ebbf7b49c7075a7b3fcba-2.1" name="Love._Angel._Music._Baby." cat="20">
<text>
''Love. Angel. Music. Baby.'' takes influence from a variety of 1980s genres to the extent that one reviewer commented, "The only significant '80s radio style skipped is the ska punk revival that No Doubt rode to success".Smith, RJ. . ''Blender''. Retrieved February 27, 2007. The album is primarily pop, with the synthesizers characteristic of synthpop, most popular from the late 1970s through the mid 1980s.Cinquemani, Sal. . ''Slant''. 2004. Retrieved February 27, 2007. 

New Wave, present in some of No Doubt's later work, continues into ''Love. Angel. Music. Baby.'', drawing comparisons to The Go-Go's and Cyndi Lauper.Damas, Jason. . PopMatters. November 29, 2004. Retrieved February 26, 2007. Stefani cited Club Nouveau, Depeche Mode, Lisa Lisa, Prince, New Order, The Cure, and early Madonna as major influences for the album.Mar, Alex and Halperin, Shirley. . ''Rolling Stone''. October 1, 2004. Retrieved March 20, 2007. To a lesser degree, the album draws from pop genres such as bubblegum pop, electro pop, and dance punk.Sheffield, Rob. . ''Rolling Stone''. December 9, 2004. Retrieved February 27, 2007.

Like pop albums of the 1980s, ''L.A.M.B.'' focuses primarily on money, with songs such as "Rich Girl" and "Luxurious" featuring descriptions of riches and wealth.Browne, David.  ''Entertainment Weekly''. November 23, 2004. Retrieved January 25, 2007. The album contains several references to Stefani's clothing line, L.A.M.B., and alludes to contemporary fashion designers such as John Galliano, Rei Kawakubo, and Vivienne Westwood.Soghomonian, Talia. . OMH. January 2005. Retrieved March 18, 2007. Stefani also released a series of dolls named the "Love. Angel. Music. Baby. Fashion Dolls", designed after the costumes from her tour.Associated Press. . MSNBC. September 6, 2006. Retrieved March 6, 2007. Although Stefani intended for the album to be a light dance record, she stated that "no matter what you do, things just come out."Vineyard, Jennifer. . MTV News. June 21, 2005. Retrieved March 21, 2007. The album's opening track "What You Waiting For?" discusses her desire to be a mother and in 2006, she and her husband, Bush singer Gavin Rossdale, had a son named Kingston Rossdale.Salmon, Chris. . ''The Guardian''. March 2, 2007. Retrieved March 21, 2007. The fourth track "Cool" discusses Stefani's friendship with Kanal after he ended a romantic relationship with her in 1995.. MuchMusic. July 19, 2005. Retrieved March 21, 2007.

''Love. Angel. Music. Baby.'' introduced the Harajuku Girls, an entourage of four Japanese women whom Stefani referred to as a figment of her imagination. The Harajuku Girls are discussed in several of the songs, including one named after and entirely dedicated to them. They appear in most of the music videos produced for the album and those for Stefani's second album ''The Sweet Escape'' (2006). ''L.A.M.B.'' includes various styles of music. Songs are influenced by electro beats designed for club play.Erlewine, Stephen Thomas. . Allmusic. Retrieved February 25, 2007. Producers Dallas Austin and Tony Kanal incorporated R&B into the song "Luxurious" which contains a sample of the Isley Brothers' 1983 slow jam single "Between the Sheets". Jimmy Jam and Terry Lewis, incorporate new jack swing, a fusion genre of R&B that the pair had developed and popularized during the mid 1980s.Merwin, Charles. . ''Stylus''. November 24, 2004. Retrieved March 22, 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e01bd9b3b561cc51db3147c8b8956a47" name="GwenStefaniHarajukuGirls2" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/e01bd9b3b561cc51db3147c8b8956a47.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>