<document id="4d370bdadc7ebbf7b49c7075a7b3fcba-4" name="Love._Angel._Music._Baby." cat="20">
<text>
The album debuted on the U.S. ''Billboard'' 200 at number seven, selling 309,000 copies.Whitmire, Margo. . ''Billboard''. December 1, 2004. Retrieved February 27, 2007. Following the April 2005 release of "Hollaback Girl", ''Love. Angel. Music. Baby.'' re-entered the top fifteen for twenty-one weeks and reached a peak at number five in June 2005.. αCharts.us. Retrieved July 14, 2007. The Recording Industry Association of America certified the album triple platinum that December,Hooper, Joseph. ''ELLE''. . Retrieved February 27, 2007. and it went on to sell 4 million copies.Cohen, Jonathan. . ''Billboard''. October 5, 2006. Retrieved March 30, 2007. At the ''Billboard'' Music Awards, Stefani won the Digital Song of the Year award for "Hollaback Girl" and the New Artist of the Year Award, and she performed "Luxurious" with Slim Thug at the event.Jeckell, Barry A. . ''Billboard''. December 7, 2005. Retrieved February 27, 2007. At the 2005 Grammy Awards, Stefani received a nomination for Best Female Pop Vocal Performance for "What You Waiting For?". ''The Hollywood Reporter''. Retrieved February 27, 2007. and performed "Rich Girl" with Eve.Cohen, Jonathan. . ''Billboard''. February 14, 2005. Retrieved February 27, 2007. At the next year's awards, Stefani received five nominations for Record of the Year, Album of the Year, Best Female Pop Vocal Performance, Best Pop Vocal Album, and Best Rap/Sung Collaboration.. American Society of Composers, Authors, and Publishers. Retrieved February 27, 2007.

The album had similar success in Europe. ''L.A.M.B.'' reached number four on the UK Albums Chart in May 2005, on which it remained for over a year. The British Phonographic Industry certified the album triple platinum on September 16, 2005, for shipping over 900,000 copies.. British Phonographic Industry. Retrieved April 11, 2007. At the end of 2005, the album charted as the 20th highest selling album of the year in the UK. The album reached the top ten in Finland, Ireland, Norway, and Sweden and the top twenty in Austria, Belgium, France Germany, the Netherlands, and Switzerland. The International Federation of the Phonographic Industry certified it platinum at the May 2005 Platinum Europe Awards.. International Federation of the Phonographic Industry. June 8, 2005. Retrieved March 22, 2007.

In Australia, the album topped the ARIA Albums Chart for two consecutive weeks in February 2005 and remained on the chart for fifty-one weeks. It ended 2005 as the fourth best-selling album,. Australian Recording Industry Association. Retrieved February 27, 2007. and was certified quadruple platinum for shipping 280,000 copies.. Australian Recording Industry Association. Retrieved February 27, 2007. In Canada, ''Love. Angel. Music. Baby.'' peaked at number three for two weeks on the albums chart. Mariah-charts.com. Retrieved February 27, 2007. and sold over half a million copies, certified quintuple platinum in April 2006.. Canadian Recording Industry Association. Retrieved February 28, 2007. ''L.A.M.B.'' sold seven million copies worldwide.Infantry, Ashante. "Stefani has it all, baby". ''Toronto Star''. A27. Retrieved December 6, 2006.

The success of the album's urban contemporary-oriented songs in the adult contemporary market allowed for the success of other artists while Stefani was pregnant and later recording ''The Sweet Escape''. Nelly Furtado's third album ''Loose'' was released in June 2006 and was primarily produced by and written with hip hop producers Timbaland and Danja. Furtado's reinvention from a worldbeat singer-songwriter was to Stefani's previous forays into urban contemporary music.Erlewine, Stephen Thomas. . All Music Guide. Retrieved July 23, 2007. In its review of ''Loose'', ''Rolling Stone'' stated that Timbaland aimed to "produce an omnipop multiformat blockbuster in the style of  -- but without Gwen."Sheffield, Rob. ". ''Rolling Stone''. June 15, 2006. Retrieved June 23 2007. Black Eyed Peas member Fergie released her solo debut album ''The Dutchess'' in September 2006. The cholas that accompanied Fergie in some of her music videos were viewed as derivatives of the Harajuku Girls and Stefani's "Luxurious" music video.Phanor, Alexandra. . ''Giant''. September 20, 2006. Retrieved July 16, 2007. The album's lead single "London Bridge" was paralleled to "Hollaback Girl" and the third single "Glamorous" to "Luxurious".Vincentelli, Elisabeth.. ''Time Out New York'', issue 573. September 21–26, 2006. Retrieved July 22, 2007. Fergie refuted accusations of piggybacking on Stefani's music, stating that "this is all so ridiculous … The Peas and I make music we love, and for others to speculate is their problem."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="90607d94e2d743d1c1f9c5fdd0ed193a" name="WhatYouWaitingFor1" sectnum="4#1">../img/90607d94e2d743d1c1f9c5fdd0ed193a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>