<document id="4e1fb86d435ce0ddc629de9c36c00080-3.3" name="Serial_Experiments_Lain" cat="19">
<text>
''Serial Experiments Lain'' is not a conventionally linear story, but "an alternative anime, with modern themes and realization".''Benkyo!'' Magazine, March 1999, p.16, "In My Humble Opinion" Themes range from theological to psychological and are dealt with in a number of ways: from classical dialogue to image-only introspection, passing by direct interrogation of imaginary characters.

Communication, in its wider sense, is one of the main themes of the series, not only as opposed to loneliness, but also as a subject in itself. Writer Konaka said he wanted to directly "communicate human feelings". Director Nakamura wanted to show the audience — and particularly viewers between 14 and 15 — "the multidimensional wavelength of the existential self: the relationship between self and the world". The intrusion of technology in the social structure is part of the process described: as Lain embraces the Wired, the viewer can see her drifting apart from her friends and family, to the point where "she can no longer relate to and interact with her fellow humans".

Loneliness, if only as representing a lack of communication, is recurrent through ''Lain''. Lain herself (according to Anime Jump) is "almost painfully introverted with no friends to speak of at school, a snotty, condescending sister, a strangely-apathetic mother, and a father who seems to want to care but is just too damn busy to give her much of his time".  Friendships turn on the first rumor;''Serial Experiments Lain'', Layer 08: RUMORS and the only insert song of the series is named ''Kodoku no shigunaru'', literally "signal of loneliness".


Mental illness, especially dissociative identity disorder, is a significant theme in ''Lain'': the main character is constantly confronted with alter-egos, to the point where writer Chiaki Konaka and Lain's seiyū Kaori Shimizu had to agree on subdividing the character's dialogues between three different orthographs. The three names designate distinct "versions" of Lain: the real-world, "childish" Lain has a shy attitude and bear pajamas. The "advanced" Lain, her Wired personality, is bold and questioning. Finally, the "evil" Lain is sly and devious, and does everything she can to harm Lain or the ones close to her. As a writing convention, the authors spelled their respective names in kanji, katakana, and roman characters (see picture)., page 42 

Reality never has the pretense of objectivity in ''Lain''.''Manga Max'' Magazine, September 1999, p.21, "God's Eye View" Acceptations of the term are battling throughout the series, such as the "natural" reality, defined through normal dialog between individuals; the material reality; and the tyrannic reality, enforced by one person onto the minds of others. A key debate to all interpretations of the series is to decide whether matter flows from thought, or the opposite.Serial Experiments Lain, Layer 06: KIDS: "your physical body exists only to confirm your existence". The production staff carefully avoided "the so-called God's Eye Viewpoint" to make clear the "limited field of vision" of the world of ''Lain''.

Theology plays its part in the development of the story too. ''Lain'' has been viewed as a questioning of the possibility of an infinite spirit in a finite body. by Felicity J. Coleman, lecturer at the University of Melbourne. From the Internet Archive. From self-realization as a goddess to deicide, religion (the title of a layer) is an inherent part of ''Lain'' 's background.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="83c51ed2ef6d620da9d2b5b26d0eda12" name="Lain_Split_Personnalities" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/83c51ed2ef6d620da9d2b5b26d0eda12.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>