<document id="4e1fb86d435ce0ddc629de9c36c00080-3.4" name="Serial_Experiments_Lain" cat="19">
<text>
''Lain'' contains extensive references to Apple computers, as the brand was used at the time by most of the creative staff, such as writers, producers, and the graphical team. As an example, the title at the beginning of each episode is announced by the Apple Computer Speech synthesis program  PlainTalk, using the voice ''"Whisper"''. Tachibana Industries, the company that creates the NAVI computers, is a reference to Apple computers: "tachibana" means "Mandarin orange" in Japanese. NAVI is the abbreviation of Knowledge Navigator, and the HandiNAVI is based on the Apple Newton, one of the world's first PDAs. The NAVIs are seen to run "Copland OS Enterprise" (this reference to Copland was an initiative of Konaka, a declared Apple fan), and Lain's and Alice's NAVIs closely resembles the Twentieth Anniversary Macintosh and the iMac respectively. The HandiNAVI programming language, as seen on the sixth episode, is a dialect of LISP. Notice that the Newton also used an LISP dialect (NewtonScript). The program being typed by Lain can be found here: 

During a series of disconnected images, an iMac and the Think Different advertising slogan appears for a short time, while the ''Whisper'' voice says it.''Serial Experiments Lain'', Layer 11: INFORNOGRAPHY. This was an unconcerted insertion from the graphic team, also Mac-enthusiasts. Other subtle allusions can be found: "Close the world, Open the nExt" is the slogan for the ''Serial Experiments Lain'' video game. NeXT was the company that produced NeXTSTEP, which later evolved into Mac OS X after Apple bought NeXT. Another example is "To Be Continued." at the end of episodes 1–12, with a blue "B" and a red "e" on "Be": ''this'' "Be" is the original logo of Be Inc., NeXT's main competitor in its time. A hacker is seen using Apple's HotSauce software.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1953fdcf89ee959e8e1906a684d060c5" name="LainThinkDifferent" sectnum="3.4#1">../img/1953fdcf89ee959e8e1906a684d060c5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>