<document id="4e1fb86d435ce0ddc629de9c36c00080-3.1" name="Serial_Experiments_Lain" cat="19">
<text>
The authors have been asked in interviews if they had been influenced by ''Neon Genesis Evangelion'', in the themes and graphic design. This was strictly denied by writer Chiaki J. Konaka in an interview, arguing that he had not seen ''Evangelion'' until he finished the fourth episode of ''Lain''. 
Being primarily a horror movies writer, his stated influences are Godard (specially for using typography on screen), ''The Exorcist'', ''Hell House'', and Dan Curtis's ''House of Dark Shadows''.
Alice's name, like the names of her two friends Julie and Reika, came from a previous production from Konaka, ''Alice in Cyberland'', which in turn was largely influenced by ''Alice in Wonderland''. As the series developed, Konaka was "surprised" by how close Alice's character became to the original ''Wonderland'' character.



''Lain'''s creators have been said to be "quite well read" and to "draw upon dozens if not hundreds of real-world sources for what seem to be the most outré concepts in the story":, retrieved on 10-10-2006.

Vannevar Bush (and Memex), John C. Lilly, Timothy Leary and his 8-Circuit Model of Consciousness, Ted Nelson and Project Xanadu are cited as precursors to the Wired.Animerica, (Vol. 7 No. 9, p.28) Douglas Rushkoff and his book ''Cyberia'' were originally to be cited as such, and in ''Lain'' Cyberia became the name of a nightclub populated with hackers and techno-punk teenagers. Likewise, the series' Deus ex machina lies in the conjunction of the Schumann resonance and Jung's collective unconscious (the authors chose this term over Kabbalah and Akashic Record). Majestic 12 and the Roswell UFO incident are used as examples of how a hoax might still have an impact on history, even after having been exposed as such, by creating sub-cultures. This links again to Vannevar Bush, the alleged "brains" of MJ12. Two of the literary references in ''Lain'' are quoted through Lain's father: he first logs onto a website with the password "Think Bule Count One Tow" ("Think Blue, Count Two" is an Instrumentality of Man story featuring virtual persons projected as real ones in people's minds); and his saying that "madeleines would be good with the tea" in the last episode makes ''Lain'' "one of the only cartoons ever to allude to Proust".'''Yasuo:''' "I will bring madeleines next time. They will taste good with the tea." ''Serial Experiments Lain'', Episode 13, "Ego".  Lain has just erased herself from her friends' memories, while for Proust the taste of madeleines triggers memories of his childhood.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="30b0c3a09eee90849396dcae6634fff4" name="Lain_hacker_small" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/30b0c3a09eee90849396dcae6634fff4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>