<document id="4e1fb86d435ce0ddc629de9c36c00080-4" name="Serial_Experiments_Lain" cat="19">
<text>
''Lain'' was first broadcast in Tokyo at 1:15 a.m. JST. The word "weird" appears almost systematically in English language reviews of the series,, ,  or the alternatives "bizarre", and "atypical", due mostly to its almost total absence of sexual and violent content, and due to its philosophical and psychological context. Critics responded positively to these thematic and stylistic characteristics, and it was awarded an Excellence Prize by the 1998 Japan Media Arts Festival for "its willingness to question the meaning of contemporary life" and the "extraordinarily philosophical and deep questions" it asks.From the Internet Archive.  According to Christian Nutt from Newtype USA, the main attraction to the series is its keen view on "the interlocking problems of identity and technology". Nutt saluted ABe's "crisp, clean character design" and the "perfect soundtrack" in his 2005 review of series, saying that "''Serial Experiments Lain'' might not yet be considered a true classic, but it's a fascinating evolutionary leap that helped change the future of anime." ''Anime Jump'' gave it 4.5/5, and Anime on DVD gave it A+ on all criteria for volume 1 and 2, and a mix of A and A+ for volume 3 and 4.  

''Lain'' was subject to commentary in the literary and academic worlds. The ''Asian Horror Encyclopedia'' calls it "an outstanding psycho-horror anime about the psychic and spiritual influence of the Internet"., page 162. It notes that the red spots present in all the shadows look like blood pools (see picture). It notes the death of a girl in a train accident is "a source of much ghost lore in the twentieth century", more so in Tokyo. The ''Anime Essentials'' anthology by Gilles Poitras describes it as a "complex and somehow existential" anime that "pushed the enveloppe" ''(sic)'' of anime diversity in the 1990s, alongside the much better known ''Neon Genesis Evangelion'' and ''Cowboy Bebop''., page 28. Professor Susan J. Napier, in her 2003 reading to the American Philosophical Society called ''The Problem of Existence in Japanese Animation'' (published 2005), compared ''Serial Experiments Lain'' to ''Ghost in the Shell'' and Hayao Miyazaki's ''Spirited Away''.'''', by Pr. Susan J. Napier, in ''Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society'', Vol. 149, No. 1, March 2005. According to her, the main characters of the two other works cross barriers; they can cross back to our world, but Lain cannot. Napier asks whether there is something to which Lain should return, "between an empty 'real' and a dark 'virtual'". Mitchell Tribbett from Reed College interprets ''Lain'' as a symbol of Japan's post-war social and cultural struggles. In his essay ''Serial Experiments: Lain as a Reflection of Modern Japanese Anxieties in the Digital Era'', Tribbett sees the Wired in ''Lain'' as representative of the westernized, non hierarchical society that co-exists with traditional Japanese culture.'''', by Mitchell Tribbett. Anthropology of Japan, Reed College.

Producer Ueda had to answer repeated queries about a statement made in an Animerica interview. The controversial statement said ''Lain'' was ''"a sort of cultural war against American culture and the American sense of values we  adopted after World War II"''.Animerica, (Vol. 7 No. 9, p.29) 
He later explained in numerous interviews that he created ''Lain'' with a set of values he took as distinctly Japanese; he hoped Americans would not understand the series as the Japanese would. This would lead to a "war of ideas" over the meaning of the anime, hopefully culminating in new communication between the two cultures. When he discovered that the American audience held the same views on the series as the Japanese, he was disappointed.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b0244ff5c950f905cfa45f3f55dc7db0" name="Serial_Experiments_Lain_(TV)_Screenshot_01" sectnum="4#1">../img/b0244ff5c950f905cfa45f3f55dc7db0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>