<document id="4e3d8679cfdb4347c7f7f87a00d3b7f6-5" name="Shrimp_farm" cat="3">
<text>
The total global production of farmed shrimp reached more than 1.6 million tonnes in 2003, representing a farm-gate value of nearly 9 billion U.S. dollars.FIGIS; FAO databases, 2007. This accounts for 25% of the total shrimp production that year (farming and wild catches combined).Josueit, p. 9. The largest market for shrimp is the United States, importing more than 500,000 tonnes of shrimp in 2003. About 250,000 tonnes went to Japan, while the four major European shrimp importing countries (France, Spain, the UK, and Italy) imported together about another 500,000 tonnes.FAO: ''''; FAO GlobeFish; 2003 &ndash; 2005.

The import prices for shrimp fluctuate wildly. In 2003 the import price per kilogram shrimp in the United States was US$ 8.80, slightly higher than in Japan at US$8.&ndash;. The average import price in the EU was only about US$5.&ndash;/kg; this much lower value is explained by the fact that the EU imports more coldwater shrimp (from catches) that are much smaller than the farmed warm water species and thus attain lower prices. In addition, Mediterranean Europe prefers head-on shrimp which weigh approximately 30% more but have a lower unit price.Josueit, p. 16.

About 75% of the world production of farmed shrimp comes from Asian countries; the two leading nations being China and Thailand, closely followed by Vietnam, Indonesia, and India. The other 25% are produced in the western hemisphere, where the South-American countries (Brazil, Ecuador, Mexico) dominate. In terms of export, Thailand is by far the leading nation with a market share of more than 30%, followed by China, Indonesia, and India, accounting each for about 10%. Other major export nations are Vietnam, Bangladesh, and Ecuador.FoodMarket: ''''; data from GlobeFish, 2001. URL last accessed 2005-06-23. Thailand exports nearly all of its production, while China uses most of its shrimp in the domestic market. The only other major export nation that has a strong domestic market for farmed shrimp is Mexico.





Disease problems have repeatedly impacted the shrimp production negatively. Besides the near-wipeout of ''P. chinensis'' in 1993, there were outbreaks of viral diseases that led to marked declines in the per-country production in 1996/97 in Thailand and repeatedly in Ecuador.Josueit p. 7f. In Ecuador alone, production suffered heavily in 1989 (IHHN), 1993 (Taura), and 1999 (whitespot).Funge-Smith & Briggs, 2003. Another reason for sometimes wild changes in shrimp farm output are the import regulations of the destination countries, which do not allow shrimp contaminated by chemicals or antibiotics to be imported.

In the 1980s and through much of the 1990s, shrimp farming promised high profits. The investments required for extensive farms were low, especially in regions with low land prices and wages. For many tropical countries, especially those with poorer economies, shrimp farming was an attractive business, offering jobs and incomes for poor coastal populations and has, due to the high market prices of shrimp, provided many developing countries with non-negligible foreign currency earnings. Many shrimp farms were funded initially by the World Bank or substantially subsidized by local governments.Lewis ''et al.''

In the late 1990s, the economic situation changed. Governments and farmers alike were under increasing pressure from NGOs and the consumer countries, who criticized the practices of the trade. International trade conflicts erupted, such as import bans by consumer countries on shrimp containing antibiotics, the United States' shrimp import ban against Thailand in 2004 as a measure against Thai shrimp ''fishers'' not using Turtle Excluder Devices in their nets,Thai Farmers Research Center, 2004. or the "anti-dumping" case initiated by U.S. shrimp fishers in 2002 against shrimp farmers worldwide,Rosenberry, ''Shrimpnews'', 2005. which resulted two years later in the U.S. imposing anti-dumping tariffs of the order of about 10% against many producer countries (except China, which received a 112% duty).Global Aquaculture Alliance: ''''. URL last accessed 2005-08-23. Diseases caused significant economic losses. In Ecuador, where shrimp farming was a major export sector (the other two are Bananas and Oil), the whitespot outbreak of 1999 caused an estimated 130,000 workers to lose their jobs. Furthermore, shrimp prices dropped sharply in 2000.Rosenberry, B.: ''''; Comments on shrimp prices in the on-line excerpts 2000–2004. URL last accessed 2005-08-18. All of these factors contributed to the slowly growing acceptance by farmers that improved farming practices were needed, and resulted in tighter government regulation of the business, both of which internalized some of the external costs that were ignored during the boom years.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="13fd6238199cba32a04f32651af426b2" name="Litopenaeus_vannamei_specimen" sectnum="5#1">../img/13fd6238199cba32a04f32651af426b2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>