<document id="4e9261acce01f7b573f08ceac213fe64-5.8" name="Frank_Zappa" cat="20">
<text>
Zappa's relationship with long-time manager Herb Cohen ended in 1976. The breakup was an acrimonious affair in which Zappa sued Cohen for skimming more than he was allocated from DiscReet Records, as well as for signing acts of which Zappa did not approve.Miles, 2004, ''Frank Zappa'', p. 250. Cohen filed a lawsuit against Zappa in return, which froze the money Zappa and Cohen had gained from an out-of-court settlement with MGM over the rights of the early Mothers of Invention recordings. It also prevented Zappa access to any of his previously recorded material during the trials. Zappa therefore took his personal master copies of the rock-oriented ''Zoot Allures'' (1976) directly to Warner Bros., thereby bypassing DiscReet.Miles, 2004, ''Frank Zappa'', p. 253; pp. 258–259.

In the mid-1970s Zappa prepared material for ''Läther'' (pronounced "leather"), a four-LP project. ''Läther'' encapsulated all the aspects of Zappa's musical styles—rock tunes, orchestral works, complex instrumentals, and Zappa's own trademark distortion-drenched guitar solos. Wary of a quadruple-LP, Warner Bros. Records refused to release it.Lowe, 2006, ''The Words and Music of Frank Zappa'', p. 131. Zappa managed to get an agreement with Mercury-Phonogram, and test pressings were made targeted at a Halloween 1977 release, but Warner Bros. prevented the release by claiming rights over the material.Miles, 2004, ''Frank Zappa'', p. 261. Zappa responded by appearing on the Pasadena, California radio station KROQ, allowing them to broadcast ''Läther'' and encouraging listeners to make their own tape recordings.Slaven, 2003, ''Electric Don Quixote'', p. 248. A lawsuit between Zappa and Warner Bros. followed, during which no Zappa material was released for more than a year. Eventually, Warner Bros. issued major parts of ''Läther'' against Zappa's will as four individual albums with limited promotion.Miles, 2004, ''Frank Zappa'', p. 267. ''Läther'' was released posthumously in 1996.It remains debated whether Zappa had conceived the material as a four-LP set from the beginning, or only when approaching Mercury-Phonogram; see, e.g., Watson, 2005, ''Frank Zappa. The Complete Guide to His Music'', p. 49. In the liner notes to the 1996 release, however, Gail Zappa states that "As originally conceived by Frank, ''Läther'' was always a 4-record box set."

Although Zappa eventually gained the rights to all his material created under the MGM and Warner Bros. contracts,Watson, 2005, ''Frank Zappa. The Complete Guide to His Music'', p. 49. the various lawsuits meant that for a period Zappa's only income came from touring, which he therefore did extensively in 1975–1977 with relatively small, mainly rock-oriented, bands. Drummer Terry Bozzio became a regular band member, Napoleon Murphy Brock stayed on for a while, and original Mothers of Invention bassist Roy Estrada joined. Among other musicians were bassist Patrick O'Hearn, singer-guitarist Ray White and keyboardist Eddie Jobson. In December 1976, Zappa appeared as a featured musical guest on the NBC television show ''Saturday Night Live''.Miles, 2004, ''Frank Zappa'', p. 262.In 1978, Zappa served both as host and musical act on the show, and as an actor in various sketches. The performances included an impromptu musical collaboration with cast member John Belushi during the instrumental piece "The Purple Lagoon". Belushi appeared as his Samurai Futaba character playing a strange guitar/microphone contraption with Zappa conducting.Zappa, Frank, 1978, ''Zappa in New York'', Liner Notes. Zappa's song, "I'm the Slime", was performed with a voice-over by ''SNL'' booth announcer Don Pardo, who also introduced "Peaches En Regalia" on the same airing.

Zappa in Toronto, 1977

Zappa's band at the time, with the additions of Ruth Underwood and a horn section (featuring Michael and Randy Brecker), performed during Christmas in New York, recordings of which appear on one of the albums released by Warner Bros., ''Zappa in New York'' (1978). It mixes intense instrumentals such as "The Black Page" and humorous songs like "Titties and Beer".Lowe, 2006, ''The Words and Music of Frank Zappa'', p. 132. The former composition, written originally for drum kit but later developed for larger bands, is notorious for its complexity in rhythmic structure, radical changes of tempo and meter, and short, densely arranged passages.. Retrieved on December 29, 2007.. Retrieved on July 24, 2008.



''Zappa in New York'' featured a song about sex criminal Michael H. Kenyon, "The Illinois Enema Bandit", which featured Don Pardo providing the opening narrative in the song. Like many songs on the album, it contained numerous sexual references, leading to many critics objecting and being offended by the content.Miles, 2004, ''Frank Zappa'', pp. 261–262; Lowe, 2006, ''The Words and Music of Frank Zappa'', p. 134. Zappa dismissed the criticism by noting that he was a journalist reporting on life as he saw it.Miles, 2004, ''Frank Zappa'', p. 234. Predating his later fight against censorship, he remarked: "What do you make of a society that is so primitive that it clings to the belief that certain words in its language are so powerful that they could corrupt you the moment you hear them?". The remaining albums released by Warner Bros. Records without Zappa's consent were ''Studio Tan'' in 1978 and ''Sleep Dirt'' in 1979, which contained complex suites of instrumentally-based tunes recorded between 1973 and 1976, and which was overlooked in the midst of the legal problems.Lowe, 2006, ''The Words and Music of Frank Zappa'', p. 138. Also released by the label without the artist's consent was ''Orchestral Favorites'' in 1979, which featured recordings of a concert with orchestral music from 1975.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="717b29270200e08b4f55ed92a8929a7d" name="Frank_Zappa_-_Capt._Beefheart" sectnum="5.8#1">../img/717b29270200e08b4f55ed92a8929a7d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>