<document id="4ea89fd7baaeb35e25c50cef0fb2fa96-7.13" name="Olympic_Games" cat="26">
<text>
Contrary to the founding principles, the Olympic Games have been used as a platform to promote political ideologies.  Nazi Germany wished to demonstrate the Nationalist Socialist Party's benevolence and desire for peace when they hosted the 1936 Games.Findling & Pelle (2004) p. 107 The Games were also intended to show the superiority of the Aryan race; a goal that was not met due in part to the achievements of athletes such as Jesse Owens, who won four gold medals at this Olympics.Findling & Pelle (2004) p. 111&ndash;112  The Soviet Union did not participate until the 1952 Summer Olympics in Helsinki. Instead, starting in 1928, the Soviets organized an international sports event called Spartakiads. Other communist countries organized Workers Olympics during the interwar period of the 1920s and 1930s.  These events were held as an alternative to the Olympics, which were perceived as a capitalist and aristocratic event.Roche (2000), p. 106  It was not until the 1956 Summer Games that the Soviets emerged as a sporting superpower and, in doing so, took full advantage of the publicity that came with winning at the Olympics.
 
Individual athletes have also used the Olympic stage to promote their own political agenda.  At the 1968 Summer Olympics, in Mexico City, two American track and field athletes, Tommie Smith and John Carlos, who finished first and third in the 200 meter sprint race, performed the Black Power salute on the victory stand. The second place finisher Peter Norman wore an Olympic Project for Human Rights badge in support of Smith and Carlos. In response to the protest, IOC President Avery Brundage told the United States Olympic Committee (USOC) to either send the two athletes home or withdraw the track and field team. The USOC opted for the former.

Currently, the government of Iran has taken steps to avoid any competition between its athletes and those from Israel.  An Iranian judoka did not compete in a match against an Israeli during the 2004 Summer Olympics.  Although he was officially disqualified for excessive weight, Arash Miresmaeli was awarded US$125,000 in prize money by the Iranian government, an amount paid to all Iranian gold medal winners.  He was officially cleared of intentionally avoiding the bout, but his receipt of the prize money raised suspicion.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9b80b29a06f7d6e72b891583216ffd3d" name="Bundesarchiv_Bild_183-G00630,_Sommerolympiade,_Siegerehrung_Weitsprung" sectnum="7.13#1">../img/9b80b29a06f7d6e72b891583216ffd3d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>