<document id="4ea89fd7baaeb35e25c50cef0fb2fa96-6.11" name="Olympic_Games" cat="26">
<text>
The ethos of the aristocracy as exemplified in the English public schools greatly influenced Pierre de Coubertin.  The public schools subscribed to the belief that sport formed an important part of education, an attitude summed up in the saying ''mens sana in corpore sano'', a sound mind in a sound body. In this ethos, a gentleman was one who became an all-rounder, not the best at one specific thing.  There was also a prevailing concept of fairness, in which practicing or training was considered tantamount to cheating. Those who practiced a sport professionally were considered to have an unfair advantage over those who practiced it merely as a hobby.

The exclusion of professionals caused several controversies throughout the history of the modern Olympics. The 1912 Olympic pentathlon and decathlon champion Jim Thorpe was stripped of his medals when it was discovered that he had played semi-professional baseball before the Olympics. His medals were restored by the IOC in 1983 on compassionate grounds. Swiss and Austrian skiers boycotted the 1936 Winter Olympics in support of their skiing teachers, who were not allowed to compete because they earned money with their sport and were thus considered professionals.

As class structure evolved through the 20th century, the definition of the amateur athlete as an aristocratic gentleman became outdated. The advent of the state-sponsored "full-time amateur athlete" of the Eastern Bloc countries further eroded the ideology of the pure amateur, as it put the self-financed amateurs of the Western countries at a disadvantage. Nevertheless, the IOC held to the traditional rules regarding amateurism. Beginning in the 1970s, amateurism requirements were gradually phased out of the Olympic Charter. Eventually the decisions on professional participation were left to the IFs. As of 2004, the only sport in which no professionals compete is boxing, although even this requires a definition of amateurism based on fight rules rather than on payment, as some boxers receive cash prizes from their National Olympic Committees. In men's football (soccer), only three players over the age of 23 are eligible to participate per team in the Olympic tournament.  This is done in order to maintain a level of amateurism.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c2e8281ba70aa2e2047667967bcba79d" name="Nagano_1998-Russia_vs_Czech_Republic" sectnum="6.11#1">../img/c2e8281ba70aa2e2047667967bcba79d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>