<document id="4ecd8b1ceecb0ebf9b2a164a4efd8d9e-7.14" name="Ian_Thorpe" cat="26">
<text>
During his career, Thorpe was one of the most prominent and popular sportspeople in Australia. Despite competing in a sport in which the vast majority of international athletes' earnings are below the poverty line, marketing surveys consistently ranked Thorpe as the most sought-after Australian athlete for sponsorship deals, surpassing footballers who compete on a weekly basis in much larger stadia.Hunter, pp. vii&ndash;viii. Aside from his swimsuit sponsor Adidas, Thorpe was sponsored by Australian corporate giants such as Qantas, Telstra, and the Seven Network.Hunter, pp. 90, 140, 168.



Thorpe's interests in fashion and culture led him to make frequent visits to New York City&mdash;which he describes as a second home&mdash;often for engagements with Armani.Swanton, p. 113. He was present at the World Trade Center on the morning of September 11, 2001, having stopped there on his jog, before returning to his hotel after forgetting his camera.Swanton, pp. 114&ndash;115. It was during this trip that he appeared on ''The Tonight Show with Jay Leno'', which was notable because of the relative lack of interest in competitive swimming in America.Hunter, pp. 280&ndash;281. Thorpe later became a spokesperson for the unsuccessful New York bid for the 2012 Summer Olympics, even promising to continue his career until the games if New York won the hosting rights. Thorpe's interests have also seen him involved in television. In 2002, he played the lead role in the reality television show ''Undercover Angels'', which imitated the ''Charlie's Angels'' series. In the program, Thorpe directed three young women who performed good deeds for people in need. Although it averaged more than a million viewers per episode, it was widely panned by critics.Hunter, pp. 294&ndash;295. Thorpe has also appeared as an extra in the American sitcom ''Friends''.Hunter, p. 244.

Thorpe is widely popular in Asia, particularly Japan. In 2000, TV Asahi identified him as the swimmer likely to be the most successful at the 2001 World Championships in Fukuoka, so they selected him as the event's marketing figurehead. In the lead-up, Thorpe visited Japan to promote Asahi in a series of television events,Hunter, pp. 236, 249, 257&ndash;260. and upon returning for the competition, he was mobbed at the airport by youthful crowds 25 m deep; hundreds camped outside the Australian team's hotel.Swanton, pp. 117, 120. He was also praised by older sections of Japanese society as a role model for youth, due to what they interpreted as his humility and work ethic.Hunter, pp. 264&ndash;265, 275&ndash;276. It was estimated that more than 80% of the Japanese public watched his races on television.Swanton, p. 120. In 2002, in the wake of a tourism slump after the September 11 terrorist attacks, Thorpe agreed to be an ambassador for the Australian Tourism Commission in Japan. The high-profile campaign included a meeting with the Japanese Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi. The marketing drive resulted in an upturn in Japanese tourism to Australia, which was credited to Thorpe.Hunter, pp. 292&ndash;293.Swanton, p. 142. In 2005, Yakult released a 'Thorpedo' energy drink&mdash;which featured a picture of the swimmer on the bottle&mdash;in Japan. This was part of an equity deal with the So Natural food group, in which Thorpe was given a 5% stake in the company&mdash;at the time worth A$1.1m&mdash;in return for the use of his name and image on their products. The 15-year deal covers East and Southeast Asia and Thorpe's share in the venture could increase to 50% depending on its success.Hunter, pp. 350&ndash;351.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="52a32e999660d38a669283402290e6cd" name="Ian_Thorpe_on_a_plane" sectnum="7.14#1">../img/52a32e999660d38a669283402290e6cd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>