<document id="4ef68b8d83f625a7725c485c7507c077-2.2" name="December_to_Dismember_(2006)" cat="26">
<text>
The final match was the Extreme Elimination Chamber main event for the ECW World Championship. Before it began, Paul Heyman came out to the ring and explained the rules of the match and said that there was a weapon in each of the four different pods that housed the wrestlers. In a conversation backstage with The Big Show before heading to the ring not seen by television viewers, Heyman revealed that for the first time in his professional career he was not motivated to give the promo. Rob Van Dam and Hardcore Holly started off the match, and one of the other four competitors entered every five minutes afterward. The first person to be released from his pod was CM Punk, who entered the match with a steel chair in hand. Test came out five minutes after Punk with a crowbar. Punk was the first person eliminated from the match when Van Dam performed a body splash from the top turnbuckle. Moments later, Test charged at Holly and hit his head with his boot and pinned him. Van Dam was the third person eliminated by Test, as he stood on The Big Show's pod and dove toward Van Dam, driving his elbow into his chest onto a folding chair, a move known as a diving elbow drop. When Bobby Lashley's pod was supposed to open, he could not get out of it because Heyman's Security Force had bolted the pod shut. Lashley used the table that was with him to smash the pod open, allowing him to escape. Lashley then hit Test with a spear, a variation of a takedown, to get a pinfall. The Big Show was the final man to exit his pod and enter the match, with a baseball bat wrapped in barbed wire. Lashley blocked The Big Show's swing of the bat with a folding chair and then threw The Big Show into a pod, causing him to bleed. Lashley managed to turn an attempted chokeslam from The Big Show into a DDT, a move in which the wrestler falls down or backwards to drive the opponent's held head into the mat, and then speared The Big Show to win the match and become the new ECW World Champion.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="011f96ff8b5e3da133d4b79ce170af6c" name="Elimination_chamber_nyr06" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/011f96ff8b5e3da133d4b79ce170af6c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>