<document id="4f1411629c6e068c44d61b172149ce40-8.5" name="USS_Princess_Matoika_(ID-2290)" cat="29">
<text>
After completion of her maiden voyage, ''City of Honolulu'' began regular service from Los Angeles to Honolulu and Hilo on what  called the "Great Circle Route of Sunshine". After arriving at Honolulu, the ship would sail southeast to Hilo, passing the islands of Molokai and Maui on their north sides. On the return from Hilo, the liner would traverse the ʻAlalākeiki, the ʻAuʻau, and the Kalohi Channels, taking the ship between Maui and Molokai on the north and the islands of Kahoolawe and Lanai on the south. (Convenience copy located at .)

Throughout her career, ''City of Honolulu'' transported many notable passengers to Hawaii. In July 1927, for example, Henry Smith Pritchett, president of the Carnegie Foundation, sailed to Hawaii en route to a meeting with the Institute of Pacific Relations.  In June 1928, movie stars Norma Talmadge, Gilbert Roland, and Lottie Pickford began a Hawaiian vacation, and on 28 July, Jane Addams, the founder of Hull House and a pioneer of the settlement movement, headed there as well. Addams was on her way to attend the Pan-Pacific Women's Conference and the congress of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom; a former Governor of Hawaii, Walter F. Frear, returned to the islands on that same voyage. In December, Al Jolson and his wife, Ruby Keeler, sailed on the liner for a vacation, and early the next February, the reigning British Open golf champion, Walter Hagen, sailed to start a four-month golfing tour and exhibition in Australia. Hagan was accompanied by Australian golfer Joe Kirkwood; Arctic explorer Donald B. MacMillan also left for Hawaii on the same sailing.


''City of Honolulu'' also carried notable visitors to the mainland. Farris M. Brown, a dealer in Stradivarius instruments, arrived in Los Angeles in May 1928 with three of the famous maker's violins, including the Baron Knoop Stradivarius. In April 1929, Swedish swimmer Arne Borg, accompanied by his wife, arrived in Los Angeles on a world swimming tour, and in May, Sir James Gunnson, a former Mayor of Auckland, arrived for a one-month visit to promote increased trade between California and New Zealand. The next January, Herbert Hagerman, former Governor of New Mexico Territory; author Basil Woon, who had been doing research for a Hawaiian story; and aviation promoter and chewing gum magnate William Easterwood all sailed stateside on the ship.

Apart from notable passengers carried during her tenure, ''City of Honolulu'' also frequently served as a conveyance for newlyweds heading for Hawaiian honeymoons.See, for example, "Sundays on new honeymoon", ''Los Angeles Times'', 7 May 1928, p. A11; and "Honeymooners 'in the same boat'", ''Los Angeles Times'', 27 August 1928, p. A1. She also carried, in addition to passengers, cargo in both directions, transporting commodities, such as fertilizer and oil, to Hawaii, and Hawaiian goods, like sugar and fresh and canned pineapple to the mainland.See, for example, "Excursionists land today", ''Los Angeles Times'', 18 August 1928, p. A9.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="28beeb4babe6dd1acc8b848bf5c1c0a6" name="Alohatoweratnight" sectnum="8.5#1">../img/28beeb4babe6dd1acc8b848bf5c1c0a6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>