<document id="4f1411629c6e068c44d61b172149ce40-8.4" name="USS_Princess_Matoika_(ID-2290)" cat="29">
<text>
''City of Honolulu'' was rebuilt to  and had accommodations for around 450 first-class and 50 third-class passengers. Her hull was painted all white for  service, and she sported period designs in her common areas. The dining room, large enough to seat 300 in a single sitting, was decorated in a Grecian theme, and featured 18 stained glass windows designed by San Diego architect Carleton M. Winslow. The smoking room was done up in a Tudor style; the music room was decorated in a combined French and Italian Renaissance manner; and the writing room was in Adam style. The suites were all done in either Adam, Queen Anne, or Louis XVI styles. The ship featured six passenger elevators, and a swimming pool patterned on a Pompeian design. One of the few remaining traces of her pre-war German decoration was the rosewood railing on her grand staircase.

On 4 June 1927, a crowd of 7,000 well-wishers saw ''City of Honolulu'' depart on her maiden voyage. The festivities were also broadcast on radio station KGFO, a portable station operating form the front cargo deck of the ship. During the journey, broadcasts of the ''City of Honolulu''s orchestra, along with radio personalities and musicians from Los Angeles station KHJ, entertained both passengers and listeners on shore (while the ship was in range). Brant Radio Power Co., the owners of KGFO, were granted special permission from the Federal Radio Commission to transmit from their broadcast truck aboard the ship while at sea, and while ashore at Hawaii.

Several notable passengers sailed on the liner's maiden voyage. Jay Gould II, tennis champion and grandson of railroad tycoon Jay Gould, sailed for a three-month stay at his Hawaiian home. Also sailing were movie star Laura La Plante and her husband, director William A. Seiter, and, Western Auto founder George Pepperdine, who began a three-month tour of the Orient with his daughters. On arrival in Honolulu on 10 June, ''City of Honolulu'' was adorned with flowers and received a welcome from airplanes and a flotilla of outrigger canoes that escorted her into the harbor. After a ten-day stay in the islands, she departed for Los Angeles, returning there on 26 June.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4116deb283cc59fc7551e77586082c45" name="Maui_coast_panorama" sectnum="8.4#1">../img/4116deb283cc59fc7551e77586082c45.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>