<document id="4f31ae3fa65d74533726cd47e498b71f-1.2" name="T-34" cat="29">
<text>
The T-34 posed new challenges for Soviet industry. It had heavier armour than any medium tank produced to that point, and subassemblies originated at several plants: Kharkov Diesel Factory No. 75 supplied the model V-2 engine, Leningrad Kirovsky Factory (former Putilov works) made the original L-11 gun, and the Dinamo Factory in Moscow produced electrical components. Tanks were initially built at KhPZ No. 183, in early 1941 at the Stalingrad Tractor Factory (STZ), and starting in July shortly after the German invasion at Krasnoye Sormovo Factory No. 112 in Gorky. There were problems with defective armour plates, however (Zaloga 1983:6). Due to a shortage of new V-2 diesel engines, the initial production run from the Gorky factory were equipped with the BT tank's MT-17 gasoline-burning aircraft engine, and inferior transmission and clutch (Zheltov 2001:40–42). Only company commanders' tanks could be fitted with radios, which were expensive and in short supply. The L-11 gun did not live up to expectations, so the Grabin design bureau at Gorky Factory No. 92 designed a superior F-34 76.2 mm gun. No bureaucrat would approve production, but Gorky and KhPZ started producing the gun anyway; official permission only came from Stalin's State Defense Committee after troops in the field sent back praise for the gun's performance (Zaloga & Grandsen 1984:130).

Political pressure came from conservative elements in the army to redirect resources into building the older T-26 and BT tanks, or to cancel T-34 production pending completion of the more advanced T-34M design. This political pressure was brought to bear by the developer of the KV-1 and IS-2 tanks which were in competition with the T-34. (Political pressure between designers and factories producing different tanks to meet the same requirements continued much later post-war, including a period when the T-55, T-64, T-72, and T-80 were in concurrent production at several factories with differing political patrons on the supreme council of the USSR m tanks
Category:World War II Soviet tanks
Category:Tanks of the Korean War
Category:Tanks of Finland




ar:تي-34
bg:Т-34
ca:T-34
cs:T-34
da:T-34
de:T-34
et:T-34
el:Τ-34/76
es:T-34
eo:T-34
fr:T-34
ko:T-34
hr:T-34
it:T-34 (carro armato)
he:T-34
lb:T-34
lt:T-34
hu:T–34
ms:Kereta kebal T-34
nl:T-34
ja:T-34
no:T-34
nn:T-34
pl:T-34
pt:T-34
ro:T-34
ru:Т-34
sk:T-34
sl:T-34
sr:Т-34
sh:T-34
fi:T-34
sv:T-34
th:ที-34
tr:T-34
uk:Т-34
vi:Xe tăng T-34
zh:T-34坦克
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="01cbe0bb22623482581f3fbaf91b57bf" name="T-34_Model_1940" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/01cbe0bb22623482581f3fbaf91b57bf.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>