<document id="4f46dd0bedbc68c91be78f75a8be118c-5" name="Sargon_of_Akkad" cat="25">
<text>
Sargon died, according to the short chronology, around 2215 BC. His empire immediately revolted upon hearing of the king's death. Most of the revolts were put down by his son and successor Rimush, who reigned for nine years and was followed by another of Sargon's sons, Manishtushu (who reigned for 15 years).Kramer, ''The Sumerians'' 61–63; Roux 155. Sargon was regarded as a model by Mesopotamian kings for some two millennia after his death. The Assyrian and Babylonian kings who based their empires in Mesopotamia saw themselves as the heirs of Sargon's empire. Kings such as Nabonidus (r. 556–539 BC) showed great interest in the history of the Sargonid dynasty, and even conducted excavations of Sargon's palaces and those of his successors.Oates 162. Indeed, such later rulers may have been inspired by the king's conquests to embark on their own campaigns throughout the Middle East. The Neo-Assyrian Sargon text challenges his successors thus:



Another source attributed to Sargon the challenge "now, any king who wants to call himself my equal, wherever I went , let him go."Nougayrol 169.

Stories of Sargon's power and that of his empire may have influenced the body of folklore that was later incorporated into the Bible. A number of scholars have speculated that Sargon may have been the inspiration for the biblical figure of Nimrod, who figures prominently in the Book of Genesis as well as in midrashic and Talmudic literature. The Bible mentions Akkad as being one of the first city-states of Nimrod's kingdom, but does not explicitly state that he built it.Genesis 10:10. In the Sumerian king list, Sargon is credited with the construction of the city, but see above for controversy surrounding this assertion.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d11e80b90c82624ee4e98017211a3289" name="Stele_Naram_Sim_Louvre_Sb4" sectnum="5#1">../img/d11e80b90c82624ee4e98017211a3289.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>