<document id="4fabd0ceb387d5ac14d3a1eefb2e7281-2.11" name="Sunday_Times_Golden_Globe_Race" cat="26">
<text>
On the same day, 22 April, Knox-Johnston completed his voyage where it had started, in Falmouth. This made him the winner of the Golden Globe trophy, and the first person to sail single-handed and non-stop around the world, which he had done in 313 days.''A Voyage for Madmen'', page 267. This left Tetley and Crowhurst apparently fighting for the £5,000 prize for fastest time.

However, Tetley knew that he was pushing his boat too hard. On 20 May he ran into a storm near the Azores and began to worry about the boat's severely weakened state. Hoping that the storm would soon blow over, he lowered all sail and went to sleep with the boat lying ahull. In the early hours of the next day he was awoken by the sounds of tearing wood. Fearing that the bow of the port hull might have broken off, he went on deck to cut it loose, only to discover that in breaking away it had made a large hole in the main hull, from which ''Victress'' was now taking on water too rapidly to stop. He sent a Mayday, and luckily got an almost immediate reply. He abandoned ship just before ''Victress'' finally sank and was rescued from his liferaft that evening, having come to within  of finishing what would have been the most significant voyage ever made in a multi-hulled boat.''Trimaran Solo'', pages 149—160.

Crowhurst was left as the only person in the race, and — given his high reported speeds — virtually guaranteed the £5,000 prize. This would, however, also guarantee intense scrutiny of himself, his stories, and his logs by genuine Cape Horn veterans such as the sceptical Chichester. Although he had put great effort into his fabricated log, such a deception would in practice be extremely difficult to carry off, particularly for someone who did not have actual experience of the Southern Ocean; something of which he must have been aware at heart. Although he had been sailing fast — at one point making over  in a day — as soon as he learned of Tetley's sinking, he slowed down to a wandering crawl.''Strange Last Voyage'', pages 186, 190—191.

Crowhurst's main radio failed at the beginning of June, shortly after he had learned that he was the sole remaining competitor. Plunged into unwilling solitude, he spent the following weeks attempting to repair the radio, and on 22 June was finally able to transmit and receive in morse code. The following days were spent exchanging cables with his agent and the press, during which he was bombarded with news of syndication rights, a welcoming fleet of boats and helicopters, and a rapturous welcome by the British people. It became clear that he could not now avoid the spotlight.


Unable to see a way out of his predicament, he plunged into abstract philosophy, attempting to find an escape in metaphysics, and on 24 June he started writing a long essay to express his ideas. Inspired (in a misguided way) by the work of Einstein, whose book ''Relativity: The Special and General Theory'' he had aboard, the theme of Crowhurst's writing was that a sufficiently intelligent mind can overcome the constraints of the real world. Over the following eight days, he wrote 25,000 words of increasingly tortured prose, drifting farther and farther from reality, as ''Teignmouth Electron'' continued sailing slowly north, largely untended. Finally, on 1 July, he concluded his writing with a garbled suicide note, and jumped overboard.''A Voyage for Madmen'', pages 195—251.

Moitessier, meanwhile, had concluded his own personal voyage more happily. He had circumnavigated the world and sailed almost two-thirds of the way round a second time, all non-stop and mostly in the roaring forties. Despite heavy weather and a couple of severe knockdowns, he contemplated rounding the Horn again. However, he decided that he and ''Joshua'' had had enough and sailed to Tahiti, where he and his wife had set out for Alicante. He thus completed his second personal circumnavigation of the world (including the previous voyage with his wife) on 21 June 1969. He started work on his book.''The Long Way'', pages 172–175.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="563db4fb80f14d654349483cc4cb6846" name="Bernard_Moitessier_Golden_Globe" sectnum="2.11#1">../img/563db4fb80f14d654349483cc4cb6846.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>