<document id="4fabd0ceb387d5ac14d3a1eefb2e7281-3" name="Sunday_Times_Golden_Globe_Race" cat="26">
<text>
Knox-Johnston, as the only finisher, was awarded both the Golden Globe trophy and the £5,000 prize for fastest time. He continued to sail and circumnavigated three more times. He was awarded a CBE in 1969 and was knighted in 1995., from boats.com. Retrieved 6 March 2006. His book, ''A World of My Own'', tells the story of his trip in typically down-to-earth, blunt style.


It is impossible to say whether Moitessier would have won if he had completed the race, as he would have been sailing in different weather conditions than Knox-Johnston did, but based on his time from the start to Cape Horn being about 77% of that of Knox-Johnston, it would have been extremely close. His book, ''The Long Way'', tells the story of his voyage as a spiritual journey as much as a sailing adventure and is still regarded as a classic of sailing literature., by John Kretschmer; from SailNet. Retrieved 6 March 2006. ''Joshua'' was beached, along with many other yachts, by a famous hurricane at Cabo San Lucas in 1982; with a new boat, ''Tamata'', Moitessier sailed back to Tahiti from the San Francisco Bay. He died in 1994.''A Voyage for Madmen'', pages 293–294.

When ''Teignmouth Electron'' was discovered drifting in the Atlantic on 10 July, a fund was started for Crowhurst's wife and children; Knox-Johnston donated his £5,000 prize to the fund, and more money was added by press and sponsors.''A Voyage for Madmen'', pages 283–285.  The news of his deception, mental breakdown, and suicide, as chronicled in his surviving logbooks, was made public a few weeks later, causing a sensation. Nicholas Tomalin and Ron Hall, two of the journalists connected with the race, wrote a 1970 book on Crowhurst's voyage, ''The Strange Last Voyage of Donald Crowhurst'', described by Hammond Innes in its ''Sunday Times'' review as "fascinating, uncomfortable reading" and a "meticulous investigation" of Crowhurst's downfall., from the back cover; at amazon.com. Retrieved 1 July 2006.

Tetley found it impossible to adapt to his old way of life after his adventure. He was awarded a consolation prize of £1,000, with which he decided to build a new trimaran for a round-the-world speed record attempt. His  boat ''Miss Vicky'' was built in 1971, but his search for sponsorship to pay for fitting-out met with consistent rejection. His book, ''Trimaran Solo'', sold poorly. Although he outwardly seemed to be coping, the repeated failures must have taken their toll, and in February 1972, he committed suicide.''A Voyage for Madmen'', pages 275–282.

Blyth devoted his life to the sea and to introducing others to its challenge. In 1970–1971 he sailed a sponsored boat, ''British Steel'', single-handedly around the world "the wrong way", against the prevailing winds. He subsequently took part in the Whitbread Round the World Yacht Race and founded the Global Challenge race, which allows amateurs to race around the world. His old rowing partner, John Ridgway, followed a similar course; he started an adventure school in Scotland, and circumnavigated the world twice under sail: once in the Whitbread Round the World Yacht Race, and once with his wife. King finally completed a circumnavigation in ''Galway Blazer II'' in 1973.''A Voyage for Madmen'', pages 294–295.

''Suhaili'' was sailed for some years more, including a trip to Greenland, and spent some years on display at the National Maritime Museum at Greenwich. She has since been returned to the water and is now based at the National Maritime Museum Cornwall; she is expected to take part in the 2006 ''Round the Island Race''., from This Is Hampshire.  Retrieved 17 October 2008. ''Teignmouth Electron'' was sold to a tour operator in Jamaica and eventually ended up damaged and abandoned on Cayman Brac, where she lies to this day.''A Voyage for Madmen'', pages 295–296.

There was considerable controversy over the race and its organisation, given the failure of most starters and the tragic outcome of Crowhurst's voyage; no follow-up race was held for some time. However, in 1982 the ''BOC Challenge'' race was organised; this single-handed round-the-world race with stops was inspired by the Golden Globe and has been held every four years since. In 1989, Philippe Jeantot founded the ''Vendée Globe'' race, a non-stop, single-handed, round-the-world race. Essentially the successor to the Golden Globe, this race is also held every four years and has attracted an enormous public following for the sport.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2e4d77d65fcfb46897c36c48c5123e45" name="Joshua001" sectnum="3#1">../img/2e4d77d65fcfb46897c36c48c5123e45.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>