<document id="4fabd0ceb387d5ac14d3a1eefb2e7281-2.5" name="Sunday_Times_Golden_Globe_Race" cat="26">
<text>
Blyth and Knox-Johnston were well down the Atlantic by this time. Knox-Johnston, the experienced seaman, was enjoying himself, but ''Suhaili'' had problems with leaking seams near the keel. However, he had managed a good repair by diving and caulking the seams underwater.''A World of My Own'', pages 42–44.

Blyth was not far ahead, and although leading the race, he was having far greater problems with his boat, which was suffering in the hard conditions. He had also discovered that the fuel for his generator had been contaminated, which effectively put his radio out of action. On 15 August, Blyth went in to Tristan da Cunha to pass a message to his wife, and spoke to crew from an anchored cargo ship, ''Gillian Gaggins''. On being invited aboard by her captain, a fellow Scot, Blyth found the offer impossible to refuse and went aboard, while the ship's engineers fixed his generator and replenished his fuel supply.

By this time he had already shifted his focus from the race to a more personal quest to discover his own limits; and so, despite his technical disqualification for receiving assistance, he continued sailing towards Cape Town. His boat continued to deteriorate, however, and on 13 September he put into East London. Having successfully sailed the length of the Atlantic and rounded Cape Agulhas in an unsuitable boat, he decided that he would take on the challenge of the sea again, but in a better boat and on his own terms.''A Voyage for Madmen'', pages pages 92–101.

Despite the retirements, other racers were still getting started. On Thursday, 22 August, Moitessier and Fougeron set off, with King following on Saturday (none of them wanted to leave on a Friday).''The Long Way'', page 3. With ''Joshua'' lightened for a race, Moitessier set a fast pace — more than twice as fast as Knox-Johnston over the same part of the course. Tetley sailed on 16 September,''Trimaran Solo'', pages 23—24. and on 23 September, Crowhurst's boat, ''Teignmouth Electron'', was finally launched in Norfolk. Under severe time pressure, Crowhurst planned to sail to Teignmouth, his planned departure point, in three days; but although the boat performed well downwind, the struggle against headwinds in the English Channel showed severe deficiencies in the boat's upwind performance, and the trip to Teignmouth took 13 days.''Strange Last Voyage'', pages 50—56.

Meanwhile, Moitessier was making excellent progress. On 29 September he passed Trindade in the south Atlantic, and on 20 October he reached Cape Town, where he managed to leave word of his progress. He sailed on east into the Southern Ocean, where he continued to make good speed, covering  on 28 October.''The Long Way'', pages 19–29, 36–45, 56.

Others were not so comfortable with the ocean conditions. On 30 October, Fougeron passed Tristan da Cunha, with King a few hundred nautical miles ahead.  The next day — Halloween — they both found themselves in a severe storm. Fougeron hove-to but still suffered a severe knockdown; King, who allowed his boat to tend to herself (a recognised procedure known as ''lying ahull''), had a much worse experience, as his boat was rolled, and he lost his foremast. Both men decided to retire from the race.''A Voyage for Madmen'', page 142, 149—151.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fababc22283ccd08d1a631e76dd01e9a" name="Satellite_image_of_Cape_peninsula" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/fababc22283ccd08d1a631e76dd01e9a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>