<document id="507f3aa1e9bd0536fda39bb8e2e15118-5.7" name="Hastings_Ismay,_1st_Baron_Ismay" cat="29">
<text>
In January 1943, Ismay accompanied Churchill to the Casablanca Conference."Mr. Churchill Meets Mr. Roosevelt" Ismay attended nearly all of the proceedings of the Conference, and helped work towards consensus where the Americans and British disagreed on issues.Ismay, pp. 286–287 Ismay was also appointed to the committee which wrote the formal report of the conference.US Department of State Historical Office, p. 640 After the conference, Ismay visited the American headquarters in Algiers to meet with Eisenhower, and helped resolve some differences of opinion between Eisenhower and his British colleagues.Ismay, p. 291 Wingate, p. 90

After Casablanca, Ismay accompanied Churchill to the third Washington Conference in May 1943.Ismay, p. 293 At the conference, Ismay first met the American Admiral William D. Leahy, who is often described as his American counterpart. The two developed a friendly relationship, and Leahy wrote in his memoirs: "General Sir Hastings Ismay became my favorite, perhaps because his position closely paralleled my own".Leahy, p. 163

After the Washington Conference came the Quebec Conference in August 1943. Once again, Ismay attended along with Churchill."The Prime Minister in Canada" The Quebec Conference was the first time that the Allied leaders discussed the full details of Operation Overlord, so Ismay spent much of his time explaining details of the operation to Churchill and other leaders.Ismay, p. 310 During the conference, Ismay also observed that Dudley Pound "had had a breakdown". He took the information to Churchill who demanded Pound's resignation a week later.Ismay, p. 316

Shortly after returning from Quebec, Ismay participated in his next conference, travelling with Anthony Eden to the Moscow Conference in October and November, where he served as Eden's top military adviser."Mr. Eden at Kremlin" At the conference, Ismay handled all of the Soviet questions about the planning for Operation Overlord,Ismay, p. 327 Wingate, p. 102  and met Joseph Stalin personally for the first time."Mr. Eden sees Marshal Stalin" After the conference, Ismay wrote that he "was optimistic about  post-war relations with Russia", showing his belief that the meeting had gone well.Ismay, p. 328

Only four days after returning from the Moscow Conference, Ismay left England again for the Cairo Conference and Teheran Conference with Churchill.Ismay, p. 332 One major source of conflict at the Cairo Conference was an American proposal to appoint an overall commander for the strategic bombing of Germany. Ismay and the British were strongly opposed, and Ismay wrote a long paper against the idea, which became the basis of British policy on the subject.Sainsbury, p. 208 At Teheran, Ismay helped to argue the case for Operation Overlord, but immediately after the conference he developed bronchitis and returned to England by ship, scrapping his other plans for the trip.Ismay, p. 342
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e75127b68be97cc596710151323bcbb3" name="Bundesarchiv_Bild_183-S68745,_Konferenz_von_Casablanca" sectnum="5.7#1">../img/e75127b68be97cc596710151323bcbb3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>