<document id="507f3aa1e9bd0536fda39bb8e2e15118-3.3" name="Hastings_Ismay,_1st_Baron_Ismay" cat="29">
<text>
In 1924, Air Vice-Marshal Philip Game suggested to Ismay that he apply for a seat at the RAF Staff College, Andover. Although Ismay "had no desire to learn to be a pilot", he was happy for the opportunity to return to England, and went to study at the college. Wingate, p. 18  After completing the program, he was approached about the possibility of serving as an Assistant Secretary of the Committee of Imperial Defence (CID) under Maurice Hankey. Ismay gladly accepted the position, starting work in December 1925.Ismay, pp. 41–42  In the six months between finishing the Staff College and beginning at the CID, Ismay returned to India and held a staff position at the headquarters of the Indian Army in Simla. Wingate, p. 19 

As Assistant Secretary, Ismay directed several of the subcommittees of the Committee of Imperial Defence, including those for Censorship and War Emergency Legislation, Principal Supply Officers, and Co-ordination of Departmental Action.Ismay, p. 53 As the Secretary of the Committee for the Co-ordination of Departmental Action, Ismay "was responsible for seeing that all plans and preparations made by Government Departments or sub-committees of the CID to meet the eventuality of war, were incorporated under appropriate headings in a document known as the War Book."Ismay, pp. 55–56 This task ended up consuming most of Ismay's time as Assistant Secretary, and gave him "exceptional insight into the ways of Whitehall."

While serving as Assistant Secretary, Ismay made important friends and gained the backing of Hankey, by whom he was "greatly valued". Largely through Hankey's influence, Ismay was nominated as a Companion of the Order of the Bath in the Civil Division,Roskill (Volume 1), p. 531 Wingate, p. 23  an honour which he received in 1931.Lewin, p. 439
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e2f2a4ea4e0bbf305c4448cfcee8d02a" name="Maurice_Hankey" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/e2f2a4ea4e0bbf305c4448cfcee8d02a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>