<document id="507f3aa1e9bd0536fda39bb8e2e15118-5.5" name="Hastings_Ismay,_1st_Baron_Ismay" cat="29">
<text>
In April 1940, Winston Churchill took control of the Military Co-ordination Committee, charged with overseeing all of the military services. He selected Ismay as his chief staff officer, which also gave Ismay the additional responsibility of serving on the Chiefs of Staff Committee. While serving under Churchill had been a life-long dream for Ismay, he was initially skeptical about the duties of his new position, which seemed unclear and poorly defined.Ismay, p. 113



On 10 May, after the beginning of the Battle of France, Chamberlain resigned, and Churchill became both Prime Minister and Minister of Defence.Ismay, p. 115 Wingate, p. 44  Ismay, who later called Churchill "the greatest War Prime Minister in our history", was "thrilled" by this development, and continued to act as Churchill's chief staff officer and military adviser.Ismay, p. 117 According to Churchill, the two developed a close "personal and official connection  was preserved unbroken and unweakened" throughout the war.Churchill (1948), p. 645 As part of this relationship, not long after Churchill became Prime Minister, he arranged for Ismay to be appointed Knight Commander of the Order of the Bath in June 1940."Knighthoods for the Services" From the very moment he became Prime Minister, Churchill "relied heavily on General Pug Ismay," who provided a crucial bridge to the military establishment.Lamb, p. 45 Ismay served as the "principal assistant to Mr. Churchill in his capacity as Minister of Defence", continued to serve as the Secretary of the Imperial Defence Chiefs of Staff Committee,"Prime Minister in the United States" and became Deputy Secretary of the War Cabinet."General Ismay Promoted" Ismay was crucial to running the war effort, as he was able to effectively link the military and civilian leadership. Jock Colville, Churchill's private secretary, wrote that Ismay had the "tact, patience, and skill in promoting compromise" needed to keep the war running smoothly."Colville, p. 161 Ismay had the additional advantage of being admired by the Service Chiefs for his long and distinguished record as a soldier.Colville, pp. 161–162

In his role, Ismay handled "nearly all military messages" from Churchill to the Service Chiefs.Churchill (1949), p. 22 Ismay also gave Churchill advice on military matters, and often "begged him to be reasonable"Gilbert, p. 662 when he contemplated foolish actions, believing that Churchill's greatest fault was his "impetuous nature and impatience with opposition."Colville, p. 165 When the Chiefs of Staff found Churchill's demands unfeasible, Ismay took the role of "converting the Prime Minister" to their viewpoint.Colville, p.163
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e937bae1154c4448db234a46e8c0e9da" name="Churchill_and_Generals" sectnum="5.5#1">../img/e937bae1154c4448db234a46e8c0e9da.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>