<document id="507f3aa1e9bd0536fda39bb8e2e15118-5.8" name="Hastings_Ismay,_1st_Baron_Ismay" cat="29">
<text>
In the first several months of 1944, Ismay spent almost all of his time planning for the Normandy Landings.Ismay, p. 343 As part of the planning, Ismay personally coordinated the plans for Operation Bodyguard and Operation Fortitude, which were designed to deceive the Germans about the planned Normandy landings.Wingate, p. 107–109 In March, Duncan Sandys, Churchill's nephew, told Ismay that Basil Liddell Hart, a noted strategist and historian, had somehow discovered the secret plans for the Normandy landings. This development had the potential to compromise the entire operation, so Ismay personally interviewed Liddell Hart, who claimed to have simply "worked it all out for himself" without any access to secret information.Evans After their interview, Ismay directed the matter to the MI5, who never found evidence of wrongdoing, although it is suspected that Liddell Hart may in fact have received information from military planners."Other subjects of Security Service enquiries"



On 20 May 1944, less than a month before the Normandy Landings were scheduled to take place, Ismay was promoted to the rank of full general."Sir H Ismay Promoted" After the successful D-Day landings, King George VI decided to visit the troops in Normandy, and selected Ismay to accompany him on the visit."Allied Chiefs with The King" In September, Ismay accompanied Churchill to another conference, the Second Quebec Conference.Ismay, p. 372 Ismay also accompanied Churchill on his visits to Moscow and Paris in late 1944.Ismay, p. 376

In February 1945, Ismay attended the Yalta Conference. He found the conference different from the previous ones where "the military element had been the prima donna, occupying the centre of the stage."Ismay, p. 387 Instead, at Yalta, political issues took precedence, leaving Ismay and other military advisers "waiting for calls that never came". Wingate, p. 122 

On VE Day, Ismay found it "quite impossible to be completely happy about the future," due to the lingering Japanese threat, and the rising threat of the Soviet Union.Ismay, p. 395 Nonetheless, he was happy to be one of only three men to hold the same high government position throughout the war in Europe, along with Edward Bridges, 1st Baron Bridges and the King.Ismay, pp. 395–396
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="dd14c81cf8ff13e5fa6f9648d996a684" name="Ismay_and_Simon" sectnum="5.8#1">../img/dd14c81cf8ff13e5fa6f9648d996a684.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>