<document id="507f3aa1e9bd0536fda39bb8e2e15118-7" name="Hastings_Ismay,_1st_Baron_Ismay" cat="29">
<text>
Shortly after Ismay's retirement, Lord Mountbatten of Burma was appointed as the last British Viceroy of India and Ismay offered to serve as his chief of staff.Ismay, pp. 409–410 Wingate, p. 138  Thus, in March 1947, Ismay left with Mountbatten for India to help preside over its transition to independence."New Viceroy in Delhi" After arriving in India, Ismay soon came to the conclusion that the situation there was dire, heading for civil war, and told Mountbatten that "India was a ship on fire in mid-ocean with ammunition in her hold."Collins, p. 95


When Ismay and Mountbatten arrived, they were committed to preserving a unified India, but Ismay soon realised "that the Moslem League would not agree to any plan which did not provide for the creation of Pakistan as an independent sovereign state."Ismay, p. 419 In April, after several unsuccessful meetings with Muhammad Ali Jinnah, Mountbatten came to the same conclusion and began drawing up plans for the partition.Collins, p. 120 Over the next month Mountbatten finalised his partition plan, and on 2 May 1947, he sent Ismay back to London to present it to the British government.Collins, p. 134 Ismay presented the plan to the Prime Minister and Cabinet, casting partition as a Hobson's choice.Ismay, pp. 420–421 Wingate, p. 154  Ismay stayed in England for the next month, and helped to alter the plan based on the cabinet's suggestions, before returning to India on 31 May.Ismay, pp. 421–422

Once the partition plan had been accepted, Ismay worked on implementing the details. In particular, Ismay dealt with the issue of dividing the Indian Army. Based on his own experiences and love of the Indian Army, Ismay did his "utmost to persuade" the leaders of the new Indian and Pakistani states not to separate the army immediately. His efforts failed due to the opposition of Jinnah.Ismay, p. 428

Ismay also travelled to Kashmir to ask Hari Singh to hold an immediate referendum over whether his territory would join India or Pakistan. Once again, Ismay was unsuccessful and Singh "changed the subject" each time that Ismay tried to discuss the referendum.Ismay, p. 433 Throughout the period immediately following independence, Ismay also tried to ensure that stories printed in the Indian and Pakistani press about the partition were accurate, but once again he was largely unsuccessful.Ismay, p. 442

The situation in India continued to deteriorate throughout the summer and autumn of 1947.  Nevertheless, Ismay and Mountbatten had agreed that Ismay would remain in his position for only three to four months after partition. In December 1947, he left India to return to England.Ismay, pp. 445–446 Shortly after his return, Ismay served briefly on the British delegation to the United Nations to deal with the Kashmir issue. Ismay played only a limited role, as the Pakistanis suspected him of pro-Indian sympathies.Ismay, p. 447 Wingate, p. 176–177
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5a00e7a3b9ca9408e1822627d8c55329" name="Mountbatten_Jinnah" sectnum="7#1">../img/5a00e7a3b9ca9408e1822627d8c55329.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>