<document id="50ae8313d6fefcbddcc9b5d3d1c7496e-3" name="Charlotte_Stuart,_Duchess_of_Albany" cat="25">
<text>
Only after his childless marriage to Louise was over, and Charles had fallen seriously ill, did he take an interest in Charlotte. She was now thirty, and she had not seen her father since she was seven. On 23 March 1783, he altered his will to make her his heir and a week later he signed an act of legitimisation. This act, recognising her as his natural daughter and entitling her to succeed to his private estate, was sent to Louis XVI of France. Henry Stuart, however, wrote contesting the legitimisation as being irregular and confusing to the succession. Louis XVI eventually did confirm the act and register it with the Parlement of Paris, but not until 6 September 1787. 

In July 1784, having granted Louise a legal separation, he summoned Charlotte to Florence, where he was now resident, and in November installed her in the Palazzo Guadagni as Duchess of Albany, styling her "Her Royal Highness" – and appointing her to the Order of the Thistle. Nevertheless, being illegitimate at birth, Charlotte still had no right of succession to the Stuart claim to the British throne. However, by this stage the claims were of little value: European rulers had long since ceased to take Charles seriously; even the Pope was refusing to recognise his royal title, and the famous Casanova had wittily called him the "pretender-in-vain". He was reduced to styling himself the 'Count d'Albany'.

That a Stuart restoration was now unlikely, did not prevent the Prince presenting Charlotte as the next generation of the cause. He had medals struck for her, bearing the figure of Hope, the map of England and the Stuart arms, with legends such as ''"Spes Tamen Est Una"'' (there is one hope). He also had her idealised in art; the Scottish artist Gavin Hamilton was commissioned to draw her in chalk in the neo-classical style, whilst Hugh Douglas Hamilton painted a flattering portrait in a tiara.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c8f09bd2b50ca3868ba5041c5906624e" name="CharlotteStuart2" sectnum="3#1">../img/c8f09bd2b50ca3868ba5041c5906624e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>