<document id="510ba149696f075bf15c53a85280915e-1" name="Surrender_of_Japan" cat="29">
<text>
By 1945, the Japanese had suffered an unbroken string of defeats for nearly two years, in the South West Pacific, the Marianas campaign, and the Philippines campaign. In July 1944, following the loss of Saipan, General Hideki Tōjō was replaced as prime minister by General Kuniaki Koiso, who declared that the Philippines would be the site of the decisive battle.Frank, 90.  After the Japanese loss of the Philippines, Koiso was in turn replaced by Admiral Kantarō Suzuki. The first half of 1945 saw the Allies capture the nearby islands of Iwo Jima and Okinawa. Okinawa was to be a staging area for the Invasion of Japan itself.Skates, 158, 195

The Allied submarine campaign and the mining of Japanese coastal waters had largely destroyed the Japanese merchant fleet. Japan, which has few natural resources, was dependent on raw materials imported from the Asian mainland and from the conquered territory in the Dutch East Indies—particularly oil.Frank, 87–88 The destruction of the Japanese merchant fleet, combined with the strategic bombing of Japanese industry, had wrecked Japan's war economy. Production of coal, iron, steel, rubber and other vital supplies were only a fraction of their pre-war levels.Frank, 81 Robert A. Pape ''"Why Japan Surrendered,"'' International Security, Vol. 18, No. 2 (Fall 1993), 154–201. 

The rebuilt battlecruiser  was sunk at her moorings in the naval base of Kure on 24 July during a series of bombings.

As a result of the losses it had suffered, the Imperial Japanese Navy (IJN) had ceased to be an effective fighting force. Following a series of raids on the Japanese shipyard at Kure, Japan, the only major warships in fighting order were six aircraft carriers, four cruisers, and one battleship, none of which could be adequately fueled. Although 19 destroyers and 38 submarines were still operational, their use was limited by the lack of fuel.Feifer, 418Reynolds, 363

Faced with the prospect of an invasion of the Japanese Home Islands starting with Kyūshū, the War Journal of the Imperial Headquarters concluded:We can no longer direct the war with any hope of success. The only course left is for Japan's one hundred million people to sacrifice their lives by charging the enemy to make them lose the will to fight.Frank, 89, citing Daikichi Irokawa, ''The Age of Hirohito''. Note that Japan consistently overstated its population as 100 million, when in fact the 1944 census counted 72 million. 

As a last-ditch attempt to stop the Allied advances, the Japanese Imperial High Command planned an all-out defense of Kyushu codenamed Operation Ketsu-Go.Skates, 100–115 This plan was to be a radical departure from the "defense in depth" plans used in the invasions of Peleliu, Iwo Jima and Okinawa. Instead, everything was staked on the beachhead; more than 3,000 kamikazes would be sent to attack the amphibious transports before troops and cargo were disembarked on the beach. If this did not drive the Allies away, they planned to send another 3,500 kamikazes along with 5,000 ''Shinyo'' suicide boats and the remaining destroyers and submarines&mdash;"the last of the Navy's operating fleet"&mdash;to the beach. If the Allies had fought through this and successfully landed on Kyushu, only 3,000 planes would have been left to defend the remaining islands, although Kyushu would be "defended to the last" regardless. A set of caves were excavated near Nagano. These caves, the Matsushiro Underground Imperial Headquarters, were to be used in the event of invasion by the army to direct the war and to house the Emperor and his family.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7efe886e85712460cbd9c7893eda2200" name="US_landings" sectnum="1#1">../img/7efe886e85712460cbd9c7893eda2200.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>