<document id="5188f17b561517f7d720197b074d4617-2.1.5" name="Ice_hockey_at_the_Olympic_Games" cat="26">
<text>
At the 1984 Winter Olympics in Sarajevo, Yugoslavia, the Soviet Union won its sixth gold medal. Czechoslovakia and Sweden won the silver and bronze medals. The 1988 Winter Olympics were held in Calgary, Alberta, Canada, where the Soviet team captured its seventh and final gold medal. The Soviets' last Olympic game was a loss to Finland. The Finnish team was not considered a serious medal contender—it had competed in the World Championships since 1939 and had not won a single medal. However, Finland upset the Soviets 2–1 and won silver.Podnieks and Szemberg 2008, . The IIHF decided to change the tournament format because in several cases, the gold medal winner had been decided before the final day of play. During a congress in 1990, the IIHF introduced a playoff system.Podnieks and Szemberg 2008, . The new system was used at the 1992 Winter Olympics in Albertville, France. Preliminary round-robin games were held and followed by an eight-team cup-system style medal round that culminated in a gold medal game.

Before 1989, players who lived in the Soviet Union, Czechoslovakia, and other nations behind the Iron Curtain were not allowed to leave and play in the NHL.Podnieks and Szemberg 2008, . Soviet officials agreed to allow players to leave following the 1989 World Championships. Many of the Soviet Union's top players left to play in the NHL, including the entire "Green Unit"—Igor Larionov, Viacheslav Fetisov, Vladimir Krutov, Sergei Makarov and Alexei Kasatonov. The Soviet Union dissolved in December 1991. Nine former Soviet states became part of the IIHF and started competing internationally, including Belarus, Kazakhstan, Latvia and Ukraine.Podnieks and Szemberg 2008, . At the 1992 Olympics, Armenia, Belarus, Kazakhstan, Russia, Ukraine and Uzbekistan competed as one entity, known as the Unified Team. In the final, the Unified Team defeated Canada to win gold while Czechoslovakia won the bronze.Podnieks and Szemberg 2008, .

Czechoslovakia split into the Czech Republic and Slovakia in January 1993. The IIHF recognized the Czech Republic as the successor to Czechoslovakia, allowing the team to retain its position in the top World Championship division, while Slovakia started in the lowest division (Pool C) in 1994 and was forced to work its way up.Podnieks and Szemberg 2008, . Both nations competed in the tournament at the 1994 Winter Olympics, as did Russia. Slovakia and Finland finished the preliminary round undefeated. Slovakia lost to Russia in their medal round quarter-final and Russia went on to lose to Finland in the bronze medal game. The gold medal game was between Sweden and Canada. The two teams finished regulation and overtime play with a 2–2 tie. In the resulting shootout, the first in Olympic competition, both nations scored two goals, which resulted in a sudden death shootout. Peter Forsberg of Sweden scored one of the most famous goals in Olympic history by faking a forehand shot, then sliding a one-handed backhand shot past goaltender Corey Hirsch. Canada's final shooter did not score and Sweden won the game and its first gold medal.Podnieks and Szemberg 2008, .
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="79478ccaf656bead7d7b162f6f027f0d" name="Helminen's_last_game" sectnum="2.1.5#1">../img/79478ccaf656bead7d7b162f6f027f0d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>