<document id="5188f17b561517f7d720197b074d4617-2.3" name="Ice_hockey_at_the_Olympic_Games" cat="26">
<text>
Both the men's and women's tournaments will be held at the 2010 Winter Olympics in Vancouver, Canada and the 2014 Winter Olympics in Sochi, Russia. The games of the 2010 tournament will be held at the UBC Winter Sports Centre and General Motors Place, which is to be renamed Canada Hockey Place during the event because corporate sponsorship is not allowed for an Olympic venue.

Twelve teams have qualified for the men's event and will be split into three groups of four teams. The NHL break will begin after February 14 and the tournament will start on February 16. At the NHL's request, the number of preliminary games was lowered to three. Following the completion of the preliminary round, all teams will be ranked 1 through 12 based on points. The top four ranked teams will receive byes to the quarter-finals, and the other eight teams will play for the remaining four positions. Following that, the final eight teams will compete in a playoff.

For the women's tournament, eight teams have qualified, including Slovakia for the first time. They will be split into two divisions of four teams and each team will play three preliminary games. Following the preliminary round, the top two teams from each division will advance to the medal round playoff. The other four will play classification games. Each team is allowed to have 15 to 18 skaters and two goaltenders.

It will be the first time since NHL players were allowed to compete that the Olympics will be held in a city with an NHL team. For the first time, Olympic games will be played on a narrower NHL-sized ice rink, measuring 61 metres × 26 metres (200 ft × 85 ft), instead of the international size of 61 m × 30 m (200 ft × 98.5 ft). This change is expected to save $10 million (CAD) in construction costs and allow more spectators to attend games. Each team is allowed to have between 15 and 20 skaters (forwards and defencemen) and two or three goaltenders, all of whom must be citizens of the nation they play for.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="cbe686a66a261887f4650a0f175e8a2f" name="Vancouver-gmplace3" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/cbe686a66a261887f4650a0f175e8a2f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>