<document id="5188f17b561517f7d720197b074d4617-2.1.4" name="Ice_hockey_at_the_Olympic_Games" cat="26">
<text>
The Winter Olympics returned to Lake Placid, New York in 1980. Twelve teams participated in the tournament, including Canada for the first time since 1968. The Soviet Union entered the tournament as heavy favourites and were considered natural rivals with the American team due to the Cold War. The Americans, coached by Herb Brooks and consisting mainly of college students, tied Sweden and scored an upset win over Czechoslovakia in the preliminary round. They finished with four wins and a tie and advanced to the medal round, which also consisted of Sweden, Finland and the Soviet Union.Podnieks and Szemberg 2008, .

The tournament became most famous for the "Miracle on Ice", the February 22 medal-round game between the Soviet Union and the United States that took place at the Olympic Center (now known as the Herb Brooks Arena). The Soviets scored first, then took a 2–1 lead, but the Americans tied the game with one second left in the first period. In the second period, Soviet goaltender Vladislav Tretiak was replaced by Vladimir Myshkin. The Soviets regained the lead early in the second period but the Americans kept the game close thanks to the goaltending of Jim Craig. In the final period, the Americans tied the game and captain Mike Eruzione scored with exactly 10 minutes to play in the contest to give the Americans a 4–3 lead. Craig withstood another series of Soviet shots to finish the match with the win. In the final seconds of the game, American Broadcasting Company sportscaster Al Michaels delivered his famous line: "Do you believe in miracles? Yes!"

A common myth is that the Americans won gold the night they beat the Soviets. However, the medals were awarded based on points accumulated against teams that made the medal round. The Americans did not win the gold until February 24, when they defeated Finland 4–2 and finished the tournament undefeated. The Soviets defeated Sweden and won the silver. In 2008, the IIHF picked the Miracle on Ice as the top international hockey story of the past 100 years.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="cc6f3e1f17bd0647ca0dea693f9b4ce3" name="2002_Winter_Olympics_flame_-_Cropped" sectnum="2.1.4#1">../img/cc6f3e1f17bd0647ca0dea693f9b4ce3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>