<document id="5188f17b561517f7d720197b074d4617-2.1.3" name="Ice_hockey_at_the_Olympic_Games" cat="26">
<text>
The Soviet Union competed in its first World Championship in 1954, defeating Canada and winning the gold medal.Podnieks and Szemberg 2008, . At the 1956 Winter Olympics in Cortina d'Ampezzo, Italy, the Soviet team went undefeated and won its first gold medal. Canada's team lost to the Soviets and the United States in the medal round, winning the bronze. The 1960 Winter Olympics, in Squaw Valley, United States, saw the first, and to date only, team from Australia compete in the tournament. Canada, the Soviet Union, Czechoslovakia and Sweden were the top four teams heading into the Games, but were all defeated by the American team, which won all seven games en route to its first Olympic gold medal. Canada won the silver medal and the Soviet Union won the bronze.Podnieks and Szemberg 2008, .

At the 1964 Winter Olympics in Innsbruck, Austria, the Soviet team won all seven of its games, earning the gold medal. Canada finished the tournament with five wins and two losses, putting the team in a three-way tie for second place with Sweden and Czechoslovakia. Before 1964, the tie-breaking procedure was based on goal difference in games against teams in the medal round; under that system, Canada would have placed third ahead of the Czechoslovakian team. During the tournament the procedure was changed to take all games into consideration, which meant that the Canadians finished fourth. At the time, the Olympics counted as the World Championships; under their (unchanged) rules, Canada should have received bronze for the World Championships.

Soviet domination continued at the 1968 Winter Olympics held in Grenoble, France, as the team won its third gold medal. Czechoslovakia and Canada won the silver and bronze medals. It was the last time that the Olympics were counted as the World Championships. In 1970, Canada withdrew from international ice hockey competition following a dispute over the use of professional players, and the team did not participate in the 1972 or 1976 Winter Olympics. Led by goaltender Vladislav Tretiak and forwards Valeri Kharlamov, Alexander Yakushev, Vladimir Petrov and Boris Mikhailov, the Soviet team won gold at both the 1972 Games in Sapporo, Japan and 1976 Winter Olympics in Innsbruck, Austria.Podnieks and Szemberg 2008, . In 1971, the United States finished last at the World Championships and was relegated to Pool B. The team qualified for the 1972 Olympics and won silver, making it the first Pool B team to win an Olympic medal.Podnieks and Szemberg 2008, . Czechoslovakia won the bronze medal in 1972. In 1976, Czechoslovakia won the silver and West Germany won bronze. Along with Canada, the Swedish, East German and Norwegian teams did not participate in the 1976 tournament in protest of their inability to use professional players.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="be3e9e60329bf214946f21ea3b477d5c" name="Vladislav_Tretiak" sectnum="2.1.3#1">../img/be3e9e60329bf214946f21ea3b477d5c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>