<document id="5188f17b561517f7d720197b074d4617-2.1.1" name="Ice_hockey_at_the_Olympic_Games" cat="26">
<text>
The men's tournament held at the 1920 Summer Olympics was organised by a committee that included future IIHF president Paul Loicq. The tournament used the Bergvall System, in which three rounds were played.Podnieks and Szemberg 2008, . The first round was an elimination tournament that determined the gold medal winner. The second round consisted of the teams that were defeated by the gold medal winner; the winner of that round was awarded the silver medal. The final round was played between teams that had lost to the gold or silver medal winners; the winner of that round received the bronze medal.

The tournament was played from April 23 to April 29. Seven teams participated: Canada, Czechoslovakia, the United States, Switzerland, Sweden, France and Belgium. Canada chose to send the Allan Cup-winning Winnipeg Falcons. The Americans began a tournament to determine their representative team but abandoned it, deciding instead to send an all-star team that included four Canadian-born players. The Swedish team consisted of mostly bandy players, many of whom had only started playing hockey in preparation for the tournament. Canada won all three of the team's games in the first round and won the gold medal, defeating Sweden in the final and outscoring opponents 27–1. In the two subsequent rounds, the United States and Czechoslovakia won the silver and bronze medals respectively. The Bergvall System was criticised, especially in Sweden, because the Swedish team had to play six games (winning three) while the bronze medal winning Czech team only had to play three (winning one). Erik Bergvall, the creator of the system, stated that it was used incorrectly and that a tournament of all of the losing teams from the first round should have been played for the silver medal. Because of these criticisms, the Bergvall System was not used again for ice hockey.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f27dff9a74ce58623f9c085454cfcf57" name="1920_olympics_poster" sectnum="2.1.1#1">../img/f27dff9a74ce58623f9c085454cfcf57.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>