<document id="51912e2b3eaebf7f0d8a63e0319174a4-4.2" name="Tarbosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
The skull of ''Tarbosaurus'' was completely described for the first time in 2003. Scientists noted key differences between ''Tarbosaurus'' and the North American tyrannosaurids. Many of these differences are related to the handling of stress by the skull bones during a bite. When the upper jaw bit down on an object, force was transmitted up through the maxilla, the primary tooth-bearing bone of the upper jaw, into surrounding skull bones. In North American tyrannosaurids, this force went from the maxilla into the fused nasal bones on top of the snout, which were firmly connected in the rear to the lacrimal bones by bony struts. These struts locked the two bones together, suggesting that force was then transmitted from the nasals to the lacrimals.

''Tarbosaurus'' lacked these bony struts, and the connection between the nasals and lacrimals was weak. Instead, a backwards projection of the maxilla was massively developed in ''Tarbosaurus'' and fit inside a sheath formed from the lacrimal. This projection was a thin, bony plate in North American tyrannosaurids. The large backwards projection suggests that force was transmitted more directly from the maxilla to the lacrimal in ''Tarbosaurus''. The lacrimal was also more firmly anchored to the frontal and prefrontal bones in ''Tarbosaurus''. The well-developed connections between the maxilla, lacrimal, frontal and prefrontal would have made its entire upper jaw more rigid.

Another major difference between ''Tarbosaurus'' and its North American relatives was its more rigid mandible (lower jaw). While many theropods, including North American tyrannosaurids, had some degree of flexibility between the bones in the rear of the mandible and the dentary in the front, ''Tarbosaurus'' had a locking mechanism formed from a ridge on the surface of the angular, which articulated with a square process on the rear of the dentary.

Some scientists have hypothesized that the more rigid skull of ''Tarbosaurus'' was an adaptation to hunting the massive titanosaurid sauropods found in the Nemegt Formation, which did not exist in most of North America during the Late Cretaceous. The differences in skull mechanics also have an impact on tyrannosaurid phylogeny. ''Tarbosaurus''-like articulations between the skull bones are also seen in ''Alioramus'' from Mongolia, suggesting that it, and not ''Tyrannosaurus'', is the closest relative of ''Tarbosaurus''. Similarities between ''Tarbosaurus'' and ''Tyrannosaurus'' might therefore be related to their large size, independently developed through convergent evolution.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="feb1084c061a063a821cf01afb3fe44b" name="Tarbosaurus_-_Copenhagen" sectnum="4.2#1">../img/feb1084c061a063a821cf01afb3fe44b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>