<document id="51912e2b3eaebf7f0d8a63e0319174a4-4.3" name="Tarbosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
A ''Tarbosaurus'' skull found in 1948 by Soviet and Mongolian scientists (PIN 553-1, originally called ''Gorgosaurus lancinator'') included the skull cavity that held the brain. Making a plaster cast, called an ''endocast'', of the inside of this cavity  allowed Maleev to make preliminary observations about the shape of a ''Tarbosaurus'' brain. A newer polyurethane rubber cast allowed a more detailed study of ''Tarbosaurus'' brain structure and function.

''Tyrannosaurus rex'' brain structure has also been analyzed, and ''Tarbosaurus'' was similar, differing only in the positions of some cranial nerve roots, including the trigeminal and accessory nerves. Tyrannosaurid brains were more similar to those of crocodilians and other reptiles than to birds. The total brain volume for a 12 meter (40 foot) ''Tarbosaurus'' is estimated at only 184 centimeters3 (11.2 in3). The large size of the olfactory bulbs, as well as the terminal and olfactory nerves, suggest that ''Tarbosaurus'' had a keen sense of smell, as was also the case with ''Tyrannosaurus''. The vomeronasal bulb is large and differentiated from the olfactory bulb, indicating a well-developed Jacobsen's organ, which was used to detect pheromones. This may imply that ''Tarbosaurus'' had complex mating behavior. The auditory nerve was also large, suggesting good hearing, which may have been useful for auditory communication and spatial awareness. The nerve had a well-developed vestibular component as well, which implies a good sense of balance and coordination. In contrast, the nerves and brain structures associated with eyesight were smaller and undeveloped. The midbrain tectum, responsible for visual processing in reptiles, was very small in ''Tarbosaurus'', as were the optic nerve and the oculomotor nerve, which controls eye movement. Unlike ''Tyrannosaurus'', which had forward-facing eyes that provided some degree of binocular vision, ''Tarbosaurus'' had a narrower skull more typical of other tyrannosaurids in which the eyes faced primarily sideways. All of this suggests that ''Tarbosaurus'' relied more on its senses of smell and hearing than on its eyesight.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="92be18ea291e1615d9ab145183299164" name="Tarbosaurus_skull" sectnum="4.3#1">../img/92be18ea291e1615d9ab145183299164.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>