<document id="51912e2b3eaebf7f0d8a63e0319174a4-5" name="Tarbosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
The vast majority of ''Tarbosaurus'' fossils are known from the Nemegt Formation of southern Mongolia. This geologic formation has never been dated radiometrically, but the fauna present in the fossil record indicate it was probably deposited during the Maastrichtian stage, at the end of the Late Cretaceous. The Maastrichtian stage occurred 70 to 65 million years ago. The Subashi Formation, in which ''Shanshanosaurus'' remains were discovered, is also Maastrichtian in age.

Nemegt sediments preserve large river channels and soil deposits that indicate a far more humid climate than those suggested by the underlying Barun Goyot and Djadochta Formations. However, caliche deposits indicate at least periodic droughts. Sediment was deposited in the channels and floodplains of large rivers. Occasional mollusc fossils are found, as well as a variety of other aquatic animals like fish and turtles. Crocodilians included several species of ''Shamosuchus'', a genus with teeth adapted for crushing shells. Mammal fossils are exceedingly rare in the Nemegt Formation, but many birds are known, including the enantiornithine ''Gurilynia'' and the hesperornithiform ''Judinornis'', as well as ''Teviornis'', an early representative of the still-existing Anseriformes (waterfowl), a bird order. Scientists have described many dinosaurs from the Nemegt, including ankylosaurids such as ''Tarchia'' and pachycephalosaurs such as ''Homalocephale'' and ''Prenocephale''. By far the largest predator of the time, adult ''Tarbosaurus'' most likely preyed upon large hadrosaurs such as ''Saurolophus'' and ''Barsboldia'' or sauropods such as ''Nemegtosaurus'' and ''Opisthocoelicaudia''.  Adults would have received little competition from small theropods such as troodontids (''Borogovia'', ''Tochisaurus'', ''Saurornithoides''), oviraptorosaurs (''Elmisaurus'', ''Nemegtomaia'', ''Rinchenia'') or ''Bagaraatan'', sometimes considered a basal tyrannosauroid. Other theropods, like the gigantic ''Therizinosaurus'', may have been herbivorous, and ornithomimosaurs such as ''Anserimimus'', ''Gallimimus'' and ''Deinocheirus'' might have been omnivores that only took small prey and were therefore no competition for ''Tarbosaurus''. However, as in other large tyrannosaurids as well as modern Komodo dragons, juveniles and subadult ''Tarbosaurus'' may have filled niches between the massive adults and these smaller theropods.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="191f73325ae3cbc7c7633d26b4ddaa67" name="TarbosaurusDB" sectnum="5#1">../img/191f73325ae3cbc7c7633d26b4ddaa67.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>