<document id="51a6a166bfaf59dce23a10b13f17d6a7-3" name="England_expects_that_every_man_will_do_his_duty" cat="14">
<text>
The phrase has become well known in Britain because of Lord Nelson's enduring fame and the importance of the Battle of Trafalgar in British history. Generations of British schoolchildren have been taught about Trafalgar, alongside other seminal moments of British history such as the Battle of Hastings, Magna Carta, the Gunpowder Plot, and the Battle of Britain.

Charles Dickens quotes it in Chapter 43 of ''Martin Chuzzlewit'': 
:"...as the poet informs us, England expects Every man to do his duty, England is the most sanguine country on the face of the earth, and will find itself continually disappointed."Martin Chuzzlewit, Chapter 43.

In Lewis Carroll's ''The Hunting of the Snark'', the Bellman says: 
:"For England Expects — I forbear to proceed. Tis a maxim tremendous, but trite."The Hunting of the Snark, Fit the Fourth, 10th stanza, lines 1 and 2. 

In Ogden Nash's collection of poems ''I'm a Stranger Here Myself (1938)'' there is a short poem "England Expects" 

It was also referenced by Margaret Thatcher during her crucial speech to the cabinet which finally persuaded them to rally behind her over the divisive issue of the Poll Tax. Further afield, it has been used by James Joyce in his novel, ''Ulysses'', which contains numerous repetitions of Nelson's message, including several that are deliberately fragmented or misquoted (even as "Ireland expects every man will do his duty"). In the United States, former Secretary of the Navy Gordon England wore a tie with the flags representing the famous quote when he visited naval vessels. 
The phrase is said by a character on a raft in ''Jaws 2'' pretending that he is a British naval commander just before the shark attacks.

Today "England expects...", as an abbreviated version of the phrase, is often adapted for use in the media, especially in relation to the expectations for the victory of English sporting teams. Such is the sentence's connotation with sport that a recent book on the history of the England national football team by James Corbett was entitled ''England Expects''. A BBC Scotland television drama also bears its name.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a200a2fae60ceac5f08826b9dabd713a" name="England_Expects_Plaque" sectnum="3#1">../img/a200a2fae60ceac5f08826b9dabd713a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>