<document id="5261f6b91eebbb90ea8e7fddfa3b0170-5.2" name="Aspasia" cat="14">
<text>
Aspasia appears in several significant works of modern literature. Her romantic attachment with Pericles has inspired some of the most famous novelists and poets of the last centuries. In particular the romanticists of the 19th century and the historical novelists of the 20th century found in their story an inexhaustible source of inspiration. In 1835 Lydia Maria Child, an American abolitionist, novelist, and journalist, published ''Philothea'', a classical romance set in the days of Pericles and Aspasia. This book is regarded as the most successful and elaborate of the author's productions, because the female characters, especially Aspasia, are portrayed with great beauty and delicacy.E.A. Duyckinc-G.L. Duyckinck, ''Cyclopedia of American Literature'', 198

In 1836, Walter Savage Landor, an English writer and poet, published ''Pericles and Aspasia'', one of his most famous books. ''Pericles and Aspasia'' is a rendering of classical Athens through a series of imaginary letters, which contain numerous poems. The letters are frequently unfaithful to actual history but attempt to capture the spirit of the Age of Pericles.R. MacDonald Alden, ''Readings in English Prose'', 195 Robert Hamerling is another novelist and poet who was inspired by Aspasia's personality. In 1876 he published his novel ''Aspasia'', a book about the manners and morals of the Age of Pericles and a work of cultural and historical interest. Giacomo Leopardi, an Italian poet influenced by the movement of romanticism, published a group of five poems known as the ''circle of Aspasia''. These Leopardi poems were inspired by his painful experience of desperate and unrequited love for a woman named Fanny Targioni Tozzetti. Leopardi called this person Aspasia, after the companion of Pericles. M. Brose, ''A Companion to European Romanticism'', 271

In 1918, novelist and playwright George Cram Cook produced his first full-length play, ''The Athenian Women'', which portrays Aspasia leading a strike for peace.D.D. Anderson, ''The Literature of the Midwest'', 120 Cook combined an anti-war theme with a Greek setting.M Noe,  American writer Gertrude Atherton in ''The Immortal Marriage'' (1927) treats the story of Pericles and Aspasia and illustrates the period of the Samian War, the Peloponnesian War and the Plague of Athens. Taylor Caldwell's ''Glory and the Lightning'' (1974) is another novel that portrays the historical relationship of Aspasia and Pericles.L.A. Tritle, The Peloponnesian War, 199
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a1fe5f216a8e1b373de3203a65a89346" name="Aspasia_painting" sectnum="5.2#1">../img/a1fe5f216a8e1b373de3203a65a89346.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>