<document id="52973432b8eb57cdc3309a4215490d46-2.4" name="HMS_Cardiff_(D108)" cat="29">
<text>
After the Gulf War, ''Cardiff''’s assignments included a deployment with the Standing Naval Force Mediterranean, a post Cold War NATO immediate reaction force in the Mediterranean, and counter-narcotics patrols in the West Indies, during which she also assisted with relief tasks on the island of Eleuthera in the wake of Hurricane Andrew. ''Cardiff'' later returned to the Gulf for seven months.

On 14 October 1994, in response to renewed Iraqi deployment of troops near the Kuwaiti border, the US-led Operation Vigilant Warrior began.Pike 2005. The operation was designed to deter Saddam's "sabre-rattling" by sending large amounts of allied military forces to Kuwait; HM Ships  and ''Cardiff'' were the UK contribution. The operation ended on 21 December 1994, when Saddam pulled back his forces.


Upon her return to the UK from Operation Vigilant Warrior, ''Cardiff'' participated in the 1995 NATO exercise "Strong Resolve", a training exercise conducted every four years in dual crisis management. The ship next underwent Operational Sea Training (OST) at Portland, in preparation for assuming the duty of Fleet Ready Escort, which required a ship to be available to deploy anywhere in the world at short notice. After completing OST, she attended the 50th VE Day anniversary in Copenhagen and Oslo and provided navigational sea training for frigate and destroyer navigating officer candidates. A visit to her namesake city of Cardiff for VJ Day celebrations followed, after which she sailed to Plymouth for a trials and weapon training programme. She then took part in Operation Bright Star, a multi-national exercise conducted every two years in Egypt. In November, ''Cardiff'' became the first Royal Navy ship to enter the Lebanese capital of Beirut in 27 years, spurring the creation of the Beirut Phoenicians Rugby Club, followed by visits to Tunisia and Gibraltar.

In 2000, as part of the Royal Navy's Atlantic Patrol Task North, ''Cardiff'' spent six months in the Caribbean with RFA ''Black Rover''. They provided relief aid to the island of Caye Caulker, near Belize, in the wake of Hurricane Keith. In addition to clearing routes, distributing supplies, and making buildings and electrical cables safe, ''Cardiff''’s surgeon and medical team monitored sanitation. In October, they also took part in the NATO exercise "Unified Spirit", held off the east coast of the United States. "Unified Spirit" is a training exercise conducted every four years in NATO-led "out-of-area" UN peace support operations. In the same year she participated in the US Navy Fleet Battle Exercise after her combat system was integrated into the Digital Fires Network.

''Cardiff'' conducted her last Armilla Patrol in early 2003. During her time in the Persian Gulf, ''Cardiff'' prevented more than £2 million of illegal cargo from being smuggled out of Iraq, inspected 178 vessels, and seized more than 25,000 tonnes of oil. The destroyer was relieved by  before the beginning of the Iraq War and returned to Portsmouth on 4 April 2003. In late 2003, the ship was involved in the annual Sea Days demonstration exercise, and in October was used for tests of QinetiQ's Maritime Tactical Network.

In 2005, she participated in the Trafalgar 200 International Fleet Review, just two weeks before she was decommissioned. In this post Gulf War period, the Royal Navy's first female chaplain also served onboard.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="34294f889e111c70b5c41d4e97e49d84" name="HMS_Cardiff_Marines_2002_2" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/34294f889e111c70b5c41d4e97e49d84.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>