<document id="52973432b8eb57cdc3309a4215490d46-2.3" name="HMS_Cardiff_(D108)" cat="29">
<text>
When Saddam Hussein's Iraq invaded Kuwait on 2 August 1990, British Secretary of State for Defence Tom King soon announced that the UK military contribution to the region was to be increased.Hine 1991, pp. 39, 43. A coalition of nations was formed, and a combined naval force entered the Persian Gulf and sailed north, neutralising the Iraqi Navy as it went, and then began conducting naval gunfire support and mine counter-measure missions in preparation for the main amphibious landing force.

In September 1990, HM Ships ''Cardiff'',  and  were formed into Group X-ray and sailed to the Gulf to relieve Armilla Group Whiskey, which consisted of HM Ships ,  and . ''Cardiff'' and  were to form part of the air defence barrier protecting three United States aircraft carriers: ,  and . ''Cardiff'' had other responsibilities, including surface surveillance and boarding operations, to maintain the security around the task force.


Royal Navy Lynxes worked in combination with US Seahawks during the Gulf War. The American helicopters lacked an effective anti-ship missile, but had superior surveillance capability compared to the British Lynx. They would locate hostile boats for the British helicopters, which would then attack the target with its Sea Skua missiles. In total, Lynx helicopters flew nearly 600 sorties during the Gulf War, while their crews maintained flying rates three times their norm.

''Cardiff''’s Lynx helicopter, no. 335 of 815 NAS, saw more of the combat in the Gulf War than ''Cardiff'' actually did. On 24 January 1991, no. 335 spotted three Iraqi minesweepers off Qaruh Island, attacked, and sank two. Later that day, the island was captured by coalition forces, becoming the first Kuwaiti territory to be liberated. Five days later, with Lynxes from ''Gloucester'' and ''Brazen'', no. 335 attacked invading Iraqi vessels en-route to the Battle of Khafji. ''Cardiff'' and her group were relieved in late January by Group Yankee, comprising HM Ships , ,  and .
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8408fddea67ed5b46a0555839a8ce8fc" name="Lynx_335" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/8408fddea67ed5b46a0555839a8ce8fc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>