<document id="52ed19ec1e08e29f66df098678e7e3e1-3.5" name="Woodes_Rogers" cat="14">
<text>
The expedition arrived on 22 July 1718, surprising and trapping a ship commanded by pirate Charles Vane.  After negotiations failed, Vane used a captured French vessel as a fireship in an attempt to ram the naval vessels.  The attempt failed, but the naval vessels were forced out of the west end of Nassau harbour, giving Vane's crew an opportunity to raid the town and secure the best local pilot.  Vane and his men then escaped in a small sloop via the harbour's narrow east entrance. The pirates had evaded the trap, but Nassau and New Providence Island were in Rogers' hands.


At the time, the island's population consisted of about two hundred former pirates and several hundred fugitives who had escaped from nearby Spanish colonies.  Rogers organized a government, granted the King's Pardon to those former pirates on the island who had not yet accepted it, and began to rebuild the defences, which had fallen into decrepitude under pirate domination.  However, less than a month into his residence on New Providence, Rogers was faced with a double threat: Vane wrote, threatening to join with Edward Teach (better known as Blackbeard) to retake the island, and Rogers learned that the Spanish also planned to drive the British out of the Bahamas.

Rogers' expedition suffered further setbacks.  An unidentified disease killed almost a hundred of his expedition members, while leaving the long-term residents nearly untouched.  Two of the three navy vessels, having no orders to remain, left for New York.  Ships sent to Havana to conciliate the Spanish governor there never arrived, their crew revolting and becoming pirates mid-voyage.  Finally, the third naval vessel left in mid-September, its commander promising to return in three weeks—a promise he had no intention of keeping.  Work on rebuilding the island's fortifications proceeded slowly, with the locals showing a disinclination to work.

On 14 September 1718, Rogers received word that Vane was at Green Turtle Cay near Abaco, about  north of Nassau.Letter of Woodes Rogers to the Council of Trade and Plantations, 31 October 1718 in Cecil Hedlam (ed), ''Calendar of State Papers, Colonial Series: America and the West Indies'', Vol 30, London: 1930, p. 376; . Some of the pardoned pirates on New Providence took boats to join Vane, and Rogers decided to send two ex-pirate captains, Benjamin Hornigold and John Cockram, with a crew to gather intelligence, and, if possible, to bring Vane to battle.  As the weeks passed, and hopes of their return dimmed, Rogers declared martial law and set all inhabitants to work on rebuilding the island's fortifications.  Finally, the former pirates returned.  They had failed to find an opportunity to kill Vane or bring him to battle, but had captured one ship and a number of pirate captives.  Captain Hornigold was then sent to recapture the ships and crews who had gone pirate en route to Havana.  He returned with ten prisoners and three corpses.  On 9 December 1718, Rogers brought the ten men captured by Hornigold to trial.  Nine were convicted, and Rogers had eight hanged three days later, reprieving the ninth on hearing he was of good family.  One of the condemned, Thomas Morris, quipped as he climbed the gallows, "We have a good governor, but a harsh one."  The executions so cowed the populace that when, shortly after Christmas, several residents plotted to overthrow Rogers and restore the island to piracy, the conspirators attracted little support. Rogers had them flogged, then released as harmless.

On 16 March 1719 Rogers learned that Spain and Britain were at war again.  He redoubled his efforts to repair the island's fortifications, buying vital supplies on credit in the hope of later being reimbursed by the expedition's investors.  The Spanish sent an invasion fleet against Nassau in May, but when the fleet's commodore learned that the French (now Britain's ally) had captured Pensacola, he directed the fleet there instead.  This gave Rogers time to continue to fortify and supply New Providence, and it was not until 24 February 1720 that a Spanish fleet arrived.  Wary of Rogers' defences, the Spanish landed troops on Paradise Island (then known as Hog Island), which shelters Nassau's harbour. They were driven off by Rogers' troops.

The year 1720 brought an end to external threats to Rogers' rule. With Spain and Britain at peace again, the Spanish made no further move against the Bahamas.  Vane never returned, having been shipwrecked and captured in the Bay Islands—a year later, he was hanged in Jamaica.  This did not end Rogers' problems as governor.  Overextended from financing New Providence's defences, he received no assistance from Britain, and merchants refused to give him further credit.  His health suffered, and he spent six weeks in Charleston, South Carolina, hoping to recuperate.  Instead, he was wounded in a duel with Captain John Hildesley of HMS ''Flamborough'', a duel caused by disputes between the two on New Providence. Troubled by the lack of support and communication from London, Rogers set sail for Britain in March 1721.  He arrived three months later to find that a new governor had been appointed, and his company had been liquidated.  Personally liable for the obligations he had contracted at Nassau, he was imprisoned for debt.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a6839c32b93e486ea7f46e637862042b" name="Vane" sectnum="3.5#1">../img/a6839c32b93e486ea7f46e637862042b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>