<document id="53a577bb3bc587b0c28ab808390f1c9b-13" name="Japan" cat="11">
<text>
Japanese culture has evolved greatly over the years, from the country's original Jōmon culture to its contemporary culture, which combines influences from Asia, Europe and North America. Traditional Japanese arts include crafts (ikebana, origami, ukiyo-e, dolls, lacquerware, pottery), performances (bunraku, dance, kabuki, noh, rakugo), traditions (games, tea ceremony, Budō, architecture, gardens, swords) and cuisine. The fusion of traditional woodblock printing and Western art led to the creation of manga, a typically Japanese comic book format that is now popular within and outside Japan. Manga-influenced animation for television and film is called anime. Japanese-made video game consoles have prospered since the 1980s. 

Japanese music is eclectic, having borrowed instruments, scales and styles from neighboring cultures. Many instruments, such as the koto, were introduced in the ninth and tenth centuries. The accompanied recitative of the Noh drama dates from the fourteenth century and the popular folk music, with the guitar-like shamisen, from the sixteenth.Japanese Culture, The Concise Columbia Encyclopedia, 1983 edition, © Columbia University Press ISBN 0-380-63396-5 Western music, introduced in the late nineteenth century, now forms an integral part of the culture. Post-war Japan has been heavily influenced by American and European modern music, which has led to the evolution of popular band music called J-pop. 

Karaoke is the most widely practiced cultural activity. A November 1993 survey by the Cultural Affairs Agency found that more Japanese had sung karaoke that year than had participated in traditional cultural pursuits such as flower arranging or tea ceremony.Kelly, Bill. (1998). "Japan's Empty Orchestras: Echoes of Japanese culture in the performance of karaoke", ''The Worlds of Japanese Popular Culture: Gender, Shifting Boundaries and Global Cultures'', p. 76. Cambridge University Press. 

The earliest works of Japanese literature include two history books the ''Kojiki'' and the ''Nihon Shoki'' and the eighth century poetry book ''Man'yōshū'', all written in Chinese characters. In the early days of the Heian period, the system of transcription known as ''kana'' (Hiragana and Katakana) was created as phonograms. ''The Tale of the Bamboo Cutter'' is considered the oldest Japanese narrative. An account of Heian court life is given by ''The Pillow Book'' written by Sei Shōnagon, while ''The Tale of Genji'' by Lady Murasaki is often described as the world's first novel. During the Edo period, literature became not so much the field of the samurai aristocracy as that of the chōnin, the ordinary people. Yomihon, for example, became popular and reveals this profound change in the readership and authorship. The Meiji era saw the decline of traditional literary forms, during which Japanese literature integrated Western influences. Natsume Sōseki and Mori Ōgai were the first "modern" novelists of Japan, followed by Ryūnosuke Akutagawa, Jun'ichirō Tanizaki, Yasunari Kawabata, Yukio Mishima and, more recently, Haruki Murakami. Japan has two Nobel Prize-winning authors—Yasunari Kawabata (1968) and Kenzaburo Oe (1994).


File:Great Wave off Kanagawa2.jpg|''The Great Wave off Kanagawa'' (1832), an ''ukiyo-e'' from ''Thirty-Six Views of Mount Fuji'' by Hokusai.
File:Japan-Kyoto-Geisha.jpg|Geisha performing in traditional kimono.
File:Sorakuen14st3200.jpg|A Japanese garden created in a traditional style.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="745b8a96153bb624de21b4f9edd8981b" name="Kamidaigo05_1024" sectnum="13#1">../img/745b8a96153bb624de21b4f9edd8981b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>