<document id="53b28fa81ed88da3ee7b47b7979bb9fb-7.4" name="Barton_Fink" cat="19">
<text>
The character of Barton Fink is based loosely on Clifford Odets, a playwright from New York who in the 1930s joined the Group Theatre, a gathering of dramatists which included Harold Clurman, Cheryl Crawford, and Lee Strasberg. Their work emphasized social issues, and employed Stanislavski's system of acting to recreate human experience as truthfully as possible. Several of Odets' plays were successfully performed on Broadway, including ''Awake and Sing!'' and ''Waiting for Lefty'' (both in 1935). When public tastes turned away from politically engaged theatre and toward the familial realism of Eugene O'Neill, Odets had difficulty producing successful work, so he moved to Hollywood and spent twenty years writing film scripts.Palmer, pp. 114–116.


The Coens wrote with Odets in mind; they imagined Barton Fink as "a serious dramatist, honest, politically engaged, and rather naive".Ciment and Niogret, p. 173. As Ethan said in 1991: "It seemed natural that he comes from Group Theater and the decade of the thirties." Like Odets, Barton believes that the theatre should celebrate the trials and triumphs of everyday people; like Barton, Odets was highly egotistical.Rowell, p. 125. She notes that Odets "purportedly proclaimed to the ''New York Times'' that he was the most talented dramatist". In the movie, a review of Barton's play ''Bare Ruined Choirs'' indicates that his characters face a "brute struggle for existence ... in the most squalid corners". This wording is similar to the comment of biographer Gerald Weales that Odets' characters "struggle for life amidst petty conditions". Lines of dialogue from Barton's work are reminiscent of Odets' play ''Awake and Sing!''. For example, one character declares: "I'm awake now, awake for the first time." Another says: "Take that ruined choir. Make it sing."Quoted in Palmer, p. 119.

However, many important differences exist between the two men. Joel Coen said: "Both writers wrote the same kind of plays with proletarian heroes, but their personalities were quite different. Odets was much more of an extrovert; in fact he was quite sociable even in Hollywood, and this is not the case with Barton Fink!" Although he was frustrated by his declining popularity in New York, Odets was successful during his time in Hollywood. Several of his later plays were adapted by him and others into movies. One of these, ''The Big Knife'', matches Barton's life much more than Odets'. In it, an actor becomes overwhelmed by the greed of a movie studio which hires him, and eventually commits suicide.Palmer, pp. 116–117. Another similarity to Odets' work is Audrey's death, which mirrors a scene in ''Deadline at Dawn'', a 1946 film noir written by Odets. In that film, a character wakes to find that the woman he bedded the night before has been inexplicably murdered.Bergan, p. 137.

Odets chronicled his difficult transition from Broadway to Hollywood in his diary, published in 1988 as ''The Time Is Ripe: The 1940 Journal of Clifford Odets''. The diary explored Odets' philosophical deliberations about writing and romance. He often invited women into his apartment, and describes many of his affairs in the diary. These experiences, like the extended speeches about writing, are echoed in ''Barton Fink'' when Audrey visits and seduces Barton at the Hotel Earle.Palmer, pp. 115–116. Turturro was the only member of the production who read Odets' ''Journal'', however, and the Coen brothers urge audiences to "take account of the difference between the character and the man".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="61933019fbe41d75eb96b1b31a87bfce" name="Cliffordodets" sectnum="7.4#1">../img/61933019fbe41d75eb96b1b31a87bfce.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>