<document id="53b28fa81ed88da3ee7b47b7979bb9fb-2" name="Barton_Fink" cat="19">
<text>
In 1989 filmmakers Joel and Ethan Coen began writing the script for a movie eventually released as ''Miller's Crossing''. The many threads of the story became complicated, and after four months they found themselves lost in the process.Bergan, pp. 114–115. Although biographers and critics later referred to it as writer's block,See for example Rowell, p. 104 and  in ''The Washington Post''. the Coen brothers rejected this description. "It's not really the case that we were suffering from writer's block," Joel said in a 1991 interview, "but our working speed had slowed, and we were eager to get a certain distance from ''Miller's Crossing''."Ciment and Niogret, p. 172. They went from Los Angeles to New York and began work on a different project.Bergan, p. 115.


In three weeks, the Coens wrote a script with a title role written specifically for actor John Turturro, with whom they'd been working on ''Miller's Crossing''. The new movie, ''Barton Fink'', was set in a large, seemingly-abandoned hotel. This setting, which they named the ''Hotel Earle'', was a driving force behind the story and mood of the new project. While filming their 1985 film ''Blood Simple'' in Austin, Texas, the Coens had seen a hotel which made a significant impression: "We thought, 'Wow, Motel Hell.' You know, being condemned to live in the weirdest hotel in the world."Quoted in Bergan, p. 140.

The writing process for ''Barton Fink'' was smooth, they said, suggesting that the relief of being away from ''Miller's Crossing'' may have been a catalyst. They also felt satisfied with the overall shape of the story, which helped them move quickly through the composition. "Certain films come entirely in one's head; we just sort of burped out ''Barton Fink''."Quoted in Bergan, p. 130. As a number of critics and journalists have noted, Joel and Ethan sometimes finish each others' sentences. (Actress Kelly MacDonald said in a featurette on the DVD of ''No Country for Old Men'' that they seem like "one person with two heads".) Thus many quotes in the Bergan biography are attributed to "the Coens". While writing, the Coens created a second leading role with another actor in mind: John Goodman, who had appeared in their 1987 comedy ''Raising Arizona''. His new character, Charlie, was Barton's next-door neighbor in the cavernous hotel. Even before writing, the Coens knew how the story would end, and wrote Charlie's final speech at the start of the writing process.Ciment and Niogret, p. 177.

The script served its diversionary purpose, and the Coens put it aside: "''Barton Fink'' sort of washed out our brain and we were able to go back and finish ''Miller's Crossing''."Quoted in Bergan, p. 115. Note the singular "brain" despite the plural possessive pronoun. Once production of the first movie was finished, the Coens began to recruit staff to film ''Barton Fink''. Turturro looked forward to playing the lead role, and spent a month with the Coens in Los Angeles to coordinate views on the project: "I felt I could bring something more human to Barton.  Joel and Ethan allowed me a certain contribution. I tried to go a little further than they expected."Quoted in Bergan, p. 131.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d795a1012c43575bc751f61438d27dd3" name="COEN_Brothers_(cannesPH)" sectnum="2#1">../img/d795a1012c43575bc751f61438d27dd3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>