<document id="53b28fa81ed88da3ee7b47b7979bb9fb-4" name="Barton_Fink" cat="19">
<text>
The peeling wallpaper in Barton's room was designed to mimic the pus dripping from Charlie's infected ear.

The spooky, inexplicably empty feel of the Hotel Earle was central to the Coens' conception of the movie. "We wanted an art deco stylization," Joel explained in a 1991 interview, "and a place that was falling into ruin after having seen better days."Ciment and Niogret, p. 179. Barton's room is sparsely furnished with two large windows facing another building. The Coens later described the hotel as a "ghost ship floating adrift, where you notice signs of the presence of other passengers, without ever laying eyes on any". In the movie, residents' shoes are an indication of this unseen presence; another rare sign of other inhabitants is the sound from adjacent rooms.Rowell, p. 113; Palmer, pp. 124–125. Joel said: "You can imagine it peopled by failed commercial travelers, with pathetic sex lives, who cry alone in their rooms." Heat and moisture are other important elements of the setting. The wallpaper in Barton's room peels and droops; Charlie experiences the same problem, and guesses heat is the cause. The Coens used green and yellow colors liberally in designing the hotel "to suggest an aura of putrefaction".

The atmosphere of the hotel was meant to connect with the character of Charlie. As Joel explained: "Our intention, moreover, was that the hotel function as an exteriorization of the character played by John Goodman. The sweat drips off his forehead like the paper peels off the walls. At the end, when Goodman says that he is a prisoner of his own mental state, that this is like some kind of hell, it was necessary for the hotel to have already suggested something infernal." The peeling wallpaper and the paste which seeps through it also mirror Charlie's chronic ear infection and the resultant pus.Rowell, p. 124.

When Barton first arrives at the Hotel Earle, he is asked by the friendly bellhop Chet (Steve Buscemi) if he is "a trans or a res" transient or resident. Barton explains that he isn't sure, but will be staying "indefinitely".Coen and Coen, p. 14. The dichotomy between permanent inhabitants and guests reappears several times, notably in the hotel's motto, "A day or a lifetime", which Barton notices on the room's stationery. This idea returns at the end of the movie, when Charlie describes Barton as "a tourist with a typewriter". His ability to leave the Earle (while Charlie remains) is presented by critic Erica Rowell as evidence that Barton's story represents the process of writing itself. Barton, she says, represents an author who is able to leave a story, while characters like Charlie cannot.


In contrast, the offices of Capitol Pictures and Lipnick's house are pristine, lavishly decorated, and extremely comfortable. The company's rooms are bathed in sunlight, and Ben Geisler's office faces a lush array of flora. Barton meets Lipnick in one scene beside an enormous, spotless swimming pool. This echoes his position as studio head, as he explains: "...you can't always be honest, not with the sharks swimming around this town ... if I'd been totally honest, I wouldn't be within a mile of this pool—unless I was cleaning it."Coen and Coen, p. 92. In his office, Lipnick showcases another trophy of his power: statues of Atlas, the Titan of Greek mythology who declared war on the gods of Mount Olympus and was severely punished.Rowell, p. 131.

Originally, the historical moment just after the United States entered World War II was to be a significant impact on the place. As the Coens explained: "e were thinking of a hotel where the lodgers were old people, the insane, the physically handicapped, because all the others had left for the war. The further the script was developed, the more this theme got left behind, but it had led us, in the beginning, to settle on that period."Ciment and Niogret, pp. 172–173. The connection to World War II is not made explicit until the end of the movie, when Lipnick appears in a colonel's uniform. Although he is wearing a costume and has not actually entered the military, he declares himself ready to fight the "little yellow bastards".Coen and Coen, p. 128. In an earlier scene, Barton watches dailies from another wrestling movie being made by Capitol Pictures; the date on the clapperboard is 9 December, two days after the attack on Pearl Harbor. When he celebrates the completed script later by dancing at a USO show, he is surrounded by soldiers who are presumably heading toward the battlefield.Rowell, p. 130.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e3791f427fd332bc68c6a25d198337a1" name="USS_SHAW_exploding_Pearl_Harbor_Nara_80-G-16871_2" sectnum="4#1">../img/e3791f427fd332bc68c6a25d198337a1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>