<document id="53b28fa81ed88da3ee7b47b7979bb9fb-8.8" name="Barton_Fink" cat="19">
<text>
The world of Broadway theatre in ''Barton Fink'' is a place of high culture, where the creator believes most fully that his work embodies his own values. Although he pretends to disdain his own success, Barton believes he has achieved a great victory with ''Bare Ruined Choirs''. He seeks praise; when his agent Garland asks if he's seen the glowing review in the ''Herald'', Barton says "no", even though his producer had just read it to him. Barton feels close to the theatre, confident that it can help him create work that honors "the common man". The men and women who funded the production "those people", as Barton calls them demonstrate that Broadway is just as concerned with profit as Hollywood; but its intimacy and smaller scale allow the author to feel that his work has real value.Rowell, p. 106; Palmer, p. 119.



Barton does not believe Hollywood offers the same opportunity. In the film, Los Angeles is a world of false fronts and phony people. This is evident in an early line of the screenplay (filmed, but not included in the theatrical releaseIt is included as a deleted scene in home video editions.); while informing Barton of Capitol Pictures' offer, his agent tells him: "I'm only asking that your decision be informed by a little realism—if I can use that word and Hollywood in the same breath."Quoted in Rowell, p. 106. Later, as Barton tries to explain why he's staying at the Earle, studio head Jack Lipnick finishes his sentence, recognizing that Barton wants a place that is "less Hollywood". The assumption is that Hollywood is fake and the Earle is genuine. Producer Ben Geisler takes Barton to lunch at a restaurant featuring a mural of the "New York Cafe", a sign of Hollywood's effort to replicate the authenticity of the east coast.Rowell, p. 130. Lipnick's initial overwhelming exuberance is also a façade. Although he begins by telling Barton that "the writer is king here at Capitol Pictures", in the penultimate scene he insists: "If your opinion mattered, then I guess I'd resign and let ''you'' run the studio. It doesn't, and you won't, and the lunatics are not going to run ''this'' particular asylum."Coen and Coen, p. 128. Original emphasis.

Deception in ''Barton Fink'' is emblematic of Hollywood's focus on low culture, its relentless desire to efficiently produce formulaic entertainment for the sole purpose of economic gain. Capitol Pictures assigns Barton to write a wrestling picture with superstar Wallace Beery in a leading role. Although Lipnick declares otherwise, Geisler assures Barton that "it's just a B picture". Audrey tries to help the struggling writer by telling him: "Look, it's really just a formula. You don't have to type your soul into it."Quoted in Palmer, p. 126. This formula is made clear by Lipnick, who asks Barton in their first meeting whether the main character should have a love interest or take care of an orphaned child. Barton shows his iconoclasm by answering: "Both, maybe?"Palmer, pp. 121–122. In the end, his inability to conform to the studio's norms destroys not only Barton himself, but also producer Geisler.Rowell, p. 135.

A similar depiction of Hollywood appears in Nathanael West's 1939 novel ''The Day of the Locust'', which many critics see as an important precursor to ''Barton Fink''.Palmer, pp. 117–119; Rowell, p. 107; Bergan, p. 133. Set in a run-down apartment complex, the book describes a painter reduced to work decorating movie sets. It portrays Hollywood as crass and exploitative, devouring talented individuals in its neverending quest for profit. In both West's novel and ''Barton Fink'', protagonists suffer under the oppressive industrial machine of the movie studio.Palmer, pp. 117–119. He adds: "While borrowing heavily from West's ideas, ''Barton Fink'' notably expands the novelist's critique".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4aa9adc957c035be63a9d8df5760356f" name="HollywoodSign" sectnum="8.8#1">../img/4aa9adc957c035be63a9d8df5760356f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>