<document id="53b28fa81ed88da3ee7b47b7979bb9fb-3" name="Barton_Fink" cat="19">
<text>
As they designed detailed storyboards for ''Barton Fink'', the Coens began looking for a new cinematographer, since their associate Barry Sonnenfeld who had filmed their first three movies was occupied with his own directorial debut, ''The Addams Family''. The Coens had been impressed with the work of English cinematographer Roger Deakins, particularly the interior scenes of the 1988 movie ''Stormy Monday''. After screening other films he had worked on (including ''Sid and Nancy'' and ''Pascali's Island''), they sent a script to Deakins and invited him to join the project. His agent advised against working with the Coens, but Deakins met with them at a cafe in Notting Hill and they soon began working together on ''Barton Fink''.Ciment and Niogret, p. 180; Bergan, pp. 138–139.


Filming began in June 1990 and took eight weeks (a third less time than required by ''Miller's Crossing''), and the estimated final budget for the movie was US$9 million.Bergan, pp. 140–141. The Coens worked well with Deakins, and they easily translated their ideas for each scene onto film. "There was only one moment we surprised him," Joel Coen recalled later. An extended scene called for a tracking shot out of the bedroom and into a sink drain "plug hole" in the adjacent bathroom as a symbol of sexual intercourse. "The shot was a lot of fun and we had a great time working out how to do it," Joel said. "After that, every time we asked Roger to do something difficult, he would raise an eyebrow and say, 'Don't be having me track down any plug-holes now.'"Quoted in Bergan, p. 139.

Three weeks of filming were spent in the Hotel Earle, a set created by art director Dennis Gassner. The film's climax required a huge spreading fire in the hotel's hallway, which the Coens originally planned to add digitally in post-production. When they decided to use real flames, however, the crew built a large alternate set in an abandoned aircraft hangar at Long Beach. A series of gas jets was installed behind the hallway, and the wallpaper was perforated for easy penetration. As Goodman ran through the hallway, a man on an overhead catwalk opened each jet, giving the impression of a fire racing ahead of Charlie. Each take required a rebuild of the apparatus, and a second hallway (sans fire) stood ready nearby for filming pick-up shots between takes. The final scene was shot near Zuma Beach, as was the image of a wave crashing against a rock.

The Coens edited the movie themselves, as is their custom. "We prefer a hands-on approach," Joel explained in 1996, "rather than sitting next to someone and telling them what to cut."Ciment and Niogret, p. 191. Because of rules for membership in film production guilds, they are required to use a pseudonym; "Roderick Jaynes" is credited with editing ''Barton Fink''.Yuan, Jada.  ''New York Entertainment''. 22 January 2008. ''New York'' magazine. Retrieved on 20 November 2008. The introduction to the screenplay book for ''Barton Fink'' was written by "Roderick Jaynes"; in a satirical preview, it calls the plot "crushingly tedious". Only a few filmed scenes were removed from the final cut, including a transition scene to show Barton's movement from New York to Hollywood. (In the movie, this is shown enigmatically with a wave crashing against a rock.) Several scenes representing work in Hollywood studios were also filmed, but edited out because they were "too conventional".Ciment and Niogret, pp. 179–180.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c1a107bc31b2dc83e3f7b24f356b448e" name="RMS_Queen_Mary_Grand_Salon_edit" sectnum="3#1">../img/c1a107bc31b2dc83e3f7b24f356b448e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>