<document id="54474bf87b0281e5b897518789fba114-4" name="George_I_of_Great_Britain" cat="25">
<text>
Though both England and Scotland recognised Anne as their Queen, only the English Parliament had settled on Sophia, Electress of Hanover, as the heir. The Estates of Scotland (the Scottish Parliament) had not yet formally settled the question over who would succeed to the Scottish throne on Anne's death. In 1703, the Estates passed a bill that declared that their selection for Queen Anne's successor would not be the same individual as the successor to the English throne, unless England granted full freedom of trade to Scottish merchants in England and its colonies. At first, Royal Assent was withheld but the following year Anne capitulated to the wishes of the Estates, and assent was granted to the bill, which became the Act of Security 1704. In response, the English Parliament passed measures which threatened to restrict Anglo-Scottish trade and cripple the Scottish economy if the Estates did not agree to the Hanoverian succession. Eventually, in 1707, both Parliaments agreed an Act of Union, creating the largest free trade area in eighteenth-century Europe. It united England and Scotland into a single political entity, the Kingdom of Great Britain, and established the rules of succession as laid down by the Act of Settlement 1701.

George's mother, the Electress Sophia, died on 28 May 17148 June in the New Style Gregorian calendar adopted by Hanover in 1700. at the age of 83. She had collapsed after rushing to shelter from a shower of rain in Herrenhausen gardens. George was now Queen Anne's direct heir. He swiftly revised the membership of the Regency Council that would take power after Anne's death, as it was known that Anne's health was failing and politicians in Britain were jostling for power.Hatton, p.108 She suffered a stroke, which left her unable to speak, and died on 1 August. The list of regents was opened, the members sworn in, and George was proclaimed King of Great Britain and Ireland.Hatton, p.109 Partly due to contrary winds, which kept him in The Hague awaiting passage,Hatton, p.123 he did not arrive in Britain until 18 September. George was crowned at Westminster Abbey on 20 October.



George mainly lived in Great Britain after 1714, though he visited his home in Hanover in 1716, 1719, 1720, 1723 and 1725;Hatton, p.158 in total George spent about one fifth of his reign as King in Germany. A clause in the Act of Settlement that forbade the British monarch from leaving the country without Parliament's permission was unanimously repealed in 1716. During all but the first of the King's absences, power was vested in a Regency Council rather than his son, George Augustus, Prince of Wales.

Within a year of George's accession, the Whigs won an overwhelming victory in the general election of 1715. Several members of the defeated Tory Party sympathised with the Jacobites, and some disgruntled Tories sided with a Jacobite rebellion, which became known as "The Fifteen". The Jacobites sought to put Anne's Catholic half-brother, James (whom they called "James III", and who was known to his opponents as the "Pretender") on the Throne. The Pretender's supporters, led by Lord Mar, an embittered Scottish nobleman who had previously supported the "Glorious Revolution", instigated rebellion in Scotland, where support for Jacobitism was stronger than in England. The Fifteen, however, was a dismal failure; Lord Mar's battle plans were poor, and the Pretender arrived late with too little money and too few arms. By the end of the year, the rebellion had all but collapsed. Faced with impending defeat, Lord Mar and the Pretender fled to France in February 1716. After the rebellion was defeated, although there were some executions and forfeitures, George acted to moderate the Government's response, showed leniency, and spent the income from the forfeited estates on schools for Scotland and paying off part of the national debt.Hatton, pp.174–179

George's distrust of the Tories aided the passing of power to the Whigs. Whig dominance would grow to be so great under George that the Tories would not return to power for another half-century. After the election, the Whig-dominated Parliament passed the Septennial Act 1715, which extended the maximum duration of Parliament to seven years (although it could be dissolved earlier by the Sovereign). Thus, Whigs already in power could remain in such a position for a greater period of time.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="92a529fae989d51881228bc7a2883f78" name="George_I_Oval" sectnum="4#1">../img/92a529fae989d51881228bc7a2883f78.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>