<document id="54474bf87b0281e5b897518789fba114-7" name="George_I_of_Great_Britain" cat="25">
<text>
As requested by Walpole, George revived The Most Honourable Order of the Bath in 1725, which enabled Walpole to reward or gain political supporters by offering them the honour. Walpole became extremely powerful, and was largely able to appoint ministers of his own choosing. Unlike his predecessor, Queen Anne, George rarely attended meetings of the Cabinet; most of his communications were in private. George only exercised substantial influence with respect to British foreign policy. He, with the aid of Lord Townshend, arranged for the ratification by Great Britain, France and Prussia of the Treaty of Hanover, which was designed to counter-balance the Austro-Spanish Treaty of Vienna and protect British trade.Hatton, p.274

George, although increasingly reliant on Walpole, could still have replaced his ministers at will. Walpole was actually afraid of being removed towards the end of George I's reign,"" (1911). ''Encyclopædia Britannica,'' 11th ed. London: Cambridge University Press but such fears were put to an end when George died during his sixth trip to his native Hanover since his accession as King. George suffered a stroke on the road between Delden and Nordhorn on the 9 June 1727.Hatton, p.282 He was taken by carriage to the prince-bishop's palace at OsnabrückHis younger brother, Ernest Augustus, Duke of York and Albany, was Prince-Bishop of Osnabrück from 1715 until 1728. where he died in the early hours of 11 June 1727.22 June in the New Style Gregorian calendar adopted by Hanover in 1700. He was buried in the Chapel of Leine Castle but his remains were moved to the chapel at Herrenhausen after World War II.

George was succeeded by his son, George Augustus, who took the throne as George II. It was widely assumed, even by Walpole for a time, that George II planned to remove Walpole from office but was prevented from doing so by his wife, Queen Caroline. However, Walpole commanded a substantial majority in Parliament and George II had little choice but to retain him or risk ministerial instability.Black, pp.29–31, 53, and 61 In subsequent reigns, the power of the Prime Minister increased further at the expense of the power of the Sovereign.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2f32dc0ab745701bf4fc9d6b486c22dc" name="George-I_lafontaine2" sectnum="7#1">../img/2f32dc0ab745701bf4fc9d6b486c22dc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>