<document id="54474bf87b0281e5b897518789fba114-3" name="George_I_of_Great_Britain" cat="25">
<text>
Ernest Augustus died on 23 January 1698, leaving all of his territories to George, with the exception of the Prince-Bishopric of Osnabrück, an office he had held since 1661.The Prince-Bishopric was not an hereditary title; instead, it alternated between Protestant and Roman Catholic incumbents. George thus became Duke of Brunswick-Lüneburg (also known as Hanover, after its capital) as well as Archbannerbearer and a Prince-Elector of the Holy Roman Empire. His court in Hanover was graced by many cultural icons, such as the mathematician Gottfried Leibniz and the composer Georg Friederich Händel.

Shortly after George's accession to his paternal dukedom, the second-in-line to the English and Scottish thrones, Prince William, Duke of Gloucester died. The Parliament of England passed the Act of Settlement 1701, whereunder George's mother, Sophia, was designated heir to the English throne if the then-reigning monarch (William III) and his sister-in-law, Princess Anne of Denmark (later Queen Anne), died without surviving issue. The succession was so designed because Sophia was the closest Protestant relative of the British Royal Family; fifty-six Catholics with superior hereditary claims were bypassed. The likelihood of any of them converting to Protestantism for the sake of the succession was remote, and some had already refused.Hatton, p.74

In August 1701, George was invested with the Order of the Garter, and, within six weeks, the nearest Catholic claimant to the throne of England, ex-King James II, died. William III died the following March, and Sophia became heir presumptive to the new Queen of England, Anne. Sophia was in her seventy-first year, older than Anne by thirty-five years, but she was very fit and healthy, and invested time and energy in securing the succession either for herself or her son.Hatton, pp.75–76 However, it was George who understood the complexities of English politics and constitutional law, which required further acts in 1705 to naturalize Sophia and her heirs as English citizens, and detail arrangements for the transfer of power through a Regency Council.Hatton, pp.77–78 The same year, George's surviving uncle died and he inherited further German dominions: Lüneberg-Grubenhagen, centred at Celle.Hatton, p.90



Shortly after George's accession in Hanover, the War of the Spanish Succession broke out.  At issue was the right of Philip, the grandson of the French King Louis XIV, to succeed to the Spanish throne under the terms of King Charles II of Spain's will.  The Holy Roman Empire, the United Provinces, England, Hanover and many other German states opposed Philip's right to succeed because they feared that France would become too powerful if it also controlled Spain.  As part of the war effort George invaded his neighbouring state, Brunswick-Wolfenbüttel, which was pro-French, writing out some of the battle orders himself.  The invasion succeeded with few lives lost, and as a reward, the Hanoverian claim to Saxony-Lauenburg, which George's uncle had invaded and annexed on the death of its ruler several years before, was recognised by the British and Dutch.Hatton, pp.86–89

In 1706, the Elector of Bavaria was deprived of his offices and titles for siding with France against the Empire.  The following year, George was made Imperial Field Marshal, in command of the Empire's army stationed along the Rhine.  His tenure was not altogether successful, partly because he was deceived by his ally John Churchill, 1st Duke of Marlborough into a diversionary attack, and partly because the Emperor Joseph appropriated the funds necessary for George's campaign for his own use.  Despite this, the German princes knew, or at least thought, that he had acquitted himself well.  In 1708, they formally confirmed George's position as a Prince-Elector in recognition of or because of his service.  George did not hold Marlborough's actions against him, which he appreciated were part of a plan to lure French forces from the main attack.Hatton, pp.101–104, 122

In 1709, George resigned as Field Marshal, never to go on active service again, and in 1710 was conferred the dignity of Archtreasurer of the Empire,Hatton, p.104 formerly held by the Elector Palatine—the absence of the Elector of Bavaria allowed a re-shuffling of offices.  In 1711, the Emperor Joseph died, which threatened to destroy the balance of power in the opposite direction, and the war ended in 1713 with the ratification of the Treaty of Utrecht.  Philip was allowed to succeed to the Spanish throne, but he was removed from the line of succession to the French throne, and the Elector of Bavaria was restored.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1ae3ae1f116554af64bc97c00e517e78" name="George_I_Elector_of_Hanover" sectnum="3#1">../img/1ae3ae1f116554af64bc97c00e517e78.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>