<document id="55012ec79588c404ce85340847090c2e-2" name="Morotai_Mutiny" cat="29">
<text>
In March 1945, frustrated by the lack of response from Cobby and his staff and convinced that operations were becoming yet more wasteful, Arthur began discussing his concerns with other senior 1TAF pilots. First, he spoke to Wing Commander Kenneth Ranger, a senior staff officer who had served with No. 9 Operational Group RAAF and had made allegations regarding the leadership of its commander, Air Commodore Joe Hewitt, who was eventually dismissed from his post. Arthur sought out Ranger as someone  with "moral guts", who would take "a stand against the type of operations we were engaged in".  Next, he enlisted Caldwell's support, although Caldwell was, at the time, facing charges from Cobby over liquor trafficking which made it a risk that his involvement in a protest over operations would be misconstrued as an attempt to divert attention from the charges. Arthur believed, however, that Caldwell "would go as far as he possibly could to back up his opinions  were worth a lot more than the opinions of most other people in the area". 

Through Caldwell more officers joined the protest, including two other celebrated aces, Wing Commander Bobby Gibbes and Squadron Leader John Waddy, as well as Squadron Leader Bert Grace, Squadron Leader Douglas Vanderfield, and later, Squadron Leader Stuart Harpham.Odgers, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', p. 125. Caldwell's official tally for the war was 28½ kills, Waddy's 15½, Gibbes' 10¼, and Arthur's 10. During a series of meetings early in April 1945, Caldwell proposed that the eight resign ''en masse'', and the others agreed. Arthur later stated that, "I meant to make as big a fuss as I possibly could with the object of getting the position corrected ... All the same, we realised that, to lay ourselves open to any charge of mutiny, we might lessen the force of what we were doing, which was the reason we put the things in as resignations and not as any attempt to unseat people higher up."


Arthur also attempted to secure Cobby's support for the protest. The commander of 1TAF had been the Australian Flying Corps' leading ace in World War I, as Caldwell was the RAAF's in World War II. Arthur reasoned that, although Cobby was partly to blame for the morale issue, "we felt that his value to our move, because of his name with the Public, together with Group Captain Caldwell, would give us a very considerable amount of public support ... he was the prima donna of one war, and ... arm-in-arm with the prima donna of the next war, we would put up a reasonable front and attract a lot of attention in the headlines of the newspapers." Cobby, however, refused to join in and later claimed to be unaware of the depth of feeling among the pilots.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="01d4e3252220a41b7ac3dfde1ab7df48" name="Caldwell_spitfire_pilots" sectnum="2#1">../img/01d4e3252220a41b7ac3dfde1ab7df48.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>