<document id="554d43231f76d714144256ce01da0532-1" name="Lisa_del_Giocondo" cat="1">
<text>
At the time of the Quattrocento, Florence was among the largest cities in Europe, considered rich and economically successful. Life was not "idyllic" for all residents though, among whom there were great disparities in wealth.Pallanti 2006, pp. 17, 23, 24 Lisa's family was old and aristocratic but over time had lost its influence.Pallanti 2006, p. 58 They were comfortable but not wealthy, and lived on farm income.

Antonmaria di Noldo Gherardini, Lisa's father, lost two wives, Lisa di Giovanni Filippo de Carducci, whom he married in 1465, and Caterina Rucellai, whom he married in 1473. Both died in childbirth.Pallanti 2006, p. 37 Lisa's mother was Lucrezia del Caccia, daughter of Piera Spinelli and Gherardini's wife by his third marriage in 1476. Gherardini at one time owned or rented six farms in Chianti that produced wheat, wine and olive oil and where livestock was raised.Pallanti 2006, pp. 41-44

Study by Leonardo for the hands of the ''Mona Lisa'', in red chalk (Windsor Library)
Lisa was born in Florence on June 15, 1479 on Via Maggio,Pallanti 2006, p.37 although for many years it was thought she was born on one of the family's rural properties, Villa Vignamaggio just outside Greve. She is named for Lisa, a wife of her paternal grandfather.Pallanti 2006, p. 40 The eldest of seven children, Lisa had three sisters, one of whom was named Ginevra, and three brothers, Giovangualberto, Francesco, and Noldo.Pallanti 2006, p. 44

The family lived in Florence, originally near Santa Trinita and later in rented space near Santo Spirito, most likely because they were not able to afford repairs to their former house when it was damaged. Lisa's family moved to what today is called Via dei Pepi and then near Santa Croce, where they lived near Ser Piero da Vinci, Leonardo's father.Pallanti 2006, pp. 45-46 They also owned a small country home in St. Donato in the village of Poggio about  south of the city.Zöllner 1993, p. 4 Noldo, Gherardini's father and Lisa's grandfather, had bequeathed a farm in Chianti to the Santa Maria Nuova hospital. Gherardini secured a lease for another of the hospital's farms, and so that he could oversee the wheat harvest, the family spent summers there at the house named Ca' di Pesa.Pallanti 2006, pp.41-44
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fd852d17af2ec189f7e1d7fb892e8e08" name="Leonardo_design_attributed" sectnum="1#1">../img/fd852d17af2ec189f7e1d7fb892e8e08.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>