<document id="554fe8369659c3cb51ace14fe08b38a4-2" name="Elagabalus" cat="25">
<text>
When the emperor Macrinus came to power he suppressed the threat against his reign by the family of his assassinated predecessor, Caracalla, by exiling them—Julia Maesa, her two daughters, and her eldest grandson Elagabalus—to their estate at Emesa in Syria. Almost upon arrival in Syria she began a plot, with her eunuch advisor and Elagabalus' tutor Gannys, to overthrow Macrinus and elevate the fourteen-year-old Elagabalus as emperor. Elagabalus and his mother readily complied and announced, falsely, that he was the illegitimate son of Caracalla, therefore due the loyalties of Roman soldiers and senators who had sworn allegiance to Caracalla. After Julia Maesa displayed her wealth to the Third Legion at Raphana they swore allegiance to Elagabalus. At sunrise on May 16, 218, Publius Valerius Comazon Eutychianus, commander of the legion, declared him emperor.Cassius Dio, ''Roman History''  To strengthen his legitimacy through further propaganda, Elagabalus assumed Caracalla's names, ''Marcus Aurelius Antoninus''.Cassius Dio, ''Roman History'' 

In response Macrinus dispatched his Praetorian prefect Ulpius Julianus to the region with a contingent of troops he considered strong enough the crush the rebellion. However this force soon joined the faction of Elagabalus when, during the battle, they turned on their own commanders. The officers were killed and Julianus' head was sent back to the emperor.Herodian, ''Roman History''  Macrinus now sent letters to the Senate denouncing Elagabalus as the ''False Antoninus'' and claiming he was insane.Cassius Dio, ''Roman History''  Both consuls and other high ranking members of Rome's leadership condemned him, and the Senate subsequently declared war on both Elagabalus and Julia Maesa.Cassius Dio, ''Roman History'' 

Macrinus and his son, weakened by the desertion of the Second Legion due to bribes and promises circulated by Julia Maesa, were defeated on June 8, 218 at the Battle of Antioch by troops commanded by Gannys. Macrinus fled toward Italy, disguised as a courier, but was later intercepted near Chalcedon and executed in Cappadocia. His son Diadumenianus, sent for safety to the Parthian court, was captured at Zeugma and also put to death.

Elagabalus declared the date of the victory at Antioch to be the beginning of his reign and assumed the imperial titles without prior Senatorial approval,Cassius Dio, ''Roman History''  which violated tradition but was a common practice among third-century emperors nonetheless. Letters of reconciliation were dispatched to Rome extending amnesty to the Senate and recognizing the laws, while also condemning the administration of Macrinus and his son.Cassius Dio, ''Roman History''  The Senators responded by acknowledging Elagabalus as emperor and accepting his claim to be the son of Caracalla.Herodian, ''Roman History''  Caracalla and Julia Domna were both deified by the Senate, both Julia Maesa and Julia Soaemias were elevated to the rank of Augustae, and the memory of Macrinus and Diadumenianus was condemned and vilified by the Senate. The former commander of the Third Legion, Comazon, was appointed to be commander of the Praetorian Guard.Cassius Dio, ''Roman History''
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5e3296390f8686a22e77698a01ce6e4d" name="Elagabalus_Denarius_Fides" sectnum="2#1">../img/5e3296390f8686a22e77698a01ce6e4d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>