<document id="55b2f53edf071c0facf93979af408b12-2" name="The_Shape_of_Things_to_Come_(Lost)" cat="19">
<text>
The Writers Guild of America went on strike on November 4, 2007,McNary, Dave & Littleton, Cynthia, (November 2, 2007) "", ''Variety''. Retrieved on November 3, 2007. by which time only eight of the planned sixteen episodes of ''Lost'''s fourth season had been written.Lindelof, Damon & Cuse, Carlton, (November 5, 2007) "", ''Variety''. Retrieved on November 8, 2007.  These episodes aired from January to March 2008.Grossman, Ben, (November 7, 2007) "", Broadcasting & Cable. Retrieved on November 8, 2007.  After the strike ended on February 12, 2008, the writers found that there was only enough time to produce five episodes, although the fifth episode would later be expanded to two episodesAusiello, Michael, (April 11, 2008) "", ''TV Guide''.  Retrieved on April 26, 2008.—and they proceeded to compress most of the storylines of the planned eight episodes into six,Levin, Gary, (February 11, 2008) "", ''USA Today''.  Retrieved on March 22, 2008. with some carrying over into the fifth season.  Executive producer/head writer Damon Lindelof stated that "we are going to execute our full story plan for season four.  This simply requires a shift from high-octane storytelling to superhigh-octane storytelling.  It requires no cramming, only a slightly heavier foot on the gas pedal … so, hold on to your hats.  Those of you waiting for the long-anticipated The Economist" for his alias Dean Moriarty,Kitsis, Edward (writer) & Horowitz, Adam (writer) & Bender, Jack (director), "The Economist".  ''Lost'', ABC.  Episode 3, season 4.  Aired on February 14, 2008. which is also the name of the central character in the Jack Kerouac's 1951 novel ''On the Road''.Medley, Mark, (April 25, 2008) "", ''The National Post''.  Retrieved on July 14, 2008.  Among the most frequent questions that the writers are asked is whether they have planned out future storylines,Lindelof, Damon, (May 9, 2007) "", ''Kuwait Times''.  Retrieved on April 26, 2008. so the writers try to allude to future plot points, such as with the Dharka scene, that they can later call on as proof that they do know where the story is headed.  Director Jack Bender described the scene, which was filmed in a Hawaiian rock quarry, as especially hard to shoot because the actors had to ride horses and use guns, the crew had to relocate due to rocks present that were unsuitable for the scene, and Bender walked head-first into a crane.Jensen, Jeff "Doc", (April 27, 2008) "", ''Entertainment Weekly''.  Retrieved on May 19, 2008.  Emerson stated that the set is "definitely a no-glamour zone … I thought we would ease into things.  Instead, I get this all-Ben extravaganza: combat, riding horses, foreign languages. And piano playing!  All waaaay outside my comfort zone.  How can you work two weeks and feel like you need a vacation already?"Jensen, Jeff "Doc", (April 10, 2008) "", ''Entertainment Weekly''.  Retrieved on April 26, 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="81837d7a9fc69446d234fd59b7b0bf47" name="Dharka" sectnum="2#1">../img/81837d7a9fc69446d234fd59b7b0bf47.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>