<document id="55c40b8c6964e2d03b4c5fa2f597487a-6.19" name="Everglades_National_Park" cat="11">
<text>
Another growing threat in recent years is the introduction of non-native species into the park. The melaleuca tree causes the most destruction of any plant species, taking large amounts of water and leaving marsh areas desiccated. Brazilian pepper (''Schinus terebinthifolius'') has invaded as well, competing with native plants that serve as food for animals, and is difficult to eradicate. The Burmese python (''Python molurus bivittatus'') is one of the most formidable animal species. These snakes are capable of growing up to  in length, and park visitors have seen them struggling with alligators. As Kenneth Krysko from the  Florida Museum of Natural History puts it, "These  are now the huge apex predator in the Everglades. There's nothing bigger." The first python was found in 1979, with none seen until 1995; between 2001 and 2005, however, more than 230 pythons have been discovered within the park boundaries, and they have begun reproducing on their own. Sunday section: Sports. When found, pythons are immediately captured and removed. Park biologists say that the exotic pet trade and pet owners who release pythons into the wilderness are responsible for the existence of the snakes within the Everglades. Skip Snow, wildlife biologist at Everglades National Park, said, "All of the Burmese pythons that we see in the park are a product of the international pet trade." Coyotes (''Canis latrans'') have also been spotted in the park, as well as in Big Cypress National Preserve. Park managers have attributed the lower numbers of wild pigs (''Sus scrofa'') in both parks to the arrival of coyotes. Sports section.  Numerous exotic bird species are often seen in or on the fringes of the park (mostly on the East Side).  Some established species include the common mynah (''Acridotheres tristis'') and various parrot species, while newcomers such as the sacred ibis (''Threskiornis aethiopicus'') show signs of increasing numbers.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2db862936583f5eee0b936631f6c7dba" name="Everglades_FH020005" sectnum="6.19#1">../img/2db862936583f5eee0b936631f6c7dba.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>