<document id="55c40b8c6964e2d03b4c5fa2f597487a-2.4" name="Everglades_National_Park" cat="11">
<text>
Several species of mangrove trees, which thrive in saline and brackish water, act as a nursery for many marine and bird species. They are also Florida's first defense against the destructive forces of hurricanes, absorbing flood waters and preventing coastal erosion. Due to their high tolerance of salt water, winds, extreme tides, high temperatures, and muddy soils, mangrove trees are uniquely adapted to extreme conditions. The mangrove system in Everglades National Park is the largest continuous system of mangroves in the world. 

There are 220 species of fish living in the Florida mangrove systems, along with a variety of crabs, crayfish, shrimp, mollusks, and other invertebrates, which serve as the main source of food for many birds.Whitney, p. 292&ndash;293 Dozens of bird species use mangroves as nurseries and food stores, including pelicans, grebes, tricolored herons (''Egretta tricolor''), gulls, terns, hawks and kites, and arboreal birds like mangrove cuckoos (''Coccyzus minor''), yellow warblers (''Dendroica petechia''), and white-crowned pigeons (''Patagioenas leucocephala'').Whitney, p. 295&ndash;296 The mangroves also support 24 species of amphibians and reptiles, and 18 species of mammals, including the endangered green turtle (''Chelonia mydas''), Hawksbill turtle (''Eretmochelys imbricata''), and West Indian manatee (''Trichechus manatus'').Whitney, p. 297

Cypress trees, conifers that are adapted to live in standing fresh water, grow in compact structures called cypress domes and in long strands over limestone. Water levels may fluctuate dramatically around cypress domes and strands, so cypresses develop "knees" that protrude from the water at high levels. Dwarf cypress trees grow in drier areas with poorer soil. Air plants called epiphytes, such as bromeliads, Spanish moss (''Tillandsia usneoides''), orchids and ferns grow on the branches and trunks of cypress trees. Everglades National Park features twenty-five species of orchids. Tall cypress trees provide excellent nesting areas for birds including wild turkeys (''Meleagris gallopavo''), ibis, herons, egrets, anhingas (''Anhinga anhinga''), and belted kingfishers (''Megaceryle alcyon''). Mammals in cypress regions include white-tailed deer, squirrels, raccoons, opossums, skunks, swamp rabbits, river otters (''Lontra canadensis''), and bobcats, as well as small rodents.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="dee1cca4c7b51166da2338629f43b5eb" name="Everglades_Nat'l_Park_Mangrove" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/dee1cca4c7b51166da2338629f43b5eb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>