<document id="55c40b8c6964e2d03b4c5fa2f597487a-6.15" name="Everglades_National_Park" cat="11">
<text>
Less than 50 percent of the Everglades which existed prior to drainage attempts remains intact today. Populations of wading birds have dwindled 90 percent from their original numbers. The diversion of water to South Florida's still-growing metropolitan areas is the Everglades National Park's number one threat. In the 1950s and 1960s,  of canals and levees, 150 gates and spillways, and 16 pumping stations were constructed to direct water toward cities and away from the Everglades. Low levels of water leave fish vulnerable to reptiles and birds, and as sawgrass dries it can burn or die off, which in turn kills apple snails and other animals that wading birds feed upon.National Park Service (2005). "Everglades." (Brochure) Entire populations of birds disappeared in the 1960s;Grunwald, p. 202. following three years of higher numbers, ''The Miami Herald'' reported in 2009 that populations of wading birds have again decreased.Sessa, Whitney (March 1, 2009). "Taking A Dive: The Wading Bird Population at Everglades National Park Dropped by 29 Percent in 2008...", ''The Miami Herald'', State and Regional News.  

The west coast of Florida relies on desalinization for its fresh water; the quantity demanded is too great for the land to provide. Nitrates in the underground water system and high levels of mercury also impact the quality of fresh water the park receives. In 1998 a Florida panther was found dead in Shark Water Slough, with levels of mercury high enough to kill a human. Increased occurrences of algae blooms and red tide in Biscayne Bay and Florida Bay have been traced to the amounts of controlled water released from Lake Okeechobee. Domestic News. The brochure given to all visitors at Everglades National Park includes a statement that reads, "Freshwater flowing into the park is engineered. With the help of pumps, floodgates, and retention ponds along the park's boundary, the Everglades is presently on life support, alive but diminished."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b689e0b78f02be44abda159e73a1a92b" name="Everglades_National_Park_cypress" sectnum="6.15#1">../img/b689e0b78f02be44abda159e73a1a92b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>