<document id="55c40b8c6964e2d03b4c5fa2f597487a-3.8" name="Everglades_National_Park" cat="11">
<text>
Humans likely first inhabited the South Florida region 10,000 to 20,000 years ago.Tebeau (1963), p. 17 Two tribes of Native Americans developed on the peninsula's southern tip: the Tequesta lived on the eastern side and the Calusa, greater in numbers, on the western side. The Everglades served as a natural boundary between them. The Tequesta lived in a single large community near the mouth of the Miami River, while the Calusa lived in 30 villages. Both groups traveled through the Everglades, but rarely lived within them, remaining mostly along the coast.Tebeau (1963), p. 17

The diets of both groups consisted mostly of shellfish and fish, small mammals, game, and wild plants. Having access only to soft limestone, most of the tools fashioned by Native Americans in the region were made of shell, bone, wood, and animal teeth; shark teeth were used as cutting blades,Tebeau (1963), p. 19 and sharpened reeds became arrows and spears.Robertson, p. 55 Shell mounds still exist today within the park, giving archaeologists and anthropologists evidence of the raw materials available to the indigenous people for tool construction. Spanish explorers estimated the number of Tequesta at first contact to be around 800, and Calusa at 2,000, although the National Park Service reports there were probably about 20,000 natives living in or near the Everglades when the Spanish established contact in the late 1500s. The Calusa society was more advanced, as they lived in social strata, and were able to create canals, earthworks, and shellworks. The Calusa were also able to resist Spanish attempts at conquest.Tebeau (1963), p. 19

Although the Spanish had contact with these societies, they established missions further north, near Lake Okeechobee. In the 1700s, invading Creeks incorporated the dwindling numbers of the Tequesta into their own. Neither the Tequesta nor Calusa tribe existed by 1800.Tebeau (1963), p. 23 Disease, warfare, and capture for slavery were the probably reasons for the eradication of both groups. The only evidence of their existence within the park boundaries is a series of shell mounds that were built by the Calusa.

In the early 1800s, Creeks, escaped African slaves, and other Indians from northern Florida displaced by the Creek War formed the area's Seminole nation. After the end of the Seminole Wars in 1842, the Seminoles faced relocation to Indian territory near Oklahoma. A few hundred Seminole hunters and scouts settled within what is today Big Cypress National Preserve, to escape the emigration to the west.Tebeau (1963), p. 28 From 1859 to about 1930, the Seminoles and Miccosukee, a similar but linguistically unique tribe, lived in relative isolation, making their living by trading. In 1928, surveying and construction began on the Tamiami Trail, along the northern border of Everglades National Park. The road not only bisected the Everglades but also introduced a steady, if small, traffic of white settlers into the Everglades.Tebeau (1963), p. 31

Some members of the Miccosukee and Seminole tribes continue to live within park boundaries. Management of the park includes approval of new policies and procedures by tribal representatives "in such a manner that they do not conflict with the park purpose".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7668c661cadb43afe604273e20b13c71" name="Watching_Sunset_Over_Marshes" sectnum="3.8#1">../img/7668c661cadb43afe604273e20b13c71.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>