<document id="55c40b8c6964e2d03b4c5fa2f597487a-6.17" name="Everglades_National_Park" cat="11">
<text>
Thirty-six federally protected animals live in the park, some of which face grave concern for survival. The American crocodile is found only in South Florida within the United States. Overhunted for their hides, today they are protected from hunting, but are still threatened due to habitat destruction, and injury from cars when they cross roads to reach waterways. Roughly 50 nests exist in Everglades and Biscayne National Parks, and about 1,000 crocodiles currently live in Florida. Numbers of crocodiles in South Florida have risen recently along with the numbers of alligators, and crocodiles were reclassified as "threatened" in the United States in 2007. Domestic News. 

The Florida panther is one of the most endangered mammals on earth, and they live primarily in the Everglades and the Big Cypress Swamp. Fewer than 100 live in the wild. The biggest threats to the panther include habitat destruction from human development, vehicle collisions, inbreeding due to a limited gene pool, parasites, diseases, and mercury poisoning. 

Four species of sea turtles including the Atlantic green sea turtle, Atlantic hawksbill, Atlantic loggerhead (''Caretta caretta''), and the Atlantic ridley (''Lepidochelys kempii'') are endangered, and the leatherback sea turtle (''Dermochelys coriacea'') is threatened. Although numbers are difficult to determine, since males and juveniles do not return to their birthplace, females lay eggs in the same location every year. Habitat loss and illegal poaching and destructive fishing practices are the biggest threats to these animals. 

Two species of birds in the park are most in danger of disappearing. The Cape Sable seaside sparrow is restricted to Everglades National Park and the Big Cypress Swamp. - Accessed February 12, 2008 In 1981 there were 6,656 Cape Sable seaside sparrows reported in its boundaries, but surveys over 10 years documented a decline to an estimated 2,624 birds by 2002. Attempts to return natural levels of water to the park have been controversial; Cape Sable seaside sparrows nest about a foot off the ground, and rising water levels may harm future populations, as well as threaten the endangered snail kite. Domestic News. The Everglades snail kite eats apple snails almost exclusively, and the Everglades is the only location in the United States where this bird of prey exists. There is some evidence that the population may be increasing, but loss of habitat and food sources keep the estimated number of these birds at several hundred. 

The West Indian manatee has recently been upgraded from endangered to threatened. Collisions with boats and habitat loss are still its biggest threats.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c9ceab3ffc16edbb1e7c79d410284a1e" name="Everglades_American_Crocodile" sectnum="6.17#1">../img/c9ceab3ffc16edbb1e7c79d410284a1e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>