<document id="56754c98f49c04325f506991a7bab3d6-3.9" name="Letters_Written_in_Sweden,_Norway,_and_Denmark" cat="17">
<text>
All of Wollstonecraft's writings, including the ''Letters Written in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark'', address the concerns of women in eighteenth-century society. As in previous works, she discusses concrete issues such as childcare and relationships with servants, but unlike her more polemical books such as ''Thoughts on the Education of Daughters'' (1787) or the ''Rights of Woman'', this text emphasizes her emotional reactions to nature and maternity. Yet she does not depart from her interest in promoting women's education and rights. In Letter 19, the most explicitly feminist letter, Wollstonecraft anticipates readers' criticisms: “still harping on the same subject, you will exclaim – How can I avoid it, when most of the struggles of an eventful life have been occasioned by the oppressed state of my sex: we reason deeply, when we forcibly feel.”Wollstonecraft (Holmes/Penguin), 171. Wollstonecraft comes to the realization that she has always been forced to experience the world as a woman—it is the defining feature of her sense of self.Poovey, 89; Jacobus, 74. 

Throughout ''Letters Written in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark'', Wollstonecraft comments on the precarious position women occupy in society. She defends and sympathizes with Queen Caroline of Denmark, for example, who had been accused of "licentiousness" for her extra-marital affair during her marriage to the insane Christian VII. (Wollstonecraft herself had had unorthodox love affairs and an illegitimate child.) Wollstonecraft describes this royal, who was also a progressive social reformer, as a woman of courage who tried to revolutionize her country before it was prepared. Jacobus, 75; Todd, 368, Swaab, 25–26. Such examples fuel Wollstonecraft's increasing despair and melancholy. At one point, she laments the fate of her daughter:



You know that as a female I am particularly attached to her – I feel more than a mother's fondness and anxiety, when I reflect on the dependent and oppressed state of her sex. I dread lest she should be forced to sacrifice her heart to her principles, or principles to her heart. With trembling hand I shall cultivate sensibility, and cherish delicacy of sentiment, lest, whilst I lend fresh blushes to the rose, I sharpen the thorns that will wound the breast I would fain guard – I dread to unfold her mind, lest it should render her unfit for the world she is to inhabit – Hapless woman! what a fate is thine!Wollstonecraft (Holmes/Penguin), 97.

Wollstonecraft's anger and frustration over the secondary status afforded women compels her to define herself in antithesis to conventional images of femininity. In the first letter she proudly announces “at supper my host told me bluntly that I was a woman of observation, for I asked him ''men's questions''” (emphasis Wollstonecraft's).Wollstonecraft (Holmes/Penguin), 68; see also Myers, 174.

Wollstonecraft casts the female imagination as the productive counterpoint to destructive masculine commerce, a feat she achieves primarily through her use of the genre of the letter. While the ''Rights of Woman'' argued that women should be "useful" and "productive", importing the language of the market into the home, ''Letters Written in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark'' adopts the values of the domestic space for the larger social and political world.Favret, 120; see also, 96; 127.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1616357d17c8a4d99b5a1b4e203ba024" name="Caroline_Mathilde_by_Juel" sectnum="3.9#1">../img/1616357d17c8a4d99b5a1b4e203ba024.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>