<document id="56754c98f49c04325f506991a7bab3d6-2.2" name="Letters_Written_in_Sweden,_Norway,_and_Denmark" cat="17">
<text>
One half of the "generic hybridity" of ''Letters Written in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark'' is the epistolary travel narrative.Myers, 169–70. Wollstonecraft's conception of this genre was shaped by eighteenth-century empirical and moral travel narratives, particularly Oliver Goldsmith's ''The Traveller, or a Prospect of Society'' (1764), Laurence Sterne's ''A Sentimental Journey Through France and Italy'' (1768), Samuel Johnson's ''A Journey to the Western Islands of Scotland'' (1775), James Boswell's ''Journal of a Tour to the Hebrides'' (1785), and Arthur Young's travel books.Myers, 173; Swaab, 17–18; Kelly, 177; Holmes, 17; Parks, 32.

After reviewing twenty-four travel books for Joseph Johnson's periodical, the ''Analytical Review'', Wollstonecraft was well-versed in the genre. This extensive reading solidified her ideas of what constituted a good travel book; in one review, she maintained that travel writers should have “some decided point in view, a grand object of pursuit to concentrate their thoughts, and connect their reflections” and that their books should not be “detached observations, which no running interest, or prevailing bent in the mind of the writer rounds into a whole”.Qtd. in Swaab, 15; see also, Swaab, 14; Myers, 166; Kelly, 177. Her reviews praised detailed and engaging descriptions of people and places, musings on history, and an insatiable curiosity in the traveller.Swaab, 14; see also Holmes, 32.

“The art of travel is only a branch of the art of thinking", Wollstonecraft wrote.Qtd. in Swaab, 15. Her journey and her comments on it are, therefore, not only sentimental but also philosophical. She uses the two modes to continue the critique of the roles afforded women and the progress of civilization that she had outlined in ''A Vindication of the Rights of Men'' (1790), ''A Vindication of the Rights of Woman'' (1792), and ''An Historical and Moral View of the French Revolution''.Kelly, 178–79. After overturning the conventions of political and historical writing, Wollstonecraft brought what scholar Gary Kelly calls "Revolutionary feminism" to yet another genre that had typically been considered the purview of male writers, transforming the travel narrative's "blend of objective facts and individual impressions . . . into a rationale for autobiographical revelation".Myers, 181. As one editor of the ''Letters Written in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark'' writes, the book is “nothing less than a revolution in literary genres”; its sublimity, expressed through scenes of intense feeling, made “a new wildness and richness of emotional rhetoric” desirable in travel literature.

One scholar has called Wollstonecraft the “complete passionate traveler”.Parks, 33. Her desire to delve into and fully experience each moment in time was fostered by the works of Jean-Jacques Rousseau, particularly his ''Reveries of a Solitary Walker'' (1782).Sapiro, 286–87; Jacobus, 64; Todd, 368; Favret, 104. Several of Rousseau's themes appear in the ''Letters Written in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark'', such as "the search for the source of human happiness, the stoic rejection of material goods, the ecstatic embrace of nature, and the essential role of sentiment in understanding".Favret, 104–106. However, while Rousseau ultimately rejects society, Wollstonecraft celebrates both domesticity and industrial progress.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="813aae6e5385ea4c58080259683dfb1a" name="Jean-Jacques_Rousseau_(painted_portrait)" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/813aae6e5385ea4c58080259683dfb1a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>