<document id="56754c98f49c04325f506991a7bab3d6-3.6" name="Letters_Written_in_Sweden,_Norway,_and_Denmark" cat="17">
<text>
Often categorized as a rationalist philosopher, Wollstonecraft demonstrates her commitment to and appreciation of feeling in ''Letters Written in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark''. She argues that subjective experiences, such as the transcendent emotions prompted by the sublime and the beautiful, possess a value equal to the objective truths discovered through reason.Poovey, 83–84; Myers, 167. In Wollstonecraft's earlier works, reason was paramount, because it allowed access to universal truths. In ''Letters Written in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark'', however, reason serves as a tool for reflection, mediating between the sensual experiences of the world and an abstract notion of truth (not necessarily universal truth). Maturation is not only the acquisition of reason—the view Wollstonecraft had adopted in ''Original Stories from Real Life'' (1788)—but also an understanding of when and how to trust one's emotions.Poovey, 85–86; see also Myers, 180.

Wollstonecraft's theories regarding reason, emotion, and the imagination are closely tied together. Some scholars contend that Wollstonecraft uses the imagination to liberate the self, especially the feminine self; it allows her to envision roles for women outside the traditional bounds of eighteenth-century thought and offers her a way to articulate those new ideas.Myers, 180; Poovey, 106 In contrast, others view Wollstonecraft's emphasis on the power of the imagination as detrimental, imprisoning her in an “individualized, bourgeois desire” which can never truly embrace sociality.Poovey, 106; see also, Kaplan, 239. 

Favret has argued that Wollstonecraft uses the imagination to reconcile "masculine understanding" and "female sensibility". Readers must imaginatively "work" while reading: their efforts will save them from descending into sentimentality as well as from being lured into commercial speculation. Even more importantly, readers become invested in the story of the narrator. Wollstonecraft's language demands that they participate in the "plot": 

'they' rescue the writer from the villain; 'they' accompany her on her flight from sorrow . . . With the readers' cooperation, the writer reverses the standard epistolary plot: here the heroine liberates herself by rejecting her correspondent and by embracing the 'world' outside of the domestic circle.Favret, 112. 

In giving the imagination the power to reshape society (a power suggested through numerous allusions to Shakespeare's ''The Tempest''), Wollstonecraft reveals that she has become a Romantic.Favret, 96; 109; 118.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0c1a37b1f3ec81c4165dae96d9feb43e" name="Caspar_David_Friedrich_032" sectnum="3.6#1">../img/0c1a37b1f3ec81c4165dae96d9feb43e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>