<document id="56754c98f49c04325f506991a7bab3d6-2.5" name="Letters_Written_in_Sweden,_Norway,_and_Denmark" cat="17">
<text>
Wollstonecraft relies extensively on the language of the sublime in ''Letters Written in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark''. She draws on and redefines Edmund Burke's central terms in ''A Philosophical Enquiry into the Origin of Our Ideas of the Sublime and Beautiful'' (1757). Burke privileges the sublime (which he associates with masculinity, terror, awe, and strength) over the beautiful (which he associates with femininity, passivity, delicacy, and weakness), while Wollstonecraft ties the sublime to sterility and the beautiful to fertility. For her, the beautiful is connected to the maternal; this aesthetic shift is evident, for example, in the many passages focusing on the affectionate tie between Wollstonecraft and little Fanny, her daughter. She thus claims the feminine category of the "beautiful" for the most virtuous and useful of women: mothers.Moskal, 264; see also 277–78.

Wollstonecraft also revises the conventional negative associations between the sublime and death; thoughts of death, prompted by a waterfall, for example, lead her to contemplate rebirth and immortality as well:

Reaching the cascade, or rather cataract, the roaring of which had a long time announced its vicinity, my soul was hurried by the falls into a new train of reflections. The impetuous dashing of the rebounding torrent from the dark cavities which mocked the exploring eye, produced an equal activity in my mind: my thoughts darted from earth to heaven, and I asked myself why I was chained to life and its misery? Still the tumultuous emotions this sublime object excited, were pleasurable; and, viewing it, my soul rose, with renewed dignity, above its cares – grasping at immortality – it seemed as impossible to stop the current of my thoughts, as of the always varying, still the same, torrent before me – I stretched out my hand to eternity, bounding over the dark speck of life to come.Wollstonecraft (Holmes/Penguin), 152–53.

Like her other manipulations of the language of the sublime, this passage is also heavily inflected by gender. As one scholar puts it, “because Wollstonecraft is a woman, and is therefore bound by the legal and social restrictions placed on her sex in the eighteenth century, she can only envisage autonomy of any form after death".Moore, 149–50.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="edff5b5117f8682d52489b9584e0ba4d" name="Joseph_Anton_Koch_010" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/edff5b5117f8682d52489b9584e0ba4d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>