<document id="570b86ec6ec8e1e2051c6ab59d19adb5-8" name="Manuel_I_Komnenos" cat="25">
<text>
During Manuel's reign three major theological controversies occurred. In 1156–1157 the question was raised, whether Christ had offered himself a sacrifice for the sins of the world to the Father and to the Holy Spirit only, or also to the Logos (i.e., to himself).J.H. Kurtz, ''History of the Christian Church to the Restoration'', 265–266 In the end a synod held at Constantinople in 1157 adopted a compromise formula, that the Word made flesh offered a double sacrifice to the Holy Trinity, despite the dissidence of Patriarch of Antioch-elect Soterichus Panteugenus.

Ten years later, a controversy arose as to whether the saying of Christ, "My Father is greater than I" referred to his divine nature, to his human, or the union of these two natures. Demetrius of Lampe, a Byzantine diplomat recently returned from the West, ridiculed the way the verse was interpreted there, that Christ was inferior to his father in his humanity, but equal in his divinity. Manuel on the other hand, perhaps with an eye on the project for Church union, found that the formula made sense, and prevailed over a majority in a synod convened on March 2, 1166 to decide the issue, where he had the support of the patriarch Luke Chrysoberges. Those who refused to submit to the synod's decisions had their property confiscated or were exiled. The political dimensions of this controversy are apparent from the fact that a leading dissenter from the Emperor's doctrine was his nephew Alexios Kontostephanos.P. Magdalino, ''The Empire of Manuel I Komnenos'', 217 

A third controversy sprung up in 1180, when Manuel objected to the formula of solemn abjuration, which was exacted from Moslem converts. One of the more striking anathemas of this abjuration was that directed against the deity worshipped by Muhammad and his followers:



The emperor ordered the deletion of this anathema from the Church's catechetical texts, a measure that provoked vehement opposition from both the Patriarch and bishops.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="93ec8e4a477b0e10c11660aa7da71189" name="Johnchrysostom" sectnum="8#1">../img/93ec8e4a477b0e10c11660aa7da71189.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>