<document id="570b86ec6ec8e1e2051c6ab59d19adb5-3.8" name="Manuel_I_Komnenos" cat="25">
<text>
During the Italian campaign, and, afterwards, during the struggle of the Papal Curia with Frederick, Manuel tried to seduce the Popes by hints of a possible union between the Eastern and Western Churches. Although in 1155 Pope Hadrian had expressed his eagerness to prompt the reunion of the Catholic and Orthodox Churches, hopes for a lasting Papal-Byzantine alliance came up against insuperable problems. Pope Adrian IV and his successors demanded recognition of their religious authority over all Christians everywhere, and wished themselves to reach superiority over the Byzantine Emperor; they were not at all willing to fall into a state of dependence from one emperor to the other. Manuel, on the other side, wanted an official recognition of his secular authority on both East and West.J.W. Birkenmeier, ''The Development of the Komnenian Army'', 114 Such conditions would not be accepted by either side. Even if a pro-western Emperor such as Manuel agreed to it, the Greek citizens of the Empire would have rejected outright any union of this sort, as they did almost three hundred years later when the Orthodox and Catholic churches were briefly united under the Pope. In spite of his friendliness towards the Roman Church and his cordial relations with all the Popes, Manuel was never honoured with the title of ''Augustus'' by the Popes. And although he sent twice (in 1167 and 1169) an embassy to Pope Alexander III offering to reunite the Greek and Latin churches, the latter refused, under pretext of the troubles that would follow that union.Abbé Guettée, ''The Papacy'', * J.W. Birkenmeier, ''The Development of the Komnenian Army'', 114 Ultimately, a deal proved elusive, and the two churches have remained divided.  

The final results of the Italian campaign were limited in terms of the advantages gained by the Empire. The city of Ancona became a Byzantine base in Italy, accepting the Emperor as sovereign. The Normans of Sicily had been damaged, and now came to terms with the Empire, ensuring peace for the rest of Manuel's reign. The Empire's ability to get involved in Italian affairs had been demonstrated. However, given the enormous quantities of gold which had been lavished on the project, it also demonstrated the limits of what money and diplomacy alone could achieve. The expense of Manuel's involvement in Italy must have cost the treasury a great deal (probably more than 2,160,000 ''hyperpyra'' or 30,000 pounds of gold), and yet it produced only limited solid gains.J.W. Birkenmeier, ''The Development of the Komnenian Army'', 116W. Treadgold, ''A History of the Byzantine State and Society'', 643
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1ef36e65b69ad20606afa2550a62b83a" name="Pope_Hadrian_IV" sectnum="3.8#1">../img/1ef36e65b69ad20606afa2550a62b83a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>