<document id="570b86ec6ec8e1e2051c6ab59d19adb5-2.4" name="Manuel_I_Komnenos" cat="25">
<text>
Yet Manuel's attention was to be drawn to Antioch again in 1156, when Raynald of Chatillon, the new Prince of Antioch, claimed that the Byzantine emperor had reneged on his promise to pay him a sum of money, and vowed to attack the Byzantine province of Cyprus.P.P. Read, ''The Templars'', 238 He arrested the governor of the island and nephew of the emperor, John Komnenos, and the general Michael Branas.P.P. Read, ''The Templars'', 239 The Latin historian William of Tyre deplored this act of war against fellow Christians, and described the atrocities committed by Raynald's men in considerable detail.William of Tyre, ''Historia'', XVIII,  Having ransacked the island and plundered all its wealth, Raynald's army mutilated the survivors before forcing them to buy back their flocks at exorbitant prices with what little they had left. Thus enriched with enough booty to make Antioch wealthy for years, the invaders boarded their ships and set sail for home.C. Hillenbrand, ''The Imprisonment of Raynald of Chatillon'', 80* T.F. Madden, ''The New Concise History of the Crusades'', 65 Raynald also sent some of the mutilated hostages to Constantinople as a vivid demonstration of his disobedience and his contempt for the Byzantine emperor.

Manuel responded to this outrage in a characteristically energetic way. In the winter of 1158–59, he marched to Cilicia at the head of a huge army; the speed of his advance (Manuel had hurried on ahead of the main army with 500 cavalry) was such that he managed to surprise the Armenian Thoros of Cilicia, who had participated in the attack on Cyprus.P. Magdalino, ''The Empire of Manuel I Komnenos'', 67 All the towns and cities of Cilicia fell to Manuel immediately, and Thoros himself was forced to flee into the mountains at the last moment: he is said to have survived by sheltering alone under rocks on a hillside, where an old shepherd would bring him food to keep him alive.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3da2246ba27f3391fbd1ee13fdc54019" name="Image-Manuel-Pope" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/3da2246ba27f3391fbd1ee13fdc54019.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>