<document id="57267c26958d246f697fcfd5738e596e-3.1.2" name="Thoroughbred" cat="3">
<text>
All modern Thoroughbreds trace back to three stallions imported into England from the Middle East in the late 17th and early 18th centuries: the Byerley Turk (1680s), the Darley Arabian (1704), and  the Godolphin Arabian (1729).Milner ''The Godolphin Arabian'' pp. 3&ndash;6Wall ''Famous Running Horses'' p. 8  Other stallions of oriental breeding were less influential, but still made noteworthy contributions to the breed. These included the Alcock Arabian,Willett ''The Thoroughbred'' p. 25  D'Arcy's White Turk, Leedes Arabian, and Curwen's Bay Barb.Phifer ''Track Talk'' p. 45Morris ''Thoroughbred Stallions'' pp. 1&ndash;2 Another was the Brownlow Turk, who, among other attributes, is thought to be largely responsible for the gray coat color in Thoroughbreds.  The addition of Arabian bloodlines to the native English mares ultimately led to the creation of the General Stud Book (GSB) in 1791 and the practice of official registration of horses.



Each of the three major foundation sires was, coincidentally, the ancestor of a grandson or great-great-grandson who was the only male descendant to perpetuate each respective horse's male line: Matchem was the only descendant of his grandsire, the Godolphin Arabian, to maintain a male line to the present;Milner ''The Godolphin Arabian'' p. 140 the Byerly Turk's male line was preserved by Herod (or King Herod), a great-great-grandson;Willett ''The Thoroughbred'' pp. 38–39 and the male line of the Darley Arabian owes its existence to great-great-grandson Eclipse, who was the dominant racehorse of his day and never defeated.Willett ''The Thoroughbred'' p. 37  One genetic study indicates that 95% of all male Thoroughbreds trace their direct male line (via the Y chromosome) to the Darley Arabian.Pickrell  ''New Scientist'' However, in modern Thoroughbred pedigrees, most horses have more crosses to the Godolphin Arabian (13.8%) than to the Darley Arabian (6.5%) when all lines of descent (maternal and paternal) are considered.  Further, as a percentage of contributions to current Thoroughbred bloodlines, Curwen's Bay Barb (4.2%) appears more often than the Byerly Turk (3.3%).  The majority of modern Thoroughbreds alive today trace to a total of only 27 or 28 stallions from the 18th and 19th centuries.Cunningham  ''Animal Genetics''Cunningham  ''Animal Genetics''
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e2d2ef04aba12e621f88d5000decd554" name="Matchem" sectnum="3.1.2#1">../img/e2d2ef04aba12e621f88d5000decd554.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>