<document id="57acfa52b2616f13857f6e317ef8942f-4" name="Shen_Kuo" cat="14">
<text>
Although the ''Dream Pool Essays'' is certainly his most extensive and important work, Shen Kuo wrote other books as well.  In 1075, Shen Kuo wrote the ''Xining Fengyuan Li'' (; ''The Oblatory Epoch astronomical system of the Splendid Peace reign period''), which was lost, but listed in a 7th chapter of a Song Dynasty bibliography.Sivin (1995), III, 46.  This was the official report of Shen Kuo on his reforms of the Chinese calendar, which were only partially adopted by the Song court's official calendar system.  Shen Kuo wrote a pharmaceutical treatise known as the ''Liang Fang'' (; ''Good medicinal formulas''), compiled sometime during his years of retirement from governmental service. Around the year 1126 it was combined into a written work of the famous Su Shi (1037&ndash;1101), who was ironically a political opponent to Shen Kuo's faction of Reformers and New Policies supporters at court,Sivin (1995), III, 47. yet it was known that Shen Kuo and Su Shi were nonetheless friends and associates.Needham (1986), Volume 1, 137. Shen wrote the ''Mengqi Wanghuai Lu'' (; ''Record of longings forgotten at Dream Brook''), which was also compiled during Shen's retirement.  This book was a treatise in the working since his youth on rural life and ethnographic accounts of living conditions in the isolated mountain regions of China.Sivin (1995), III, 48.  Only quotations of it survive in the ''Shuo Fu'' () collection, which mostly describe the agricultural implements and tools used by rural people in high mountain regions.  Shen Kuo also wrote the ''Changxing Ji'' (; ''Collected Literary Works of  Changxing'').  However, this book was without much doubt a posthumous collection, including various poems, prose, and administrative documents written by Shen. By the 15th century (during the Ming Dynasty), this book was reprinted, yet only the 19th chapter remained.  This chapter was reprinted in 1718, yet poorly edited.  Finally, in the 1950s the author Hu Daojing supplemented this small yet valuable work with additions of other scattered poems written by Shen, in the former's ''Collection of Shen Kua's Extant Poetry'' (Shanghai: Shang-hai Shu-tian, 1958). In the tradition of the popular Song era literary category of 'travel record literature' ('youji wenxue'),Hargett (1985), 67. Shen Kuo also wrote the ''Register of What Not to Forget'', a traveler's guide to what type of carriage is suitable for a journey, the proper foods one should bring, the special clothing one should bring, and many other items.Hargett (1985), 71.

In his ''Sequel to Numerous Things Revealed'', the Song author Cheng Dachang (1123&ndash;1195) noted that stanzas prepared by Shen Kuo for military victory celebrations were later written down and published by Shen.Stock (1993), 94. This includes a short poem "Song of Triumph" by Shen Kuo, who uses the musical instrument ''mawei huqin'' ('horse-tail barbarian stringed instrument' or 'horse-tail fiddle'Stock (1993), 108.) of the northwestern Inner Asian nomads as a metaphor for prisoners-of-war led by Song troops:



Historian Jonathan Stock notes that the bent bow described in the poem above represents the arched bow used to play the ''huqin'', while the sound of the instrument itself represented the discontent expressed by the prisoners-of-war with their defeated khan.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ea4fb5b2226d12c710c73790fef40285" name="SuShi-Portrait" sectnum="4#1">../img/ea4fb5b2226d12c710c73790fef40285.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>