<document id="57acfa52b2616f13857f6e317ef8942f-1.3" name="Shen_Kuo" cat="14">
<text>
The new Chancellor Cai Que (; 1036&ndash;1093) held Shen responsible for the disaster and loss of life. Along with abandoning the territory which Shen Kuo had fought for, Cai ousted Shen from his seat of office. Shen's life was now forever changed, as he lost his once reputable career in state governance and the military. Shen was then put under probation in a fixed residence for the next six years. However, as he was isolated from governance, he decided to pick up the quill and dedicate himself to intensive scholarly studies. After completing two geographical atlases for a state-sponsored program, Shen was rewarded by having his sentence of probation lifted, allowing him to live in a place of his choice. Shen was also pardoned by the court for any previous faults or crimes that were claimed against him.   
 
 
In his more idle years removed from court affairs, Shen Kuo enjoyed pastimes of the Chinese gentry and literati that would indicate his intellectual level and cultural taste to others.Lian (2001), 24. As described in his ''Dream Pool Essays'', Shen Kuo enjoyed the company of the "nine guests" (''jiuke''), a figure of speech for the Chinese zither, Chinese chess, Zen Buddhist meditation, ink (calligraphy and painting), tea drinking, alchemy, chanting poetry, conversation, and drinking wine.Lian (2001), 20. These nine activities were an extension to the older so-called Four Arts of the Chinese Scholar.

According to Zhu Yu's book ''Pingzhou Table Talks'' (; ''Pingzhou Ketan'') of 1119, Shen Kuo had two marriages; the second wife was the daughter of Zhang Chu (), who came from Huainan. Lady Zhang was said to be overbearing and fierce, often abusive to Shen Kuo, even attempting at one time to pull off his beard. Shen Kuo's children were often upset over this, and prostrated themselves to Lady Zhang to quit this behavior. Despite this, Lady Zhang went as far as to drive out Shen Kuo's son from his first marriage, expelling him from the household. However, after Lady Zhang died, Shen Kuo fell into a deep depression and even attempted to jump into the Yangtze River to drown himself. Although this suicide attempt failed, he would die a year later.Hongen.com (2000&ndash;2006). . Beijing Golden Human Computer Co., Ltd. . Retrieved on 2007-08-27.   

In the 1070s, Shen had purchased a lavish garden estate on the outskirts of modern-day Zhenjiang, Jiangsu province, a place of great beauty which he named "Dream Brook" ("Mengxi") after he visited it for the first time in 1086. Shen Kuo permanently moved to the Dream Brook Estate in 1088, and in that same year he completed his life's written work of the ''Dream Pool Essays'', naming the book after his garden-estate property. This book was Shen's ultimate attempt to comprehend and describe a multitude of various aspects of nature, science, and reality, and all the practical and profound curiosities found in the world. The literal translation of ''Mengxi Bitan'' is '' Dream Brook Brush Talks''. For this, Shen Kuo is quoted as saying: "Because I had only my writing brush and ink slab to converse with, I call it Brush Talks." It was there at his peaceful garden estate that Shen Kuo spent the last several years of his life in leisure, isolation, and illness, until his death in 1095.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f30625492cac58d61cc019465240405a" name="Liu_Songnian,_Luohan" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/f30625492cac58d61cc019465240405a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>