<document id="57acfa52b2616f13857f6e317ef8942f-2.9" name="Shen_Kuo" cat="14">
<text>
Since the time of the engineer and inventor Ma Jun (c. 200&ndash;265), the Chinese had used a mechanical device known as the South Pointing Chariot in order to navigate on land (and possibly at sea, as the ''Song Shu'' text of c. 500 alludes). This device was especially impressive, since it featured the use of a differential gear, an essential component used in the correct steering and application of equal amount of torque for the wheels of all modern automobiles. In 1044 the ''Collection of the Most Important Military Techniques'' (; ''Wujing Zongyao'') recorded that fish-shaped objects cut from sheet iron, magnetized by thermoremanence (essentially, heating that produced weak magnetic force), and placed in a water-filled bowl enclosed by a box were used for directional pathfinding alongside the South Pointing Chariot.Needham (1986), Volume 4, Part 1, 252. 


However, it was not until the time of Shen Kuo that the earliest magnetic compasses would be used for navigation. In his written work, Shen Kuo made one of the first references in human history to the magnetic compass-needle, the concept of true north, and its use for navigation at sea.Hsu (1988), 102. He wrote that steel needles were magnetized once they were rubbed with lodestone, and that they were put in floating position or in mountings; he described the suspended compass as the best form to be used, and noted that the magnetic needle of compasses pointed either south or north.Sivin (1995), III, 21.Elisseeff (2000), 296. Shen Kuo asserted that the needle will point south but with a deviation, stating " are always displaced slightly east rather than pointing due south."

Shen Kuo wrote that it was preferable to use the twenty-four-point rose instead of the old eight compass cardinal points — and the former was recorded in use for navigation shortly after Shen's death. The preference of use for the twenty-four-point-rose compass may have arisen from Shen's finding of a more accurate astronomical meridian, determined by his measurement between the polestar and true north; however, it could also have been inspired by geomantic beliefs and practices. The book of the author Zhu Yu, the ''Pingzhou Table Talks'' published in 1119 (written from 1111 to 1117), was the first record of use of a compass for seafaring navigation. However, Zhu Yu's book recounts events back to 1086, when Shen Kuo was writing the ''Dream Pool Essays''; this meant that in Shen's time the compass might have already been in navigational use.Needham (1986), Volume 4, Part 3, 463. In any case, Shen Kuo's writing on magnetic compasses has proved invaluable for understanding China's earliest use of the compass for seafaring navigation.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8d3abcff815049ea7ac5d20b67de7fad" name="Model_Si_Nan_of_Han_Dynasty" sectnum="2.9#1">../img/8d3abcff815049ea7ac5d20b67de7fad.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>