<document id="57acfa52b2616f13857f6e317ef8942f-2.14" name="Shen_Kuo" cat="14">
<text>
Shen Kuo wrote that during the Qingli reign period (1041&ndash;1048), under Emperor Renzong of Song (1022&ndash;1063), an obscure commoner and artisan known as Bi Sheng (990&ndash;1051) invented ceramic movable type printing.Needham (1986), Volume 5, Part 1, 201.Gernet (1996), 335. Although the use of assembling individual characters to compose a piece of text had its origins in antiquity, Bi Sheng's methodical innovation was something completely revolutionary for his time. Shen Kuo noted that the process was tedious if one only wanted to print a few copies of a book, but if one desired to make hundreds or thousands of copies, the process was incredibly fast and efficient. Beyond Shen Kuo's writing, however, nothing is known of Bi Sheng's life or the influence of movable type in his lifetime.Needham (1986), Volume 5, Part 1, 202–203. Although the details of Bi Sheng's life were scarcely known, Shen Kuo wrote: 
When Bi Sheng died, his fount of type passed into the possession of my followers (i.e. one of Shen's nephews), among whom it has been kept as a precious possession until now.Sivin (1995), III, 27. 


There are a few surviving examples of books printed in the late Song Dynasty using movable type printing.Wu (1943), 211-212. This includes Zhou Bida's ''Notes of The Jade Hall'' () printed in 1193 using the method of baked-clay movable type characters outlined in the ''Dream Pool Essays''.Xu Yinong Moveable Type Books () ISBN 7806437959 Yao Shu (1201&ndash;1278), an advisor to Kublai Khan, once persuaded a disciple Yang Gu to print philological primers and Neo-Confucian texts by using what he termed the "movable type of Shen Kuo".Needham (1986), Volume 5, Part 1, 203. Wang Zhen (fl. 1290&ndash;1333), who wrote the valuable agricultural, scientific, and technological treatise of the ''Nong Shu'', mentioned an alternative method of baking earthenware type with earthenware frames in order to make whole blocks. Wang Zhen also improved its use by inventing wooden movable type in the years 1297 or 1298, while he was a magistrate of Jingde, Anhui province.Needham (1986), Volume 5, Part 1, 206. The earlier Bi Sheng had experimented with wooden movable type,Needham (1986), Volume 5, Part 1, 205–206. but Wang's main contribution was improving the speed of typesetting with simple mechanical devices, along with the complex, systematic arrangement of wooden movable type involving the use of revolving tables.Needham (1986), Volume 5, Part 1, 208. Although later metal movable type would be used in China, Wang Zhen experimented with tin metal movable type, but found its use to be inefficient.Needham (1986), Volume 5, Part 1, 217.

By the 15th century, metal movable type printing was developed in Ming Dynasty China (and earlier in Joseon Korea, by the mid 13th century), and was widely applied in China by at least the 16th century.Needham (1986), Volume 5, Part 1, 211. In Jiangsu and Fujian, wealthy Ming era families sponsored the use of metal type printing (mostly using bronze). This included the printing works of Hua Sui (1439–1513), who pioneered the first Chinese bronze-type movable printing in the year 1490.Needham (1986), Volume 5, Part 1, 212. In 1718, during the mid Qing Dynasty (1644&ndash;1912), the scholar of Tai'an known as Xu Zhiding developed movable type with enamelware instead of earthenware. There was also Zhai Jinsheng (b. 1784), a teacher of Jingxian, Anhui, who spent thirty years making a font of earthenware movable type, and by 1844 he had over 100,000 Chinese writing characters in five sizes. 

Despite these advances, movable type printing never gained the amount of widespread use in East Asia that woodblock printing had achieved since the Chinese Tang Dynasty in the 9th century. With written Chinese, the vast amount of written morpheme characters impeded movable type's acceptance and practical use, and was therefore seen as largely unsatisfactory. Furthermore, the European printing press, first invented by Johannes Gutenberg (1398&ndash;1468), was eventually wholly adopted as the standard in China, yet the tradition of woodblock printing remains popular in East Asian countries still.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6456aae2244390479221752de2467489" name="Jingangjing" sectnum="2.14#1">../img/6456aae2244390479221752de2467489.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>