<document id="57acfa52b2616f13857f6e317ef8942f-2.4" name="Shen_Kuo" cat="14">
<text>
If the account of Sima Qian (c. 145&ndash;86 BC) in his ''Records of the Grand Historian'' is proven correct upon the unearthing of Qin Shi Huang's (r. 221&ndash;210 BC) tomb, the raised-relief map has existed since the Qin Dynasty (221&ndash;206 BC).Temple (1986), 179. Robert Temple and Joseph Needham suggest that certain pottery vessels of the Han Dynasty (202 BC &ndash; 220 AD) showing artificial mountains as lid decorations may have influenced the raised-relief map. The Han Dynasty general Ma Yuan (14 BC &ndash; 49 AD) made a raised-relief map of valleys and mountains in a rice-constructed model of 32 AD.Crespigny (2007), 659. Such rice models were expounded on by the Tang Dynasty (618&ndash;907) author Jiang Fang in his ''Essay on the Art of Constructing Mountains with Rice'' (c. 845 AD). A raised-relief map made of wood representing all the provinces of the empire and put together like a giant 0.93 m2 (10 ft2) jigsaw puzzle was invented by Xie Zhuang (421&ndash;466 AD) during the Liu Song Dynasty (420&ndash;479). 

Shen's largest atlas included twenty three maps of China and foreign regions that were drawn at a uniform scale of 1:900,000. Shen also created a three dimensional raised-relief map using sawdust, wood, beeswax, and wheat paste.Needham (1986), Volume 3, 579&ndash;580.Temple (1986), 180. Zhu Xi (1130&ndash;1200) was inspired by the raised-relief map of Huang Shang and so made his own portable map made of wood and clay which could be folded up from eight hinged pieces.Needham (1986), Volume 3, 580. Later, Ibn Battuta (1304&ndash;1377) described a raised-relief map while visiting Gibraltar, while European raised-relief maps started with a Paul Dox who made one to represent Kufstein, Austria, in 1510.Needham (1986), Volume 3, 579Temple (1986), 181. The Englishman John Evelyn (1620&ndash;1706), in his 1665 paper featured in the ''Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society'', wrote that the raised-relief map was something new from France.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="759d1847b67f984f06f432febb7e1120" name="FFM-HanWeingefäß" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/759d1847b67f984f06f432febb7e1120.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>