<document id="583d1520ad0d801390cc18bf148faa8a-4" name="Banksia_epica" cat="3">
<text>
Pollinators of ''B. epica'' include ''Phylidonyris novaehollandiae'' (New Holland Honeyeater) and ''Acanthiza chrysorrhoa'' (Yellow-rumped Thornbill). No other pollinators have been recorded, but the species is poorly surveyed, and studies of other ''Banksia'' species have consistently indicated a wide range of invertebrate and vertebrate pollinators. For example, a survey of the closely related and co-occurring ''B. media'' found that "honeyeater birds and marsupial nectarivores were abundant in the study area and most carried the pollen of ''Banksia media'' while it flowered.… Self-pollination and pollination by insects clearly also play major roles in seed production." 

Like most other Proteaceae, ''B. epica'' has proteoid roots, roots with dense clusters of short lateral rootlets that form a mat in the soil just below the leaf litter. These enhance solubilisation of nutrients, allowing nutrient uptake in low-nutrient soils such as the phosphorus-deficient native soils of Australia. The species lacks a lignotuber, so is thought to be killed by fire. Like most ''Banksia'' species, however, it is adapted to release its aerial seed bank following a bushfire, so populations regenerate rapidly. It is highly susceptible to ''Phytophthora cinnamomi'' dieback.

Because so few populations are known, ''B. epica'' has been listed on the Department of Environment and Conservation's Declared Rare and Priority Flora List as "Priority Two - Poorly Known Taxa""; and as 2RC under the ROTAP system (rare but not currently endangered or vulnerable, and having a range less than 100 km). It is not considered to be under threat, however, because both known populations occur within the Nuytsland Nature Reserve, and are undisturbed and healthy. Furthermore, the area in which it occurs is poorly surveyed, so it is possible that other populations exist.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f3fe5dce434f67365990dfe0e3e6bfc2" name="Banksia_epica_purp_foll_email" sectnum="4#1">../img/f3fe5dce434f67365990dfe0e3e6bfc2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>