<document id="586d23ad75fd82330ae7363d6ca9cf01-4" name="Green_and_Golden_Bell_Frog" cat="3">
<text>
As a member of the tree frog family, the Green and Golden Bell Frog spends much time basking in the sun on rocks and reeds. Unlike most frog species it is often active during the day. When handled, this species secretes a slimy acrid mucusBarker, J.; Grigg, G.C.; Tyler, M.J. (1995) Surrey Beatty & Sons.. ''A Field Guide to Australian Frogs'' - The ''Litoria aurea'' complex, page 99. which consists of 17 aurein peptides. Thirteen of these show broad-spectrum antibiotic and anti-cancer activity, which is useful in fighting off harmful microorganisms.  

The Green and Golden Bell Frog is generally associated with coastal swamps, woodland, and forest; but populations have also been found at former industrial sites (for instance, the Brickpit). The requirements of its habitat have been difficult to determine, for it has been found in a wide range of water bodies except fast-flowing streams.   It is most typically found in short-lived freshwater ponds that are still, shallow, unshaded and unpolluted; and it tends to avoid waters that contain predatory fish, whether native or introduced. The frog prefers water bodies that support emergent vegetation such as reeds and bullrushes for basking, and winter habitats consist of available shelters around the breeding site. Grassy habitats are usually close at hand to provide suitable terrestrial feeding grounds.

The Green and Golden Bell Frog's reproduction depends on salinity and water temperature. Salinity affects tadpoles' development and metamorphosis, and breeding generally only occurs in ponds that measure 20 °C (68 °F) or above. The Green and Golden Bell Frog tadpoles can tolerate salinity levels of six parts per thousand (ppt) without any apparent effects, while salinity of 8 ppt or higher decreases growth rates and increases mortality rates. On the other hand, salinity levels of at least 1–2 ppt can be beneficial to the Green and Golden Bell Frog because this kills pathogens such as the chytrid fungus.

The voracious adults have a very broad diet, including insects and other frogs, even of the same species. The tadpoles feed on detritus, algae and bacteria. Natural predators include wading birds and snakes, and are eaten by tortoises, eels, other fish, and a range of invertebrate predators.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="747d51059244d542d74b93a9d2e82f33" name="Litoria_aurea_green" sectnum="4#1">../img/747d51059244d542d74b93a9d2e82f33.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>