<document id="586d23ad75fd82330ae7363d6ca9cf01-3" name="Green_and_Golden_Bell_Frog" cat="3">
<text>
The Green and Golden Bell Frog is a large, stout frog; adults range from 4.5 centimetres to 11 centimetres (1¾ to 4¼ in) in length; typical specimens measure 6 to 8 centimetres (2½&ndash;3¼ in). The Green and Golden Bell Frog is therefore one of the largest Australian frogs. Mature male Green and Golden Bell Frogs are generally smaller than mature females, and the colour on their dorsal surface differs greatly to females. It may be almost completely green, of shades from dark pea-green to bright emerald; green with metallic, brassy, dull copper-brown, or gold markings; or almost completely bronze. During the cooler months (May-August), when Green and Golden Bell frogs are inactive, colouration may darken almost to black. They can also darken in this way by simply staying in a dark place for a few minutes.

A creamy-white or pale yellow stripe, bordered above with gold and below with black, extends from behind the eye, across the tympanum to the groin. This stripe rises to form a dorso-lateral fold towards the groin. Another stripe of the same colour begins below the eye and continues to the shoulder. The abdomen is cream or white, and has a coarsely granular texture. The legs are green, bronze, or a combination of both, and the inside thigh and groin are blue-green. Mature males develop a yellowish colouration to the vocal sac on the throat. The pupil is restricted to a horizontal slit and the iris is golden-brown with a black streak that runs from the corners of the pupil to the horizontal limits of the eye. The tympanum is distinct and ovular in shape, and the species has enlarged toe discs to aid in climbing. As this species is often found in water, the fingers are free from webbing while the toes are almost completely webbed. When in breeding condition, males develop nuptial pads on their thumbs, which are used to grip females during mating.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="85a5cfd03293b6720b61766d706c443f" name="Litoria_aurea_dark" sectnum="3#1">../img/85a5cfd03293b6720b61766d706c443f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>