<document id="586d23ad75fd82330ae7363d6ca9cf01-1" name="Green_and_Golden_Bell_Frog" cat="3">
<text>
The common name, "Green and Golden Bell Frog", was first adopted by Harold Cogger in his 1975 book ''Reptiles & Amphibians of Australia''. Before this, its common names were "Golden Frog" and "Golden Treefrog". The Green and Golden Bell Frog has many physical and behavioural characteristics representative of ranids; hence its original classification as ''Rana''. It has a pointy snout, long legs, and almost complete toe webbing; the tympanum is large and distinct; and the overall body shape is similar to many ''Rana'' species. Like many frogs in the ''Rana'' genus, Green and Golden Bell Frogs are mostly aquatic, and only travel over land during periods of rainfall. It was removed from the genus because of anatomical differences with the family Ranidae. The bone and cartilage structural formations of the Green and Golden Bell Frog are closest to those of species in the family Hylidae; it was therefore reclassified.

The Green and Golden Bell Frog was first described as ''Rana aurea'' by Lesson in 1827. It has changed classification 20 times; it was first named ''Litoria aurea'' in 1844 by Günther, and changed another nine times before being named again as ''Litoria aurea''.   The specific epithet ''aurea'' derived from the Latin ''aureus'' for 'golden'. The species is now classified within the ''Litoria aurea'' complex, a closely related group of frogs in the ''Litoria'' genus. This complex is scattered throughout Australia: three species occur in south-east Australia, one in northern Australia, and two in Southwest Australia. The complex consists of the Green and Golden Bell Frog (''Litoria aurea''), Growling Grass Frog (''Litoria raniformis''), Tablelands Bell Frog (''Litoria castanea''), Dahl's Aquatic Frog (''Litoria dahlii''), Spotted-thighed Frog (''Litoria cyclorhyncha'') and the Motorbike Frog (''Litoria moorei''). The ranges of ''L. raniformis'' and ''L. castanea'' overlap with the Green and Golden Bell Frog; this as well as physical similarities may make it difficult to distinguish between the species. The Tablelands Bell Frog has not been seen since 1980 and may now be extinct, although the large yellow spots present on its thighs help distinguish it from the Green and Golden Bell Frog. The Growling Grass Frog, which is very similar to the Green and Golden Bell Frog, can only be readily distinguished by raised bumps on the dorsal surface.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="aa4cc95fa933198e0a3a9e19eb8de49a" name="Litoria_aurea_Rana_comparison" sectnum="1#1">../img/aa4cc95fa933198e0a3a9e19eb8de49a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>