<document id="5909e31b3075748c4c9710b18c198739-5" name="Ficus_aurea" cat="3">
<text>
''Ficus aurea'' is a strangler fig&mdash;it tends to establish on a host tree which it gradually encircles and "strangles", eventually taking the place of that tree in the forest canopy.  While this makes ''F. aurea'' an agent in the mortality of other trees, there is little to indicate that its choice of hosts is species specific.  However, in dry forests on Great Exuma in The Bahamas, ''F. aurea'' establishes exclusively on palms, in spite of the presence of several other large trees that should provide suitable hosts.  Swagel and colleagues attributed this to the fact that humus accumulates on the leaf bases of these palms and provides a relatively moist microclimate in a dry environment, facilitating seedling survival.

Figs are sometimes considered to be potential keystone species in communities of fruit-eating animals because of their asynchronous fruiting patterns.   Wheelwright reports that Emerald Toucanets fed on unripe ''F. aurea'' fruit at times of fruit scarcity in Monteverde, Costa Rica.  Wheelwright listed the species as a year-round food source for the Resplendent Quetzal at the same site.  In the Florida Keys, ''F. aurea'' is one of the five fruit species that dominate the diet fed by White-crowned Pigeons to their nestlings.  ''F. aurea'' is also important in the diet of mammalian frugivores&mdash;both fruit and young leaves are consumed by black howler monkeys in Belize.

The interaction between figs and fig wasps is especially well-known (see section on reproduction, above).  In addition to its pollinators (''Pegoscapus mexicanus''), ''F. aurea'' is exploited by a group of non-pollinating chalcidoid wasps whose larvae develop in its figs.  These include gallers, inquilines and kleptoparasites as well as parasitoids of both the pollinating and non-pollinating wasps.

As a large tree, ''F. aurea'' can be an important host for epiphytes.  In Costa Rican cloud forests, where ''F. aurea'' is "the most conspicuous component" of intact forest, trees in forest patches supported richer communities of epiphytic bryophytes, while isolated trees supported greater lichen cover. 

Florida International University ecologist Suzanne Koptur reported the presence of extrafloral nectaries on ''F. aurea'' figs in the Florida Everglades.  Extrafloral nectaries are structures which produce nectar but are not associated with flowers.  They are usually interpreted as defensive structure and are often produced in response to attack by insect herbivores.  They attract insects, primarily ants, which defend the nectaries, thus protecting the plant against herbivores.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="62e7ae4a36f52b550ab781b42391229c" name="Rubber,_or_Banyan_Tree,_on_Banana_River,_Florida" sectnum="5#1">../img/62e7ae4a36f52b550ab781b42391229c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>