<document id="5927bc35ce53b83946c55ee95b63da1f-3.7" name="William_III_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
By 1678, Louis sought peace with the Dutch Republic.Troost, 141–145 Even so, tensions remained: William remained very suspicious of Louis, thinking the French king desired "Universal Kingship" over Europe; Louis described William as "my mortal enemy" and saw him as an obnoxious warmonger. France's small annexations in Germany (the ''Réunion'' policy) and the revocation of the Edict of Nantes in 1685, caused a surge of Huguenot refugees to the Republic.Troost, 153–156 This led William III to join various anti-French alliances, such as the Association League, and ultimately the League of Augsburg (an anti-French coalition that also included the Holy Roman Empire, Sweden, Spain and several German states) in 1686.Troost, 156–163

After his marriage in November 1677, William became a possible candidate for the English throne if his father-in-law (and uncle) James would be excluded because of his Catholicism. During the crisis concerning the Exclusion Bill in 1680, Charles at first invited William to come to England to bolster the king's position against the ''exclusionists'', then withdrew his invitation—after which Lord Sunderland also tried unsuccessfully to bring William over but now to put pressure on Charles.Troost, 150–151 Nevertheless, William secretly induced the States-General to send the ''Insinuation'' to Charles, beseeching the king to prevent any Catholics from succeeding him, without explicitly naming James.Troost, 152–153 After receiving indignant reactions from Charles and James, William denied any involvement.

In 1685, when James II succeeded Charles, William at first attempted a conciliatory approach, whilst at the same time trying not to offend the Protestants in England.Troost, 173–175 William hoped James would join the League of Augsburg, but by 1687 it became clear that James would not join the anti-French alliance. Relations worsened between William and James thereafter.Troost, 180–183 In November, James's wife Mary of Modena was announced to be pregnant.Troost, 189 That month, to gain the favour of English Protestants, William wrote an open letter to the English people in which he disapproved of James's religious policies. Seeing him as a friend, and often having maintained secret contacts with him for years, many English politicians began to negotiate an armed invasion of England.Troost, 186
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5927bc35ce53b83946c55ee95b63da1f" name="William_III_of_England" sectnum="3.7#1">../img/5927bc35ce53b83946c55ee95b63da1f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>