<document id="5927bc35ce53b83946c55ee95b63da1f-5.11" name="William_III_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
Although the Whigs were William's strongest supporters, he initially favoured a policy of balance between the Whigs and Tories.Troost, 220–223 The Marquess of Halifax, a man known for his ability to chart a moderate political course, gained William's confidence early in his reign.Troost, 221 The Whigs, a majority in Parliament, had expected to dominate the government, and were disappointed that William denied them this chance.Van der Zee, 296–297 This "balanced" approach to governance did not last beyond 1690, as the conflicting factions made it impossible for the government to pursue effective policy, and William called for new elections early that year.Troost, 222; van der Zee, 301–302


After the Parliamentary elections of 1690, William began to favour the Tories, led by Danby and Nottingham.Troost, 223–227 While the Tories favoured preserving the king's prerogatives, William found them unaccommodating when he asked Parliament to support his continuing war with France.Troost, 226 As a result, William began to prefer the Whig faction known as the Junto.Troost, 228–232 The Whig government was responsible for the creation of the Bank of England. William's decision to grant the Royal Charter in 1694 to the Bank, a private institution owned by bankers, is his most relevant economic legacy.Claydon, 129–131 It laid the financial foundation of the English take-over of the central role of the Dutch Republic and Bank of Amsterdam in global commerce in the 18th century.

William dissolved Parliament in 1695, and the new Parliament that assembled that year was led by the Whigs. There was a considerable surge in support for William following the exposure of a Jacobite plan to assassinate him in 1696.Van der Zee, 402–403 Parliament passed a bill of attainder against the ringleader, John Fenwick, and he was beheaded in 1697.Van der Zee, 414
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d9ecc45683fc420be6c2dd5c76b1851b" name="William%26MaryEngraving1703" sectnum="5.11#1">../img/d9ecc45683fc420be6c2dd5c76b1851b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>