<document id="5927bc35ce53b83946c55ee95b63da1f-4.9" name="William_III_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
In 1689, William summoned a Convention Parliament to discuss the appropriate course of action following James's flight.Davies, 614–615 William felt insecure about his position; though only his wife was formally eligible to assume the throne, he wished to reign as King in his own right, rather than as a mere consort.Troost, 207–210 The only precedent for a joint monarchy in England dated from the sixteenth century, when Queen Mary I married the Spanish Prince Philip.Davies, 469; Israel, 136 Philip remained King only during his wife's lifetime, and restrictions were placed on his power. William, on the other hand, demanded that he remain as King even after his wife's death.Van der Kiste, 107–108 Although the majority of Tory Lords proposed to acclaim her as sole ruler, Mary, remaining loyal to her husband, refused.Troost, 209

On 13 February 1689, Parliament passed the Declaration of Right, in which it deemed that James, by attempting to flee, had abdicated the government of the realm, thereby leaving the Throne vacant.Troost, 210–212 The Crown was not offered to James's eldest son, James Francis Edward (who would have been the heir-apparent under normal circumstances), but to William and Mary as joint Sovereigns. It was, however, provided that "the sole and full exercise of the regal power be only in and executed by the said Prince of Orange in the names of the said Prince and Princess during their joint lives".

William and Mary were crowned together at Westminster Abbey on 11 April 1689 by the Bishop of London, Henry Compton.Troost, 219–220 Normally, the coronation is performed by the Archbishop of Canterbury, but the Archbishop at the time, William Sancroft, refused to recognise James's removal. On the day of the coronation, the Convention of the Estates of Scotland&mdash;which was much more divided than the English Parliament&mdash;finally declared that James was no longer King of Scotland.Troost, 266–268 William and Mary were offered the Scottish Crown; they accepted on 11 May.Davies, 614–615. William was "William II" of Scotland, for there was only one previous Scottish King named William.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="af8baab6f79ddbe3a9923d1f5c58054b" name="William_III_Silver_Coin" sectnum="4.9#1">../img/af8baab6f79ddbe3a9923d1f5c58054b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>