<document id="5927bc35ce53b83946c55ee95b63da1f-1.2" name="William_III_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
William's mother showed little personal interest in her son, sometimes being absent for years, and had always deliberately kept herself apart from Dutch society.Van der Kiste, 5–6; Troost, 27 William's education was first laid in the hands of several Dutch governesses, and some of English descent, including Walburg Howard. From April 1656 the Calvinist preacher Cornelis Trigland, a follower of the Contra-Remonstrant theologian Gisbertus Voetius, instructed the prince daily in the reformed religion.Troost, 34–37 A short treatise, perhaps by one of William's tutors, Constantijn Huygens, details the ideal education for William entitled ''Discours sur la nourriture de S.H. Monseigneur le Prince d'Orange''.Troost, 27. The author may also have been Johan van den Kerckhoven. ''Ibid.'' In these lessons, the prince was taught that he was predestined to become an instrument of Divine Providence, fulfilling the historical destiny of the House of Orange.Troost, 36–37



From early 1659, William spent seven years at the University of Leiden for a formal education—though never officially enrolling as a student—under the guidance of ethics professor Hendrik Bornius.Troost, 37–40 While residing in the ''Prinsenhof'' at Delft, William had a small personal retinue including Hans Willem Bentinck, and a new governor: Frederick Nassau de Zuylestein, the illegitimate son of stadtholder Frederick Henry of Orange. He was taught French by Samuel Chappuzeau (who was dismissed by William's grandmother after the death of his mother).Meinel

On 25 September 1660 the States of Holland under the prime movers  Grand Pensionary Johan de Witt and his uncle Cornelis de Graeff resolved to take charge of William's education to ensure he would acquire the skills to serve in a future—though undetermined—state function.Troost, 43 This first involvement of the authorities would not last long. On 23 December 1660, when William was ten years old, his mother died of smallpox at Whitehall Palace, London while visiting her brother King Charles II. In her will, Mary requested that Charles look after William's interests, and the English King now demanded the States of Holland end their interference.Troost, 43–44 To appease Charles, they complied on 30 September 1661.Troost, 44 In 1661, Zuylenstein began to work for Charles, and induced William to write letters to the English king asking his uncle to interfere on his behalf to improve his prospects on the stadtholderate.Troost, 49 After his mother's death, William's education and guardianship became a point of contention between his dynasty's supporters and the advocates of a more republican Netherlands.Van der Kiste, 12–17

The Dutch authorities did their best at first to ignore these intrigues, but in the Second Anglo-Dutch War one of Charles's peace conditions was the improvement of the position of his nephew. As a countermeasure in 1666, when William was sixteen, the States of Holland officially made him a ward of the government, or a "Child of State". All pro-English courtiers, including Zuylenstein, were removed from William's company. William begged De Witt to allow Zuylenstein to stay, but he refused.Van der Kiste, 14–15 De Witt, the leading politician of the Republic, took William's education into his own hands, instructing him weekly in state matters—and joining him in a regular game of real tennis.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f8ddff20e5cbbcbe55dbb84555a38bb7" name="Charles_II_of_England" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/f8ddff20e5cbbcbe55dbb84555a38bb7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>