<document id="5a0a88d00631f43ae7773c7ed0931cba-3" name="Neilston" cat="11">
<text>
At  (55.784°, -4.423°) Neilston is situated in Scotland's Central Lowlands. The community lies  above sea level,  southwest of Barrhead,  south of Paisley, and  southwest of Glasgow. The chief river is the Levern, which has its source at Long Loch. It flows eastwards through Neilston towards Barrhead, before uniting its waters with those of the White Cart Water.

The topography of Neilston is irregular; to the east nearly flat, and to the south and west, rising to heights of  to  above the level of the River Clyde. The highest points are Neilston Pad and the Corkendale-law, at about  and  above sea level, respectively. Neilston Pad is characterised by a craggy face on its eastern side. Between these hills lies the narrow valley of the River Levern, along which passes the turnpike-road to Glasgow and Paisley. The soil in the eastern parts of Neilston is a dry loam, occasionally intermixed with gravel. Amongst the hilly areas of the village, the soil is less fertile, whilst in all other rural parts, the land is moss covered moor. The local geology is represented by basalt. The surrounding landscape is dominated by Duncarnock, the resistant core of an ancient and long extinct volcano, known locally as 'the Craigie'.

Neilston experiences a temperate maritime climate, like much of the British Isles, with relatively cool summers and mild winters. Regular but generally light precipitation occurs throughout the year. Several lakes and small lochs have formed around Neilston: Long Loch, Loch Libo, and Loch Cawpla. Aboon the Brae (Scots language for "above the hill") is the site of a spring. There are a number of small named-localities in and around Neilston: Arthurlie, Holehouse, Crofthead, Kirkstyle, Coldoun, Gateside, Hollows, Broadley, Nether Kirkton and Neilstonside.

Neilston's built environment is characterised by its mixture of nineteenth- and twentieth-century detached cottages, single and two-story buildings. Several mansion houses were built for the owners of former mills and factories. Many of Neilston's dwellings are painted in whites or ivories. In his book ''Ordnance Survey of Scotland'' (1884), Francis Hindes Groome remarked that Neilston "presents an old-fashioned yet neat and compact appearance", a view echoed by Hugh McDonald in ''Rambles Round Glasgow'' (1910), who stated that Neilston "is a compact, neat, and withal somewhat old-fashioned little township", although continued that it has "few features calling for special remark". It is frequently described as a quiet dormitory village, although some sources from around the turn of the twentieth century describe Neilston as a town. There is a mixture of suburbs, semi-rural, rural and former-industrial locations in Neilston, but overwhelmingly the land use in central Neilston is sub-urban. The territory of Neilston is not contiguous with any other settlement, and according to the General Register Office for Scotland, does not form part of Greater Glasgow, the United Kingdom's fifth largest conurbation.

The Killoch Burn and glen, at the north of Neislton, have become associated with a witch because at low water the numerous pot-holes or rock-cut basins have worn into one another, giving unusual shapes. Locals named some of these the witch's floor, hearth, craddle, water-stoup and grave.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e23ada053947643dc61f80af84d2170a" name="Neilston_Pad" sectnum="3#1">../img/e23ada053947643dc61f80af84d2170a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>