<document id="5a508830664397f934e078082c5e0f6e-2" name="Philitas_of_Cos" cat="17">
<text>
Philitas wrote a vocabulary explaining the meanings of rare literary words, words from local dialects, and technical terms; it probably took the form of a lexicon. The vocabulary, called ''Disorderly Words'' (Ἄτακτοι γλῶσσαι, ''''), has been lost, with only a few fragments quoted by later authors. One example, quoted in Athenaeus, is that the word πέλλα ('''') meant "wine cup" in the ancient Greek region of Boeotia;Athenaeus (tr. C.D. Yonge). ''The Gastronomers'', . Retrieved 2009-08-26. this was evidently contrasted to the same word meaning "milk pail" in Homer's ''Iliad''. ''Hermeneia'', another scholarly work, probably contained Philitas' versions and critical interpretations of Homer and other authors.

About thirty fragments of Philitas' poetry are known, along with four definite titles:
* ''Demeter'', Philitas' most famous work, consisted of elegiac couplets, or couplets in the elegiac meter. Its few surviving fragments suggest that it narrated the grain goddess Demeter's hunt for her daughter Persephone. The fragments describe Demeter's arrival on Cos and warm welcome by its royal family of Meropids, or humans twice normal size, thus presenting the founding myth of a local cult of Demeter on Cos.
* ''Hermes'' was an epyllion, or brief mythological narrative, written in hexameter. It had the structure of a hymn, with a central narrative telling of Odysseus' visit to the island of the king Aeolus, keeper of the winds, and of Odysseus' secret affair with the king's daughter Polymele.
* ''Playthings'' (Παίγνια, ) had two shorter collections. These poems had the structure of epigrams and their themes may have included erotica. The only surviving poem contains two elegiac couplets and has a puzzle or riddle structure characteristic of some ancient Greek drinking-party songs.
* Only one of the ''Epigrams'' has been fully reconstructed.
Another possible poem is ''Telephus'', which may have been a companion to ''Demeter''.

At most fifty verses of Philitas survive. Below is an example fragment of two verses, which was quoted in the ''Collection of Paradoxical Stories'', whose putative author Antigonus (often identified with Antigonus of Carystus, a near-contemporary) does not specify which work they came from; indirect evidence suggests ''Demeter''. These two verses show the confluence of Philitas' interests in poetry and obscure words:




The deer can sing when it has lost its lifeif it avoids the prick of the sharp "cactus".


According to Antigonus, the "cactus" (κάκτος, '''') was a thorny plant from Sicily, and "When a deer steps on it and is pricked, its bones remain soundless and unusable for flutes. For that reason Philitas spoke of it." Antigonus quotes one more passage, and the 5th century AD anthologist Stobaeus quotes eleven passages from Philitas; the remaining fragments are derived from ancient commentators who quoted Philitas when discussing rare words or names used by other authors.Bulloch, "Hellenistic poetry", p. 5.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="84181bf57b460fae8e693fc8455b4272" name="POxy.XX.2260.i-Philitas-highlight" sectnum="2#1">../img/84181bf57b460fae8e693fc8455b4272.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>