<document id="5a5c6909c4ec726cf7b5d4f3a2d6346b-1.3" name="Firefly_(TV_series)" cat="19">
<text>
Production designer Carey Meyer built the ship ''Serenity'' in two parts (one for each level) as a complete set with ceilings and practical lighting installed as part of the set that the cameras could use along with moveable parts.Whedon, ''Firefly Companion, Vol 1'', 11  The two-part set also allowed the second unit to shoot in one section while the actors and first unit worked undisturbed in the other.  As Whedon recalled: "...you could pull it away or move something huge, so that you could get in and around everything. That meant the environment worked for us and there weren't a lot of adjustments that needed to be made." There were other benefits to this set design. One was that it allowed the viewers to feel they were really in a ship. For Whedon, the design of the ship was crucial in defining the known space for the viewer, and that there were not "fourteen hundred decks and a holodeck and an all-you-can-eat buffet in the back."Whedon, ''Firefly Companion, Vol 1'', 10 He wanted to convey that it was utilitarian and that it was "beat-up but lived-in and ultimately, it was home."Whedon, ''Firefly Companion, Vol 1'', 10–11 As Joss Whedon discusses in the DVD commentary, each room represented a feeling or character, usually conveyed by the paint color.  He explains that as you move from the back of the ship in the engine room, toward the front of the ship to the bridge, the colors and mood progress from extremely warm to cooler. In addition to evoking a mood associated with the character who spends most time in each area, the color scheme also alludes to the heat generated in the tail of the ship.
Whedon was also keen on utilizing vertical space; thus, having the crew's quarters accessible by ladder was important. Another benefit of the set design was that it also allowed the actors to stay in the moment and interact, without having to stop after each shot and reset up for the next. This helped contribute to the documentary style Whedon strove for.

The set had several influences, including the sliding doors and tiny cubicles reminiscent of Japanese hotels. Artist Larry Dixon has noted that the cargo bay walls are "reminiscent of interlaced, overlapping Asian designs, cleverly reminding us of the American-Chinese Alliance setting while artistically forming a patterned plane for background scale reference."Dixon, "The Reward, the Details, the Devils, the Due", ''Finding Serenity'', 8 Dixon has also remarked on how the set design contributed to the storytelling through the use of color, depth and composition, lighting, as well as its use of diagonals and patterned shadows.

Their small budget was another reason to use the ship for much of the storytelling. When the characters did go off the ship, the worlds all had Earth atmosphere and coloring because they could not afford to design alien worlds. "I didn't want to go to Yucca Flats every other episode and transform it into Bizarro World by making the sky orange", recalled Whedon. As Meyer recalled: "I think in the end the feel was that we wound up using a lot of places or exteriors that just felt too Western and we didn't necessarily want to go that way; but at some point, it just became the lesser of two evils—what could we actually create in three days?"Whedon, ''Firefly Companion, Vol 1'', 130
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0b0289d5f319d467d30f4fb3a7104e5a" name="Serenityship" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/0b0289d5f319d467d30f4fb3a7104e5a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>