<document id="5a619e55b724080f946f9f5c22bc6c1e-1" name="Jacques_Plante" cat="26">
<text>
Plante was born on January 17, 1929 on a farm near Mont Carmel, in Mauricie, Quebec,  the first of 11 children born to Palma and Xavier Plante.Plante, R., pg. 13 The family moved to Shawinigan Falls, where his father worked in one of the local factories. In 1932, Plante began to play hockey, skateless and with a tennis ball, using a goaltender's hockey stick his father had carved from a tree root.  When he was five years old, Plante fell off a ladder and broke his hand; the fracture failed to heal properly and affected his playing style during his early hockey career; he underwent successful corrective surgery as an adult.Plante, R., pg. 198 Plante suffered from asthma starting in early childhood, which prevented him from skating for extended periods; because of this, he naturally gravitated to playing goaltender.Plante, R., pg. 14 As his playing progressed, Jacques received his first regulation goaltender's stick for Christmas of 1936. His father made Plante's first pads by stuffing potato sacks and reinforcing them with wooden panels. As a child, Plante played hockey outdoors in the bitter cold Quebec winter. His mother taught him how to knit his own tuques to protect him from the cold; Plante continued knitting and embroidering throughout his life, and wore his hand-knitted tuques while playing and practicing until entering the National Hockey League (NHL).

Plante's first foray into organized hockey came at age 12. He was watching his school's team practice, when the coach ordered the goaltender off the ice after a heated argument over his play, and Plante asked to replace him. The coach permitted him to play since there was no other available goaltender; it quickly became apparent that Plante could hold his own, despite the other players being many years older than him.Plante, R., pg. 15 He impressed the coach and stayed on as the team's number one goaltender.Plante, R., pg. 16

Two years later, Plante was playing for five different teams, including the local factory team, and teams in the  midget, juvenile, junior and intermediate categories.Plante, R., pg. 18 After being told by his father that the rest of the players on the factory team were being paid because they were company employees, Plante decided to demand a salary from the team's coach; the coach paid Plante 50 cents per game to retain him and so the team's popularity. Afterwards, Plante began to receive various offers from other teams; he was offered $80 a week—a considerable sum in those day—to play for a team in England, and a similar sum to play for the Providence Reds of the American Hockey League. However, Plante passed up these offers; his parents wanted him to finish high school, and he graduated with top honours in 1947.Plante, R., pg. 19 Upon graduation, he took a job as a clerk in a Shawinigan factory. A few weeks later, the Quebec Citadels offered Plante $85 a week to play for them; he accepted, marking the beginning of his professional career.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="47a87c43f322335f04d0a53bd3ff4e64" name="Jacques_Plante_1944-1945" sectnum="1#1">../img/47a87c43f322335f04d0a53bd3ff4e64.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>