<document id="5aac98936b970830510f1facd2f3d956-2.1" name="The_Cat_and_the_Canary_(1927_film)" cat="19">
<text>
''The Cat and the Canary'' features veteran silent film stars Laura La Plante, Creighton Hale, and Forrest Stanley. La Plante played roles in more than 50 films before starring in ''The Cat and the Canary''.Laura La Plante at the ; last accessed January 4, 2007. According to film historian Gary Don Rhodes, her part in ''The Cat and the Canary'' was typical for women in horror and mystery films: "The female in the horror film ... becomes the hunted, the quarry. She has little to do, and so the question becomes 'What will be done ''with'' her?'" Rhodes adds, "The heroines are young and beautiful, but represent more a prize to be possessed&mdash;whether 'stolen' by a villain or 'owned' by a young hero at the film's conclusion."Gary Don Rhodes, ''White Zombie: Anatomy of a Horror Film'' (Jefferson, N.C.: McFarland, 2001), p. 19, ISBN 0786409886. Following ''The Cat and the Canary'', La Plante maintained a career with Universal, but she is described as a "victim of talkies."Hans J. Wollstein, Laura La Plante biography at ; last accessed January 12, 2007. She received a star on the Hollywood Walk of Fame before her death in 1996 from Alzheimer’s disease.



Universal chose Irish actor Creighton Hale to play hero Paul Jones, Annabelle's cousin. Hale had appeared in 64 silent films before ''The Cat and the Canary'', notably the 1914 serial ''The Exploits of Elaine'' and D. W. Griffith's ''Way Down East'' (1920) and ''Orphans of the Storm'' (1921).Hal Erickson, Creighton Hale biography at ; last accessed January 12, 2007. Hale's role in ''The Cat and the Canary'' was to provide comedic relief. According to critic John Howard Reid, "He is forever backing into furniture or finding himself in a risqué position under a bed or wrestling with stray objects like falling books or enormous bed-springs."John Howard Reid, ''These Movies Won No Hollywood Awards'' (Lulu Press, 2005), p. 39, ISBN 1411658469. Hale had trouble finding a solid career in sound film. Many of his parts were minor and uncredited.Joseph M. Curran, ''Hibernian Green on the Silver Screen: The Irish and American Movies'' (Westport, Conn: Greenwood Press, 1989), p. 27, ISBN 0313264910.

The villain Charles Wilder was played by Forrest Stanley, an actor who had been cast in films such as ''Bavu'' (1923), ''Through the Dark'' (1924) and ''Shadow of the Law'' (1926). After his performance in ''The Cat and the Canary'', Stanley played lesser roles in films such as ''Show Boat'' (1936) and ''Curse of the Undead'' (1959) and the television series ''Alfred Hitchcock Presents'', ''Studio 57'', and ''Gunsmoke''.Hans J. Wollstein, Forrest Stanley biography at ; last accessed January 12, 2004.

The film contained a supporting cast referred to by one film historian as "second-rate"Thomas Schatz, ''The Genius of the System: Hollywood Filmmaking in the Studio Era'' (New York: Owl Books, 1996), p. 89, ISBN 0805046666. and "excellent" by another. Tully Marshall played the suspicious lawyer Roger Crosby, Martha Mattox was cast as the sinister and superstitious housekeeper Mammy Pleasant, and Gertrude Astor and Flora Finch played greedy relatives Cecily Young and Aunt Susan Sillsby, respectively. Lucien Littlefield was cast as deranged psychiatrist Dr. Ira Lazar who bore an eerie resemblance to Werner Krauss's title character in ''The Cabinet of Dr. Caligari''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b578625a10c128c4ed5d022a1ef725ed" name="CanaryCast" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/b578625a10c128c4ed5d022a1ef725ed.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>