<document id="5aac98936b970830510f1facd2f3d956-3" name="The_Cat_and_the_Canary_(1927_film)" cat="19">
<text>
''The Cat and the Canary'' debuted in New York City's Colony Theatre on September 9, 1927,"Projection Jottings," ''New York Times'', May 15, 1927, p. X5. and was a "box office success". ''Variety'' opined, "What distinguishes Universal's film version of the ... play is Paul Leni's intelligent handling of a weird theme, introducing some of his novel settings and ideas with which he became identified .... The film runs a bit overlong .... Otherwise it's a more than average satisfying feature ...."''Variety'' review of ''The Cat and the Canary'', quoted in Roy Kinnard, ''Horror In Silent Films:  A Filmography, 1896–1929'' (Jefferson, N.C.: McFarland, 1995), p. 200, ISBN 0786407514. A ''New York Times'' review expounded, "This is a film which ought to be exhibited before many other directors to show them how a story should be told, for in all that he does Mr. Leni does not seem to strain at a point. He does it as naturally as a man twisting the ends of his mustache in thought."Mourdant Hall, "Mr. Leni's Clever Film; 'Cat and Canary' an Exception to the Rule in Mystery Pictures," ''New York Times'', September 18, 1927, p. X5. Nonetheless, as film historian Bernard F. Dick points out, "xponents of ''Caligarisme'', expressionism in the extreme ... naturally thought Leni had vulgarized the conventions ".  Dick, however, notes that Leni had only "lighten  so they could enter American cinema without the baggage of a movement that had spiraled out of control."Bernard F. Dick, ''City of Dreams: The Making and Remaking of Universal Pictures'' (Lexington: University Press of Kentucky, 1997), p. 56, ISBN 0813120160. 

Modern critics address the film's impact and influence. Michael Atkinson of ''The Village Voice'' remarks, " adroitly atmospheric film is virtually an ideogram of narrative suspension and impact";Michael Atkinson, review of ''The Cat and the Canary'' DVD, ''The Village Voice'' (New York), March 3, 2005, available . Chris Dashiell states that "verything is so exaggerated, so lacking in subtlety, that we soon stop caring what happens, despite a few mildly scary effects", although he admits that the film "had a great effect on the horror genre, and even Hitchcock cited it as an influence."Chris Dashiell, review of ''The Cat and the Canary'', at  ; last accessed January 4, 2007.  Tony Rayns has called the film "the definitive 'haunted house' movie .... Leni wisely plays it mainly for laughs, but his prowling, Murnau-like camera work generates a frisson or two along the way.  It is, in fact, hugely entertaining ...."Tony Rayns, ''The Time Out Film Guide'', Second Edition, Edited by Tom Milne (London: Penguin Books, 1991), p. 106, ISBN 0140145923.  John Calhoun  feels that what makes the film both "important and influential" was "Leni's uncanny ability to bring out the period's slapstick elements in the story's hackneyed conventions: the sliding panels and disappearing acts are so fast paced and expertly timed that the picture looks like a first-rate door-slamming farce .... At the same time, Leni didn't short-circuit the horrific aspects ...."John Calhoun, ''The Penguin Encyclopedia of Horror and the Supernatural'', edited by Jack Sullivan (New York: Viking, 1986), p. 73, ISBN 0670809020. 

Although not the first film set in a supposed haunted house, ''The Cat and the Canary'' started the pattern for the "old dark house" genre.Schatz, ''Genius of the System'', p. 88. The term is derived from English director James Whale's ''The Old Dark House'' (1932), which was heavily influenced by Leni's film,Clarens, ''Illustrated History of Horror'', p. 57. and refers to "films in which murders are committed by masked killers in old mansions."Jeffrey S. Miller, ''Horror Spoofs of Abbott and Costello: A Critical Assessment of the Comedy Team's Monster Films'' (Jefferson, N.C.: McFarland, 2004), p. 2, ISBN 0786419229. Supernatural events in the film are all explained at the film's conclusion as the work of a criminal. Other films in this genre influenced by ''The Cat and the Canary'' include ''The Last Warning'', ''House on Haunted Hill'' (1959), and the monster films of Abbott and Costello and Laurel and Hardy.Miller, ''Horror Spoofs'', pp. 2–3.Joseph Maddrey, ''Nightmares in Red, White, and Blue: The Evolution of the American Horror Film'' (Jefferson, N.C.: McFarland, 2004), p. 40, ISBN 0786418605.

A tinted version was released on both VHS and DVD in 1997 and 2005 by Image Entertainment. The original black and white version airs infrequently on the cable television network Turner Classic Movies.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="feb0e27cf51de7abc9a4215405579e7d" name="CatandtheCanaryPoster" sectnum="3#1">../img/feb0e27cf51de7abc9a4215405579e7d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>