<document id="5b0e3f209033fb350bb67481b8177079-2.3.1" name="2005_ACC_Championship_Game" cat="26">
<text>
The Virginia Tech offense was led by quarterback Marcus Vick, brother of former Tech all-star Michael Vick. Coming off a season-long suspension in 2004, Vick threw for 1,855 yards, 14 touchdowns and nine interceptions in the 2005 season leading up to the ACC Championship. Vick also ran for four touchdowns during the season and earned first-team All-ACC honors. (PDF) Virginia Tech Sports Information, Hokiesports.com. "All Eyes on Vick", Page 13. Accessed March 5, 2008. Receiving Vick's passes were a number of wide receivers and tight ends. Tight end Jeff King, a second-team All-ACC selection, had 20 receptions for 230 yards and five touchdowns for the season before the ACC Championship. (PDF) Virginia Tech Sports Information, Hokiesports.com. "Using the Tight Ends", Page 14. Accessed March 5, 2008. Wide receivers Eddie Royal and David Clowney also had statistically significant seasons heading into the conference championship. Royal had 21 catches for 271 yards and two touchdowns during the regular season, while Clowney had 28 catches for 515 yards and three touchdowns. (PDF) Virginia Tech Sports Information, Hokiesports.com. "Royal Flush", Page 13. Accessed March 5, 2008.

Virginia Tech's rushing offense was led by several different running backs: Mike Imoh, Branden Ore, and Cedric Humes. In 2005, Hokie running back Cedric Humes had accumulated a career-high 134 yards and two touchdowns against North Carolina in the Hokies' final regular-season game. Backup running back Branden Ore ran for 104 yards and a touchdown on 17 attempts, the second time in as many games that Humes and Ore ran for 100 yards or more in the same game. The Hokies ran 31 times in the second half and threw only two passes. A similar running game was predicted for the ACC Championship Game. Mark Schlabach, ''The Washington Post'', E01, November 27, 2005. Accessed December 24, 2007. Imoh, meanwhile, was limited by an ankle injury suffered during the course of the season. Heading into the conference championship game, he had rushed for 415 yards and three touchdowns. (PDF) Virginia Tech Sports Information, Hokiesports.com. "Finding Imoh", Page 12. Accessed March 5, 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c96b463969b829a53f4203f5eaaeb14b" name="Vick_back_to_pass_against_Duke" sectnum="2.3.1#1">../img/c96b463969b829a53f4203f5eaaeb14b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>