<document id="5b0e3f209033fb350bb67481b8177079-1.1" name="2005_ACC_Championship_Game" cat="26">
<text>
The Hokies began the 2005 regular season ranked eighth in the country, and played their first game at ACC opponent . It was a close-fought game, but quarterback Marcus Vick threw a game-winning touchdown early in the fourth quarter and the defense slowed a late NC State rally as Virginia Tech earned a 20&ndash;16 win. Jimmy Robertson, Virginia Tech Sports Information, Hokiesports.com, September 5, 2005. Accessed January 12, 2008. Following the close call against NC State, the Hokies blew out their next several opponents. Virginia Tech defeated  and  by scores of 45&ndash;0 each. The Virginia Tech defense held Duke's offense to just 35 total yards, an NCAA record. Jimmy Robertson, Virginia Tech Sports Information, Hokiesports.com, September 10, 2005. Accessed January 12, 2008. Following those victories, Tech hosted 15th-ranked Georgia Tech, beating the Yellow Jackets by a score of 51&ndash;7. Tech's defensive success in those games was typical of the season as Virginia Tech won the first eight games of its season. 2005&ndash;2006 Football Schedule, Virginia Tech Sports Information, Hokiesports.com. Accessed January 12, 2008.

In their ninth game, however, third-ranked Virginia Tech suffered its first loss. On a Thursday night game at home, the Hokies lost 27&ndash;7 to the fifth-ranked Miami Hurricanes. Normally, a loss to the division-rival Hurricanes would have knocked the Hokies out of contention for the ACC Championship Game, as Miami had the tie-breaking head-to-head victory and was expected to win the remainder of its games. But because Virginia Tech won the rest of its games and the Hurricanes lost two ACC contests, (Virginia Tech's only ACC loss was to Miami) the Hokies won the Coastal Division championship and qualified for the championship game over Miami. Matthew Spiers, Virginia Tech Sports Information, Hokiesports.com, November 26, 2005. Accessed January 12, 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="020988a1fab82bd11bd624723a76a031" name="VT_UNC_2005_entrance_fireworks" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/020988a1fab82bd11bd624723a76a031.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>