<document id="5b6d2a9f9b3abe873dc8c7d9dec0fe9d-2.2" name="The_Halo_Graphic_Novel" cat="17">
<text>
"The Last Voyage of the Infinite Succor" takes place during and after the sixth mission of the video game ''Halo: Combat Evolved''. During the game, players discover that the ringworld on which they are trapped, dubbed "Halo" by the enemy alien collective Covenant, is in fact a prison for a parasite known as the Flood, which breaks out of stasis and begins to spread across the ring.'''343 Guilty Spark''': Someone has released the Flood. My function is to prevent it from leaving this installation. — Halo was built by an ancient alien race known as the Forerunner to contain and study the Flood, but also as a weapon of last resort; faced with the prospect of the Flood consuming every thinking being in the universe, the Forerunner activated Halo, destroying themselves but also starving the Flood.'''Cortana''': You have no idea how this ring works, do you? Why the forerunners built it? Halo doesn't kill Flood, it kills their food. Humans, Covenant, whatever. We're all equally edible. The only way to stop the Flood is to starve them to death. And that's exactly what Halo is designed to do: wipe the galaxy clean of all sentient life. You don't believe me? Ask him. / '''Master Chief''': Is this true? / '''343 Guilty Spark''': More or less. Technically, this installation's pulse has a maximum effective radius of twenty-five thousand light years. But, once the others follow suit, this galaxy will be quite devoid of life, or at least any life with sufficient biomass to sustain the Flood. — 

In contrast to the player's point of view in the game, "The Last Voyage" focuses on the Covenant. In ''Halo: Combat Evolved''s sequel ''Halo 2'', players experience some of the plot through the eyes of the Arbiter, a Covenant warrior. The Arbiter is aided by a fellow Covenant Elite who is never named in the game itself; fans called the character "Half-Jaw" due to the Elite missing his mandibles on one side of his face. "The Last Voyage" names the Elite Rtas 'Vadumee, explains his injury, and describes events during ''Halo'' that the player did not see.

In "The Last Voyage", Elite Special Operations Commander Rtas 'Vadumee and his team respond to a distress call and board the crippled supply craft ''Infinite Succor'', which the Covenant believe has been attacked by humans. The only crew member still alive, a Covenant Prophet, tells 'Vadumee that the ''Succor'' has been infested by the Flood, which escaped Halo on a Covenant dropship and crash landed in the ''Succor''s hangar. Currently stuck on the ship, the parasite intends to activate the ''Succor''s slipspace drive to escape the star system and find new planets to infect. Fighting waves of Flood, including the reanimated remains of his fallen soldiers, 'Vadumee plots a slipspace course that will destroy both the ''Succor''  and the Flood, then escapes via a Covenant shuttle.

The central premise behind the story of "The Last Voyage of the Infinite Succor" was to showcase both the true danger posed by the Flood and the inner workings of the Covenant military machine, to dispel the image that the Covenant "simply stand around waiting for the Chief to blast them".''Halo Graphic Novel'', page 6 (ISBN 0785123725) The story was written by Lee Hammock with art provided by Simon Bisley. Hammock described the process of writing the story as a "heady task" since he had to respect ''Halo'' fans' knowledge of the characters and canon, ensuring that "characters that  know as a part of themselves are portrayed aptly". These difficulties were mitigated by the knowledge that fans were not as intimately connected to the history of the character of Rtas as they were to the likes of the Master Chief; this allowed ample room to expand 'Vadumee's background in sync with the ''Halo'' canon while permitting the writer to "bring something new to the table".''Halo Graphic Novel'', page 55 (ISBN 0785123725)
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="482fed7deac7e9134a7fd52e1c8ffaa0" name="Supremecommander" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/482fed7deac7e9134a7fd52e1c8ffaa0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>