<document id="5b80b71611400db800202ca10cad4635-4.6.3" name="Albert_Kesselring" cat="29">
<text>
Although his command was already "written off",Kesselring, ''The Memoirs of Field Marshal Kesselring'', p. 177 Kesselring intended to fight. At the Battle of Salerno in September 1943, he launched a full-scale counterattack against the Allied landings there with ''Generaloberst'' Heinrich von Vietinghoff's Tenth Army.Blumenson, ''Salerno to Casino'', pp. 112–117. The counterattack inflicted heavy casualties on the Allied forces, forced them back in several areas, and, for a time, made Allied commanders contemplate evacuation.Blumenson, ''Salerno to Casino'', p. 130. The short distance from German airfields allowed ''Luftflotte 2'' to put 120 aircraft over the Salerno area on 11 September 1943.Blumenson, ''Salerno to Casino'', pp. 102. Using Fritz X anti-ship missiles, hits were scored on the battleship  and cruisers  and , while a Liberty ship was sunk on 14 September and another damaged the next day.Blumenson, ''Salerno to Casino'', p. 148. The offensive ultimately failed to throw the Allies back into the sea because of the intervention of Allied naval gunfire which decimated the advancing German units, stubborn Allied resistance and the advance of the British Eighth Army. On 17 September 1943, Kesselring gave Vietinghoff permission to break off the attack and withdraw.Blumenson, ''Salerno to Casino'', pp. 135–136

Kesselring had been defeated but gained precious time. Already, in defiance of his orders, he was preparing a series of successive fallback positions on the Volturno Line, the Barbara Line and the Bernhardt Line.Blumenson, ''Salerno to Casino'', pp. 182–183. Only in November 1943, after a month of hard fighting, did the Allies reach Kesselring's main position, the Gustav Line.Blumenson, ''Salerno to Casino'', p. 235. According to his memoirs, Kesselring felt that much more could have been accomplished if he had access to the troops held "uselessly" under Rommel's command.Kesselring, ''The Memoirs of Field Marshal Kesselring'', pp. 186–187

In November 1943, Kesselring met with Hitler. Kesselring gave an optimistic assessment of the situation in Italy and gave reassurances that he could hold the Allies south of Rome on the Winter Line. Kesselring further promised that he could prevent the Allies reaching the Northern Apennines for at least six months. As a result, on 6 November 1943, Hitler ordered Rommel and his Army Group B headquarters to move to France to take charge of the Atlantic Wall and prepare for the Allied attack that was expected there in the Spring of 1944. On 21 November 1943, Kesselring resumed command of all German forces in Italy, combining Commander-in-Chief South, a joint command, with that of Army Group C, a ground command.Blumenson, ''Salerno to Casino'', pp. 244–245. "I had always blamed Kesselring", Hitler later explained, "for looking at things too optimistically... events have proved Rommel wrong, and I have been justified in my decision to leave Field Marshal Kesselring there, whom I have seen as an incredible political idealist, but also as a military optimist, and it is my opinion that military leadership without optimism is not possible."Blumenson, ''Salerno to Casino'', pp. 245–246.

The ''Luftwaffe'' scored a notable success on the night of 2 December 1943 when 105 Ju88 bombers struck the port of Bari. Skilfully using chaff to confuse the Allied radar operators, they found the port packed with brightly lit Allied shipping. The result was the most destructive air raid on Allied shipping since the attack on Pearl Harbor. Hits were scored on two ammunition ships and a tanker. Burning oil and exploding ammunition spread over the harbour. Some 16 ships were sunk and eight damaged, and the port was put out of action for three weeks. Moreover, one of the ships sunk, SS ''John Harvey'', had been carrying mustard gas, which enveloped the port in a cloud of poisonous vapours.Morison, ''Sicily-Salerno-Anzio'', pp. 319–322
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="33c22cc82bd539fa0e3f6528c6df4023" name="ItalyDefenseLinesSouthofRome1943_4" sectnum="4.6.3#1">../img/33c22cc82bd539fa0e3f6528c6df4023.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>