<document id="5b80b71611400db800202ca10cad4635-4.6.1" name="Albert_Kesselring" cat="29">
<text>
Kesselring expected that the Allies would next invade Sicily, as a landing could be made there under fighter cover from Tunisia and Malta.Garland and Smyth, ''Sicily and the Surrender of Italy'', p. 46 He reinforced the six coastal and four mobile Italian divisions there with two mobile German divisions, the 15th ''Panzergrenadier'' Division and the ''Hermann Göring Panzer'' Division, both rebuilt after being destroyed in Tunisia.Garland and Smyth, ''Sicily and the Surrender of Italy'', pp. 80–82 Kesselring was well aware that while this force was large enough to stop the Allies from simply marching in, it could not withstand a large scale invasion. He therefore pinned his hopes on repelling the Allied invasion of Sicily on an immediate counterattack, which he ordered Colonel Paul Conrath of the ''Hermann Göring Panzer'' Division to carry out the moment the objective of the Allied invasion fleet was known, with or without orders from the island commander, ''Generale d'Armata'' Alfredo Guzzoni.Kesselring, ''The Memoirs of Field Marshal Kesselring'', p. 161

Kesselring hoped that the Allied invasion fleet would provide good targets for U-boats, but they had few successes.Kesselring, ''The Memoirs of Field Marshal Kesselring'', p. 160 ''U-953'' sank two American LSTs and with ''U-375'' sank three vessels from a British convoy on 4–5 July, while ''U-371'' sank a Liberty ship and a tanker on 10 July.Morison, ''Sicily-Salerno-Anzio'', p. 40 Pressure from the Allied air forces forced ''Luftflotte 2'', commanded since June by von Richthofen, to withdraw most of its aircraft to the mainland.Morison, ''Sicily-Salerno-Anzio'', p. 57

The Allied invasion of Sicily on 10 July 1943 was stubbornly opposed. A ''Stuka'' attacked and sank the ;Morison, ''Sicily-Salerno-Anzio'', pp. 100–101 an Me109 destroyed an LST;Morison, ''Sicily-Salerno-Anzio'', pp. 107–108 and a Liberty ship filled with ammunition was bombed by Ju88s and caught fire, later exploding without loss of life.Morison, ''Sicily-Salerno-Anzio'', pp. 119–120 Unaware that Guzzoni had already ordered a major counterattack on 11 July, Kesselring bypassed the chain of command to order the ''Hermann Göring Panzer'' Division to attack that day in the hope that a vigorous attack could succeed before the Americans could bring the bulk of their artillery and armoured support ashore.Garland and Smyth, ''Sicily and the Surrender of Italy'', p. 163 Although his troops gave the Americans "quite a battering", they failed to capture the Allied position.Garland and Smyth, ''Sicily and the Surrender of Italy'', p. 174

Kesselring flew to Sicily himself on 12 July to survey the situation and decided that no more than a delaying action was possible and that the island would eventually have to be evacuated. Nonetheless, he intended to fight on and he reinforced Sicily with the 29th ''Panzergrenadier'' Division on 15 July. Kesselring returned to Sicily by flying boat on 16 July to give the senior German commander, ''General der Panzertruppe'' Hans-Valentin Hube, his instructions. Unable to provide much more in the way of air support, Kesselring gave Hube command of the heavy Flak units on the island, although this was contrary to ''Luftwaffe'' doctrine. In all, Kesselring managed to delay the Allies in Sicily for another month and the Allied conquest of the Sicily was not complete until 17 August.Kesselring, ''The Memoirs of Field Marshal Kesselring'', pp. 163–164

Kesselring's evacuation of Sicily, which began a week earlier on 10 August, was perhaps the most brilliant action of the campaign. In spite of the Allies' superiority on land, at sea, and in the air, Kesselring was able to evacuate not only 40,000 men, but also 96,605 vehicles, 94 guns, 47 tanks, 1,100 tons of ammunition, 970 tons of fuel, and 15,000 tons of stores. He was able to achieve near-perfect coordination between the three services under his command while his opponent, Eisenhower, could not.Garland and Smyth, ''Sicily and the Surrender of Italy'', pp. 409–417
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="413959ae6645ae1cf28c5b43711f79af" name="SC180476" sectnum="4.6.1#1">../img/413959ae6645ae1cf28c5b43711f79af.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>