<document id="5b80b71611400db800202ca10cad4635-5.9" name="Albert_Kesselring" cat="29">
<text>
By the end of the war, for most Italians the name of Kesselring, whose signature appeared on posters and printed orders announcing draconian measures adopted by the German occupation, had become synonymous with the oppression and terror that had characterised the German occupation. Kesselring's name headed the list of German officers blamed for a long series of atrocities perpetrated by the German forces.von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', p. 78.

The Moscow Declaration of October 1943 promised that "those German officers and men and members of the Nazi party who have been responsible for or have taken a consenting part in the above atrocities, massacres and executions will be sent back to the countries in which their abominable deeds were done in order that they may be judged and punished according to the laws of these liberated countries and of free governments which will be erected therein." However, the British, who had been a driving force in moulding the war crimes trial policy that culminated in the Nuremberg Trials, explicitly excluded high-ranking German officers in their custody. Thus, Kesselring's conviction became "a legal ''prerequisite'' if perpetrators of war crimes were to be found guilty by Italian courts".von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', p. 78. Emphasis original.

The British held two major trials against the top German war criminals who had perpetrated crimes during the Italian campaign. For political reasons it was decided to hold the trials in Italy,von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', pp. 76–77. but a request by Italy to allow an Italian judge to participate was denied on the grounds that Italy was not an Allied country.von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', pp. 80–81. The trials were held under the Royal Warrant of 18 June 1945,See  thus essentially under British Common Military Law. The decision put the trials on a shaky legal basis, as foreign nationals were being tried for crimes against foreigners in a foreign country.von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', p. 73. The first trial, held in Rome, was of von Mackensen and the Commandant of Rome, ''Generalleutnant'' Kurt Mältzer, only, for their part in the Ardeatine massacre. Both were sentenced to death on 30 November 1946.von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', pp. 87–89.

Kesselring's own trial began in Venice on 17 February 1947.von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', p. 109. The British Military Court was presided over by Major General Sir Edmund Hakewill-Smith, assisted by four lieutenant colonels. Colonel Richard C. Halse – who had already obtained the death penalty for von Mackensen and Mältzer – was the prosecutor.von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', p. 107. Kesselring's legal team was headed by Hans Laternser, a skilful German lawyer who specialised in Anglo-Saxon law, had represented several defendants at the Nuremberg Trials, and would later go on to represent ''Generalfeldmarschall'' Erich von Manstein. Kesselring's ability to pay his legal team was hampered because his assets had been frozen by the Allies, but his legal costs were eventually met by friends in South America and relatives in Franconia.von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', pp. 92–96.

Kesselring was arraigned on two charges: the shooting of 335 Italians in the Ardeatine massacre and incitement to kill Italian civilians. Kesselring did not invoke the "Nuremberg defence". Rather, he maintained that his actions were lawful. On 6 May 1947 the Court found him guilty of both charges and sentenced him to death by firing squad, which was considered more honourable than hanging.von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', pp. 110–118. The court left open the question of the legality of killing innocent persons in reprisals.

The planned major trial for the campaign of reprisals never took place, but a series of smaller trials was held instead in Padua between April and June 1947 for SS ''Brigadeführer'' Willy Tensfeld, Kapitänleutnant Waldemar Krummhaar, the 26th ''Panzer'' Division's ''Generalleutnant'' Edward Crasemann and SS ''Gruppenführer'' Max Simon of the 16th SS ''Panzergrenadier'' Division ''Reichsführer-SS''.von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', p. 307. Tensfeld was acquitted; Crasemann was sentenced to 10 years; and Simon was sentenced to death, but his sentence was commuted. Simons's trial was the last held in Italy by the British. By 1949, British military tribunals had sentenced 230 Germans to death and another 447 to custodial sentences. None of the death sentences imposed between the end of 1946 and 1948 were carried out.von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', p. 84. A number of officers, all below the rank of General, including Herbert Kappler, were transferred to the Italian courts for trial. These applied very different legal standards to the British – ones which were often more favourable to the defendants.von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', p. 297. Ironically, in view of the repeated attempts by many senior ''Wehrmacht'' commanders to shift blame for atrocities onto the SS, the most senior SS commanders in Italy, Karl Wolff and Himmler's personal representative in Italy, SS ''Standartenführer'' Eugen Dollmann, escaped prosecution.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="98b5ed1427370773e35316d5eff0c108" name="KesselringDetentionReport" sectnum="5.9#1">../img/98b5ed1427370773e35316d5eff0c108.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>