<document id="5b80b71611400db800202ca10cad4635-3" name="Albert_Kesselring" cat="29">
<text>
At the conclusion of the war, Kesselring was involved in the demobilisation of III Bavarian Corps in the Nuremberg area.Kesselring, ''The Memoirs of Field Marshal Kesselring'', p. 18 A dispute with the leader of the local ''Freikorps'' led an arrest warrant being issued for his alleged involvement in a ''putsch'' against the command of III Bavarian Corps, and Kesselring was thrown into prison. He was soon released but his superior, Major Hans Seyler, censured him for having "failed to display the requisite discretion".von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', p. 20

From 1919 to 1922, Kesselring served as a battery commander with the 24th Artillery Regiment. He joined the ''Reichswehr'' on 1 October 1922 and was posted to the Military Training Department at the ''Reichswehr'' Ministry in Berlin. He remained at this post until 1929, when he returned to Bavaria as commander of Wehrkreis VII in Munich. In his time with the ''Reichswehr'' Ministry, Kesselring was involved in the organisation of the army, trimming staff overheads to produce the best possible army with the limited resources available. He helped reorganise the Ordnance Department, laying the groundwork for the research and development efforts that would produce new weapons. He was involved in secret military manoeuvres held in the Soviet Union in 1924, and in the so-called Great Plan for a 102-division army, which was prepared in 1923 and 1924.von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', p. 22 After another brief stint at the ''Reichswehr'' Ministry, Kesselring was promoted to lieutenant colonel in 1930 and spent two years in Dresden with the 4th Artillery Regiment.Kesselring, ''The Memoirs of Field Marshal Kesselring'', pp. 19–26

Against his wishes, Kesselring was discharged from the army on 1 October 1933 and appointed head of the Department of Administration at the Reich Commissariat for Aviation (''Reichskommissariat für die Luftfahrt''), the forerunner of the Reich Air Ministry (''Reichsluftfahrtministerium''), with the rank of colonel.Kesselring, ''The Memoirs of Field Marshal Kesselring'', pp. 25, 31–33 Since the Treaty of Versailles forbade Germany from establishing an air force, this was nominally a civilian agency. The ''Luftwaffe'' would formally be re-established in 1935.Hooten, ''Luftwaffe at War: Gathering Storm 1933–39'', pp. 30–31 As chief of administration, he had to assemble his new staff from scratch. He was involved in the re-establishment of the aviation industry and the construction of secret factories, forging alliances with industrialists and aviation engineers.Kesselring, ''The Memoirs of Field Marshal Kesselring'', pp. 31–33 He was promoted to ''Generalmajor'' in 1934 and ''Generalleutnant'' in 1936. Like other generals of Nazi Germany, he received personal payments from Adolf Hitler; in Kesselring's case, RM 6,000, a considerable sum at the time.von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', p. 23


At the age of 48, he learned to fly. Kesselring believed that first-hand knowledge of all aspects of aviation was crucial to being able to command airmen, although he was well aware that latecomers like himself did not impress the old pioneers or the young aviators. He qualified in various single and multi-engined aircraft and continued flying three or four days per week until March 1945. At times, his flight path took him over the concentration camps at Oranienburg, Dachau, and Buchenwald.Macksey, ''Kesselring - The Making of the Luftwaffe'', p. 44

Following the death of ''Generalleutnant'' Walther Wever in an air crash, Kesselring became Chief of Staff of the ''Luftwaffe'' on 3 June 1936. In that post, Kesselring oversaw the expansion of the ''Luftwaffe'', the acquisition of new aircraft types such as the Bf 109 and Ju 87, and the development of paratroops. Like many ex-Army officers, he tended to see air power in the tactical role, providing support to land operations. He rejected strategic bombing and cancelled the Ural bomber.von Lingen, ''Kesselring's Last Battle'', p. 24

Kesselring's main operational task during this time was the support of the Condor Legion in the Spanish Civil War. However, his tenure was marred by personal and professional conflicts with his superior, ''General der Flieger'' Erhard Milch, and Kesselring asked to be relieved.Kesselring, ''The Memoirs of Field Marshal Kesselring'', pp. 35–36 The head of the ''Luftwaffe'', Hermann Göring, acquiesced and Kesselring became the commander of Air District III in Dresden. On 1 October 1938, he was promoted to ''General der Flieger'' and became commander of ''Luftflotte 1'', based in Berlin.Kesselring, ''The Memoirs of Field Marshal Kesselring'', p. 37
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="735f02393f2a897f74ef8eb38b59c021" name="Bundesarchiv_Bild_146-1981-066-21A,_Albert_Kesselring_in_seinem_Flugzeug" sectnum="3#1">../img/735f02393f2a897f74ef8eb38b59c021.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>