<document id="5b992d44a7a07558bfed960d70903ab9-3.5" name="Samuel_Adams" cat="14">
<text>
After the Boston Massacre, politics in Massachusetts entered what is sometimes known as the "quiet period".Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 93. In April 1770, Parliament repealed the Townshend duties, except for the tax on tea. Adams urged colonists to keep up the boycott of British goods, arguing that paying even one small tax allowed Parliament to establish the precedent of taxing the colonies, but the boycott faltered.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 91; Fowler, ''Radical Puritan'', 111. As economic conditions improved, support for Adams's causes waned.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 105. John Adams withdrew from politics, while John Hancock and James Otis appeared to become more moderate.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 97–99. Adams was reelected to the Massachusetts House in April 1772, but he received far fewer votes than ever before.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 104.



A struggle over the power of the purse brought Adams back into the political limelight. Traditionally, the Massachusetts House of Representatives paid the salaries of the governor, lieutenant governor, and superior court judges. From the Whig perspective, this arrangement, by keeping royally appointed officials accountable to democratically elected representatives, was an important check on executive power.Fowler, ''Radical Puritan'', 117; Maier, ''Old Revolutionaries'', 22. In 1772, Massachusetts learned that the those officials would henceforth be paid by the British government rather than by the province.Adams and others had previously suspected that Hutchinson's salary was being paid by the Crown, but this was unconfirmed until now; Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 106. To protest this development, in November 1772 Adams and his colleagues devised a system of committees of correspondence; the towns of Massachusetts would consult with each other concerning political matters via messages sent through a network of committees that recorded British activities and protested imperial policies.Wells, ''Life and Public Services'', 2:84. Committees of correspondence soon formed in other colonies as well.

Governor Hutchinson, concerned that the committees of correspondence were growing into an independence movement, convened the General Court in January 1773.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 111–12. Addressing the legislature, Hutchinson argued that to deny the supremacy of Parliament, which some committees had done, came dangerously close to rebellion. "I know of no line that can be drawn," he said, "between the supreme authority of Parliament and the total independence of the colonies."Fowler, ''Radical Puritan'', 120; Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 112. Adams and the House responded that the Massachusetts Charter did not establish Parliament's supremacy over the province, and so Parliament could not claim that authority now.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 112–13. Hutchinson soon realized that he had made a major blunder by initiating a public debate about independence and the extent of Parliament's authority in the colonies.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 114. The Boston Committee of Correspondence published its statement of colonial rights, along with Hutchinson's exchange with the Massachusetts House, in the widely distributed "Boston Pamphlet".Fowler, ''Radical Puritan'', 120.

The quiet period in Massachusetts was over. Adams was easily reelected to the Massachusetts House in May 1773, and was also elected as moderator of the Boston Town Meeting.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 116. In June 1773, Adams introduced in the Massachusetts House a set of private letters written by Hutchinson several years earlier. In one letter, Hutchinson appeared to recommend to London that there should be "an abridgement of what are called English liberties" in Massachusetts. Although Hutchinson denied that this is what he meant, his career in Massachusetts was effectively over. The House sent a petition to the king asking for his recall.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 118–19; Fowler, ''Radical Puritan'', 121. Hutchinson maintained that he was predicting, rather an recommending, a curtailment of liberty; for the modern scholarly analysis of the letters affair, see Bernard Bailyn, ''The Ordeal of Thomas Hutchinson'' (Cambridge, 1974).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="297c423fe52263656a54c11dea80cfb3" name="Samuel_adams_illustration.3" sectnum="3.5#1">../img/297c423fe52263656a54c11dea80cfb3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>