<document id="5b992d44a7a07558bfed960d70903ab9-3.6" name="Samuel_Adams" cat="14">
<text>
Adams took a leading role in the events that led up to the famous Boston Tea Party of December 16, 1773, although the precise nature of his involvement has been disputed.

In May 1773, the British Parliament passed the Tea Act, a tax law to help the struggling East India Company, one of Great Britain's most important commercial institutions. Because of the heavy taxes imposed on tea imported into Great Britain, Britons could buy smuggled Dutch tea more cheaply than the East India Company's tea, and so the company amassed a huge surplus of tea that it could not sell.Thomas, ''Townshend Duties'', 248–49; Labaree, ''Tea Party'', 334. The British government's solution to the problem was to sell the surplus in the colonies. The Tea Act permitted the East India Company, for the first time, to export tea directly to the colonies, bypassing most of the merchants who had previously acted as middlemen.Labaree, ''Tea Party'', 67, 70. The act also reduced the taxes on tea paid by the company in Britain, but kept the controversial Townshend duty on tea imported in the colonies. A few merchants in New York, Philadelphia, Boston, and Charlestown were selected to receive the company's tea for resale.Labaree, ''Tea Party'', 75–76. In late 1773, seven ships carrying East India Company tea were sent to the colonies, including four bound for Boston.Labaree, ''Tea Party'', 78–79.

News of the Tea Act set off a firestorm of protest in the colonies.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 120; Fowler, ''Radical Puritan'', 122. This was not a dispute about high taxes: the price of legally imported tea was actually reduced by the Tea Act. Protesters were instead concerned with a variety of other issues. The familiar "no taxation without representation" argument, along with the question of the extent of Parliament's authority in the colonies, remained prominent.Thomas, ''Townshend Duties'', 246. Some colonists worried that by buying the cheaper tea, they would be conceding that Parliament had the right to tax them.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 120. The "power of the purse" conflict was still at issue: The tea tax revenues were to be used to pay the salaries of certain royal officials, making them independent of the people.Labaree, ''Tea Party'', 78, 106. Colonial smugglers played a significant role in the protests, since the Tea Act made legally imported tea cheaper, which threatened to put smugglers of Dutch tea out of business.Labaree, ''Tea Party'', 102; see also John W. Tyler, ''Smugglers & Patriots: Boston Merchants and the Advent of the American Revolution'' (Boston, 1986). Legitimate tea importers who had not been named as consignees by the East India Company were also threatened with financial ruin by the Tea Act,Thomas, ''Townshend Duties'', 256. and other merchants worried about the precedent of a government-created monopoly.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 120.



Adams and the correspondence committees promoted opposition to the Tea Act.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 120–21; Fowler, ''Radical Puritan'', 122. In every colony except Massachusetts, protestors were able to force the tea consignees to resign or to return the tea to England.Labaree, ''Tea Party'', 96–100. In Boston, however, Governor Hutchinson was determined to hold his ground. He convinced the tea consignees, two of whom were his sons, not to back down.Labaree, ''Tea Party'', 104–05. The Boston Caucus and then the Town Meeting attempted to compel the consignees to resign, but they refused.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 121–22; Labaree, ''Tea Party'', 109–112. With the tea ships about to arrive, Adams and the Boston Committee of Correspondence contacted nearby committees to rally support.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 122–23.

When the tea ship ''Dartmouth'' arrived in the Boston Harbor in late November, Adams wrote a circular letter calling for a mass meeting to be held at Faneuil Hall on November 29. Thousands of people arrived, so many that the meeting was moved to the larger Old South Meeting House.This was not an official town meeting, but a gathering of "the body of the people" of greater Boston; Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 123. British law required the ''Dartmouth'' to unload and pay the duties within twenty days or customs officials could confiscate the cargo.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 124. The mass meeting passed a resolution, introduced by Adams, urging the captain of the ''Dartmouth'' to send the ship back without paying the import duty.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 123; Puls, ''Father of Revolution'', 143. Meanwhile, the meeting assigned twenty-five men to watch the ship and prevent the tea from being unloaded.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 123.

Governor Hutchinson refused to grant permission for the ''Dartmouth'' to leave without paying the duty. Two more tea ships, the ''Eleanor'' and the ''Beaver'', arrived in Boston Harbor. On December 16—the last day of the ''Dartmouth's'' deadline—about 7,000 people had gathered around the Old South Meeting House.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 125. After receiving a report that Governor Hutchinson had again refused to let the ships leave, Adams announced that "This meeting can do nothing further to save the country."Wells, ''Life and Public Services'', 2:122–23; Miller, ''Pioneer'', 294. According to a popular story, Adams's statement was a prearranged signal for the "tea party" to begin. However, this claim did not appear in print until nearly a century after the event, in a biography of Adams written by his great-grandson, who apparently misinterpreted the evidence.Raphael, ''Founding Myths'', 53. According to eyewitness accounts, people did not leave the meeting until ten or fifteen minutes after Adams' alleged "signal", and Adams in fact tried to stop people from leaving because the meeting was not yet over.Maier, ''Old Revolutionaries'', 27–28n32; Raphael, ''Founding Myths'', 53. For firsthand accounts that contradict the story that Adams gave the signal for the tea party, see L. F. S. Upton, ed., "Proceeding of Ye Body Respecting the Tea," ''William and Mary Quarterly'', Third Series, 22 (1965), 297–98; Francis S. Drake, ''Tea Leaves: Being a Collection of Letters and Documents'', (Boston, 1884), LXX; ''Boston Evening Post'', December 20, 1773; ''Boston Gazette'', December 20, 1773; ''Massachusetts Gazette and Boston Weekly News-Letter'', December 23, 1773.

While Adams tried to reassert control of the meeting, people poured out of the Old South Meeting House and headed to Boston Harbor. That evening, a group of 30 to 130 men, some of them thinly disguised as Mohawk Indians, boarded the three vessels and, over the course of three hours, dumped all 342 chests of tea into the water.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 125–26; Labaree, ''Tea Party'', 141–44. Adams never revealed if he went to the wharf to witness the destruction of the tea.Fowler, ''Radical Puritan'', 124. Whether or not he helped plan the event is unknown, but Adams immediately worked to publicize and defend it.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 126; Fowler, ''Radical Puritan'', 124. He argued that the Tea Party was not the act of a lawless mob, but was instead a principled protest and the only remaining option the people had to defend their constitutional rights.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 129.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="94a64caf0e23e1bf8aa7108ba89f6d72" name="Boston_tea_party" sectnum="3.6#1">../img/94a64caf0e23e1bf8aa7108ba89f6d72.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>