<document id="5b992d44a7a07558bfed960d70903ab9-4.8" name="Samuel_Adams" cat="14">
<text>
Because the Continental Congress worked under a secrecy rule, Adams's precise role in congressional deliberations is not fully documented. He appears to have had a major influence, working behind the scenes as a sort of "parliamentary whip".Nobles, "Old Republicans", 264, citing Jack N. Rakove, ''The Beginnings of National Politics: An Interpretive History of the Continental Congress'' (New York 1979), 103. He served on numerous committees, often dealing with military matters.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 150.



Adams was a cautious advocate for a declaration of independence, urging eager correspondents back in Massachusetts to wait for more moderate colonists to come around to supporting separation from Great Britain.Maier, ''Old Revolutionaries'', 26; Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 151. He was pleased when, in 1775, the colonies began to replace their old governments with independent republican governments.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 152–53. In early 1776, writing as "Candidus", he praised Thomas Paine's popular pamphlet ''Common Sense'' and supported the call for American independence.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 153. On June 7, Adams's political ally Richard Henry Lee introduced a three-part resolution calling for Congress to declare independence, create a colonial confederation, and seek foreign aid. After a delay to rally support, Congress approved the language of the United States Declaration of Independence on July 4, 1776, which Adams signed.

After the Declaration of Independence, Congress continued to manage the war effort. Adams served on military committees, including an appointment to the Board of War in 1777.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 157; Wells, ''Life and Public Services'', 2:468. He advocated paying bonuses to Continental Army soldiers to encourage them to reenlist for the duration of the war.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 158–59. He called for harsh state legislation to punish Loyalists—Americans who continued to support the British crown—who Adams believed were as dangerous to American liberty as British soldiers. In Massachusetts, more than 300 Loyalists were banished and their property confiscated.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 161–62. After the war, Adams opposed allowing Loyalists to return to Massachusetts, fearing that they would work to undermine republican government.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 193–94.

Adams was the Massachusetts delegate appointed to the committee to draft the Articles of Confederation, the plan for the colonial confederation. With its emphasis on state sovereignty, the Articles reflected Congress's wariness of a strong central government, a concern shared by Adams. Like others at the time, Adams considered himself a citizen of the United States while continuing to refer to Massachusetts as his "country".Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 162–63, 197. After much debate, the Articles were sent to the states for ratification in November 1777. From Philadelphia, Adams urged Massachusetts to ratify, which it did. Adams signed the Articles of Confederation with the other Massachusetts delegates in 1778, but they were not ratified by all the states until 1781.

Adams returned to Boston in 1779 to attend a state constitutional convention. The Massachusetts General Court had proposed a new constitution the previous year, but voters rejected it, and so a convention was held to try again. Adams was appointed to a three-man drafting committee with his cousin John Adams and James Bowdoin.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 181. They drafted the Massachusetts Constitution, which was amended by the convention and approved by voters in 1780. The new constitution established a republican form of government, with annual elections and a separation of powers. It reflected Adams's belief that "a state is never free except when each citizen is bound by no law whatever that he has not approved of, either directly, or through his representatives".Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 184. By modern standards, the new constitution was not "democratic"; Adams, like most of his peers, believed that only free males who owned property should be allowed to vote, and that the senate and the governor served to balance any excesses that might result from majority rule.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 183–85.

In 1781, Adams retired from the Continental Congress. His health was one reason: he was approaching his sixtieth birthday, and suffered from tremors that made writing difficult.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 167. But he also wanted to return to Massachusetts to influence politics in the Commonwealth.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 188. He returned to Boston in 1781, and was never to leave Massachusetts again.Alexander, ''Revolutionary Politician'', 170–71.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ff7ce7b21c9909bb107ea726a0b5d4d5" name="Declaration_independence" sectnum="4.8#1">../img/ff7ce7b21c9909bb107ea726a0b5d4d5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>