<document id="5b9bbb014ea6ae201f5a6fa5162f351c-5" name="The_Dark_Side_of_the_Moon" cat="20">
<text>
With the exception of Wright, the band boycotted the press reception at the London Planetarium on 27 February, as the quadraphonic mix was not yet complete.  The guests were presented with a quartet of life-sized cardboard cutouts of the band, and the stereo mix of the album was presented through a poor-quality public address system.  Generally however, the press were enthusiastic; ''Melody Maker'''s Roy Hollingworth described side one as: "... so utterly confused with itself it was difficult to follow", but went on to praise side two, writing "The songs, the sounds, the rhythms were solid and sound, Saxophone hit the air, the band rocked and rolled, and then gushed and tripped away into the night."  Steve Peacock of ''Sounds'' wrote "I don't care if you've never heard a note of the Pink Floyd's music in your life, I'd unreservedly recommend everyone to ''The Dark Side of the Moon'' ..."  In his 1973 album review for ''Rolling Stone'' magazine, Lloyd Grossman wrote: "a fine album with a textural and conceptual richness that not only invites, but demands involvement".

''The Dark Side of the Moon'' was released first in the US on 10 March 1973, and then in the UK on 24 March.  It became an instant chart success in Britain and throughout Western Europe; by the following month, it had gained a gold disc in the UK and US.  Throughout March 1973 the band played the album as part of their US tour, including a midnight performance at Radio City Music Hall in New York on 17 March.  Highlights included an aircraft launched from the back of the hall at the end of "On the Run", crashing into the stage in a cloud of orange smoke.  The performance was watched by an audience of 6,000 people.  The album reached the ''Billboard'' album chart No.1 spot on 28 April 1973,  and was so successful that the band returned two months later for another tour.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a763b5748de05cceb4c15df89564bad5" name="DarkSideOfTheMoon1973" sectnum="5#1">../img/a763b5748de05cceb4c15df89564bad5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>