<document id="5c5397d543fd429dd9d4206263979723-2.2" name="Western_Chalukya_architecture" cat="1">
<text>
Chalukyan temples fall into two categories — the first being temples with a common ''mantapa'' (a colonnaded hall) and two shrines (known as ''dvikuta''), and the second being temples with one ''mantapa'' and a single shrine (''ekakuta'').

Both kinds of temples have two or more entrances giving access to the main hall.Cousens (1926), p 22 This format differs from both the designs of the northern Indian temples, which have a small closed ''mantapa'' leading to the shrine and the southern Indian temples which generally have a large, open, columned ''mantapa''.

The Chalukyan architects retained features from both northern and southern styles. However, in the overall arrangement of the main temple and of the subsidiary shrines, they inclined towards the northern style and tended to build one main shrine with four minor shrines, making the structure a ''panchayatna'' or five-shrined complex.Cousens (1926), p 19 Chalukyan temples were, almost always, built facing the east.Cousens (1926), p 85

The Sanctum (cella) is connected by a vestibule (''ardha mantapa'' or ante-chamber) to the closed ''mantapa'' (also called the ''navaranga''), which is connected to the open ''mantapa''.  Occasionally there can be two or more open ''mantapas''. In Shaiva temples, directly opposite the sanctum and opposite the closed ''mantapa'' is the ''nandi mantapa'', which enshrines a large image of Nandi, the bull attendant of Shiva.Kamath (2001), p 116 The shrine usually has no ''pradakshina''.

The pillars that support the roof of the ''mantapa'' are monolithic shafts from the base up to the neck of the capital. Therefore, the height of the ''mantapa'' and the overall size of the temple were limited by the length of the stone shafts that the architects were able to obtain from the quarries.Cousens (1926), p 23 The height of the temple was also constrained by the weight of the superstructure on the walls and, since Chalukyan architects did not use mortar, by the use of dry masonry and bonding stones without clamps or cementing material.

The absence of mortar allows some ventilation in the innermost parts of the temple through the porous masonry used in the walls and ceilings. The modest amount of light entering the temples comes into the open halls from all directions, while the very subdued illumination in  the inner closed ''mantapa'' comes only through its open doorway. The vestibule receives even less light, making it necessary to have some form of artificial lighting (usually, oil lamps) even during the day. This artificial source of light perhaps adds "mystery" to the image of the deity worshipped in the sanctum.Cousens (1926), p 21
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1ecc8333be36b91aa91c65a48ec09497" name="Yellamma_temple_at_Badami" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/1ecc8333be36b91aa91c65a48ec09497.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>