<document id="5c5397d543fd429dd9d4206263979723-2.4" name="Western_Chalukya_architecture" cat="1">
<text>
The  11th-century temple-building boom continued in the 12th century with the addition of new features. Mahadeva Temple at Itagi and the Siddhesvara Temple in Haveri are standard constructions incorporating these developments. Based on the general plan of the Amrtesvara Temple at Annigeri, the Mahadeva Temple was built in 1112 CE and has the same architectural components as its predecessor. There are however differences in their articulation; the ''sala'' roof (roof under the finial of the superstructure) and the miniature towers on pilasters are chiseled instead of moulded.Foekema (2003), p 57 The difference between the two temples, built fifty years apart, is the more rigid modelling and decoration found in many components of the Mahadeva Temple. The voluptuous carvings of the 11th century were replaced with a more severe chiselling.Foekema (2003), p 56



As developments progressed, the Chalukyan builders modified the pure ''dravida'' tower by reducing the height of each stepped storey and multiplying their number.  From base to top, the succeeding storeys get smaller in circumference and the topmost storey is capped with a crown holding the ''kalasa'', a finial in the shape of a  decorative water pot. Each storey is so richly decorated that the original ''dravida'' character becomes almost invisible. In  the ''nagara'' tower the architects modified the central panels and niches on each storey, forming a more-or-less continuous vertical band and simulating the vertical bands up the centre of each face of the typical northern style tower.Cousens (1926), p 18 Old and new architectural components were juxtaposed but introduced separately. Some superstructures are essentially a combination of southern ''dravida'' and northern ''nagara'' structures and is termed "Vesara Sikhara" (also called Kadamba Sikhara).

The characteristically northern stepped-diamond plan of projecting corners was adopted in temples built with an entirely ''dravida'' articulation. Four 12th century structures constructed according to this plan are extant: the Basaveshwara Temple at Basavana Bagevadi, the Ramesvara Temple at Devur and the temples at Ingleshwar and Yevur, all in the vicinity of the Kalyani region, where ''nagara'' temples were common. This plan came into existence in northern India only in the 11th century, a sign that architectural ideas traveled fast.Foekema (2003), pp 54–55
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0f809a2939804729f10fae126846c70f" name="Dodda_Basappa_temple_Stellate_plan" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/0f809a2939804729f10fae126846c70f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>