<document id="5c5397d543fd429dd9d4206263979723-2.1" name="Western_Chalukya_architecture" cat="1">
<text>
A typical Western Chalukya temple may be examined from three aspects — the basic floor plan, the architectural articulation, and the figure sculptures.Foekema (2003), p 47

'''The basic floor plan''' is defined by the size of the shrine, the size of the sanctum, the distribution of the building mass, and by the ''pradakshina'' (path for circumambulation), if there is one.

'''Architectural articulation'''  refers to the ornamental components that give shape to the outer wall of the shrine. These include projections, recesses, and representations that can produce a variety of patterns and outlines, either stepped, stellate (star-shaped), or square.Foekema (2003), pp 35, 47 If stepped (also called "stepped diamond of projecting corners"), these components form five or seven projections on each side of the shrine, where all but the central one are projecting corners (projections with two full faces created by two recesses, left and right, that are at right angles with each other). If square (also called "square with simple projections"), these components form three or five projections on a side, only two of which are projecting corners. Stellate patterns form star points which are normally 8-, 16-, or 32-pointed and are sub-divided into interrupted and uninterrupted stellate components. In an 'interrupted' stellate plan, the stellate outline is interrupted by orthogonal (right-angle) projections in the cardinal directions, resulting in star points that have been skipped.Foekema (2003), p 63 Two basic kinds of architectural articulation are found in Indian architecture: the southern Indian ''dravida'' and the northern Indian ''nagara''.Foekema (2003), p 42

'''Figure sculptures''' are  miniature representations that stand by themselves, including architectural components on pilasters, buildings, sculptures, and complete towers. They are generally categorised as "figure sculpture" or "other decorative features".Foekema (2003), pp 35, 37, 48 On occasion, rich figure sculpture can obscure the articulation of a shrine, when representations of gods, goddesses, and mythical figures are in abundance.Foekema (2003), p 37
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4b0f04e9f2c1d0b0a939066bbeb5962d" name="Amrtesvara_Temple_at_Annigeri" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/4b0f04e9f2c1d0b0a939066bbeb5962d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>