<document id="5c5a341c9b94dd01fa84893f9d9eb62e-1" name="Halo_3_Original_Soundtrack" cat="20">
<text>
The score for ''Halo 3'' gave O'Donnell and Salvatori a chance to rework and revise existing themes heard in the games, as well as create new ones. ''Halo: Combat Evolved'' featured more strings, while the soundtrack to ''Halo 2'' featured more conventional video game music staples such as guitars by Steve Vai; in an interview, O'Donnell noted that "to be honest, when I got to the end of ''Halo 2'' I thought to myself: 'that was probably enough guitar.'" He intentionally made the score to the final game a shift back to the orchestral roots of the series, stating "I took an orthodox, almost formal approach to the trilogy." O'Donnell acknowledged that some games and movies used entirely different music with each sequel, but such an approach wasn't an option with ''Halo 3'', the third installment of a trilogy: "The Master Chief is still green, Cortana is still blue, and so you're going to hear the monks and the cellos."

O'Donnell began by writing out the reworked themes and music he wanted to hear in the game, without knowing where he would eventually use the sounds. He  approaches composition from the piano, and described his process as looking for something that "makes me go 'oh, ''thats'' a good feeling'". O'Donnell's approach to writing music for games is to put in the audio at the last minute of development, so that his music meshes with the game play in the best possible way; he still had not added in the score when ''Halo 3'' was demoed at Electronic Entertainment Expo 2007, less than three months away from the game's debut. Scoring for a video game, O'Donnell noted, is different from a film in that a good score sounds like it is narrating what the player does on screen; ''Halo 3'' uses an audio engine which allows music cues to naturally start, stop, and transition in response to game triggers.

Unlike previous soundtracks, where much of the music had been synthesized on computer, the soundtrack for ''Halo 3'' was recorded using a 60-piece orchestra, along with a 24 voice chorus. The music was recorded by the Northwest Sinfonia at Studio X in Seattle, Washington. 

The tracks are presented, similarly to the previous soundtrack for ''Halo 2'', in a suite form. The suites are named after the nine Campaign missions and unlike ''Volume Two'', are broken into separate tracks. Since the interactive mixing of sounds in ''Halo 3'' depends of what occurs in the game, O'Donnell instead "froze" the music into set suites and transitions for the CD, so that a listener playing the soundtrack through would hear a musical representation of the game. Interviewed by some of Bungie's staff for the Bungie Podcast, O'Donnell noted that there was more "techno" and "tribal" sounds than on previous soundtracks. O'Donnell also tried to avoid outside musical influences, as he believes that "Bungie should be creating culture, not being influenced by it."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="730558b5838de9e293a08c0826587e9f" name="Halo_3_Midnight_Madness_Bellevue_Best_Buy_243" sectnum="1#1">../img/730558b5838de9e293a08c0826587e9f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>