<document id="5c5cc66c9e0cff64ac88b31c457b9809-4" name="Yarralumla,_Australian_Capital_Territory" cat="11">
<text>
The Yarralumla local shopping centre is located on the corner of Bentham and Novar Streets. The centre contains a supermarket, bakery, dry-cleaners, video store/post office, chemist and newsagent as well as several restaurants and speciality shops. The shopping area has undergone redevelopment in recent years, including the addition of a two-storey office development facing the shopping centre. 

Yarralumla's first school, the Catholic St Peter Chanel's Primary School, opened in 1956; it later closed in the 1990s. Yarralumla Primary School, a public school, opened a year after St Peter Chanel's in 1957. Half of the original primary school is now used as a behavioural centre catering to problem students.   There are two preschools in Yarralumla: Hill Corner Preschool, which is now the ''St Nicholas Greek-Australian Preschool''; and the Montessori preschool, which is located in the former St Peter Chanel's Primary school buildings.

Weston Park is situated on a peninsula near the western end of Lake Burley Griffin. The park includes swimming areas, children's play equipment and wading pools, and a miniature railway, and is a popular barbecue spot on weekends. Weston Park forms part of a string of parks that line southern shore of Lake Burley Griffin; other parks include Yarralumla Bay, Lennox Gardens (incorporating a Japanese garden) and Stirling Park. 

Like most of Canberra, Yarralumla's only scheduled public transport is provided by ACTION buses. On weekdays, route 2 provides a service from Yarralumla to Woden and City Interchanges along Novar Street, Schlich Street and Hopetoun Circuit. Route 2 operates every 30 minutes until 6pm and hourly from 6pm to 11pm. On weekends and public holidays, route 932 provides an hourly service along the same streets as route 2.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7b14701eaeaf99cac393a49f7163580e" name="Weston_Park_Yarralumla" sectnum="4#1">../img/7b14701eaeaf99cac393a49f7163580e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>