<document id="5cf5f1b0466fee61c379f5e609ad65e1-1.1" name="Chat_Moss" cat="11">
<text>
The beginning of the 19th century saw the first attempt at the reclamation of Chat Moss. In 1793, William Roscoe began work on reclaiming the smaller Trafford Moss, now part of Trafford Park. By 1798, that work was sufficiently advanced for Roscoe to enter into a lease of part of Chat Moss from the de Trafford family, but no reclamation work was carried out until 1805.

Reclamation methods varied somewhat during the 19th century, but three basic operations featured; constructing drains at appropriate intervals; building a system of roads to allow access to the land so that materials such as clay, lime or marl could be dumped on it, to give it body; and fertilising the land by adding manure, often in the form of the euphemistically named night soil, collected from neighbouring towns.


The reclamation of Chat Moss and Trafford Moss was innovative in that instead of constructing roads to give access for the material to be dumped onto the bog, a movable light railway was developed. Narrow gauge track &ndash; which allowed the weight of the wagons to be spread evenly across an area of the bog &ndash; was temporarily laid down and then picked up and relaid elsewhere as needed. Roscoe was declared bankrupt in 1821, but the reclamation work continued under the stewardship of others who took over his leasehold interest, amongst them William Baines, the anti-Corn Law MP and owner of the ''Leeds Mercury'' newspaper.

Between 1831 and 1851, the population of nearby Manchester increased by more than 150%. This put considerable pressure on refuse disposal, a problem exacerbated by the gradual switch from the 1870s onwards from the older cesspit methods of sewage disposal to pail closets, which required regular emptying. By the 1880s, Manchester was producing more than  of refuse annually, about 75% of that being night soil. In 1895, Manchester Corporation purchased  of Chat Moss known as Chat Moss Estate from Sir Humphrey de Trafford, with a view to using the moss as a refuse disposal site. The final price paid by the corporation was £137,531 7s 1d (£ as of ).

A 1937 map of Chat Moss
Refuse was carried on barges down the Manchester Ship Canal as far as Boysnope Wharf, where it was loaded onto a light railway system to be taken into the moss for dumping. Farmers on Chat Moss were legally required by their tenancy agreements to accept a specified amount of refuse on their land, and were even obliged to pay for it. Farmers could themselves undertake reclamation work, with the land reclaimed being incorporated into their tenancies. An agreement dated 1905, between Manchester Corporation and Plant Cottage Farm, shows that the corporation agreed to  of refuse per acre free of charge for the first year, with the tenant being obliged to accept  of refuse per acre each year thereafter. The dumping of night soil on Chat Moss ended in 1923, but general refuse continued to be dumped on a diminishing scale until it finally ended in 1966.

Once drained, stabilised, and fertilised, Chat Moss became prime agricultural land, supplying Manchester with salad and vegetables. The drainage channels, required today, give the area its distinctive flat landscape broken up by ditches instead of hedges or walls. Even after all of the reclamation work that has taken place, parts of the area remain remote and bleak.

A scheme was devised during the Second World War to protect major cities from enemy bombing by lighting decoy fires on nearby open land. Manchester was protected by four of these Starfish sites as they were known, two of them on Chat Moss. RAF Balloon Command was responsible for the administration and manning of the sites, which were fully operational by 23 January 1941. Each consisted of an air raid shelter for the crew along with various devices to simulate street lighting and the explosions of incendiary bombs. The effectiveness of the decoy sites is uncertain, and they were closed in 1943.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="add0e12c76192787d572bcc86a210337" name="IrlamMoss" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/add0e12c76192787d572bcc86a210337.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>