<document id="5d7e72ace310425ab36edb9e72dee271-1" name="Halo:_Contact_Harvest" cat="17">
<text>
According to Staten, Tor Books asked Bungie Studios if they had someone suited to writing the next novel; Staten, having written much of the ''Halo'' series canon, was the obvious choice. The author found that the book was the perfect way to elaborate on the ''Halo'' story without stripping it down for a video game: "''I always felt we shortchanged . We don't have a lot of time to tell story while the bullets are flying.''" In addition, Staten said that the novel was the perfect way to do the character of Sergeant Johnson—who had appeared somewhat one-dimensional in the games—proper justice as a round character. Replying to G4TV's question about writing action, Staten replied that he felt that writing "involves slowing things down", in comparison to a game of ''Halo''. The author also said that the work of his favorite science-fiction authors helped teach him the importance of honing a "strong, consistent voice".

Originally, the novel was due to ship before the September 25 release of ''Halo 3''; Staten stated that due to his involvement with both projects, the novel slipped behind. He also emphasized that he hoped ''Contact Harvest'' was a good novel, not just a good ''Halo'' novel; "... someone who isn't a ''Halo'' fan &ndash; someone who hasn't read any of the previous novels &ndash; will be able to pick up ''Contact Harvest'' and enjoy the read". 

This focus on accuracy was a challenge for Staten, as he believes his audience is highly intelligent, willing, and able to report flaws; fellow Bungie employees cross-referenced his drafts with the "''Halo'' Story Bible" to ensure canonical agreement. One example of fans taking Staten to task over the novel occurred soon after the novel's cover was revealed in July 2007. The cover depicts the protagonist, Sergeant Avery Johnson holding a weapon known as the Battle Rifle. As the weapon was first introduced in the video game ''Halo 2'' and the events of ''Contact Harvest'' take place decades before the game, fans were quick to say that Staten had made a mistake. Staten later pointed out he had good reasons for including the offending weapon in the book, and justified the inclusion by stating that the weapon is a prototypical form of the version players use in the game.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2f3dee39c4b52188e585d82c9c253beb" name="Joe_Staten_and_Eric_Nylund" sectnum="1#1">../img/2f3dee39c4b52188e585d82c9c253beb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>