<document id="5e268f76fcf80f6183f4db6babb7f2e6-3" name="Halloween_(1978_film)" cat="19">
<text>
''Halloween'' premiered on October 25, 1978 in Kansas City (whether Kansas City, Missouri or Kansas City, Kansas, is unclear) and sometime afterward in Chicago, Illinois, and in New York City, New York.Distribution at ; last accessed April 19, 2006. It opened in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, on November 22, 1978., ''Pittsburgh Post-Gazette'', November 23, 1978. "Opening yesterday at the Gateway, Downtown, the Cinemette East in Monroeville and the Showcase West in Robinson Township...."

Although it performed well with little advertising — relying mostly on word-of-mouth — many critics seemed uninterested or dismissive of the film. The first glowing review by a prominent film critic came from Tom Allen of ''The Village Voice'' in November 1978, Allen noted that the film was sociologically irrelevant but applauded Carpenter's camera work as "duplicitous hype" and "the most honest way to make a good schlock film". Allen pointed out the stylistic similarities to ''Psycho'' and George A. Romero's ''Night of the Living Dead'' (1968)., ''The Village Voice'', November 6, 1978, pp. 67, 70. While the review gives no New York City premiere date or specific theater, a display advertisement on page 72 reads: "Held over! 2nd week of horror! At a Flagship Theatre near you". Per the movie listings on pages 82, 84 and 85, respectively, it played at four since-defunct theaters: the Essex, located at 375 Grand Street in Chinatown, per ; the RKO 86th Street Twin, on East 86th Street near Lexington Avenue; the Rivoli, located at 1620 Broadway, in the Times Square area, per ; and the Times Square Theater, located at 217 West 42nd Street, per , reprinted at Criterion.com, "The Criterion Collection, Online Cinematheque" The following month,  ''Voice'' lead critic Andrew Sarris wrote a follow-up feature on cult films, citing Allen's appraisal of ''Halloween'' and saying in the lead sentence that the film "bids fair to become the cult discovery of 1978. Audiences have been heard screaming at its horrifying climaxes"., ''The Village Voice'', December 18, 1978.

Following Allen's laudatory essay, other critics took notice. Renowned American critic Roger Ebert gave the film similar praise in his 1979 review in the ''Chicago Sun-Times'', and selected it as one of his top five films of 1978. Once-dismissive critics were impressed by Carpenter's choice of camera angles and simple music, and surprised by the lack of blood, gore, and graphic violence..
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2af58a934acab7901201933a625052e1" name="Halloween-Ad-Village-Voice-1978" sectnum="3#1">../img/2af58a934acab7901201933a625052e1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>