<document id="5e268f76fcf80f6183f4db6babb7f2e6-2.3" name="Halloween_(1978_film)" cat="19">
<text>
Historian Nicholas Rogers notes that film critics contend that John Carpenter's direction and camera work made ''Halloween'' a "resounding success".Nicholas Rogers, ''Halloween: From Pagan Ritual to Party Night'' (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2002), p. 111, ISBN 0-19-516896-8. Roger Ebert remarks, "It's easy to create violence on the screen, but it's hard to do it well. Carpenter is uncannily skilled, for example, at the use of foregrounds in his compositions, and everyone who likes thrillers knows that foregrounds are crucial ...."Roger Ebert, review of ''Halloween'', ''Chicago Sun-Times'', October 31, 1979, at ; last accessed April 19, 2006.


The opening title, featuring a jack-o'-lantern placed against a black backdrop, sets the mood for the entire movie. The camera slowly moves toward one of the jack-o'-lantern's eyes as the main title theme is heard. Film historian J.P. Telotte says that this scene "clearly announces that  primary concern will be with the way in which we see ourselves and others and the consequences that often attend our usual manner of perception".J.P. Telotte, "Through a Pumpkin's Eye: The Reflexive Nature of Horror," in Gregory Waller, ed., ''American Horrors: Essays on the Modern American Horror Film'' (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1992), p. 116, ISBN 0-252-01448-0.

During the conception of the plot, Yablans instructed "that the audience shouldn't see anything. It should be what they thought they saw that frightens them". Carpenter seemingly took Yablans' advice literally, filming many of the scenes from Michael Myers' point-of-view that allowed audience participation. Carpenter is not the first director to employ this method or use of a steadicam; for instance, the first scene of ''Psycho'' offers a voyeuristic look at lovers in a seedy hotel. Telotte argues, "As a result of this shift in perspective from a disembodied, narrative camera to an actual character's eye ... we are forced into a deeper sense of participation in the ensuing action".Telotte, "Through a Pumpkin's Eye," pp. 116 – 117. Along with the 1974 Canadian horror film ''Black Christmas'', Halloween made use of seeing events through the killer's eyes.

The first scene of the young Michael's voyeurism is followed by the murder of Judith Myers seen through the eye holes of Michael's clown costume mask. According to one commentator, Carpenter's "frequent use of the unmounted first-person camera to represent the killer's point of view ... invited  to adopt the murderer's assaultive gaze and to hear his heavy breathing and plodding footsteps as he stalked his prey".Rogers, ''Halloween'', p. 111.

Another technique that Carpenter adapted from Hitchcock's ''Psycho'' and Tobe Hooper's ''The Texas Chain Saw Massacre'' (1974) was suspense with minimal blood and gore. Debra Hill comments, "We didn't want it to be gory. We wanted it to be like a jack-in-the box." Film analysts refer to this as the "false startle" or "the old tap-on-the-shoulder routine" in which the stalkers, murderers, or monsters "lunge into our field of vision or creep up on a person."David Scott Diffrient, "A Film is Being Beaten: Notes on the Shock Cut and the Material Violence of Horror," in Steffen Hantke, ''Horror Film: Creating and Marketing Fear'' (Jackson: University Press of Mississippi, 2004), p. 61, ISBN 1-57806-692-1.

Carpenter worked with the cast to create the desired effect of terror and suspense. According to Jamie Lee Curtis, Carpenter created a "fear meter" because the film was shot out-of-sequence and she was not sure what her character's level of terror should be in certain scenes. "Here's about a 7, here's about a 6, and the scene we're going to shoot tonight is about a 9 1/2", remembered Curtis. She had different facial expressions and scream volumes for each level on the meter.Jamie Lee Curtis interview, quoted at ; last accessed April 19, 2006.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="61a7ab15ad5c4b1964555b013cfeeb7e" name="HalloweenTitle" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/61a7ab15ad5c4b1964555b013cfeeb7e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>