<document id="5e268f76fcf80f6183f4db6babb7f2e6-2.2" name="Halloween_(1978_film)" cat="19">
<text>
The cast of ''Halloween'' included veteran actor Donald Pleasence and then-unknown actress Jamie Lee Curtis. The low budget limited the number of big names that Carpenter could attract, and most of the actors received very little compensation for their roles. Pleasence was paid the highest amount at $20,000, Curtis received $8,000, and Nick Castle earned $25 a day.

The role of Dr. Sam Loomis was offered to Peter Cushing and Christopher Lee; both declined the part due to the low pay (though Lee would later tell Carpenter that declining the role was his biggest career mistake).''Halloween: A Cut Above the Rest'', documentary on Divimax 25th Anniversary Edition DVD of ''Halloween'' (1978; Troy, Mich.: Anchor Bay, 2003) English actor Pleasence — Carpenter's third choice — agreed to star. Pleasence has been called "John Carpenter's big landing." Americans were already acquainted with Pleasence as the villain Ernst Stavro Blofeld in the James Bond film ''You Only Live Twice'' (1967).Donald Pleasence casting information at ; last accessed April 19, 2006.

In an interview, Carpenter admits that "Jamie Lee wasn't the first choice for Laurie. I had no idea who she was. She was 19 and in a TV show at the time, but I didn't watch TV." He originally wanted to cast Anne Lockhart, the daughter of June Lockhart from ''Lassie'', as Laurie Strode. Lockhart, however, had commitments to several other film and television projects.Carpenter interview. Debra Hill says of learning that Jamie Lee was the daughter of ''Psycho'' actress Janet Leigh, "I knew casting Jamie Lee would be great publicity for the film because her mother was in ''Psycho''." ''Halloween'' was Jamie Lee Curtis' feature film debut and launched her career as a "scream queen" horror star.

Another relatively unknown actress, Nancy Kyes (credited in the film as Nancy Loomis) was cast as Laurie's promiscuous friend Annie Brackett, daughter of Haddonfield sheriff Leigh Brackett (Charles Cyphers). Kyes had previously starred in ''Assault on Precinct 13'' (as had Cyphers) and happened to be dating ''Halloween'''s art director Tommy Lee Wallace when filming began.Nancy Loomis casting information at ; last accessed April 19, 2006. Carpenter chose P. J. Soles to play Lynda Van Der Klok, another promiscuous friend of Laurie's, best remembered in the film for dialogue peppered with the word "totally." Soles was an actress known for her supporting role in ''Carrie'' (1976) and her minor part in ''The Boy in the Plastic Bubble'' (1976). According to one source, "Carpenter realized she had captured the aura of a happy go lucky teenage girl in the 70s."P. J. Soles casting information at ; last accessed April 19, 2006

The role of "The Shape" — as the masked Michael Myers character was billed in the end credits — was played by Nick Castle, who befriended Carpenter while they attended the University of Southern California. After ''Halloween'', Castle became a director, taking the helm of films such as ''The Last Starfighter'' (1984), ''The Boy Who Could Fly'' (1986), ''Dennis The Menace'' (1993) and ''Major Payne'' (1995).Nick Castle casting information at ; last accessed April 19, 2006.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4e338711fbdee8503ee51a38dcdb9674" name="LaurieStrode" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/4e338711fbdee8503ee51a38dcdb9674.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>