<document id="5ed183ab17a0b19b8e6843124262aad7-6" name="E.T._the_Extra-Terrestrial" cat="19">
<text>
An extended version of the film, including altered special effects, was released on March 22, 2002. Certain shots of E.T. had bothered Spielberg since 1982, as he did not have enough time to perfect the animatronics. Computer-generated imagery (CGI), provided by Industrial Light & Magic (ILM), was used to modify several shots, including ones of E.T. running in the opening sequence and being spotted in the cornfield. The spaceship's design was also altered to include more lights. Scenes shot for but not included in the original version were introduced. These included E.T. taking a bath, and Gertie telling Mary that Elliott went to the forest. Spielberg did not add the scene featuring Harrison Ford, feeling that would reshape the film too drastically. Having become a father, Spielberg was more sensitive about the scene where gun-wielding federal agents threaten Elliott and his escaping friends; he digitally replaced the guns with walkie-talkies. 

At the premiere, John Williams conducted a live performance of the score. The new release grossed $35 million domestically, bringing the film's total worldwide gross to $793 million since 1982. The 20th anniversary version was released as part of a two-disc DVD set on December 10, 2002; it was also packaged in a collector's edition with the original version. The changes to the film, particularly the escape scene, were criticized as political correctness. Peter Travers of ''Rolling Stone'' wondered, "Remember those guns the feds carried? Thanks to the miracle of digital, they're now brandishing walkie-talkies.... Is this what two decades have done to free speech?" Chris Hewitt of ''Empire'' wrote, "The changes are surprisingly low-key  while ILM's CGI E.T. is used sparingly as a complement to Carlo Rambaldi's extraordinary puppet." ''South Park'' parodied many of the changes in the 2002 episode "Free Hat".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d0f427e71c55675ed87e7b342ec944a0" name="ET1982" sectnum="6#1">../img/d0f427e71c55675ed87e7b342ec944a0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>