<document id="5ed183ab17a0b19b8e6843124262aad7-7" name="E.T._the_Extra-Terrestrial" cat="19">
<text>
In July 1982, during the film's first theatrical run, Spielberg and Mathison wrote a treatment for a sequel to be titled ''E.T. II: Nocturnal Fears''. It would have seen Elliott and his friends kidnapped by evil aliens and follow their attempts to contact E.T. for help. Spielberg decided against pursuing the sequel, feeling it "would do nothing but rob the original of its virginity".

Atari made a video game based on the film. Released in 1982, it was widely considered to be one of the worst video games ever. William Kotzwinkle—author of the film's novelization—wrote a sequel, ''E.T.: The Book of the Green Planet'', published in 1985. The novel concerns E.T.'s return to its planet, Brodo Asogi; its subsequent demotion and exile to its childhood "farm"; and its attempts to return to Earth by effectively breaking all the laws of Brodo Asogi.William Kotzwinkle, ''E.T.: The Book of the Green Planet'', Berkley Books, March 1985, ISBN 0-425-07642-3 ''E.T. Adventure'', a theme park ride, debuted at Universal Studios Florida in 1990. The $40 million attraction features the title character saying goodbye to visitors by name.

In 1998, E.T. was licensed to appear in television public service announcements produced by the Progressive Corporation. The announcements featured E.T.'s voice reminding drivers to "buckle up" their safety belts. Traffic signs depicting a stylized E.T. wearing a safety belt were installed on selected roads around the United States. The following year, British Telecommunications launched the "Stay in Touch" campaign, with E.T. as the star of various advertisements. The campaign's slogan was "B.T. has E.T.", with "E.T." also taken to mean "extra technology". At Spielberg's suggestion, George Lucas included members of E.T.'s race as background characters in ''Star Wars Episode I: The Phantom Menace'' (1999).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="70e3ebc29f0b85e1ede2dbff22c6bdc9" name="ETbuckleup" sectnum="7#1">../img/70e3ebc29f0b85e1ede2dbff22c6bdc9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>