<document id="5ed183ab17a0b19b8e6843124262aad7-4" name="E.T._the_Extra-Terrestrial" cat="19">
<text>
Spielberg drew the story of ''E.T.'' from the divorce of his own parents; Gary Arnold of ''The Washington Post'' called the film "essentially a spiritual autobiography, a portrait of the filmmaker as a typical suburban kid set apart by an uncommonly fervent, mystical imagination". References to Spielberg's childhood occur throughout: Elliott feigns illness by holding his thermometer to a light bulb while covering his face with a heating pad, a trick frequently employed by the young Spielberg. Michael's picking on Elliott echoes Spielberg's teasing of his younger sisters, and Michael's evolution from tormentor to protector reflects how Spielberg had to take care of his sisters after their father left.

Critics have focused on the parallels between the life of E.T. and Elliott, who is "alienated" by the loss of his father.Thomas A. Sebeok. "Enter Textuality: Echoes from the Extra-Terrestrial." In ''Poetics Today'' (1985), Porter Institute for Poetics and Semiotics. Published by Duke University Press.Ilsa J. Beck, "The Look Back in E.T.," ''Cinema Journal'' 31(4) (1992): 25-41, 33. A.O. Scott of  ''The New York Times'' wrote that while E.T. "is the more obvious and desperate foundling", Elliott "suffers in his own way from the want of a home" (coincidentally, E.T. is the first and last letter of Eliott's name). At the film's heart is the theme of growing up. Critic Henry Sheehan described the film as a retelling of Peter Pan from the perspective of a Lost Boy (Elliott): E.T. cannot survive physically on Earth, as Pan could not survive emotionally in Neverland; government scientists take the place of Neverland’s pirates. Vincent Canby of ''The New York Times'' similarly observed that the film "freely recycles elements from  ''Peter Pan'' and ''The Wizard of Oz''". Some critics have suggested that Spielberg's portrayal of suburbia is very dark, contrary to popular belief. According to A.O. Scott, "The suburban milieu, with its unsupervised children and unhappy parents, its broken toys and brand-name junk food, could have come out of a Raymond Carver story." Charles Taylor of Salon.com wrote, "Spielberg's movies, despite the way they're often characterized, are not Hollywood idealizations of families and the suburbs. The homes here bear what the cultural critic Karal Ann Marling called 'the marks of hard use'."


Other critics found religious parallels between E.T. and Jesus.Anton Karl Kozlovic.  ''Journal of Religion and Popular Culture'' 8 (Fall 2004). Andrew Nigels described the story of E.T. as "crucifixion by military science" and "resurrection by love and faith".Nigel Andrews. "Tidings of comfort and joy." ''Financial Times'' (December 10, 1982), I11 According to Spielberg biographer Joseph McBride, Universal Pictures appealed directly to the Christian market, with a poster reminiscent of Michelangelo's ''Creation of Adam'' and a logo reading "Peace". Spielberg answered that he did not intend the film to be a religious parable, joking, "If I ever went to my mother and said, 'Mom, I've made this movie that's a Christian parable,' what do you think she'd say? She has a kosher restaurant on Pico and Doheny in Los Angeles."

As a substantial body of film criticism has built up around ''E.T.'', numerous writers have analyzed the film in other ways as well. ''E.T.'' has been interpreted as a modern fairy tale and in psychoanalytic terms.Andrew Gordon. "E.T. as a Fairy Tale," ''Science Fiction Studies'' 10 (1983): 298-305. Producer Kathleen Kennedy noted that an important theme of ''E.T.'' is tolerance, which would be central to future Spielberg films such as ''Schindler's List''. Having been a loner as a teenager, Spielberg described the film as "a minority story". Spielberg's characteristic theme of communication is partnered with the ideal of mutual understanding: he has suggested that the story's central alien-human friendship is an analogy for how real-world adversaries can learn to overcome their differences.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b8b3d8ff8bff5b2ab82f27a2108f9913" name="ETChrist" sectnum="4#1">../img/b8b3d8ff8bff5b2ab82f27a2108f9913.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>