<document id="5f0015ad7dbf64194a6e97e30ab83720-4" name="Richard_II_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
The threat of a French invasion did not subside, but instead grew stronger into 1386. At the parliament of October that year, Michael de la Pole in his capacity of chancellor requested taxation of an unprecedented level for the defence of the realm.Saul (1997), p. 157. Rather than consenting, parliament responded by refusing to treat any request until the chancellor was removed.McKisack (1959), p. 443. It is assumed that this congregation, which has later become known as the Wonderful Parliament, was working with the support of Gloucester and Arundel.Saul (1997), p. 160. The king famously responded that he would not dismiss as much as a scullion from his kitchen at parliament's request.Saul (1997), pp. 157&ndash;8. Only when threatened with deposition was Richard forced to give in, and let de la Pole go.Saul (1997), p. 158. A commission was set up to review and control royal finances for a year.Harriss (2005), p. 459.

Richard was deeply perturbed by this affront to his royal prerogative, and from February to November 1387 set about on a "gyration" (circuit) of the country to muster support for his cause.Tuck (1985), p. 189. By installing de Vere as justice of Chester, he began the work of creating a loyal military power base in Cheshire.Goodman (1971), p. 22. He also assured a legal ruling from Chief Justice Robert Tresilian, asserting that parliament's conduct had been both unlawful and treasonable.

On his return to London, the king was confronted by Gloucester, Arundel and Thomas de Beauchamp, Earl of Warwick, who brought an appeal of treason against de la Pole, de Vere, Tresilian, and two other loyalists: the mayor of London, Nicholas Brembre, and Alexander Neville, the archbishop of York.Goodman (1971), p. 26. Richard stalled the negotiations to gain time, as he was expecting de Vere from Cheshire with military reinforcements.Saul (1997), p. 187. The three earls then joined forces with Henry, Earl of Derby (Gaunt's son, and the later King Henry IV) and Thomas de Mowbray, Earl of Nottingham the group known to history as the Lords Appellant. On 20 December 1387, they intercepted de Vere at Radcot Bridge, where he was routed and forced to flee the country.Goodman (1971), pp. 129&ndash;30.

Richard now had no choice but to comply with the appellants' demands; Brembre and Tresilian were condemned and executed, while de Vere and de la Pole who had by now also left the country were sentenced to death ''in absentia'' at the Merciless Parliament in February 1388.Neville, as a man of the clergy, was deprived of his temporalities, also ''in absentia''; Saul (1997), pp. 192&ndash;3. The proceedings went further, and a number of Richard's chamber knights were also executed, among these Burley.McKisack (1959), p. 458. The appellants had now succeeded completely in breaking up the circle of favourites around the king.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5c17689575fbf12c536cd1b3c4b5f724" name="Robert_de_Vere_fleeing_Radcot_Bridge" sectnum="4#1">../img/5c17689575fbf12c536cd1b3c4b5f724.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>