<document id="5f0015ad7dbf64194a6e97e30ab83720-6" name="Richard_II_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
Towards the end of the 1390s began the period that historians refer to as the "tyranny" of Richard II.Saul (1997), p. 203. The king had Gloucester, Arundel and Warwick arrested in July 1397. The motivation and timing are not entirely clear; even though one chronicle suggested a plot was being planned against the king, there is no evidence that this was the case.Saul (1997), pp. 371&ndash;5. It is more likely that Richard now simply felt strong enough to retaliate for the events of 1386&ndash;88, and eliminate a number of his potential enemies.Harriss (2005), p. 479. At the parliament of September 1397, Arundel was put on trial first, and after a heated quarrel with the king, he was condemned and executed.Saul (1997), p. 378. As time came for Gloucester to be tried, the Earl of Nottingham brought news that he was dead. Gloucester had been Nottingham's prisoner at Calais, and it is likely that he was killed on the king's order, to avoid the disgrace of executing a prince of the blood.Saul (1997), pp. 378&ndash;9. Warwick was also condemned to death, but his life was spared and he was instead exiled, as was Arundel's brother, Thomas Arundel, archbishop of Canterbury.Tuck (1985), p. 210. Richard then took his persecution of adversaries to the localities. While recruiting retainers for himself in various counties, he prosecuted local men who had been loyal to the appellants. The fines levied on these men brought great revenues to the crown, but the legalities of the proceedings were questioned by chroniclers.

These actions were made possible primarily through the collusion of John of Gaunt, but also with the support of a number of men lifted to prominence by the king, and disparagingly referred to as Richard's "duketti".Saul (2005), p. 63. John and Thomas Holland, the king's half-brother and nephew, were promoted from earls of Huntingdon and Kent to dukes of Exeter and Surrey respectively. Among the other loyalists were John Beaufort, Earl of Somerset, Edward, Earl of Rutland, John Montacute, Earl of Salisbury and Thomas Despenser. With the forfeited land of the convicted appellants, the king could now reward these men with lands and incomes suited to their new ranks.McKisack (1959), pp. 483&ndash;4

A threat to Richard's authority still existed though, in the form of the Lancaster dynasty represented by John of Gaunt and his son Henry, Earl of Derby (also called Henry of Bolingbroke). The house of Lancaster not only possessed greater wealth than any other family in England; they were also of royal descent, and as such likely candidates to succeed the childless Richard.Saul (1997), pp. 196&ndash;7. Discord broke out in the inner circles of court in December 1397, when Bolingbroke and Thomas de Mowbray who had now been made Duke of Hereford and Duke of Norfolk respectively became engaged in a quarrel. According to Hereford, Norfolk had claimed that the two, as former Lords Appellant, were next in line for royal retribution. Norfolk vehemently denied these charges, as such a claim would have amounted to treason. A parliamentary committee decided that the two should settle the matter by battle, but at the last moment Richard exiled the two dukes instead; Norfolk for life, Bolingbroke for ten years.Harriss (2005), p. 482. On 3 February 1399, John of Gaunt died. Rather than allowing Bolingbroke to succeed, Richard extended his exile to life, and had him disinherited.Saul (1997), pp. 403&ndash;4. The king felt safe from Henry, who was residing in Paris, since the French had little interest in any challenge to Richard and his peace policy.Saul (2005), p. 64. Richard left the country in May for another expedition in Ireland.McKisack (1959), p. 491.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="76ba4abe7d53a0530ab915edfe9529fd" name="Johnofgaunt" sectnum="6#1">../img/76ba4abe7d53a0530ab915edfe9529fd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>