<document id="5f0015ad7dbf64194a6e97e30ab83720-9" name="Richard_II_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
As part of Richard's programme of asserting his authority, he also tried to cultivate the royal image. Unlike any other English king before him, he had himself portrayed in panel paintings of elevated majesty,Saul (1997), p. 238. of which two survive: the over life-size Westminster Abbey portrait of the king (c. 1390, see top of page), and the Wilton Diptych (1394-99), a portable work probably intended to accompany Richard on his Irish campaign.Alexander and Binski, pp. 134-135.  See also Levey, pp. 20-24.  It is one of the few surviving English examples of the courtly International Gothic style of painting that was developed in the courts of the Continent, especially Prague and Paris.Levey, pp. 13-29.  Richard's expenditure on jewellery, rich textiles and metalwork was far higher than on paintings, but as with his illuminated manuscripts there are hardly any surviving works that can be connected with him, except for a crown, "one of the finest achievements of the Gothic goldsmith", that probably belonged to Anne.Alexander and Binski, pp. 202-3 and 506. It is documented in the royal collection from 1399 and accompanied Blanche, daughter of Henry IV, to her Bavarian marriage. It is still in Munich.  See also , The Institute of Historical Research and Royal Holloway. Accessed 12 October 2008


Among Richard's grandest projects in the field of architecture was Westminster Hall, which was extensively rebuilt during his reign, perhaps spurred on by the completion in 1391 of John of Gaunt's magnificent hall at Kenilworth Castle.  Fifteen life-size statues of kings were placed in niches on the walls, and the hammer-beam roof by the royal carpenter Hugh Herland, "the greatest creation of medieval timber architecture", allowed the original three Romanesque aisles to be replaced with a single huge open space, with a dais at the end for Richard to sit in soliary state.Alexander and Binski, pp. 506-7 and 515. Only six of the statues, rather damaged, remain, and the dias has been remodelled, but otherwise the hall remains largely as Richard and his architect Henry Yevele left it.  The rebuilding had been begun by Henry III in 1245, but had by Richard's time been dormant for over a century.Saul (1997), p. 315.

The court's patronage of literature is especially important, because this was the period in which the English language took shape as a literary language. There is little evidence to tie Richard directly to patronage of poetry, but it was nevertheless within his court that this culture was allowed to thrive.Saul (1997), pp. 361&ndash;4. The greatest poet of the age, Geoffrey Chaucer, served the king as a diplomat, a customs official and a clerk of The King's Works while producing some of his best-known work.McKisack (1959), pp. 529&ndash;30. He was also in the service of John of Gaunt, and wrote ''The Book of the Duchess'' as a eulogy to Gaunt's wife Blanche.Benson (1988), p. xv. Chaucer's colleague and friend John Gower wrote his ''Confessio Amantis'' on a direct commission from Richard, although he later grew disenchanted with the king.Saul (1997), pp. 362, 437.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3b2fd7cb02f79382f29655744231798d" name="Westminster_Hall_edited" sectnum="9#1">../img/3b2fd7cb02f79382f29655744231798d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>