<document id="5f04e33f68bc6d78ba943eea3dbf9bf6-4.2" name="Western_Ganga_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
The Western Ganga society in many ways reflected the emerging religious, political and cultural developments of those times. Women became active in local administration because Ganga kings distributed territorial responsibility to their queens such as the feudal queen Parabbaya-arasi of KundatturFrom the Kuntur inscription of 10th century (Adiga 2006, p203) and the queens of King Sripurusha, Butuga II and feudal king Permadi.Karmarkar (1947), p66 Inheritance of fiscal and administrative responsibility by the son-in-law, the wife or by the daughter is evident. The position of prime minister of King Ereganga II and position of ''nalgavunda'' (local landlord) bestowed upon Jakkiabbe, the wife of a fallen hero are examples. When Jakkiabbe took to asceticism, her daughter inherited the position.from the Bandalike inscription of 919 (Adiga 2006, p203)From the Shravanabelagola inscription (Adiga 2006, p204)

The devadasi system (''sule'' or courtesan) in temples was prevalent and was modelled after the structures in the royal palace.Adiga (2006), p398 Contemporaneous literature such a ''Vaddaradhane'' makes a mention of the chief queen (''Dharani Mahadevi'') accompanied by lower ranking queens (''arasiyargal'') and courtesans of the women's royal quarter (''pendarasada suleyargal'').Adiga (2006), p398 Some of the courtesans and concubines employed in the harem of the kings and chieftains were well respected, examples being Nandavva at whose instance a local chief made land grant to a Jain temple.From the Perur plates (Adiga 2006, p398) Education in the royal family was closely supervised and included such subjects as political science, elephant and horse riding, archery, medicine, poetry, grammar, drama, literature, dance, singing and use of musical instruments. Brahmins enjoyed an influential position in society and were exempt from certain taxes and customs due on land. In turn they managed public affairs such as teaching, local judiciary, functioned as trustees and bankers, managed schools, temples, irrigation tanks, rest houses, collected taxes due from villages and raised money from public subscriptions.Karmarkar (1947), p72,p74

By virtue of a Hindu belief that killing of a brahmin (''Bramhatya'') was a sin, capital punishment was not applicable to them.Altekar (1934), p329 Upper caste kshatriyas (''satkshatriya'') were also exempt from capital punishment due to their higher position in the caste system. Severe crimes committed were punishable by the severing of a foot or hand.From the notes of Alberuni and Bouchet (Karmarkar 1947, p103) Contemporary literary sources reveal up to ten castes in the Hindu caste system; three among kshatriya, three among brahmin, two among vaishya and two among shudras.From the notes of Yuan Chwang (Karmarkar 1947, p103) Family laws permitted a wife or daughter or surviving relatives of a deceased person to claim properties such as his home, land, grain, money etc. if there were no male heirs. If no claimants to the property existed, the state took possession of these properties as ''Dharmadeya'' (charitable asset).From a modern Bijapur inscription of 1178 (Karmarkar, 1947, p104) Intercaste marriage, child marriage, marriage of a boy to maternal uncles daughter, ''Svayamvara'' marriage (where the bride garlands her choice of a groom from among many aspirants) were all in vogue.The ''Svayamvara'' marriage of Chalukya King Vikramaditya VI to Chandaladevi in the 11th century being an example (Karmarkar, 1947 p105) Memorials containing hero stones (''virkal'') were erected for fallen heroes and the concerned family received monetary aid for maintenance of the memorial.Karmarkar (1947) , p109

The presence of numerous ''Mahasatikals'' (or ''Mastikal'' - hero stones for a woman who accepted ritual death upon the demise of her husband) indicates the popularity of Sati among royalty.From the writings of Marco Polo, Ibn Batuta, Bernier and Tavernier (Karmarkar 1947, p110) Ritual death by ''sallekhana'' and by ''jalasamadhi'' (drowning in water) were also practiced.Karmarkar (1947), p110 Popular clothing among men was the use of two unrestricted garments, a Dhoti as a lower garment and a plain cloth as upper garment while women wore Saris with stitched petticoats. Turbans were popular with men of higher standing and people used umbrellas made with bamboo or reeds.Karmarkar (1947), p111 Ornaments were popular among men and women and even elephants and horses were decorated. Men wore finger rings, necklaces (''honnasara'' and ''honnagala sara''), bracelets (''Kaduga'') and wristlets (''Kaftkina''). Women wore a nose jewel (''bottu''), nose ring (''mugutti''), bangles (''bale'' or ''kankana'') and various types of necklaces (''honna gante sara'' and ''kati sutra''). During leisure, men amused themselves with horse riding, watching wrestling bouts, cock fights and ram fights.Karmarkar (1947), p112 There existed a large and well organised network of schools for imparting higher education and these schools were known by various names such as ''agraharas'', ''ghatikas'', ''brahmapura'' or ''matha''.Karmarkar (1947), p113 Inscriptions mention schools of higher education at Salotgi, Balligavi, Talagunda, Aihole, Arasikere and other places.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b194c1f68ff5834c8d7fcf182e1a2ceb" name="KalleshwaraTemple" sectnum="4.2#1">../img/b194c1f68ff5834c8d7fcf182e1a2ceb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>