<document id="5f04e33f68bc6d78ba943eea3dbf9bf6-2" name="Western_Ganga_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
The Western Ganga administration was influenced by principles stated in the ancient text ''Arthashastra''. The ''praje gavundas'' mentioned in the Ganga records held similar responsibilities as the village elders (''gramavriddhas'') mentioned by Kautilya. Succession to the throne was hereditary but there were instances when this was overlooked.Kamath (2001), p46 The kingdom was divided into ''Rashtra'' (district) and further into ''Visaya'' (consisting of possibly 1000 villages) and ''Desa''. From the 8th century, the Sanskrit term ''Visaya'' was replaced by the Kannada term ''Nadu''. Examples of this change are Sindanadu-8000 and Punnadu-6000,Adiga (2006), p10 with scholars differing about the significance of the numerical suffix. They opine that it was either the revenue yield of the division computed in cash termsRice in Adiga (2006), p15) or the number of fighting men in that division or the number of revenue paying hamlets in that divisionSharma in Adiga (2006), p16 or the number of villages included in that territory.

Inscriptions have revealed several important administrative designations such as prime minister (''sarvadhikari''), treasurer (''shribhandari''), foreign minister (''sandhivirgrahi'') and chief minister (''mahapradhana''). All of these positions came with an additional title of commander (''dandanayaka''). Other designations were royal steward (''manevergade''), master of robes (''mahapasayita''), commander of elephant corps (''gajasahani''), commander of cavalry (''thuragasahani'') etc.Kamath (2001), p47 In the royal house, ''Niyogis'' oversaw palace administration, royal clothing and jewellery etc. and the ''Padiyara'' were responsible for court ceremonies including door keeping and protocol. Adiga (2006), p238

Officials at the local level were the ''pergade'', ''nadabova'', ''nalagamiga'', ''prabhu'' and ''gavunda''.Adiga (2006), pp161-177 The ''pergades'' were superintendents from all social classes such as artisans, gold smiths, black smiths etc. The ''pergades'' dealing with the royal household were called ''manepergade'' (house superintendent) and those who collected tolls were called ''Sunka vergades''.From the Kanatur inscription (Adiga 2006, p161) The ''nadabovas'' were accountants and tax collectors at the ''Nadu'' level and sometimes functioned as scribes.From the Kanatur inscription (Adiga 2006, p164) The ''nalagamigas'' were officers who organized and maintained defence at the ''Nadu'' level.From the Mavali inscription of 8th century and Indravalli inscription (Adiga 2006), p165 The ''prabhu'' constituted a group of elite people drawn together to witness land grants and demarcation of land boundaries.Doddakunce inscription, the Karagada and Maruru inscription (Adiga 2006, p167-68) The ''gavundas'' who appear most often in inscriptions were the backbone of medieval polity of the southern Karnataka region. They were landlords and local elite whom the state utilized their services to collect taxes, maintain records of landownership, bear witness to grants and transactions and even raise militia when required.Bedirur inscriptions of 635 (Adiga 2006, p168)

Inscriptions that specify land grants, rights and ownership were descriptive of the boundaries of demarcation using natural features such as rivers, streams, water channels, hillocks, large boulders, layout of the village, location of forts (''kote'') if any in the proximity, irrigation canals, temples, tanks and even shrubs and large trees. Also included was the type of soil, the crops meant to be grown and tanks or wells to be excavated for irrigation.From the Kumsi inscription of 931 and Doddahomma inscription of 977 (Adiga 2006, pp21-22, p27, p29)From the Mavali inscription and Indivalli inscription (Adiga 2006, p31) Inscriptions mention wet land, cultivable land, forest and waste land.From the Devarahalli and Hosur copper plates (Adiga 2006, p33) There are numerous references to hamlets (''palli'') belonging to the hunter communities who resided in them (''bedapalli'').From inscriptions and literary writings such as ''Vaddaradhane'' (920) and ''Pampa Bharata'' (940) (Adiga 2006, p36-37) From the 6th century onwards, the inscriptions refer to feudal lords by the title ''arasa''. The ''arasas'' were either brahmins or from tribal background who controlled hereditary territories paying periodic tribute to the king.Adiga (2006), p208 The ''velavali'' who were loyal bodyguards of the royalty were fierce warriors under oath (''vele''). They moved with the royal family and were expected to fight for the master and be willing to lay down their lives in the process. If the king died, the ''velavali'' were required to self immolate on the funeral pyre of the master.Adiga (2006), pp233-234
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="03e7420a9307a06ba0ea3a47b846d284" name="Bharatha" sectnum="2#1">../img/03e7420a9307a06ba0ea3a47b846d284.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>