<document id="5f04e33f68bc6d78ba943eea3dbf9bf6-4.5" name="Western_Ganga_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
The Western Gangas used Kannada and Sanskrit extensively as their language of administration. Some of their inscriptions are also bilingual in these languages. In bilingual inscriptions the formulaic passages stating origin myths, genealogies, titles of Kings and benedictions tended to be in Sanskrit, while the actual terms of the grant such as information on the land or village granted, its boundaries, participation of local authorities, rights and obligations of the grantee, taxes and dues and other local concerns were in the local language.Thapar 2003, pp393-394 The usage of these two languages showed important changes over the centuries. During the first phase (350-725), Sanskrit copper plates dominated, indicating the initial ascendancy of the local language as a language of administration and the fact that majority of the records from this phase were ''Brahmadeya'' grants (grants to Brahmin temples).Adiga (2006), p110 In the second phase (725-1000), lithic inscriptions in Kannada outnumbered Sanskrit copper plates, consistent with the patronage Kannada received from rich and literate Jains who used Kannada as their medium to spread the Jain faith.Adiga (2006), p10Thapar 2003, p396 Recent excavations at Tumbula near Mysore have revealed a set of early copper plate bilingual inscriptions dated 444. The genealogy of the kings of the dynasty is described in Sanskrit while Kannada was used to describe the boundary of the village. An interesting inscription discovered at Beguru near modern Bangalore that deserves mention is the epigraph dated 890 that refers to a ''Bengaluru'' war. This is in ''Hale Kannada'' (old Kannada) language and is the earliest mention of the name of Bangalore city. The Western Gangas minted coins with Kannada and Nagari legends,Kamath (2001), p12 the most common feature on their coins was the image of an elephant on the obverse and floral petal symbols on the reverse. The Kannada legend ''Bhadr'', a royal umbrella or a conch shell appeared on top of the elephant image. The denominations are the ''pagoda'' (weighing 52 grains), the ''fanam'' weighting one tenth or one half of the ''pagoda'' and the quarter ''fanams''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ac17712364989352b4456b7d173b8005" name="Shravanabelagola_Vindyagiri_oldKannada_inscription" sectnum="4.5#1">../img/ac17712364989352b4456b7d173b8005.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>