<document id="5f10ff39392fea90cd7a810a10c6e818-2.2" name="Bart_King" cat="26">
<text>
King won the Child's Bowling Cup, the premier award for bowling in American cricket, for the first time in 1896, and joined the Philadelphian cricket team's tour of England in 1897. The tour was very ambitious, and was arranged mainly for educational purposes: few of those on the American side expected to win many matches.  Previous tours had tended to involve amateur English sides with a low level of competition. In 1897, the tour started on June 7 at Oxford, ending in late July at The Oval almost 2 months later. The schedule included fifteen matches against all of the top county cricket teams, the Oxford and Cambridge University teams, the Marylebone Cricket Club, and two other sides, though only a few of the counties thought it worth while to put their best elevens onto the field. 

While the tour initially aroused some curiosity, many English fans lost interest until Bart King and the Philadelphians met the full Sussex team at Brighton on June 17. King demonstrated his batting ability in first innings with a fourth-wicket stand of 107 with John Lester.  He then took 7 wickets for 13 runs, and Philadelphia dismissed Sussex for 46 in less than an hour.  King took 6 for 102 in Sussex's second innings, helping the Philadelphians to a victory by 8 wickets. 

Despite the excitement surrounding King's performance, the Americans did not fare well overall, and the results may have been worse than hoped for the tour's promoters. Philadelphia won only two of their fifteen matches, losing nine and earning a draw in the remaining four. After their win against Sussex, the only other win of the tour came against Warwickshire. During this match, King took 5 for 95 and 7 for 72 and scored 46 runs. According to ''Wisden Cricketers' Almanack'', King proved himself to be the best bowler on the American side and had to do much of the work. He bowled three hundred overs, more than anyone else in the team, taking 72 wickets with a bowling average of a little over 24 runs. In addition to his bowling, King scored 441 runs as a batsman  at a batting average of just over 20.

Following the 1897 tour, many English counties were interested in securing King's services. It was thought that he would not play as a professional, so alternative means of remuneration had to be found: one county reportedly offered to arrange a marriage with a widow who had an income of £7000 per year.  In the end, King returned to the United States, where he continued to perform very well in club cricket.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="730c8cdcb6deac9ebe82e71bd222d39d" name="Bart_King_at_Bat" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/730c8cdcb6deac9ebe82e71bd222d39d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>