<document id="5febbff9a5e62ce653ef1499995b94a6-3.1" name="Sicilian_Baroque" cat="1">
<text>
The great Sicilian earthquake of 1693 severely damaged 54 cities and towns and 300 villages. The epicentre of the disaster was in Val di Noto, where the city of Noto was destroyed, while the city of Catania was very severely damaged. In total it is estimated over 100,000 people were killed. Other towns which suffered severely were Ragusa, Modica, Scicli, and Ispica. Rebuilding began almost immediately.  

The lavishness of the architecture that was to arise from this disaster is connected with the politics of Sicily at the time; Sicily was still officially under Spanish rule, but rule was effectively delegated to the native aristocracy. This was led by the Duke of Camastra, whom the Spanish had appointed viceroy to appease the aristocracy, who were numerous.  The aristocracy was relatively concentrated compared to most of Europe, and a gentry class was missing.  In the 18th century, one estimate held that there were 228 noble families, who provided Sicily with a ruling class consisting of 58 princes, 27 dukes, 37 marquesses, 26 Counts, one viscount and 79 barons; the Golden Book of the Sicilian nobility (last published in 1926) lists even more.Gefen, p. 8. In addition to these were the younger scions of the families, with their courtesy titles of ''nobile'' or baron. 

Architecture was not the only legacy of the Normans. Rule over the peasants (there was no established middle class) was also enforced by a feudal system, unchanged since its introduction following the Norman conquest of 1071. Thus the Sicilian aristocracy had not only wealth but vast manpower at their command, something that had by this time declined in many other parts of Europe.  As in Southern Spain, the huge rural estates remained almost as concentrated as when they had been Roman "latifundi".  The Sicilian economy, though very largely agriculturally based, was very strong, and became more so during the eighteenth century as shipping became more efficient and the threat of Muslim piracy died away. The export markets for lemons (for the great eighteenth century fashion for lemonade) and wines increased greatly, and Sicilian wheat remained, as it had been since Roman times, the backbone of the economy.  The disaster that was to give Sicily its modern reputation of poverty, namely the opening-up of the American Middle West to wheat-farming, was a century away.  When it came, this permanently more than halved the price of wheat, and destroyed the old economy forever.  
 
The aristocracy shared their power only with the Roman Catholic Church. The Church ruled by fear of damnation in the next life and of the Inquisition in the present, and consequently both upper and lower classes gave as generously as they could on all major saints' days. Many priests and bishops were members of the aristocracy. The wealth of the Church in Sicily was further enhanced by the tradition of pressing younger children of the aristocracy to enter monasteries and convents, in order to preserve the family estates from division; a large fee, or dowry, was usually paid to the Church to facilitate this, in the form of property, jewels, or money. Thus the wealth of certain religious orders grew out of all proportion to the economic growth of any other group at this time. This is one of the reasons that so many of the Sicilian Baroque churches and monasteries, such as San Martino delle Scale, were rebuilt after 1693 on such a lavish scale.

Once rebuilding began, the poor rebuilt their basic housing in the same primitive fashion as before. By contrast, the wealthiest residents, both secular and spiritual, became caught in an almost manic orgy of building. Most members of the nobility had several homes in Sicily.The Prince of Lampedusa, author of ''The Leopard'', wrote of his family's six homes: a townhouse in Palermo, a villa at Bagheria, a palazzo at Toretta, a country house at Reitano, a "great" castle at Santa Marherita de Belice, and "two where we never went": a castle and house at Palma de Montechiaro ("I luoghi della mia prima infanzia" ). For one thing, the Spanish viceroy spent six months of the year in Palermo and six in Catania, holding court in each city, and hence members of the aristocracy needed a town palazzo in each city. Once the palazzi in devastated Catania were rebuilt in the new fashion, the palazzi in Palermo seemed antiquated by comparison, so they too were eventually rebuilt. Following this, from the middle of the 18th century, villas to retire to in the autumn, essentially status symbols, were built at the fashionable enclave at Bagheria. This pattern was repeated, on a smaller scale, throughout the lesser cities of Sicily, each city providing a more entertaining social life and a magnetic draw for the provincial aristocrat than their country estate. The country estate also did not escape the building mania. Often Baroque wings or new façades were added to ancient castles, or country villas were completely rebuilt. Thus the frenzy of building gained momentum until the increasingly fantastical Baroque architecture demanded by these hedonistic patrons reached its zenith in the mid-18th century.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9da1c509d55e04ad89a8c2dace754505" name="Palazzo_Biscari" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/9da1c509d55e04ad89a8c2dace754505.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>