<document id="5ff9fe26c6db514e11552af4a0c7e7ae-3" name="Rokeby_Venus" cat="1">
<text>
The ''Rokeby Venus'' was long held to be one of Velázquez's final works.López-Rey noted that based on stylistic qualities, Beruete (Aureliano de Berueute, ''Velázquez'', Paris, 1898) assigned the painting to the late 1650s. López-Rey, vol. I, p. 155. In 1951, it was found recorded in an inventory of June 1, 1651 from the collection of Gaspar Méndez de Haro, 7th Marquis of Carpio,From 1648; before that Marquis of Heliche, by which title he is sometimes referred to. Portús, p. 57. a close associate of Philip IV of Spain. Haro was the great-nephew of Velázquez's first patron, the Count-Duke of Olivares, and a notorious libertine. According to the art historian Dawson Carr, Haro "loved paintings almost as much as he loved women",Carr, p. 217 and "even his panegyrists lamented his excessive taste for lower-class women during his youth". For these reasons it seemed likely that he would have commissioned the painting.Fernandez, Angel Aterido. "". ''The Burlington Magazine'', Vol. 143, No. 1175, February, 2001. pp. 91–94. However, in 2001 the art historian Ángel Aterido discovered that the painting had first belonged to the Madrid art dealer and painter Domingo Guerra Coronel, and was sold to Haro in 1652 following Coronel's death the previous year.Aterido, pp. 91–92. Coronel's ownership of the painting raises a number of questions: how and when it came into Coronel's possession, and why Velázquez's name was omitted from Coronel's inventory. The art critic Javier Portús has suggested that the omission may have been due to the painting's portrayal of a female nude, "a type of work which was carefully supervised and whose dissemination was considered problematic".Portús, p. 57.



These revelations make the painting difficult to date. Velázquez's painting technique offers no assistance, although its strong emphasis on colour and tone suggest that the work dates from his mature period. The best estimates of its origin put its completion in the late 1640s or early 1650s, either in Spain or during Velázquez's last visit to Italy. If this is the case, then the breadth of handling and the dissolution of form can be seen to mark the beginning of the artist's final period. The conscientious modelling and strong tonal contrasts of his earlier work are here replaced by a restraint and subtlety which would culminate in his late masterpiece, ''Las Meninas''.Gudiol, p. 261.

The painting passed from Haro into the collection of his daughter Catalina de Haro y Guzmán, the eighth Marchioness of Carpio, and her husband, Francisco Álvarez de Toledo, the tenth Duke of Alba.López-Rey, vol. II, p. 262. In 1802, Charles IV of Spain ordered the family to sell the painting (with other works) to Manuel de Godoy, his favourite and chief minister.MacLaren, p. 126. He hung it alongside two masterpieces by Francisco Goya that he may have commissioned himself, ''The Nude Maja'' and ''The Clothed Maja''. These bear obvious compositional similarities with Velázquez's ''Venus'', although unlike Velázquez, Goya clearly painted his nude in a calculated attempt to provoke shame and disgust in the relatively unenlightened climate of 18th-century Spain.Schwarz, Michael. "The Age of the Rococo". London: Pall Mall Press, 1971. p. 94. ISBN 0-2690-2564-2

''Venus'' was brought to England in 1813, where it was purchased (for £500, and on the advice of his friend Sir Thomas Lawrence) by John Morritt,Brought to England by William Buchanan, a Scottish art dealer who kept an agent in Spain, G.A. Wallis. Bray, in Carr, p. 99; MacLaren, p. 127. who hung it in his house at Rokeby Park, Yorkshire—thus the painting's popular name. In 1906, the painting was acquired for the National Gallery by the newly created National Art Collections Fund, its first campaigning triumph.The painting was not universally accepted as Velázquez's work on its reintroduction to the public. The critic, James Grieg hypothesised that it was by Anton Raphael Mengs—although he found little support for his idea—and there was more serious discussion about the possibility of Velázquez's son-in-law and pupil, Juan del Mazo as the artist. MacLaren p. 76 dismisses both claims: "The supposed signatures of Juan Bautista Mazo and Anton Raphael Mengs in the bottom left corner are purely accidental marks." King Edward VII greatly admired the painting, and anonymously provided £8,000 towards its purchase,Bray; in Carr, p. 107 and became Patron of the Fund thereafter.Smith, Charles Saumarez. "The Battle for Venus: In 1906, the King Intervened to Save a Velazquez Masterpiece for the Nation. If Only Buckingham Palace, or Indeed Downing Street, Would Now Do the Same for Raphael's Madonna of the Pinks". ''New Statesman'', Volume 132, Issue 4663, November 10, 2003. p. 38.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a08e50ddd41ad2072c0df2257036dc20" name="Francisco_de_Goya_y_Lucientes_011" sectnum="3#1">../img/a08e50ddd41ad2072c0df2257036dc20.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>