<document id="600c3f1e9d7284a7daab1533fbdd774a-3" name="William_Bostock" cat="29">
<text>
Bostock married his Australian fiancée, Gwendolen Norton, in Southampton on 6 March 1919. The couple had two daughters, one of whom, Gwendolen Joan, would serve as a cipher officer in the Women's Auxiliary Australian Air Force (WAAAF) during World War II.Thomson, ''The WAAAF in Wartime Australia'', p.337 Bostock retired from the RAF and returned to civilian life in Australia that October. On 14 September 1921, he joined the recently formed Royal Australian Air Force (RAAF) and was commissioned a Flight Lieutenant. He became a friend and mentor to Flying Officer (later Air Marshal Sir) George Jones, another World War I veteran, who had flown with the Australian Flying Corps and had joined the Air Force in March.Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp.116&ndash;119Helson, ''"10 Years at the Top"'', pp.16&ndash;19 

Bostock attended RAF Staff College, Andover, from 1926 to 1928. Whilst there he was admonished by the college's commandant, via letter, due to the particular school he had chosen for his daughter and because he did his own gardening;  Bostock was said to have returned the letter marked "noted and ignored". On his return to Australia as a Squadron Leader in December 1929, he was made Director of Training at RAAF Headquarters in Melbourne. From 1931 to 1936 Bostock was Commanding Officer of No. 3 Squadron, flying Westland Wapitis and, later, Hawker Demons. At the time, his position as 3 Squadron commander doubled as CO of the unit's base, RAAF Station Richmond.Roylance, ''Air Base Richmond'', pp.46,123 A Wing Commander from 1934, he was appointed an Officer of the Order of the British Empire in the King's Birthday Honours on 31 May 1935. Following a two-year posting in Britain with No. 6 Auxiliary Group, RAF Bomber Command,Gillison,  Bostock was promoted to Group Captain on 1 September 1938 and made Director of Operations and Intelligence. Within a year he had become Deputy Chief of the Air Staff.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6e0440fc42cad5361fff6e45e10878e7" name="P00448.195RichmondWapitis" sectnum="3#1">../img/6e0440fc42cad5361fff6e45e10878e7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>