<document id="609b77f61aa56b2327326d2957dbb072-2" name="Italian_War_of_1542–1546" cat="29">
<text>
The French immediately launched a two-front offensive against Charles.  In the north, the Duke of Orléans attacked Luxembourg, briefly capturing the city; in the south, a larger army under Claude d'Annebault and Francis's eldest son, the Dauphin Henry, unsuccessfully besieged the city of Perpignan in northern Spain.Black, ''European Warfare'', 80; Blockmans, ''Emperor Charles V'', 72; Knecht, ''Renaissance Warrior'', 480.  Francis himself was meanwhile in La Rochelle, dealing with a revolt caused by popular discontent with a proposed reform of the ''gabelle'' tax.Knecht, ''Renaissance Warrior'', 480.  For more details of the ''gabelle'' revolt, see Knecht, ''Renaissance Warrior'', 480–483.



By this point, relations between Francis and Henry VIII were collapsing.  Henry—already angered by the French refusal to pay the various pensions, which were owed to him under the terms of past treaties—was now faced with the potential of French interference in Scotland, where he was entangled in the midst of an attempt to marry his son to Mary, Queen of Scots, that would develop into the open warfare of the "Rough Wooing".Knecht, ''Renaissance Warrior'', 486.  He had intended to begin a war against Francis in the summer of 1543, but negotiating a treaty to that effect with the Emperor proved difficult; since Henry was, in Charles's eyes, a schismatic, the Emperor could not promise to defend him against attack, nor sign any treaty which referred to him as the head of the Church—both points upon which Henry insisted.Scarisbrick, ''Henry VIII'', 388–389.  The matter of royal style was finally resolved by referring to Henry as "Defender of the Faith, etc." in the final documents.  Negotiations continued for weeks; finally, on 11 February 1543, Henry and Charles signed a treaty of offensive alliance, pledging to invade France within two years.Blockmans, ''Emperor Charles V'', 72; Knecht, ''Renaissance Warrior'', 486; Scarisbrick, ''Henry VIII'', 388–389.  In May 1543, Henry sent Francis an ultimatum threatening war within twenty days; and, on 22 June, at last declared war.Blockmans, ''Emperor Charles V'', 72; Knecht, ''Renaissance Warrior'', 486; Scarisbrick, ''Henry VIII'', 389.  Elton argues that the only explanation for this move is that Henry believed his Scottish entanglements to be concluded (Elton, ''England Under the Tudors'', 194).

Hostilities now flared up across northern France.  On Henry's orders, Sir John Wallop crossed the Channel to Calais with an army of 5,000 men, to be used in the defense of the Low Countries.Scarisbrick, ''Henry VIII'', 389.  The French, under Antoine de Bourbon, Duke of Vendôme, had captured Lillers in April; by June, d'Annebault had taken Landrecies as well.Knecht, ''Renaissance Warrior'', 486–487.  Wilhelm of Cleves openly joined the war on Francis's side, invading Brabant, and fighting began in Artois and Hainaut.Knecht, ''Renaissance Warrior'', 486.  Francis inexplicably halted with his army near Rheims; in the meantime, Charles attacked Wilhelm, invading the Duchy of Julich and capturing Düren.Black, ''European Warfare'', 80; Knecht, ''Renaissance Warrior'', 487.

Concerned about the fate of his ally, Francis ordered the Duke of Orléans and d'Annebault to attack Luxembourg, which they took on 10 September; but it was too late for Wilhelm, as he had already surrendered on 7 September, signing the Treaty of Venlo with Charles.Knecht, ''Renaissance Warrior'', 487.  Wilhelm's surrender made his marriage to Jeanne d'Albret pointless, and it was annulled in 1545.  By the terms of this treaty, Wilhelm was to concede the overlordship of Guelders and Zutphen to Charles, and to assist him in suppressing the Reformation.Blockmans and Prevenier, ''Promised Lands'', 232; Hughes, ''Early Modern Germany'', 57.  Charles now advanced to besiege Landrecies, seeking battle with Francis; but, after a brief standoff, Francis withdrew to Saint-Quentin on 4 November, leaving the Emperor free to march north and seize Cambrai.Black, ''European Warfare'', 80; Blockmans, ''Emperor Charles V'', 72; Knecht, ''Renaissance Warrior'', 487.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b7314b09c6189fe99f4d29fd300c000c" name="Battles_in_northern_France_during_the_Italian_War_of_1542-46" sectnum="2#1">../img/b7314b09c6189fe99f4d29fd300c000c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>