<document id="60d28e7d879c0dc48b9a593468cf11e5-4.8" name="Lion" cat="3">
<text>
Though adult lions have no natural predators, evidence suggests that the majority die violently from humans or other lions.Schaller, p. 183 This is particularly true of male lions, who, as the main defenders of the pride, are more likely to come into aggressive contact with rival males. In fact, even though a male lion may reach an age of 15 or 16 years if he manages to avoid being ousted by other males, the majority of adult males do not live to be more than 10 years old. This is why the average lifespan of a male lion tends to be significantly less than that of a lioness in the wild. However, members of both sexes can be injured or even killed by other lions when two prides with overlapping territories come into conflict. 

Various species of tick commonly infest the ears, neck and groin regions of most lions.Schaller, p. 184 Adult forms of several species of the tapeworm genus ''Taenia'' have been isolated from intestines, the lions having ingested larval forms from antelope meat. Lions in the Ngorongoro Crater were afflicted by an outbreak of stable fly (''Stomoxys calcitrans'') in 1962; this resulted in lions becoming covered in bloody bare patches and emaciated. Lions sought unsuccessfully to evade the biting flies by climbing trees or crawling into hyena burrows; many perished or emigrated as the population dropped from 70 to 15 individuals. A more recent outbreak in 2001 killed six lions. Lions, especially in captivity, are vulnerable to the Canine distemper virus (CDV), feline immunodeficiency virus (FIV), and feline infectious peritonitis (FIP). CDV is spread through domestic dogs and other carnivores; a 1994 outbreak in Serengeti National Park resulted in many lions developing neurological symptoms such as seizures. During the outbreak, several lions died from pneumonia and encephalitis. FIV, which is similar to HIV while not known to adversely affect lions, is worrisome enough in its effect in domestic cats that the Species Survival Plan recommends systematic testing in captive lions. It occurs with high to endemic frequency in several wild lion populations, but is mostly absent from Asiatic and Namibian lions.''
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2f6ea6e2a2d227f1bb3118bcc73e2ff4" name="Lion_female_in_tree,_Serengeti" sectnum="4.8#1">../img/2f6ea6e2a2d227f1bb3118bcc73e2ff4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>