<document id="60d28e7d879c0dc48b9a593468cf11e5-2.1.2" name="Lion" cat="3">
<text>
Several additional subspecies of lion existed in prehistoric times:

* ''P. l. atrox'', known as the American Lion or American cave lion, was abundant in the Americas from Alaska to Peru in the Pleistocene Epoch until about 10,000 years ago. This form as well as the cave lion sometimes are considered to represent separate species, but recent phylogenetic studies suggest that they are in fact, subspecies of the lion (''Panthera leo''). One of the largest lion subspecies to have existed, its body length is estimated to have been 1.6–2.5 m (5–8 ft).
* ''P. l. fossilis'', known as the Early Middle Pleistocene European cave lion, flourished about 500,000 years ago; fossils have been recovered from Germany and Italy. It was larger than today's African lions, reaching the American cave lion in sizeErnst Probst: Deutschland in der Urzeit. Orbis Verlag, 1999. ISBN 3-572-01057-8

* ''P. l. spelaea'', known as the European cave lion, Eurasian cave lion, or Upper Pleistocene European cave lion, occurred in Eurasia 300,000 to 10,000 years ago. This species is known from Paleolithic cave paintings (such as the one displayed to the right), ivory carvings, and clay busts, indicating it had protruding ears, tufted tails, perhaps faint tiger-like stripes, and that at least some males had a ruff or primitive mane around their necks. With this example being a hunting scene it is likely that it depicts females hunting for the pride using the same strategy as their contemporary relatives and males may not be part of the subject. 
* ''P. l. vereshchagini'', known as the East Siberian- or Beringian cave lion, was found in Yakutia (Russia), Alaska (USA), and the Yukon Territory (Canada). Analysis of skulls and mandibles of this lion demonstrate that it is distinctly—larger than the European cave lion and smaller than the American cave lion with differing skull proportions.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8a091d9b246841da6e11809ff75e0906" name="Lascaux-diverticule-félins" sectnum="2.1.2#1">../img/8a091d9b246841da6e11809ff75e0906.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>