<document id="6162ee68a7a60104b110db6e3735ca19-3" name="Adore_(album)" cat="20">
<text>
The year prior to the album's release was marked by confusing and conflicting statements made by the band and its management in promotion of the album.  Amid the release of the heavy-metal-guitar-and-electronic music-driven "The End is the Beginning is the End" in summer 1997, Corgan remarked that the sound is "probably like what you would expect from us in the future.""."  Mtv Online.  Retrieved on 2007/09/23.  A few months later, the band's management said the album would be all-acoustic.  Later that month, Corgan nuanced that assessment, calling the album "electric folk." "."  MTV Online.  1997/09/29.  Retrieved on 2007/09/23.  In January 1998, Corgan described the new album as "arcane night music." Corgan later clarified:
The people that say it's acoustic will be wrong. The people that say it's electronic will be wrong. The people that say it's a Pumpkins' record will be wrong. I will try to make something that is indescribable.

In early 1998, Corgan debuted ten new songs in a short set at Johnny Depp's Viper Room in L.A.; only two, "Blissed and Gone" and "Let Me Give the World to You", were not released on the final album. Iha also played a short set of songs from his new solo album, ''Let It Come Down''.

The band headed to London to film a video for the album's first single "Ava Adore". Their highest budgeted video yet, "Ava Adore" featured a large cast of extras and was filmed in one continuous shot. The three Pumpkins showed off a new image adopted for the new album—an almost Gothic look, featuring elegant robes and make-up. While in Europe, The Smashing Pumpkins began their tour for ''Adore'' just before the album's release with a performance on BBC's ''Later with Jools Holland''.

''Adore'' was released to most of the world on June 1, 1998 and in the U.S. on June 2. The video for "Perfect" was shot in Los Angeles in July 1998. Ultimately, "Perfect" was not quite as strong as the lead single, "Ava Adore", and the success of the album lagged. Corgan would later attribute the album's commercial failure to the confused promotion.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f5abca882cb530f1e7349e4be7d9c559" name="Smashing_pumpkins_1998_promo" sectnum="3#1">../img/f5abca882cb530f1e7349e4be7d9c559.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>