<document id="6188d59e537ed86d9e2b0199c6abbd72-3" name="Ring-tailed_Lemur" cat="3">
<text>
An adult Ring-tailed Lemur may reach a body length between  and a weight between .Mittermeier, pp. 246&ndash;249  The species has a slender frame and narrow face, reminiscent of a vulpine muzzle. Like all lemurs, its hind limbs are longer than its forelimbs. Females have two pairs of mammary glands, but only one pair is functional.

Furless scent glands are present on both males and females. Both genders have apocrine and sebaceous glands in their genital regions, as well as antebrachial glands located on the inner surface of the forearm in proximity of the wrist. However, only the male has a horny spur that overlays this scent gland.  The males also have brachial glands on the axillary surface of their shoulders.

The Ring-tailed Lemur's trademark, a long, bushy tail, is ringed in alternating black and white transverse stripes, numbering 13 to 15 each for both colors, and always ending in a black tip. Its tail is longer than its body, measuring up to  in length. The tail is not prehensile and is only used for balance, communication, and group cohesion.

The pelage, or fur, is dense. The ventral (chest) coat and throat are white or cream, and the dorsal (back) coat is gray to rosy-brown. The crown is dark gray, while the ears and cheeks are white. The muzzle is dark grayish and the nose is black, and the eyes are encompassed by black lozenge-shaped patches.

The black skin is visible on the nose, genitalia, and the palms and soles of the limbs. The Ring-tailed Lemur shares several adaptations with other lemurs.  Its fingers are slender, padded, and semi-dexterous with flat, human-like nails. It grooms orally by licking and tooth-scraping with narrow, procumbent lower incisors and canines, called a toothcomb. Lastly, it has a toilet-claw (sometimes referred to as a ''grooming claw'') on the second toe of each hind limb specialized for personal grooming, specifically to rake through fur that is unreachable by the mouth and toothcomb.

The species' eyes can be a bright yellow or orange. Unlike most diurnal primates, but like all strepsirhine primates, the Ring-tailed Lemur has a tapetum lucidum, or reflective layer behind the retina of the eye, that enhances night vision.


Image:Lemur catta brachial glands.jpg|A male's brachial glands on the upper chest near the axilla
Image:Lemur catta spur and antebrachial gland.jpg|Spur and antebrachial gland on the forearm of a male
Image:Lemur catta toilet claw.jpg|Toilet-claw on the second toe, contrasted with the nail on the third toe
Image:Lemur catta toothcomb.jpg|Front, lower dentition includes a toothcomb
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3fd79f147ee246ca253904b054bc35eb" name="Ringtailed_lemur_tail" sectnum="3#1">../img/3fd79f147ee246ca253904b054bc35eb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>