<document id="6188d59e537ed86d9e2b0199c6abbd72-5.6" name="Ring-tailed_Lemur" cat="3">
<text>
The Ring-tailed Lemur is polygynous, although the dominant male in the troop typically breeds with more females than other males. Fighting is most common during the breeding season. A receptive female may initiate mating by presenting her backside, lifting her tail and looking at the desired male over her shoulder. Males may inspect the female's genitals to determine receptiveness. Females typically mate within their troop, but may seek outside males.


The breeding season runs from mid-April to mid-May. Estrus lasts 4 to 6 hours, and females mate with multiple males during this period.  Within a troop, females stagger their receptivity so that each female comes into season on a different day during the breeding season, reducing competition for male attention. Gestation lasts for about 135 days, and parturition occurs in September or occasionally October. In the wild one offspring is the norm, although twins may occur. Ring-tailed Lemur infants have a birth weight of  and are carried ventrally (on the chest) for the first 1 to 2 weeks, then dorsally (on the back).

The young lemurs begin to eat solid food after two months and are fully weaned after five months. Sexual maturity is reached between 2.5 and 3 years. Male involvement in infant rearing is limited, although the entire troop, regardless of age or sex, can be seen caring for the young. Alloparenting between troop females has been reported. Kidnapping by females and infanticide by males also occur occasionally. Due to harsh environmental conditions, predation and accidents such as falls infant mortality can be as high as 50% within the first year and as few as 30% may reach adulthood.  The Ring-tailed Lemur can go on to live 16 to 19 years (27 years in captivity).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a9290ca28eee2ca56fd8770af8f92f02" name="Ring_tailed_lemur_and_twins" sectnum="5.6#1">../img/a9290ca28eee2ca56fd8770af8f92f02.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>