<document id="61d1d2284cc0949e7fb2b4cce6ac6203-6" name="Rhys_ap_Gruffydd" cat="25">
<text>
Rhys had at least nine sons and eight daughters.Moore p.102 Confusingly, three of the sons were named Maredudd and two of the daughters were named Gwenllian. Gruffydd ap Rhys (died 1201) was the eldest legitimate son and was nominated by Rhys as his successor. He married Matilda de Braose.Turvey p. 79 Maelgwn ap Rhys (died 1231), who was the eldest son but illegitimate, refused to accept Gruffydd as his father's successor. A bitter feud developed between the two, with several of Rhys's other sons becoming involved. Rhys Gryg (died 1233) married Joan de Clare Jones p. 38 and eventually became the main power in Deheubarth, but never ruled more than a portion of his father's realm and was a client prince of Llywelyn the Great of Gwynedd.

Hywel ap Rhys (died 1231) spent many years as a hostage at the court of Henry II and on his return became known as ''Hywel Sais'' (Hywel the Saxon, i.e. Englishman). Maredudd ap Rhys (died 1239) was also given as a hostage, but was less fortunate than Hywel. He was blinded by King Henry after the failure of the invasion of Wales in 1165, and became known as ''Maredudd Ddall'' (Maredudd the Blind). He ended his days as a monk at Whitland Abbey. Another Maredudd (died 1227) became Archdeacon of Cardigan.

His daughter Gwenllian ferch Rhys married Rhodri ab Owain, prince of the western part of Gwynedd. Another Gwenllian (died 1236) married Ednyfed Fychan, seneschal of Gwynedd under Llywelyn the Great, and through her Rhys became an ancestor of the Tudor dynasty. When Henry Tudor landed in Pembrokeshire in 1485 to make a bid for the throne, his descent from Rhys was one of the factors which enabled him to attract Welsh support.Rees, D. pp. 38-9. Sir Rhys ap Thomas of Dinefwr, who was Henry's most prominent supporter in Wales, was also a descendant of Rhys. Angharad ferch Rhys married William FitzMartin, lord of Cemais. Other daughters married the Welsh rulers of Gwrtheyrnion and Elfael.Turvey p. 80
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e2927bae885e9bc0cf2654329bcbf00c" name="DSCN4297-strata-florida-arch" sectnum="6#1">../img/e2927bae885e9bc0cf2654329bcbf00c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>