<document id="61d21377b86d391a3c1cdb00c5a1f0c9-3.1" name="Lambeosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
Although the early workers in Alberta did not recognize it at the time, they were finding the remains of juvenile ''Lambeosaurus'' as well.  These fossils of small-bodied crested duckbills were interpreted as adults of a distinct lineage of hadrosaurids, the subfamily Cheneosaurinae.Lull, Richard Swann; and Wright, Nelda E. (1942). ''Hadrosaurian Dinosaurs of North America''. 178–187. The first such animal to be named was ''Didanodon altidens'', a left upper jaw (GSC 1092) from the Dinosaur Park Formation described by Henry Fairfield Osborn in 1902. It was referred to as ''Trachodon''  ''altidens'' by Lambe, and the name ''Didanodon'' seems to have rapidly fallen into obscurity, as it is not mentioned in Richard Swann Lull and Nelda Wright's influential 1942 monograph on North American hadrosaurids.
 
In 1920, William Diller Matthew used the name ''Procheneosaurus'' (no species name) in a caption for a photograph of a skeleton at the American Museum of Natural History, from the Dinosaur Park Formation (AMNH 5340). Parks believed that the procedure and description were inadequate for the name to be considered valid, and to address the situation, he coined the genus ''Tetragonosaurus''.  Into this genus he placed the type species ''T. praeceps'' (based on ROM 3577) and a second species ''T. erectofrons'' (based on ROM 3578) for small skulls from the Dinosaur Park Formation, and assigned Matthew's ''Procheneosaurus'' skeleton to ''T. praeceps''. Charles M. Sternberg followed in 1935 by adding the slightly larger ''T. cranibrevis'', based on GSC (now NMC) 8633. The use of ''Tetragonosaurus'' was rejected by Lull in favor of ''Procheneosaurus''. In 1942 he and Wright transferred the ''Tetragonosaurus'' species and, tentatively, ''Trachodon'' ''altidens'', to ''Procheneosaurus'', with ''P. praeceps'' serving as the type species.Lull, Richard Swann;  and Wright, Nelda E. (1942). ''Hadrosaurian Dinosaurs of North America''. 1–242  This usage was generally followed until 1975, when Peter Dodson showed that the "cheneosaurs" were actually juveniles of other dinosaurs. ''Procheneosaurus praeceps'' and ''altidens'' are considered probable synonyms of ''Lambeosaurus lambei'', although both predate that name.

The "procheneosaurs" weren't the only crested duckbills being studied and named in the early 1900s.  It was then the accepted practice to name genera and species for what is now seen as more likely individual variation, variation due to age or sex, or distortion from fossilization.  Three more species were named during this period that relate to ''Lambeosaurus'', all in 1935. Sternberg, in the same paper as ''T. cranibrevis'', named a skull and partial skeleton (GSC—now NMC—8705) ''L. magnicristatum'' (corrected to ''magnicristatus''), and a smaller skull (GSC—now NMC—8703) ''L. clavinitialis'', with a less prominent crest and reduced spine pointing from the back. Parks contributed ''Corythosaurus frontalis'', based on skull GSC 5853 (now ROM 869), which differed from the well-known tall, straight, rounded crest of other specimens of ''Corythosaurus'' by having a low crest cocked forward.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b1c1d082ee31c61084c53cfff1741171" name="Procheneosaurus" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/b1c1d082ee31c61084c53cfff1741171.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>