<document id="61d21377b86d391a3c1cdb00c5a1f0c9-3.2" name="Lambeosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
New specimens were not described for many years following the activity of the early 1900s.  In 1964 John Ostrom noted that an old species named by Othniel Charles Marsh, ''Hadrosaurus paucidens'', based on USNM 5457, a partial maxilla and squamosal from the Judith River Formation of Fergus County, Montana, was probably a specimen of ''Lambeosaurus''.  

In 1975, Peter Dodson, examining why there should be so many species and genera of lambeosaurine duckbills within such a short geological time frame and small area, published the results of a morphometric study in which he measured dozens of skulls.  He found that many of the species had been based on remains that were better interpreted as juveniles or different sexes. For ''Lambeosaurus'', he found that ''L. clavinitialis'' was probably the female of ''L. lambei'', and ''Corythosaurus frontalis'' and ''Procheneosaurus praeceps'' were probably its juveniles.  ''L. magnicristatus'' was different enough to warrant its own species.  He interpreted ''Procheneosaurus cranibrevis'' and ''P. erectofrons'' as juvenile corythosaurs. However, restudy of the ''Procheneosaurus''/''Tetragonosaurus'' remains indicates that within species, assignments had become confused, and the type specimen of ''P. cranibrevis'' was a ''Lambeosaurus'' juvenile, whereas others were ''Corythosaurus'', based on the distinctive form of the contact of the nasal bone with the premaxilla.  

Also during the 1970s, Bill Morris was studying giant lambeosaurine remains from Baja California.  He named them ?''L. laticaudus'' in 1981 (type specimen LACM 17715).  Morris used a question mark in his work because no complete crest had been found for his species, and without it a definitive assignment could not be made.  From what was known of the skull, he considered it to be most like ''Lambeosaurus''. He interpreted this species as water-bound, due to features like its size, its tall and narrow tail (interpreted as a swimming adaptation), and weak hip articulations, as well as a healed broken thigh bone that he thought would have been too much of a handicap for a terrestrial animal to have survived long enough to heal.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a7fdb243026b5090f551f17a6500db96" name="Lambeosaurus_laticaud1DB" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/a7fdb243026b5090f551f17a6500db96.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>