<document id="61d21377b86d391a3c1cdb00c5a1f0c9-4" name="Lambeosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
Two species of ''Lambeosaurus'' are currently confirmed valid, with a third widely accepted and a fourth sometimes accepted.  ''L. lambei'' Parks, 1923 is known from at least 17 individuals, with seven skulls and partial skeletons and around ten isolated skulls.  ''L. clavinitialis'' C.M. Sternberg, 1935, ''Corythosaurus frontalis'' Parks, 1935, and ''Procheneosaurus praeceps'' Parks, 1931 are all regarded as synonyms of ''L. lambei'' in the most recent review. It is possible that ''L. clavinitialis'' skulls without the backward spine may represent ''L. magnicristatus'' individuals instead, although this was rejected in the 2007 redescription of ''L. magnicristatus''. ''L. magnicristatus'' C.M. Sternberg, 1935 is only definitely known from two specimens, both with skulls. Unfortunately, the majority of the articulated skeleton of the type specimen has been lost. Many of the bones were extensively damaged by water while in storage and were discarded before description; other portions of this skeleton have also been lost. Its remains come from slightly younger rocks than ''L. lambei''. The specific name is derived from the Latin ''magnus'' "large" and ''cristatus'' "crested", referring to its bony crest. Additionally, Jack Horner has identified fragmentary lambeosaurine jaws from the Bearpaw Formation of Montana as possibly belonging to ''L. magnicristatus''; these represent the first lambeosaurine remains from marine rocks. The large ''L. laticaudus'' Morris, 1981, known from disassociated remains from several individuals, is accepted as a potential species as well, although it could instead be a species of ''Hypacrosaurus''. Its validity has been questioned by the describers of ''Velafrons'', who find its remains to be nondiagnostic but distinct from their genus. The specific name here is derived from the Latin ''latus'' "broad" and ''cauda'' "tail". 

''L. paucidens'' (Marsh, 1889) is regarded as a dubious name and is listed as ''Hadrosaurus paucidens'' in the latest review, although at least one author, Donald F. Glut, accepts it as a species of ''Lambeosaurus''. In this case, the specific epithet is derived from the Latin ''pauci-'' "few" and ''dens'' "tooth". The irregularities of ''Procheneosaurus cranibrevis'', and the identity of the type as a juvenile lambeosaur, were recognized in 2005, and thus have not yet entered wide circulation.  Finally, ''Didanodon'' and ''Trachodon altidens'' have received confusing treatment in the most recent review: ''Didanodon'' was assigned without comment to ''Lambeosaurus'', yet the species ''Trachodon altidens'' was listed separately in a table of dubious names.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8ab2163c88600a16798450340e347bc1" name="Lambeosaurus_lambei_BW" sectnum="4#1">../img/8ab2163c88600a16798450340e347bc1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>