<document id="61e3986e60baed5fa928d42136ff3386-1.2" name="Book_of_Kells" cat="17">
<text>
Kells Abbey was plundered and pillaged by Vikings many times in the 10th century, and how the book survived there is not knownSir Edward Sullivan, p.4. Book of Kells 1920. The earliest historical reference to the book, and indeed to the book's presence at Kells, can be found in a 1007 entry in the Annals of Ulster. This entry records that "the great Gospel of Columkille, (Columba)Columkille is the name by which St. Columba is best known in Ireland.  the chief relic of the Western World, was wickedly stolen during the night from the western sacristy of the great stone church at Cenannas on account of its wrought shrine". The manuscript was recovered a few months later—minus its golden and bejewelled cover—"under a sod".O'Donovan, John. "". University College Cork. Retrieved on 29 February 2008. It is generally assumed that the "great Gospel of Columkille" is the Book of Kells. If this is correct, then the book was in Kells by 1007 and had been there long enough for thieves to learn of its presence. The force of ripping the manuscript free from its cover may account for the folios missing from the beginning and end of the Book of Kells. The description in the Annals of the book as "of Columkille" - that is, having belonged to, and perhaps being made by Columba - suggests that the book was believed at that time to have been made on Iona.Dodwell, p. 84. As mentioned above, Columba in fact lived before any plausible date for the manuscript. 

Regardless, the book was certainly at Kells in the 12th century, when land charters pertaining to the Abbey of Kells were copied onto some of its blank pages. The practice of copying of charters into important books was widespread in the mediaeval period, and such inscriptions in the Book of Kells provide concrete evidence about its location at the time.

The Abbey of Kells was dissolved due to the ecclesiastical reforms of the 12th century. The abbey church was converted to a parish church in which the Book of Kells remained.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2bbcea4cfa9591540d9af5b0fe7a13e6" name="KellsFol027v4Evang" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/2bbcea4cfa9591540d9af5b0fe7a13e6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>