<document id="62b2e4ed392cf817f1f7f1b75c2be0a5-6" name="George_IV_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
On George's death ''The Times'' commented:


During the political crisis caused by Catholic emancipation, the Duke of Wellington said that George was "the worst man he ever fell in with his whole life, the most selfish, the most false, the most ill-natured, the most entirely without one redeeming quality",Hibbert, ''George IV: Regent and King 1811–1830'', p.310 but his eulogy delivered in the House of Lords called George "the most accomplished man of his age" and praised his knowledge and talent.Hibbert, ''George IV: Regent and King 1811–1830'', p.344 Wellington's true feelings probably lie somewhere between these two extremes; as he said later, George was "a magnificent patron of the arts ... the most extraordinary compound of talent, wit, buffoonery, obstinacy, and good feeling—in short a medley of the most opposite qualities, with a great preponderence of good—that I ever saw in any character in my life."


George IV was described as the "First Gentleman of England" on account of his style and manners.''The Diary of Prince Pückler-Muskau'' (May 1828). Quoted in Parissien, p.420 Certainly, he possessed many good qualities; he was bright, clever, and knowledgeable. However, his laziness and gluttony led him to squander much of his talent. As ''The Times'' once wrote, he would always prefer "a girl and a bottle to politics and a sermon."

There are many statues of George IV, a large number of which were erected during his reign. In the United Kingdom, they include a bronze statue of him on horseback by Sir Francis Chantry in Trafalgar Square and another outside the Royal Pavilion in Brighton.

In Edinburgh, ''George IV Bridge'' is a main street linking the Old Town ''High Street'' to the south over the ravine of the ''Cowgate'', designed by the architect Thomas Hamilton in 1829 and completed in 1835. King's Cross, now a major transport hub sitting on the border of Camden and Islington in north London, takes its name from a short-lived monument erected to George IV in the early 1830s.

The Regency period saw a shift in fashion that was largely determined by George. After political opponents put a tax on wig powder, he abandoned wearing a powdered wig in favour of natural hair.Parissien, p.112 He wore darker colours than had been previously fashionable as they helped to disguise his size, favoured pantaloons and trousers over knee breeches because they were looser, and popularised a high collar with neck cloth because it hid his double chin.Parissien, p.114 His visit to Scotland in 1822 led to the revival, if not the creation, of Scottish tartan dress as it is known today.Parissien, pp.324–6
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3db298a75dd47b07d586975521b13568" name="a-voluptuary" sectnum="6#1">../img/3db298a75dd47b07d586975521b13568.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>