<document id="63173262bb4c8f4d7d52cd89d35519bf-4.5" name="Emu" cat="3">
<text>
The Emu was an important source of meat to the Aborigines in the areas to which it was endemic. Emu fat was used as bush medicine, and was rubbed on the skin. It also served as a valuable lubricant. It was mixed with ochre to make the traditional paint for ceremonial body adornment, as well as to oil wooden tools and utensils such as the coolamon.

An example of how the Emu was cooked comes from the Arrernte of Central Australia who call it ''Kere ankerre'':




Commercial Emu farming started in Western Australia in 1987 and the first slaughtering occurred in 1990.O'Malley, P. 1997.  in ''The New Rural Industries''. Rural Industries Research & Development Corporation In Australia, the commercial industry is based on stock bred in captivity and all states except Tasmania have licensing requirements to protect wild Emus. Outside Australia, Emus are farmed on a large scale in North America, with about 1 million birds in the US,USDA.  Peru, and China, and to a lesser extent in some other countries. Emus breed well in captivity, and are kept in large open pens to avoid leg and digestive problems that arise with inactivity. They are typically fed on grain supplemented by grazing, and are slaughtered at 50&ndash;70 weeks of age. They eat two times a day and prefer  of leaves each meal.

Emus are farmed primarily for their meat, leather, and oil. Emu meat is a low-fat meat (less than 1.5% fat), and with cholesterol at 85 mg/100 g, it is comparable to other lean meats. Most of the usable portions (the best cuts come from the thigh and the larger muscles of the drum or lower leg) are, like other poultry, dark meat; Emu meat is considered for cooking purposes by the USDA to be a red meat because its red colour and pH value approximate that of beef,USDA. 2005. USDA National Nutrient Database for Standard Reference, Release 18  but for inspection purposes it is considered poultry.
Emu fat is rendered to produce oil for cosmetics, dietary supplements, and therapeutic products. There is some evidence that the oil has anti-inflammatory properties;Yoganathan, S. et al. 2003. Antagonism of croton oil inflammation by topical Emu oil in CD-1 mice. ''Lipids'' 38:603–07. PMID 12934669 however, the US Food and Drug Administration regards pure Emu oil product as an unapproved drug. Emu leather has a distinctive patterned surface, due to a raised area around the feather follicles in the skin; the leather is used in such small items as wallets and shoes, often in combination with other leathers. The feathers and eggs are used in decorative arts and crafts.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8f933bf296a233595d1cf84c58e2925a" name="Feeding_farmed_Emu" sectnum="4.5#1">../img/8f933bf296a233595d1cf84c58e2925a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>