<document id="639fa6d9cab3927d8426f4c1149f8925-4" name="Christ_Illusion" cat="20">
<text>
Several aspects of ''Christ Illusion'''s content and promotion generated adverse attention and publicity. In particular the cover art, painted by Larry Carroll and depicting a mutilated, stoned Jesus. Carroll, who had painted the cover artwork to previous Slayer albums such as ''Reign in Blood'', ''South of Heaven'' and ''Seasons in the Abyss'', resumed duties on ''Christ Illusion''. Working solely from track names and formative lyrics, Carroll produced the original on a 4-by-4-foot slab of wood using a combination of mediums. Having requested an image of Christ in "a sea of despair", King commented that an early version seemed as though Christ was "chilling out in the water". The final image portrays Christ with a missing eye and amputated hands, and standing amidst a sea of blood and severed heads. Araya deemed this version "much better because he looked like a drug addict!", while King admired the artwork enough to purchase the original. Certain album pre-orders gave fans the chance to win one of ten autographed lithographs of the artwork, while an alternative, non-graphic cover was made to appease retailers who had refused to stock the original version. 

''World Entertainment News Network'' reported Slayer were attracting controversy through issuing the artwork. Joseph Dias, general secretary of the Mumbai Christian group ''Catholic Secular Forum'', (''CSF'') took "strong exception" to the original album artwork, and issued a memorandum to Mumbai's police commissioner in protest. Chris Steffen of ''Rolling Stone'' magazine commented that "The album art takes it all over the top with an image axeman Kerry King dubs 'Christ in a Sea of Despair'", while ''KNAC.com'''s Peter Atkinson deemed the artwork "defiantly sacrilegious".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="326723afd7cfe289f450bde7585de6c9" name="Christ_Illusion_Alternate_Cover" sectnum="4#1">../img/326723afd7cfe289f450bde7585de6c9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>