<document id="63db44496d352f4b59a88542e7fd2498-1.2" name="Noël_Coward" cat="17">
<text>
In 1920, at the age of 20, Coward starred in his own play, the light comedy ''I'll Leave It to You''. After a tryout in Manchester, it opened in London at the New Theatre (renamed the Noël Coward Theatre in 2006), his first full-length play in the West End.Thaxter, John.  British Theatre Guide, 2009  Neville Cardus's praise in ''The Manchester Guardian'' was grudging.Cardus, Neville. "Gaiety Theatre", ''The Manchester Guardian'', 4 May 1920, p. 13 Notices for the London production were mixed, but encouraging. ''The Observer'' commented, "Mr Coward... has a sense of comedy, and if he can overcome a tendency to smartness, he will probably produce a good play one of these days."Ervine, St John. "At the Play", ''The Observer'', 25 July 1920, p. 9 ''The Times'', on the other hand, was enthusiastic: "It is a remarkable piece of work from so young a head – spontaneous, light, and always 'brainy'.""I'll Leave It to You", ''The Times'', 22 July 1920, p. 10

 
The play ran for a month (and was Coward's first play seen in America), after which Coward returned to acting in works by other writers, starring as Ralph in ''The Knight of the Burning Pestle'' in Birmingham and then London.Coward (''Present Indicative''), pp. 104–05 and 112 He did not enjoy the role, finding Francis Beaumont and his sometime collaborator John Fletcher "two of the dullest Elizabethan writers ever known ... I had a very, very long part, but I was very, very bad at it".Castle, p. 38 Nevertheless, ''The Manchester Guardian'' thought that Coward got the best out of the role,"The Knight of the Burning Pestle", ''The Manchester Guardian'', 25 November 1920, p. 14 and ''The Times'' called the play "the jolliest thing in London"."A Jacobean Romp", ''The Times'', 25 November 1920, p. 10

Coward completed a one-act satire, ''The Better Half'', about a man's relationship with two women. It had a short run at The Little Theatre, London, in 1922. The critic St. John Ervine wrote of the piece, "When Mr Coward has learned that tea-table chitter-chatter had better remain the prerogative of women he will write more interesting plays than he now seems likely to write."Ervine, St John. "New Grand Guignol Series", ''The Observer'', 4 June 1922, p. 9 The play was thought to be lost until a typescript was found in 2007 in the archive of the Lord Chamberlain's Office, the official censor of stage plays in the UK until 1968.Thorpe, Vanessa.  ''The Observer'', 16 September 2007, accessed 16 September 2007

In 1921 Coward made his first trip to America, hoping to interest producers there in his plays. Although he had little luck, he found the Broadway theatre stimulating. He absorbed its smartness and pace into his own work, which brought him his first real success as a playwright with ''The Young Idea''. The play opened in London in 1923, after a provincial tour, with Coward in one of the leading roles.Hoare, pp. 89–91 The reviews were good: "Mr Noël Coward calls his brilliant little farce a 'comedy of youth', and so it is. And youth pervaded the Savoy last night, applauding everything so boisterously that you felt, not without exhilaration, that you were in the midst of a 'rag'.""New Play at the Savoy", ''The Times'', 2 February 1923, p. 8 One critic, who noted the influence of George Bernard Shaw on Coward's writing, thought more highly of the play than of Coward's newly found fans: "I was unfortunately wedged in the centre of a group of his more exuberant friends who greeted each of his sallies with 'That's a Noëlism!'""The Young Idea", ''The Observer'', 4 February 1923, p. 11. Coward himself acknowledged that Shaw's ''You Never Can Tell'' was the primary inspiration for ''The Young Idea'': see Coward (''Present Indicative''), p. 114 The play ran in London from 1 February to 24 March 1923, after which Coward turned to revue, co-writing and performing in André Charlot's ''London Calling!''Coward (''Present Indicative''), pp. 112 and 150



In 1924, Coward achieved his first great critical and financial success as a playwright with ''The Vortex.'' The story is about a nymphomaniac socialite and her cocaine-addicted son (played by Coward). Some saw the drugs as a mask for homosexuality,Hoare, p. 129 while Kenneth Tynan later described it as "a jeremiad against narcotics with dialogue that sounds today not so much stilted as high-heeled".Tynan, pp. 286–88 ''The Vortex'' was considered shocking in its day for its depiction of sexual vanity and drug abuse among the upper classes. Its notoriety and fiery performances attracted large audiences, justifying a move from a small suburban theatre to a larger one in the West End.Coward (''Present Indicative''), pp. 182–85 Coward, still having trouble finding producers, raised the money to produce the play himself. During the run of ''The Vortex'', Coward met Jack Wilson, an American stockbroker (later a director and producer), who became his business manager and lover. Wilson used his position to steal from Coward, but the playwright was in love and accepted both the larceny and Wilson's heavy drinking.Kenrick, John.  Coward 101 at ''Musicals 101: The Cyber Encyclopedia of Musical Theatre, TV and Film'', 2000, accessed 9 March 2009

The success of ''The Vortex'' in both London and America caused a great demand for new Coward plays. In 1925 he premiered ''Fallen Angels'', a three-act comedy that amused and shocked audiences with the spectacle of two middle-aged women slowly getting drunk while awaiting the arrival of their mutual lover."Fallen Angels", ''The Manchester Guardian'', 23 April 1925, p. 12 ''Hay Fever'', the first of Coward's plays to gain an enduring place in the mainstream theatrical repertoire, also appeared in 1925. It is a comedy about four egocentric members of an artistic family who casually invite acquaintances to their country house for the weekend and bemuse and enrage each other's guests. Some writers have seen elements of Coward's old mentor, Mrs Astley Cooper, and her set in the characters of the family.Hoare, pp. 42–43 By the 1970s the play was recognised as a classic, described in ''The Times'' as a "dazzling achievement; like ''The Importance of Being Earnest'', it is pure comedy with no mission but to delight, and it depends purely on the interplay of characters, not on elaborate comic machinery." By June 1925 Coward had four shows running in the West End: ''The Vortex'', ''Fallen Angels'', ''Hay Fever'' and ''On With the Dance''.Morley, p. 107 Coward was turning out numerous plays and acting in his own works and others'. Soon, his frantic pace caught up with him, and he collapsed on stage in 1926 while starring in ''The Constant Nymph'' and had to take an extended rest in Hawaii.

Other Coward works produced in the mid-to-late 1920s included the plays ''Easy Virtue'' (1926), a drama about a divorcée's clash with her snobbish in-laws; ''The Queen Was in the Parlour'', a Ruritanian romance; ''This Was a Man'' (1926), a comedy about adulterous aristocrats; ''The Marquise'' (1927), an eighteenth-century costume drama; ''Home Chat'' (1927), a comedy about a married woman's fidelity; and the revues ''On With the Dance'' (1925) and ''This Year of Grace'' (1928). None of these shows has entered the regular repertoire, but the last introduced one of Coward's best-known songs, "A Room with a View". Noël Coward Music Index, accessed 9 March 2009 His biggest failure in this period was the play ''Sirocco'' (1927), which concerns free love among the wealthy. It starred Ivor Novello, of whom Coward said, "the two most beautiful things in the world are Ivor's profile and my mind".Richards, p. 56 Theatregoers hated the play, showing violent disapproval at the curtain calls and spitting at Coward as he left the theatre. Coward later said of this flop, "My first instinct was to leave England immediately, but this seemed too craven a move, and also too gratifying to my enemies, whose numbers had by then swollen in our minds to practically the entire population of the British Isles."Richards, p. 26

By then one of the world's highest-earning writers, with an annual income in 1929 of £50,000,More than £2,000,000 in terms of 2007 values: see  Measuring Worth website, accessed 10 March 2009 Coward thrived during the Great Depression, writing a succession of popular hits.Lahr, p. 93 These ranged from large-scale spectaculars to intimate comedies. Examples of the former were the operetta ''Bitter Sweet'' (1929), about a woman who elopes with her music teacher, and the historical extravaganza ''Cavalcade'' (1931) at Drury Lane, about thirty years in the lives of two families, which required a huge cast, gargantuan sets and a complex hydraulic stage. Its 1933 film adaptation won the Academy Award for best picture. Coward's intimate-scale hits of the period included ''Private Lives'' (1930) and ''Design for Living'' (1932). In ''Private Lives'', Coward starred alongside his most famous stage partner, Gertrude Lawrence, together with the young Laurence Olivier. It was a highlight of both Coward's and Lawrence's career, selling out in both London and New York. Coward disliked long runs, and after this he made a rule of starring in a play for no more than three months at any venue. ''Design for Living,'' written for Alfred Lunt and Lynn Fontanne, was so risqué, with its theme of bisexuality and a ''ménage à trois'', that Coward premiered it in New York, knowing that it would not survive the censor in London.Hoare, p. 249

In 1933, Coward wrote, directed and co-starred with French singer Yvonne Printemps in both London and New York productions of an operetta, ''Conversation Piece'' (1933). Coward next wrote, directed and co-starred with Lawrence in ''Tonight at 8:30'' (1936), a cycle of ten short plays that were shuffled to make a different playbill of three plays each night. One of these plays, ''Still Life'', was expanded into the 1945 David Lean film ''Brief Encounter''.Morley, pp. 226–28 and 230 ''Tonight at 8:30'' was followed by a musical, ''Operette'' (1937), from which the most famous number is "The Stately Homes of England", and a revue entitled ''Set to Music'' (1938, a Broadway version of his 1932 London revue, ''Words and Music'').Morley, pp. 237 and 239

Coward's last pre-war plays were ''This Happy Breed'', a drama about a working-class family, and ''Present Laughter'', a comic self-caricature with an egomaniac actor as the central character. These were first performed in 1942, although they were both written in 1939.Lahr, pp. 32 and 93

Between 1929 and 1936 Coward recorded many of his best-known songs for His Master's Voice (HMV), now reissued on CD, including the romantic "I'll See You Again" from ''Bitter Sweet'', the comic "Mad Dogs and Englishmen" from ''Words and Music'', and "Mrs Worthington".Naxos CDs 8.120559 and 8.120623
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ed665a3eecd1542f2d798d9124325b94" name="Coward_pestle" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/ed665a3eecd1542f2d798d9124325b94.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>