<document id="63db44496d352f4b59a88542e7fd2498-1.1" name="Noël_Coward" cat="17">
<text>
Coward was born in 1899 in Teddington, England, a suburb of London. His parents were Arthur Sabin Coward (1856–1937), a piano salesman, and Violet Agnes Coward (1863–1954), daughter of Henry Gordon Veitch, a captain and surveyor in the Royal Navy.Morley, p. 2 Noël Coward was the second of their three sons, the eldest of whom had died in 1898 at the age of six.Morley, p. 3 Coward's father lacked drive, and family finances were often poor. Coward was bitten by the performing bug early and appeared in amateur concerts by the age of seven. He attended the Chapel Royal Choir School as a young child. He had little formal schooling but was a voracious reader.Kenrick, John.  Coward 101 at ''Musicals 101: The Cyber Encyclopedia of Musical Theatre, TV and Film'', 2000, accessed 9 March 2009

Encouraged by his ambitious mother, who sent him to a dance academy in London,Hoare, p. 19 Coward's first professional engagement was in January 1911 as Prince Mussel in the children's play ''The Goldfish''."The Little Theatre", ''The Times'', 28 January 1911, p. 12 In ''Present Indicative'', his first volume of memoirs, Coward wrote:




The leading actor-manager Charles Hawtrey, whom the young Coward idolised and from whom he learned a great deal about the theatre, cast him in the children's play ''Where the Rainbow Ends''. Coward played in the piece in 1911 and 1912 at the Garrick Theatre in London's West End.Hoare, pp. 23–26"Garrick Theatre", ''The Times'', 12 December 1912, p. 8 In 1912 Coward also appeared at the Savoy Theatre in ''An Autumn Idyll'' (as a dancer in the ballet) and at the London Coliseum in ''A Little Fowl Play'', by Harold Owen, in which Hawtrey starred."The Savoy Theatre", ''The Times'', 26 June 1912, p. 10; "The Coliseum", 29 October 1912, p. 8; and "Varieties etc", 18 November 1912, p. 1 Italia Conti engaged Coward to appear at the Liverpool Repertory Theatre in 1913, and in the same year he was cast as the Lost Boy Slightly in ''Peter Pan''."The Cult of Peter Pan", ''The Times'', 24 December 1913, p. 8 He reappeared in ''Peter Pan'' the following year, and in 1915 he was again in ''Where the Rainbow Ends''."Fairies at the Garrick", ''The Times'', 28 December 1915, p. 10 He worked with other child actors in this period, including Hermione Gingold (whose mother threatened to turn "that naughty boy" out);Castle, p. 12 Fabia Drake; Esmé Wynne, with whom he collaborated on his earliest plays; Alfred Willmore, later known as Micheál MacLíammóir; and Gertrude Lawrence who, Coward wrote in his memoirs, "gave me an orange and told me a few mildly dirty stories, and I loved her from then onwards."Hoare, pp. 27, 30 and 51"The Happy Family", ''The Times'', 19 December 1916, p. 11

In 1913, when Coward was 14, he became the protégé and probably the lover of Philip Streatfeild, a society painter.Hoare, pp. 33–34 Streatfeild introduced him to Mrs Astley Cooper and her high society friends.Evangeline Julia Marshall, eccentric society hostess (1854–1944), married Clement Paston Astley Cooper, grandson of Sir Astley Paston Cooper, on 10 July 1877. She inherited Hambleton Hall from her brother Walter Marshall (d. 1899), and there she entertained rising talents in the artistic world, including the painter Philip Streatfeild, the conductor Malcolm Sargent and the writer Charles Scott Moncrieff, as well as the young Coward. See Callow, Simon.  ''Guardian'', 19 April 2006, accessed 8 February 2009;  The Peerage, accessed 8 February 2009; and  Hambleton Hall website, accessed 8 February 2009 Streatfeild died from tuberculosis in 1915, but Mrs Astley Cooper continued to encourage her late friend's protégé, who remained a frequent guest at her estate, Hambleton Hall.Hoare, pp. 39–43

Coward continued to perform during most of World War I, appearing at the Prince of Wales's Theatre in 1916 in ''The Happy Family'' and on tour with Amy Brandon Thomas's company in ''Charley's Aunt''. In 1917, he appeared in ''The Saving Grace'', a comedy produced by Hawtrey. Coward recalled in his memoirs, "My part was reasonably large and I was really quite good in it, owing to the kindness and care of Hawtrey's direction. He took endless trouble with me... and taught me during those two short weeks many technical points of comedy acting which I use to this day."Coward (''Present Indicative''), p. 66

In 1918, Coward was drafted into the Artists Rifles but was assessed as unfit for active service because of a tubercular tendency, and he was discharged on health grounds after nine months.Lesley, pp. 41–42 That year he appeared in the D. W. Griffith film ''Hearts of the World'' in an uncredited role. He sold short stories to several magazines to help his family financially. He also began writing plays, collaborating on the first two (''Ida Collaborates'' (1917) and ''Women and Whisky'' (1918)) with his friend Esmé Wynne. ''The Noel Coward Society'', noelcoward.net, accessed 8 February 2009 His first solo effort as a playwright was ''The Rat Trap'' (1918) which was eventually produced at the Everyman Theatre, Hampstead, in October 1926.Thaxter, John.  British Theatre Guide, 2006, accessed 8 February 2009 During these years, he met Lorn McNaughtan,later known by her married name, Lorn Loraine who became his private secretary and served in that capacity for more than forty years, until her death.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3f80b9052bedfd562af59f5a6d55c50a" name="coward_Hawtrey_1911" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/3f80b9052bedfd562af59f5a6d55c50a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>