<document id="63db44496d352f4b59a88542e7fd2498-1.4" name="Noël_Coward" cat="17">
<text>
Coward's new plays after the war were moderately successful but failed to match the popularity of his pre-war hits.Lahr, p. 136 ''Relative Values'' (1951) addresses the culture clash between an English aristocratic family and a Hollywood actress with matrimonial ambitions; ''South Sea Bubble'' (1951) is a political comedy set in a British colony; ''Quadrille'' (1952) is a drama about Victorian love and elopement; and ''Nude with Violin'' (1956, starring John Gielgud in London and Coward in New York) is a satire on modern art.Lesley, pp. 314, 370 and 361 A revue, ''Sigh No More'' (1945), was a moderate success,Morley, p. 308 but two musicals, ''Pacific 1860'' (1946), a lavish South Seas romance, and ''Ace of Clubs'' (1949), set in a night club, were financial failures.Lesley, pp. 248 and 289 In addition, his friends Charles Cochran and Gertrude Lawrence died in 1951 and 1952, respectively. Despite his disappointments during this period, Coward maintained a high public profile; his performance as King Magnus in Shaw's ''The Apple Cart'' for the Coronation season of 1953, co-starring Margaret Leighton, received much coverage in the press,"Haymarket Theatre", ''The Times'', 8 May 1953, p. 12; and Brown, Ivor. "Royal and Ancient", ''The Manchester Guardian'', 8 May 1953, p. 5 and his cabaret act, honed during his wartime tours entertaining the troops, was a supreme success, first in London at the Café de Paris, and later in Las Vegas.Morley, pp. 339–40 The theatre critic Kenneth Tynan wrote:


In 1955, Coward's cabaret act at Las Vegas, recorded live for the gramophone,Reissued in 2003 on CD by CBS – DRG 19037 was so successful that CBS engaged him to write and direct a series of three 90-minute television specials for the 1955-1956 season.  The first of these, ''Together With Music'', paired Coward with Mary Martin, featuring him in many of the numbers from his Las Vegas act.Kenrick, John.  Coward 101 at ''Musicals 101: The Cyber Encyclopedia of Musical Theatre, TV and Film'', accessed 16 February 2009  It was followed by productions of ''Blithe Spirit'' in which he starred with Claudette Colbert, Lauren Bacall and Mildred Natwick and ''This Happy Breed'' with Edna Best and Roger Moore. Despite excellent reviews, the audience viewing figures were moderate.Payne and Morley, pp. 287–88, 304 and 314

During the 1950s and 60s, Coward continued to write musicals and plays. ''After the Ball'', his 1953 adaptation of ''Lady Windermere's Fan'', was the last musical he debuted in the West End; his last two musicals premiered on Broadway. ''Sail Away'' (1961), set on a luxury cruise liner, was Coward's most successful post-war musical, with productions in America, Britain and Australia.Lesley, pp. 410–14, and 428–29 ''The Girl Who Came to Supper'', a musical adaptation of ''The Sleeping Prince'' (1963), ran for only three months.Lesley, p. 430. He directed the successful 1964 Broadway musical adaptation of ''Blithe Spirit'', called ''High Spirits''. Coward's late plays include a farce, ''Look After Lulu!'' (1959), and a tragi-comic study of old age, ''Waiting in the Wings'' (1960), both of which were successful despite "critical disdain".Simon, John.  ''The NY Magazine'', January 3, 2000, accessed February 8, 2009 Coward argued that the primary purpose of a play was to entertain, and he made no attempt at modernism, which he felt was boring to the audience although fascinating to the critics. His comic novel, ''Pomp and Circumstance'' (1960), about life in a tropical British colony, met with more critical success.Payne and Morley, pp. 451 and 453 Coward's final stage success came with ''Suite in Three Keys'' (1966), a trilogy set in a hotel penthouse suite. He wrote it as his swan song as a stage actor: "I would like to act once more before I fold my bedraggled wings."Coward, ''Plays, Five'', introduction, unnumbered page. The trilogy gained glowing reviews and did good box office business in the UK.Morley, p. 375 In one of the three plays, ''A Song at Twilight'', Coward abandoned his customary reticence on the subject and played an explicitly homosexual character. The daring piece earned Coward new critical praise."Noel Coward's Skeleton Feast", ''The Times'', 15 April 1966, p. 16 He intended to star in the trilogy on Broadway but was too ill to travel. Only two of the ''Suite in Three Keys'' plays were performed in New York, with the title changed to ''Noël Coward in Two Keys'', starring Hume Cronyn.Hoare, p. 502



Coward won new popularity in several notable films later in his career, such as ''Around the World in 80 Days'' (1956), ''Our Man in Havana'' (1959), ''Bunny Lake is Missing'' (1965), ''Boom!'' (1968) and ''The Italian Job'' (1969).Hoare, pp. 380, 414, 491, 507 and 508 Stage and film opportunities he turned down in the 1950s included an invitation to compose a musical version of ''Pygmalion'' (two years before ''My Fair Lady'' was written), and offers of the roles of the king in the original stage production of ''The King and I'', and Colonel Nicholson in the film ''The Bridge on the River Kwai''.Hoare, pp. 387, 386, and 473 Invited to play the title role in the 1962 film ''Dr. No'', he replied, "No, no, no, a thousand times, no."Day (2007), p. 310 In the same year, he turned down the role of Humbert Humbert in ''Lolita'', saying, "At my time of life the film story would be logical if the 12-year-old heroine was a sweet little old lady."Richards, p. 83

In the mid-1960s and early 1970s successful productions of his 1920s and 30s plays, and new revues celebrating his music, including ''Oh, Coward!'' on Broadway and ''Cowardy Custard'' in London, revived Coward's popularity and critical reputation. He dubbed this comeback "Dad's Renaissance".Hoare p. 479 ''et seq''. This began with a hit 1963 revival of ''Private Lives'' in London and then New York.Morley, pp. 370-72 Invited to direct ''Hay Fever'' with Edith Evans at the National Theatre, he wrote in 1964, "I am thrilled and flattered and frankly a little flabbergasted that the National Theatre should have had the curious perceptiveness to choose a very early play of mine and to give it a cast that could play the Albanian telephone directory."Morley, p. 369

Other examples of "Dad's Renaissance" included a 1968 Off Broadway production of ''Private Lives'' at the Theatre de Lys starring Elaine Stritch, Lee Bowman and Betsy von Furstenberg, and directed by Charles Nelson Reilly. Despite this impressive cast, Coward's popularity had risen so high that the theatre poster for the production used an Al Hirschfeld caricature of Coward (''pictured''The caricature was also used in connection with other Coward works, for example on his album of his ballet suite, "London Morning" (1959; reissued in 1978 on LP on DRG SL 5180 with the Hirschfeld drawing on the cover)) instead of an image of the production or its stars. The illustration captures how Coward's image had changed by the 1960s: he was no longer seen as the smooth 1930s sophisticate, but as the doyen of the theatre. As ''The New Statesman'' wrote in 1964: "Who would have thought the landmarks of the Sixties would include the emergence of Noël Coward as the grand old man of British drama? There he was one morning, flipping verbal tiddlywinks with reporters about "Dad's Renaissance"; the next he was... beside Forster, T. S. Eliot and the OMs, demonstrably the greatest living English playwright."Ronald Bryden in ''The New Statesman'', August 1964, ''quoted'' in Hoare, p. 479 ''Time'' magazine wrote that "in the '60s... his best work, with its inspired inconsequentiality, seemed to exert not only a period charm but charm, period."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6dde93c19aab99e009bdd7fc70890137" name="Private_Lives_Theatre_De_Lys" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/6dde93c19aab99e009bdd7fc70890137.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>