<document id="652ccf6eb1863fd79c8c2c9337bea987-2.4" name="History_of_Puerto_Rico" cat="14">
<text>
The latter half of the 19th century was marked by the Puerto Rican struggle for autonomy. A census conducted in 1860 revealed a population of 583,308. Of these, 300,406 (51.5%) were white and 282,775 (48.5%) were persons of color, the latter including people of primarily African heritage, mulattos and mestizos. Grose, Howard B., ''Advance in the Antilles; the new era in Cuba and Porto Rico'',   The majority of the population in Puerto Rico was illiterate (83.7%) and lived in poverty, and the agricultural industry—at the time, the main source of income—was hampered by lack of road infrastructure, adequate tools and equipment, and natural disasters, including hurricanes and droughts.Brás, Marisabel  The economy also suffered from increasing tariffs and taxes imposed by the Spanish Crown. Furthermore, Spain had begun to exile or jail any person who called for liberal reforms. 

On September 23, 1868, hundreds of men and women in the town of Lares—stricken by poverty and politically estranged from Spain—revolted against Spanish rule, seeking Puerto Rican independence. The ''Grito de Lares'' ("Lares Cry" or "Lares Uprising") was planned by a group led by Dr. Ramón Emeterio Betances, at the time exiled to the Dominican Republic, and Segundo Ruiz Belvis. Dr. Betances had founded the ''Comité Revolucionario de Puerto Rico'' (Revolutionary Committee of Puerto Rico) in January 1868. The most important figures in the uprising were Manuel Rojas, Mathias Brugman, Mariana Bracetti, Francisco Ramirez Medina and Lola Rodríguez de Tió. The uprising, although significant, was quickly controlled by Spanish authorities.Brás, Marisabel, par. 8


Following the ''Grito de Lares'' revolt, political and social reforms occurred toward the end of the 19th century.Brás, Marisabel, par. 8-13 On June 4, 1870, due to the efforts of Román Baldorioty de Castro, Luis Padial and Julio Vizcarrondo, the Moret Law was approved, giving freedom to slaves born after September 17, 1868 or over 60 years old;  on March 22, 1873, the Spanish National Assembly officially abolished, with a few special clauses, These clauses included that slaves were required to continue working for three more years and that the owners would be compensated 35 million pesetas per slave. slavery in Puerto Rico. In 1870, the first political organizations on the island were formed as two factions emerged. The Traditionalists, known as the ''Partido Liberal Conservador'' (Liberal Conservative Party) were led by José R. Fernández, Pablo Ubarri and Francisco Paula Acuña and advocated assimilation into the political party system of Spain, while the Autonomists, known as the ''Partido Liberal Reformista'' (Liberal Reformist Party) were led by Román Baldorioty de Castro, José Julián Acosta, Nicolás Aguayo and Pedro Gerónimo Goico and advocated decentralization away from Spanish control.Brás, Marisabel, par. 9 Both parties would later change their names to ''Partido Federal Reformista'' (Reformist Federal Party) and ''Partido Español Incondicional'' (Unconditional Spanish Party), respectively. In March 1887, the ''Partido Federal Reformista'' was reformed and named the ''Partido Autonomista Puertorriqueño'' (Puerto Rican Autonomist Party); it tried to create a political and legal identity for Puerto Rico while emulating Spain in all political matters. It was led by Román Baldorioty de Castro, José Celso Barbosa, Rosendo Matienzo Cintrón and Luis Muñoz Rivera.

The struggle for autonomy came close to achieving its goal on November 25, 1897, when the ''Carta Autonómica'' (''Charter of Autonomy''), which conceded political and administrative autonomy to the island, was approved in Spain. In the past 400-plus years, after centuries of colonial rule, Práxedes Mateo Sagasta, the Prime Minister of Spain granted the island an independent government on November 25, 1897 in the empire's legislative body in Cádiz, Spain and trade was opened up with the United States and European colonies. The charter maintained a governor appointed by Spain, who held the power to veto any legislative decision he disagreed with, and a partially elected parliamentary structure. This legislature consisted of a Council of Administration with eight elected and seven appointed members, and a Chamber of Representatives with one member for every 25,000 inhabitants. That same year, the ''Partido Autonomista Ortodoxo'' (Orthodox Autonomist Party), led by José Celso Barbosa and Manuel Fernández Juncos, was founded. On February 9, 1898, the new government officially began. Local legislature set its own budget and taxes. They accepted or rejected commercial treaties concluded by Spain. In February 1898, Governor General Manuel Macías inaugurated the new government of Puerto Rico under the Autonomous Charter which gave town councils complete autonomy in local matters. Subsequently, the governor had no authority to intervene in civil and political matters unless authorized to do so by the Cabinet. General elections were held in March and on July 17, 1898 Puerto Rico's autonomous government began to function, but not for long.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="936edd458f6fb1babb679ba32d562630" name="Roman_baldorioty_de_castro" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/936edd458f6fb1babb679ba32d562630.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>