<document id="654855e02c249c77120d0e72159fed90-7" name="Germany_women's_national_football_team" cat="26">
<text>
Current team captain Birgit Prinz holds the record for Germany appearances, having played 198 times since 1994. She is one of 15 German players to have reached 100 caps. Kerstin Stegemann is second, having played 191 times and she has the highest number of appearances among retired players. Bettina Wiegmann, Germany's team captain during the 2003 World Cup win, comes fourth with 154 games. Prinz exceeded Wiegmann’s record as the most capped player in November 2006.Deutscher Fußball-Bund. . DFB.de. Accessed 11 August 2008. Wiegmann is the only honorary captain of the German women’s national football team.Deutscher Fußball-Bund. . DFB.de. Accessed 6 August 2008.  At 30 years old, Kerstin Garefrekes is the youngest player with over 100 caps.

The title of Germany’s highest goalscorer is also held by Prinz. She scored her first goal in July 1994 against Canada and since then has scored 125 goals (averaging 0.63 goals per game). Heidi Mohr, as well as being the second-highest scorer, is also the most prolific with 83 goals coming from 104 games (averaging 0.80 goals per game). Two players share the record for goals scored in one match: Conny Pohlers scored five goals in October 2001 against Portugal,Deutscher Fußball-Bund. . DFB.de. Accessed 11 August 2008. and Inka Grings scored five times in February 2004, again facing Portugal.Deutscher Fußball-Bund. . DFB.de. Accessed 11 August 2008. Silvia Neid, the current German national coach, is the fifth highest goalscorer with 48 goals in 111 games.

The largest margin of victory achieved by Germany is 13–0 against Portugal during a European Championship qualifying game in November 2003; it was the first match following the 2003 World Cup win.. ''Spiegel Online''. 15 November 2003. Accessed 6 August 2008.  The record defeat, a 0–6 deficit against the United States, occurred during a friendly match in March 1996.Deutscher Fußball-Bund. . DFB.de. Accessed 11 August 2008.

Silke Rottenberg has the most appearances for a goalkeeper with 126 caps and 67 games without conceding a goal.Deutscher Fußball-Bund. . DFB.de. Accessed 11 August 2008. Current goalkeeper Nadine Angerer is second, with 86 games (49 without conceding a goal).Deutscher Fußball-Bund. . DFB.de. Accessed 11 August 2008. Bettina Wiegmann holds the record of 14 goals from penalty kicks; Renate Lingor comes in second with 8 goals.Deutscher Fußball-Bund. . DFB.de. Accessed 11 August 2008. Tina Wunderlich scored the team's only own goal in the semi-final of the 2000 Summer Olympics against Norway; it was the game's only goal.Deutscher Fußball-Bund. . DFB.de. Accessed 11 August 2008.

The German team also holds several international records. In 2007, they were the first to win two consecutive Women's World Cup titles and they achieved the biggest win in tournament history by beating Argentina 11–0.. FIFA.com. Accessed 11 August 2008. Germany is also the only team (men's and women's game) to win the World Cup without conceding a goal and the only country to win both the men's and the women's World Cup.Hooper, Simon. . CNN.com. 3 October 2007. Accessed 15 August 2008. With 14 goals, Prinz became the overall top goalscorer at the Women's World Cup in 2007, and she and Brazilian Marta are the only women to have received the FIFA World Player of the Year award three times.. FIFA.com. Accessed 11 August 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d1d519370313b0721a0027f2b692b5b0" name="Stege" sectnum="7#1">../img/d1d519370313b0721a0027f2b692b5b0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>