<document id="65a79674145a2ea7a72030cde6104375-1" name="Privilege_of_Peerage" cat="25">
<text>
Just as commoners have a right to trial by a jury of their equals (other commoners), peers and peeresses formerly had a right to trial by other peers. The right of peers to trial by their own order was formalized during the fourteenth century. A statute passed in 1341 provided:15 Edward III., st. 1, sec. 2. quoted in Spooner, Lysander (1852).  Boston: Hobart and Robbins. Retrieved on 2007-10-19.
:Whereas before this time the peers of the land have been arrested and imprisoned, and their temporalities, lands, and tenements, goods and cattels, asseized in the King's hands, and some put to death without judgment of their peers: It is accorded and assented, that no peer of the land ... shall be brought in judgment to lose his temporalities, lands, tenements, goods and cattels, nor to be arrested, imprisoned, outlawed, exiled, nor forejudged, nor put to answer, nor be judged, but by award of the said peers in Parliament.
The privilege of trial by peers was still ill-defined, and the statute did not cover peeresses. In 1442, after an ecclesiastical court (which included King Henry VI of England, Henry Beaufort and John Kemp) found Eleanor, Duchess of Gloucester guilty of witchcraft and banished her to the Isle of Man, a statute was enacted granting peeresses the right of trial by peers.

By the reign of Henry VII of England, there were two methods of trial by Peers of the Realm: trial in the House of Lords (or, in proper terms, by the High Court of Parliament) and trial in the Court of the Lord High Steward. The House of Lords tried the case if Parliament was in session; otherwise, trial was by the Lord High Steward's Court.Pike, pp.218–227 In both cases, the Lord High Steward presided. Before the trial, a peer would be indicted by a Grand Jury, as was normally done with commoners, but instead of being decided by the Assize Courts, the Lord High Steward's Court or Parliament would issue a writ of certiorari ordering the lower court to certify the case up to it. 

In the House of Lords, the Lord High Steward was the President or Chairman of the Court, but the entire House determined both questions of fact and questions of law. At the end of the trial, peers voted on the question before them, starting with the most junior baron and proceeding in order of precedence, ending with the Lord High Steward himself, by standing and declaring the verdict on their honour—not on oath, as is the case in juries trying commoners. By convention, Bishops and Archbishops did not vote on the verdict, though they were able to cast votes on procedural questions arising during the course of the trial. Instead, they sat until the conclusion of the deliberations, withdrawing from the chamber just prior to the final vote. All decisions were by simple majority, provided that at least twelve peers voted. The entire House also determined the punishment to be imposed, which had to accord with the law. For capital crimes the punishment was death; the last peer to be executed was Laurence Shirley, 4th Earl Ferrers, who was hanged for murder in 1760.

In the Lord High Steward's Court, the Lord High Steward functioned as a judge, determining questions of law, while a group of Lords Triers, essentially a jury composed of other peers, decided questions of fact and the verdict. By custom the number of Triers was not fewer than 23, so that a majority was a minimum of 12, but in fact the number ranged from 20 to 35. The power to choose which peers served as Triers lay with the Crown and was sometimes subject to abuse, as only those peers who agreed with the monarch's position would be summoned to the Court of the Lord High Steward, thereby favouring the desired verdict. This practice was ended by the Treasons Act, passed during the reign of King William III. The Act required that all peers be summoned as triers. All subsequent trials were held before the full High Court of Parliament.

From 1547 if a peer or peeress was convicted of a crime, except treason or murder, he or she could claim "privilege of peerage" to escape punishment if it was their first offence. In all, the privilege was exercised five times,Baron Morley found guilty of manslaughter in 1666; the Earl of Pembroke found guilty of manslaughter in 1678; the Earl of Warwick and Holland found guilty of manslaughter in 1699; Lord Byron found guilty of manslaughter in 1765; and the Duchess of Kingston found guilty of bigamy in 1776. until it was formally abolished in 1841 when James Brudenell, 7th Earl of Cardigan announced he would claim the privilege and avoid punishment if he was convicted of duelling. He was acquitted before the introduction of the bill.

The last trial in the House of Lords was that of Edward Southwell Russell, 26th Baron de Clifford in 1935 for motor manslaughter (he was acquitted); the following year the Lords passed a bill to abolish trial by peers but the Commons ignored it. In 1948, the right to trial by peers was abolished when the Lords added an amendment to the Criminal Justice Act, which the Commons accepted. Now, peers are tried by juries composed of commoners, though they were themselves excluded from jury service until the passage of the House of Lords Act 1999.

Peers were, and still are hypothetically, subject to impeachment. Impeachment was a procedure distinct from the aforementioned procedure of trial in the House of Lords, though the House of Lords is the court in both cases. Charges were brought by the House of Commons, not a Grand Jury. Additionally, while in normal cases the House of Lords tried peers only for felonies or treason, in impeachments the charges could include felonies, treason and misdemeanours. The case directly came before the House of Lords, rather than being referred to it by a writ of certiorari. The Lord High Steward presided only if a peer was charged with high treason; otherwise the Lord Chancellor presided. Other procedures in trials of impeachment were similar, however, to trials before the House of Lords: at the conclusion of the trial, the spiritual peers withdrew, and the temporal Lords gave their votes on their honour. The last impeachment was that of Henry Dundas, 1st Viscount Melville in 1806 for misappropriating public money (he was acquitted). Since then, impeachment has become an obsolete procedure in the United Kingdom.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="507f03ef50c1fc30b84df0d1ee7ed704" name="House_of_Lords_Microcosm_edited" sectnum="1#1">../img/507f03ef50c1fc30b84df0d1ee7ed704.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>