<document id="661729e340be9124fdc6c25d2988de33-3" name="History_of_Solidarity" cat="14">
<text>
Encouraged by the success of the August strikes, on September 17 workers' representatives, including Lech Wałęsa, formed a nationwide labor union, Solidarity (''Niezależny Samorządny Związek Zawodowy (NSZZ) "Solidarność"'').  in WIEM Encyklopedia. Last accessed on 10 October 2006  It was the first independent labor union in a Soviet-bloc country. Its name was suggested by Karol Modzelewski, and its famous logo was conceived by Jerzy Janiszewski, designer of many Solidarity-related posters. The new union's supreme powers were vested in a legislative body, the Convention of Delegates (''Zjazd Delegatów''). The executive branch was the National Coordinating Commission (''Krajowa Komisja Porozumiewawcza''), later renamed the National Commission (''Komisja Krajowa''). The Union had a regional structure, comprising 38 regions (''region'') and two districts (''okręg''). On December 16, 1980, the Monument to Fallen Shipyard Workers was unveiled in Gdansk, and on June 28, 1981, another monument was unveiled in Poznan, which commemorated the Poznań 1956 protests. On January 15, 1981, a Solidarity delegation, including Lech Wałęsa, met in Rome with Pope John Paul II. From September 5 to 10, and from September 26 to October 7, Solidarity's first national congress was held, and Lech Wałęsa was elected its president. . Last accessed on 15 October 2006  Last accord of the congress was adoption of republican program "Self-governing Republic"Piotr Gliński, The Self-governing Republic in the Third Republic, “Polish Sociological Review”, 2006, no.1.


Meanwhile Solidarity had been transforming itself from a trade union into a social movement
 or more specifically, a revolutionary movement.Jeff Goodwin, ''No Other Way Out: States and Revolutionary Movements, 1945–1991''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2001. Chapter 1 and 8. Over the 500 days following the Gdańsk Agreement, 9–10 million workers, intellectuals and students joined it or its suborganizations, such as the Independent Student Union (''Niezależne Zrzeszenie Studentów'', created in September 1980), the Independent Farmers' Trade Union (''NSZZ Rolników Indywidualnych "Solidarność"'', created in May 1981) and the Independent Craftsmen's Trade Union. It was the only time in recorded history that a quarter of a country's population (some 80% of the total Polish work force) had voluntarily joined a single organization. ''"History has taught us that there is no bread without freedom,"'' the Solidarity program stated a year later. ''"What we had in mind was not only bread, butter and sausages, but also justice, democracy, truth, legality, human dignity, freedom of convictions, and the repair of the republic."'' Tygodnik Solidarność, a Solidarity-published newspaper, was started in April 1981.

Using strikes and other protest actions, Solidarity sought to force a change in government policies. At the same time, it was careful never to use force or violence, so as to avoid giving the government any excuse to bring security forces into play.

 After 27 Bydgoszcz Solidarity members, including Jan Rulewski, were beaten up on March 19, a four-hour warning strike on March 27, involving around twelve million people, paralyzed the country. This was the largest strike in the history of the Eastern bloc,
 and it forced the government to promise an investigation into the beatings. This concession, and Wałęsa's agreement to defer further strikes, proved a setback to the movement, as the euphoria that had swept Polish society subsided. Nonetheless the Polish communist party—the Polish United Workers' Party (''PZPR'')—had lost its total control over society.

Yet while Solidarity was ready to take up negotiations with the government,
 the Polish communists were unsure what to do, as they issued empty declarations and bided their time. Against the background of a deteriorating communist shortage economy and unwillingness to negotiate seriously with Solidarity, it became increasingly clear that the Communist government would eventually have to suppress the Solidarity movement as the only way out of the impasse, or face a truly revolutionary situation. The atmosphere was increasingly tense, with various local chapters conducting a growing number of uncoordinated strikes as well as street protests, such as the Summer 1981 hunger demonstrations in Poland, in response to the worsening economic situation. On December 3, 1981, Solidarity announced that a 24-hour strike would be held if the government were granted additional powers to suppress dissent, and that a general strike would be declared if those powers were used.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9d3eb18e8294cb8259c714d3491ce30d" name="WieczorWroclawia20marca1981" sectnum="3#1">../img/9d3eb18e8294cb8259c714d3491ce30d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>