<document id="662669445dc1de9707a5a1bdd5cd8d11-1.6" name="Captain_Marvel_(DC_Comics)" cat="17">
<text>
When superhero comics became popular again in the mid-1960s in what is now called the Silver Age of comics, Fawcett was unable to revive Captain Marvel because in order to settle the lawsuit it had agreed never to publish the character again. Eventually, they licensed the characters to DC Comics in 1972, and DC began planning a revival. Because Marvel Comics had by this time established its own claim to the use of ''Captain Marvel'' as a comic book title, DC published their book under the name ''Shazam!'' Since then, that title has become so linked to Captain Marvel that many people have taken to identifying the character as "Shazam" instead of his actual name.

The ''Shazam!'' comic series began with issue #1, dated February 1973. It contained both new stories and reprints from the 1940s and 1950s. The first story attempted to explain the Marvel Family's absence by stating that they, Dr. Sivana, Sivana's children, and most of the supporting cast had been accidentally trapped in suspended animation for twenty years until finally breaking free.

Dennis O'Neil was the primary writer of the book; his role was later taken over by writers Elliott S. Maggin and E. Nelson Bridwell. C. C. Beck drew stories for the first ten issues of the book before quitting due to creative differences; Bob Oksner, Fawcett alumnus Kurt Schaffenberger, and Don Newton were among the later artists of the title.

With DC's Multiverse concept in effect during this time, it was stated that the revived Marvel Family and related characters lived within the DC Universe on the parallel world of "Earth-S". While the series began with a great deal of fanfare, the book had a lackluster reception. The creators themselves had misgivings; Beck said, "As an illustrator I could, in the old days, make a good story better by bringing it to life with drawings. But I couldn't bring the new  stories to life no matter how hard I tried."Benton, p. 77 ''Shazam!'' was canceled with issue #35 (June 1978) and relegated to a back-up position in ''World's Finest Comics'' (from #253, October-November 1978, to #282, August 1982, skipping only #271 which featured a full-length origin of the Superman-Batman team story) and ''Adventure Comics'' (from #491, September 1982, through #498, April 1983; only #491 and #492 featured original stories however, the rest containing Fawcett era reprint stories). With their 1985 ''Crisis on Infinite Earths'' maxi-series, DC fully integrated the characters into the DC Universe.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="953d474a409598c9c12ff10b36424ee3" name="Shazam-no-1" sectnum="1.6#1">../img/953d474a409598c9c12ff10b36424ee3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>