<document id="662669445dc1de9707a5a1bdd5cd8d11-2" name="Captain_Marvel_(DC_Comics)" cat="17">
<text>
The ''Superman/Shazam: First Thunder'' mini-series, written by Judd Winick with art by Josh Middleton, and published between September 2005 and March 2006, depicted the first post-''Crisis'' meeting between Superman and Captain Marvel. The meeting proves to be amicable, with Superman noting that he is impressed to have an ally who may have similar powers to himself, but who is also far more resistant to the kind of magic attacks that he is vulnerable to.  However, he is disturbed when he learns that the Captain is actually a child and agrees to Shazam's suggestion that he mentor the boy.

A second Captain Marvel mini-series, ''Shazam! The Monster Society of Evil'', written and illustrated by Jeff Smith (creator of ''Bone''), was published in four 48-page installments between February and July 2007. Smith's ''Shazam!'' mini-series, in the works since 2003, is a more traditional take on the character, which updates and re-imagines Captain Marvel's origin. Warmoth, Brian. "". ''Wizard'' magazine. Retrieved March 4, 2007. Smith's story features Billy Batson and Captain Marvel as separate personalities, as they were in the pre-1985 stories, and features a prepubescent Mary Marvel as Captain Marvel's sidekick instead of the traditional teenaged or adult version.

An all-ages Captain Marvel comic, ''Billy Batson and the Magic of Shazam!'', debuted in July 2008 under DC's Johnny DC youth-oriented imprint and is published bi-monthly. Following the lead and continuity of Smith's version, it is written and drawn by Mike Kunkel, creator of ''Herobear''.Pumpelly, Danny (August 11, 2007). "". ComicBookResources.com. Retrieved August 26, 2007. Kunkel's version returns to the modern concept of having Captain Marvel retain Billy's personality, and also introduces a version of Black Adam whose alter ego, Theo Adam, is a child like Billy Batson.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2aafd8ec2018d8e4291378e2bcba3c9b" name="Billy-batson-magic-of-shazam-no1-2008" sectnum="2#1">../img/2aafd8ec2018d8e4291378e2bcba3c9b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>