<document id="662669445dc1de9707a5a1bdd5cd8d11-7.17" name="Captain_Marvel_(DC_Comics)" cat="17">
<text>
Captain Marvel's adventures have contributed a number of elements to both comic book culture and pop culture in general. The most notable of these is the regular use of Superman and Captain Marvel as adversaries in Modern Age comic book stories.
 
The National Comics/Fawcett Comics rivalry was parodied in "Superduperman," a satirical comic book story by Harvey Kurtzman and Wally Wood in the fourth issue of ''Mad'' (April-May, 1953). In the parody, inspired by the Fawcett/DC legal battles,Wright, p. 146 Superduperman, endowed with muscles on muscles, does battle with Captain Marbles, a Captain Marvel caricature. Marbles' magic word is "SHAZOOM", which stands for '''S'''trength, '''H'''ealth, '''A'''ptitude, '''Z'''eal, '''O'''x—power of, '''O'''x—power of another and '''M'''oney. In contrast to Captain Marvel's perceived innocence and goodness, Marbles was greedy and money-grubbing.
 
While publishing its ''Shazam!'' revival in the 1970s, DC Comics published a story in ''Superman'' #276 (June 1974) featuring a battle between the Man of Steel and a thinly disguised version of Captain Marvel called Captain Thunder, a reference to the character's original name.''Superman'' (vol. 1) #276 (June 1974) Two years later, ''Justice League of America'' #135-137 featured a story arc which featured the heroes of Earth-1, Earth-2, and Earth-S teaming together against their enemies. It was in this story that Superman and Captain Marvel first met, albeit briefly. They would later on meet teaming-up together in various titles such as ''DC Comics Presents''.

Following this ''Justice League'' story, DC followed ''Mad'''s cue and often pitted Captain Marvel and Superman against each other for any number of reasons, but usually as an inside joke to the characters' long battles in court; they are otherwise staunch allies. Notable Superman/Captain Marvel battles in DC Comics include ''All-New Collectors' Edition'' #C-58 (1978), in "When Earths Collide", written by Gerry Conway with art by Rich Buckler & Dick Giordano. ''All-Star Squadron'' #36 & 37 (1984), and ''Superman (vol. 2)'' #102 (1995). The Superman/Captain Marvel battle depicted in ''Kingdom Come'' #4 (1996) served as the climax of that mini-series, with Marvel having been brainwashed by Lex Luthor and Mister Mind to turn against the other heroes. The "Clash" episode of the DC-based animated TV series ''Justice League Unlimited'', which included Captain Marvel as a guest character, featured a Superman/Captain Marvel fight as its centerpiece. By contrast, the depiction of the pair's first meeting in the ''Superman/Shazam!: First Thunder'' mini-series establishes them as firm friends and allies to the point of Superman volunteering to be Billy's mentor when he learns the boy's true age. In contrast to Alex Ross' earlier depiction in ''Kingdom Come'', ''Justice'' has Captain Marvel rescuing Superman and then closely working with the Kryptonian to find a means to save the Flash who is running out of control.

Marvel and Superman combat each other again in the recently released ''Superman/Batman: Public Enemies''. Working for President Lex Luthor, Marvel tracks down Superman and Batman at Luthor's command center. Alongside Hawkman, Marvel engages the "fugitive" heroes, but is ultimately defeated.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="99c112b611792d12da66ab85bded7c3a" name="Supermanmarvel_kingdomcome" sectnum="7.17#1">../img/99c112b611792d12da66ab85bded7c3a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>