<document id="679396c5cc11afd7b5486d6db4f49dba-6.2" name="Hasekura_Tsunenaga" cat="14">
<text>
The embassy remained two months in Acapulco and entered Mexico City on 24 March, where it was received with great ceremony. The ultimate mission for the embassy was to go on to Europe. The embassy spent some time in Mexico, and then went to Veracruz to board the fleet of Don Antonio Oquendo.

Chimalpahin gives some account of the visit of Hasekura.

:"This is the second time that the Japanese have landed one of their ships on the shore at Acapulco. They are transporting here all things of iron, and writing desks, and some cloth that they are to sell here." (Chimalpahin, "Annals of His Time").Chimalpahin "Annals of his time", 4th March 1614, p275
:"It became known here in Mexico and was said that the reason their ruler the Emperor of Japan sent this said lordly emissary and ambassador here, is to go in Rome to see the Holy Father Paul V, and to give him their obedience concerning the holy church, so that all the Japanase want to become Christians" (Chimalpahin, "Annals of His Time").Chimalpahin "Annals of his time", 24th March 1614, p275


Hasekura was settled in a house next to the Church of San Francisco, and met with the Viceroy. He explained to him that he was also planning to meet King Philip III to offer him peace and to obtain that the Japanese could come to Mexico for trade. On Wednesday 9 April, 20 Japanese were baptized, and 22 more on 20 April by the archbishop in Mexico, don Juan Pérez de la Serna, at the Church of San Francisco. Altogether 63 of them received confirmation on 25 April. Hasekura waited for his travel to Europe to be baptized there:
:"But the lordly emissary, the ambassador, did not want to be baptized here; it was said that he will be baptized later in Spain" (Chimalpahin, "Annals of His Time").Chimalpahin "Annals of his time", 9th April 1614, p277
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="83f3001eb5345c8552d196a3c77ae1b1" name="Oldmexicocity" sectnum="6.2#1">../img/83f3001eb5345c8552d196a3c77ae1b1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>