<document id="681830061f34470d2a957dccaf39d154-2.6" name="Mozart_family_grand_tour" cat="20">
<text>
The family remained in Paris for two months. No concerts were given by them in this period although, according to Grimm, there were performances of Wolfgang's symphonies.Zaslaw, pp. 64&ndash;66 Grimm was effusive about the development of both children; Nannerl, he wrote, "had the finest and most brilliant execution on the harpsichord", and: "no-one but her brother can rob her of supremacy".Sadie, pp. 96&ndash;99 Of Wolfgang he quoted a Prince of Brunswick as saying that many Kapellmeisters at the peak of their art would die without knowing what the boy knew at the age of nine. "If these children live," wrote Grimm, "they will not remain in Salzburg. Monarchs will soon be disputing about who should have them".

The only surviving music composed by Wolfgang during this Paris visit is his ''Kyrie'' in F major, K.33, his first attempt to write formal church music.Blom. p. 32 On 9 July the family left Paris for Dijon, following an invitation from the Prince of Condé. The children played in a concert there on 19 July, accompanied by a local orchestra, about whose players Leopold made disparaging comments: ''Très mediocre &ndash; Un miserable italien detestable &ndash; Asini tutti &ndash; Un racleur'' (a scratcher) ''&ndash; Rotten''.Zaslaw, p. 67. The other terms may be translated: ''très mediocre'', "very undistinguished"; ''Un miserable italien detestable'', "a repulsive Italian misery"; ''Asini tutti'', "all idiots"; and ''Rotten'', "inadequate". They moved on to Lyon where Wolfgang "preluded for an hour and a quarter with the most capable master here, yielding nothing to him".Quoted by Sadie, p. 99, from a contemporary report 

A letter to Hagenauer dated 16 August indicated that Leopold wished to proceed to Turin, then across northern Italy to Venice, and home via the Tyrol. "Our own interest and love of travel should have induced us to follow our noses", he wrote, but added: "...I have said I shall go  home and I shall keep my word".Sadie, pp. 99&ndash;103 The family took a shorter route through Switzerland, arriving in Geneva on 20 August, where the children gave two concerts, and were received by the distinguished composer André-Ernest-Modeste Grétry. Many years later Grétry wrote of this encounter: "I wrote for him  an Allegro in E flat, difficult but without pretension; he played it, and everyone, except myself, thought it was a miracle. The child had never broken off, but following the modulations, he had substituted a number of passages for those I had written". This claim, that Wolfgang improvised when faced with passages he could not play, appears to be the only adverse comment from all those called upon to test him. 

The journey through Switzerland continued, with concerts at Lausanne and Zürich. Since leaving the Netherlands Wolfgang had composed little; a minor harpsichord piece, K.33B, written for the Zürich concerts, and later some cello pieces (since lost) written for the Prince of Fürstenberg, who received the party on its arrival in Donaueschingen, on the German border, on 20 October. They spent 12 days here before resuming their journey towards Munich, which they reached on 8 November. They were delayed here for nearly two weeks after Wolfgang fell ill, but he was well enough to perform before the Elector, with Nannerl, on 22 November. A few days later they set out for Salzburg, arriving at their home on the Getreidegasse on 29 November 1766.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3c224c9a8ad08c84f336ab93b4226645" name="Mozart.birth.500pix" sectnum="2.6#1">../img/3c224c9a8ad08c84f336ab93b4226645.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>