<document id="681830061f34470d2a957dccaf39d154-2.5" name="Mozart_family_grand_tour" cat="20">
<text>
Leopold had been quite specific in letters to Hagenauer that the family would not visit the Dutch Republic, but would go to Paris and then return home to Salzburg.Zaslaw, pp. 44&ndash;45 However, he was persuaded by an envoy of the Princess Caroline of Nassau-Weilburg, sister of the Prince of Orange, to go instead to The Hague and to present the children to her, as official guests of the court. After the party's landing at Calais there was a month's delay at Lille, as first Wolfgang fell sick with tonsillitis, then Leopold suffered prolonged dizziness attacks.Sadie, pp. 90&ndash;95 Early in September the family moved on to Ghent, where Wolfgang played on the new organ at the Bernardines chapel; a few days later he played on the cathedral organ at Antwerp.Blom, p. 30 On 11 September the family finally reached The Hague.


After arriving in The Hague, Nannerl developed a severe cold and was unable to participate in the initial concerts before the Princess during their first week, nor in a performance before the Prince a few days later. Leopold was sufficiently confident of Nannerl's recovery to announce the appearances of both prodigies at a concert to be given at the hall of the Oude Doelen on 30 September. The notice for this concert gives Wolfgang's age as eight (he was nine), but correctly gives Nannerl's as fourteen. The advertisement concentrates on Wolfgang: "All the overtures will be from the hands of this young composer  Music-lovers may confront him with any music at will, and he will play it at sight". It is not certain whether this concert in fact took place&mdash;Sadie believes it may have been postponed. If it did happen, Wolfgang appeared alone, for by this time Nannerl's cold had turned into typhoid fever. Her condition grew steadily worse, and on 21 October she was given the last sacrament. A visit from the royal physician turned the tide; he changed the treatment, and by the end of the month she was recovering. Then Wolfgang fell ill, and it was mid-December before he was on his feet again. 

Both children were able to appear at the Oude Doelen on 22 January 1766, in a concert which may have included the first public performance of one of Wolfgang's London symphonies, K.19, and possibly of a new symphony in B flat major K.22, composed in the Netherlands. Zaslaw, pp. 47&ndash;51 Following this concert they spent time in Amsterdam before returning to The Hague early in March. The main reason for their return was the forthcoming public celebrations of the Prince of Orange's coming of age. Wolfgang had composed a quodlibet (song medley) for small orchestra and harpsichord, entitled ''Galimathias musicum'', K.32, which was played at a special concert to honour the Prince on 11 March.Zaslaw, pp. 52&ndash;55 This was one of several pieces composed for the occasion; Wolfgang also wrote arias for the Princess using words from Metastasio's libretto ''Artaserse'' (including ''Conservati fedele'', K. 23), and keyboard variations on a Dutch song ''Laat ons juichen, Batavieren!'' K. 24. He wrote a set of keyboard and violin sonatas for the Princess, as he had earlier for the French princess and for the Queen of Great Britain. Another symphony, K.45a, commonly known as "Old Lambach" and once thought to have been written several years later, was also written in The Hague, possibly for the Prince's concert.Zaslaw, p. 64 

The family left The Hague at the end of March, moving first to Haarlem, where the organist of St Bavo's Church invited Wolfgang to play on the church's organ, one of the largest in the country. From there they travelled east and south, giving concerts along the way at Amsterdam and Utrecht, before leaving the Netherlands and travelling through Brussels and Valenciennes, to arrive in Paris on 10 May.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1f408f60c19880ba4bb98777440825f7" name="WilliamV" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/1f408f60c19880ba4bb98777440825f7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>