<document id="681830061f34470d2a957dccaf39d154-2.2" name="Mozart_family_grand_tour" cat="20">
<text>
The journey's beginning, on 9 July 1763, was inauspicious; on the first day a carriage wheel broke, requiring a 24-hour interlude while repairs were carried out. Leopold turned this delay to advantage, by taking Wolfgang to the nearby church at Wasserburg, where according to Leopold the boy played on the organ pedals as if he had been studying it for months.Leopold Mozart letter, quoted by Sadie, p. 37 In Munich, on successive evenings, the children played before Elector Maximilian III, earning from these engagements the equivalent of half of Leopold's annual salary of 354 gulden or florins.The florin, or gulden, was the currency of the Austro-Hungarian empire. A florin was worth about one-tenth of a £ sterling.Sadie, pp. 37&ndash;47Sadie, p. 35 The next stop was Augsburg, where Leopold's estranged mother refused to attend any of the three concerts given there.Glover, p. 20 The family then moved on to Schwetzingen and the Mannheim court, where the children's performance apparently amazed Elector Palatine Karl Theodor and his Electress.

The next extended stop was at Mainz. The Elector was ill, but the Mozarts gave three concerts in the town, which brought in 200 gulden.Sadie, p. 41 From Mainz the family took the market boat up the River Main to Frankfurt, where several public concerts were given. Among those present at the first of these was the fourteen-year-old Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, who would many years later recall "the little fellow with his wig and his sword". An advertisement for these concerts announced that "the girl" would play "the most difficult pieces by the greatest masters", while "the boy" would play a concerto on the violin and also repeat his Vienna trick of playing with the keyboard completely covered by a cloth. Finally "he will improvise out of his head, not only on the fortepiano but also on the organ...in all the keys, even the most difficult, that he may be asked".

Then the family took another riverboat to Koblenz, thence to Bonn and Cologne. At Aachen a performance was given before Princess Anna Amalia of Prussia, the sister of Frederick the Great. The princess tried to persuade Leopold to abandon his itinerary and go to Berlin, but Leopold resisted. "She has no money," he wrote to Hagenauer, recounting that she had repaid the performance with kisses. "Howbeit, neither mine host nor the postmaster are to be contented with kisses."Blom, p. 17 The next stage of the journey took them to the Austrian Netherlands,This area corresponds roughly to present-day Belgium and Luxembourg. Sadie, p. 46 where they visited Liège before arriving in the regional capital, Brussels, on 5 October. After a long wait for the governor-general, Prince Charles of Lorraine, to summon them ("His highness the prince does nothing but hunt, gobble and swill", wrote Leopold to Hagenauer), a grand concert was held in the prince's presence on 7 November. On the 15th the family departed for Paris.

During the long hiatus in Brussels, Wolfgang turned his attention briefly from performing to composing. On 14 October he finished an Allegro for harpsichord, which would later be incorporated into the C major sonata, K.6,"K" refers to the catalogue of Mozart's works, completed in 1862 by Ludwig von Köchel and revised several times subsequently. which he completed in Paris.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e6151613b3a5854af17db8a3b49161c6" name="Goethe" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/e6151613b3a5854af17db8a3b49161c6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>