<document id="681b873f7f4353f8bcb0feb7d51111bc-5.9" name="Bedřich_Smetana" cat="20">
<text>
In 1861, it was announced that a Provisional Theatre would be built in Prague, as a home for Czech opera.The official title for this theatre was the "Royal Provincial Czech Theatre" ( (Section 4) Smetana saw this as an opportunity to write and stage opera that would reflect Czech national character, similar to the portrayals of Russian life in Mikhail Glinka's operas. He hoped that he might be considered for the theatre's conductorship, but the post went to Jan Nepomuk Maýr, apparently because the conservative faction in charge of the project considered Smetana a "dangerous modernist", in thrall to avant garde composers such as Liszt and Wagner.Clapham (1972), pp. 32–33Large, p. 126 Smetana then turned his attention to an opera competition, organised by Count Jan von Harrach, which offered prizes of 600 gulden each for the best comic and historical operas based on Czech culture.  With no useful model on which to base his work—Czech opera as a genre scarcely existed—Smetana had to create his own style. He engaged Karel Sabina, his comrade from the 1848 barricades, as his librettist,Large, pp. 140–43 and received Sabina's text in February 1862, a story of the 13th century invasion of Bohemia by Otto of Brandenburg. In April 1863 he submitted the score, under the title of ''The Brandenburgers in Bohemia''.  


At this stage in his career, Smetana's command of the Czech language was poor. His generation of Czechs was educated in German,Grout, p. 532 and he had difficulty expressing himself in his native tongue. (Section 4) To overcome these linguistic deficiencies he studied Czech grammar, and made a point of writing and speaking in Czech as his daily norm.  He had become Chorus Master of the nationalistic Hlahol Choral Society soon after his return from Sweden, and as his fluency in the Czech language developed he composed patriotic choruses for the Society; ''The Three Riders'' and ''The Renegade'' were performed at concerts in early 1863.Large, pp. 121–25 In March of that year Smetana was elected president of the music section of Umělecká Beseda, a society for Czech artists.  By 1864 he was proficient enough in the Czech language to be appointed as music critic to the main Czech language newspaper ''Národní listy''.Newmarch, p. 62 Meanwhile, Bettina had given birth to another daughter, Božena. Clapham (1972), p. 33

On 23 April 1864 Smetana conducted Berlioz's choral symphony ''Roméo et Juliette'' at a concert celebrating the Shakespeare tercentenary, adding to the programme his own ''March for the Shakespearean Festival''.  That year, Smetana's bid to become Director of the Prague Conservatory failed. He had set high hopes on this appointment: "My friends are trying to persuade me that this post might have been especially created for me," he wrote to a Swedish friend.Large, p. 134 His hopes were again dashed by his affiliation with the perceived radical Liszt, the appointing committee choosing the  conservative patriot Josef Krejčí for the post.Clapham (1980), p. 394

Almost three years passed before Smetana was declared the winner of Harrach's opera competition. Before then, on 5 January 1866, ''The Brandenburgers'' had been performed to an enthusiastic reception at the Provisional Theatre—over strong opposition from Maýr, who had refused to rehearse or conduct the piece. The idiom was too advanced for Maýr's liking, and the opera was eventually staged under the composer's own direction. "I was called on stage nine times," Smetana wrote, recording that the house was sold out and that the critics were full of praise.Large, p. 145 Music historian Rosa Newmarch believes that, although ''The Brandenburgers'' has not stood the test of time, it contains all the germs of Smetana's operatic art.Newmarch, p. 64
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6f91c269289c137af0ea68f1d6aa4cda" name="Na_Rejdišti_str,_Prague_Old_Town" sectnum="5.9#1">../img/6f91c269289c137af0ea68f1d6aa4cda.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>