<document id="681b873f7f4353f8bcb0feb7d51111bc-3.6" name="Bedřich_Smetana" cat="20">
<text>
In the years between 1854 and 1856 Smetana suffered a series of personal blows. In July 1854 his second daughter, Gabriela, died of tuberculosis. A year later his eldest daughter Bedřiška, who at the age of four was showing signs of musical precocity, died of scarlet fever.Clapham (1972), p. 22 Smetana wrote his Piano Trio in G minor as a tribute to her memory; it was performed in Prague on 3 December 1855 and, according to the composer, was received "harshly" by the critics, although Liszt praised it.Large, pp. 63–65 Smetana's sorrows continued; just after Bedřiška's death a fourth daughter, Kateřina, had been born but she, too, died in June 1856. By this time Smetana's wife Kateřina had also been diagnosed with tuberculosis. 

In July 1856 Smetana received news of the death in exile of his revolutionary friend Karel Havlíček.Large, pp. 67–69 The political climate in Prague was a further source of gloom; hopes of a more enlightened government and social reform following Franz Josef's accession in 1848 had faded as Austrian absolutism reasserted itself under Baron Alexander von Bach.  Despite the good name of the Piano Institute, Smetana's status as a concert pianist was generally considered to be below that of contemporaries such as Alexander Dreyschock. Critics acknowledged Smetana's "delicate, crystalline touch", closer in style to Chopin than Liszt, but believed that his physical frailty was a serious drawback to his concert-playing ambitions. His main performance success during this period was his playing of Mozart's D minor Piano Concerto at a concert celebrating the centenary of Mozart's birth, in January 1856. His disenchantment with Prague was growing and, perhaps influenced by Dreyschock's accounts of opportunities to be found in Sweden, Smetana decided to seek success there. On 11 October 1856, after writing to his parents that "Prague did not wish to acknowledge me, so I left it", he departed for Gothenburg. (Section 3)
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ea33fe01c2e68d3c0a57f1845109b370" name="Smetana1854portrait" sectnum="3.6#1">../img/ea33fe01c2e68d3c0a57f1845109b370.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>