<document id="681b873f7f4353f8bcb0feb7d51111bc-6.13" name="Bedřich_Smetana" cat="20">
<text>
In worsening health, Smetana continued to compose. In June 1876 he, Bettina and their two daughters left Prague for Jabkenice, the home of his eldest daughter Žofie where, in tranquil surroundings, Smetana was able to work undisturbed.Steen, p. 702 Before leaving Prague he had begun a cycle of six symphonic poems, called ''Má vlast'' ("My Fatherland"),Originally, the work was entitled simply ''Vlast'' ("Fatherland"). The pronoun had been added by May 1883. Large, pp. 266–67 and had completed the first two, ''Vyšehrad'' and ''Vltava'', which had both been performed in Prague during 1875.Clapham (1972), p. 47 In Jabkenice Smetana composed four more movements, the complete cycle being first performed on 5 November 1882 under the baton of Adolf Čech. Other major works composed in these  years were the E minor String Quartet, ''From My Life'', a series of Czech dances for piano, several choral pieces and three more operas: ''The Kiss'', ''The Secret'' and ''The Devil's Wall'', all of which received their first performances  between 1876 and 1882. (Section 5)

The long-delayed premiere of Smetana's opera ''Libuše'' finally arrived when the National Theatre opened on 11 June 1881. He had not initially been given tickets, but at the last minute was asked into the theatre director's box. The audience received the work enthusiastically, and Smetana was called to the stage repeatedly.Clapham (1972), p. 51Large, pp. 222–23 Shortly after this event the new theatre was  destroyed by fire; despite his infirmities, Smetana helped to raise funds for the rebuilding.Steen, pp. 702–03  The restored theatre reopened on 18 November 1883, again with ''Libuše''

These years saw Smetana's growing recognition as the principal exponent of Czech national music. This status was celebrated by several events during Smetana's final years. On 4 January 1880 a special concert in Prague marked the 50th anniversary of his first public performance; Smetana attended, and played his Piano Trio in G minor from 1855. In May 1882 ''The Bartered Bride'' was given its 100th performance, an unprecedented event in the  history of Czech opera, and so popular that a repeat "100th performance" was staged. A gala concert and banquet was arranged to honour Smetana's 60th birthday in March 1884, but he was too ill to attend.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4a4b3cff36bec3f7aa1ae37744f0e6c8" name="Národní_divadlo_prg" sectnum="6.13#1">../img/4a4b3cff36bec3f7aa1ae37744f0e6c8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>