<document id="681b873f7f4353f8bcb0feb7d51111bc-4.7" name="Bedřich_Smetana" cat="20">
<text>
Smetana initially went to Gothenburg without Kateřina. Writing to Liszt, he said that the people there were  musically unsophisticated, but he saw this as an opportunity "for an impact I could never have achieved in Prague." Within a few weeks of his arrival he had given his first recital, opened a music school which was rapidly overwhelmed by applications,Large, pp. 71–75 and become conductor of the Gothenburg Society for Classical Choral Music. In a few months Smetana had achieved both professional and social recognition in the city, although he found little time for composition; two intended orchestral works, provisionally entitled ''Frithjof'' and ''The Viking's Voyage'', were sketched but abandoned.Large. p. 78 

In summer 1857 Smetana came home to Prague and found Kateřina in failing health.  In June, Smetana's father František died.Clapham (1972), p. 25   That autumn Smetana returned to Gothenburg,  with Kateřina and their surviving daughter Žofie,  but before doing so he visited Liszt in Weimar. The occasion was the Karl August Goethe-Schiller Jubilee celebrations; Smetana attended performances of Liszt's ''Faust Symphony'' and the symphonic poem ''Die Ideale'', which invigorated and inspired him.Large, p. 79 Liszt was Smetana's principal teacher throughout the latter's creative life, and at this time was crucially able to revive his spirits and rescue him from the relative artistic isolation of Gothenburg.

Back in Sweden, Smetana found among his new pupils  a young housewife, Fröjda Benecke, who briefly became his muse and his mistress. In her honour Smetana transcribed two songs from Schubert's ''Die schöne Müllerin'' cycle, and transformed one of his own early piano pieces into a polka entitled ''Vision at the Ball''.Large, pp. 80–82 He also began composing on a more expansive scale. In 1858 he completed the symphonic poem ''Richard III'', his first major orchestral composition since the ''Triumphal Symphony''. He followed  this with  ''Wallenstein's Camp'', inspired by Friedrich Schiller's  ''Wallenstein'' drama trilogy,Newmarch, p. 60 and began a third symphonic poem ''Hakon Jarl'', based on the tragic drama by Danish poet Adam Gottlob Oehlenschläger. Smetana also wrote a two large-scale piano works: ''Macbeth and the Witches'', and an Étude in C in the style of Liszt.Large, pp. 84–94
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b03aa2420a00dd97ca169ccc6e118708" name="Göteborg" sectnum="4.7#1">../img/b03aa2420a00dd97ca169ccc6e118708.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>