<document id="681b873f7f4353f8bcb0feb7d51111bc-9" name="Bedřich_Smetana" cat="20">
<text>
Smetana's biographers describe him as physically frail and unimpressive in appearance, yet at least in his youth he had  a ''joie-de-vivre'' which women evidently found attractive. Large, p. 3 and p. 10 He was also excitable, passionate and strong-willed, determined to make his career in music whatever the hardships, over the wishes of his father who wanted him to become a brewer or a civil servant. Throughout his career he stood his ground; when under the severest of criticism for the "Wagnerism" in ''Dalibor'' he responded by writing ''Libuše'', even more firmly based on the  scale and concept of Wagnerian music drama.Large, p. 205 His personal life became stressful; his marriage to Bettina was loveless, and effectively broke down altogether in the years of illness and relative poverty towards the end of his life.Large, pp. 304–05 Little of his relationships with his children is recorded, although it is reported that, on the day that he was transferred to the asylum, Žofie was "crying as though her heart would break".Large, p. 391

There is broad agreement among most commentators that Smetana created a canon of Czech opera where none had previously existed, and that he developed a style of music in all his compositions that equated with the emergent Czech national spirit.Clapham (1972), p. 123Large, preface p. xvii A modified view is presented by music writer Michael Steen, who questions whether "nationalistic music" can in fact exist: "We should recognise that, whereas music is infinitely expressive, on its own it is not good at describing concrete, earthly objects or concepts."Steen, pp. 690–91 He concludes that much is dependent upon what listeners are conditioned to hear.

According to musicologist John Tyrrell, Smetana's close identification with Czech nationalism, and the tragic circumstances of his last years, have tended to affect the objectivity with which his work has been assessed, particularly in his native land. Tyrrell argues that the almost iconic status awarded to Smetana in his homeland "monumentalized him into a figure where any criticism of his life or work was discouraged" by the Czech authorities, even as late as the last part of the 20th century. As a result, Tyrrell claims, a view of Czech music has been propagated which downplays the contributions of contemporaries and successors such as Dvořák, Janáček, Josef Suk and other lesser-known figures. This is at odds with perceptions in the outside world, where Dvořák is far more frequently played and much better known. Harold Schonberg observes that "Smetana was the one who founded Czech music, but Antonín Dvořák ... was the one who popularized it."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5e5f60c8d27045ac6d7f996bc925cf84" name="Prague_Vltava_2001" sectnum="9#1">../img/5e5f60c8d27045ac6d7f996bc925cf84.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>