<document id="681b873f7f4353f8bcb0feb7d51111bc-5.11" name="Bedřich_Smetana" cat="20">
<text>
Early in his conductorship Smetana had made a powerful enemy in František Pivoda, the Director of the Prague School of Singing. Formerly a supporter of Smetana's, Pivoda was aggrieved when the conductor recruited singing talent from abroad rather than from Pivoda's school.Steen, p. 701Clapham (1980) p. 394 In an increasingly bitter public correspondence, Pivoda claimed that Smetana was using his position to further his own career, at the expense of other composers.Clapham (1972), pp. 38–40 


Pivoda then took  issue with ''Dalibor'', calling it an example of extreme "Wagnerism" and thus, unsuited as a model for Czech national opera.Newmarch, p. 71 "Wagnerism" meant the adoption of Wagner's theories of a continuous role for the orchestra and the building of an integrated musical drama, rather than a stringing together of lyrical numbers. The Provisional Theatre's chairman, František Rieger, had first accused Smetana of Wagnerist tendencies after the first performance of ''The Brandenburgers'', and the issue eventually divided Prague's musical society. Music critic Otakar Hostinský believed that Wagner's theories should be the basis of the national opera, and argued that ''Dalibor'' was the beginning of the "correct" direction. The opposite camp, led by Pivoda, supported the principles of Italian opera, in which the voice rather than the orchestra was the predominant dramatic device. 

Even within the theatre itself there was division. Rieger led a campaign to eject Smetana from the conductorship and reappoint Maýr, and in December 1872 a petition signed by 86 subscribers to the theatre called for Smetana's resignation. Strong support from vice-chairman Antonín Čísek, and an ultimatum from prominent musicians among whom was Antonín Dvořák, ensured Smetana's survival. In January 1873 he was reappointed, with a bigger salary and increased responsibility as Artistic Director.

Smetana gradually brought more operas by emergent Czech composers to the theatre, but little of his own work. By 1872 he had completed his monumental fourth opera, ''Libuše'', his most ambitious work to date,Clapham (1972), p. 99 but was withholding its premiere for the future opening of the National Theatre.Large, p. 220  The machinations of Pivoda and his supporters  distracted Smetana from composition, and he had further vexation when ''The Bartered Bride'' was produced in St Petersburg, in January 1871. Although the audience was enthusiastic, press reports were hostile, one describing the work as "no better than that of a gifted fourteen-year-old boy."Large, p. 171 Smetana was deeply offended, and blamed his old adversary, Balakirev, for inciting negative feelings against the opera.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8f3ad6a460710ac544c7c15180570f78" name="Richard_Wagner,_Paris,_1860" sectnum="5.11#1">../img/8f3ad6a460710ac544c7c15180570f78.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>