<document id="681b873f7f4353f8bcb0feb7d51111bc-8.18" name="Bedřich_Smetana" cat="20">
<text>
Smetana had virtually  no precursors in Czech opera apart from František Škroup, whose works had rarely lasted beyond one or two performances. In his mission to create a new canon, rather than using traditional folksong Smetana turned to the popular dance music of his youth, especially the polka, to establish his link with the vernacular. (Section 6) He drew  on existing European traditions, notably Slavonic and French, but made only scarce use of arias, preferring to base his scores on ensembles and choruses.Grout, p. 534



Although a follower of Wagner's reforms of the operatic genre, which he believed would be its salvation, Newmarch, p. 65 Smetana rejected accusations of excessive Wagnerism, claiming that he was sufficiently occupied with "Smetanism, for that is the only honest style!"Letter to Adolf Cech 4, December 1882, quoted in Clapham (1972), p. 100 The predominantly "national" character of the first four operas is tempered by the lyrical romanticism of those written later,Clapham (1972), p. 104 particularly  the last three, composed in the years of Smetana's  deafness. The first of this final trio, ''The Kiss'', written when Smetana was receiving painful medical treatment is described by Newmarch as a work of serene  beauty, in which tears and smiles alternate throughout the score.Newmarch, pp. 83–84 Smetana's librettist for "The Kiss" was the young feminist Eliška Krásnohorská, who also supplied the texts for his final two operas. She dominated the ailing composer, who had no say in the subject-matter, the voice types or the balance between solos, duets and ensembles. Nevertheless, critics have noted few signs of a decline in Smetana's powers in these works, while his increasing proficiency in the Czech language meant that his settings of the language are much superior to those of his earlier operas.

Smetana's eight operas created the bedrock of the Czech opera repertory, but of these only ''The Bartered Bride'' is performed regularly outside the composer's homeland. After reaching Vienna in 1892,  and London in 1895, it rapidly became part of the repertory of every major opera company worldwide. Newmarch argues that ''The Bartered Bride'', while not a "gem of the first order", is nevertheless "a perfectly cut and polished stone of its kind."Newmarch, p. 67 Its trademark overture, which Newmarch says "lifts us off our feet with its madcap vivacity", was composed in a piano version before Smetana received the draft libretto. Clapham believes that this has few precedents in the entire history of opera.Clapham (1972), p. 94  Smetana himself was later inclined to disparage his achievement: "''The Bartered Bride'' was merely child's play, written straight off the reel". In the view of German critic William Ritter, Smetana's creative powers reached their zenith with his third opera, ''Dalibor''.Newmarch, p. 72
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="868919b97755e3d8f34e33c722c3873a" name="Prodana_cover_1919" sectnum="8.18#1">../img/868919b97755e3d8f34e33c722c3873a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>