<document id="681d9191dcea58f4c270203455cfe13a-6" name="Sheffield_Wednesday_F.C." cat="26">
<text>
Wednesday have enjoyed good support despite their recent decline in fortunes. They had the highest average attendance during both seasons in Division Two/League One  and continued the trend when returning to the Championship with the highest attendances in that division.  At the 2005 playoff final Wednesday took over 42,000 fans to the Millennium Stadium., which remains the highest number of supporters any football team has taken to the Millenium Stadium.

One of their most famous fans is Paul Gregory. Known to many as "Tango" or "Tango Man" due to his similarity to a character appearing in advertisements for the eponymous soft drink in the 1990s, he takes his shirt off for every away match. He achieved national fame during the 1990s appearing on ''The Big Breakfast'' and ''The Sunday Show''. Another famous Wednesday institution was the Wednesday Band, a brass band that played during matches. Although unpopular amongst many rival fans (and some home fans), they have released several records and have been invited to regularly attend England matches. They were often banned from away grounds and suffered the same fate at home until March 22 2009, when the band returned to Hillsborough. The future of the band is unknown, their return was a success and now decisions have to made at boardroom level to see if their position back on the Kop is long-term.

Supporters' groups include Wednesdayite, an independent football supporters' organisation which owns over 10% of Sheffield Wednesday Football Club and The London Owls, an active supporters' club for Wednesday fans living in London and South East England.

Sheffield Wednesday have had a large variety of fanzines over the years; examples include ''Just Another Wednesday'', ''Out of the Blue'', ''Spitting Feathers'', ''Boddle'', ''A View From The East Bank'', ''Cheat!'' and ''War of the Monster Trucks'', which acquired its name from the programme that Yorkshire Television elected to show instead of the celebrations after the 1991 League Cup victory over Manchester United.

Below are recent average attendances at Hillsborough:
* 2008–09: 21,542 (Football League Championship) second tier
* 2007–08: 21,410 (Football League Championship) second tier
* 2006–07: 23,638 (Football League Championship) second tier
* 2005–06: 24,853 (Football League Championship) second tier
* 2004–05: 23,107 (Football League One) third tier
* 2003–04: 22,336 (Division Two) third tier
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e979c12bbeb963fef60c63b33fac1ace" name="Sheffield_Wednesday_fans" sectnum="6#1">../img/e979c12bbeb963fef60c63b33fac1ace.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>