<document id="682d47cfc2525e53766afe833dbe8712-1" name="Barn_Swallow" cat="3">
<text>
The adult male Barn Swallow of the nominate subspecies ''H. r. rustica'' is 17–19 cm (6.7–7.5 in) long including 2–7 cm (0.8–2.8 in) of elongated outer tail feathers. It has a wingspan of 32–34.5 cm (12.6–13.6 in) and weighs 16–22 g (0.56–0.78 oz). It has steel blue upperparts and a rufous forehead, chin and throat, which are separated from the off-white underparts by a broad dark blue breast band. The outer tail feathers are elongated, giving the distinctive deeply forked "swallow tail." There is a line of white spots across the outer end of the upper tail. p1061–1064 

The female is similar in appearance to the male, but the tail streamers are shorter, the blue of the upperparts and breast band is less glossy, and the underparts more pale. The juvenile is browner and has a paler rufous face and whiter underparts. It also lacks the long tail streamers of the adult.

The song of the Barn Swallow is a cheerful warble, often ending with ''su-seer'' with the second note higher than the first but falling in pitch. Calls include ''witt'' or ''witt-witt'' and a loud ''splee-plink'' when excited. The alarm calls include a sharp ''siflitt'' for predators like cats and a ''flitt-flitt'' for birds of prey like the Hobby. This species is fairly quiet on the wintering grounds.

The distinctive combination of a red face and blue breast band render the adult Barn Swallow easy to distinguish from the African ''Hirundo'' species and from the Welcome Swallow (''Hirundo neoxena'') with which its range overlaps in Australasia. In Africa the short tail streamers of the juvenile Barn Swallow invite confusion with juvenile Red-chested Swallow (''Hirundo lucida''), but the latter has a narrower breast band and more white in the tail.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1e92c33a20fba5cc0164cad4bea6c5ae" name="Barn_Swallow_800" sectnum="1#1">../img/1e92c33a20fba5cc0164cad4bea6c5ae.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>