<document id="6851fb450fd1e824b599b2a000360252-2.6" name="Bids_for_the_2012_Summer_Olympics" cat="26">
<text>
In early 2003, Madrid beat out Seville to represent the country on the international Olympic bidding stage. Madrid presented an above average bid where almost all sports venues were located within three clusters close to each other and to the city's centre. Several existing facilities ensured low expenditures would be sufficient to host the Olympics, while new and permanent sports venues would have provided a lasting Olympic legacy to the city. For the first time in the history of the Games, the transportation and accommodation of the hundreds of thousands of tourists gathering in the capital would be entirely dependent on the public transport infrastructure. All venues and public transports would have run on renewable energies, turning the Games of Madrid into "green Olympics". The city had experience in hosting numerous European and World championships and cups in several Olympic sports. Of the five candidate bids, Madrid's was the most supported by its city and national population, and its promotion was boosted with the support of the former IOC president Juan Antonio Samaranch, who lobbied votes for the Spanish capital. During the last stages of the bidding process, IOC member Prince Albert of Monaco questioned the security of Madrid, remembering the Al Qaeda terrorist attacks which took place in the city on 11 March 2004, and killed 191 people. The Spanish delegation found this remark especially offensive and regarded the final election of London over Madrid as a consequence of Albert's words. On 7 July 2005, merely a day after the announcement of London as the winning candidate to host the 2012 Olympic Games, there were terrorist attacks on London's public transport infrastructure, killing 52 people.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c771de9552ca20d92164197b704ab13d" name="Madrid2012_palaciocorreos" sectnum="2.6#1">../img/c771de9552ca20d92164197b704ab13d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>