<document id="6884cf25d9a9e12073e8a9166bef2230-1" name="Simon_Byrne" cat="26">
<text>
During the first half of the 19th century, pugilism (better known as prize-fighting) held a curious position in British society. Though supported by members of the establishment from the royal princes downwards, it was illegal. It has been arguedAnderson, Jack, , School of Law, University of Limerick, Ireland. Accessed 28 February 2006. that the reason for the illegality was less concern for the welfare of the individual pugilist than concerns arising from the civil unrest, riots and tumult which often arose following a planned fight. Despite the ban, matches were publicised by posters in public places, with the venue changed at the last minute to avoid the authorities&mdash; which often led to further public inconvenience and disturbance.

Rules governing the sport were based on those drawn up by Jack Broughton in 1743, which were ambiguous and often open to vague interpretation. Wrestling, biting, gouging of eyes and hitting below the belt  were often ignored by the referee. The sport enjoyed an unprecedented surge in popularity during the Regency period when it was openly patronised by the Prince Regent and his brothers. Championship boxing matches acquired a louche reputation as the places to be seen by the wealthy upper classes. Thus a match would often be attended by thousands of people, many of whom had wagered money on the outcome. The Duke of Cumberland (an uncle of King George III) was reported to have bet thousands of pounds on the legendary boxer Jack Broughton., International Boxing Hall of Fame. Accessed 27 March 2006.

By the 1820s, boxing had become a nest of "gambling related corruption". The epitome of this era was the championship reign of Jem Ward: a fighter known to lose a fight for a fee, who on one occasion admitted taking £100, equivalent to several thousand pounds today. By 1830, the sport had become openly known for its corruption; disqualification and open cheating were common. The gang of "supporters" which followed Ward's brother Nick often openly intimidated the referee into disqualifying his partners., The Cyber Boxing Zone. It was against this background that Simon Byrne earned his living.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="31fee02addbec555a777e4e5a3d8b032" name="Ward_painting" sectnum="1#1">../img/31fee02addbec555a777e4e5a3d8b032.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>