<document id="68927b0249440979a4243b875e821941-1.4" name="Mutual_Broadcasting_System" cat="19">
<text>
Toward the end of 1950, the executors of the estate of Thomas S. Lee (the son of Don Lee, who had died in 1934) decided to liquidate the estate's interests in the broadcasting field. The Don Lee Broadcasting System, with its major station groups KHJ in Los Angeles and KFRC in San Francisco and its shares in the Mutual Broadcasting System, was sold to General Tire (which already had a stake in Mutual via its Yankee Network holdings)."Don Lee Sale Approval Asked," ''Los Angeles Times'', November 21, 1950; "Sale of Don Lee System Approved: Cash Payment of $12,320,000 Involved in FCC Decision," ''Los Angeles Times'', December 28, 1950. A scholarly journal article claims that the Don Lee purchase brought with it a "19 percent interest in the Mutual Broadcasting System," which would be down from the 25 percent of the 1940 restructuring. However, the reliability of this source is questionable, as it incorrectly claims in the same paragraph that the "East Coast-based Yankee Network ... was also acquired at this time" by General Tire (Crane, Marie Brenne, "Radio Station KGB and the Development of Commercial Radio In San Diego," ''Journal of San Diego History'', vol. 26, no. 1  (available )). As detailed above, General Tire in fact acquired Yankee in 1943. Around the same time, MBS acquired the television broadcast rights to the World Series and All-Star Game for the next six years. Mutual may have been reindulging in TV network dreams or simply taking advantage of a long-standing business relationship; in either case, the broadcast rights were sold to NBC in time for the following season's games at an enormous profit.Marshall (1998), 384; Day (2004), 230–231. Note that Marshall and Day describe the details of the original deal very differently, agreeing only that it was for six years at $1 million a year. Marshall says that a contract was signed on December 26, 1950, between baseball's major leagues, in the person of Commissioner Happy Chandler, on one side and MBS and the Gillette Safety Razor Company on the other for the television rights. Day says baseball's contract was solely with Gillette, that it was for both radio and television rights, and that Gillette "ess than a year after acquiring the broadcast rights ... transferred" them to Mutual. They also characterize the original contract rather differently. Marshall calls it "one of the outstanding achievements of the Chandler commissionership." Day credits Chandler with "deftly avoid a financial crisis," but agrees with the prevailing opinion of the players that Chandler "vastly underestimated the value" of the rights. The fact, which Day provides, that Mutual sold the package to NBC for $4 million a year lends support to his position.

Early in 1952, General Tire purchased the Bamberger Broadcasting Service from R.H. Macy and Company. With the deal, General Tire acquired the WOR radio and TV stations and the rights to the name General Teleradio, under which the company merged its broadcasting interests as a new division (Bamberger had previously sold its TV station in the nation's capital, WOIC, to CBS and the ''Washington Post'')."Radio-TV Merger Approved By F.C.C.; Deal Covers Macy's Transfer of WOR Interests to General Tire's Don Lee System", ''New York Times,'' January 18, 1952; "Earnings Fall 5% for Macy System; Television's High Cost for Subsidiary, General Teleradio, Cuts Consolidated Net," ''New York Times'', October 11, 1950; Howard (1979), 150–152. Most importantly, as far as the future of the Mutual Broadcasting System was concerned, WOR's founding shares in the network, when added to the Yankee and Don Lee holdings, gave General Tire majority control of MBS."General Tire Gets Control of M. B. S.; Shareholders at Meeting Vote 2-for-1 Stock Split—Company Buys More TV Stations," ''New York Times'', April 2, 1952. That same year, NBC began its attempts to win the television rights to ''Queen for a Day'' from Mutual. As a measure of the afternoon show's success, its audience at its new Los Angeles home, General Teleradio/Don Lee's KHJ-TV, was triple that of the city's six other stations combined.Cassidy (2005), 41. Mutual might not have had a TV network, but it controlled one of the most profitable properties in the early history of commercial television.Mutual does have a TV network in the realm of imagination. ''The Amazing Adventures of Kavalier & Clay'', by novelist Michael Chabon, refers to ''The Escapist'', a show starring Peter Graves that ran from 1951 to 1955 on the Mutual Television Network (596).

Mutual was at this point the largest U.S. radio network in affiliate numbers, by far—it had 560, almost three times as many as its most powerful competitors, CBS (194) and NBC (191).Cox (2002), 178. See also Cox, 127–128, for the 1950 and 1960 figures for the four major networks. Note that in August 1951, the low-powered, baseball-oriented Liberty Broadcasting System (LBS) had 431 affiliates (Garay , 32). In 1955, General Tire expanded its media holdings by acquiring RKO Radio Pictures from Howard Hughes, only to close the movie studio a year and a half later (General Teleradio, renamed RKO Teleradio after the acquisition, would soon be known as RKO General). General Tire also decided to spin off its holdings in Mutual and sell it as a programming service even as it retained the stations that had given it control. Indeed, in 1956, General purchased a governing interest in yet another Mutual shareholder, Western Ontario Broadcasting, and its station in Windsor, CKLW. In July 1957, General Tire sold the Mutual Broadcasting business to a group led by Dr. Armand Hammer."Sale of Mutual Expected Today; Radio Network Is Going to Group From West Coast," ''New York Times'', July 17, 1957. 

The network soon changed hands again: in September 1958, it was acquired by the Scranton Corporation."Mutual Network Brings 2 Million; Radio System Is Purchased by Scranton Corporation in Move for Expansion," ''New York Times'', September 12, 1958. Scranton was under the control of the F.L. Jacobs Company, whose chairman, Alexander Guterma, envisioned a media empire uniting Mutual with another recent purchase, the Hal Roach movie studio. After being questioned by federal investigators in February 1959 about financial improprieties, Guterma stepped down. Mutual, by this point, was floundering. For some years it had been run by owners who were either uninterested (General Tire, Armand Hammer) or now, as a growing amount of evidence would show, criminal. Mutual was also confronted with the situation the entire industry was facing: major advertisers were abandoning radio for television. Commercial rates had been cut. Limited sponsorship packages had been introduced, in which an advertiser could back a show for an abbreviated period rather than an entire season—but there was no reversing the trend. The networks were left with the bills for an increasing number of nonsponsored programs, known as "sustaining" shows in the industry.See Bareiss (1998), 379–382; in particular, 381, for the development of limited sponsorship. The loss of mainstay advertisers was accompanied by what historian Ronald Garay describes as the "mass desertion of network radio talent, management and technicians for television .... hese people were taking with them the programming that had popularized the radio networks."Garay (1992), 64.

Under its new chairman, Hal Roach Jr., F.L. Jacobs put Mutual into Chapter 11 bankruptcy. In September 1959, Guterma, Roach, and Garland Culpepper, a Scranton Corp. vice president, were indicted for failing to register as "foreign agents"; they were charged with secretly accepting money from Dominican Republic dictator Rafael Trujillo that previous January in return for favorable coverage of the country and its government on Mutual news programs.Ward (2005), 152–155; "The Price of Publicity," ''Time'', September 14, 1959 (available ). It was never proven that Guterma, who was identified as the primary player on Mutual's side and pleaded no contest to the charge, actually fulfilled his part of the deal and arranged for slanted coverage. Nonetheless, the incident led to a reported 130 stations cutting their affiliation with Mutual.Cox (2002), 127. Whether precipitated by the scandal or not, among the stations cutting its ties with Mutual in 1959 was one of the network's two original flagships, WOR.Jaker et al. (1998), 155. Businessman Albert G. McCarthy, meanwhile, had taken over the network, arranging to settle its debts while seeking an owner interested in running it on an ongoing basis."Mutual Network 3 Million in Debt; Files Petition in U.S. Court Seeking Settlement While Continuing in Control," ''New York Times'', July 2, 1959; "News of TV and Radio," ''New York Times'', July 5, 1959.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7fcec473062d49059c307a0cd0c7aaeb" name="MutualComo54a" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/7fcec473062d49059c307a0cd0c7aaeb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>