<document id="68927b0249440979a4243b875e821941-1.4.3" name="Mutual_Broadcasting_System" cat="19">
<text>
Before the Guterma fiasco, the network had maintained its reputation for running a strong news organization. As the conflict on the Korean peninsula began to heat up in mid-1950, Mutual started airing two special reports nightly on the situation, featuring the commentary of Major George Fielding Eliot, military analyst for CBS during World War II. By August, Mutual was represented by six correspondents in Korea, more than ABC or NBC.Bliss (1991), 258, 259. In June 1958, just a few months before the Scranton takeover, the network had launched a nightly 25-minute newscast, ''The World Today'', hosted by Westbrook Van Voorhis, famous as the voice of ''The March of Time''. On occasion, Mutual's commentary programs made the news: On March 11, 1954, Fulton Lewis Jr. featured Senator Joseph McCarthy as his guest, two days after the senator's ethics had been called into question on the TV show ''See It Now'', hosted by Edward R. Murrow. In his radio interview, McCarthy dismissed Murrow as "the extreme left-wing, bleeding-heart element of television."Doherty (2003), 184.

By the end of the 1950s, Mutual had forsworn original dramatic programming. Early in the decade, however, it picked up the adventure series ''Challenge of the Yukon'', which had originated at MBS cofounder WXYZ in 1938 after the station's departure from the network. The show, subsequently renamed ''Sergeant Preston of the Yukon'', ran on Mutual from January 1950 until its finale in June 1955. In 1950 as well, Mutual introduced radio listeners to adult science fiction with ''2000 Plus'', which first aired on March 15, almost a month before the premiere of NBC's similarly themed ''Dimension X''. ''The Shadow'''s long run finally ended in December 1954. In November 1957, Mutual aired the final episodes of its last two remaining half-hour original dramatic shows, ''Counterspy'' and ''Gang Busters'', both picked up from other networks earlier in the decade. It would be almost sixteen years before the network again aired a new dramatic series. In 1955, the famous comedy team Bob and Ray came over from NBC for a five-day-a-week afternoon show.Griffith, Benjamin,  entry in the ''St. James Encyclopedia of Pop Culture'' (2002). Kate Smith returned in 1958 for her final radio series, which ran from January to August. Sports began to occupy an increasing portion of Mutual's schedule: the network began regularly airing a Major League Baseball ''Game of the Day,'' every day except Sunday. This expansion into daily sports programming would run well into the 1960s.Garay (1992) says MBS launched its Game of the Day in 1949 (50). Gorman et al. (1994) say it was 1950 (91, 105). Garay indicates that the concept was picked up from the Liberty Broadcasting System, founded in 1947. Yet the  lists among famed broadcaster France Laux's credits "Mutual Game of the Day (1939-41, '44)." Retrieved 11/23/06. While baseball's World Series and All-Star Game would go to rival NBC in 1957, Mutual secured exclusive national radio rights the following year to Notre Dame football, which would remain a cornerstone for the rest of the network's existence. detailed report on ''Notre Dame Fighting Irish, The Official Athletic Site'', September 13, 1999. Note that this source refers to "Mutual/Westwood One" months after Mutual's dissolution had been announced. Retrieved 1/11/07. See also  excerpt from ''Notre Dame Odyssey'', by Herb Juliano; part of the ''Irish Legends'' website. Retrieved 1/11/07.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fc56549ccfe157dd00b0687c6cd2c5a1" name="MutualFisher54a" sectnum="1.4.3#1">../img/fc56549ccfe157dd00b0687c6cd2c5a1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>