<document id="68927b0249440979a4243b875e821941-1.2.1" name="Mutual_Broadcasting_System" cat="19">
<text>
On the programming front, 1936 saw Mutual launch the first network advice show, ''The Good Will Hour'', hosted by John J. Anthony and sponsored by  physical culture guru Bernarr Macfadden. The program was a new take on ''Ask Mister Anthony'', which had aired on a local New York station in 1932, "dedicated to helping the sufferers from an antiquated and outmoded domestic relations code." Anthony, whose real name was Lester Kroll, brought a wealth of relevant experience to his work—he had once been jailed for failing to make alimony payments.Hilmes (1997), 99–100; Jaker et al. (1998), 129. In July 1937 came the premiere of a seven-part adaptation of ''Les Misérables'', produced, written, and directed by Orson Welles and featuring many of his Mercury Theatre performers—Mercury's first appearance on the air. September 26, 1937, proved a particularly momentous date: that evening, ''The Shadow'' came to Mutual. The show would become a mainstay of the network for more than a decade and a half and one of the most popular programs in radio history. For the first year of its Mutual run, Welles provided the voice of The Shadow and his newly created alter ego, Lamont Cranston. He played the part anonymously at first. But, as one chronicler put it, "nothing to do with Welles could remain a secret for very long."Callow (1995), 321.

In April 1938, the network picked up ''The Green Hornet'' from former member WXYZ. Mutual gave the twice-a-week series its first national exposure until November 1939, when it switched to NBC Blue. (The series would return very briefly to Mutual in the fall of 1940). part of ''Jerry Haendiges' Vintage Radio Logs'' website. Retrieved 11/21/06. MBS also provided the national launching pad for ''Kay Kyser and His Kollege of Musical Knowledge;'' Kyser's enormous success at Mutual soon allowed his show to move to NBC and its much larger audience.McDougal (2001), 68. By May 1939, MBS was broadcasting the Indianapolis 500.''Highway Traveler'' vol. 11, no. 2 (April–May 1939), 27. There are anecdotal suggestions that the network aired the Indianapolis 500 in previous years, but to date no concrete evidence has been found. For later MBS coverage of the race, see  part of the ''Speedway Audio'' website archived via the Wayback Machine. Retrieved 10/29/09. That autumn, Mutual won exclusive broadcast rights to the World Series. As described in a 1943 Supreme Court ruling upholding the regulatory power of the Federal Communications Commission, Mutual "offered this program of outstanding national interest to stations throughout the country, including NBC and CBS affiliates in communities having no other stations. CBS and NBC immediately invoked the 'exclusive affiliation' clauses of their agreements with these stations, and as a result thousands of persons in many sections of the country were unable to hear the broadcasts of the games." This was the first example given in the ruling of "abuses" perpetrated by the two leading broadcast companies. Retrieved 11/22/06.

Mutual also began building a reputation as a strong news service, rivaling the industry leaders in quality if not budget. The broadcasts of WOR reporter Gabriel Heatter from the Lindbergh kidnapping "trial of the century" in 1935, heard over Mutual, were highly regarded; Heatter soon had his own regularly scheduled newscast, aired nationally five nights a week.Bliss (1991), 34, 36. In 1936, also via WOR, Mutual began broadcasting the reports of news commentator Raymond Gram Swing, who became one of the country's leading voices on foreign affairs.Bliss (1991), 60–61. In November 1937, conservative commentator Fulton Lewis Jr., heard five nights weekly from Mutual affiliate WOL, became the first national news personality to broadcast out of Washington, D.C.; he would remain with the network until his death almost three decades later.Nimmo and Newsome (1997), 173. In 1938, Mutual started rebroadcasting news reports from the BBC and English-language newscasts from the European mainland. The network also began employing its own reporters in Europe as the continent headed toward crisis, including John Steele, Waverly Root, Arthur Mann, and Victor Lusinchi. Among these was Sigrid Schultz, the first accomplished female foreign correspondent to appear on American news radio.Brown (1998), 180; Bliss (1991), 97–98.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="430ab8763ca1cf79f8a21c3edbde9b35" name="WellesShadow" sectnum="1.2.1#1">../img/430ab8763ca1cf79f8a21c3edbde9b35.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>