<document id="68927b0249440979a4243b875e821941-1.3.2" name="Mutual_Broadcasting_System" cat="19">
<text>
Offscreen, Mutual remained an enterprising broadcaster. In 1940, a program featuring Cedric Foster joined Mutual's respected schedule of news and opinion shows. Foster's claim to fame was as the first daytime commentator to be heard nationally on a daily basis.Bliss (1991), 65. Over the following half decade, Mutual's war coverage held its own with that of the wealthier networks, featuring field correspondents such as Henry Shapiro and Piet Van T Veer and commentators such as Cecil Brown, formerly of CBS.Brown (1998), 183, 190. At 2:26 p.m. Eastern time, on Sunday, December 7, 1941, Mutual flagship WOR interrupted a football game broadcast with a news flash reporting the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor. It was the initial public announcement of the attack heard on the U.S. mainland. The first bombs had dropped 63 minutes earlier.Bliss (1991), 135;  part of the ''Authentic History Center'' website. Retrieved 1/12/07. In May 1945, Sigrid Schultz reported from one of the last Nazi concentration camps to be discovered, Ravensbrück.Crook (1998), 206–207. The following month, ''Meet the Press'' premiered with Martha Rountree as moderator.Nimmo and Newsome (1997), 311. For a year and a half in the late 1940s, William Shirer came over from CBS to do current events commentary after his famous falling out with Edward Murrow.Bliss (1991), 202–203. In 1948, Mutual's four-part series ''To Secure These Rights'', dramatizing the findings of President Truman's Committee on Civil Rights, outraged many politicians and the network's own affiliates in the segregated South.Savage (1999), 345 n. 123.

In the field of entertainment, Mutual built on the incomparable success of ''The Shadow''. WGN's ''The Theater of the Air'', featuring hour-long opera and musical theater productions before a live audience, was broadcast for the first time in May 1940. By 1943, the weekly show was being recorded in front of houses 4,000 strong, gathered to see performances featuring a full orchestra and chorus. ''The Theater of the Air'' would run on Mutual through March 1955. part of the ''WGN Gold'' historical website;  part of ''Jerry Haendiges' Vintage Radio Logs'' website. Retrieved 11/21/06. Mutual provided an early national outlet for the influential, iconoclastic satirist Henry Morgan, whose show ''Here's Morgan'' began its network run in October 1940. Though ''The Lone Ranger'' moved over to NBC Blue in May 1942, within a few months Mutual had another reliable, and no less famous, action hero. ''The Adventures of Superman'', picked up from WOR, would run on the network from August 1942 to June 1949. In April 1943, Mutual launched what would turn into one of its longest-lasting shows: debuting as ''The Return of Nick Carter'' and later retitled ''Nick Carter, Master Detective'', it would be a network staple through September 1955. From May 1943 through May 1946, Mutual aired ''The New Adventures of Sherlock Holmes'', starring Basil Rathbone and Nigel Bruce. An earlier incarnation of the show had run briefly on the network in 1936; a less starry version would return to MBS from September 1947 through June 1949. part of ''Jerry Haendiges' Vintage Radio Logs'' website. Retrieved 11/21/06. ''The Mysterious Traveler'', a proto–''Twilight Zone'' anthology series, aired every week on Mutual from December 1943 until September 1952. 

In February 1946, MBS introduced a quiz show, ''Twenty Questions'', that would run for more than seven years. In October, the detective series ''Let George Do It'', starring Bob Bailey, launched as a Mutual/Don Lee presentation; it would also run into the mid-1950s. For two years, starting in 1946 as well, Steve Allen got his first network exposure on the Mutual/Don Lee morning show ''Smile Time'', out of Los Angeles's KHJ. In February 1947, the religiously oriented ''Family Theater'' premiered; with frequent appearances by major Hollywood stars, the series aired on Mutual for ten and a half years. That March, Kate Smith, a major star on CBS since 1931, moved over to Mutual. During most of her initial run at the network, which lasted until September 1951, she had two distinct weekday shows, each 15 minutes long: ''Kate Smith Speaks'', at noon, and ''Kate Smith Sings'', later in the hour.Dunning (1998), 382. The network gave an outlet to radio dramatist Wyllis Cooper and his highly regarded suspense anthology ''Quiet, Please'', which ran on Mutual from June 1947 to September 1948. It also aired actor Alan Ladd's similarly lauded drama about a crime-solving mystery novelist, ''Box 13'', which ran for precisely a year. Its 52 episodes, which aired every Sunday beginning August 22, 1948, were produced by Ladd's own company, Mayfair Productions.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="423c2dd21a7ebb0a0d5dfdc434adb0c5" name="MStrangerSession" sectnum="1.3.2#1">../img/423c2dd21a7ebb0a0d5dfdc434adb0c5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>