<document id="68fd6d945eeed458a81d50fb76119953-4" name="Martin_Brodeur" cat="26">
<text>
Martin and Melanie Dubois (a native of Saint-Liboire, Quebec, Canada) married in 1995 and have four children: Anthony, born in 1995; twin sons, William and Jeremy, born in 1996; and Annabelle Antoinette, born in 2002. Melanie filed for divorce during the 2003 playoffs amid reports that Martin was having an affair with Genevieve Nault, the wife of Melanie's brother. The incident added some fuel to the fire for hecklers during the playoffs. The reports proved to be true, as Martin and Genevieve got married in June 2008.

Brodeur is regarded as a brilliant chef and an engaging raconteur in his spare time. He has hosted a street hockey tournament in his hometown of St. Leonard, Quebec, for each of the Devils' Stanley Cup championships, where he plays his childhood position of forward. His oldest brother, Denis Jr., is a photographer like their father, and his other older brother, Claude, was a pitcher in the Montreal Expos' farm system. Martin also has two sisters, Line and Sylvie.

In 2005 Brodeur began co-authoring his autobiography, ''Brodeur: Beyond the Crease'', with long-time Toronto Star columnist and ESPN contributor Damien Cox, which was released in October 2006. Some of the things Brodeur talks about in the book are player salaries and contracts, NHL marketing, Lou Lamoriello, and the Devils' new arena in Newark, the Prudential Center. Brodeur also includes his views on the "new NHL" after the lockout, and how it affects his career. The book's photographs were shot by Martin's father, Denis.

Brodeur resides in West Orange, New Jersey, near the Devils former practice facility, South Mountain Arena.  According to his autobiography, he enjoys spending time in his native Montreal in the off-season, as well as playing golf at his country club, also in West Orange.

The official website of Brodeur, MartinBrodeur30.com, was launched before the start of the 2008–09 NHL season.  The website is available in both English and French (Brodeur's first language).  According to the site, Brodeur co-owns a business called "La Pizzeria Etc." with former teammate Sheldon Souray.  The idea came about after Souray was traded to play in Montreal, the city in which the business now operates.

Brodeur is a co-owner of the Spa d'Howard, also based in his native Quebec.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="efc5468852348e93f06c6954c0f9201e" name="Brodeurbook" sectnum="4#1">../img/efc5468852348e93f06c6954c0f9201e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>