<document id="693cbd06ca2c7d132bb4b649f303903f-3.12" name="Birmingham_campaign" cat="14">
<text>
On May 8 at 4 a.m., white business leaders agreed to most of the protesters' demands. Political leaders held fast, however.  The rift between the businessmen and the politicians became clear when business leaders admitted they could not guarantee the protesters' release from jail. On May 10, Fred Shuttlesworth and Martin Luther King told reporters that they had an agreement from the City of Birmingham to desegregate lunch counters, restrooms, drinking fountains and fitting rooms within 90 days, and to hire blacks in stores as salesmen and clerks. Those in jail would be released on bond or their own recognizance. Urged by Kennedy, the United Auto Workers, National Maritime Union, United Steelworkers Union, and the American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) raised $237,000 in bail money to free the demonstrators.Garrow, (1989) p. 182. Commissioner Connor and the outgoing mayor condemned the resolution.Nunnelley, p. 157.

On May 11, a bomb destroyed the Gaston Motel where King had been staying—and had left only hours before—and another damaged the house of A.D. King, Martin Luther King's brother. When police went to inspect the motel, they were met with rocks and bottles from neighborhood blacks. By May 13, three thousand federal troops were deployed to Birmingham to restore order, even though Alabama Governor George Wallace told President Kennedy that state and local forces were sufficient.Cotman, p. 89–90. Martin Luther King returned to Birmingham to stress nonviolence. Outgoing mayor Art Hanes left office after the Alabama State Supreme Court ruled that Albert Boutwell could take office on May 21, 1963. Upon picking up his last paycheck, Bull Connor remarked tearfully, "This is the worst day of my life."Nunnelley, p. 162. In June 1963, the Jim Crow signs regulating segregated public places in Birmingham were taken down.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2b6b5c5f8f45210d0b6bd398effc3bcd" name="04293v_cropped" sectnum="3.12#1">../img/2b6b5c5f8f45210d0b6bd398effc3bcd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>