<document id="693cbd06ca2c7d132bb4b649f303903f-2.5" name="Birmingham_campaign" cat="14">
<text>
Martin Luther King's presence in Birmingham was not welcomed by all in the black community.  A black attorney was quoted in ''Time'' magazine as saying, "The new administration should have been given a chance to confer with the various groups interested in change." Black hotel owner A. G. Gaston stated, "I regret the absence of continued communication between white and Negro leadership in our city." A white Jesuit priest assisting in desegregation negotiations attested, "These demonstrations are poorly timed and misdirected."



Protest organizers knew they would meet with violence from the Birmingham Police Department but chose a confrontational approach to get the attention of the federal government. Reverend Wyatt Tee Walker, one of the SCLC founders and the executive director from 1960–1964, planned the tactics of the direct action protests, specifically targeting Bull Connor's tendency to react to demonstrations with violence. "My theory was that if we mounted a strong nonviolent movement, the opposition would surely do something to attract the media, and in turn induce national sympathy and attention to the everyday segregated circumstance of a person living in the Deep South," Walker said. He headed the planning of what he called Project C, which stood for "confrontation". According to this historians Isserman and Kazin, “the demands on the city authorities were straightforward: desegregate the economic life of Birmingham – it’s restaurants, hotels, public toilets, and the unwritten policy of hiring blacks for menial jobs only”Maurice Isserman & Michael Kazin, ‘America Divided: The Civil War of the 1960s’, (Oxford, 2008), p.90.  

Organizers believed their phones were tapped, so to prevent their plans from being leaked and perhaps influencing the mayoral election, they used code words for demonstrations.Garrow, (1989) p. 175. The plan called for direct nonviolent action to attract media attention to "the biggest and baddest city of the South".Hampton, p. 126. In preparation for the protests, Walker timed the walking distance from the Sixteenth Street Baptist Church, headquarters for the campaign, to the downtown area. He surveyed the segregated lunch counters of department stores, and listed federal buildings as secondary targets should police block the protesters' entrance into primary targets such as stores, libraries, and all-white churches.Garrow, (1989) p. 176&ndash;177.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="657a7dc7ed7aaf459ac2f23b79684bb0" name="Sixteenth_Street_Baptist_Church_in_Birmingham" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/657a7dc7ed7aaf459ac2f23b79684bb0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>