<document id="693cbd06ca2c7d132bb4b649f303903f-3.9.3" name="Birmingham_campaign" cat="14">
<text>
A battle-hardened ''Huntley-Brinkley'' reporter later said that no military action he had witnessed had ever frightened or disturbed him as much as what he saw in Birmingham. Two out-of-town photographers in Birmingham that day were Charles Moore, who had previously worked with the ''Montgomery Advertiser'' and was now working for ''Life'' magazine, and Bill Hudson, with the Associated Press.  Moore was a Marine combat photographer who was "jarred" and "sickened" by the use of children and what the Birmingham police and fire departments did to them.McWhorter, p. 370&ndash;374.  Moore was hit in the ankle by a brick meant for the police. He took several photos that were printed in ''Life''.  The first photo Moore shot that day showed three teenagers being hit by a water jet from a high-pressure firehose. It was titled "They Fight a Fire That Won't Go Out".  A shorter version of the caption was later used as the title for Fred Shuttlesworth's biography.  The ''Life'' photo became an "era-defining picture" and was compared to the photo of Marines raising the U.S. flag on Iwo Jima.  Moore suspected that the film he shot "was likely to obliterate in the national psyche any notion of a 'good southerner'." Hudson remarked later that his only priorities that day were "making pictures and staying alive" and "not getting bit by a dog." 

Right in front of Hudson stepped Parker High School senior Walter Gadsden when a police officer grabbed the young man's sweater and a police dog charged him.  Gadsden had been attending the demonstration as an observer.  He was related to the editor of Birmingham's black newspaper, ''The Birmingham World'', who strongly disapproved of King's leadership in the campaign. Gadsden was arrested for "parading without a permit", and after witnessing his arrest, Commissioner Connor remarked to the officer, "Why didn't you bring a meaner dog; this one is not the vicious one."  Hudson's photo of Gadsden and the dog ran across three columns in the prominent position above the fold on the front page of ''The New York Times'' on May 4, 1963. 

Television cameras broadcast to the nation the scenes of fire hoses knocking down schoolchildren and police dogs attacking unprotected demonstrators.  Such coverage and photos were given credit for shifting international support to the protesters and making Bull Connor "the villain of the era".McWhorter, ''photo spread'', p. 9. President Kennedy told a group of people at the White House that ''The New York Times'' photo made him "sick".Branch, p. 764.  Kennedy called the scenes "shameful" and said that they were "so much more eloquently reported by the news camera than by any number of explanatory words."Fairclough, p. 138.

The images also had a profound effect in Birmingham.  Despite decades of disagreements, when the photos were released, "the black community was instantaneously consolidated behind King", according to David Vann, who would later serve as mayor of Birmingham.Hampton, p. 133.  Horrified at what the Birmingham police were doing to protect segregation, New York Senator Jacob K. Javits declared, "the country won't tolerate it", and pressed Congress to pass a civil rights bill.
 Similar reactions were reported by Kentucky Senator Sherman Cooper, and Oregon Senator Wayne Morse, who compared Birmingham to South Africa under apartheid.
 A ''New York Times'' editorial called the behavior of the Birmingham police "a national disgrace."
 The ''Washington Post'' editorialized, "The spectacle in Birmingham ... must excite the sympathy of the rest of the country for the decent, just, and reasonable citizens of the community, who have so recently demonstrated at the polls their lack of support for the very policies that have produced the Birmingham riots. The authorities who tried, by these brutal means, to stop the freedom marchers do not speak or act in the name of the enlightened people of the city."
 President Kennedy sent Assistant Attorney General Burke Marshall to Birmingham to help negotiate a truce.  Marshall faced a stalemate when merchants and protest organizers refused to budge.Eskew, p. 270.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="aa02c7f1f1aa33aeee2c56287298cecf" name="Birmingham_campaign_dogs" sectnum="3.9.3#1">../img/aa02c7f1f1aa33aeee2c56287298cecf.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>