<document id="6955ec08f8a39245ca478737a226da78-3" name="André_Kertész" cat="1">
<text>
Kertész emigrated to Paris in September 1925 against his mother's wishes, leaving her behind along with both his brothers, his wife and his uncle Lipót, who died shortly thereafter. Jenő also left Hungary to live in Argentina, but Elizabeth remained until her future husband was well established in Paris and they could live together. Kertész became one of the many Hungarian born artists who had left the Austro-Hungarian Empire for another country, such as François Kollar, Robert Capa, Emeric Fehér and Brassaï, and was certainly not the only artist emigrating to Paris; Man Ray, Germaine Krull (who also took part in exhibitions with Kertész) and Lucien Aigner all emigrated there during this period. In Paris he found critical and commercial success with magazine publications after doing commissioned work for several magazines across Europe from Germany to France to Italy to Great Britain. Kertész was the first photographer to have a one-man exhibition when Jan Slivinsky organised to have 30 of his photographs presented in 1927 at the gallery ''Sacre du Printemps Gallery''. Over the next years, Kertész would appear in many solo exhibitions and shows with other artists. In one show at the Julien Levy Gallery in New York in 1932, the price of Kertész's proofs was set at US$20, a large sum of money during the Great Depression of America.

Kertész changed his first name to André soon after arriving in Paris, and would keep that name for the rest of his life. At that time, Dadaism was beginning to attract numerous photographers and was becoming a large movement amongst artists, especially in France. Kertész quickly became acquainted with the movement's members and one of them, Paul Dermée, dubbed him "Brother Seer" and "Brother Seeing Eye" during Kertész's first solo exhibition in 1927; this was an allusion to a medieval monastery where all the monks were blind bar one. Kertész continued for the entirety of his time in Paris to contact and visit various other Hungarian photographers and artists, and would eventually star in exhibitions with some of them later in his life. Indeed, he enjoyed visiting many of his sculptor friends, and was impressed by the Cubism movement. In his spare time, he created portraits of, among others, painters Piet Mondrian and Marc Chagall, writer Colette, and film-maker Sergei Eisenstein. In 1928, Kertész switched from the usage of cameras with plates and moved on to a Leica, which he became accustomed to quickly. This period of work was arguably one of his most productive, when he took photographs every day and had some of them published in magazines throughout the late 1920s, carefully dividing his time between commissioned work and his own personal photography. In 1930, Kertész was awarded a silver medal for services to photography at the ''Exposition Coloniale'' in Paris where he attended.

Kertész was published in French magazines such as ''Vu'' and ''Art et Médecine'', in which he made numerous covers. His greatest journalistic collaboration was with the French editor and publisher of ''Vu'', Lucien Vogel, who ran his photographs without explanatory prose and let him report on various subjects. Kertész enjoyed travelling in and around Paris taking photographs on the varied subject Vogel set for him to capture. Kertész was commissioned to create one of his most famous series of works, the "Distortion" photographs, in 1933: a series of about 200 photographs of two nude, female models in various poses with their reflections in a combination of distortion mirrors, similar to those found in a carnival's house of mirrors. In some cases the models, Najinskaya Verackhatz and Nadia Kasine, were so distorted that only certain limbs or features were visible in the mirror's reflection. Some of the images appeared in the 2 March issue of the so-called "girly magazine" ''Le Sourire'' and later in the 15 September 1933 issue of ''Arts et métiers graphiques''. Kertész published the book ''Distortions'' later that year containing the photographs.

After his first book of photographs ''Enfants'' in 1933, which was dedicated to Elizabeth and his mother, who had died earlier that year, what followed was a series of other book publications. His next book, ''Paris'', was published in 1934 and dedicated to his brothers Imre and Jenő. ''Nos Amies les bêtes'' ("Our Friends the Animals") was released in 1936 and ''Les Cathédrales du vin'' ("The Cathedrals of Wine") in 1937.

Unknown to his family and indeed most people, Kertész had married a French portrait photographer by the name of Rosza Klein (although she used the name Rogi André) in the late 1920s. The marriage was short-lived and he never spoke about it until his dying day, so as not to upset Elizabeth. In 1930, he ventured back to Hungary to visit his family. After returning to Paris, Elizabeth followed him in 1931, despite firm opposition from her family, to be with the love of her life. Elizabeth and André were never separated again. Despite his mother dying that same year, Kertész married Elizabeth on 17 June 1933. Following this, he is said to have spent increasingly less time with his artist and photographer friends to favor his new wife.

At the time of Kertész's marriage, the Nazi Party was growing in power in Germany. This prompted the magazine industries to publish stories about political topics and many stopped publishing his work due to its neutral demeanor and unpolitical subject matter. From then on, Kertész received increasingly less commissioned work and, with Elizabeth's consent, made plans to move to New York to work at the Keystone agency owned by Ernie Prince. So in 1936, amidst the threat of World War II and lack of work, Kertész and Elizabeth boarded the SS ''Washington'' bound for Manhattan.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3f853c5da7898337dbd86751086a2e30" name="Kertesz_The_Fork" sectnum="3#1">../img/3f853c5da7898337dbd86751086a2e30.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>