<document id="6955ec08f8a39245ca478737a226da78-4" name="André_Kertész" cat="1">
<text>
Kertész arrived in New York with his wife on 15 October 1936, intent on rekindling his inspiration and finding fame as a photographer in America. He and his wife lived out of the Beaux Arts Hotel in Greenwich Village. From his arrival, Kertész found life in America harder than he had imagined and thus started what he would refer to later in his life as the "absolute tragedy". He was now deprived of his French artist friends and the people in America did not respond as kindly as in Paris when their picture was being taken. Soon after his arrival, Kertész approached Beaumont Newhall, the Museum of Modern Art's photographic department director, who was readying a show entitled ''Photography 1839–1937''. But when Kertész offered Newhall some of his ''Distortions'' photographs to display, Newhall criticized them, which offended Kertész, who never forgave him. Despite this, Newhall took the photographs and displayed them; Kertész went on to star in his own solo December 1937 exhibition at the PM Gallery. The final nail in the coffin for Kertész was when the Keystone agency, who had offered him offsite work which would take him to various locations for his photojournalism, instead made him spend the entirety of his work day in the company's studio. Kertész tried to return to France to visit, but had no money, and when he had saved enough, World War II had broken out, making travel to France nearly impossible. His struggles with English only compounded his problems. He had coped with his inability to speak French while in France, but in New York, where he already felt like an outsider, the language barrier was debilitating.

Growing more and more frustrated with the city, Kertész left Keystone to look for other work after his boss Ernie Prince left the company in 1937. He was commissioned by the magazine ''Harper's Bazaar'' for an article on the Saks Fifth Avenue department store in their April 1937 issue. The magazine continued to work with him in further issues and Kertész took commissions from ''Town and Country'' to supplement his income. He was invited by ''Vogue'' to work for the magazine, but turned the offer down, fearing he could not enthusiastically photograph a set studio series as seen in the fashion world. He instead opted to work for ''Life'' magazine, starting with a piece called ''The Tugboat''. However, despite orders, he photographed more than just the subject matter of tugboats, instead photographing the whole harbour and its goings-on. Due to this, ''Life'' refused to publish the photographs and Kertész was once again frustrated with the constriction of the city and its photographic industry.

In the 25 October 1938 issue of ''Look'', the magazine finally printed a series of photographs called ''A Fireman Goes to School''; but credited them to Ernie Prince, Kertész's former boss. Infuriated, Kertész considered never working with illustrated magazines ever again. He did however appear in the magazine ''Coronet'' in 1937, but was snubbed in 1939 when the magazine published a special issue containing a selection of ''Coronet's'' "Most memorable photographs", none of which were his. He later severed all ties to the magazine and its editor Arnold Gingrich. This was repeated in the June 1941 issue of ''Vogue'', which was dedicated to photography in honour of Condé Montrose Nast, head of Condé Nast Publishing. Despite having contributed to more than 30 commissioned photo essays and articles in both ''Vogue'' and ''House and Garden'', Kertész was omitted from the list of photographers. In the same year, since he and Elizabeth carried Hungarian passports, Kertész was designated an enemy alien due to World War II and was not permitted to photograph outside or anything to do with national security, and was later fingerprinted. Not wanting to be arrested or get in trouble with the police because Elizabeth had started a cosmetics company (''Cosmia Laboratories'') with a Hungarian friend, Kertész ceased to do commissioned work and disappeared from all photographic work for three years.

Elizabeth became a US citizen on 20 January 1944, followed on 3 February by her husband. Despite fierce competition from other photographers such as Irving Penn, Kertész thrust himself back into commissioned work. Although he was left out of the 63 photographers listed in ''Vogue's'' "photographic genealogical tree", listing important photographers of the era, he was hired for Christmas commission work by ''House and Garden'', which he had worked for before. He was offered a position teaching photography to students at the New Bauhaus - American School of Design in June 1944 by its director László Moholy-Nagy. Despite the honour, he turned the offer down. He also released a new photographic book, ''Day of Paris'' in 1945, composed of photographs taken just before he left Europe. The book gained critical success. With his wife's cosmetic business booming, Kertész agreed when the new art director of ''House and Garden'' offered him a long-term, exclusive contract in 1946. Although the contract restricted his editorial abilities and forced him to spend many hours in the studio, the pay of at least US$10,000 per annum was satisfactory and all photographic negatives would be returned to him within six months.

Although his subject range was limited, Kertész was sent to many famous homes and places, and indeed overseas, passing through England as well as Budapest and Paris once more. During that 1945 to 1962 period at ''House and Garden'', more than 3,000 of his photographs were published in the magazine and he created a reputation for himself in the industry. However, Kertész made few personal pieces during this time and was starved for artistic creativity.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="38f089ece6e53d629e435fac3c35365d" name="Kertesz_distortion_1933" sectnum="4#1">../img/38f089ece6e53d629e435fac3c35365d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>