<document id="69d79312e938fceca842a9ef3788fee7-1.2" name="Concerto_delle_donne" cat="20">
<text>
The most prominent member of the new ensemble was Laura Peverara, followed by Livia d'Arco and Anna Guarini, daughter of the prolific poet Giovanni Battista Guarini. Giovanni wrote poems for many of the madrigals which were set for the ensemble, and choreographed scenes for the ''balletto delle donne''. Judith Tick believes Tarquinia Molza sang with the group, but Anthony Newcomb says she was involved solely as an advisor and instructor.Newcomb, "Tarquinia Molza"Women in music Whether Tarquinia Molza ever performed with them or not, she was ousted from any role in the group after her affair with the composer Giaches de Wert came to light in 1589. Luzzasco Luzzaschi directed and composed music to showcase the ensemble,Springfels and accompanied them on the harpsichord. Ippolito Fiorini was the ''maestro di capella'', in charge of the entire court's musical activities.Fenlon, "Ippolito Fiorini" In addition to his duties to the overall court, he accompanied the ''concerto'' on the lute. Vittorio Baldini was brought to the court as ducal music printer in 1582.

The singers of the second era of the ''concerto delle donne'' were officially ladies-in-waiting of Duchess Margherita Gonzaga d'Este, but were hired primarily as singers. Peverara's musical abilities prompted the Duke to specifically ask his wife Margherita to bring Peverara from Mantua as part of her retinue. The new singers played instruments, including the lute, harp, and viol, but focused their energies on developing vocal virtuosity.Newcomb 1980, pg. 19 This skill became highly prized in the mid-sixteenth century, beginning with basses like Brancaccio, but by the end of the century virtuosic bass singing went out of style, and higher voices came into vogue.Newcomb 1980, pg. 23 The ladies' musical duties included performing with the duchess' ''balletto delle donne'', a group of female dancers who frequently crossdressed.Newcomb 1980, pg. 35 Despite their upper-class background, the singers would not have been welcomed into the court's inner circle had they not been such skilled performers. D'Arco belonged to the nobility, but a minor family only. Peverara was the daughter of a wealthy merchant, and Molza came from a prominent family of artists. 



The women performed up to six hours a day, either singing their own florid repertoire from memory, sight-reading from partbooks, or participating in the ''balletti'' as singers and dancers.Pendle, pg. 82 Thomasin LaMay posits that the women of the ''concerti delle donne'' provided sexual favors for members of the court,LaMay, pg. 49 but there is no evidence for this, and the circumstances of their marriages and dowries argues against this interpretation. The women were paid salaries and received other benefits, such as dowries and apartments in the ducal palace. Peverara received 300 ''scudi'' a year and lodging in the ducal palace for herself, her husband, and her mother - as well as a dowry of 10,000 ''scudi'' upon her marriage.Knighton, pg. 95 

Despite having married three times in the hopes of producing an heir, Alfonso II died in 1597 without issue, legitimate or otherwise. His cousin Cesare inherited the Duchy, but the city of Ferrara, which was legally a Papal fief, was annexed to the Papal States in 1598 through a combination of "firm diplomacy and unscrupulous pressure" by Pope Clement VIII.Haskell, pg. 25 The Este court had to abandon Ferrara in disarray and the ''concerto delle donne'' was disbanded.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8e266611fa1ea958460171b07d34f8f8" name="Scudo_Alfonso_d'este" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/8e266611fa1ea958460171b07d34f8f8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>