<document id="6a448be8ed7a0156939c90a4a1f7d559-1" name="History_of_the_Australian_Capital_Territory" cat="14">
<text>
Indigenous Australian peoples have long inhabited the lands incorporated by the Australian Capital Territory. Archæological evidence from the Birrigai rock shelter in Tidbinbilla Nature Reserve indicates habitation dating back at least 21,000 years.Flood, JM., David, B., Magee, J. and English, B. 1987. Birrigai: a Pleistocene site in the south eastern highlands, ''Archaeology in Oceania'' 22:9-22 It is possible that the area had been inhabited for considerably longer, with evidence of Aboriginal presence in south-western New South Wales dating to around 40,000-62,000 years ago. Other sites of significance in the reserve include the Bogong Rocks shelter, which contains the oldest evidence of Aboriginal occupation at a bogong moth resting site. Bogong moths were an important source of food for the Aboriginal peoples of the Southern Alps;Fitzgerald, p. 4. the moths would collect in their thousands in caves and rock crevices where they were collected and later roasted in sand or ashes and eaten whole.Wigmore, p. 14. Numerous other culturally significant and archæologically notable sites are known across the Territory, including shelters, rock art sites, stone artefact scatters, scarred trees and chert quarries. Tidbinbilla Mountain is also believed to have long been used for Aboriginal initiation ceremonies.

The Ngunnawal People are the custodians of the land that includes the Territory, whose association with the area is known through both early European settler accounts and the oral histories of the people themselves. Other groups known to have been active in the region and in the surrounding areas include the Ngarigo Moolingoolah Monaroo to the south and south-east of the Australian Capital Territory; the Gundungurra, the Pagong and Parramarragoo associated with lands to the northeast; the Ngunawal to the north and the Ngurmal to the west. These indigenous Australian groups were hunter-gatherers, whose oral traditions maintained and explained their connections with the landscape, the cultural significance of particular features, and their account of their historical identities. Many of these traditions are documented, and from what can be reconstructed from evidence obtained from remaining archæological sites, there is an adequate record of the history of the local indigenous peoples prior to European exploration and settlement.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c77956d121a8df519c914fd535f371b0" name="Yankee_Hat_art-MJC" sectnum="1#1">../img/c77956d121a8df519c914fd535f371b0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>