<document id="6a448be8ed7a0156939c90a4a1f7d559-3" name="History_of_the_Australian_Capital_Territory" cat="14">
<text>
When the limits of location for settlement in New South Wales were determined, the Limestone Plains were authorised for settlement by British settlers and settlers of other European origins.Wigmore, pp. 10&ndash;11. The first land grant in the area was made to Joshua John Moore in 1823,Gillespie, p. 8. and European settlement in the area began in 1824 with the construction of a homestead, on what is now the Acton peninsula, by stockmen employed by him. Moore formally purchased the site in 1826 and named the property ''Canberry'', or ''Canberra'',Fitzgerald, p. 12. although he never visited the site. His 4 km² claim covered much of the future North Canberra. Adjacent to the eastern boundary on Moore's claim was land occupied by James Ainslie on behalf of Robert Campbell, which was known as Duntroon.Fitzgerald, p. 7. John Palmer was granted land in the region which was taken up by his son George Palmer in 1826.Fitzgerald, pp. 10&ndash;11. He established ''Palmerville'' near Ginninderra Creek in 1829, and the "Squire" at Gungahlin was completed in 1861. Ginninderra Village was the site of first school, which operated from 1844 to 1848. The region's second school opened at Duntroon, adjacent St John's Church. St John's was Canberra's first church; it was consecrated and opened for use in 1845.Gillespie, p. 78.Fitzgerald, p. 17.

The region situated ten kilometres south of the Molonglo River and known today as the Tuggeranong Plains, was settled in the late 1820s, officially beginning with Peter Murdoch in 1827.Gillespie, p. 12. The Waniassa Homestead (also known as Tuggeranong Homestead) was completed in 1836 by John McQuoid, and the first buildings of the Lanyon estate, owned by John Lanyon and James Wright, were built in 1838.Gillespie, pp. 20&ndash;22. Tharwa was settled in 1834; the homestead in this area was named ''Cuppacumbalong'', and was established by James Wright in 1839.Gillespie, p. 29. Tharwa is the oldest official settlement in the Australian Capital Territory, having being proclaimed in 1862.Gillespie, p. 130.

Further south into the area that is now a part of the Namadgi National Park. The ''Naas'' and ''Orroral'' stations in the Naas and Orroral river valleys were built in 1836. During the 1830s Garrett Cotter inhabited the Cotter River Valley so named because of his long association with it. From the late 1830s, the Boboyan Homestead and station were established. Gudgenby was settled in the early 1840s; the Gudgenby Homestead was also built around this time. By 1848 most of the major valleys of the Namadgi area had been settled.

Convict labour was widely used in the region, and the first bushrangers in the region were runaway convicts. John Tennant was the earliest and best-known bushranger of the region, and lived in a hideout on a mountain behind Tharwa, now known as Mt Tennant. From 1827 he raided the local homesteads stealing stock, food and possessions until his arrest in 1828.Gillespie, p. 13. He was later hung for his crimes in Sydney. The lawlessness of the region led to the appointment of the first resident magistrate on November 28, 1837. The magistrate oversaw legal matters and issued liquor licenses to several establishments, the first of which was the Oaks Estate in 1841. A significant influx of population and economic activity occurred around the 1850s goldrushes, particularly the Kiandra rush of 1859 to 1860. The gold rushes saw the establishment of communication between Sydney and the region by way of the Cobb & Co coaches, which transported mail and passengers.Wigmore, p. 20. The first post office opened in Ginninderra in 1859 and a second at Lanyon in 1860.Gillespie, pp. 110&ndash;111. Bushranger activity continued with the gold rushes: Australian-born bushrangers Ben Hall and the Clarke brothers were active in the area, targeting mail coaches and gold shipments.Gillespie, pp. 112&ndash;113, 134&ndash;137. 


Terence Aubrey Murray was born in Ireland in 1810 and moved to Sydney, Australia with his family in 1827.Fitzgerald, p. 36. In 1837 he acquired the property of ''Yarralumla'' and moved to the area.Fitzgerald, p. 6. He became the first parliamentary representative for the district from 1860. The Robertson Land Acts and the Closer Settlement Acts altered the mechanism for granting land tenure and brought about the break-up of large properties in New South Wales. With the changes in land tenure, the economic focus of the region shifted from grazing to agriculture. 

During colonial times, present-day Canberra was occupied by various local communities referred to by local names such as Ginninderra, Molonglo and Tuggeranong. The region was also called the Queanbeyan/Yass district, which were the two largest towns in close proximity to Canberra. The villages of Ginninderra and Tharwa developed to service the local farming communities. In 1882 the first allotments the village of Hall, named after early pastoralist Henry Hall were sold. Gillespie, p. 180. It was by 1901 an established town with two stores, a hotel, coachbuilder, blacksmith, butcher, shoemaker, saddler and a dairy.Gillespie, pp. 290&ndash;291. 

In 1886 agronomist William Farrer, established the research farm 'Lambrigg' on the banks of the Murrumbidgee River south of present-day Tuggeranong. Farrer experimented with rust and drought-resistant wheat; the varieties he bred were widely used by Australian wheat growers, and he was later credited with establishing Australia as a major global wheat producer.Wigmore, p. 20.Fitzgerald, pp. 63&ndash;65.Gillespie, p. 182. Tharwa Bridge, the oldest surviving bridge in the region, was opened in 1895 and was the first bridge across the Murrumbidgee River.Gillespie, pp. 188&ndash;180. By 1911 when the region came under federal control, the population had grown to 1,714 settlers.Australian Bureau of Statistics. 1988. Year Book Australia,
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c14ab07c75cf1719387a9d9483ab1d8d" name="Tharwa_Bridge_construction-O'Hanlon" sectnum="3#1">../img/c14ab07c75cf1719387a9d9483ab1d8d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>