<document id="6a4eb1890a3ac1dc71cf1d48a0e7ac8a-2" name="Triptych,_May–June_1973" cat="1">
<text>
Bacon's work from the 1970s has been described by the art critic Hugh Davies as the "frenzied momentum of a struggle against death". Bacon admitted during a 1974 interview that he thought the most difficult aspect of aging was "losing your friends". This was a bleak period in his life, and though he was to live for another seventeen years, he felt that his life was almost over, "and all the people I've loved are dead". His concern is reflected in the darkened flesh and background tones of his paintings from this period.Davies; Yard (1986), p. 65. His acute sense of mortality and awareness of the fragility of life were heightened by Dyer's death in Paris. In the next three years he painted many images of his former lover, including the series of three "Black Triptychs" which have come to be seen as among his best work. A number of characteristics bind the triptychs together: the form of a monochromatically rendered doorway features centrally in all, and each is framed by flat and shallow walls. In each three Dyer is stalked by a broad shadow; which takes the form of pools of blood or flesh in the first and third panels, and the wings of the angel of death in the second and first.Davies; Yard (1986), pp. 67–76. In its display caption for the ''Triptych–August 1972'' the Tate gallery wrote, "What death has not already consumed seeps incontinently out of the figures as their shadows.""". tate.org.uk. Retrieved on 13 June 2007.


Each of the three "Black Triptychs" displays sequential views of a single figure, and each seems to be intended to be viewed as if stills from a film.Davies; Yard (1986), p. 74. The figures rendered are not drawn from any of Bacon's usual intellectual sources; they do not depict Golgotha, Handes, or Leopold Bloom. In these pictures Bacon strips Dyer from the context of both Dyer's own life and the artist's life, and presents him as a nameless, slumped, gathering of flesh, awaiting the onset of death.Schmied (1996), p. 84. Describing the Black Triptychs in 1993, the art critic Juan Vicente Aliaga wrote that "the horror, the abjection that oozed from the crucifixes has been transformed in his last paintings into quiet solitude. The masculine bodies entwined in a carnal embrace have given way to the solitary figure leaning over the washbasin, standing firm on the smooth ground, neutral, bald-headed, his convex back deformed, his testicles contracted in a fold."Aliaga, Juan Vicente. "". ''ArtForum'', February, 1993. Retrieved on 8 May 2007.

When asked by the broadcaster Melvyn Bragg in 1984 if the portraits painted in the wake of Dyer's death were depictions of his emotional reaction to the event, Bacon replied that he did not consider himself to be an "expressionist painter". He explained that he was "not trying to express anything, I wasn't trying to express the sorrow about somebody committing suicide ... but perhaps it comes through without knowing it". When Bragg inquired if he often thought about death, the artist replied that he was always aware of it, and that although "it's just around the corner for , I don't think about it, because there's nothing to think about. When it comes, it's there. You've had it." Reflecting on the loss of Dyer, Bacon observed that as part of aging, "life becomes more of a desert around you". He told Bragg that he believed in "nothing. We are born and we die and that's it. There is nothing else." Bragg asked Bacon what he did about that reality, and after the artist told him he did nothing about it, Bragg pleaded, "No Francis, you try and paint it."

Throughout his career, Bacon consciously and carefully avoided explaining the meaning behind his paintings, and pointedly observed that they were not intended as narratives, nor open to interpretation. When Bragg challenged him with the observation that ''Triptych, May–June 1973'' was the nearest the artist had come to telling a story, Bacon admitted that "it is in fact the nearest I've ever done to a story, because you know that is the triptych of how  was found". He went on to say that the work reflected not just his reaction to Dyer's passing, but his general feelings about the fact that his friends were then dying around him "like flies".Sylvester (1987), p. 129. "People have been dying around me like flies and I’ve had nobody else to paint but myself ... I loathe my own face, and I’ve done self-portraits because I’ve had nothing else to do". A borderline alcoholic himself, Bacon continued to explain that his dead friends were "generally heavy drinkers", and that their passing led directly to his composition of a series of meditative self-portraits which emphasised his own aging and awareness of the passage of time.Bragg, Melvyn. "Francis Bacon". ''South Bank Show''. BBC documentary film, first aired 9 June 1985.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6064c02a8bdbe272100ab0b1979e2a44" name="Triptych_-_August_1972" sectnum="2#1">../img/6064c02a8bdbe272100ab0b1979e2a44.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>