<document id="6b16103d6f7317970590cf64b0384db6-2" name="Operation_Camargue" cat="29">
<text>
A model of a typical Viet Minh ambush, using information from Bernard Fall's ''Street Without Joy'', 1961

Road One, also known as Route Coloniale One (or RC1), had been the main north–south artery along the coastline of North Vietnam since the outbreak of violence in 1949. Communications and convoys along these lines suffered from regular attacks by Viet Minh irregulars,Windrow (2004), 102. despite efforts by the French during 1952 in ''Operation Sauterelle''.Dunstan, 9. The Viet Minh paramilitary forces around Road One originated mainly from a region of fortified villages dispersed along sand dunes and salt marshes between Hué to the south, and Quang-Tri to the north.Fall, 144. French forces had suffered from Viet Minh ambushes, an attack that the latter had become very proficient at throughout the war, most notably in the annihilation of Group Mobiles 42 and 100.Fall, 242. The roads in Vietnam were almost all closed during the night and "abandoned to the enemy".

Between 1952 and 1954, 398 armored vehicles were destroyed, 84% of them from mines and booby traps.Fall, 354. Typically, the Viet Minh ambushed convoys by obstructing the road with a fallen tree or pile of boulders, and then destroying the first and last vehicles of the halted convey with remote mines.Dunstan, 15. Caltraps, mines and the steep cliff faces naturally found at the road side aided in funneling the target convoy into a small area, where machine guns, mortars and recoilless rifles were trained.Fall, 54. Viet Minh Regiment 95 repeatedly deployed these tactics, inflicting severe losses on the French forces passing along Road One, which led to its French nickname of ''la rue sans joie'' ("the street without joy"). Regiment 95 was, along with Regiments 18 and 101, part of the Viet Minh Division 325, commanded by General Tran Quy Ha. The division was formed in 1951 from pre-existing units in Thua Thien just north of Road One, and became operational in the summer of 1952.

By early summer 1953, thanks in part to the wind-down of hostilities in the Korean War, the French command had "sufficient reserves" at hand to begin clearing the Viet Minh back from Road One. They assembled 30 battalions, two armored regiments and two artillery regiments for one of the largest operations of the conflict.Fall, 145. Called ''Operation Camargue'', it was named for the sandy marshland to the west of Marseilles, France. The difficult terrain was to prove the decisive factor and gave a major advantage to the one Viet Minh regiment tasked with defending the ''Street Without Joy''. 



From a  deep beach of "hard sand" the French landing forces were to advance through a series of dunes. The dunes were up to  high and interspersed with precipices, ditches and a handful of small villages. Beyond this was an  belt of pagodas and temples, which war correspondent Bernard Fall describes as having excellent defensive potential. Beyond these temples was Road One itself with a series of closely packed and fortified villages, including Tan An, My Thuy, Van Trinh and Lai-Ha.Fall, 146. This network of villages and hedgerows made both ground and air surveillance difficult. Across from Road One the villages continued amid an area of quicksand, swamps and bogs, which would stop all but a few of the vehicles at the disposal of the French. Although there were roads, most were mined or damaged. Throughout the area, the civilian population remained and provided a further complication for the French high command.Fall, 147.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="872aede2678314ac990801bbddcf13bf" name="Vietnam1amap" sectnum="2#1">../img/872aede2678314ac990801bbddcf13bf.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>