<document id="6b16103d6f7317970590cf64b0384db6-3.3" name="Operation_Camargue" cat="29">
<text>
On 27 July 1953, the French landing craft departed from their assembly points, and by 04:00 on the following had begun disembarking 160 amphibious landing craft belonging to Group A's 3rd Amphibious opposite the coastline. By 06:00, these vehicles had landed on the beach and proceeded to occupy sand ridges overlooking the dunes beyond. Proceeding into the dunes, the vehicles of 3rd Amphibious became stuck in the sand; in the meantime, other regular infantry elements of Group A were experiencing more difficulties in the sea, taking two extra hours to reach the beach. Thus unsupported, elements of 3rd Amphibious that either disembarked floundering vehicles or were pushed, managed to escape the dunes and advance between Tan An and My Thuy.Fall, 149. The French amphibious vehicles were the World War II-era 29-C cargo carriers, nicknamed the ''Crab'' or ''Crabe'' and LVT 4 or 4As, known as the ''Alligator''. The latter was armed with two  and two  Browning machine guns and an M20 recoilless rifle.Dunstan, 21. While the Alligators were heavily armored and well suited to the water, they struggled on land. In contrast, the Crab had difficulty in water and its large size presented too great a target on land; however, it was lighter and more maneuverable,Fall, 148. except in paddy fields where its suspension became clogged with vegetation.Dunstan, 20.

While Group A's forward elements were breaching the dune barrier unopposed, two of Group B's battalions crossed the Van Trinh Canal. By 07:45, when they made visual contact with the Crabs and Alligators of Group A, they had succeeded in sealing off the northern escape route of  By 08:30, the 6th Moroccan Spahis also reached the canal, having had difficulty crossing the swamps on the landward side with their M24 Chaffee tanks. No French units, as yet, had made any major contact with the Viet Minh. A minor fire-fight had taken place on the southern edge of  advance when an Algerian company exchanged fire with 20–30 Viet Minh and suffered the first French fatalities.Fall, 150. Simultaneously,  had advanced into the center of the area of operation, and executed "the most complicated maneuver of the operation". This involved crossing Road One and sealing off the land side of the operational area, and was completed by 08:30.

Group D, finally, was tasked with advancing south from its landing point to close off an escape route that ran between the sea and an inland lagoon towards the city of Hué. Landing at 04:30, the group made quick progress through the beach and dunes, secured the small city of Thé Chi Dong and hit the north coast of the lagoon by 05:30, thereby sealing off that escape route with no enemy contact. The final act of sealing the noose was to move some of the French Navy vessels north to the Vietnamese villages of Ba-Lang and An-Hoi where any attempt by Regiment 95 to flee by sea would have taken place.Fall, 151.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2ee182230dc821f01a77cea5fb6db608" name="Tracked_landing_vehicles_(LVTs)_approach_Iwo_Jima;fig14" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/2ee182230dc821f01a77cea5fb6db608.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>