<document id="6b5ee0e06260a46b4d47e8843441c46f-1" name="Battle_of_the_Alamo" cat="29">
<text>
Under President Antonio López de Santa Anna, the Mexican government began to shift away from a federalist model.  The increasingly dictatorial policies, including the revocation of the Constitution of 1824 in early 1835, incited many federalists to revolt.Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 6.  The Mexican border region Texas was largely populated by immigrants from the United States; accustomed to a federalist government and extensive individual rights, these settlers were very vocal in their displeasure at the country's shift towards centralism.Henson (1982), p. 96.  Already leery of previous American attempts to purchase Texas,Edmondson (2000), p. 78. Mexican authorities blamed much of the Texian unrest on American immigrants, most of whom had made little effort to adapt to the Mexican culture.Barr (1990), p. 4.

In October, Texians engaged Mexican troops in the first official battle of the Texas Revolution. Determined to quash the rebellion, Santa Anna began assembling a large force, the Army of Operations in Texas, to restore order.Hardin (1994), p. 98.   Most of his soldiers were raw recruits;Hardin (1994), p. 99. a large number had been forcibly conscripted.Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 20.


The Texians systematically defeated the Mexican troops already stationed in Texas.  The last group of Mexican soldiers in the region&mdash;commanded by Santa Anna's brother-in-law, General Martin Perfecto de Cos&mdash;surrendered on December 9 following the siege of Béxar.Barr (1990), p. 56.  By this point, the Texian Army was dominated by very recent arrivals to the region, primarily adventurers from the United States.  Many Texas settlers, unprepared for a long campaign, had returned home.  Angered by what he perceived as American interference in Mexican affairs, Santa Anna spearheaded a resolution classifying foreigners found fighting in Texas as pirates. The resolution effectively banned the taking of prisoners of war; in this time period, captured pirates were executed immediately.Barr (1990), p. 63.Scott (2000), p. 71.   Santa Anna reiterated this message in a strongly worded letter to United States President Andrew Jackson. The letter was not widely distributed, and it is unlikely that most of the American recruits serving in the Texian Army were aware that there would be no prisoners of war.Scott (2000), pp. 74&ndash;75.

When Mexican troops departed San Antonio de Béxar (now San Antonio, Texas), Texian soldiers established a garrison at the Alamo Mission, a former religious outpost which had been converted to a makeshift fort.  Described by Santa Anna as an "irregular fortification hardly worthy of the name",Edmondson (2000), p. 129. the Alamo had been designed to withstand an attack by native tribes, not artillery.Edmondson (2000), p. 128. The complex sprawled across , providing almost  of perimeter to defend.  An interior plaza was bordered on the east by the chapel and to the south by a one-story building known as the Low Barracks. A wooden palisade stretched between these two buildings.Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 10.  The two-story Long Barracks extended north from the chapel.Myers (1948), p. 181.  At the northern corner of the east wall stood a cattle pen and horse corral.Edmondson (2000), p. 364.  The walls surrounding the complex were at least  thick and ranged from  high.Myers (1948), p. 180.The plaza covered an area  long and  wide. The Low Barracks was  long, and the Long Barracks was  long and  wide. (Myers (1948), pp. 180&ndash;81.) 

To compensate for a lack of firing ports, Texian engineer Green B. Jameson constructed catwalks to allow defenders to fire over the walls; this method, however, left the shooter's upper body exposed.Edmondson (2000), p. 131.  Mexican forces had left behind 19 cannons, including an 18-pounder, which Jameson installed along the walls. He boasted to Texian army commander Sam Houston that the Texians could "whip 10 to 1 with our artillery".Hardin (1994), p. 111.

The Texian garrison was woefully undermanned and under provisioned, with fewer than 100 soldiers remaining by January 6, 1836.Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 29.   Colonel James C. Neill, the acting Alamo commander, wrote to the provisional government: "If there has ever been a dollar here I have no knowledge of it".  Neill requested additional troops and supplies, stressing that the garrison was likely unable to withstand a siege lasting longer than four days.Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 30.  The Texian government was in turmoil and unable to provide much assistance.Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 31.A week after Neill sent his letter, the Texian provisional legislature impeached the governor, who in turn disbanded the legislature. The interim constitution had given neither party the authority to take those actions, and no one in Texas was entirely sure who was in charge. (Todish ''et al.'' (1998), pp. 30&ndash;31.) Four different men claimed to have been given command over the entire army; Houston, James Fannin, Frank W. Johnson, and Dr. James Grant (Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 30.)  on January 14, Neill approached one of them, Sam Houston, for assistance in gathering supplies, clothing, and ammunition.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="33f9746cf137cecd6322bda9d83d195f" name="Fall-of-the-alamo-gentilz_1844" sectnum="1#1">../img/33f9746cf137cecd6322bda9d83d195f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>