<document id="6b5ee0e06260a46b4d47e8843441c46f-5.7" name="Battle_of_the_Alamo" cat="29">
<text>
According to many accounts of the battle, between five and seven Texians surrendered.Edmondson speculates that these men might have been sick or wounded and were therefore unable to fight. (Edmondson (2000), p. 373)Edmondson (2000), p. 373.Petite (1998), p. 123. Incensed that his orders had been ignored, Santa Anna demanded the immediate execution of the survivors.Hardin (1994), p. 148. Weeks after the battle, stories circulated that Crockett was among those who surrendered. However, Ben, a former American slave who cooked for one of Santa Anna's officers, maintained that Crockett's body was found surrounded by "no less than sixteen Mexican corpses".Tinkle (1985), p. 214. Historians disagree on which version of Crockett's death is accurate.According to Petite (1998), p. 124, "Every account of the Crockett surrender-execution story comes from an avowed antagonist (either on political or military grounds) of Santa Anna's. It is believed that many stories, such as the surrender and execution of Crockett, were created and spread in order to discredit Santa Anna and add to his role as villain."Petite (1998), p. 124. 

Santa Anna reportedly told Captain Fernando Urizza that the battle "was but a small affair".Lord (1961), p. 167.  Another officer then remarked that "with another such victory as this, we'll go to the devil".The identify of this officer is disputed. Edmondson (2000), p. 374 claims that this remark was made by Colonel Juan Almonte, and overheard by Almonte's cook, Ben. Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 55. attributes the remark to Lieutenant Colonel José Juan Sanchez Navarro.   In his initial report Santa Anna claimed that 600 Texians had been killed, with only 70 Mexican soldiers killed and 300 wounded.Edmondson (2000), p. 374. His secretary, Ramon Martinez Caro, later repudiated the report.Hardin (1994), p. 156. Other estimates of the number of Mexican soldiers killed ranged from 60&ndash;2,000, with an additional 250&ndash;300 wounded. Most Alamo historians place the number of Mexican casualties at 400&ndash;600 Mexicans.Hardin (1961), p. 155.Nofi (1992), p. 136. This would represent about one-third of the Mexican soldiers involved in the final assault, which Todish remarks is "a tremendous casualty rate by any standards".  Most  eyewitnesses counted between 182&ndash;257 Texians killed.Nofi (1992), p. 133. Some historians believe that at least one Texian, Henry Warnell, successfully escaped from the battle. Warnell died several months later of wounds incurred either during the final battle or during his escape as a courier.Edmondson (2000), p. 407.Groneman (1990), p. 119.

Mexican soldiers were buried in the local cemetery, Campo Santo.According to Francisco Ruiz, possibly the ''alcade'' of Béxar, the graveyard was near full and that he instead threw some of the corpses in the river. (Edmondson (2000), p. 374.) However, Sam Houston reported on March 13 that all Mexicans were buried. (Lindley (2003), p. 277.)  The Texian bodies were stacked and burned.Cremating bodies was anathema at the time, as most Christians believed that a body could not be resurrected unless it were whole. (Petite (1998), p. 139.) The only exception was the body of Gregorio Esparza, whose brother Francisco, an officer in Santa Anna's army, received permission to give Gregorio a proper burial. The ashes were left where they fell until February 1837, when Juan Seguin returned to Béxar to examine the remains. A simple coffin inscribed with the names Travis, Crockett, and Bowie was filled with ashes from the funeral pyres.Petite (1998), p. 131.  According to a March 28, 1837 article in the ''Telegraph and Texas Register'',Chariton (1990), p. 78. Seguin buried the coffin under a peach tree grove. The spot was not marked and cannot now be identified.Petite (1998), p. 132.  However, Seguin later claimed that he had placed the coffin in front of the altar at the San Fernando Cathedral. In July 1936, a coffin was discovered buried in that location, but according to historian Wallace Chariton it is unlikely to actually contain the remains of the Alamo defenders. Fragments of uniforms were found in the coffin, and it is known that the Alamo defenders did not wear uniforms.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="aca6e26ceb5956f77ded7e8680d8de65" name="San_Antonio_067" sectnum="5.7#1">../img/aca6e26ceb5956f77ded7e8680d8de65.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>