<document id="6b5ee0e06260a46b4d47e8843441c46f-6" name="Battle_of_the_Alamo" cat="29">
<text>
Following the battle, Santa Anna was alternately viewed as a national hero or a pariah.  Mexican perceptions of the battle often mirrored the prevailing viewpoint.Glaser (1985), p. 98. Santa Anna had been disgraced following his capture at the Battle of San Jacinto, and many Mexican accounts of the battle were written by men who had been, or had become, his outspoken critics. Petite and many other historians believe that some of the stories, such as the execution of Crockett, may have been invented to further discredit Santa Anna.Petite (1998), p. 124.  In Mexican history, the Texas campaign, including the Battle of the Alamo, was soon overshadowed by the Mexican-American War of the 1840s.

alt=The rectangular base of a cenotaph. An angel is carved on one end. On the side are carvings of several men, shown wearing bucksin or 19th-century suits.  Many hold guns or knives; at the far end, one operates a cannon.
In San Antonio de Béxar, the largely ''Tejano'' population viewed the Alamo complex as more than just a battlesite; it represented decades of assistance&mdash;as a mission, a hospital, or a military post.Schoelwer (1985), p. 18.  As the English-speaking population increased, the complex became best known for the battle. Focus has centered primarily on the Texian defenders, with little emphasis given to the role of the ''Tejano'' soldiers who served in the Texian army or the actions of the Mexican army.Schoelwer (1985), pp. 52, 56.  In the early 20th century the Texas Legislature purchased the property and appointed the Daughters of the Republic of Texas as permanent caretakersTodish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 199. of what is now an official state shrine.  In front of the church, in the center of Alamo Plaza, stands a cenotaph, designed by Pompeo Coppini, which commemorates the Texians and ''Tejanos'' who died during the battle.Groneman (1998), p. 56. According to Bill Groneman's ''Battlefields of Texas'', the Alamo has become "the most popular tourist site in Texas".Groneman (1998), p. 52.

 
The first English-language histories of the battle were written and published by Texas Ranger and amateur historian John Henry Brown.Lindley (2003), p. 106. The next major treatment of the battle was Reuben Potter's ''The Fall of the Alamo'', published in ''The Magazine of American History'' in 1878. Potter based his work on interviews with many of the Mexican survivors of the battle.Nofi (1992), p. 211. The first full-length, non-fiction book covering the battle, John Myers Myers' ''The Alamo'', was published in 1948.  In the decades since, the battle has featured prominently in many non-fiction works.

According to Todish ''et al.'', "there can be little doubt that most Americans have probably formed many of their opinions on what occurred at the Alamo not from books, but from the various movies made about the battle."Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 187. The first film version of the battle appeared in 1911, when Gaston Melies directed ''The Immortal Alamo''. The battle became more widely known after it was featured in the 1950s Disney miniseries ''Davy Crockett'', which was largely based on myth.Nofi (1992), p. 213.  Within several years, John Wayne directed and starred in one of the best-known, but least accurate, film versions, 1960's ''The Alamo''.Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 188.Historians J. Frank Dobie and Lon Tinkle demanded that they not be listed as historical advisors in the credits of ''The Alamo'' because of its disjunction from reality.  (Todish ''et al.'', p. 188.) In 2004 another film, also called ''The Alamo'', was released. CNN described it as possibly "the most character-driven of all the movies made on the subject".

A number of songwriters have been inspired by the Battle of the Alamo. Tennessee Ernie Ford's "The Ballad of Davy Crockett" spent 16 weeks on the country music charts, peaking at number 4 in 1955.Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 194. Marty Robbins recorded a version of the song "The Ballad of the Alamo" in 1960 which spent 13 weeks on the pop charts, peaking at number 34.Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 196.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4fa5e36e064b752d15bd2488a4ebe328" name="Texas_centennial_half_dollar_commemorative_reverse" sectnum="6#1">../img/4fa5e36e064b752d15bd2488a4ebe328.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>