<document id="6bb294e836c0b5f7fd797217b7b4bc7b-2" name="Acrocanthosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
''Acrocanthosaurus'' is classified in the superfamily Allosauroidea within the infraorder Tetanurae. This superfamily is characterized by paired ridges on the nasal and lacrimal bones on top of the snout and tall neural spines on the neck vertebrae, among other features. It was originally placed in the family Allosauridae with ''Allosaurus'', an arrangement also supported by some more recent studies. Other scientists classify it as a member of the related family Carcharodontosauridae. 

At the time of its discovery, ''Acrocanthosaurus'' and most other large theropods were known from only fragmentary remains, leading to highly variable classifications for this genus. J. Willis Stovall and Wann Langston, Jr. first assigned it to the "Antrodemidae," the equivalent of Allosauridae, but it was transferred to the taxonomic wastebasket Megalosauridae by Alfred Sherwood Romer in 1956. To other authors, the long spines on its vertebrae suggested a relationship with ''Spinosaurus''. This interpretation of ''Acrocanthosaurus'' as a spinosaurid persisted into the 1980s, and was repeated in the semi-technical dinosaur books of the time. 

Tall spined vertebrae from the Early Cretaceous of England were once considered to be very similar to those of ''Acrocanthosaurus'', and in 1988 Gregory S. Paul named them as a second species of the genus, ''A. altispinax''. These bones were originally assigned to ''Altispinax'', an English theropod otherwise known only from teeth, and this assignment led to at least one author proposing that ''Altispinax'' itself was a synonym of ''Acrocanthosaurus''. These vertebrae were later assigned to the new genus ''Becklespinax'', separate from both ''Acrocanthosaurus'' and ''Altispinax''.

If ''Acrocanthosaurus'' was an allosaurid, it would have been most closely related to Jurassic genera like ''Allosaurus'' and ''Saurophaganax''. Those cladistic analyses which find it to be a carcharodontosaurid usually place it in a basal position relative to the African ''Carcharodontosaurus'' and ''Giganotosaurus'' from South America. ''Neovenator'', discovered in England, is often considered an even more basal carcharodontosaurid. This suggests that the family originated in Europe and then dispersed into the southern continents (at the time united as the supercontinent Gondwana). If ''Acrocanthosaurus'' was a carcharodontosaurid, then dispersal would also have occurred into North America. All known carcharodontosaurids lived during the early to middle Cretaceous Period.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="38e0b56605990a0cd178a393a71fd4fa" name="Acrocantosaurus4" sectnum="2#1">../img/38e0b56605990a0cd178a393a71fd4fa.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>