<document id="6bd22968066a2b1c8ec009eb99809859-2.3" name="Ian_Chappell" cat="26">
<text>
Chappell became SA captain when the long-serving Les Favell retired at the start of the 1970&ndash;71 season.Harte (1993), p 531. His younger brother Greg made his debut in the second Test of the summer against Ray Illingworth's England. Facing an English attack led by the hostile fast bowling of John Snow, Chappell scored a half-century in each of the first two Tests, but failed to capitalise on good starts while Greg Chappell scored 108 in his initial innings. Retrieved 13 November 2007. Rain caused the abandonment of the third Test without a ball bowled. Temporarily promoted to open the batting, Chappell failed in the fourth Test as Australia lost. In the fifth Test at Melbourne, he returned to number three and started nervously. Dropped on 0 and 14, Chappell found form and went on to post his maiden Ashes century (111 from 212 balls), Retrieved 17 August 2007. which he followed with scores of 28 and 104 in the sixth Test.

The washed-out Test resulted in a late change to the schedule and an unprecedented seventh Test was played at Sydney in February 1971. Retrieved 17 August 2007. Trailing 0&ndash;1 in the series, Australia could retain The Ashes by winning this game. Australia's performances were hampered by playing slow, defensive cricket. In a radical attempt to breathe some aggression into the team, the selectors sacked captain Bill Lawry and appointed Chappell in his stead. Retrieved 17 August 2007. Dismayed by the manner of Lawry's dismissal, Retrieved 20 August 2007. Chappell responded with an attacking performance as captain, he won the toss, put England in and dismissed them for 184, and Australia led the first innings by 80 runs, but set 223 to win they folded for 160 and lost The Ashes after holding them for 12 years. Chappell gained some consolation at the end of a dramatic summer when he led SA to the Sheffield Shield, the team's first win for seven years.Mallett (2005), p 55.

Chappell's battles against the short-pitched bowling of Snow during the season compelled him to reappraise his game. Following a conversation with Sir Donald Bradman, he decided to reinstate the hook shot and spent the winter months practising the stroke by hitting baseballs thrown by his brother Greg.Chappell (1976), pp 74&ndash;75. Although he still regularly lost his wicket after playing the shot, Chappell felt that the psychological benefit of showing aggression to opposing bowlers offset the times that he was dismissed for a low score.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="55b83f069ff1c5d5b64dd30f710bf53b" name="Chappelli" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/55b83f069ff1c5d5b64dd30f710bf53b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>