<document id="6bd22968066a2b1c8ec009eb99809859-1" name="Ian_Chappell" cat="26">
<text>
The first of three sons born in Adelaide to Martin and Jeanne (née Richardson), Chappell was steeped in the game from an early age. His father was a noted Adelaide grade cricketer who put a bat in his hands as soon as he could walk, and his maternal grandfather was a famous all-round sportsman Vic Richardson, who captained Australia at the end of a nineteen-Test career. Retrieved 11 October 2007. Chappell was given weekly batting lessons from the age of five, as were younger brothers Greg and Trevor, who both went on to play for Australia.Mallett (2005), pp 7&ndash;8. 

Chappell grew up in the beachside suburb of Glenelg and attended the local St Leonard's Primary School where he played his first competitive match at the age of seven. He was later selected for the South Australian state schoolboys team.Mallett (2005), p 11. He then enrolled at Prince Alfred College, a private secondary school noted for producing many Test cricketers, including the Australian captains Joe Darling and Clem Hill. His other sporting pursuits included Australian football and baseball: Chappell's performances for his state in the Claxton Shield won him All-Australian selection in 1964 and 1966 as a catcher. Retrieved 18 August 2007. At the age of 18, his form in grade cricket for Glenelg led to his first-class debut for South Australia (SA) against Tasmania in early 1962. Chappell replaced West Indian Garry Sobers who was selected for a Test match in the Caribbean.Chappell (1976), p 39.

The aggressive style of Sobers and SA captain Les Favell heavily influenced Chappell during his formative years in major cricket.Chappell (1976), pp 40&ndash;41. In 1962&ndash;63, Chappell made his initial first-class century against a New South Wales team led by Australian captain Richie Benaud, who was bemused by the young batsman's habit of gritting his teeth as he faced up; to Benaud, it looked as if he was grinning.Mallett (2005), p 20. Chappell spent the northern summer of 1963 as a professional in England's Lancashire League with Ramsbottom and played a single first-class match for Lancashire. Retrieved 13 November 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d395428b9d63fd7dfe89e85af59a54cc" name="Vic_Richardson" sectnum="1#1">../img/d395428b9d63fd7dfe89e85af59a54cc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>