<document id="6cc3f5e25f62cce158a0b7af74077851-3" name="Battle_of_Tulagi_and_Gavutu–Tanambogo" cat="29">
<text>
The nearby islets of Gavutu and Tanambogo housed the Japanese seaplane base as well as 536 Japanese naval personnel from the Yokohama Air Group and 3rd Kure Special Naval Landing Force and Korean and Japanese civilian technicians and laborers from the 14th Construction Unit.Frank, p. 628, Jersey, p. 150.  The 14th Construction Unit was divided into the Hashimoto and Hara Construction Forces.  The two islets were basically mounds of coral, both about 42 meters (140 ft) high, and connected to each other by a 500 meter-long causeway.  The hills on Gavutu and Tanambogo were called Hills 148 and 121 respectively by the Americans because of their height in feet.Christ, p. 46, Hough, p. 266–267.  The Japanese on both islets were well entrenched in bunkers and caves constructed on and in the two hills.Christ, p. 55, Griffith, p. 61.  Also, the two islets were mutually supportive since each was in machine gun range of the other.  The US mistakenly believed that the islets were garrisoned by only 200 naval troops and construction workers.Zimmerman, p. 34, Christ, p. 33.

At 12:00 on August 7, Gavutu was assaulted by the U.S. Marine 1st Parachute Battalion consisting of 397 men.  The assault was scheduled for noon because there were not enough aircraft to provide air cover for the Guadalcanal, Tulagi, and Gavutu landings at the same time.Christ, p. 40–41.  The preceding naval bombardment had damaged the seaplane ramp, forcing the naval landing craft to land the Marines in a more exposed location on a nearby small beach and dock at .  Japanese machine gun fire began inflicting heavy casualties, killing or wounding one in ten of the landing Marines as they scrambled inland in an attempt to get out of the crossfire coming from the two islets.Christ, p. 52–58, Frank, p. 75–76.

Surviving Marines were able to deploy two machine guns to provide suppressing fire on Gavutu's caves, allowing more Marines to push inland from the landing area.  Seeking cover, the Marines became scattered and were quickly pinned down.  Captain George Stallings, the battalion operations officer, directed Marines to begin suppressive fire with machine guns and mortars on the Japanese machine gun emplacements on Tanambogo.  Shortly thereafter, American dive bombers dropped several bombs on Tanambogo, diminishing some of the volume of fire from that location.Christ, p. 59–69, 81.  Stallings took command of the battalion after the commander, Major Robert Miller, collapsed from nervous stress and the executive officer, Major Robert Williams, was seriously wounded.

After about two hours, Marines reached and climbed Hill 148.  Working from the top, the Marines began clearing the Japanese fighting positions on the hill, most of which still remained, with explosive charges, grenades, and hand-to-hand combat.Christ, p. 94, Griffith, p. 61–62, Jersey, p. 156.  From the top of the hill, the Marines were also able to put increased suppressive fire on Tanambogo.Christ, p. 100.  The Marine battalion commander on Gavutu radioed General Rupertus with a request for reinforcements before attempting to assault Tanambogo.Jersey, p. 144, Zimmerman, p. 35.  The battalion commander, Robert Miller, had recovered from his nervous condition about 16:30 and made the request for reinforcements (Christ, p. 108).

Most of the 240 Japanese defenders on Tanambogo were aircrew and maintenance personnel from the Yokohama Air Group. Rupertus detached one company of Marines from the 1st Battalion, 2nd Marine Regiment on Florida Island to assist in assaulting Tanambogo, in spite of advice from his staff that one company was not enough.  Incorrectly believing that Tanambogo was only lightly defended, this company attempted an amphibious assault directly on Tanambogo shortly after dark on August 7.  Illuminated by fires started during a U.S. naval bombardment of the islet, the five landing craft carrying the Marines were hit by heavy fire as they approached the shore, with many of the U.S. Navy boatcrews being killed or wounded, as well as heavily damaging three of the boats.  Realizing the position was untenable the Marine company commander ordered the remaining boats to depart with the wounded marines, and he and a dozen men who had already landed sprinted across the causeway to cover on Gavutu.  The Japanese on Tanambogo suffered 10 killed in the day's fighting.Christ, p. 112–113, Frank, p. 77, Jersey, p. 160–163.  The Parachute Battalion had lost 84 men in the day's fighting, including 30 killed.

 Throughout the night, as the Japanese staged isolated attacks on the marines on Gavutu under the concealment of heavy thunderstorms, Vandegrift prepared to send reinforcements to assist with the assault on Tanambogo.  The 3rd Battalion 2nd Marines (3/2), still embarked on ships off Guadalcanal, was notified to prepare to assault Tanambogo on August 8.Griffith, p. 62.  3/2 was under the command of Lieutenant Colonel Leroy P. Hunt (Christ, p. 131).

The 3rd Battalion began landing on Gavutu at 10:00 on August 8 and assisted in destroying the remaining Japanese defenses on that islet, which was completed by 12:00.Zimmerman, p. 36–38, Christ, p. 113.  Then the 3rd Battalion prepared to assault Tanambogo.  The Marines on Gavutu provided covering fire for the attack.  In preparation for the assault, U.S. carrier dive bombers and naval gunfire bombardment were requested.  After the carrier aircraft twice accidentally dropped bombs on the U.S. Marines on Gavutu, killing four of them, further carrier aircraft support was canceled.  The ''San Juan'', however, placed its shells on the correct island and shelled Tanambogo for 30 minutes.  The Marine assault began at 16:15, both by landing craft and across the causeway, and, with assistance from two marine Stuart light tanks, began making headway against the Japanese defenses.  One of the tanks which became stuck on a stump and isolated from its infantry support was surrounded by a "frenzied mob" of about 50 Japanese airmen.  The Japanese set fire to the tank, killing two of its crew and severely beat the other two crewmembers before most of them were killed by Marine rifle fire.  The Marines later counted 42 Japanese bodies around the burned-out hulk of the tank, including the corpses of the Yokohama executive officer and several of the seaplane pilots.  One of the Japanese survivors of the attack on the tank reported, "I recall seeing my officer Lieutenant Commander Saburo Katsuta on top of the tank.  This was the last time I saw him".Christ, p. 134–135, Jersey, p. 178–179, 181, Frank, p. 78–79 and Lundstrom, p. 38, Gilbert, p. 38.  Lieutenant E. J. Sweeney, the tank platoon commander, was killed during the tank assault as he stood in his tank's turret.  Lundstrom states that Miyazaki was killed in the attack on the tank, but Jersey states that Miyazaki wasn't in the Guadalcanal area at the time and survived the war.

Throughout the day, the Marines methodically dynamited the caves, destroying most of them by 21:00.Frank, p. 78–79 and Lundstrom, p. 38.  The few surviving Japanese conducted isolated attacks throughout the night, with hand to hand engagements occurring.  By noon on August 9, all Japanese resistance on Tanambogo ended.Zimmerman, p. 38.  In the battle for Gavutu and Tanambogo, 476 Japanese defenders and 70 U.S. Marines or naval personnel died.  Of the 20 Japanese prisoners taken during the battle, most were not actually Japanese combatants but Korean laborers belonging to the Japanese construction unit.Frank, p. 79, Jersey, p. 181, Christ, p. 169.  Four members of the Yokohama Air Group were captured.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="66e9589534fb669977feb00c5b807363" name="TulagiRupertus" sectnum="3#1">../img/66e9589534fb669977feb00c5b807363.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>