<document id="6d03078e24dc3247b2c0c64fe7a139f4-6" name="Banff_National_Park" cat="11">
<text>
Banff National Park is the most visited Alberta tourist destination and one of the most visited national parks in North America, with 3,927,557 visitors in 2004/2005. During summer, 42% of park visitors are from Canada (23% from Alberta), while 35% are from the United States, and 20% from Europe. Tourism in Banff contributes an estimated C$6 billion annually to the economy.

A park pass is required for stopping in the park and permit checks are common during the summer months, especially at Lake Louise and the start of the Icefields Parkway. A permit is not required if travelling straight through the park without stopping. Approximately 5 million people pass through Banff annually on the Trans-Canada Highway without stopping.

Attractions in Banff include Upper Hot Springs, and a 27-hole golf course at Fairmont Banff Springs Hotel, and three ski resorts including Sunshine Village, Lake Louise Mountain Resort, and Mount Norquay ski resort. Day hikes, such as the Cory Pass Loop, are popular with visitors. Other activities include alpine and Nordic skiing, and horseback riding.

Backcountry activities in Banff include hiking, camping, climbing, and skiing. Parks Canada requires those using backcountry campgrounds, Alpine Club of Canada huts, or other backcountry facilities to purchase a wilderness pass. Reservations for using the campgrounds are also required.

The park saw a surge in visitors and interest in the park around August 2009 after the appearance of the "Crasher Squirrel" Internet meme. The meme is based a photograph of a Minnesotan couple visiting the park on the shore of Lake Minnewanka that was "crashed" by a Columbian ground squirrel; the photograph was quickly published in major news sources around the world and the image of the squirrel was digitally manipulated into humorous photos. The Banff Tourism Board has used the popularity of the meme to gain interest in the park, including setting up Twitter and Facebook pages for the squirrel.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e67a44c677d796ee9b38190f64e3ef40" name="Skilakelouise" sectnum="6#1">../img/e67a44c677d796ee9b38190f64e3ef40.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>