<document id="6d33f081bed371cbb6e53fa7e363d2ab-4.11" name="Alcibiades" cat="14">
<text>
With one exception, Alcibiades' role in the war ended with his command. Prior to the Battle of Aegospotami, in the last attested fact of his career,B. Perrin, ''The Death of Alcibiades '', 25–37. Alcibiades recognized that the Athenians were anchored in a tactically disadvantageous spot and advised them to move to Sestus where they could benefit from a harbor and a city.Xenophon, ''Hellenica'', 2.1.. Diodorus, however, does not mention this advice, arguing instead that Alcibiades offered the Generals Thracian aid in exchange for a share in the command. In any case, the Generals of the Athenians, "considering that in case of defeat the blame would attach to them and that in case of success all men would attribute it to Alcibiades", asked him to leave and not come near the camp ever again.Diodorus, ''Library'', xiii, . Days later the fleet would be annihilated by Lysander.  
 
After the Battle of Aegospotami, Alcibiades crossed the Hellespont and took refuge in Phrygia, with the object of securing the aid of Artaxerxes against Sparta.

Much about Alcibiades' death is now uncertain, as there are conflicting accounts.  According to the oldest of these, the Spartans and specifically Lysander were responsible.Isocrates, ''Concerning the Team of Horses,   Though many of his details cannot be independently corroborated, Plutarch's version is this:  Lysander sent an envoy to Pharnabazus who then dispatched his brother to Phrygia where Alcibiades was living with his mistress, Timandra. In 404 BC, as he was about to set out for the Persian court, his residence was surrounded and set on fire. Seeing no chance of escape he rushed out on his assassins, dagger in hand, and was killed by a shower of arrows.Plutarch, ''Alcibiades'', .  According to Aristotle, the site of Alcibiades’ death was Elaphus, a mountain in Phrygia.Aristotle, ''History of Animals'', ; cf. John & William Langhorne, ''Plutarch's Lives'' (1819), vol. 2, p. .
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2a440b06388331ffaf485fc7d3e6d644" name="Alcibiades7220" sectnum="4.11#1">../img/2a440b06388331ffaf485fc7d3e6d644.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>