<document id="6de836c077a7224e07e93a7371888abe-1.2" name="Chariot_racing" cat="26">
<text>
In the ancient Olympic Games, as well as the other Panhellenic Games, there were both four-horse (''tethrippon'', Greek: τέθριππον) and two-horse (''synoris'', Greek: ξυνωρὶς) chariot races, which were essentially the same aside from the number of horses.''Synoris'' succeeded ''tethrippon'' in 384 BC. ''Tethrippon'' was reintroduced in 268 BC (Valettas, ''Chariot Racing'', 613). The chariot racing event was first added to the Olympics in 680 BC with the games expanding from a one day to a two day event to accommodate the new event (''but'' was not, in reality, the founding event).Polidoro, ''The Games of 676 BC'', 41–46* Valettas, ''Chariot Racing'', 613 The chariot race was not as prestigious as the ''stadion'' (the foot race), but it was more important than other equestrian events such as racing on horseback, which were dropped from the Olympic Games very early on.Adkins, ''Handbook to Life in Ancient Greece'', 350, 420 

The races themselves were held in the hippodrome, which held both chariot races and riding races. Little is known of the construction of hippodromes before the Roman period (Adkins, ''Handbook to Life in Ancient Greece'', 218–219). The hippodrome was situated at the south-east corner of the sanctuary of Olympia, on the large flat area south of the stadium and ran almost parallel to the latter. Until recently, its exact location was unknown, since it is buried by several meters of sedimentary material from the . In 2008, however, Norbert Muller and staff of the German Archeological Institute used radar to locate a large, rectangular structure  similar to Pausanias's description]. Pausanias, who visited Olympia in the second century BC, describes the monument as a large, elongated, flat space, approximately 780 meters long and 320 meters wide (four ''stadia'' long and one ''stade'' four ''plethra'' wide). The elongated racecourse was divided longitudinally into two tracks by a stone or wooden barrier, the ''embolon''. All the horses or chariots ran on one track towards the east, then turned around the ''embolon'' and headed back west. Distances varied according to the event. The racecourse was surrounded by natural (to the north) and artificial (to the south and east) banks for the spectators; a special place was reserved for the judges on the west side of the north bank.Pausanias, ''Description of Greece'', 6.* Vikatou,  

The race was begun by a procession into the hippodrome, while a herald announced the names of the drivers and owners. The tethrippon consisted of twelve laps around the hippodrome,Adkins, ''Handbook to Life in Ancient Greece'', 420 with sharp turns around the posts at either end. Various mechanical devices were used, including the starting gates (''hyspleges'', singular: hysplex, Greek: ὕσπληγξ-ὕσπληγγες) which were lowered to start the race.Golden, ''Sport in the Ancient World'', 86 According to Pausanias these were invented by the architect Cleoitas, and staggered so that the chariots on the outside began the race earlier than those on the inside. The race did not actually begin properly until the final gate was opened, at which point each chariot would be more or less lined up alongside each other, although the ones that had started on the outside would have been travelling faster than the ones in the middle. Other mechanical devices known as the "eagle" and the "dolphin" were raised to signify that the race had begun, and were lowered as the race went on to signify the number of laps remaining. These were probably bronze carvings of those animals, set up on posts at starting line.Pausanias, ''Description of Greece'', 6.

In most cases, the owner and the driver of the chariot were different persons. In 416 BC the Athenian general Alcibiades had seven chariots in the race, and came in first, second and fourth; obviously he could not have been racing all seven chariots himself.Thucydides, 6.16.2 Philip II of Macedon also won an Olympic chariot race in an attempt to prove he was not a barbarian, though if he had driven the chariot himself he would likely have been considered even lower than a barbarian. However, the poet Pindar did praise the courage of Herodotos of Thebes for driving his own chariot.Pindar, ''Isthmian Odes'', I. This rule also meant that women could technically win the race, despite the fact that women were not allowed to participate in or even watch the Games.Polidoro, ''The Games of 676 BC'', 41–46  This happened rarely, but a notable example is the Spartan Cynisca, daughter of Archidamus II, who won the chariot race twice.Golden, ''Sport in the Ancient World'', 46 Chariot racing was a way for Greeks to demonstrate their prosperity at the games.  The case of Alcibiades indicates also that chariot racing was an alternative route to public exposure and fame for the wealthy.Kyle, ''Sport and Spectacle in the Ancient World'', 172 

The charioteer was usually a family member of the owner of the chariot or, in most cases, a slaveValettas, ''Chariot Racing'', 613 or a hired professional (Driving a racing chariot required unusual strength, skill and courage). Yet, we know the names of very few charioteers,One of them is Carrhotus who is praised by Pindar for keeping his chariot unscathed (Pindar, ''Pythian'', 5.). Unlike the majority of charioteers, Carrhotus was friend and brother-in-law of the man he drove for, Arcesilaus of Cyrene; so his success affirmed the success of the traditional aristocratic mode of organizing society (Nicholson, ''Aristocratic Victory Memorials'', 116). and victory songs and statues regularly contrive to leave them out of account.Golden, ''Sport in the Ancient World'', 34 Unlike the other Olympic events, charioteers did not perform in the nude, probably for safety reasons because of the dust kicked up by the horses and chariots, and the likelihood of bloody crashes. Racers wore a sleeved garment called a ''xystis''. It fell to the ankles and was fastened high at the waist with a plain belt. Two straps that crossed high at the upper back prevented the ''xystis'' from "ballooning" during the race.Adkins, ''Handbook to Life in Ancient Greece'', 416

The chariots themselves were modified war chariots, essentially wooden carts with two wheels and an open back,Valettas, Chariot Racing, 614 although chariots were by this time no longer used in battle. The charioteer's feet were held in place, but the cart rested on the axle, so the ride was bumpy. The most exciting part of the chariot race, at least for the spectators, was the turns at the ends of the hippodrome. These turns were very dangerous and often deadly. If a chariot had not already been knocked over by an opponent before the turn, it might be overturned or crushed (along with the horses and driver) by the other chariots as they went around the post. Deliberately running into an opponent to cause him to crash was technically illegal, but nothing could be done about it (at Patroclus' funeral games, Antilochus in fact causes Menelaus to crash in this wayGagarin, ''Antilochus' Strategy'', 35-39), and crashes were likely to happen by accident anyway.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="74db9987bf15c942a9b086082625360e" name="Charioteer_of_Delphi_-_detail_of_head" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/74db9987bf15c942a9b086082625360e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>