<document id="6e1b71c30173b94e73b522e42db5ee82-4.3" name="Hoysala_Empire" cat="14">
<text>
Although Sanskrit literature remained popular during the Hoysala rule, royal patronage of local Kannada scholars increased.Ayyar (1993), p600Kamath (2001), p132Narasimhacharya (1988), p19 In the 12th century some works were written  in the ''Champu'' style,A composition which is written in a mixed prose-verse style is called ''Champu'', Narasimhacharya (1988), p12 but  distinctive Kannada  metres  became more widely accepted. The ''Sangatya'' metre used in compositions,A ''Sangatya'' composition is meant to be sung to the accompaniment of a musical instrument (Sastri 1955), p359) ''Shatpadi'' (seven line), ''Tripadi'' (three line) metres in verses and ''Ragale'' (lyrical poems) became fashionable. Jain works continued to extol the virtues of Tirthankaras (Jain ascetics).Sastri(1955), p361

The Hoysala court supported scholars such as Janna, Rudrabhatta, Harihara and his nephew  Raghavanka, whose works are enduring masterpieces in Kannada. In 1209, the  Jain scholar Janna wrote ''Yashodharacharite'', the story of a king who intends to perform a ritual sacrifice of two young boys to a local deity, Mariamma. Taking pity on the boys, the king releases them and gives up the practice of human sacrifice.Sastri (1955), p359E.P. Rice (1921), p43-44 In honour of this work, Janna received the title "Emperor among poets" (''Kavichakravarthi'') from King Veera Ballala II.Narasimhacharya (1988), p20

Rudrabhatta,  a Smartha Brahmin (believer of monistic philosophy), was the earliest well known Brahminical writer whose patron was Chandramouli, a minister of King Veera Ballala II.Sastri (1955), p364 Based on the earlier work of ''Vishnu Purana'', he wrote ''Jagannatha Vijaya'' in  the ''Champu'' style relating the life of Lord Krishna leading up to his fight with the demon Banasura. 

Harihara, (also known as Harisvara) a Virashaiva writer and the patron of King Narasimha I, wrote the ''Girijakalyana'' in the old Jain ''Champu'' style which describes the marriage of Lord Shiva and Parvati in ten sections.Sastri (1955), p362Narasimhacharya, (1988), p20 He was one of the earliest Virashaiva writers who was not part of the ''Vachana'' literary tradition. He came from a family of accountants (''Karanikas'') from Halebidu and spent many years in Hampi writing more than one hundred ''Ragales'' (poems in blank verse) in praise of Lord Virupaksha  (a form of Lord Shiva).E.P.Rice (1921), p60 Raghavanka was the first to introduce the ''Shatpadi'' metre into Kannada literature in  his ''Harishchandra kavya'' which is considered a classic even though it occasionally violates strict rules of Kannada grammar.Sastri (1955), p362Narasimhacharya (1988), p20

In Sanskrit, the philosopher Madhvacharya  wrote ''Rigbhshya''  on Brahmasutras (a logical explanation of Hindu scriptures, the Vedas) as well as many polemical works rebutting the doctrines of other schools of Vedas. He relied more on the Puranic literature than the Vedas for logical proof of his philosophy.Sastri (1955), p324, Another famous writing was ''Rudraprshnabhashya'' by Vidyatirtha.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0d242835bf638881f011e6280fd50b8c" name="Jain_Temple_at_Halebidu" sectnum="4.3#1">../img/0d242835bf638881f011e6280fd50b8c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>