<document id="6e1b71c30173b94e73b522e42db5ee82-4.2" name="Hoysala_Empire" cat="14">
<text>
Hoysala society in many ways reflected the emerging religious, political and cultural developments of those times. During this period, the society became increasingly sophisticated. The status of women was varied. Some royal women were involved in administrative matters as shown in contemporary records describing  Queen Umadevi's administration of  Halebidu in the absence of Veera Ballala II  during his long military campaigns in northern territories. She also fought and defeated some antagonistic feudal rebels.This is in stark contrast to the literature of the time (like ''Vikramankadeva Charita'' of Bilhana) that portrayed women as retiring,  overly romantic and unconcerned with affairs of the state (Thapar 2003, p392) Records describe the participation of women in the fine arts, such as  Queen Shantala Devi's skill in dance and music, and the 12th century Vachana poet  and  Virashaiva mystic Akka Mahadevi's  devotion to the ''bhakti''  movement is well known.She was not only a pioneer in the era of Women's emancipation but also an example of a transcendental world-view (Thapar 2003, p392) Temple dancers (''Devadasi'') were common and some were well educated and accomplished in the arts. These qualifications gave them more freedom than other urban and rural women who were restricted to daily mundane tasks.Thapar (2003), p391 The practice of sati in a voluntary form was prevalent and prostitution was socially acceptable. As in most of India, the Indian caste system was conspicuously present.

Trade on the west coast brought many foreigners to India including Arabs, Jews, Persians, Chinese and people from the Malay Peninsula.Sastri (1955), p286 Migration of people within Southern India as a result of the expansion of the empire produced an influx of new cultures and skills.Royal patronage of education, arts, architecture, religion and establishment of new forts and military outposts caused the large scale relocation of people (Sastri 1955, p287) In South India, towns were called ''Pattana'' or ''Pattanam'' and the marketplace, ''Nagara'' or ''Nagaram'', the marketplace serving as the nuclei of a city. Some towns such as Shravanabelagola developed from a religious settlement in the 7th century to an important trading center by the 12th century with the arrival of rich traders, while  towns like Belur attained the atmosphere of a regal city when King Vishnuvardhana built the Chennakesava Temple there. Large temples supported by royal patronage served religious, social, and judiciary purposes, elevating the king to the level of "God on earth".

Temple building served a commercial as well as a religious function and was not limited to any particular sect of Hinduism. Shaiva merchants of Halebidu financed the construction of the Hoysaleswara temple to compete with the Chennakesava temple built at Belur, elevating Halebidu to an important city as well. Hoysala temples however were secular and encouraged pilgrims of all Hindu sects, the Kesava temple at Somanathapura being an exception with strictly Vaishnava sculptural depictions. Temples built by rich landlords in rural areas fulfilled fiscal, political, cultural and religious needs of the agrarian communities. Irrespective of patronage, large temples served as establishments that provided employment to hundreds of people of various guilds and professions sustaining local communities as Hindu temples began to take on the shape of wealthy Buddhist monasteries.Thapar (2003), p389
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5911f38158e00f4da8f94464f7da4e1d" name="Belur_shilabalika1" sectnum="4.2#1">../img/5911f38158e00f4da8f94464f7da4e1d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>