<document id="6e26057fe568923166f5ee47d5432501-4" name="History_of_Bradford_City_A.F.C." cat="26">
<text>
In May 1981, City appointed former England international defender Roy McFarland as their new manager. After starting the 1981&ndash;82 season with a defeat and a draw, City went top of the table during a run of nine successive league victories, equalling a 30-year club record. The run came to an end against Sheffield United in front of 13,711 fans at Valley Parade, producing then club record gate receipts of £17,938. Arctic conditions across Britain meant City played only once during December, but they went back to the top of the Division Four table in January. City finished the season second, five points behind Sheffield United, and were promoted back to Division Three. However, only three months into the following campaign, McFarland and his assistant Mick Jones handed in their resignation and left for Derby County. Derby eventually had to pay a large fine and compensation to City for poaching the pair. Chairman Bob Martin turned to another England centre-back and appointed Trevor Cherry as McFarland's replacement from West Yorkshire rivals Leeds United. Cherry and assistant Terry Yorath continued to build on McFarland's start to the period which would later be called "Bantam Progressivism" by fanzine ''The City Gent''. Despite not recording their first win for more than two months, the pair guided City to 12th position.


However the club were again in financial difficulties, and in June 1983, Martin called in the receivers and the club was put up for sale. A ''Save Bradford City Fund'' was launched on 24 July, and former chairman Stafford Heginbotham and former board member Jack Tordoff bought the club, forming a new company, and enabling the team to start the new league campaign. Centre forward Bobby Campbell was sold to Derby County to balance the books and John Hawley brought in as his replacement. City struggled on the pitch and won just one of their first 15 games leaving them in the relegation zone. However, Campbell had played just 11 games during four months with Derby and so he returned to Bradford initially on a loan transfer. His return coincided with a club record ten successive league victories. Campbell finished the season with nine goals, Hawley with 22, but City finished seventh and missed out on promotion.

The good form continued the following season, and from October to mid-December 1984, City embarked on a 13-match unbeaten run, during which time Campbell became the club's all-time leading goalscorer, beating Frank O'Rourke's 70-year-old record. City went top of the division and held onto their lead, opening an 11-point cushion by February. Promotion was secured in April and the club's first championship title since 1929 after a 2&ndash;0 win over Bolton Wanderers. However, the success was overshadowed when fire ripped through Valley Parade's main stand 40 minutes into the final game of the season on 11 May 1985 against Lincoln City. A total of 56 people died and the club did not play another game at Valley Parade for nearly 20 months.

City instead played home games at Elland Road, Leeds Road and Odsal during the 1985&ndash;86 season, when they came 13th, and for the early part of the 1986&ndash;87 campaign. They returned to Valley Parade, which had undergone a £2.6m redevelopment, on Boxing Day 1986 against Derby County. However, after managing the side during the financial hardship and time away from their home ground, Cherry was dismissed only ten days after the return to Valley Parade. Club coach Terry Dolan was appointed as manager and he led the side away from relegation and to a finish of 10th-place. By September 1987, Dolan's side topped Division Two for the first time in 54 years. They finished fourth after a final day defeat to Ipswich Town and missed out on promotion after they lost to Middlesbrough in the play-offs. Leading players Stuart McCall and John Hendrie, who had both stayed for another season in a bid to take City into Division One, both left, and within two seasons City again dropped into Division Three.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b7a49541ced699e9764afaa747417507" name="RoyMcFarland03" sectnum="4#1">../img/b7a49541ced699e9764afaa747417507.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>