<document id="6e432d09e024efd42e1dbe14b5cd795a-2.3" name="Paul_Kane" cat="1">
<text>
By mid-July Kane had reached Fort Walla Walla, where he made a minor detour to visit the Whitman Mission that a few months later would be the site of the Whitman massacre. He went with Marcus Whitman to visit the Cayuse living in the area and even drew a portrait of Tomahas (Kane gives the name as "To-ma-kus"), the man who would later be named as Whitman's murderer. According to Kane's travel report, the relations between the Cayuse and the settlers at the mission were already strained by the time of his visit in July.



Kane continued with one guide by horseback through the Grande Coulée to Fort Colville, where he stayed for six weeks, sketching and painting the natives who had set up a fishing camp below Kettle Falls at this time of the Salmon run. On September 22 1847, Kane assumed command of a canoe brigade up the Columbia river and arrived on October 10 at Boat Encampment. There, the party had to wait for three weeks until a badly delayed horse trek from Jasper arrived. Then they switched, the horse team taking over the canoes and going down the Columbia river again and Kane's group loading their cargo on the horses and taking them back over Athabasca Pass. They managed to bring all 56 horses safe and without loss to Jasper's House despite the heavy snow and intense cold. As the canoes that should have been awaiting them had already left, they were forced to set out on snowshoes and with a dog sled to Fort Assiniboine, where they arrived after much hardship and without food two weeks later. After a few days' rest, they continued to Fort Edmonton, where they spent the winter.

Kane passed the time at the fort with Buffalo hunting and also sketched among the Cree living in the vicinity. In January he undertook an excursion to Fort Pitt, some  down the Saskatchewan River, and then returned to Edmonton. In April he visited Rocky Mountain House, where he wanted to meet Blackfoot. When these did not turn up, he returned to Edmonton.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5e29c01c5a9a9048d30eb698b0035bd5" name="Kane_Winter_Scene" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/5e29c01c5a9a9048d30eb698b0035bd5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>