<document id="6e63d85b7141b63b0411cd3ef1790b42-3.9" name="Uriel_Sebree" cat="29">
<text>
On April 15, 1909, Admiral Swinburne, the commander-in-chief of the Pacific Fleet, announced his retirement, and Sebree was appointed to replace him on May 17. Good public relations remained a major goal of the fleet, and in June, the fleet was displayed at the Alaska-Yukon-Pacific Exposition. President William Howard Taft led the exposition's opening ceremony, and many American dignitaries were in attendance.

Sebree's final mission before his retirement saw him lead the Pacific Fleet on a tour of ports in east Asia. The fleet left San Francisco on September 5, 1909, sailing west to the Philippines, with only brief stops en route. Speed testing was a major goal of the early part of the voyage and he and his fleet of eight ships broke speed records by sailing to Honolulu in just over four days. Six of the eight ships were able to make the voyage in that time; the ''Colorado'' and ''West Virginia'' had mechanical failures which prevented them from completing the voyage on time. On the ''Colorado'', those failures led to the deaths of two crewmen due to a steam pipe explosion. From Hawaii, the fleet moved on to Manila where the ships performed target practices and exercises, as well as being cleaned and repainted, before resuming their primary mission by sailing to Yokohama, Japan. In Japan, the fleet dispersed and small groups of cruisers were dispatched to the ports of British-controlled Hong Kong, Wusong in China, and Kobe, Japan. Afterwards, the fleet returned home. Just before Sebree's retirement the Pacific Fleet was split into two: a smaller Pacific Fleet and an Asiatic Fleet commanded by Rear Admiral John Hubbard. On February 19, 1910, Sebree officially retired and was replaced as head of the Pacific Fleet by Rear Admiral Giles B. Harber.

Shortly after retiring, Sebree was given a farewell banquet which included British Field Marshal Herbert Kitchener as a notable guest and California Governor James Gillett as toastmaster. In retirement, Sebree continued to attend Navy functions. In 1916, Sebree reported that the United States Navy lagged behind the world's other major navies. A single dreadnought, he claimed, could ravage the entire Pacific Fleet which was at that time relying on submarines for defense. The Atlantic Fleet already had dreadnoughts in commission.

Sebree died on August 5, 1922. Sebree Peak and Sebree Island, both in Alaska, are named for the admiral, who was survived by his wife, Anne B. Sebree, and one son, John B. Sebree, a member of the United States Marine Corps.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="22c1e46c5b52fc2da50e66d42ded73e5" name="Admiral_Sebree_and_Pacific_Fleet_Staff_on_the_Tennessee" sectnum="3.9#1">../img/22c1e46c5b52fc2da50e66d42ded73e5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>