<document id="6f2b4762201dbf3584513fa72ff84dc2-4" name="Stereolab" cat="20">
<text>
Stereolab have been called "one of the most influential alternative bands of the '90s," and one of "the decade's most innovative British bands."Jenkins (1998) Simon Reynolds commented in ''Rolling Stone'' that the group's earlier records form "an endlessly seductive body of work that sounds always the same, always different." In ''The Wire,'' Peter Shapiro compared the band favorably to Britpop bands Oasis and Blur, and defended their music against the charge that it is "nothing but the sum total of its arcane reference points." Stereolab was one of the first groups to be called post-rock—in a 1996 article, journalist Angela Lewis applied the "new term" to Stereolab and three other bands who have connections to the group.Lewis (1996) The band's 1996 album ''Emperor Tomato Ketchup,'' their "high-water mark" according to critic Joshua Klein, was a critical success and underground hit. Stereolab has also received negative press. Barney Hoskyns questioned the longevity of their music in a 1996 ''Mojo'' review, saying that their records "sound more like arid experiments than music born of emotional need."Hoskyns (1996) In ''The Guardian,'' Dave Simpson stated: "With their borrowings from early, obscure Kraftwerk and hip obtuse sources,  sound like a band of rock critics rather than musicians."Simpson (2001) Lætitia Sadier's vocals were criticized by author Stuart Shea for often being "indecipherable."Shea (2002), pp.53,54


A variety of artists—musical and otherwise—have collaborated with Stereolab. In 1995 the group teamed up with sculptor Charles Long for an interactive art show in New York City, for which Long provided the exhibits and Stereolab the music. They have released tracks by and toured with post-rock band Tortoise, while John McEntire of Tortoise has in turn worked on several Stereolab albums.Jenkins (2003) In the 1990s Stereolab and veteran industrial band Nurse With Wound released two limited-edition records together; both contained Nurse With Wound remixes of original tracks provided by Stereolab. In 1994, Sadier sang vocals on Blur's single 'To The End' which reached number 16 in the UK charts.

Stylistically, music journalist J. D. Considine credits the band for anticipating and driving the late 1990s revival of vintage analog instruments among indie rock bands.Considine (1997) Indie rock band Pavement (who also toured with Stereolab) acknowledged the group's sound on their song "Half A Canyon."See:
* Erlewine (AMG: Wowee Zowee)
*  Stereolab alumni have also founded bands of their own. Guitarist Sean O'Hagan went on to form the The High Llamas, while keyboardist Katharine Gifford created Snowpony with a former member of My Bloody Valentine.Jenkins (1998); Unterberger (The High Llamas) Sadier herself has released three albums with her four-piece side-project Monade, whose sound Mark Jenkins called a "little more Parisian" than Stereolab's.Jenkins (2005)

Despite earning critical acclaim and a sizable fanbase, commercial success eluded the group.Eliscu (2004), Stevens (2003) Early in their career, their 1993 EP ''Jenny Ondioline'' entered the UK Singles Chart, but financial issues prevented the band from printing enough records to satisfy demand.See:
* Stevens (2003)
*  When Elektra Records was closed down by Warner Bros. Records in 2004, Stereolab was dropped along with many other artists, reportedly because of poor sales. Since then, Stereolab's self-owned label Duophonic has inked a worldwide distribution deal with independent label Too Pure. Through Duophonic the band both licenses their music and releases it directly (depending on geographic market). According to Tim Gane, "… we license our recordings and just give them to people, then we don't have to ask for permission if we want to use it. We just want to be in control of our own music."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="42a60ebf6e154f88caf7c90def9a5b8a" name="Amorphousbodystudy" sectnum="4#1">../img/42a60ebf6e154f88caf7c90def9a5b8a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>