<document id="6f2b4762201dbf3584513fa72ff84dc2-1.2" name="Stereolab" cat="20">
<text>
On 8 January 1994, Stereolab achieved their first chart entry when their 1993 EP ''Jenny Ondioline'' entered at #75 on the UK Singles Chart. (Over the next three years, four more releases by the band would appear on this chart, ending with the EP ''Miss Modular'' in 1997.) With their 1994 full-length, ''Mars Audiac Quintet'', Stereolab focused more on pop and less on rock, resulting in what ''Allmusic'' described as "what may be the group's most accessible, tightly-written album".Phares (AMG: Mars Audiac Quintet) ''Mars Audiac Quintet'' makes heavy use of vintage electronic instruments, and also contains the single "Ping Pong", which gained press coverage for its allegedly explicitly Marxist lyrics.DeRogatis (1994); Mason (AMG: Ping Pong); Reynolds (1996) After releasing a 1995 collection of singles and B-sides called ''Refried Ectoplasm: Switched On, Vol. 2'', Stereolab followed with an EP titled ''Music for the Amorphous Body Study Center''. This EP was their musical contribution to an interactive art exhibit put on in collaboration with New York City artist Charles Long.Reynolds (1995)

Stereolab's 1996 album, ''Emperor Tomato Ketchup'', was a critical success and was played heavily on college radio. A record that "captivated alternative rock", it represented Stereolab's "high-water mark" according to music journalists Tom Moon and Joshua Klein, respectively.Klein (2001); Moon (2004) Krautrock techniques were still present, but the band stirred the pot with hip-hop sounds and complex instrumental arrangements.Erlewine (AMG: Emperor Tomato Ketchup) Stephan Davet of French newspaper ''Le Monde'' claimed to see musical influences as diverse as The Velvet Underground, Burt Bacharach, and Françoise Hardy on the album.Davet (1996) John McEntire of the band Tortoise assisted with production and also played on ''Emperor Tomato Ketchup'', while Katharine Gifford was replaced by Morgane Lhote before its recording, and bassist Duncan Brown by Richard Harrison afterward. 





''Dots and Loops'' was released in 1997, and was Stereolab's first album to enter the Billboard 200 charts, peaking at #111. Barney Hoskyns wrote in ''Rolling Stone'' that with it the group moved "ever further away from the one-chord Velvets drone-mesh of its early days" toward easy listening and Europop.Hoskyns (1997) A review in German newspaper ''Die Zeit'' echoed this observation, claiming that in ''Dots and Loops'' Stereolab transformed the harder Velvet Underground-like riffs of previous releases into "softer sounds and noisy playfulness". Contributors to the album once again included John McEntire, along with Sean O'Hagan of ''The High Llamas'' and Jan St. Werner of German electropop duo ''Mouse on Mars''. A second Nurse With Wound collaboration, ''Simple Headphone Mind'', appeared in 1997, and the third release in the "Switched On" series, ''Aluminum Tunes'', followed in 1998.

The band then took a break from traveling while Gane and Sadier had a child. In 1999, Stereolab's next album appeared, titled ''Cobra and Phases Group Play Voltage in the Milky Night''. Co-produced by McEntire and American producer Jim O'Rourke, the album earned mixed reviews for its lighter sound, and peaked at #154 on the Billboard 200.Erlewine (AMG: Cobra and Phases Group …); Hoskyns (1999) An unsigned ''NME'' review said that "this record has far more in common with bad jazz and progressive rock than any experimental art-rock tradition." In a 1999 ''The Washington Post'' article, Mark Jenkins asked Gane about the album's apparent lack of guitars; Gane responded, "There's a lot less upfront, distorted guitar … But it's still quite guitar-based music. Every single track has a guitar on it."Jenkins (5 November 1999) Stereolab added a new bassist, Simon Johns, for the ''Cobra and Phases Group …'' tour.

The full-length ''Sound-Dust'' followed in 2001, and rose to #178 on the Billboard 200. Again featuring producers McEntire and O'Rourke, it was more warmly received than ''Cobra and Phases Group …''.Klein (2001); Walters (2001) Critic Joshua Klein said that "the emphasis this time sounds less on unfocused experimentation and more on melody … a breezy and welcome return to form for the British band." Klein also commented that "never has it been harder to discern just what  is singing, but rarely has her gibberish sounded so pleasant."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="828819a1c174d520eb21f01b54bd98d0" name="StereolabEmperorTomatoKetchup" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/828819a1c174d520eb21f01b54bd98d0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>