<document id="6f2b4762201dbf3584513fa72ff84dc2-1.1" name="Stereolab" cat="20">
<text>
In 1985, Tim Gane formed McCarthy, a band from Essex, England known for their left-wing politics.Sutton (AMG: McCarthy) Gane met the French-born Lætitia SadierShe is sometimes known as "Seaya Sadier"; see Arundel (1991). at a McCarthy concert in Paris, and the two quickly fell in love. The musically-inclined Sadier was disillusioned with the rock scene in France, and soon moved to London to be with Gane and to pursue her career.Arundel (1991) After three albums, McCarthy broke up in 1990 and Gane immediately formed Stereolab with Sadier (who had also contributed vocals to McCarthy's final album) and ex-Chills bassist Martin Kean.Erlewine (AMG: Stereolab); Sutton (AMG: McCarthy) The group's name was taken from a division of Vanguard Records demonstrating hi-fi effects.

Gane and Sadier, along with future Stereolab manager Martin Pike, created a record label called Duophonic Super 45s&mdash;which, along with later offshoot Duophonic Ultra High Frequency Disks, would be commonly known as "Duophonic".H2O (Chunklet: Tim Gane) The 10" vinyl EP ''Super 45'' was the group's and the label's first release, and was sold through mail order and the Rough Trade Shop in London. ''Super 45'''s band-designed album art and packaging was the first of many customized and limited-edition Duophonic records. In a 1996 interview in ''The Wire'' Gane calls the "do-it-yourself" aesthetic behind Duophonic "empowering", and says that by releasing one's own music "you learn; it creates more music, more ideas".Shapiro (1996) Other independent bands such as Tortoise, Broadcast, and Labradford would also release material on Duophonic.

Stereolab followed up with another EP, ''Super-Electric'', and a single, "Stunning Debut Album" (not actually their debut). The band's early material was rock and guitar-oriented; of ''Super-Electric'', Jason Ankeny wrote in ''Allmusic'' that "Droning guitars, skeletal rhythms, and pop hooks—not vintage synths and pointillist melodies—were their calling cards …."Ankeny (AMG: Super Electric) In 1992 Stereolab's first full-length album, ''Peng!'', and first compilation, ''Switched On'', were released on independent label Too Pure. Around this time, the lineup coalesced around Gane and Sadier plus vocalist Mary Hansen, drummer Andy Ramsay, bassist Duncan Brown, keyboardist Katharine Gifford, and guitarist Sean O'Hagan of the 1980s famed Microdisney duo. Hansen, an Australian, had been in touch with Gane since his McCarthy days. After joining, she and Sadier developed a style of vocal counterpoint that distinguished Stereolab's sound until Hansen's death ten years later in 2002. O'Hagan would later leave to form The High Llamas, but would frequently return to contribute to Stereolab's records.DeRogatis (1993); Erlewine (AMG: Stereolab); Perrone (2002)




Starting with their 1993 EP ''Space Age Batchelor Pad Music'', the band began incorporating easy-listening elements into their sound. This release raised Stereolab's profile and landed them a major-label American record deal with Elektra Records. Their next album, 1993's ''Transient Random-Noise Bursts with Announcements'', was their first American release under Elektra, and became an underground hit in both the U.S. and the U.K.Erlewine (AMG: Stereolab) Mark Jenkins commented in ''The Washington Post'' that with the album Stereolab "continues the glorious drones of  indie work, giving celestial sweep to  garage-rock organ pumping and rhythm-guitar strumming".Jenkins (1993) In the U.K. it was released on Duophonic Ultra High Frequency Disks, which is responsible for domestic releases of Stereolab's major albums. The year would also see a collaboration with industrial stalwarts Nurse With Wound, in the form of the ''Crumb Duck'' EP.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1c63ad9652631a006c9706ab19215da6" name="Super45" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/1c63ad9652631a006c9706ab19215da6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>