<document id="6f764e0b6c273fd9ca1af604b94eaf96-4.1" name="Rhyolite,_Nevada" cat="11">
<text>
Montgomery Shoshone Mine and mill in early 1907, looking south toward Montgomery Mountain, over the rail spur line which served the mine. Rhyolite is visible in the background, to the right.

On August 9, 1904, Cross and Harris found gold on the south side of a southwestern Nevada hill later called Bullfrog Mountain.Lingenfelter, p. 203 Assays of ore samples from the site suggested values up to $3,000 a ton,Lingenfelter, p. 204 or about $ a ton in  dollars when adjusted for inflation. Word of the discovery spread to Tonopah and beyond, and soon thousands of hopeful prospectors and speculators rushed to what became known as the Bullfrog Mining District.Lingenfelter, pp. 204&ndash;07

Within the district, gold rush settlements quickly arose near the mines, and Rhyolite became the largest.Lingenfelter, p. 210 It sprang up near the most promising discovery, the Montgomery Shoshone Mine, which in February 1905 produced ores assayed as high as $16,000 a ton,Lingenfelter, p. 208 equivalent to $ a ton in . Starting as a two-man camp in January 1905, Rhyolite became a town of 1,200 people in two weeks and reached a population of 2,500 by June 1905. By then it had 50 saloons, 35 gambling tables, cribs for prostitution, 19 lodging houses, 16 restaurants, half a dozen barbers, a public bath house, and a weekly newspaper, the ''Rhyolite Herald''. Four daily  stage coaches connected Goldfield,  to the north, and Rhyolite. Rival auto lines ferried people between Rhyolite and Goldfield and the rail station in Las Vegas in Pope-Toledos, White Steamers, and other touring cars.

Charles M. Schwab (portrait, 1901) invested heavily in the Montgomery Shoshone Mine. 

Ernest Alexander "Bob" Montgomery, the original owner, and his partners sold the mine to industrialist Charles M. Schwab in February 1906.Lingenfelter, p. 215 Schwab expanded the operation on a grand scale, hiring workers, opening new tunnels and drifts, and building a huge mill to process the ore. He had water piped in, paid to have an electric line run  from a hydroelectric plant at the foot of the Sierras to Rhyolite, and contracted with the Las Vegas and Tonopah Railroad to run a spur line to the mine.Lingenfelter, p. 218 Three railroads eventually served Rhyolite. The first was the Las Vegas and Tonopah Railroad (LVTR), which began running regular trains to the city on December 14, 1906.Lingenfelter, pp. 222&ndash;24 Its depot, built in California-mission style, cost about $130,000, equivalent to about  $ in . About a half-year later, the Bullfrog Goldfield Railroad (BGR) began regular service from the north. By December 1907, the Tonopah and Tidewater Railroad (TTR) began service to Rhyolite on tracks leased from the BGR. The TTR was built to reach the borax-bearing colemanite beds in Death Valley as well as the gold fields.

By 1907, about 4,000 people lived in Rhyolite, according to Richard E. Lingenfelter in ''Death Valley & the Amargosa: A Land of Illusion''. Russell R. Elliott cites an estimated population of 5,000 in 1907&ndash;08 in ''Nevada's Twentieth-Century Mining Boom'', noting that "accurate population figures during the boom are impossible to obtain". Alan H. Patera in ''Rhyolite: The Boom Years'' states published estimates of the peak population have been "as high as 6,000 or 8,000, but the town itself never claimed more than 3,500 through its newspapers".Patera, p. 2 The newspapers estimated that 6,000 people lived in the Bullfrog mining district, which included the towns of Rhyolite, Bullfrog, Gold Center, and Beatty as well as camps at the major mines.



Rhyolite in 1907 had concrete sidewalks, electric lights, water mains, telephone and telegraph lines, daily and weekly newspapers, a monthly magazine, police and fire departments, a hospital, school, train station and railway depot, at least three banks, a stock exchange, an opera house, and two formal church buildings. Most prominent was the three-story John S. Cook and Co. Bank on Golden Street. Finished in 1908, it cost more than $90,000,Lingenfelter, p. 219  equivalent to  $ in .  Much of the cost went for Italian marble stairs, imported stained-glass windows, and other luxuries. The building housed brokerage offices, and a post office, as well as the bank. Other large buildings included the train depot, the three-story Overbury Block, and the two-story eight-room school. A miner named Tom T. Kelly built the Bottle House in February 1906 from 50,000 discarded beer and liquor bottles. Another building housed the Rhyolite Mining Stock Exchange, which opened on March 25, 1907, with 125 members, including brokers from New York, Philadelphia, Los Angeles, and other large cities. The small, modestly equipped storefront listed shares of 74 Bullfrog companies and a similar number of companies in nearby mining districts. Sixty thousand shares changed hands on the first day, and by the end of the second week the number had topped 750,000. Lingenfelter, pp. 219&ndash;22
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="86b339b91a70f6259535dfb58f7355c1" name="Rhyolite" sectnum="4.1#1">../img/86b339b91a70f6259535dfb58f7355c1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>