<document id="6fa1ff9dda249f094059315aeff058ab-6" name="Third_Servile_War" cat="29">
<text>
The rebellion of the Third Servile War had been annihilated by Crassus.

Pompey's forces did not directly engage Spartacus' forces at any time, but his legions moving in from the north were able to capture some 5,000 rebels fleeing the battle, "all of whom he slew".'''Matyszak''', ''The Enemies of Rome'' p.133; '''Plutarch''', ''Pompey'', , ''Crassus'' . Because of this, Pompey sent a dispatch to the Senate, saying that while Crassus certainly had conquered the slaves in open battle, he himself had ended the war, thus claiming a large portion of the credit and earning the enmity of Crassus.'''Plutarch''', ''Crassus'', .

While most of the rebel slaves had been killed on the battlefield, some 6,000 survivors had been captured by the legions of Crassus. All 6,000 were crucified along the Appian Way from Rome to Capua.'''Appian''', ''Civil Wars'', .

Pompey and Crassus reaped political benefit for having put down the rebellion. Both Crassus and Pompey returned to Rome with their legions and refused to disband them, instead encamping them outside Rome. Both men stood for the consulship of 70 BC, even though Pompey was ineligible because of his youth, and lack of service as praetor or quaestor.'''Appian''', ''Civil Wars'', . Nonetheless, both men were elected consul for 70 BC,'''Appian''', ''Civil Wars'', ; '''Plutarch''', ''Crassus'', . partly due to the implied threat of their armed legions encamped outside the city.'''Fagan''', ''The History of Ancient Rome''; '''Appian''', ''Civil Wars'', .

The effects of the Third Servile War on the Roman attitudes towards slavery, and the institution of slavery in Rome, are harder to determine. Certainly the revolt had shaken the Roman people, who "out of sheer fear seem to have begun to treat their slaves less harshly than before."'''Davis''', ''Readings in Ancient History'', p.90 The wealthy owners of the latifundia began to reduce the number of agricultural slaves, opting to employ the large pool of formerly dispossessed freemen in sharecropping arrangements. With the end of Julius Caesar's Gallic Wars in 52 BC, the major Roman wars of conquest would cease until the reign of emperor Trajan (reigned 98–117 AD), and with them the supply of plentiful and inexpensive slaves through military conquest, further promoting the use of freemen laborers in agricultural estates.

The legal status and rights of the Roman slave also began to change. During the time of emperor Claudius (reigned 41–54 AD), a constitution was enacted which made the killing of an old or infirm slave an act of murder, and decreed that if such slaves were abandoned by their owners, they became freedmen.'''Suetonius''', ''Life of Claudius'',  Under Antoninus Pius (reigned 138–161 AD), the legal rights of slaves were further extended, holding owners responsible for the killing of slaves, forcing the sale of slaves when it could be shown that they were being mistreated, and providing a (theoretically) neutral third party authority to which a slave could appeal.'''Gaius''', ''Institvtionvm Commentarivs'', ; '''Seneca''', ''De Beneficiis'', . Gaius details the changes in the right of the owner to inflict whatever treatment they wished upon the slave, while Seneca details the slave's right to proper treatment and the creation of a "slave ombudsman". While these legal changes occurred much too late to be ''direct'' results of the Third Servile War, they represent the legal codification of changes in the Roman attitude toward slaves which would have been evolving for decades.

It is difficult to determine the extent to which the events of this war contributed to the changes in the use and legal rights of Roman slaves. It seems that the end of the Servile Wars coincided with the end of the period of most prominent use of slaves in Rome, and the beginning of a new perception of the slave within Roman society and law. The Third Servile War was the last of the Servile Wars, and Rome would not see another slave uprising of this type again.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="147d22f706399a1ca2b25b746efc5a82" name="Spartacus_II" sectnum="6#1">../img/147d22f706399a1ca2b25b746efc5a82.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>