<document id="6fa1ff9dda249f094059315aeff058ab-2.1" name="Third_Servile_War" cat="29">
<text>
In the Roman Republic of the first century, gladiatorial games were one of the more popular forms of entertainment. In order to supply gladiators for the contests, several training schools, or ''ludi'', were established throughout Italy.'''Smith''', ''Greek and Roman Antiquities'', . In these schools, prisoners of war and condemned criminals—who were considered slaves—were taught the skills required to fight to the death in gladiatorial games.'''Mommsen''', ''The History of Rome'', 3233–3238. In 73 BC, a group of some 200 gladiators in the Capuan school owned by Lentulus Batiatus plotted an escape. When their plot was betrayed, a force of about 70 men seized kitchen implements, ("choppers and spits"), fought their way free from the school, and seized several wagons of gladiatorial weapons and armor.'''Plutarch''', ''Crassus'', ; '''Appian''', ''Civil Wars'', ; '''Livy''', ''Periochae'', ; '''Florus''', ''Epitome'', 2.8. Plutarch claims 78 escaped, Livy claims 74, Appian "about seventy", and Florus says "thirty or rather more men". "Choppers and spits" is from ''Life of Crassus''.

Once free, the escaped gladiators chose leaders from their number, selecting two Gallic slaves—Crixus and Oenomaus—and Spartacus, who was said either to be a Thracian auxiliary from the Roman legions later condemned to slavery, or a captive taken by the legions.'''Appian''', ''Civil Wars'', ; '''Plutarch''', ''Crassus'', . Note: Spartacus' status as an auxilia is taken from the Loeb edition of Appian translated by Horace White, which states "...who had once served as a soldier with the Romans...". However, the translation by John Carter in the Penguin Classics version reads: "...who had once fought against the Romans and after being taken prisoner and sold...". There is some question as to Spartacus's nationality, however, as a ''Thraex'' (plural ''Thraces'' or ''Threses'') was a type of gladiator in Rome, so that the title "Thracian" may simply refer to the style of gladiatorial combat in which he was trained.'''Smith''', ''Greek and Roman Antiquities'', .

These escaped slaves were able to defeat a small force of troops sent after them from Capua, and equip themselves with captured military equipment as well as their gladiatorial weapons.'''Plutarch''', ''Crassus'', . Sources are somewhat contradictory on the order of events immediately following the escape, but they generally agree that this band of escaped gladiators plundered the region surrounding Capua, recruited many other slaves into their ranks, and eventually retired to a more defensible position on Mount Vesuvius.'''Appian''', ''Civil Wars'', ; '''Florus''', ''Epitome'', 2.8; - Florus and Appian make the claim that the slaves withdrew to Vesuvius, while Plutarch only mentions "a hill" in the account of Glaber's siege of the slave's encampment.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="76cc9f46767a7ceaf72ee02d6c9a4998" name="Borghese_gladiator_1_mosaic_dn_r2_c2" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/76cc9f46767a7ceaf72ee02d6c9a4998.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>