<document id="6ff09c51ca77408676c832cb730e8850-4.7.1" name="Restoration_of_the_Sistine_Chapel_frescoes" cat="1">
<text>
The restorers took for granted that all of the layers of grease and soot on the ceiling were the result of candle smoke. Contrary to this view, James Beck and numerous artists have suggested that Michelangelo used carbon black in a wash of glue to lay on shadows and crisp dark definition, ''a secco''. If this is the case, then the greater part was removed in the restoration.Colalucci refers to this opinion in his Appendix quoted above

On some of the figures, however, there still remains clear evidence of painting in carbon black. The apparent explanation for this is that over the long period that Michelangelo was at work, he probably, for a variety of reasons, varied his technique. Things that might affect the degree of finish achieved on a particular ''giornata'' include the heat and humidity of the day and the length of daylight hours. Whatever the reason for the difference is, a difference in approach to the light and shade on the individual figures is clearly apparent.

There are still intense areas of shadow which throw the Cumaean Sibyl into relief. But it is more than relief; it is the three-dimensionality which art-lovers expect to see in the work of the man who sculpted Moses. Critics of the restoration claim that this was Michelangelo's aim and that many frescoes, had brightly contrasting colours laid side-by-side that were then worked over ''a secco'' to achieve this effect and that this is what has been lost by a too-scrupulous cleaning.

Consistently missing from the restored ceiling is the crisp ''a secco'' detailing of the architecture: the scallop shells, acorns and "bead and reel" ornament which Michelangelo possibly would have left for completion by an assistant, when he moved on to the next panel. The treatment of these details varied considerably. In a few places, around the Ezekias spandrel, for example, the architectural detailing was painted ''buon fresco'' and remains intact.


A comparison of two spandrels reveals different post-restoration states. The one on the left has shadows and details defined in black. The green robe with yellow highlights has been washed with black and defined with deep shadow. On the fictive architecture each motif is picked out in black. The eyes of the child are detailed in black and white. The continued presence of these details suggests that they were completed while the plaster was damp. The entire right spandrel has an unfinished look. Before cleaning it also had black defining the shadows of the robes and crisp detailing on the architecture.

On the corner pendentives, each of which depicts a violent subject, the removal of the carbon black has diminished the dramatic intensity of all four scenes. This is particularly noticeable in the loss of depth in the ''Death of Haman''. Where once the figure projected starkly against the darkly shadowed interior, now foreshortening, definition and drama is lost in the pastel monotone that remains.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c53129de5bf2e93e6567dafee90804c2" name="Sistine_Chapel_TwoSpandrels" sectnum="4.7.1#1">../img/c53129de5bf2e93e6567dafee90804c2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>