<document id="6ff5afa5061dedbf8d2e02e07e5552da-2.4" name="Sunderland_Echo" cat="19">
<text>
Bridge Street remained the home of the ''Echo'' for the next 100 years. Old buildings were demolished, new machine and composing rooms built on West Wear Street and two rotary presses installed just before the move, each capable of printing 24,000 copies an hour. These changes brought about increased circulation, but it took another seven years before the ''Echo'' made a profit. It was a time of intense competition; the ''Sunderland Times'' converted from a bi-weekly to a daily paper in the same month as the ''Echo'' moved to Bridge Street, and Tory supporters started a paper of their own, the ''Sunderland Daily Post''. The ''Sunderland Times'' was the first to collapse, but the ''Post'' survived for the next quarter of a century, providing the ''Echo'' with an often bitter rival.

Following the deaths of two further partners, Backhouse in 1879 and Turnbull in 1880, Storey bought their shares to become the ''Echo'''s chief proprietor. A year later, in 1881, he met Scottish-born millionaire Andrew Carnegie, and formed a syndicate with him to set up new newspapers and buy up others. Among those purchased were the ''Wolverhampton Express and Star'', the ''Northern Daily Mail'' in Hartlepool and the ''Portsmouth Evening News''. An attempt to buy the ''Shields Gazette'', the country's oldest daily newspaper, failed. The syndicate finally broke up in 1885, with Storey retaining control of the ''Echo'', ''Hampshire Telegraph'', ''Portsmouth News'' and the ''Northern Daily Mail''. These papers formed the basis of a new company, Portsmouth and Sunderland Newspapers Ltd, formed in the 1930s. The 19th century ended with the rivalry between the ''Echo'' and the ''Sunderland Daily Post'' intensifying. The Silksworth Colliery strike of 1891 pitted the two papers against each other, with the ''Post'' attacking Storey for having exploited the strike for political gain. Storey successfully sued for libel.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e4edb663a0e12cddd8720d171f293ac3" name="echobridgestreet" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/e4edb663a0e12cddd8720d171f293ac3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>