<document id="700f481e683a0be686bf2e4f02a549d7-2.3" name="Steve_Bruce" cat="26">
<text>
Bruce made his Manchester United debut in a 2&ndash;1 win over Portsmouth on 19 December 1987, and played in 21 of United's remaining 22 league fixtures, helping the club to a top two place in the First Division for the first time since 1980. The team could only finish in mid-table in the following season, however, prompting manager Alex Ferguson to bring in a number of new players, including Gary Pallister, who joined the club in August 1989 from Middlesbrough. His partnership with Bruce in the centre of defence was described in 2006 by the then-United captain, Gary Neville, as the best in the club's history. Bruce and Pallister were part of the team which won the 1990 FA Cup final against Crystal Palace in a replay.

Following the lifting of the five-year ban on English clubs from European competitions, which had been imposed after the Heysel Stadium Disaster, United became England's first entrants into the UEFA Cup Winners' Cup in the 1990&ndash;91 season. Bruce played regularly, and scored three goals, in the team's progress to the final against FC Barcelona. He came close to scoring the first goal, only for Mark Hughes to deflect the ball over the line and claim the goal, and United went on to win the game 2&ndash;1. This was a particularly high-scoring season for Bruce, who found the net 13 times in the First Division and 19 times in total in all competitions. He also played again at Wembley, in the Football League Cup final, in which United were defeated by Sheffield Wednesday of the Second Division. 


Bruce missed several weeks of the 1991&ndash;92 season when he underwent an operation on a longstanding hernia problem, in which Leeds United, after a season-long tussle, beat the "Red Devils" to the championship by four points. Bruce was, however, able to help United win their first-ever League Cup in April 1992, captaining the team in the final in place of the injured Bryan Robson. Injuries continued to take their toll upon Robson during the 1992&ndash;93 season, leading to Bruce captaining the team in the majority of United's matches during the first season of the new Premier League. Bruce scored two late goals in a win over Sheffield Wednesday which proved decisive in United winning the inaugural Premier League title, the first time the club had won the championship of English football since 1967, and he and Robson received the trophy jointly after the home victory over Blackburn Rovers on 3 May.

At the height of his success with United, Bruce was contacted by Jack Charlton, manager of the Republic of Ireland national team, who had discovered that, due to his mother's place of birth, Bruce was eligible to play for Ireland. Bruce states in his autobiography that further investigation revealed that, while his earlier appearance for England B in a friendly match was not an issue, his appearances for the England Youth team in a UEFA-sanctioned tournament prohibited him from playing for the senior team of another country. He has subsequently claimed, however, that he chose not to play for Ireland as it would have caused problems for his club at a time when the Premier League restricted the number of foreign players that a club could include in its team. 

United dominated English football in the 1993&ndash;94 season, winning a second consecutive Premier League title and then defeating Chelsea in the FA Cup final to become only the fourth team, and Bruce the first English captain, to win The Double in the twentieth century,The other twentieth century Double-winning captains were Dave Mackay and Alan Hansen, both from Scotland, and Danny Blanchflower from Northern Ireland The 1994&ndash;95 season was a disappointing one for Bruce and United, however, as the club failed in its bid to win a third consecutive Premier League title and lost to Everton in the FA Cup final.

During the following season Bruce was offered the job of manager by three different clubs, but Ferguson refused to allow him to pursue the opportunities as he felt the player still had a role to play in the United team. Bruce made a further 30 Premier League appearances, as United managed to overcome a twelve-point deficit to Newcastle United to win the championship once again. A week later, however, he was left out of United's squad for the FA Cup final, due to a slight injury. At the end of the match Eric Cantona, who had captained the team and scored the only goal in a 1&ndash;0 win over Liverpool, attempted to persuade Bruce to be the one to receive the trophy, but Bruce declined. Ferguson denied that Bruce's omission was a sign that his time at the club was nearing an end, but Bruce, then 35 years old, believed that 
he would be unlikely to be selected for the team during the year remaining on his contract. He opted instead to join First Division club Birmingham City on a free transfer, having signed a contract valued at nearly £2 million over two years, which made him one of the highest-paid players in the country.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a8fea157b182da35c629303ffc1a5b5f" name="Steve_Bruce_at_the_cliff_-march_92" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/a8fea157b182da35c629303ffc1a5b5f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>