<document id="700f481e683a0be686bf2e4f02a549d7-2.2" name="Steve_Bruce" cat="26">
<text>
Bruce began the 1984&ndash;85 season by scoring an own goal in the first minute of his debut for Norwich against Liverpool, but went on to score the team's winning goal in the semi-final of the Football League Cup against local rivals Ipswich Town, and was named man of the match in Norwich's victory in the final. Bruce was voted Norwich City Player of the Year, but the team was relegated to the Second Division. Bruce played in every match as Norwich won promotion back to the top division at the first time of asking in the 1985&ndash;86 season, after which he was chosen to replace the departing Dave Watson as club captain. The following season he helped the club to its highest ever league finish of fifth position.

In 1987, he was chosen to captain the England B team in a match against the full national team of Malta, but it was to be his only appearance in an England shirt, and he has subsequently been described as one of the best defenders of his era never to be selected for the full England team. Bruce later stated "I bumped into former England manager Bobby Robson in Benfica'' (sic)''. He came up to me and said 'I should have capped you'. It was nice to hear but it still didn't get me one....I'll always be a little disappointed I didn't get one."

Bruce began to attract the attention of big-name clubs in late 1987, with Manchester United, Tottenham Hotspur, Chelsea and Rangers all reported to be interested in signing him. Manchester United quickly emerged as the front runners for his signature, and Bruce publicly expressed his desire to sign for the club. The deal came close to collapsing when Norwich asked for a transfer fee of £900,000 after initially agreeing to accept £800,000, leading to Bruce refusing to play any further matches for the club, which he felt was jeopardising his dream move. On 17 December 1987, however, shortly before his 27th birthday, the deal was finally concluded and Bruce officially left Carrow Road, for a fee reported as £800,000 or £825,000. Norwich fans remembered his contribution, however, and in 2002 voted him into the Norwich City F.C. Hall of Fame.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="538bcdb3bea81d00be0dd0e4daa9d167" name="SteveBruceNorwich1980s" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/538bcdb3bea81d00be0dd0e4daa9d167.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>