<document id="7068d3a40f59460ca6ecbe36750f169b-4" name="Alaska_class_cruiser" cat="29">
<text>
Early in its development, the class used the designation CC, which signified that they were to be battlecruisers in the tradition of the ''Lexington'' class;The ''Lexington'' class would have been designated CC-1 through CC-6, had they been built. however, the designation was later changed to CB to reflect their new name, "large cruiser", and the practice of referring to them as battlecruisers was officially discouraged. The U.S. Navy then named the individual vessels after U.S. territories, rather than states (as was the tradition with battleships) or cities (for which cruisers were named), to symbolize the belief that these ships were supposed to play an intermediate role between heavy cruisers and fully-fledged battlecruisers.

They resembled contemporary battleships in appearance, weighed only 5,000 tons less in displacement, mounted the familiar 2-A-1 main battery,It was also found on the , ''South Dakota''-class battleship,  and ''Baltimore''-class heavy cruiser. shared a similar massive columnar mast, and carried 5"/38 caliber dual-purpose guns along the sides of the superstructure, although the battleships carried eight (older refitted ships) or ten (post-''South Dakota'') 5"/38 twin mounts flanking the superstructure while the ''Alaska'' cruisers only carried six: one at each of the four superstructure corners, and one each at fore and aft on the centerline.An example of an older refitted ship: An example of a newer ship: 

There are two main arguments for referring to the ''Alaska'' class as "large cruisers". The first is their armor; while they were able to withstand more fire from guns than any other cruiser afloat, they were virtually defenseless against torpedoes because they had no sub-divisions within the hull and no anti-torpedo scheme. The lack of underwater protection would also make them vulnerable to shells which fell slightly short of their mark and continued underwater to hit the hull. In addition, their armor was only marginally capable of stopping 12" fire;Dulin Jr., Garzke Jr. (1976), p. 283 they were vulnerable to battleship fire (14–16" fire) at any range.Dulin Jr., Garzke Jr. (1976), p. 279.  The second argument lies entirely in their design. The design of the ''Alaska'' class ships was, from the keel up, just a scaled-up treaty cruiser finally unencumbered by the Washington, London and Second London naval treaties. In addition, despite being much larger than the ''Baltimore'' class, the secondary battery of the "large cruisers" was only slightly larger. Whereas the ''Alaska'' class carried twelve 5"/38 caliber, fifty-six 40 mm, and thirty-four 20 mm guns, the ''Baltimore'' class carried the same number of 5"/38s, eight fewer 40 mm, and only ten fewer 20 mm. In addition to all of this, author Richard Worth has remarked that when they were finally completed, launched, and commissioned, they had the "size of a battleship but the capabilities of a cruiser".

Despite these cruiser-like characteristics, and the U.S. Navy's insistence on their status as cruisers, the ''Alaska'' class were frequently described as battlecruisers at the time. Some modern historians take the view that this is a more accurate designationOsbourne, 245. because they believe that the ships were "in all sense of the word, battlecruisers, with all the vulnerabilities characteristic of the type." In terms of displacement, the ''Alaska'' class was about twice as heavy as the newest heavy cruisers (the ''Baltimore'' class).Morison, Morison and Polmar, 84. Second, they had much larger guns; while the ''Alaska'' class carried nine 12"/50 caliber guns that were as good as, if not superior to, the old 14"/50 caliber gun used on the U.S. Navy's pre-treaty battleships, the ''Baltimore'' class had an equal number of 8"/55 caliber Marks 12 and 15 guns.  Moreover, the traditional Anglo-American battlecruiser concept had always sacrificed protection for the sake of speed and armament.Sumida, Jon Tetsuro, ''In Defence of Naval Supremacy''. London: Routledge (1993) p.262.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d69db1997223d18c52df110bdb0a565c" name="USS_Missouri_(BB-63)_and_USS_Alaska_(CB-1)_at_Norfolk,_Virginia,_1944" sectnum="4#1">../img/d69db1997223d18c52df110bdb0a565c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>