<document id="7068d3a40f59460ca6ecbe36750f169b-3" name="Alaska_class_cruiser" cat="29">
<text>
and  served with the U.S. Navy in the last years of World War II. Similar to the  fast battleships, their speed made them useful as shore bombardment ships and fast carrier escorts. Both protected  when she was on her way to be repaired in Guam after being hit by two Japanese bombs. Afterward, ''Alaska'' supported the landings on Okinawa, while ''Guam'' went to San Pedro Bay to become the leader of a new task force, Cruiser Task Force 95. ''Guam'', joined by ''Alaska'', four light cruisers, and nine destroyers, led the task force into the East China and Yellow Seas to conduct raids upon shipping. However, they only encountered Chinese junks. By the end of the war, the two had become celebrated within the fleet as excellent carrier escorts.

After the war, both ships were decommissioned and "mothballed" in 1947 after having spent 32 and 29 months in service, respectively. In 1958, the Bureau of Ships prepared two feasibility studies to explore whether ''Alaska'' and ''Guam'' could be suitably converted into guided-missile cruisers. The first study involved removing all of the guns in favor of four different missile systems. At $160 million, this proposed removal was seen as cost-prohibitive, so a second study was initiated. The study left the forward batteries (the two 12-inch triple turrets and three of the 5-inch dual turrets) unchanged, and added a reduced version of the first plan on the stern of the ship. Even though the proposals would have cost approximately half as much as the first study's plan ($82 million), it was still seen as too expensive.Dulin, Jr., Garzke Jr., 187. As a result, both ships were stricken from the Naval Vessel Register on 1 June 1960. ''Alaska'' was sold for scrap on 30 June 1960, and ''Guam'' on 24 May 1961.

The still-incomplete  was considered for a conversion to be the Navy's first guided-missile cruiser for a time;A similar proposal was made to convert the uncompleted ''Iowa''-class battleship  into the first guided-missile battleship (BBG), but as with the proposal for ''Hawaii'' this conversion never materialized, and ''Kentucky'' was scrapped in 1958. this thought lasted until 26 February 1952, when a different conversion to a "large command ship" was contemplated. In anticipation of the conversion, her classification was changed to CBC-1. This would have made her a "larger sister" for , but a year and a half later (9 October 1954) she was re-designated CB-3. ''Hawaii'' was stricken from the Naval Vessel Register on 9 June 1958 and was sold for scrap in 1959.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fe0e6584d1b09a5f48d53290332318d3" name="Guam_shakedown" sectnum="3#1">../img/fe0e6584d1b09a5f48d53290332318d3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>