<document id="7068d3a40f59460ca6ecbe36750f169b-5.3" name="Alaska_class_cruiser" cat="29">
<text>
As built, the ''Alaska'' class had nine 12"/50 caliber Mark 8 guns mounted in three triple (3-gun) turrets, with two turrets forward and one aft, a configuration known as "2-A-1". The previous 12" gun manufactured for the U.S. Navy was the Mark 7 version, which had been designed and installed in the 1912 s. The Mark 8 was of considerably higher quality; in fact, it "was by far the most powerful weapon of its caliber ever placed in service."Dulin, Jr. and Garzke, Jr., 190. Designed in 1939, it weighed , including the breech, and could sustain an average rate of fire of 2.4–3 rounds a minute. It could throw a 1,140 lb. (517.093 kg) Mark 18 armor piercing shell 38,573 yards (35,271 meters) at an elevation of 45°, while the guns had a 344-shot "barrel life" (comparable to the 16"/50 caliber Mark 7 gun found in the ''Iowa'' battleships, ''Alaska'' cruisers could fire about 54 more shots).

The turrets were very similar to those of the ''Iowa''-class battleships, but differed in several ways; for example, the ''Alaska''-class had a two-stage powder hoist, instead of ''Iowa''-class's one-stage hoist. These differences made operating the guns safer and increased the rate of fire. Also, a "projectile rammer" was added to ''Alaska'' and ''Guam''. This machine transferred shells from storage on the ship to the rotating ring that fed the guns. However, this feature proved unsatisfactory, and it was not planned for ''Hawaii'' or any subsequent ships.

Because ''Alaska'' and ''Guam'' were the only two ships to mount these guns, only ten turrets were made during the war (three for each ship including ''Hawaii'' and one spare). They cost the Navy $1,550,000 each and were the most expensive heavy guns purchased by the U.S. Navy in World War II.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2850fef297b3e6f2b86bd53cb640b1d9" name="USS_Guam_(CB-2)_firing_main_battery,_1944-45" sectnum="5.3#1">../img/2850fef297b3e6f2b86bd53cb640b1d9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>