<document id="70780355e478c7075444edba707c92b1-7" name="Allosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
Along with ''Tyrannosaurus'', ''Allosaurus'' has come to represent the quintessential large, carnivorous dinosaur in popular culture. It is a common dinosaur in museums, due in particular to the excavations at the Cleveland Lloyd Dinosaur Quarry; by 1976, as a result of cooperative operations, 38 museums in eight countries on three continents had Cleveland-Lloyd allosaur material or casts. ''Allosaurus'' is the official state fossil of Utah.

''Allosaurus'' has been depicted in popular culture since the early years of the 20th century.  It is top predator in both Arthur Conan Doyle's 1912 novel, ''The Lost World'', and its 1925 film adaptation, the first full-length motion picture to feature dinosaurs.Glut, Donald F.; Brett-Surman, Michael K. (1997). "Dinosaurs and the media", in Farlow, James; and Brett-Surman, Michael K. (eds.): The Complete Dinosaur. Bloomington and Indianapolis: Indiana University Press, 675–706. ISBN 0-253-33349-0. It later became the starring dinosaur of the 1956 film ''The Beast of Hollow Mountain'',Lambert, ''Dinosaur Data Book'', p. 299. and the 1969 film ''The Valley of Gwangi'', two genre combinations of living dinosaurs with Westerns.  In ''The Valley of Gwangi'', Gwangi is billed as an ''Allosaurus'', although Ray Harryhausen based his model for the creature on Charles R. Knight's depiction of a ''Tyrannosaurus''. Harryhausen sometimes confuses the two, stating in a DVD interview "They're both meat eaters, they're both tyrants... one was just a bit larger than the other."''Return to the Valley'', a documentary on the Region 1 ''Valley of Gwangi'' DVD. ''Allosaurus'' also made appearances in the Hammer 1966 remake ''One Million Years B.C.'' and the 1975 film adaptation of ''The Land that Time Forgot''. In nonfictional presentations, ''Allosaurus'' appears in the second and fifth episodes of the BBC television series ''Walking with Dinosaurs'', ''Jurassic Fight Club'', and the ''Walking with Dinosaurs'' special ''The Ballad of Big Al'' which chronicles the life of the ''Allosaurus'' specimen nicknamed "Big Al".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="814b35520289175c665fe5bb790619da" name="Allosaurus_in_Baltow_20060916_1500" sectnum="7#1">../img/814b35520289175c665fe5bb790619da.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>