<document id="70780355e478c7075444edba707c92b1-6.6" name="Allosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
The wealth of ''Allosaurus'' fossils, from nearly all ages of individuals, allows scientists to study how the animal grew and how long its lifespan may have been. Remains may reach as far back in the lifespan as eggs—crushed eggs from Colorado have been suggested as those of ''Allosaurus''. Based on histological analysis of limb bones, the upper age limit for ''Allosaurus'' is estimated at 22 to 28 years, which is comparable to that of other large theropods like ''Tyrannosaurus''. From the same analysis, its maximum growth appears to have been at age 15, with an estimated growth rate of about 150 kilograms (330 lb) per year. 

Medullary bone tissue, also found in dinosaurs as diverse as ''Tyrannosaurus'' and ''Tenontosaurus'', has been found in at least one ''Allosaurus'' specimen, a shin bone from the Cleveland-Lloyd Quarry.  Today, this bone tissue is only formed in female birds that are laying eggs, as it is used to supply calcium to shells.  Its presence in the ''Allosaurus'' individual establishes sex and shows she had reached reproductive age.  By counting growth lines, it was shown that she was 10 years old at death, so sexual maturity in ''Allosaurus'' was attained well before maximum growth and size.
 
The discovery of a juvenile specimen with a nearly complete hindlimb shows that the legs were relatively longer in juveniles, and the lower segments of the leg (shin and foot) were relatively longer than the thigh.  These differences suggest that younger ''Allosaurus'' were faster and had different hunting strategies than adults, perhaps chasing small prey as juveniles, then becoming ambush hunters of large prey upon adulthood. The thigh bone became thicker and wider during growth, and the cross-section less circular, as muscle attachments shifted, muscles became shorter, and the growth of the leg slowed. These changes imply that juvenile legs has less predictable stresses compared with adults, which would have moved with more regular forward progression.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e3a0e3615282c7fc9d925951dbc5aa49" name="Allosaurus_juvenile_skeleton" sectnum="6.6#1">../img/e3a0e3615282c7fc9d925951dbc5aa49.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>