<document id="70780355e478c7075444edba707c92b1-2" name="Allosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
''Allosaurus'' was an allosaurid, a member of a family of large theropods within the larger group Carnosauria.  The family name Allosauridae was created for this genus in 1878 by Othniel Charles Marsh, but the term was largely unused until the 1970s in favor of Megalosauridae, another family of large theropods that eventually became a wastebasket taxon. This, along with the use of ''Antrodemus'' for ''Allosaurus'' during the same period, is a point that needs to be remembered when searching for information on ''Allosaurus'' in publications that predate James Madsen's 1976 monograph. Major publications using the name Megalosauridae instead of Allosauridae include Gilmore, 1920, von Huene, 1926, Romer, 1956 and 1966, Steel, 1970, and Walker, 1964.

Following the publication of Madsen's influential monograph, Allosauridae became the preferred family assignment, but it too was not strongly defined.  Semi-technical works used Allosauridae for a variety of large theropods, usually those that were larger and better-known than megalosaurids.  Typical theropods that were thought to be related to ''Allosaurus'' included ''Indosaurus'', ''Piatnitzkysaurus'', ''Piveteausaurus'', ''Yangchuanosaurus'', ''Acrocanthosaurus'', ''Chilantaisaurus'', ''Compsosuchus'', ''Stokesosaurus'', and ''Szechuanosaurus''. Given modern knowledge of theropod diversity and the advent of cladistic study of evolutionary relationships, none of these theropods is now recognized as an allosaurid, although several, like ''Acrocanthosaurus'' and ''Yangchuanosaurus'', are members of closely related families.

Allosauridae is one of three families in Carnosauria; the other two are Carcharodontosauridae and Sinraptoridae. Allosauridae has at times been proposed as ancestral to the Tyrannosauridae (which would make it paraphyletic), one recent example in Gregory S. Paul's ''Predatory Dinosaurs of the World'',Paul, Gregory S. (1988). "The allosaur-tyrannosaur group", ''Predatory Dinosaurs of the World''. 301–347. but this has been rejected, with tyrannosaurids identified as members of a separate branch of theropods, the Coelurosauria. Allosauridae is the smallest of the carnosaur families, with only ''Saurophaganax'' and a currently unnamed French allosauroid accepted as possible valid genera besides ''Allosaurus'' in the most recent review. Another genus, ''Epanterias'', is a potential valid member, but it and ''Saurophaganax'' may turn out to be large examples of ''Allosaurus''. Recent reviews have kept the genus ''Saurophaganax'' and included ''Epanterias'' with ''Allosaurus''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="48768af9b00c7876f1cefd989d62618e" name="Allosaurus_BW" sectnum="2#1">../img/48768af9b00c7876f1cefd989d62618e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>