<document id="70780355e478c7075444edba707c92b1-4" name="Allosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
It is unclear how many species of ''Allosaurus'' there were.  Seven species have been considered potentially valid since 1988 (''A. amplexus'', ''A. atrox'', ''A. europaeus'', the type species ''A. fragilis'', the as-yet not formally described "A. jimmadseni", ''A. maximus'', and ''A. tendagurensis''), although only a fraction are usually considered valid at any given time. Additionally, there are at least ten dubious or undescribed species that have been assigned to ''Allosaurus'' over the years, along with the species belonging to genera now sunk into ''Allosaurus''. In the most recent review of basal tetanuran theropods, only ''A. fragilis'' (including ''A. amplexus'' and ''A. atrox'' as synonyms), "A. jimmadseni" (as an unnamed species), and ''A. tendagurensis'' were accepted as potentially valid species, with ''A. europaeus'' not yet proposed and ''A. maximus'' assigned to ''Saurophaganax''.

''A. amplexus'', ''A. atrox'', ''A. fragilis'', "A. jimmadseni", and ''A. maximus'' are all known from remains discovered in the Kimmeridgian–Tithonian Upper Jurassic-age Morrison Formation of the United States, spread across the states of Colorado, Montana, New Mexico, Oklahoma, South Dakota, Utah, and Wyoming.  ''A. fragilis'' is regarded as the most common, known from the remains of at least sixty individuals. Debate has gone on since the 1980s regarding the possibility that there are two common Morrison Formation species of ''Allosaurus'', with the second known as ''A. atrox''; recent work has followed a "one species" interpretation, with the differences seen in the Morrison Formation material attributed to individual variation. ''A. europaeus'' was found in the Kimmeridgian-age Porto Novo Member of the Lourinhã Formation, but may be the same as ''A. fragilis''. ''A. tendagurensis'' was found in Kimmeridgian-age rocks of Tendaguru, in Mtwara, Tanzania. Although the most recent review tentatively accepted it as a valid species of ''Allosaurus'', it may be a more basal tetanuran, or simply a dubious theropod. Although obscure, it was a large theropod, possibly around 10 meters long (33 ft) and 2.5 metric tons (2.8 short tons) in weight.

''Allosaurus'' is regarded as a probable synonym of the genera ''Antrodemus'', ''Creosaurus'',  ''Epanterias'', and ''Labrosaurus''.  Most of the species that are regarded as synonyms of ''A. fragilis'', or that were misassigned to the genus, are obscure and were based on scrappy remains.  One exception is ''Labrosaurus ferox'', named in 1884 by Marsh for an oddly formed partial lower jaw, with a prominent gap in the tooth row at the tip of the jaw, and a rear section greatly expanded and turned down. Later researchers suggested that the bone was pathologic, showing an injury to the living animal, and that part of the unusual form of the rear of the bone was due to plaster reconstruction. It is now regarded as an example of ''A. fragilis.'' Other remains thought to pertain to ''Allosaurus'' have come from across the world, including Australia, Siberia, and Switzerland, but these fossils have been reassessed as belonging to other dinosaurs.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3af60b9f24d137b33f73442fca5db912" name="Allosaurus-fossilized_skull" sectnum="4#1">../img/3af60b9f24d137b33f73442fca5db912.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>