<document id="70780355e478c7075444edba707c92b1-5" name="Allosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
''Allosaurus'' was the most common large theropod in the vast tract of Western American fossil-bearing rock known as the Morrison Formation, accounting for 70 to 75% of theropod specimens, and as such was at the top trophic level of the Morrison food web. The Morrison Formation is interpreted as a semiarid environment with distinct wet and dry seasons, and flat floodplains. Vegetation varied from river-lining forests of conifers, tree ferns, and ferns, to fern savannas with rare trees.

The Morrison Formation has been a rich fossil hunting ground, holding fossils of green algae, fungi, mosses, horsetails, ferns, cycads, ginkgoes, and several families of conifers. Other fossils discovered include bivalves, snails, ray-finned fishes, frogs, salamanders, turtles, sphenodonts, lizards, terrestrial and aquatic crocodylomorphans, several species of pterosaur, numerous dinosaur species, and early mammals such as docodonts, multituberculates, symmetrodonts, and triconodonts. Such dinosaurs as the theropods ''Ceratosaurus'', ''Ornitholestes'', and ''Torvosaurus'', the sauropods ''Apatosaurus'', ''Brachiosaurus'', ''Camarasaurus'', and ''Diplodocus'', and the ornithischians ''Camptosaurus'', ''Dryosaurus'', and ''Stegosaurus'' are known from the Morrison. The Late Jurassic formations of Portugal where ''Allosaurus'' is present are interpreted as having been similar to the Morrison but with a stronger marine influence.  Many of the dinosaurs of the Morrison Formation are the same genera as those seen in Portuguese rocks (mainly ''Allosaurus'', ''Ceratosaurus'', ''Torvosaurus'', and ''Apatosaurus''), or have a close counterpart (''Brachiosaurus'' and ''Lusotitan'', ''Camptosaurus'' and ''Draconyx'').

''Allosaurus'' coexisted with fellow large theropods ''Ceratosaurus'' and ''Torvosaurus'' in both the United States and Portugal, The three appear to have had different ecological niches, based on anatomy and the location of fossils.  Ceratosaurs and torvosaurs may have preferred to be active around waterways, and had lower, thinner bodies that would have given them an advantage in forest and underbrush terrains, whereas allosaurs were more compact, with longer legs, faster but less maneuverable, and seem to have preferred dry floodplains. ''Ceratosaurus'', better known than ''Torvosaurus'', differed noticeably from ''Allosaurus'' in functional anatomy by having a taller, narrower skull with large, broad teeth. ''Allosaurus'' was itself a potential food item to other carnivores, as illustrated by an ''Allosaurus'' pubic foot marked by the teeth of another theropod, probably ''Ceratosaurus'' or ''Torvosaurus''. The location of the bone in the body (along the bottom margin of the torso and partially shielded by the legs), and the fact that it was among the most massive in the skeleton, indicates that the ''Allosaurus'' was being scavenged.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0a2840192e91f18a0fcbe1c5deeda57b" name="BrushyBasin" sectnum="5#1">../img/0a2840192e91f18a0fcbe1c5deeda57b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>