<document id="70780355e478c7075444edba707c92b1-1.1" name="Allosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
The skull and teeth of ''Allosaurus'' were modestly proportioned for a theropod of its size. Paleontologist Gregory S. Paul gives a length of 845 millimeters (33.3 in) for a skull belonging to an individual he estimates at 7.9 meters long (26 ft). Each premaxilla (the bones that formed the tip of the snout), held five teeth with D-shaped cross-sections, and each maxilla (the main tooth-bearing bones in the upper jaw) had between fourteen and seventeen teeth; the number of teeth does not exactly correspond to the size of the bone. Each dentary (the tooth-bearing bone of the lower jaw) had between fourteen and seventeen teeth, with an average count of sixteen. The teeth became shorter, more narrow, and more curved toward the back of the skull. All of the teeth had saw-like edges. They were shed easily, and were replaced continually, making them common fossils.  

The skull had a pair of horns above and in front of the eyes.  These horns were composed of extensions of the lacrimal bones, and varied in shape and size.  There were also lower paired ridges running along the top edges of the nasal bones that led into the horns. The horns were probably covered in a keratin sheath and may have had a variety of functions, including acting as sunshades for the eye, being used for display, and being used in combat against other members of the same species (although they were fragile). There was a ridge along the back of the skull roof for muscle attachment, as is also seen in tyrannosaurids.

Inside the lacrimal bones were depressions that may have held glands, such as salt glands.  Within the maxillae were sinuses that were better developed than those of more basal theropods such as ''Ceratosaurus'' and ''Marshosaurus''; they may have been related to the sense of smell, perhaps holding something like Jacobson's organ. The roof of the braincase was thin, perhaps to improve thermoregulation for the brain. The skull and lower jaws had joints that permitted motion within these units.  In the lower jaws, the bones of the front and back halves loosely articulated, permitting the jaws to bow outward and increasing the animal's gape.Paul, Gregory S. (1988). ''Predatory Dinosaurs of the World''. 91 and Figure 4–5 (93). The braincase and frontals may also have had a joint.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d7da952cfda514ee5863dcacbe125d06" name="Allosaurus-crane" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/d7da952cfda514ee5863dcacbe125d06.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>