<document id="70aa91a03722c8099e08d4ff9a29fbc4-4" name="Peterloo_Massacre" cat="14">
<text>
The exact number of those killed and injured at Peterloo has never been established with certainty.Marlow (1969), pp. 150–151. Sources claim 11–15 killed and 400–700 injured. The Manchester Relief Committee, a body set up to provide relief for the victims of Peterloo, gave the number of injured as 420, while Radical sources listed 500. The true number is difficult to estimate, as many of the wounded hid their injuries for fear of retribution by the authorities.Reid (1989), p. 187. Three of William Marsh's six children worked in the factory belonging to Captain Hugh Birley of the Manchester Yeomanry, and lost their jobs because their father had attended the meeting. James Lees was admitted to Manchester Infirmary with two severe sabre wounds to the head, but was refused treatment and sent home after refusing to confess to the surgeon that "he had had enough of Manchester meetings".Bush (2005), p. 12.

A particular feature of the meeting at Peterloo was the number of women present. Female reform societies had been formed in north west England during June and July 1819, the first in Britain. Many of them were dressed distinctively in white, and some formed all-female contingents, carrying their own flags.Bush (2005), p. 1. Of the 654 recorded casualties, at least 168 were women, four of whom died either at St Peter's Field or later as a result of their wounds. It has been estimated that less than 12% of the crowd was made up of females, suggesting that women were at significantly greater risk of injury than men by a factor of almost 3:1. Richard Carlile claimed that the women were especially targeted, a view apparently supported by the large number who suffered from wounds caused by weapons.Bush (2005), p. 31.

Eleven of the fatalities listed occurred on St Peter's Field. Some, like John Lees of Oldham, died later of their wounds, and others like Joshua Whitworth were killed in the rioting that followed the crowd's dispersal from the field.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a0f2d2744ae0a5229542e01989367dce" name="The_Massacre_of_Peterloo" sectnum="4#1">../img/a0f2d2744ae0a5229542e01989367dce.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>