<document id="70dacdd695fa0f06c096655ac1a5ed35-6.22" name="Punk_rock" cat="20">
<text>
The underground punk rock movement inspired countless bands that either evolved from a punk rock sound or brought its outsider spirit to very different kinds of music. The original punk explosion also had a long-term effect on the music industry, spurring the growth of the independent sector.Laing (1985), pp. 118, 128. During the early 1980s, British bands like New Order and The Cure that straddled the lines of post-punk and New Wave developed both new musical styles and a distinctive industrial niche. Though commercially successful over an extended period, they maintained an  underground-style, subcultural identity.Goodlad and Bibby (2007), p. 16. In the United States, bands such as Minneapolis's Hüsker Dü and their protégés The Replacements bridged the gap between punk rock genres like hardcore and the more expansive sound of what was then called "college rock".Azerrad (2001), passim; for relationship of Hüsker Dü and The Replacements, see pp. 205–206.

A 1985 ''Rolling Stone'' feature on the Minneapolis scene and innovative California hardcore acts such as Black Flag and Minutemen declared, "Primal punk is passé. The best of the American punk rockers have moved on. They have learned how to play their instruments. They have discovered melody, guitar solos and lyrics that are more than shouted political slogans. Some of them have even discovered the Grateful Dead.", ''Rolling Stone'', July 18 – August 1, 1985. By the end of the 1980s, these bands, who had largely eclipsed their punk rock forebears in popularity, were classified broadly as alternative rock. Alternative rock encompasses a diverse set of styles—including gothic rock and grunge, among others—unified by their debt to punk rock and their origins outside of the musical mainstream.Erlewine, Stephen Thomas. "". Allmusic. Retrieved on December 12, 2006

As American alternative bands like Sonic Youth, which had grown out of the No Wave scene, and Boston's Pixies started to gain larger audiences, major labels sought to capitalize on the underground market that had been sustained by hardcore punk for years.Friedlander and Miller (2006), pp. 256, 278. In 1991, Nirvana emerged from Washington State's grunge scene, achieving huge commercial success with its second album, ''Nevermind''. The band's members cited punk rock as a key influence on their style., Biography Channel. Retrieved on November 19, 2006. "Punk is musical freedom", wrote singer Kurt Cobain. "It’s saying, doing, and playing what you want."Quoted in St. Thomas (2004), p. 94. The widespread popularity of Nirvana and other punk-influenced bands such as Pearl Jam and Red Hot Chili Peppers fueled the alternative rock boom of the early and mid-1990s.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="53ced004106e181792d7deefd911354f" name="Sonic1991b" sectnum="6.22#1">../img/53ced004106e181792d7deefd911354f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>