<document id="70dacdd695fa0f06c096655ac1a5ed35-2.6" name="Punk_rock" cat="20">
<text>
Prior to the mid-1970s, ''punk'', a centuries-old word of obscure etymology, was commonly used to describe "a young male hustler, a gangster, a hoodlum, or a ruffian".Leblanc (1999), p. 35. As Legs McNeil explains, "On TV, if you watched cop shows, ''Kojak'', ''Baretta'', when the cops finally catch the mass murderer, they'd say, 'you dirty Punk.' It was what your teachers would call you. It meant that you were the lowest."Quoted in Leblanc (1999), p. 35. The first known use of the phrase ''punk rock'' appeared in the ''Chicago Tribune'' on March 22, 1970, attributed to Ed Sanders, cofounder of New York's anarcho-prankster band The Fugs. Sanders was quoted describing a solo album of his as "punk rock—redneck sentimentality".Shapiro (2006), p. 492. In the December 1970 issue of ''Creem'', Lester Bangs, mocking more mainstream rock musicians, ironically referred to Iggy Pop as "that Stooge punk".Bangs, Lester, , ''Creem'', December 1970. Retrieved on November 29, 2007. Suicide's Alan Vega credits this usage with inspiring his duo to bill its gigs as a "punk mass" for the next couple of years.Nobahkt (2004), p. 38.


Dave Marsh was the first music critic to employ the term ''punk rock'': in the May 1971 issue of ''Creem'', he described ? and the Mysterians, one of the most popular 1960s garage rock acts, as giving a "landmark exposition of punk rock".Shapiro (2006), p. 492. Note that Taylor (2003) misidentifies the year of publication as 1970 (p. 16) as does Scott Woods in the introduction to his interview with Marsh: . rockcritics.com. Retrieved on December 26, 2006. In June 1972, the fanzine ''Flash'' included a "Punk Top Ten" of 1960s albums.Taylor (2003), p. 16. That year, Lenny Kaye used the term in the liner notes of the anthology album ''Nuggets'' to refer to 1960s garage bands such as The Standells, The Sonics, and The Seeds.Houghton, Mick, "White Punks on Coke", ''Let It Rock''. December 1975. The fanzine ''Bomp!'' also used ''punk'' in this sense.Savage (1991), p. 131. In February 1973, Terry Atkinson of the ''Los Angeles Times'', reviewing the debut album by a hard rock band, Aerosmith, declared that it "achieves all that punk-rock bands strive for but most miss."Atkinson, Terry, "Hits and Misses", ''Los Angeles Times'', February 17, 1973, p. B6. Three months later, Billy Altman launched the short-lived ''punk magazine''.Laing (1985), p. 13; , ''Punk Magazine'', July 20, 2001. Retrieved on March 4, 2008.

In May 1974, ''Los Angeles Times'' critic Robert Hilburn reviewed the second New York Dolls album, ''Too Much Too Soon''. "I told ya the New York Dolls were the real thing", he wrote. "And now, we've got the album to prove it.... It is, in fact, perhaps the best example of raw, thumb-your-nose-at-the-world, punk rock since the Rolling Stones' 'Exile on Main Street.'"Hilburn, Robert, "Touch of Stones in Dolls' Album", ''Los Angeles Times'', May 7, 1974, p. C12. Bassist Jeff Jensen of Boston's Real Kids reports of a show that year, "A reviewer for one of the free entertainment magazines of the time caught the act and gave us a great review, calling us a 'punk band.' ... e all sort of looked at each other and said, 'What's punk?'"Harvard, Joe, , ''Boston Rock Storybook''. Retrieved on November 27, 2007.

By 1975, ''punk'' was being used to describe acts as diverse as the Patti Smith Group—with lead guitarist Lenny Kaye—the Bay City Rollers, and Bruce Springsteen. As the scene at New York's CBGB club attracted notice, a name was sought for the developing sound. Club owner Hilly Kristal called the movement "street rock"; John Holmstrom credits ''Aquarian'' magazine with using ''punk'' "to describe what was going on at CBGBs".Savage (1991), pp. 130–131. Holmstrom, McNeil, and Ged Dunn's magazine ''Punk'', which debuted at the end of 1975, was crucial in codifying the term.Taylor (2003), pp. 16–17. "It was pretty obvious that the word was getting very popular", Holmstrom later remarked. "We figured we'd take the name before anyone else claimed it. We wanted to get rid of the bullshit, strip it down to rock 'n' roll. We wanted the fun and liveliness back."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="03d38c1ff8bf3b0df86a86b64091e314" name="Patti_Smith_Copenhagen_1976" sectnum="2.6#1">../img/03d38c1ff8bf3b0df86a86b64091e314.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>