<document id="70dacdd695fa0f06c096655ac1a5ed35-3.10" name="Punk_rock" cat="20">
<text>
After a brief period unofficially managing the New York Dolls, Englishman Malcolm McLaren returned to London in May 1975, inspired by the new scene he had witnessed at CBGB. The Kings Road clothing store he co-owned, recently renamed Sex, was building a reputation with its outrageous "anti-fashion"., ''Rolling Stone Encyclopedia of Rock 'n' Roll'' (2001). Retrieved on September 11, 2006; Robb (2006), pp. 83–87; Savage (1992), pp. 99–103. Among those who frequented the shop were members of a band called The Strand, which McLaren had also been managing. In August, the group was seeking a new lead singer. Another Sex habitué, Johnny Rotten, auditioned for and won the job. Adopting a new name, the group played its first gig as the Sex Pistols on November 6, 1975, at St. Martin's School of ArtGimarc (2005), p. 22; Robb (2006), p. 114; Savage (1992), p. 129. and soon attracted a small but ardent following."", punk77.co.uk. Retrieved on December 3, 2006. In February 1976, the band received its first significant press coverage; guitarist Steve Jones declared that the Pistols were not so much into music as they were "chaos".Savage (1992), pp. 151–152. The quote has been incorrectly ascribed to McLaren (e.g., Laing , pp. 97, 127) and Rotten (e.g., , BBC, October 7, 2002), but Savage directly cites the ''New Musical Express'' issue in which the quote originally appeared. Robb (2006), p. 148, also describes the ''NME'' article in some detail and ascribes the quote to Jones. The band often provoked its crowds into near-riots. Rotten announced to one audience, "Bet you don't hate us as much as we hate you!"Quoted in Friedlander and Miller (2006), p. 252. McLaren envisioned the Pistols as central players in a new youth movement, "hard and tough".Quoted in Savage (1992), p. 163. As described by critic Jon Savage, the band members "embodied an attitude into which McLaren fed a new set of references: late-sixties radical politics, sexual fetish material, pop history,...youth sociology".Savage (1992), p. 163.

Bernard Rhodes, a sometime associate of McLaren's and friend of the Pistols', was similarly aiming to make stars of the band London SS. Early in 1976, London SS broke up before ever performing publicly, spinning off two new bands: The Damned and The Clash, which was joined by Joe Strummer, The 101'ers former lead singer.Savage (1992), pp. 124, 171, 172. On June 4, 1976, the Sex Pistols played Manchester's Lesser Free Trade Hall in what came to be regarded as one of the most influential rock shows ever. Among the approximately forty audience members were the two locals who organized the gig—they had formed the Buzzcocks after seeing the Sex Pistols in February. Others in the small crowd went on to form Joy Division, The Fall, and—in the 1980s—The Smiths.

In July, the Ramones crossed the Atlantic for two London shows that helped spark the nascent UK punk scene and affected its musical style—"instantly nearly every band speeded up".Taylor (2003), p. 56; McNeil and McCain (2006), pp. 230–233; Robb (2006), pp. 198, 201. Quote: Robb (2006), p. 198. On July 4, they played with the Flamin' Groovies and The Stranglers before a crowd of 2,000 at the Roundhouse.Robb (2006), p. 198. That same night, The Clash debuted, opening for the Sex Pistols in Sheffield. On July 5, members of both bands attended a Ramones club gig.Taylor (2003), p. 56. The following night, The Damned played their first show, as a Pistols opening act in London. In critic Kurt Loder's description, the Pistols purveyed a "calculated, arty nihilism,  the Clash were unabashed idealists, proponents of a radical left-wing social critique of a sort that reached back at least to ... Woody Guthrie in the 1940s". The Damned built a reputation as "punk's party boys".Taylor (2004), p. 80. This London scene's first fanzine appeared a week later. Its title, ''Sniffin' Glue'', derived from a Ramones song. Its subtitle affirmed the connection with what was happening in New York: "+ Other Rock 'n' Roll Habits for Punks!"Laing (1985), p. 13; , towerblock.co.uk. Retrieved on March 4, 2008.

Another Sex Pistols gig in Manchester on July 20, with a reorganized version of the Buzzcocks debuting in support, gave further impetus to the scene there.Cummins, Kevin, "Closer to the Birth of a Music Legend", ''The Observer'', August 8, 2007, p. 12. In August, the self-described "First European Punk Rock Festival" was held in Mont de Marsan in the southwest of France. Eddie and the Hot Rods, a London pub rock group, headlined. The Sex Pistols, originally scheduled to play, were dropped by the organizers who said the band had gone "too far" in demanding top billing and certain amenities; The Clash backed out in solidarity. The only band from the new punk movement to appear was The Damned.Strongman (2008), pp. 131–132; Savage (1992), p. 216. Strongman describes one of the Pistols' objectionable requests as "some entourage accommodation". Savage says they were dropped from the festival following a violent altercation between Sid Vicious, then part of the Pistols' "entourage",  and journalist Nick Kent at a Pistols gig. It is possible that the organizers were specifically afraid of Vicious's attendance.

Over the next several months, many new punk rock bands formed, often directly inspired by the Pistols.See, e.g., Marcus (1989), pp. 37, 67. In London, women were at the center of the scene—among the initial wave of bands were the female-fronted Siouxsie & the Banshees and X-Ray Spex and the all-female The Slits. There were female bassists Gaye Advert in The Adverts and Shanne Bradley in The Nipple Erectors. Other groups included Subway Sect, Eater, The Subversives, the aptly named London, and Chelsea, which soon spun off Generation X. Farther afield, Sham 69 began practicing in the southeastern town of Hersham. In Durham, there was Penetration, with lead singer Pauline Murray. On September 20–21, the 100 Club Punk Festival in London featured the four primary British groups (London's big three and the Buzzcocks), as well as Paris's female-fronted Stinky Toys, arguably the first punk rock band from a non-Anglophone country. Siouxsie & the Banshees and Subway Sect debuted on the festival's first night; that same evening, Eater debuted in Manchester. On the festival's second night, audience member Sid Vicious was arrested, charged with throwing a glass at The Damned that shattered and destroyed a girl's eye. Press coverage of the incident fueled punk's reputation as a social menace.Colegrave and Sullivan (2005), p. 111; Gimarc (2005), p. 39; Robb (2006), pp. 217, 224–225.

Some new bands, such as London's Alternative TV and Edinburgh's Rezillos, identified with the scene even as they pursued more experimental music. Others of a comparatively traditional rock 'n' roll bent were also swept up by the movement: The Vibrators, formed as a pub rock–style act in February 1976, soon adopted a punk look and sound.Savage (1992), pp. 221, 247. A few even longer-active bands including Surrey neo-mods The Jam and pub rockers The Stranglers and Cock Sparrer also became associated with the punk rock scene. Alongside the musical roots shared with their American counterparts and the calculated confrontationalism of the early Who, journalist Clinton Heylin describes how the British punks also reflected the influence of the "glam bands who gave noise back to teenagers in the early Seventies—T.Rex, Slade and Roxy Music".Heylin (1993), p. xii. One of the groups openly acknowledging that influence were The Undertones, from Derry in Northern Ireland.  Another punk band formed to the south, Dublin's The Radiators From Space.



In October, The Damned became the first UK punk rock band to release a single, the romance-themed "New Rose".Griffin, Jeff, "", BBC.co.uk. Retrieved on November 19, 2006. The Vibrators followed the next month with "We Vibrate" and, backing long-time rocker Chris Spedding, "Pogo Dancing". The latter was hardly a punk song by any stretch, but it was perhaps the first song ''about'' punk rock. On 26 November, the Sex Pistols' "Anarchy in the U.K." came out—with its debut single the band succeeded in its goal of becoming a "national scandal". Jamie Reid's "anarchy flag" poster and his other design work for the Pistols helped establish a distinctive punk visual aesthetic.Pardo (2004), p. 245. On December 1, an incident took place that sealed punk rock's notorious reputation: On ''Thames Today'', an early evening London TV show, Sex Pistols guitarist Steve Jones was goaded into a verbal altercation by the host, Bill Grundy. Jones called Grundy a "dirty fucker" on live television, triggering a media controversy.Lydon (1995), p. 127; Savage (1992), pp. 257–260; Barkham, Patrick, , ''The Guardian'' (UK), March 1, 2005. Retrieved on December 17, 2006. Two days later, the Pistols, The Clash, The Damned, and The Heartbreakers set out on the Anarchy Tour, a series of gigs throughout the UK. Many of the shows were cancelled by venue owners in response to the media outrage following the Grundy confrontation.Savage (1992), pp. 267–275; Lydon (1995), pp. 139–140.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b588187173c459328ccecbb660c89e25" name="AnarchyInTheUKPoster" sectnum="3.10#1">../img/b588187173c459328ccecbb660c89e25.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>