<document id="70dacdd695fa0f06c096655ac1a5ed35-5.16" name="Punk_rock" cat="20">
<text>
During 1976–77, in the midst of the original UK punk movement, bands emerged such as Manchester's Joy Division, The Fall, and Magazine, Leeds' Gang of Four, and London's The Raincoats that became central post-punk figures. Some bands classified as post-punk, such as Throbbing Gristle and Cabaret Voltaire, had been active well before the punk scene coalesced;Reynolds (2005), p. xxi. others, such as The Slits and Siouxsie & The Banshees, transitioned from punk rock into post-punk. A few months after the Sex Pistols' breakup, John Lydon (no longer "Rotten") cofounded Public Image Ltd. Lora Logic, formerly of X-Ray Spex, founded Essential Logic. Killing Joke formed in 1979. These bands were often musically experimental, like certain New Wave acts; defining them as "post-punk" was a sound that tended to be less pop and more dark and abrasive—sometimes verging on the atonal, as with Subway Sect and Wire—and an anti-establishment posture directly related to punk's. Post-punk reflected a range of art rock influences from Captain Beefheart to David Bowie and Roxy Music to Krautrock and, once again, the Velvet Underground.

Post-punk brought together a new fraternity of musicians, journalists, managers, and entrepreneurs; the latter, notably Geoff Travis of Rough Trade and Tony Wilson of Factory, helped to develop the production and distribution infrastructure of the indie music scene that blossomed in the mid-1980s.Reynolds (2005), pp. xxvii, xxix. Smoothing the edges of their style in the direction of New Wave, several post-punk bands such as New Order (descended from Joy Division), The Cure, and U2 crossed over to a mainstream U.S. audience. Bauhaus was one of the formative gothic rock bands. Others, like Gang of Four, The Raincoats and Throbbing Gristle, who had little more than cult followings at the time, are seen in retrospect as significant influences on modern popular culture.Reynolds (2005), p. xxix.

A number of U.S. artists were retrospectively defined as post-punk; Television's debut album ''Marquee Moon'', released in 1977, is frequently cited as a seminal album in the field.See, e.g.,  overview by Mike McGuirk, Rhapsody;  review by Stephen Thomas Erlewine, Allmusic;  review by Hunter Felt, PopMatters. All retrieved January 15, 2007. The No Wave movement that developed in New York in the late 1970s, with artists like Lydia Lunch, is often treated as the phenomenon's U.S. parallel.See, e.g., Buckley (2003), p. 13. The later work of Ohio protopunk pioneers Pere Ubu is also commonly described as post-punk.See. e.g., Reynolds (1999), p. 336; Savage (2002), p. 487. One of the most influential American post-punk bands was Boston's Mission of Burma, who brought abrupt rhythmic shifts derived from hardcore into a highly experimental musical context.Harrington (2002), p. 388. In 1980, Australia's Boys Next Door moved to London and changed their name to The Birthday Party, which evolved into Nick Cave and the Bad Seeds. King Snake Roost and other Australian bands would further explore the possibilities of post-punk. Later art punk and alternative rock musicians found diverse inspiration among these predecessors, New Wave and post-punk alike.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="367507ce9f5b978caa98a15b17081014" name="PIL_-_Metal_Box_original" sectnum="5.16#1">../img/367507ce9f5b978caa98a15b17081014.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>