<document id="70dacdd695fa0f06c096655ac1a5ed35-1.1" name="Punk_rock" cat="20">
<text>
The first wave of punk rock aimed to be aggressively modern, distancing itself from the bombast and sentimentality of early 1970s rock.Robb (2006), foreword by Michael Bracewell. According to Ramones drummer Tommy Ramone, "In its initial form, a lot of  stuff was innovative and exciting. Unfortunately, what happens is that people who could not hold a candle to the likes of Hendrix started noodling away. Soon you had endless solos that went nowhere. By 1973, I knew that what was needed was some pure, stripped down, no bullshit rock 'n' roll."Ramone, Tommy, "Fight Club", ''Uncut'', January 2007. John Holmstrom, founding editor of ''Punk'' magazine, recalls feeling "punk rock had to come along because the rock scene had become so tame that  like Billy Joel and Simon and Garfunkel were being called rock and roll, when to me and other fans, rock and roll meant this wild and rebellious music."McLaren, Malcolm, , BBC News, August 18, 2006. Retrieved on January 17, 2006. In critic Robert Christgau's description, "It was also a subculture that scornfully rejected the political idealism and Californian flower-power silliness of hippie myth."Christgau, Robert, , ''New York Times Book Review'', 1996. Retrieved on January 17, 2007. Patti Smith, in contrast, suggests in the documentary ''25 Years of Punk'' that the hippies and the punk rockers were linked by a common anti-establishment mentality.

Throughout punk rock history, technical accessibility and a DIY spirit have been prized. In the early days of punk rock, this ethic stood in marked contrast to what those in the scene regarded as the ostentatious musical effects and technological demands of many mainstream rock bands.See, e.g., Rodel (2004), p. 237; Bennett (2001), pp. 49–50. Musical virtuosity was often looked on with suspicion. According to Holmstrom, punk rock was "rock and roll by people who didn't have very much skills as musicians but still felt the need to express themselves through music". In December 1976, the English fanzine ''Sideburns'' published a now-famous illustration of three chords, captioned "This is a chord, this is another, this is a third. Now form a band."Savage (1992), pp. 280–281, including reproduction of the original image. Several sources incorrectly ascribe the illustration to the leading fanzine of the London punk scene, ''Sniffin' Glue'' (e.g., Wells , p. 5; Sabin , p. 111). Robb (2006) ascribes it to The Stranglers' in-house fanzine, ''Strangled'' (p. 311). In fact, ''Strangled'', which only began appearing in 1977, evolved out of ''Sideburns'' (see, e.g., ) The title of a 1980 single by New York punk band The Stimulators, "Loud Fast Rules!", inscribed a catchphrase for punk's basic musical approach.Blush (2001), pp. 173, 175. See also  Killed By Death Records (September 21, 2006).

Some of British punk rock's leading figures made a show of rejecting not only contemporary mainstream rock and the broader culture it was associated with, but their own most celebrated predecessors: "No Elvis, Beatles or the Rolling Stones in 1977", declared The Clash song "1977".Harris (2004), p. 202. The previous year, when the punk rock revolution began in Great Britain, was to be both a musical and a cultural "Year Zero".Reynolds (2005), p. 4. Even as nostalgia was discarded, many in the scene adopted a nihilistic attitude summed up by the Sex Pistols slogan "No Future"; in the later words of one observer, amid the unemployment and social unrest in 1977, "punk's nihilistic swagger was the most thrilling thing in England."Jeffries, Stuart. "A Right Royal Knees-Up". ''The Guardian''. July 20, 2007. While "self-imposed alienation" was common among "drunk punks" and "gutter punks", there was always a tension between their nihilistic outlook and the "radical leftist utopianism"Washburne, Christopher, and Maiken Derno. ''Bad Music''. Routledge, 2004. Page 247. of bands such as Crass, who found positive, liberating meaning in the movement.  As a Clash associate describes singer Joe Strummer's outlook, "Punk rock is meant to be our freedom. We're meant to be able to do what we want to do."Kosmo Vinyl, ''The Last Testament: The Making of London Calling'' (Sony Music, 2004).

The issue of authenticity is important in the punk subculture—the pejorative term "poseur" is applied to those who associate with punk and adopt its stylistic attributes but are deemed not to share or understand the underlying values and philosophy. Scholar Daniel S. Traber argues that "attaining authenticity in the punk identity can be difficult"; as the punk scene matured, he observes, eventually "veryone got called a poseur".Traber, Daniel S., "L.A.'s 'White Minority': Punk and the Contradictions of Self-Marginalization", ''Cultural Critique'' 48 (spring 2001), pp. 30–64.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3760a0e2998bec874b0d5b4da077c165" name="Ramones_album_cover" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/3760a0e2998bec874b0d5b4da077c165.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>