<document id="70dacdd695fa0f06c096655ac1a5ed35-1.3" name="Punk_rock" cat="20">
<text>
The classic punk rock look among male U.S. musicians harkens back to the T-shirt, motorcycle jacket, and jeans ensemble favored by American greasers of the 1950s associated with the rockabilly scene and by British rockers of the 1960s. The cover of the Ramones' 1976 debut album, featuring a shot of the band by ''Punk'' photographer Roberta Bayley, set forth the basic elements of a style that was soon widely emulated by rock musicians both punk and nonpunk.Bessman (1993), pp. 48, 50; Miles, Scott, and Morgan (2005), p. 136. Richard Hell's more androgynous, ragamuffin look—and reputed invention of the safety-pin aesthetic—was a major influence on Sex Pistols impresario Malcolm McLaren and, in turn, British punk style.Strongman (2008), pp. 58, 63, 64; Colegrave and Sullivan (2005), p. 78. McLaren's partner, fashion designer, Vivienne Westwood, credits Johnny Rotten as the first British punk to rip his shirt, and Sex Pistols bassist Sid Vicious as the first to use safety pins. Early female punk musicians displayed styles ranging from Siouxsie Sioux's bondage gear to Patti Smith's "straight-from-the-gutter androgyny".Strohm (2004), p. 188. The former proved much more influential on female fan styles.See, e.g., Laing (1985), "Picture Section", p. 18. Over time, tattoos, piercings, and metal-studded and -spiked accessories became increasingly common elements of punk fashion among both musicians and fans, a "style of adornment calculated to disturb and outrage".Daniel Wojcik. ''The End of the World as We Know It: Faith, Fatalism, and Apocalypse in America.''  New York: New York University Press, 1997. Page 122. The typical male punk haircut was originally short and choppy; the Mohawk later emerged as a characteristic style.Wojcik (1995), pp. 16–19; Laing (1985), p. 109. Those in hardcore scenes often adopt a skinhead look.


The characteristic stage performance style of male punk musicians does not deviate significantly from the macho postures classically associated with rock music.Laing (1985), pp. 89, 97–98, 125. Female punk musicians broke more clearly from earlier styles. Scholar John Strohm suggests that they did so by creating personas of a type conventionally seen as masculine: "They adopted a tough, unladylike pose that borrowed more from the macho swagger of sixties garage bands than from the calculated bad-girl image of bands like The Runaways." Scholar Dave Laing describes how bassist Gaye Advert adopted fashion elements associated with male musicians only to generate a stage persona readily consumed as "sexy".Laing (1985), p. 92, 88. Laing focuses on more innovative and challenging performance styles, seen in the various erotically destabilizing approaches of Siouxsie Sioux, The Slits' Ari Up, and X-Ray Spex's Poly Styrene.Laing (1985), p. 89, 92–93.

The lack of emphatic syncopation led punk dance to "deviant" forms. The characteristic style was originally the pogo.Laing (1985), pp. 34, 61, 63, 89–91. Sid Vicious, before he became the Sex Pistols' bassist, is credited with initiating the pogo in Britain as an attendee at one of their concerts.Laing (1985), p. 90; Robb (2006), pp. 159–160. Moshing is typical at hardcore shows. The lack of conventional dance rhythms was a central factor in limiting punk's mainstream commercial impact.Laing (1985), p. 34.

Breaking down the distance between performer and audience is central to the punk ethic.Laing (1985), p. 82. Fan participation at concerts is thus important; during the movement's first heyday, it was often provoked in an adversarial manner—apparently perverse, but appropriately "punk". First-wave British punk bands such as the Pistols and The Damned insulted and otherwise goaded the audience into intense reactions. Laing has identified three primary forms of audience physical response to goading: can throwing, stage invasion, and spitting or "gobbing".Laing (1985), pp. 84–85. In the hardcore realm, stage invasion is often a prelude to stage diving. In addition to the numerous fans who have started or joined punk bands, audience members also become important participants via the scene's many amateur periodicals—in England, according to Laing, punk "was the first musical genre to spawn fanzines in any significant numbers".Laing (1985), p. 14.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="68a27de2bb5dc8828e086099819b6715" name="punks" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/68a27de2bb5dc8828e086099819b6715.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>