<document id="70dacdd695fa0f06c096655ac1a5ed35-4.13" name="Punk_rock" cat="20">
<text>
The Pistols' live TV skirmish with Bill Grundy was the signal moment in British punk's transformation into a major media phenomenon, even as some stores refused to stock the records and radio airplay was hard to come by.Savage (1992), pp. 260, 263–267, 277–279; Laing (1985), pp. 35, 37, 38. Press coverage of punk misbehavior grew intense: On January 4, 1977, the ''Evening News'' of London ran a front-page story on how the Sex Pistols "vomited and spat their way to an Amsterdam flight".Savage (1992), p. 286. In February 1977, the first album by a British punk band appeared: ''Damned Damned Damned'' reached number thirty-six on the UK chart. The EP ''Spiral Scratch'', self-released by Manchester's Buzzcocks, was a benchmark for both the DIY ethic and regionalism in the country's punk movement.Savage (1992), pp. 296–298; Reynolds (2005), pp. 26–27. The Clash's self-titled debut album came out two months later and rose to number twelve; the single "White Riot" entered the top forty. In May, the Sex Pistols achieved new heights of controversy (and number two on the singles chart) with "God Save the Queen". The band had recently acquired a new bassist, Sid Vicious, who was seen as exemplifying the punk persona.Colegrave and Sullivan (2005), p. 225.


Scores of new punk groups formed around the United Kingdom. Though most survived only briefly, perhaps recording a small-label single or two, others set off new trends. Crass, from Essex, merged a vehement, straight-ahead punk rock style with a committed anarchist mission. Sham 69, London's Menace, and the Angelic Upstarts from South Shields in the Northeast combined a similarly stripped-down sound with populist lyrics, a style that became known as streetpunk. These expressly working-class bands contrasted with others in the second wave that presaged the post-punk phenomenon. Such groups expressed punk rock's energy and aggression, while expanding its musical range with a wider variety of tempos and often more complex instrumentation. London's Wire took minimalism and brevity to an extreme. London's Tubeway Army, Belfast's Stiff Little Fingers, and Dunfermline, Scotland's The Skids infused punk rock with elements of synth and noise music.Reynolds (2005), pp. xvii, xviii, xxiii Liverpool's first punk group, the theatrical Big in Japan, didn't last long, but it spun off several well-known post-punk acts.Savage (1991), p. 298.

Alongside thirteen original songs that would define classic punk rock, The Clash's debut had included a cover of the recent Jamaican reggae hit "Police and Thieves".Shuker (2002), p. 228; Wells (2004), p. 113; Myers (2006), p. 205;  Other first wave bands such as The Slits and new entrants to the scene like The Ruts and The Police interacted with the reggae and ska subcultures, incorporating their rhythms and production styles. The punk rock phenomenon helped spark a full-fledged ska revival movement known as 2 Tone, centered around bands such as The Specials, The Beat, Madness, and The Selecter.Hebdige (1987), p. 107.

June 1977 saw the release of another charting punk album: The Vibrators' ''Pure Mania''. In July, the Sex Pistols' third single, "Pretty Vacant",  reached number six and The Saints had a top-forty hit with "This Perfect Day". Recently arrived from Australia, the band was now considered insufficiently "cool" to qualify as punk by much of the British media, though they had been playing a similar brand of music for years.Wells (2004), p. 114. In August, The Adverts entered the top twenty with "Gary Gilmore's Eyes". As punk became a broad-based national phenomenon in the summer of 1977, punk musicians and fans were increasingly subject to violent assaults by Teddy boys, football yobbos, and others. A Ted-aligned band recorded "The Punk Bashing Boogie".Strongman (2008), pp. 182–184.

In September, Generation X and The Clash reached the top forty with, respectively, "Your Generation" and "Complete Control". In October, the Pistols hit number eight with "Holidays in the Sun", followed by the release of their first and only "official" album, ''Never Mind the Bollocks, Here's the Sex Pistols''. Inspiring yet another round of controversy, it topped the British charts. In December, one of the first books about punk rock was published: ''The Boy Looked at Johnny'', by Julie Burchill and Tony Parsons.The title echoes a lyric from the title track of Patti Smith's 1975 album ''Horses'' Declaring the punk rock movement to be already over, it was subtitled ''The Obituary of Rock and Roll''. In January 1978, the Sex Pistols broke up while on American tour.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c001d78f05039309b5a55b88f504557c" name="Wirepinkflagcover" sectnum="4.13#1">../img/c001d78f05039309b5a55b88f504557c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>