<document id="70dacdd695fa0f06c096655ac1a5ed35-5.18" name="Punk_rock" cat="20">
<text>
Following the lead of first-wave British punk bands Cock Sparrer and Sham 69, in the late 1970s second-wave units like Cockney Rejects, Angelic Upstarts, The Exploited, and The 4-Skins sought to realign punk rock with a working class, street-level following.Sabin (1999), p. 216 n. 17; Dalton, Stephen, "Revolution Rock", ''Vox'', June 1993. Their style was originally called ''real punk'' or streetpunk; ''Sounds'' journalist Garry Bushell is credited with labelling the genre ''Oi!'' in 1980. The name is partly derived from the Cockney Rejects' habit of shouting "Oi! Oi! Oi!" before each song, instead of the time-honored "1,2,3,4!"Robb (2006), p. 469. Oi! bands' lyrics sought to reflect the harsh realities of living in Margaret Thatcher's Britain in the late 1970s and early 1980s.Robb (2006), p. 511. A subgroup of Oi! bands dubbed "punk pathetique"—including Splodgenessabounds, Peter and the Test Tube Babies, and Toy Dolls—had a more humorous and absurdist bent.


The Oi! movement was fueled by a sense that many participants in the early punk rock scene were, in the words of The Business guitarist Steve Kent, "trendy university people using long words, trying to be artistic ... and losing touch".Quoted in Robb (2006), pp. 469–470. The Oi! credo held that the music needed to remain unpretentious and accessible. According to Bushell, "Punk was meant to be of the voice of the dole queue, and in reality most of them were not. But Oi was the reality of the punk mythology. In the places where  came from, it was harder and more aggressive and it produced just as much quality music."Robb (2006), p. 470.

Although most Oi! bands in the initial wave were apolitical or left wing, many of them began to attract a white power skinhead following.Bushell, Gary. "". Uncensored Garry Bushell. Retrieved on May 11, 2007. Racist skinheads sometimes disrupted Oi! concerts by shouting fascist slogans and starting fights, but some Oi! bands were reluctant to endorse criticism of their fans from what they perceived as the "middle-class establishment".Fleischer, Tzvi. . Australia/Israel & Jewish Affairs Council (AIJAC), August 2000. Retrieved on January 14, 2007. In the popular imagination, the movement thus became linked to the far right.Robb (2006), pp. 469, 512. ''Strength Thru Oi!'', an album compiled by Bushell and released in May 1981, stirred controversy, especially when it was revealed that the belligerent figure on the cover was a neo-Nazi jailed for racist violence (Bushell claimed ignorance). On July 3, a concert at Hamborough Tavern in Southall featuring The Business, The 4-Skins, and The Last Resort was firebombed by local Asian youths who believed that the event was a neo-Nazi gathering.Gimarc (1997), p. 175; Laing (1985), p. 112. Following the Southall riot, press coverage increasingly associated Oi! with the extreme right, and the movement soon began to lose momentum.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="61837b93a0070cc576e6bea7d389d591" name="StrengthThruOi" sectnum="5.18#1">../img/61837b93a0070cc576e6bea7d389d591.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>