<document id="7160dccf9a4253357caa2d10bc36107c-6" name="Tumbler_Ridge,_British_Columbia" cat="11">
<text>
After dinosaur trackways were discovered in 2000, and bones in 2002, the Tumbler Ridge Museum Foundation began excavations and opened the Peace Region Palaeontology Research Centre.McCrea (2003). Fossils and bones are displayed at both locations. Tours and educational programs related to dinosaur, the trackways, and the wilderness are offered.Tumbler Ridge Museum (2008).


Tumbler Ridge's location among the Rocky Mountains has allowed for the development of numerous trail systems for motorized and non-motorized recreation. The trails and open areas span numerous mountains. Kinuseo Falls along the Murray River in the Monkman Provincial Park is the most popular destination for visitors to Tumbler Ridge.Helm (2001), 261. Two other provincial parks are just outside the municipal boundaries: Bearhole Lake Provincial Park and Gwillim Lake Provincial Park.

Annual events held in Tumbler Ridge include the Grizfest Music Festival, Emperor's Challenge – the most beautiful and most challenging half-marathon in the world – and the Ridge Ramble Cross-Country Ski Race. The Grizfest Music Festival (formerly Grizzly Valley Days) is a two-day concert in August that includes a parade, dance, art show, and other community-wide events.Grizfest, 2007. The Emperor’s Challenge, also in August, is a 21 km (13 mi) marathon up Roman Mountain.Emperor's Challenge, 2007.

Tumbler Ridge has one newspaper published in the community, the locally owned and operated ''Tumbler Ridge News'' (formerly ''Community Connections''). Another newspaper, the ''Tumbler Ridge Observer'' also covers the town but is published by the ''Peace River Block Daily News'' in Dawson Creek. Two newsletters, ''Tumbler Coffee Break'' and ''Around the Ridge'', are circulated in the town.Halseth et al., (2004), 7–8. No radio station broadcasts from the town and the only television station that does so is the Community Channel Advertising run by the local chamber of commerce.Dawson Creek & District Chamber of Commerce (2003).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="aaf55d97e454cadcb154df49a9f2b900" name="Kinuseo_Falls" sectnum="6#1">../img/aaf55d97e454cadcb154df49a9f2b900.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>