<document id="7169640034220fa16e0584af65890169-4.2" name="Gorgosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
In the Dinosaur Park Formation, ''Gorgosaurus'' lived alongside a rarer species of the tyrannosaurine ''Daspletosaurus''. This is one of the few examples of two tyrannosaur genera coexisting. Similar-sized predators in modern predator guilds are separated into different ecological niches by anatomical, behavioral or geographical differences that limit competition. Niche differentiation between the Dinosaur Park tyrannosaurids is not well-understood.  In 1970, Dale Russell hypothesized the more common ''Gorgosaurus'' actively hunted fleet-footed hadrosaurs, while the rarer and more troublesome ceratopsians and ankylosaurians (horned and heavily armoured dinosaurs) were left to the more heavy-built ''Daspletosaurus''. However, a specimen of ''Daspletosaurus'' (OTM 200) from the contemporaneous Two Medicine Formation of Montana preserves the digested remains of a juvenile hadrosaur in its gut region. 

Unlike some other groups of dinosaurs, neither genus was more common at higher or lower elevations than the other. However, ''Gorgosaurus'' appears more common in northern formations like the Dinosaur Park, with species of ''Daspletosaurus'' more abundant to the south. The same pattern is seen in other groups of dinosaurs. Chasmosaurine ceratopsians and hadrosaurine hadrosaurs are also more common in the Two Medicine Formation of Montana and in southwestern North America during the Campanian, while centrosaurine and lambeosaurines dominate in northern latitudes. Holtz has suggested this pattern indicates shared ecological preferences between tyrannosaurines, chasmosaurines and hadrosaurines. At the end of the later Maastrichtian stage, tyrannosaurines like ''Tyrannosaurus rex'', hadrosaurines like ''Edmontosaurus'' and chasmosaurines like ''Triceratops'' were widespread throughout western North America, while albertosaurines and centrosaurines went extinct, and lambeosaurines were rare.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="07cacb3746fb8574f5d351f52d05798f" name="GorgosaurusDB" sectnum="4.2#1">../img/07cacb3746fb8574f5d351f52d05798f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>