<document id="71e3008097be4eb3efe341fea257e953-1" name="Vasa_(ship)" cat="1">
<text>
During the 17th century, Sweden went from being a small, poor, and peripheral northern European kingdom of little influence to one of the major players in continental politics and, between 1611 and 1718, one of the great powers of the Baltic. This rise to prominence in international affairs and increase in military prowess, called ''stormaktstiden'' ("age of greatness" or "great power period"), was made possible by a succession of able monarchs and the establishment of a powerful centralized government, supporting a highly efficient military organization. Swedish historians have described this as one of the more extreme examples of an early modern state using almost all of its available resources to wage war; the small northern kingdom transformed itself into a fiscal-military state.Hocker in ''Vasa I'', pp. 36–39; see also Jan Glete's paper ''''.


Gustavus Adolphus (1594-1632) has been considered one of the most successful martial Swedish kings. When ''Vasa'' was built, he had been in power for more than a decade. The navy was in poor shape and Sweden was embroiled in a war with Poland, and looked apprehensively at the development of the Thirty Years' War in present day Germany. The war had been raging since 1618 and from a Protestant perspective it was not going well. The king's plans for the Polish campaign and for securing Sweden's interests required a strong naval presence in the Baltic.Roberts.

The navy suffered several severe setbacks during the 1620s. In 1625, a squadron cruising off the Bay of Riga was caught in a storm and ten ships ran aground and were wrecked. In the Battle of Oliwa in 1627, a Swedish squadron was outmaneuvered and defeated by a larger Polish force and two large ships were lost. ''Tigern'' ("The Tiger"), which was the Swedish admiral's flagship, was captured by the Poles, and ''Solen'' ("The Sun") was blown up by her own crew when she was boarded and almost captured. In 1628, three more large ships were lost in less than a month; admiral Klas Fleming's flagship ''Kristina'' was wrecked in a storm in the Gulf of Danzig, ''Riksnyckeln'' ("Key of the Realm") ran aground at Viksten in the southern archipelago of Stockholm and, perhaps most inopportunely for the Swedish crown, ''Vasa'' foundered on her maiden voyage. Gustavus Adolphus was engaged in naval warfare on several fronts, which further exacerbated the difficulties of the navy. In addition to battling the Polish navy, the Swedes were threatened by Catholic forces that had invaded Jutland. The Swedish king had little sympathy for the Danish king, Christian IV, and Denmark and Sweden had been bitter enemies for well over a century. However, Sweden feared a Catholic conquest of Copenhagen and Zealand (Denmark). This would have granted the Catholic powers control over the strategic passages between the Baltic Sea and the North Sea, which would be disastrous for Swedish interests.Hocker in ''Vasa I'', p. 47.

Until the early 17th century, the Swedish navy comprised primarily smaller single-decker ships with relatively light guns; these ships were cheaper than larger ships and were well-suited for escort and patrol. However, a fleet of large ships was a bold statement and an effective way to impose authority on enemies and allies alike. For the ambitious Gustavus Adolphus, a navy with a core of powerful capital ships was an opportunity that could not be missed. ''Vasa'' was the first in a series of five ships intended to be among the heaviest and most splendid of their time. The four other ships, ''Äpplet'', ''Kronan'', ''Scepter'' and ''Göta Ark'', were successful and formed the backbone of the Swedish navy until the 1660s. Of these so-called ''regalskepp'' (usually translated as "royal ships"), ''Vasa'' was meant to be the grandest. The second of the large ships, ''Äpplet'' ("The Apple"; the Swedish term for the globus cruciger), was built simultaneously with ''Vasa''. The only difference between the design of the "Vasa" and her sister ship the "Apple" was that the "Apple" was a mere 1.5 m wider.Hocker in ''Vasa I'', p. 39; for more on ''Äpplet'', see  Jan Glete, "" in ''Marinarkeologisk tidskrift'' nr 4, 2002.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5e6c0e3c849146df60b235c5572de22f" name="Bitwa_pod_Oliwą_1627_3" sectnum="1#1">../img/5e6c0e3c849146df60b235c5572de22f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>