<document id="71e3008097be4eb3efe341fea257e953-5" name="Vasa_(ship)" cat="1">
<text>
''Vasa'' has been the subject of hundreds of books, articles and papers on topics ranging from marine archaeology to culinary history. Three children's books about ''Vasa'' have been written in Swedish and later translated into English, German, Danish, and Norwegian: ''The Vasa Saga'' by Bertil Almqvist, ''The Vasa Sets Sail'' by Mats Wahl (illustrated by Sven Nordqvist), and ''The Vasa Piglet'' by Björn Bergenholtz.

''Vasa's'' unique status has drawn considerable attention and captured the imagination of more than two generations of scholars, tourists, model builders, and authors. Though historically unfounded, the popular perception of the building of the ship as a botched and disorganized affair (dubbed "the ''Vasa''-syndrome") has been used by many authors of management literature as an educational example of how not to organize a successful business.For example this article from IEEE computing: Richard E. Fairley, Mary Jane Willshire, "Why the Vasa Sank: 10 Problems and Some Antidotes for Software Projects," ''IEEE Software'' vol. 20, no. 2, pp. 18–25, March/April, 2003; see also Hocker in ''Vasa I'', p. 58.  

The museum has produced two versions of a documentary about the history and recovery of the ship; it is shown in the museum and has been released on VHS and DVD with narration in 16 languages. An educational computer game, now in its second generation, has been made and is used in the museum and on its website to explain the fundamentals of 17th century ship construction and stability. Several mass-produced model kits and countless custom-built models of the ship have been made. In 1991, a 308-tonne (680,000 lb) pastiche reproduction of the ship was built in Tokyo to serve as a 650-passenger sightseeing ship. ''Vasa'' has inspired many works of art, including a gilded Disney-themed parody of the pilaster sculptures on the ship's quarter galleries.''Modellen: Vasamodeller från när och fjärran''. Being a popular tourist attraction, ''Vasa'' is used as a motif for various souvenir products such as T-shirts, mugs, refrigerator magnets, and posters. Commercially produced replicas—such as drinking glasses, plates, spoons, and even a backgammon game—have been made from many of the objects belonging to the crew or officers found on the ship.. Statens maritima museer. Retrieved 3 March 2009.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9256b15f0ee02ac49e75933ddbfe1ef3" name="Vasa_merchandise" sectnum="5#1">../img/9256b15f0ee02ac49e75933ddbfe1ef3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>