<document id="71f351984f1c1ed12d4db4c38e6d15f0-1.2.5" name="Ming_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
According to historian Timothy Brook, the Hongwu Emperor attempted to immobilize society by creating rigid, state-regulated boundaries between villages and larger townships, discouraging trade and travel in society not permitted by the government.Brook (1998), 19. Hongwu attempted to instill austere values by imposing uniform dress codes, standard methods of speech, and standard style of writing classical prose that did not flaunt the skills of the highly educated.Brook (1998), 30-32. His suspicion for the educated elite matched his disdain for the commercial elites, imposing inordinately high taxes upon the hotbed of powerful merchant families in the region of Suzhou in Jiangsu. He also forcibly moved thousands of wealthy families from the southeast and resettled them around Nanjing in the Jiangnan region, forbidding them to move once they were settled.Brook (1998), 28-29. To keep track of the merchants' activities, Hongwu forced them to register all of their goods once a month.Brook (1998), 65-67. One of his main goals as ruler was to permanently curb the influence of merchants and landlords, yet several of his policies would eventually encourage them to amass more wealth. 

Hongwu's oppressive system of massive relocation and the desire to escape his harsh taxes encouraged many to become itinerant retailers, peddlers, or migrant workers finding tenant landowners who would rent them space to farm and labor on.Brook (1998), 27-28, 94-95. By the mid Ming era, emperors had abandoned Hongwu's relocation scheme and instead trusted local officials to document migrant workers in order to bring in more revenue. An elite of wealthy landlords and merchants reigning over land tenants, wage laborers, domestic servants, and migrant workers was hardly the vision of Hongwu's: strict adherence to the hierarchic status system of the four occupations.Brook (1998), 85, 146, 154.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b901dc0de3e78de9c01aa9a96b65bff3" name="Nj02" sectnum="1.2.5#1">../img/b901dc0de3e78de9c01aa9a96b65bff3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>