<document id="71f351984f1c1ed12d4db4c38e6d15f0-2.10.23" name="Ming_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
After the reign of Hongwu—who from 1373 to 1384 staffed his bureaus with officials gathered through recommendations only—the scholar-officials who populated the many ranks of bureaucracy were recruited through a rigorous examination system that was first established by the Sui Dynasty (581-618).Ebrey (2006), 96.Ebrey (1999), 145-146. Theoretically the system of exams allowed anyone to join the ranks of imperial officials (although frowned upon for merchants to join); in reality the time and funding needed to support the study in preparation for the exam generally limited participants to those already coming from the landholding class.Ebrey (1999), 199. However, the government did exact provincial quotas while drafting officials. This was an effort to curb monopolization of power by landholding gentry who came from the most prosperous regions, where education was the most advanced.Ebrey (1999), 198-199. The expansion of the printing industry since Song times enhanced the spread of knowledge and number of potential exam candidates throughout the provinces.Ebrey (1999), 201-202. For young schoolchildren there were printed multiplication tables and primers for elementary vocabulary; for adult examination candidates there were mass-produced, inexpensive volumes of Confucian classics and successful examination answers.Ebrey (1999), 202.


As in earlier periods, the focus of the examination was classical Confucian texts,Hucker (1958), 12. while the bulk of test material centered on the Four Books outlined by Zhu Xi in the 12th century.Ebrey (1999), 198. Ming era examinations were perhaps more difficult to pass since the 1487 requirement of completing the "eight-legged essay", a departure from basing essays off progressing literary trends. The exams increased in difficulty as the student progressed from the local level, and appropriate titles were accordingly awarded successful applicants. Officials were classified in nine hierarchic grades, each grade divided into two degrees, with ranging salaries (nominally paid in piculs of rice) according to their rank.Hucker (1958), 11-12. While provincial graduates who were appointed to office were immediately assigned to low-ranking posts like the county graduates, those who passed the palace examination were awarded a ''jinshi'' ('presented scholar') degree and assured a high-level position.Hucker (1958), 14.Brook (1998), xxv. In 276 years of Ming rule and ninety palace examinations, the number of doctoral degrees granted by passing the palace examinations was 24,874. Ebrey states that "there were only two to four thousand of these ''jinshi'' at any given time, on the order of one out of 10,000 adult males." This was in comparison to the 100,000 ''shengyuan'' ('government students'), the lowest tier of graduates, by the 16th century.

The maximum tenure in office was nine years, but every three years officials were graded on their performance by senior officials.Hucker (1958), 15-16. If they were graded as superior then they were promoted, if graded adequate then they retained their ranks, and if graded inadequate they were demoted one rank. In extreme cases, officials would be dismissed or punished. Only capital officials of grade 4 and above were exempt from the scrutiny of recorded evaluation, although they were expected to confess any of their faults. There were over 4,000 school instructors in county and prefectural schools who were subject to evaluations every nine years.Hucker (1958), 17. The Chief Instructor on the prefectural level was classified as equal to a second-grade county graduate. The Supervisorate of Imperial Instruction oversaw the education of the heir apparent to the throne; this office was headed by a Grand Supervisor of Instruction, who was ranked as first class of grade three.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="17d4d6e626e3a57095c6080c53f28fc4" name="Ming-Beamtenprüfungen1" sectnum="2.10.23#1">../img/17d4d6e626e3a57095c6080c53f28fc4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>