<document id="71f351984f1c1ed12d4db4c38e6d15f0-1.4" name="Ming_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
The Oirat Mongol leader Esen Tayisi launched an invasion into Ming China in July of 1449. The chief eunuch Wang Zhen encouraged Emperor Zhengtong (r. 1435-1449) to personally lead a force to face the Mongols after a recent Ming defeat; marching off with 50,000 troops, Zhengtong left the capital and put his half-brother Zhu Qiyu in charge of affairs as temporary regent. In the battle that ensued on September 8, his force of 50,000 troops were decimated by Esen's army and Zhengtong was captured and held in captivity by the Mongols—an event known as the Tumu Crisis.Ebrey (2006), 273. After Zhengtong's capture, Esen's forces plundered their way across the countryside and all the way to the suburbs of Beijing.Robinson (2000), 533-534. Following this was another plundering of the Beijing suburbs in November of that year by local bandits and Ming Dynasty soldiers of Mongol descent who dressed as invading Mongols.Robinson (2000), 534. Many Han Chinese also took to brigandage soon after the Tumu incident.''Yingzong Shilu'', 184.17b, 185.5b.Robinson (1999), 85, footnote 18.


The Mongols held the Zhengtong Emperor for ransom. However, this scheme was foiled once Zhengtong's younger brother assumed the throne as the Jingtai Emperor (r. 1449-1457); the Mongols were also repelled once Jingtai's confidant and defense minister Yu Qian (1398-1457) gained control of the Ming armed forces. Holding Zhengtong in captivity was a useless bargaining chip for the Mongols as long as another sat on his throne, so they released him back into Ming China. Zhengtong was placed under house arrest in the palace until the coup against Jingtai in 1457 known as the "Wresting the Gate Incident".Robinson (1999), 83. Zhengtong retook the throne as the Tianshun Emperor (r. 1457-1464). 

Tianshun's reign was a troubled one and Mongol forces within the Ming military structure continued to be problematic. On August 7, 1461, the Chinese general Cao Qin and his Ming troops of Mongol descent staged a coup against Tianshun out of fear of being next on his purge-list of those who aided Jingtai's succession.Robinson (1999), 84-85. Mongols serving the Ming military also became increasingly circumspect as the Chinese began to heavily distrust their Mongol subjects after the Tumu Crisis.Robinson (1999), 96-97. Cao's rebel force managed to set fire to the western and eastern gates of the Imperial City (doused by rain during the battle) and killed several leading ministers before his forces were finally cornered and he was forced to commit suicide.Robinson (1999), 79, 101-108.

Under Dayan Khan and his successors, the Mongol threat to China was at its greatest level in the 15th century, although periodic raiding continued throughout the dynasty. Like in the Tumu Crisis, the Mongol leader Altan Khan (1507-1582) invaded China and raided as far as the outskirts of Beijing.Robinson (1999), 81.Laird (2006), 141. The Ming employed troops of Mongol descent to fight back Altan Khan's invasion, as well as Mongol military officers against Cao Qin's abortive coup.Robinson (1999), 83, 101. While the Ming Yongle Emperor staged five major offensives north of the Great Wall against the Mongols, following Emperor Hongwu's crushing of the remnants of the Yuan, the constant threat of Mongol incursions prompted the Ming authorities to fortify the Great Wall from the late 15th century to the 16th century; nevertheless, John Fairbank notes that "it proved to be a futile military gesture but vividly expressed China's siege mentality." Yet the Great Wall was not meant to be a purely defensive fortification; its towers functioned rather as a series of lit beacons and signalling stations to allow rapid warning to friendly units of advancing enemy troops.Ebrey (1999), 208.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c223536aa64f82c8e71795acf00fcd2a" name="Chemin_de_ronde_muraille_long" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/c223536aa64f82c8e71795acf00fcd2a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>