<document id="71f351984f1c1ed12d4db4c38e6d15f0-1.2.9" name="Ming_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
The scholar-officials' dependence upon the economic activities of the merchants became more than a trend when it was semi-institutionalized by the state in the mid Ming era. Qiu Jun (1420-1495), a scholar-official from Hainan, argued that the state should only mitigate market affairs during times of pending crisis and that merchants were the best gauge in determining the strength of a nation's riches in resources.Brook (1998), 102. The government followed this guideline by the mid Ming era when it allowed merchants to take over the state monopoly of salt production. This was a gradual process where the state supplied northern frontier armies with enough grain by granting merchants licenses to trade in salt in return for their shipping services.Brook (1998), 108. The state realized that merchants could buy salt licenses with silver and in turn boost state revenues to the point where buying grain was not an issue. The governments of both Hongwu and Zhengtong (r. 1435-1449) attempted to cut the flow of silver into the economy in favor of paper currency, yet mining the precious metal simply became a lucrative illegal pursuit practiced by many.Brook (1998), 68-69, 81-83. Hongwu was unaware of economic inflation even as he continued to hand out multitudes of banknotes as awards; by 1425, paper currency was worth only 0.025% to 0.014% its original value in the 14th century.Fairbank & Goldman (2006), 134. The value of standard copper coinage dropped significantly as well due to counterfeit minting; by the 16th century, new maritime trade contacts with Europe provided massive amounts of imported silver, which increasingly became the common medium of exchange.Fairbank & Goldman (2006), 134-135. As far back as 1436, the southern grain tax had been partially commuted to payments in silver.Brook (1998), xx. In 1581 the Single Whip Reform installed by Grand Secretary Zhang Juzheng (1525-1582) finally assessed taxes on the amount of land paid entirely in silver.Brook (1998), xxi, 89.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6a50d4212399e3cf550e3229be80cf57" name="MingLacquerTable1" sectnum="1.2.9#1">../img/6a50d4212399e3cf550e3229be80cf57.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>