<document id="71f351984f1c1ed12d4db4c38e6d15f0-1.7.18" name="Ming_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
A remarkable tribal leader named Nurhaci (r. 1616-1626), starting with just a small tribe, rapidly gained control over all the Manchurian tribes. During the Japanese invasions of Korea (1592–1598), he offered to lead his tribes in support of the Ming and Joseon army. This offer was declined, but he was granted honorific Ming titles for his gesture.Spence (1999), 27. Recognizing the weakness of Ming authority north of their border, he took control over all of the other unrelated tribes surrounding his homeland. In 1610 he broke relations with the Ming court; in 1618 he demanded the Ming pay tribute to him to redress the ''seven grievances'' which he documented and sent to the Ming court. This was effectively a declaration of war as the Ming were not about to pay money to a former tributary. 

Under the brilliant commander Yuan Chonghuan (1584-1630), the Ming were able to fight off the Manchus repeatedly, notably in 1626 at the Battle of Ningyuan (in which Nurhaci was mortally wounded) and in 1628. Under Yuan's command the Ming had securely fortified the Shanhai pass, thus blocking the Manchus from crossing the pass to attack Beijing. Using knowledge of European firearms that he might have acquired from his cook, Yuan was able to stave off Nurhaci's advances along the Liao River.Spence (1999), 24. Although he was named field marshal of all the northeastern forces in 1628, he was executed in 1630 on trumped-up charges of colluding with the Manchus as they staged their raids.Spence (1999), 24-25. Succeeding generals proved unable to eliminate the Manchu threat. 

Unable to attack the heart of Ming directly, the Manchu instead bided their time, developing their own artillery and gathering allies. They were able to enlist Ming government officials and generals as their strategic advisors. A large part of the Ming Army deserted to the Manchu banner. In 1632, they had conquered much of Inner Mongolia, resulting in a large scale recruitment of Mongol troops under the Manchu banner and the securing of an additional route into the Ming heartland. 

By 1636, the Manchu ruler Huang Taiji renamed his dynasty from the "Latter Jin" to "Qing" at Shenyang, which had fallen to the Manchu in 1621 and was made their capital in 1625.Spence (1999), 24, 28.Chang (2007), 92. Huang Taiji also adopted the Chinese imperial title ''huangdi'', took the reign title Chongde ("Revering Virtue"), and changed the ethnic name of his people from Jurchen to Manchu.Spence (1999), 31. In 1638 the Manchu defeated and conquered Ming China's traditional ally Joseon with an army of 100,000 troops. Shortly after the Koreans renounced their long-held loyalty to the Ming Dynasty.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="beafda31dfa62f0f94dad8729cbcb20c" name="ShanhaiguanGreatWall" sectnum="1.7.18#1">../img/beafda31dfa62f0f94dad8729cbcb20c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>