<document id="71f351984f1c1ed12d4db4c38e6d15f0-3.13.27" name="Ming_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
Conservative Confucian officials were wary of Wang's philosophical interpretation of the Confucian classics, the increasing number of his disciples while still in office, and his overall socially-rebellious message. To curb his political influence he was often sent out to deal with military affairs and rebellions far away from the capital. Yet his ideas penetrated mainstream Chinese thought, and spurred new interest in Daoism and Buddhism. Furthermore, people began to question the validity of the social hierarchy and the idea that the scholar was above the farmer. Wang Yangming's disciple and salt-mine worker Wang Gen gave lectures to commoners about pursuing education to improve their lives, while his follower He Xinyin 何心隱 challenged the elevation and emphasis of the family in Chinese society. His contemporary Li Zhi 李贄 (1527-1602) even taught that women were the intellectual equals of men and should be given a better education; both Li and He eventually died in prison, jailed on charges of spreading "dangerous ideas".Ebrey (2006), 283. Yet these "dangerous ideas" of educating women had long been embraced with mothers giving their children primary education,Ebrey (1999), 158. as well as courtesans who were as literate and similarly trained in calligraphy, painting, and poetry as their male hosts.Brook (1998), 230.

In opposition to the liberal views of Wang Yangming were the conservative officials in the censorate—a governmental institution with the right and responsibility to speak out against malfeasance and abuse of power—and the senior officials of the Donglin Academy, which was reestablished in 1604.Ebrey (1999), 213. These conservatives wanted a revival of orthodox Confucian ethics. Conservatives such as Gu Xiancheng (1550-1612) argued against Wang Yangming's idea of innate moral knowledge, stating that this was simply a legitimization for unscrupulous behavior such as greedy pursuits and personal gain. These two strands of Confucian thought created factionalism amongst ministers of state, who—like the old days of Wang Anshi and Sima Guang in the Song Dynasty—used any opportunity to impeach members of the other faction from court.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b99d724ad182d0abd0f4d219ba1c13d7" name="Confucius_on_his_way_to_Luoyang" sectnum="3.13.27#1">../img/b99d724ad182d0abd0f4d219ba1c13d7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>