<document id="720334cd658006fa4e2f9e33ff8afb62-4" name="Mom_and_Dad" cat="19">
<text>
In a ''Washington Post'' article covering Babb's career, the film critic Kenneth Turan wrote that ''Mom and Dad'' did not "flourish because of its birth footage or because of its puerile plot, which Babb himself disparages . . .  success flowed, rather, from Babb's extraordinary promotional abilities."  The film was exhibited across the United States, and over 300 prints were produced. In the weeks preceding the screening, local presenters sought to attract the attention of the town's inhabitants by distributing letters to local newspapers and church leaflets protesting against the film's moral basis. This strategy often utilized fabricated letters supposedly written by the mayor of a nearby city, who wished to register concern about local young women in his area who had seen the film and were awakened enough to discuss problems similar to their own.Schaefer, 116.

The campaigns were usually orchestrated by employees of either Hygienic or Hallmark Productions, and they nominally based their campaign from information provided by a standard and detailed pressbook containing cast and crew information, as well as other promotional and marketing materials. Babb's marketing strategy centered on overwhelming small towns with advertisements and letters, in an attempt to create a controversial atmosphere. In keeping with his motto of "You gotta tell 'em to sell 'em," the film became so ubiquitous that ''Time'' wrote that its presentation "left only the livestock unaware of the chance to learn the facts of life." 

The local pitch included a variety of limited screenings, including adults-only showings, viewings segregated by gender, and a live lecture by the "Fearless Hygiene Commentator Elliot Forbes" which was often placed during the intermission. At any one time, a number of "Elliot Forbes"es would give simultaneous talks in a number of locations showing the film.Schaefer, 133. In some predominantly African-American areas, Olympic gold medalist Jesse Owens was hired to make appearances instead of an actor playing Forbes. The "Elliot Forbes" actors were usually people local to the production company, sometimes out-of-work performers.Mondor, personal letter.  Along with "Forbes," presentations were often held with "nurses" in attendance, ostensibly in the event that someone fainted due to the content of the film; such "nurses" were often hired locally.Friedman, 119.

Modern Film Distributors later distributed the film, and sold over forty-five thousand copies of the books ''Man and Boy'' and ''Woman and Girl'' following Forbes's lecture. The text was written by Babb's wife,McDougal. and was filled with both biological and sexual education materials relevant to the film's subject matter; generating extra profit items for their distributors. The sales of these books netted an estimated $31,000 for the distribution company,Schaefer, 128. while Babb estimated the total sales for all distributions at 40 million copies.

Babb insisted that the program be followed closely; a contractual agreement with theaters required that each presentation follow a similar approach. Because the Forbes lecture formed part of the viewing, extra newsreels or short films were not permitted, although previews were allowed. A contractual agreement disallowed matinee pricing, set specific times for the segregated viewings, and prohibited the screening  of the film on Sundays.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e5cfb57ddfc9218f6264ff8c4b5de876" name="Babbpressbook-b" sectnum="4#1">../img/e5cfb57ddfc9218f6264ff8c4b5de876.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>