<document id="7209ec91eff50afa1f79a393670a6835-5" name="Terra_Nova_Expedition" cat="14">
<text>
As Campbell was now the senior Naval officer of the expedition, he assumed command  for its final weeks, until the arrival of ''Terra Nova'' on 18 January 1913. Before the final departure a large wooden cross was erected on the slopes of Observation Hill, overlooking Hut Point, inscribed with the five names of the dead and a quotation from Tennyson's ''Ulysses'': "To strive, to seek, to find, and not to yield".Preston, p. 229

The loss of Scott and his party overshadowed all else in the public's mind, including Amundsen's feat in being first at the Pole.Huntford, p. 526 For many years the image of Scott as a tragic hero, beyond reproach, remained virtually unchallenged, for although there were rifts among some who were close to the expedition, including relatives of the perished, this disharmony was not public. There was no real change in public perceptions until the 1970s, by which time nearly all those directly concerned with the expedition were dead. Fiennes, pp. 410&ndash;22.

Controversy was ignited with the publication of Roland Huntford's book ''Scott and Amundsen'' (1979, re-published and televised in 1985 as ''The Last Place On Earth''). Huntford was critical of Scott's supposedly authoritarian leadership style and of his poor judgement of men, and blamed him for a series of organisational failures that had collectively caused the fate of the polar party.Barczewski, pp. 252–60 Scott's personal standing suffered from these attacks; efforts to restore his reputation have included the account by Ranulph Fiennes (a direct rebuttal of Huntford's version),  Susan Solomon's scientific analysis of the weather conditions that ultimately defeated Scott, and David Cranes's 2005 biography of Scott, the last, according to historian Stephanie Barczewski, doing "a tremendous job of restoring Scott's humanity."Barczewski, pp. 305–08

In comparing the achievements of Scott and Amundsen, most polar historians generally accept that Amundsen's skills with ski and dogs, and his general familiarity with ice conditions, gave him considerable advantages in the race for the Pole.Crane, p. 426;  Preston, p. 221. Scott's  verdict on the disaster that overtook his party, written when he was close to death in extreme conditions, blames a long list of misfortunes rather than faulty organisation.Preston, pp. 214–15 While detractors such as Huntford reject this as self-justifying,Huntford, p. 509. Cherry-Garrard observes that "the whole business simply bristles with 'ifs'"; an accumulation of  decisions and circumstances that might have fallen differently ultimately led to catastrophe. But "we were as wise as anyone can be before the event."Cherry-Garrard, pp. 609–10 Diana Preston's verdict, after summarising all the circumstances of the southern journey, is: "The point is not that they ultimately failed but that they so very nearly succeeded."Preston, p. 228  
 
Given that the likely cause of the deaths of the polar party included starvation and/or scurvy, the question of sledging diets is of interest.  The rations carried and consumed by all the sledging parties on the expedition were based on nutritional science as understood in 1910, before knowledge of Vitamin C or the causes of scurvy.Preston, pp. 218&ndash;19 Emphasis was given to high protein content deemed necessary to replace calories burned during the heavy work of sledging, especially man-hauling.  In fact, the calorific values of the rations used were seriously over-estimated, although this was not apparent until much later.  The staple daily ration per man was  biscuit,  pemmican,  sugar,  butter,  tea and  cocoa.Preston p. 181. This diet would be supplemented on the Southern Journey by killing ponies for meat once their hauling function was over, but such supplements would not have bridged the calorie deficit for more than short periods.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1bac1cf46ede2c66c321abcff823d6bd" name="Observation_Hill_-_Antarctica" sectnum="5#1">../img/1bac1cf46ede2c66c321abcff823d6bd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>