<document id="72215be866ba18888af2efcead7c23ec-1" name="Rus'_Khaganate" cat="14">
<text>
The ruler of the Rus' is mentioned by the title of "khagan" in several historical sources. Most of them are foreign texts dating from the 9th century. Three others are East Slavic sources from the 11th and 12th centuries.

The earliest European reference to the khaganate comes from the Frankish ''Annals of St. Bertin''. The Annals refer to a group of Norsemen, who called themselves ''Rhos'' (''qi se, id est gentem suam, Rhos vocari dicebant'') and visited Constantinople around the year 838.Jones 249-250. Fearful of returning home via the steppes, which would leave them vulnerable to attacks by the Magyars, these Rhos travelled through Germany accompanied by Greek ambassadors from the Byzantine emperor Theophilus. When questioned by the Frankish Emperor Louis the Pious at Ingelheim, they informed him that their leader was known as ''chacanus'' (the Latin for "Khagan")''Håkan'' or ''Haakon'' was a name used among Scandinavians of the period, and it was once thought possible that the Rhos described in the court annals referred to a king by this name. and that they lived far to the north, and that they were Swedes (''comperit eos gentis esse sueonum''). 

Thirty years later, in spring 871, the eastern and western emperors, Basil I and Louis II, quarreled over control of Bari, which had been conquered by their joint forces from the Arabs. The Byzantine emperor sent an angry letter to his western counterpart, reprimanding him for usurping the title of emperor. He argued that the Frankish rulers are simple ''reges'', while the imperial title properly applied only to the overlord of the Romans, that is, to Basil himself. He also pointed out that each nation has its own title for the supreme ruler: for instance, the title of ''chaganus'' is used by the overlords of the Avars, Khazars (''Gazari''), and "Northmen" (''Nortmanno''). To that, Louis replied that he was aware only about the Avar khagans, and had never heard about the khagans of the Khazars and Normanns.''Monumenta Germaniae'' 385-394.''cagano veram non praelatum Avarum, non Gazanorum aut Nortmannorum nuncipari reperimus.'' Duczko 25. The content of Basil's letter, now lost, is reconstructed from Louis's reply, quoted in full in the ''Salerno Chronicle''.Dolger T. 59, №487. The correspondence between Louis and Basil indicates that at least one group of Scandinavians had a ruler who called himself "khagan".

Ahmad ibn Rustah, a 10th century Muslim geographer from Persia, wrote that the Rus' khagan ("khaqan rus") lived on an island in a lake.Brøndsted (1965), pp. 267–268 Constantine Zuckerman comments that Ibn Rustah, using the text of an anonymous account from the 870s, attempted to accurately convey the titles of all rulers described by its author, which makes his evidence all the more precious.Zuckerman, "Deux étapes" 96. The Muslim geographer mentions only two khagans in his treatise — those of Khazaria and Rus. A further near-contemporary reference to the Rus' comes from al-Yaqubi, who wrote in 889 or 890 that the Caucasus mountaineers, when besieged by the Arabs in 854, asked for help from the overlords (''sahib'') of al-Rum (Byzantium), Khazaria, and al-Saqaliba (Slavs).Laurent and Canard 490. According to Zuckerman, Ibn Khordadbeh and other Arab authors often confused the terms Rus and Saqaliba when describing their raids to the Caspian Sea in the 9th and 10th centuries. Thus, the ruler of al-Saqualiba in 852 was likely the same person as the khagan of the Rus. ''But n.b.'', ibn Khordadbeh's ''Book of Roads and Kingdoms'' does not mention the title of Khagan for the ruler of Rus'. Duczko 25. ''Hudud al-Alam'', an anonymous Arabic geography text written in the late 10th century, refers to the Rus' king as "rus-khaqan".Minorsky 159. As the unknown author of ''Hudud al-Alam'' relied on numerous 9th-century sources, including ibn Khordadbeh, it is possible that his reference to the Rus' Khagan was copied from earlier, pre-Rurikid texts, rather than reflecting contemporary political reality.''See, e.g''., Minorsky xvi. Finally, the 11th century Persian geographer Abu Said Gardizi mentioned "khaqan-i rus" in his work ''Zayn al-Akbar''. Like other Muslim geographers, Gardizi relied on traditions stemming from the 9th century.

There are good grounds for believing that the title "khagan" was still remembered in Kievan Rus' during the Christian period. Metropolitan Hilarion of Kiev applied the title "khagan" to the Grand Princes of Kievan Rus - Vladimir I of Kiev and Yaroslav I the Wise in the earliest surviving example of Old Kiev Rus literature, ''Slovo o Zakone i Blagodati'' ("Sermon on Law and Grace"), written around 1050.Ilarion, "Sermon on Law and Grace" 3, 17, 18, 26; for discussion, see Brook 154. Hilarion referred to Vladimir as "the great khagan of our land" (''velikago kagana nashea zemlja, Vladimera'') and Yaroslav as "our devout khagan."Duczko 25. A graffito in the north gallery of Saint Sophia Cathedral reads "O Lord, save our khagan", apparently in reference to Sviatoslav II (1073-1076).''Spasi gospodi, kagana nashego''. Duczko 25; ''see also'' Noonan, "Khazar" 91-92. As late as the end of the 12th century, ''The Tale of Igor's Campaign'' refers in passing to a "kogan Oleg","Rus", ''Encyclopaedia of Islam'' traditionally identified with Oleg of Tmutarakan.Most commentators follow Dmitry Likhachev's interpretation of the passage. Tmutarakan was a former Khazar possession and the Khazar traditions may have persisted there for an extended period of time. It is known that, while reigning in Tmutarakan, Oleg assumed the title of the "archon of all Khazaria". Other candidates include Oleg of Novgorod and Igor Svyatoslavich of Novgorod-Seversky. See: Zenkovsky 160; Encyclopaedia of The Lay 3-4.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="95392ec2348fcdbcc90513df2966aa39" name="Nicholas_Roerich,_Guests_from_Overseas" sectnum="1#1">../img/95392ec2348fcdbcc90513df2966aa39.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>