<document id="72215be866ba18888af2efcead7c23ec-2" name="Rus'_Khaganate" cat="14">
<text>
Extant primary sources make it plausible that the title of khagan was applied to the rulers of the Rus' during a rather short period, roughly between their embassy to Constantinople (838) and Basil I's letter (871). All Byzantine sources after Basil I refer to the Rus' rulers as archons. Later Kievan authors, mentioned above, appear to have revived the term "khagan" as a laudatory epithet of the ruling knyaz rather than as a valid political term.Brook 154.

The dating of the Khaganate's existence has been the subject of debates among scholars and remains unclear. Omeljan Pritsak dates the foundation of the Khaganate to around 830-840. In the 1920s, Russian historian Pavel Smirnov suggested that the Rus' Khaganate emerged only briefly at around 830 and was soon destroyed by the migration of the Magyar-Kabar tribal confederation towards the Carpathian Mountains.Smirnov 132-45 Whatever the accuracy of such estimates may be, there are no primary sources which mention the Rus' or its khagans prior to the 830s.Pritsak, ''Origin of Rus' passim.''

Equally contentious has been discussion about the date of the khaganate's disintegration. The title of Khagan is not mentioned in the Rus'-Byzantine treaties (907, 911, 944), or in ''De Ceremoniis'', a record of court ceremonials meticulously documenting the titles of foreign rulers, when it deals with Olga's reception at the court of Constantine VII in 945. Moreover, ibn Fadlan, in his detailed account of the Rus (922), designated their supreme ruler as ''malik'' ("king"). From this fact, Peter Golden concluded via an argumentum ex silentio that the khaganate collapsed at some point between 871 and 922.Golden 87, 97. Zuckerman, meanwhile, argues that the absence of the title "khagan" from the  first Russo-Byzantine Treaty proves that the khaganate had vanished by 911.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f50d8e5f39abeda5f5025fbe25818f31" name="Ög_8,_Västra_Steninge" sectnum="2#1">../img/f50d8e5f39abeda5f5025fbe25818f31.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>