<document id="7309aa510e05face6e6eeb5e35880be0-6" name="Claudius" cat="25">
<text>
Probably the most famous fictional representation of the Emperor Claudius were the books ''I, Claudius'' and ''Claudius the God'' (released in 1934 and 1935) by Robert Graves, both written in the first-person to give the reader the impression that they are Claudius' autobiography. Graves employed a fictive artifice to suggest that they were recently discovered, genuine translations of Claudius' writings. Claudius' extant letters, speeches, and sayings were incorporated into the text (mostly in the second book, ''Claudius the God'') in order to add authenticity.

In 1937 director Josef von Sternberg made an unsuccessful attempt to film ''I, Claudius'', with Charles Laughton as Claudius. Unfortunately, the lead actress Merle Oberon suffered a near-fatal accident and the movie was never finished. The surviving reels were finally shown in the documentary ''The Epic That Never Was'' in 1965, revealing some of Laughton's most accomplished acting. The motion picture rights have been obtained by Scott Rudin, with a theatrical release planned for 2010.

Graves's two books were also the basis for a thirteen-part British television adaptation produced by the BBC. The series starred Derek Jacobi as Claudius and Patrick Stewart as Sejanus, and was broadcast in 1976 on BBC2. It was a substantial critical success, and won several BAFTA awards. The series was later broadcast in the United States on ''Masterpiece Theatre'' in 1977. The DVD release of the television series contains the "The Epic that Never Was" documentary.

Claudius has been portrayed in film on several other occasions, including in the 1979 motion picture ''Caligula'', the role being performed by Giancarlo Badessi in which the character was depicted as an idiot, in complete contrast to Robert Graves' portrait of Claudius as a cunning and deeply intelligent man. In the parody ''Gore Vidal's Caligula'', which advertises itself as a remake of the original film, Claudius is portrayed by Glenn Shadix.

On television, the actor Freddie Jones became famous for his role as Claudius in the 1968 British television series ''The Caesars'' while the 1985 made-for-television miniseries ''A.D.'' features actor Richard Kiley as Claudius. There is also a reference to Claudius' suppression of one of the coups against him in the movie ''Gladiator'', though the incident is entirely fictional.

In literature, Claudius and his contemporaries appear in the historical novel ''The Roman'' by Mika Waltari. Canadian-born science fiction writer A. E. van Vogt reimagined Robert Graves' Claudius story in his two novels ''Empire of the Atom'' and ''The Wizard of Linn''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e74d9ff2cf659ef1072d017d8a7745ed" name="IClaudius" sectnum="6#1">../img/e74d9ff2cf659ef1072d017d8a7745ed.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>