<document id="7309aa510e05face6e6eeb5e35880be0-2.3" name="Claudius" cat="25">
<text>
Claudius personally judged many of the legal cases tried during his reign. Ancient historians have many complaints about this, stating that his judgments were variable and sometimes did not follow the law.Suet. ''Claud.'' 15. Dio ''Rom. Hist.'' LXI 33. He was also easily swayed. Nevertheless, Claudius paid detailed attention to the operation of the judicial system. He extended the summer court session, as well as the winter term, by shortening the traditional breaks. Claudius also made a law requiring plaintiffs to remain in the city while their cases were pending, as defendants had previously been required to do. These measures had the effect of clearing out the docket. The minimum age for jurors was also raised to 25 in order to ensure a more experienced jury pool.Scramuzza (1940), Chap. 6

Claudius also settled disputes in the provinces. He freed the island of Rhodes from Roman rule for their good faith and exempted Troy from taxes. Early in his reign, the Greeks and Jews of Alexandria sent him two embassies at once after riots broke out between the two communities. This resulted in the famous "Letter to the Alexandrians", which reaffirmed Jewish rights in the city but also forbade them to move in more families en masse. According to Josephus, he then reaffirmed the rights and freedoms of all the Jews in the empire.Josephus ''Ant. Iud.'' XIX, 287. An investigator of Claudius' discovered that many old Roman citizens based in the modern city of Trento were not in fact citizens.Scramuzza (1940), Chap. 7, p.129 The emperor issued a declaration that they would be considered to hold citizenship from then on, since to strip them of their status would cause major problems. However, in individual cases, Claudius punished false assumption of citizenship harshly, making it a capital offense. Similarly, any freedmen found to be impersonating equestrians were sold back into slavery.Scramuzza (1940), Chap. 7

Numerous edicts were issued throughout Claudius' reign. These were on a number of topics, everything from medical advice to moral judgments. Two famous medical examples are one promoting Yew juice as a cure for snakebite, Suetonius, ''Claud.'' 16 and another promoting public flatulence for good health.Suetonius, ''Claud.'' 32 One of the more famous edicts concerned the status of sick slaves. Masters had been abandoning ailing slaves at the temple of Aesculapius to die, and then reclaiming them if they lived. Claudius ruled that slaves who recovered after such treatment would be free. Furthermore, masters who chose to kill slaves rather than take the risk were liable to be charged with murder.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b8a6adbc1ef05ea1bb0c00c36daef88f" name="Claudius_sestertius_spes" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/b8a6adbc1ef05ea1bb0c00c36daef88f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>