<document id="7312e6fd1b7c259f4fa4ad7fed2a35d3-9" name="Sale,_Greater_Manchester" cat="11">
<text>
The first turnpike road in the area was the latter-day A56 Chester Road between Manchester and Crossford Bridge (on the border between Sale and Stretford). Turnpike trusts collected tolls from road users and used the proceeds to maintain the highway. There was a toll booth on the Sale side of Crossford Bridge. Another section of road between Altrincham and Crossford Bridge was turnpiked in 1765.Nevell (1997), pp. 96&ndash;97. The commencement of "swift packet" services on the newly opened Bridgewater Canal in 1776 made commuting from Sale into Manchester both practical and convenient, with boats travelling at a relatively swift .Swain (1987), p. 46. However the arrival in 1849 of the Manchester, South Junction and Altrincham Railway sounded a death-knell for both the canal packet services and turnpike trusts. Many trusts went into terminal decline, mirroring a national trend.  By 1888 almost all roads and highways were the responsibility of the local authority. Sale's railway station, originally named Sale Moor, was renamed to Sale in 1856.Swain (1987), p. 89. Three years later Brooklands railway station was opened, followed in 1931 by the opening of Dane Road railway station along with the electrification of the entire line.Nevell (1997), p. 100. The line was renovated in the early 1990s and is now part of the Metrolink.

Following the completion of a tramway between Manchester and Stretford in 1901, the British Electric Traction Company applied to Parliament for an extension to Sale. The proposal was amended to continue the line further south, into Altrincham. The line through Sale was owned by Sale Urban District Council and leased to the Manchester Corporation. Services to Sale commenced in 1907. A branch along Northenden Road from the line to Sale Moor was created in 1912.  Sale Moor's line had only a single track which in 1925 resulted in a head-on collision between two tramcars, injuring eight passengers.Swain (1987), pp. 119&ndash;120. Bus services were first introduced to the area in the 1920s, but became more widespread in the 1930s.Swain (1987), pp. 129&ndash;130.  The buses did not suffer the drawback of being limited to tracks and were therefore more practical than the tram services which from the 1930s went into decline. The tramlines along Northenden Road were removed between 1932 and 1934, and throughout Sale in the 1940s.

The Metrolink system connects Sale with other locations in Greater Manchester. Trams depart the town's three stations every six minutes between 7:15 am and 6:30 pm, and every 12 minutes at other times of the day. Retrieved on 6 May 2007. The nearest main line railway station is Navigation Road in Altrincham, from where trains run to Manchester Piccadilly, Stockport and Chester. Bus routes operated by various companies provide services to Manchester and Altrincham. Retrieved on 6 May 2007. The A56 road runs between Chester and North Yorkshire via Sale, Manchester, and Burnley, and the M60 motorway &ndash; which encircles Manchester &ndash; can be accessed via junction 7, just to the north of Sale. The M56 and M62 motorways are about  away, and the M6 motorway, which runs between Warwickshire and Carlisle, is about  to the west. Manchester Airport, the busiest airport in the UK outside the London area, is  to the south.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="edbbe1f63fe6dc87e7cf291b64d49a3f" name="Sale_Metrolink_station" sectnum="9#1">../img/edbbe1f63fe6dc87e7cf291b64d49a3f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>