<document id="7312e6fd1b7c259f4fa4ad7fed2a35d3-3" name="Sale,_Greater_Manchester" cat="11">
<text>
At  (53.4246, &minus;2.322), Sale lies respectively to the north and south of the neighbouring towns of Altrincham and Stretford, and  south-west of Manchester city centre. The district of Wythenshawe is to the southeast. Sale is in the Mersey Valley, about  above sea level on generally flat ground. The River Mersey, which runs just north of the town, is prone to flooding during heavy rains, so the Sale Water Park, close to the town's northern boundary, acts as an emergency flood basin. Retrieved on 6 May 2007. The man-made, and thus more controllable, Bridgewater Canal runs through the centre of the town.

Sale's local drift geology consists of sand and gravel deposited about 10,000 years ago, during the last ice age.Nevell (1997), p. 1. The bedrock is Bunter sandstone in the west and Triassic waterstone in the east.Nevell (1997), p. 3. United Utilities obtains the town's drinking water from the Lake District. Retrieved on 26 December 2008. Sale's climate is generally temperate, like the rest of Greater Manchester. The mean highest and lowest temperatures ( and ) are slightly above the national average, while the annual rainfall () and average hours of sunshine (1394.5 hours) are respectively above and below the national averages.



The town's main districts are Ashton upon Mersey in the northwest, Sale Moor in the southeast, and Brooklands in the southwest. The main commercial area is Sale town centre, in the central northern area of the town, but smaller commercial centres are also found in Ashton upon Mersey and Sale Moor. Brooklands is the most densely populated area. Most of the parks, including Worthington and Walton, are in the central and southern areas, leaving Ashton upon Mersey and Sale Moor with a shortage of accessible green space. Retrieved on 30 June 2007. Retrieved on 30 June 2007. Retrieved on 30 June 2007.

Sale's built environment is varied, with a mixture of modern and old buildings. Some terraces, semi-detached houses, and villas, survive from the Victorian period,Swain (1987), pp. 91&ndash;93. although many of the larger houses have been converted into flats.Swain (1987), p. 122. Many semi-detached houses survive from 1930s, when there was a need for new housing in the town as a result of a growing population and an increasingly wealthy middle class.Swain (1987), pp. 124&ndash;126. Interspersed with these older structures are newer housing developments, such as the estates built in Ashton upon Mersey and the east of Sale during the 1970s.Swain (1987) p. 134.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d3b79d6acff4c26fcc7229cc5e7db4b5" name="Sale_Moor_2007" sectnum="3#1">../img/d3b79d6acff4c26fcc7229cc5e7db4b5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>