<document id="7312e6fd1b7c259f4fa4ad7fed2a35d3-8" name="Sale,_Greater_Manchester" cat="11">
<text>
Sale is a diverse community with a synagogue and Christian churches of various denominations. The church buildings were mostly constructed in the late 19th or early 20th century in the wake of the population boom created by the arrival of the railway in 1849,Swain (1987), p. 76. although records show that the Church of St Martin in Ashton upon Mersey dates back to at least 1304.Nevell (1997), p. 28. Before the English Reformation, the inhabitants of Sale were predominantly Catholic, but afterwards were members of the Church of England. Roman Catholics returned to the area in the 19th century in the form of Irish immigrants. Two of the three Grade II* listed buildings in the town are churches. The Church of St Martin, which was probably originally an early 14th-century timber framed structure, was rebuilt in 1714 after the church had been destroyed in a storm. Retrieved on 23 February 2008.Richards (1947), pp. 22–24. The Church of St John the Divine was built in 1868, to the design of Alfred Waterhouse. Retrieved on 23 March 2008. There are three Grade II listed churches in Sale: the Church of St Anne; the Church of St Mary Magdalene; and the Church of St Paul.

As of the 2001 UK census, 78.0% of Sale residents reported themselves as Christian, 1.4% Muslim, 0.7% Hindu, 0.6% Jewish, 0.2% Buddhist and 0.2% Sikh. A further 12.9% had no religion, 0.2% had an alternative religion, and 5.9% did not state their religion. Retrieved on 5 August 2008. Sale is part of the Roman Catholic Diocese of Shrewsbury, Retrieved on 7 May 2007. and the Church of England Diocese of Chester. Retrieved on 11 April 2009. Sale and District Synagogue is on Hesketh Road in Sale, Retrieved on 12 August 2008. and is part of United Synagogue under the aegis of the Chief Rabbi of Britain, Jonathan Sacks. Retrieved on 14 August 2008. The only mosque in Trafford is the Masjid-E-Noor in Old Trafford,  away. Retrieved on 12 August 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1892bf010ddc0b62cfe370df866b5923" name="St_martins_ashton_upon_mersey" sectnum="8#1">../img/1892bf010ddc0b62cfe370df866b5923.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>