<document id="7312e6fd1b7c259f4fa4ad7fed2a35d3-6.2" name="Sale,_Greater_Manchester" cat="11">
<text>
Sale has three Grade II* listed buildings &ndash; two churches (St. Martin and St. John the Divine) and Ashton New Hall &ndash; and eighteen Grade II listed buildings. Retrieved on 31 July 2008.  The cenotaph outside the town hall was designed by Ashton upon Mersey sculptor Arthur Sherwood Edwards and is a Grade II listed building. It commemorates the 400 men from Sale who died in the First World War and the 300 who died in the Second World War. The memorial consists of a statue of a mourning Saint George on top of a granite pedestal. Costing £600 (£ as of ), it was funded by public subscription and unveiled in May 1925 in front of a crowd of 10,000.Wyke (2004), pp. 393&ndash;394.

The oldest surviving building in Sale is Eyebrow Cottage.Nevell (1997), pp. 2, 77–8. Built around 1670, it was originally a yeoman farmhouse and is one of the earliest brick buildings in the area. Its name is derived from the decorative brickwork above the windows. It was built in Cross Street, which at the time was a separate village from Sale.

A bronze bust of James Joule, the physicist who gave his name to the SI unit of energy, is in Worthington Park. Originally a tower was to have been erected in his honour, but lack of donations led to the production of the bust as a substitute; it was unveiled in 1905.Wyke (2004), p. 394. Joule moved to Sale in the 1870s for his health; he died at his home at 12 Wardle Road in 1889, and is buried in Brooklands Cemetery.Swain (1987), p. 96.

The area has several parks and green spaces.  Worthington Park, originally called Sale Park, was opened in 1900. It features a bandstand, gardens, play areas, and a skate ramp and is maintained by Trafford Council and The Friends of Worthington Park. Retrieved on 24 December 2008. Opened in 1939, Walton Park is in the southwest of the town and features a miniature railway. Retrieved on 24 December 2008. Sale Water Park is an artificial lake, created from a  deep gravel pit left during the construction of the M60. It opened in 1980 and is a venue for water sports, fishing and bird watching. The water park is the site of the Broad Ees Dole wildlife refuge, a Local Nature Reserve that provides a home for migratory birds. Retrieved on 27 April 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2e5b7a0eb90801515f4a2be427aea00d" name="Sale_water_park" sectnum="6.2#1">../img/2e5b7a0eb90801515f4a2be427aea00d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>