<document id="7312e6fd1b7c259f4fa4ad7fed2a35d3-2" name="Sale,_Greater_Manchester" cat="11">
<text>
Historically, Sale was a township in the ancient parish of Ashton upon Mersey in the hundred of Bucklow and county of Cheshire. Throughout the Middle Ages it was governed by the Lord of the Manor. Following the Poor Law Amendment Act 1834, Sale was joined with the Altrincham Poor Law Union, an inter-parish unit established to provide social security. The unit changed its name to Bucklow Poor Law Union in 1895. Sale adopted the Local Government Act 1858 in November 1866, and Sale Local Board was formed to govern the township at the beginning of 1867. Retrieved on 12 August 2008. Members were elected to the local board by the town's ratepayers. A household had one vote for every £10 (£ as of ) of rateable value.Swain (1987), p. 119. Under the Local Government Act 1888 Sale became an urban district of the administrative county of Cheshire. The local board was replaced by Sale Urban District Council in 1894. The parish of Ashton upon Mersey became an urban district in 1895.Youngs (1991), pp. 6, 33, 644–646 In 1930, the Ashton upon Mersey UD was merged into Sale UD under a county review order.

In December 1933, Sale Urban District submitted a petition to the Privy Council in an attempt to gain a charter of incorporation. At the time, Sale UD had the largest population and highest rateable value of any urban district in the country. The petition was successful and on 21 September 1935 Sale UD was granted borough status, and became the Municipal Borough of Sale. Following the Local Government Act 1972, on 1 April 1974 the Municipal Borough of Sale was abolished. Sale became an unparished area of the Metropolitan Borough of Trafford, a local government district of the metropolitan county of Greater Manchester. The town's education, town planning, waste collection, health, social care and other services are administered by Trafford Council. Retrieved on 6 January 2008.

For national elections, Sale was in the parliamentary constituency of Altrincham and Sale from 1945 until 1997, when it was split between Altrincham and Sale West and Wythenshawe and Sale East. The Altrincham and Sale West constituency is not only one of the Conservative Party's few seats in North West England but also the only Conservative seat in Greater Manchester. The Sale area consists of five electoral wards, which between them have 15 of the 63 seats on the council. The wards are Ashton upon Mersey, Brooklands, Priory, Sale Moor, and St. Mary's. Retrieved on 17 April 2007. As of the 2008 local elections, the Conservative Party held ten of the seats and the Labour Party held five. Retrieved on 1 August 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="84e2b8e0ab3e42cec811f8dc52f3d97e" name="Sale_coat_of_arms" sectnum="2#1">../img/84e2b8e0ab3e42cec811f8dc52f3d97e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>