<document id="733300b3a45446bcac5ccee1836c2b26-2.1" name="Harry_Trott" cat="26">
<text>
Included in the Australian squad to tour England, Trott was selected in the team for the First Test at Lord's. He had an inauspicious Test debut: he made a duck in the first innings and three runs in the second, and did not bowl.  The Australians won the game by 62 runs, only their second Test match victory in England.  However, England retained The Ashes by winning the remaining two Tests and Trott's influence on the series was negligible: he did not pass 20 in an innings, and he failed to take a wicket.  Nevertheless, his performances in the other matches of the season prompted ''Wisden Cricketers Almanack'' to write that he, "... fully justif his selection by scoring the highly creditable total of 1,212 runs, with an average of over 19 per innings", and that his fielding was "excellent at point".  ''Wisden'' was less complimentary about his bowling: "We have no great opinion of Trott's leg break bowling, and think it probably too slow to be effectual against good batsmen." Trott's opportunities were limited as his teammates Charles Turner and John Ferris, "monopolised the bowling".  


On his return to Australia, Trott's batting continued to improve. He scored 172 runs for an Australian XI against New South Wales, his maiden century in first-class cricket. The ''Sydney Morning Herald'' wrote that the innings "... stamped him as a batsman of the highest class". In first-class matches, Trott posted 507 runs (at 39.00 average) and claimed 25 wickets (at 17.44 average) for the summer, and hit a double century in a club match against Melbourne. Another good all-round season in 1889&ndash;90 ensured his place for the next trip to England.

The 1890 Australian team touring England was relatively inexperienced.Pollard (1988), p. 405.  The team missed the all-round ability of George Giffen who had refused to tour, thinking it unlikely the tour would be a sporting or financial success.Robinson (1996), p. 62.  The Australians won 13 matches on tour, losing 16 and drawing 9.  Trott scored 1,211 first-class runs (at 20.87 average) with a highest score of 186 against Cambridge University Past and Present, and captured 20 wickets.  Disappointed by Trott's performances, ''Wisden'' felt that he "... barely maintained the reputation he had so honestly gained during the tour of 1888 ... it cannot be said that he came up to expectations".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bdeafbee049df56aa245bfe1f09ce1ad" name="HarryTrottFielding" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/bdeafbee049df56aa245bfe1f09ce1ad.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>