<document id="733300b3a45446bcac5ccee1836c2b26-3.6" name="Harry_Trott" cat="26">
<text>
Because Trott's illness precluded his selection for the 1899 Australian team to England, the Australian captaincy passed to Joe Darling. On 8 May 1899, Trott was committed to the Kew Asylum, a psychiatric hospital in the eastern suburbs of Melbourne.  The facility opened in 1871 during an era when large asylums were in vogue.  By the time of Trott's admission, expert opinion had changed; in January 1898 ''The Argus'' reported a specialist's claim that the asylum was likely to make a patient, "just mad enough to be put under restraint"&mdash;that is, worse rather than better. Trott was recorded as suffering "dementia" and "alcoholism", although there is little empirical evidence for either diagnosis.  Cricket writer Gideon Haigh suggests that his symptoms would possibly be identified in modern times as depressive psychosis and treated with antipsychotics or electroconvulsive therapy.

Doctors observed that Trott continually stood in one place, showing little interest in events around him.  A doctor noted on Trott's file: "Refuses to converse not appearing to be able to follow what is said to him. Answers questions in monosyllables. Does not rouse up when subjects are spoken of that formerly he was interested in." Attempting to reach him, doctors sent Trott to play cricket which he did in a, "mechanical, indifferent fashion". In a departure from normal hospital procedure, he was allowed newspapers reporting the details of Darling's Australian side in England; this left him unmoved. Trott's friend Ben Wardill, the secretary of the Melbourne Cricket Club, visited in November 1899 but Trott did not recognise him.  A fellow patient, when released, wrote of Trott: "Here is a well-known cricketer, whom we once treated as a hero.  But alas! Like everything else, times have changed and he is almost forgotten."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7106ef0c57acfcd2f16922948ce5e3d3" name="KewAsylum" sectnum="3.6#1">../img/7106ef0c57acfcd2f16922948ce5e3d3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>