<document id="7367b22e19fb8c48dc46281abd2875d8-10.9.8" name="Fungus" cat="3">
<text>
''Amanita phalloides'' accounts for the majority of fatal mushroom poisonings worldwide.
Edible mushrooms are well-known examples of fungi. Many are commercially raised, but others must be harvested from the wild. ''Agaricus bisporus'', sold as button mushrooms when small or Portobello mushrooms when larger, is a commonly-eaten species, used in salads, soups, and many other dishes. Many Asian fungi are commercially grown and have increased in popularity in the West. They are often available fresh in grocery stores and markets, including straw mushrooms (''Volvariella volvacea''), oyster mushrooms (''Pleurotus ostreatus''), shiitakes (''Lentinula edodes''), and enokitake (''Flammulina'' spp.).

There are many more mushroom species that are harvested from the wild for personal consumption or commercial sale. Milk mushrooms, morels, chanterelles, truffles, black trumpets, and ''porcini'' mushrooms (''Boletus edulis'') (also known as king boletes) demand a high price on the market. They are often used in gourmet dishes.Hall, pp. 13–26.

Certain types of cheeses require inoculation of milk curds with fungal species that impart a unique flavor and texture to the cheese. Examples include the blue color in cheeses such as Stilton or Roquefort, which are made by inoculation with ''Penicillium roqueforti''. Molds used in cheese production are non-toxic and are thus safe for human consumption; however, mycotoxins (e.g., aflatoxins, roquefortine C, patulin, or others) may accumulate due to growth of other fungi during cheese ripening or storage.

Many mushroom species are poisonous to humans, with toxicities ranging from slight digestive problems or allergic reactions as well as hallucinations to severe organ failures and death. Genera with mushrooms containing deadly toxins include ''Conocybe'', ''Galerina'', ''Lepiota'', and most infamously, ''Amanita''. The latter genus includes the destroying angel ''(A. virosa)'' and the death cap ''(A. phalloides)'', the most common cause of deadly mushroom poisoning. The false morel (''Gyromitra esculenta'') is occasionally considered a delicacy when cooked, yet can be highly toxic when eaten raw. ''Tricholoma equestre'' was considered edible until being implicated in serious poisonings causing rhabdomyolysis.  Fly agaric mushrooms (''Amanita muscaria'') also cause occasional non-fatal poisonings, mostly as a result of ingestion for use as a recreational drug for its hallucinogenic properties. Historically, fly agaric was used by different peoples in Europe and Asia and its present usage for religious or shamanic purposes is reported from some ethnic groups such as the  Koryak people of north-eastern Siberia.

As it is difficult to accurately identify a safe mushroom without proper training and knowledge, it is often advised to assume that a wild mushroom is poisonous and not to consume it.Hall, p. 7.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6c2ffef186d9393767b2258a8cab6932" name="Blue_Stilton_Quarter_Front" sectnum="10.9.8#1">../img/6c2ffef186d9393767b2258a8cab6932.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>