<document id="737ec6b56df795cb7dd091ed8d0847e0-1.3" name="Virginia_Eliza_Clemm_Poe" cat="17">
<text>
The "tattling of many tongues" in Virginia's Valentine poem was a reference to actual incidents.Moss, 214 In 1845, Poe had begun a flirtation with Frances Sargent Osgood, a married 34-year-old poet.Silverman, 280 Virginia was aware of the friendship and may even have encouraged it.Meyers, 190 She often invited Osgood to visit them at home, believing that the older woman had a "restraining" effect on Poe, who had made a promise to "give up the use of stimulants" and was never drunk in Osgood's presence.Silverman, 287

At the same time, another poet, Elizabeth F. Ellet, became enamored of Poe and jealous of Osgood. Though, in a letter to Sarah Helen Whitman, Poe called her love for him "loathsome" and wrote that he "could do nothing but repel  with scorn", he printed many of her poems to him in the ''Broadway Journal'' while he was its editor.Moss, 212 Ellet was known for being meddlesome and vindictiveSilverman, 288 and, while visiting the Poe household in late January 1846, she saw one of Osgood's personal letters to Poe.Meyers, 191 According to Ellet, Virginia pointed out "fearful paragraphs" in Osgood's letter.Moss, 213 Ellet contacted Osgood and suggested she should beware of her indiscretions and asked Poe to return her letters, motivated either by jealousy or by a desire to cause scandal. Osgood then sent Margaret Fuller and Anne Lynch Botta to ask Poe on her behalf to return the letters. Angered by their interference, Poe called them "Busy-bodies" and said that Ellet had better "look after her ''own'' letters", suggesting indiscretion on her part.Silverman, 290 He then gathered up these letters from Ellet and left them at her house.

Though these letters had already been returned to her, Ellet asked her brother "to ''demand of me the letters''". Her brother, Colonel William Lummis, did not believe that Poe had already returned them and threatened to kill him. In order to defend himself, Poe requested a pistol from Thomas Dunn English. English, Poe's friend and a minor writer who was also a trained doctor and lawyer, likewise did not believe that Poe had already returned the letters and even questioned their existence. The easiest way out of the predicament, he said, "was a retraction of unfounded charges".Moss, 220 Angered at being called a liar, Poe pushed English into a fistfight. Poe later claimed he was triumphant in the fight, though English claimed otherwise, and Poe's face was badly cut by one of English's rings. In Poe's version, he said, "I gave E. a flogging which he will remember to the day of his death." Either way, the fight further sparked gossip over the Osgood affair.Silverman, 291

Osgood's husband stepped in and threatened to sue Ellet unless she formally apologized for her insinuations. She retracted her statements in a letter to Osgood saying, "The letter shown me by Mrs Poe ''must have been a forgery''" created by Poe himself.Moss, 215 She put all the blame on Poe, suggesting the incident was because Poe was "intemperate and subject to acts of lunacy".Silverman, 292 Ellet spread the rumor of Poe's insanity, which was taken up by other enemies of Poe and reported in newspapers. The St. Louis ''Reveille'' reported: "A rumor is in circulation in New York, to the effect that Mr. Edgar A. Poe, the poet and author, has been deranged, and his friends are about to place him under the charge of Dr. Brigham of the Insane Retreat at Utica."Meyers, 192 The scandal eventually died down only when Osgood reunited with her husband. Virginia, however, had been very affected by the whole affair. She had received anonymous letters about her husband's alleged indiscretions as early as July 1845. It is presumed that Ellet was involved with these letters, and they so disturbed Virginia that she allegedly declared on her deathbed that "Mrs. E. had been her murderer."Moss, 213–214
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3523578c8372ab85238247e0c768353f" name="FannyOsgood" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/3523578c8372ab85238247e0c768353f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>