<document id="73ac4cac6961fa8744ca2937a97b810b-1.1" name="Stamata_Revithi" cat="26">
<text>
Stamata Revithi was born in Syros in 1866. Records of her life from 1896 show that she was living in poverty in Piraeus 30 years later. At that point she had given birth to two children, a son who died in 1895, aged seven, and another child who was seventeen months old by the time of the 1896 Olympics. Contemporary sources do not mention her husband, so she was likely widowed. According to Olympic historian Athanasios Tarasouleas, Revithi, who was blonde and thin with large eyes, looked much older than her age.Tarasouleas, ''The Female Spiridon Loues'', 11 

Revithi believed that she could gain employment in Athens, and so walked there from her home&mdash;a distance of . Her journey took place several days prior to the Olympic marathon, a special race of  invented as part of the athletics program, and based on Michel Bréal's idea of a race from the city of Marathon to the Pnyx. Bréal took inspiration from Pheidippides, who, according to the legend, ran the distance from Marathon to Athens to announce the Greek victory over Persia at the Battle of Marathon.Martin & Gynn, ''Running through the Ages'', 5&ndash;6; Young, ''A Brief History of the Olympic Games'', 166 

En route to Athens, Revithi encountered a male runner along the road. He gave her money and advised her to run the marathon to become famous, and, consequently, earn money or more easily find a job.Olympic historians do not all agree on why Revithi decided to run the marathon race. It is thought by some of them that Revithi's goal in this decision was to secure a position for work (DeFrantz, ''Women in Sport'', 185; Eleftheratos,  ). Jere Longman () wonders "why anyone would want to run 24 miles for a civil service job". According to Martin & Gynn (''Running through the Ages'', 21), "the male runner told her (Revithi), apparently in jest, that the best way to get rich was to run the marathon and win" (see a similar version of the story by Tarasouleas ). Emet Malone () believes that, after Revithi was rejected, "she ran the course anyway to prove a point". After this discussion Revithi decided to run the race: she had enjoyed long-distance running as a child, and believed she could beat the male competitors.Tarasouleas, ''Stamata Revithi, "Alias Melpomeni"'', 53; Tarasouleas, ''The Female Spiridon Loues'', 11

The 1896 Olympic Games were the first held in the Modern era and the most important international multi-sport event Greece had ever hosted.The Greeks believed that substantial advantages for their country might arise from the hosting of the Games (Philimon, ''Organization of the Games of 1896'', 10). The rules of the Games generally excluded women from competition. Influenced by both his times&mdash;in the Victorian era women were considered to be inferior to menDomosh & Seager, ''Putting Women in Place'', 143; Payne, ''Different but Equal'', 21&mdash;and his admiration for the ancient Olympic Games, when only men were allowed to participate in the events, Baron Pierre de Coubertin, the visionary of the modern Olympic Games, was not in favor of women's participation in the Olympic Games or in sports generally. He believed that a woman's greatest achievement would be to encourage her sons to be distinguished in sports and to applaud a man's effort.DeFrantz, ''Women in Sport'', 185; Miragaya, ''The Female Olympian'', 313&ndash;314
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a62a6370f3e2ffa714416726b641d1a7" name="Baron_Pierre_de_Coubertin" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/a62a6370f3e2ffa714416726b641d1a7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>