<document id="73ac4cac6961fa8744ca2937a97b810b-1.2" name="Stamata_Revithi" cat="26">
<text>
Revithi arrived at the race location, the small village of Marathon, on Thursday, 9 April , where the athletes had already assembled for the following day's race. She attracted the attention of the reporters and was warmly greeted by Marathon's mayor, who sheltered her in his house.Eleftheratos,  (PDF) She answered the reporters' questions and was quick-witted when a male runner from Chalandri teased her, predicting that when she entered the Stadium, there would be no crowds left. Revithi retorted that he should not insult women, since male Greek athletes had already been humiliated by the Americans.Tarasouleas, ''The Female Spiridon Loues'', 11. Americans had won golden medals in nine of the twelve athletics events during the previous days.

Prior to the start of the race on the morning of Friday, 10 April , the old priest of Marathon, Ioannis Veliotis, was scheduled to say a prayer for the athletes in the church of Saint John.  Veliotis refused to bless Revithi because she was not an officially recognized athlete.  The organizing committee ultimately refused her entry into the race. Officially, she was rejected because the deadline for participations had expired; however, as Olympic historians David Martin and Roger Gynn point out, the real problem was her gender.Greek participants had been chosen through two trial national races, which had taken place on 10  and 24 March . Another athlete, Carlo Airoldi, was also not allowed to run because he was a professional (Martin&ndash;Gynn, ''Running through the Ages'', 12, 21).  According to Tarasouleas, the organizers promised that she would compete with a team of American women in another race in Athens, which never took place.Tarasouleas, ''Stamata Revithi, "Alias Melpomeni"'', 54; Tarasouleas, ''The Female Spiridon Loues'', 12


Beginning at 8:00 the following day, Revithi ran the marathon course on her own. Before starting, she had the town's only teacher, the mayor, and the city magistrate sign a statement testifying to the time she departed from the village.  She ran the race at a steady pace and reached Parapigmata (the place where the Evangelismos Hospital stands today, near the Hilton Athens) at 13:30 (5½ hours).Martin & Gynn, ''Running through the Ages'', 22; Tarasouleas, ''Stamata Revithi, "Alias Melpomeni"'', 55; Tarasouleas, ''The Female Spiridon Loues'', 12. However, some of the authors who believe that "Melpomene" and Revithi are the same person attribute to the latter the more favorable time of 4½ hours. E.g. Miragaya, ''The Female Olympian'', 314, who cites  Revithi was not allowed to enter Panathinaiko Stadium—her race was stopped in Parapigmata by a few Greek military officers who she asked to sign her handwritten report to certify her time of arrival in Athens.Eleftheratos,  (PDF); Tarasouleas, ''Stamata Revithi, "Alias Melpomeni"'', 54 She stated to the reporters that she wanted to meet Timoleon Philimon (the General-Secretary of the Hellenic Olympic Committee) to present her case. Historians believe that she intended to present her documents to the Hellenic Olympic Committee in the hopes that they would recognize her achievement. Neither her reports nor documents from the Hellenic Olympic Committee have been discovered to provide corroboration.Martin & Gynn, ''Running through the Ages'', 22
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0c8709d698a969ca7b4de2796ec04225" name="Stade1896" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/0c8709d698a969ca7b4de2796ec04225.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>