<document id="73ac4cac6961fa8744ca2937a97b810b-2" name="Stamata_Revithi" cat="26">
<text>
In March 1896, a French-language newspaper in Athens (the ''Messager d' Athènes'') reported that there was "talk of a woman who had enrolled as a participant in the Marathon race. In the test run which she completed on her own  she took 4½ hours to run the distance of 42  kilometers which separates Marathon from Athens."Martin & Gynn, ''Running through the Ages'', 20 Later that year, Franz Kémény, a founding International Olympic Committee member from Hungary, wrote in German that, "indeed a lady, Miss Melpomene, completed the 40 kilometers marathon in 4½ hours and requested an entry into the Olympic Games competition. This was reportedly denied by the commission."Martin & Gynn, ''Running through the Ages'', 21 According to Martin and Gynn, "a peculiarity here is why there is no first name for Melpomene". The ''Messager'' report faded into obscurity for about 30 years before it was revived in 1927 in an issue of ''Der Leichtathlet''.Tamini, ''Women always in the Race'', 206

Olympic historian Karl Lennartz contends that two women ran the marathon in 1896, and that the name "Melpomene" was confirmed by both Kémény and Alfréd Hajós, two-time Olympic swim champion of 1896.However, Hajós confuses the race at the beginning of March with the one 11 April, about which Tarasouleas reports (Lennartz , 20). Lennartz presents the following account: a young woman named Melpomene wanted to run the race and completed the distance in 4½ hours at the end of February or the beginning of March. The organizing committee, however, did not allow her to run, and the newspaper ''Akropolis'' criticized the committee for its decision.Hungarian sport
historian Eva Fóldes, ''Women at the Olympics'', 105&ndash;114, gives a similar account of Melpomene's story. The Olympic Marathon took place on 10 April  1896, but another female runner, Stamata Revithi, took 5½ hours to run the course on 11 April  1896. The newspapers ''Asti'', ''New Aristophanes'' and ''Atlantida'' reported this on 12 April  1896.Lennartz, ''Two Women Run the Marathon'', 20. For a similar account of events, see Jenkins, ''Sports Science Handbook '', 314; Lovett, ''Olympic Marathon'', ; Mallon & Widlund, ''The 1896 Olympic Games'', 14. Lucas (''A History of the Marathon Race'', 132) refers to "Melpomene" and her time (4½ hours) but not to Revithi.

However, Tarasouleas argues that no contemporary press reports in Greek newspapers mention Melpomene by name, while the name Revithi appears many times;Tarasouleas, ''Stamata Revithi, "Alias Melpomeni"'', 55. Martin & Gynn (''Running through the Ages'', 22) assert that the name "Melpomene" was described in foreign reports many years later (in 1927, when ''Der Leichtathlet'' revived the Messenger's report). Tarasouleas suggests that Melpomene and Revithi are the same person, and Martin and Green argue that "a contemporary account referring to Revithi as a well-known marathon runner could explain the earlier run by a woman over the marathon course&mdash;this was by Revithi herself, not Melpomene".Martin & Gynn, ''Running through the Ages'', 22; Tarasouleas, ''Stamata Revithi, "Alias Melpomeni"'', 55, quoting ''Estia'' of 4 April , and ''Asti'' of April 11 . The daily Athens newspaper ''Estia'' of 4 April  1896 refers to "the strange woman, who, having run a few days ago in the Marathon as a try-out, intends to compete the day after tomorrow. Today she came to our offices and said 'should my shoes hinder me, I will remove them on the way and continue barefoot'." Moreover, Tarasouleas notes that on 13 March  1896, another local newspaper indicated that a woman and her baby had registered to run the marathon, but again her name is not mentioned.  Trying to resolve the mystery, Tarasouleas asserts that "perhaps Revithi had two names, or perhaps for reasons unknown she was attributed the name of the Muse Melpomene".Tarasouleas, ''Stamata Revithi, "Alias Melpomeni"'', 54&ndash;55. Miragaya (''The Female Olympian'', 314) believes that after her marathon run, athletics officials could not remember Revithi's name so they labeled her "Melpomene", who is the Greek muse of tragedy. "Looking at Stamata Revithi, they could see only tragedy, not her extraordinary feat."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f49b0e3b72ae02ad1214a554c56ef6a4" name="Melpomene-Simmons-Highsmith-detail-1" sectnum="2#1">../img/f49b0e3b72ae02ad1214a554c56ef6a4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>