<document id="74562b4c13f60189655149467ec33d43-5" name="1984_Rajneeshee_bioterror_attack" cat="29">
<text>
''The Oregonian'' ran a 20-part series on Rajneesh's movement, beginning in June 1985, which included an investigation into the salmonella incident.  As a result of a follow-up investigation, ''The Oregonian'' learned that Leslie L. Zaitz, one of their investigative journalists, had been placed as number three on a top-ten hit list by Sheela's group.  Then-Oregon Attorney General Dave Frohnmayer commented on the poisoning incident and other acts perpetrated by the group, stating: "The Rajneeshees committed the most significant crimes of their kind in the history of the United States ... The largest single incident of fraudulent marriages, the most massive scheme of wiretapping and bugging, and the largest mass poisoning."  Looking back on the incident, Dr. Skeels stated, "We lost our innocence over this ... We really learned to be more suspicious ... The first significant biological attack on a U.S. community was not carried out by foreign terrorists smuggled into New York, but by legal residents of a U.S. community. The next time it happens it could be with more lethal agents ... We in public health are really not ready to deal with that."

The Rajneesh group is the only known organization to have cultured its own pathogen for terrorist purposes. Federal and state investigators requested that details of the incident not be published in the ''Journal of the American Medical Association'' (JAMA) for 12 years, for they feared a description of the events could spark copycat crimes, and ''JAMA'' complied.  No repeat attacks or hoaxes subsequently occurred, and a detailed account of the incident and investigation was published in ''JAMA'' in 1997.   A 1999 empirical analysis in the journal ''Emerging Infectious Diseases'' published by the CDC described six motivational factors associated with bioterrorism, including: charismatic leadership, no outside constituency, apocalyptic ideology, loner or splinter group, sense of paranoia and grandiosity, and defensive aggression.  According to the article, the "Rajneesh Cult" satisfied all motivational factors except for an "apocalyptic ideology".  An analysis in the book ''Cults, Religion and Violence'' disputes the link to charismatic leadership, pointing out that in this and other cases, it was organizational lieutenants who played a pivotal role in the initiation of violence.  Arguing for a contextual rather than decisive view of charisma, the authors state that the attribution of outcomes to the personality of a single individual, even a charismatic leader, usually camouflages a far more complex field of social relationships. 


The media revisited the incident during the 2001 anthrax attacks in the United States.  The 2001 publication of Judith Miller's ''Germs: Biological Weapons and America's Secret War'', which contained an analysis and detailed description of the events, also brought discussion of the incident back into the news.  Residents of The Dalles commented that they have an understanding of how bioterrorism can occur in the United States.  The incident had spread fear in the community, and drained the local economy.  All but one of the restaurants affected went out of business.  In 2005, the Oregon State Land Board agreed to sell  of Wasco County, including Rajneeshpuram, to the Colorado-based youth ministry Young Life.  On February 18, 2005, Court TV aired an episode of ''Forensic Files'' about the incident, entitled: "'Bio-Attack' – Oregon Cult Poisonings".  The salmonellosis outbreak was also discussed in the media within the context of the 2006 North American E. coli outbreak.

The book ''Emerging Infectious Diseases: Trends and Issues'' cites the 1984 Rajneeshee bioterror attack, along with the Aum Shinrikyo group's attempts to use anthrax and other agents, as exceptions to the belief "that only foreign-state supported groups have the resources to execute a credible bioterrorism event". According to ''Deadly Cultures: Biological Weapons Since 1945'', these are the only two confirmed uses of biological weapons for terrorist purposes to harm humans.  The incident was the single largest bioterrorist attack in United States history. In the chapter titled: "Influencing An Election: America's First Modern Bioterrorist Attack" in his 2006 book ''Terrorism on American Soil: A Concise History of Plots and Perpetrators from the Famous to the Forgotten'', author Joseph T. McCann concludes: "In every respect, the salmonella poisoning carried out by the cult members was a major bioterrorist attack that fortunately failed to achieve its ultimate goal and resulted in no fatalities."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1b0eabda826c6f24095b0401af87fac7" name="AntelopePlaque" sectnum="5#1">../img/1b0eabda826c6f24095b0401af87fac7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>