<document id="74625027de86d75fb7854b96140e90d8-17" name="Guadalcanal_Campaign" cat="29">
<text>
The Japanese continued to experience problems in delivering sufficient supplies to sustain their troops on Guadalcanal.  Attempts to use only submarines the last two weeks in November failed to provide sufficient food for Hyakutake's forces.  A separate attempt to establish bases in the central Solomons to facilitate barge convoys to Guadalcanal also failed because of destructive Allied air attacks.  On November 26, the 17th Army notified Imamura that it faced a critical food crisis.  Some front-line units had not been resupplied for six days and even the rear-area troops were on one-third rations.  The situation forced the Japanese to return to using destroyers to deliver the necessary supplies.Evans, p. 197–198, Crenshaw, p. 136, Frank, p. 499–502.


Eighth Fleet personnel devised a plan to help reduce the exposure of destroyers delivering supplies to Guadalcanal.  Large oil or gas drums were cleaned and filled with medical supplies and food, with enough air space to provide buoyancy, and strung together with rope.  When the destroyers arrived at Guadalcanal they would make a sharp turn and the drums would be cut loose and a swimmer or boat from shore could pick up the buoyed end of a rope and return it to the beach, where the soldiers could haul in the supplies.Hara, p. 160–161, Roscoe, p. 206, Dull, p. 262, Evans, p. 197–198, Crenshaw, p. 137, Toland, p. 419, Frank, p. 502, Morison, p. 295.

The Eighth Fleet's Guadalcanal Reinforcement Unit (the Tokyo Express), currently commanded by Raizo Tanaka, was tasked by Mikawa with making the first of five scheduled runs to Tassafaronga on Guadalcanal using the drum method on the night of November 30.  Tanaka's unit was centered around eight destroyers, with six destroyers assigned to carry between 200 to 240 drums of supplies apiece.Dull, p. 262–263, Evans, p. 198–199, Crenshaw, p. 137, Morison, p. 297, Frank, p. 502–504.  Notified by intelligence sources of the Japanese supply attempt, Halsey ordered the newly formed Task Force 67, comprising four cruisers and four destroyers under the command of U.S. Rear Admiral Carleton H. Wright, to intercept Tanaka's force off Guadalcanal.  Two additional destroyers joined Wright's force en route to Guadalcanal from Espiritu Santo during the day of November 30.Brown, p. 124–125, USSBS, p. 139, Roscoe, p. 206, Dull,p. 262, Crenshaw, p. 26–33, Kilpatrick, p. 139–142, Morison, p. 294–296, Frank, p. 504.

At 22:40 on November 30, Tanaka's force arrived off Guadalcanal and prepared to unload the supply barrels.  Meanwhile, Wright's warships were approaching through Ironbottom Sound from the opposite direction.  Wright's destroyers detected Tanaka's force on radar and the destroyer commander requested permission to attack with torpedoes.  Wright waited four minutes before giving permission, allowing Tanaka's force to escape from an optimum firing setup.  All of the American torpedoes missed their targets.  At the same time, Wright's cruisers opened fire, quickly hitting and destroying one of the Japanese guard destroyers.  The rest of Tanaka's warships abandoned the supply mission, increased speed, turned, and launched a total of 44 torpedoes in the direction of Wright's cruisers.Hara, p. 161–164, Dull, p. 265, Evans, p. 199–202, Crenshaw, p. 34, 63, 139–151, Morison, p. 297–305, Frank, p. 507–510.

The Japanese torpedoes hit and sank the U.S. cruiser ''Northampton'' and heavily damaged the cruisers ''Minneapolis'', ''New Orleans'', and ''Pensacola''.  The rest of Tanaka's destroyers escaped without damage, but failed to deliver any of the provisions to Guadalcanal.Dull, p. 265, Crenshaw, p. 56–66, Morison, p. 303–312, Frank, p. 510–515.

By December 7, 1942, Hyakutake's forces were losing about 50 men each day from malnutrition, disease, and Allied ground or air attacks.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 527.  Further attempts by Tanaka's force to deliver provisions on December 3, December 7, and December 11, failed to alleviate the crisis, and one of Tanaka's destroyers was sunk by a U.S. PT boat torpedo.Dull, p. 266–267; Evans, p. 203–205; Morison, p. 318–319; Frank, p. 518–521.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d06b89e3b6a08b760ab596418df1f60f" name="RaizoTanaka" sectnum="17#1">../img/d06b89e3b6a08b760ab596418df1f60f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>