<document id="74625027de86d75fb7854b96140e90d8-1" name="Guadalcanal_Campaign" cat="29">
<text>
On December 7, 1941, Japanese forces attacked the United States Pacific Fleet at Pearl Harbor, Hawaii. The attack crippled much of the U.S. battleship fleet and precipitated an open and formal state of war between the two nations. The initial goals of Japanese leaders were to neutralize the U.S. Navy, seize possessions rich in natural resources, and establish strategic military bases to defend Japan's empire in the Pacific and Asia. To further those goals, Japanese forces captured the Philippines, Thailand, Malaya, Singapore, the Dutch East Indies, Wake Island, Gilbert Islands, New Britain, and Guam. Joining the U.S. in the war against Japan were the rest of the Allied powers, several of whom, including Great Britain, Australia, and the Netherlands, had also been attacked by Japan.Murray, p. 169–195.


Two attempts by the Japanese to maintain the strategic initiative and extend their defensive perimeter in the south and central Pacific were thwarted at the naval battles of Coral Sea and Midway respectively. Midway was not only the Allies' first major victory against the previously undefeated Japanese, it significantly reduced the offensive capability of Japan's carrier forces. Up to this point, the Allies had been on the defensive in the Pacific, but these strategic victories provided them an opportunity to seize the strategic initiative from Japan.Murray, p. 196. 

The Allies chose the Solomon Islands (a protectorate of Great Britain), specifically the southern Solomon Islands of Guadalcanal, Tulagi, and Florida as the first target.Loxton, p. 3. The Japanese Navy (IJN) had occupied Tulagi in May 1942 and had constructed a seaplane base near there. Allied concern grew when, in early July 1942, the IJN began constructing a large airfield at Lunga Point on nearby Guadalcanal. By August 1942, the Japanese had about 900 naval troops on Tulagi and nearby islands, and 2,800 personnel (2,200 being Korean and Japanese construction specialists) on Guadalcanal. These bases, when completed, would protect Japan's major base at Rabaul, threaten Allied supply and communication lines, and establish a staging area for a planned offensive against Fiji, New Caledonia, and Samoa (Operation FS). The Japanese planned to deploy 45 fighters and 60 bombers to Guadalcanal once the airfield was complete.  These aircraft could provide air cover for Japanese naval forces advancing farther into the South Pacific.Alexander, p. 72, Frank, p. 23–31, 129, 628; Smith, p. 5; Bullard, p. 119, Lundstrom, p. 39, Bullard, p. 127.  The Japanese aircraft assigned to Guadalcanal were to come from the 26th Air Flotilla, then located at bases in the Central Pacific (Bullard).

The Allied plan to invade the southern Solomons was conceived by U.S. Admiral Ernest King, Commander in Chief, United States Fleet. He proposed the offensive to deny the use of the islands by the Japanese as bases to threaten the supply routes between the United States and Australia, and to use them as starting points. With Roosevelt's tacit consent, King also advocated the invasion of Guadalcanal. When U.S. Army General George C. Marshall resisted this line of action as well as who would command the operation, King stated that the Navy and Marines would carry out the operation by themselves, and instructed Admiral Chester Nimitz to proceed with the preliminary planning.  King eventually won the argument, and the invasion went ahead with the backing of the Joint Chiefs.


Guadalcanal would be carried out in conjunction with an Allied offensive in New Guinea under Douglas MacArthur, to capture the Admiralty Islands and the Bismarck Archipelago, including the major Japanese base at Rabaul. The eventual goal was the American reconquest of the Philippines.Morison, p. 12, Frank, p. 15–16, Miller, ''Cartwheel'', p. 5. The U.S. Joint Chiefs of Staff created the South Pacific theater, with Vice Admiral Robert L. Ghormley taking command on June 19, 1942, to direct the offensive in the Solomons.  Admiral Chester Nimitz, based at Pearl Harbor, was designated as overall Allied commander in chief for Pacific forces.Murray, p. 199–200; Jersey, p. 85; and Lundstrom, p. 5. 


In preparation for the future offensive in the Pacific in May 1942, U.S. Marine Major General Alexander Vandegrift was ordered to move his 1st Marine Division from the United States to New Zealand. Other Allied land, naval, and air force units were sent to establish bases in Fiji, Samoa, New Hebrides, and New Caledonia.Loxton, p. 5; and Miller, p. 11. Espiritu Santo, New Hebrides, was selected as the headquarters and main base for the offensive, codenamed ''Operation Watchtower'', with the commencement date set for August 7, 1942. At first, the Allied offensive was planned just for Tulagi and the Santa Cruz Islands, omitting Guadalcanal. However, after Allied reconnaissance discovered the Japanese airfield construction efforts on Guadalcanal, its capture was added to the plan, and the Santa Cruz operation was (eventually) dropped.Frank, p. 35–37, 53.  The Japanese were aware, via signals intelligence, of the large-scale movement of Allied assets in the South Pacific area, but concluded that the Allies were reinforcing Australia and perhaps Port Moresby in New Guinea.Bullard, p. 122.

The ''Watchtower'' force, numbering 75 warships and transports (including vessels from both the U.S. and Australia), assembled near Fiji on July 26, 1942, and engaged in one rehearsal landing prior to leaving for Guadalcanal on July 31.Morison, p. 15; and McGee, p. 20–21. The on-scene commander of the Allied expeditionary force was U.S. Vice Admiral Frank Fletcher (flag in aircraft carrier USS ''Saratoga''). Commanding the amphibious forces was U.S. Rear Admiral Richmond K. Turner. Vandegrift led the 16,000 Allied (primarily U.S. Marine) infantry earmarked for the landings.Frank, p. 57, 619–621.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="617c66b68c58077208ab7c6d8b807302" name="Pacific_Theater_Areas;map1" sectnum="1#1">../img/617c66b68c58077208ab7c6d8b807302.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>