<document id="74625027de86d75fb7854b96140e90d8-2" name="Guadalcanal_Campaign" cat="29">
<text>
Bad weather allowed the Allied expeditionary force to arrive in the vicinity of Guadalcanal unseen by the Japanese on the morning of August 7.McGee, p. 21, Bullard, pp. 125–126.  Several patrol aircraft from Tulagi searched the very area where the Allied invasion convoy was moving, but missed seeing the Allied ships because of severe storms and heavy clouds (Bullard).  The landing force split into two groups, with one group assaulting Guadalcanal, and the other Tulagi, Florida, and nearby islands.Frank, p. 60; Jersey, p. 95.  The landing force, designated Task Force 62, included six heavy cruisers, two light cruisers, 15 destroyers, 13 transports, six cargo ships, four destroyer transports, and five minesweepers.  Allied warships bombarded the invasion beaches while U.S. carrier aircraft bombed Japanese positions on the target islands and destroyed 15 Japanese seaplanes at their base near Tulagi.Hammel, p. 46–47; and Lundstrom, p. 38.

Tulagi and two nearby small islands, Gavutu and Tanambogo, were assaulted by 3,000 U.S. Marines.Frank, p. 51. The 886 IJN personnel manning the naval and seaplane bases on the three islands fiercely resisted the Marine attacks.Frank, p. 50.  The IJN personnel included Japanese and Korean construction specialists as well as trained combat troops.  With some difficulty, the Marines secured all three islands; Tulagi on August 8, and Gavutu and Tanambogo by August 9.Shaw, p. 8–9; and McGee, p. 32–34.  The Japanese defenders were killed almost to the last man, while the Marines suffered 122 killed.Frank, p. 79. Approximately 80 Japanese personnel escaped to Florida Island, where they were found and killed by Marine patrols over the next two months. 

In contrast to Tulagi, Gavutu, and Tanambogo, the landings on Guadalcanal encountered much less resistance. At 09:10 on August 7, Vandegrift and 11,000 U.S. Marines came ashore on Guadalcanal between Koli Point and Lunga Point. Advancing towards Lunga Point, they encountered no resistance except for "tangled" rain forest, and they halted for the night about  from the Lunga Point airfield. The next day, again against little resistance, the Marines advanced all the way to the Lunga River and secured the airfield by 16:00 on August 8. The Japanese naval construction units and combat troops, under the command of Captain Kanae Monzen, panicked by the warship bombardment and aerial bombing, had abandoned the airfield area and fled about  west to the Matanikau River and Point Cruz area, leaving behind food, supplies, intact construction equipment and vehicles, and 13 dead.Jersey, p. 113–115, 190, 350; Morison, p. 15; and Frank, p. 61–62 & 81.


During the landing operations on August 7 and August 8, Japanese naval aircraft based at Rabaul, under the command of Sadayoshi Yamada, attacked the Allied amphibious forces several times, setting afire the U.S. transport ''George F. Elliot'' (which sank two days later) and heavily damaging the destroyer USS ''Jarvis''.Loxton, p. 90–103. In the air attacks over the two days, the Japanese lost 36 aircraft, while the U.S. lost 19, both in combat and to accident, including 14 carrier fighters.Frank, p. 80.

After these clashes, Fletcher was concerned about the losses to his carrier fighter aircraft strength, anxious about the threat to his carriers from further Japanese air attacks, and worried about his ship's fuel levels.  Fletcher withdrew from the Solomon Islands area with his carrier task forces the evening of August 8.Hammel, p. 99; and Loxton, p. 104–5. Loxton, Frank (p. 94), and Morison (p. 28) contend Fletcher's fuel situation was not at all critical, but Fletcher implied it was in order to provide further justification for his withdrawal from the battle area. As a result of the loss of carrier-based air cover, Turner decided to withdraw his ships from Guadalcanal, even though less than half of the supplies and heavy equipment needed by the troops ashore had been unloaded.Hammel, p. 100. Turner planned, however, to unload as many supplies as possible on Guadalcanal and Tulagi throughout the night of August 8 and then depart with his ships early on August 9.Morison, p. 31.

That night, as the transports unloaded, two groups of screening Allied warships under the command of British Rear Admiral Victor Crutchley were surprised and defeated by a Japanese force of seven cruisers and one destroyer from the 8th Fleet, based at Rabaul and Kavieng and commanded by Japanese Vice Admiral Gunichi Mikawa. One Australian and three American cruisers were sunk, and one American cruiser and two destroyers were damaged in the Battle of Savo Island.  The Japanese suffered moderate damage to one cruiser.  Mikawa, who was unaware Fletcher had withdrawn with the U.S. carriers, immediately retired to Rabaul without attempting to attack the now unprotected transports. Mikawa was concerned about daylight U.S. carrier air attacks if he remained in the area.  Turner withdrew all remaining Allied naval forces by the evening of August 9, leaving the Marines ashore without much of the heavy equipment, provisions, and troops still aboard the transports.  However, Mikawa's decision not to attack the Allied transport ships when he had the opportunity would prove to be a crucial strategic mistake.Morison, p. 19–59.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c36dfa1d5f170287449310cc0f3a31cb" name="GuadLandingsLunga" sectnum="2#1">../img/c36dfa1d5f170287449310cc0f3a31cb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>