<document id="74625027de86d75fb7854b96140e90d8-21.1" name="Guadalcanal_Campaign" cat="29">
<text>
After the Japanese withdrawal, Guadalcanal and Tulagi were developed into major bases supporting the Allied advance further up the Solomon Islands chain.  In addition to Henderson Field, two additional fighter runways were constructed at Lunga Point and a bomber airfield was built at Koli Point.  Extensive naval port and logistics facilities were established at Guadalcanal, Tulagi, and Florida.  The anchorage around Tulagi became an important advanced base for Allied warships and transport ships supporting the Solomon Islands Campaign.  Major ground units were staged through large encampments and barracks on Guadalcanal before deployment further up the Solomons.U.S. Navy, ''Building the Navy's Bases in World War II'', p. 246–256.

After Guadalcanal the Japanese were clearly on the defensive in the Pacific. The constant pressure to reinforce Guadalcanal had weakened Japanese efforts in other theaters, contributing to a successful Australian and American counteroffensive in New Guinea which culminated in the capture of the key bases of Buna and Gona in early 1943.  The Allies had gained a strategic initiative which they never relinquished. In June, the Allies launched Operation Cartwheel, which, after modification in August, 1943, formalized the strategy of isolating Rabaul and cutting its sea lines of communication. The subsequent successful neutralization of Rabaul and the forces centered there facilitated the South West Pacific campaign under General Douglas MacArthur and Central Pacific island hopping campaign under Admiral Chester Nimitz, with both efforts successfully advancing toward Japan.  The remaining Japanese defenses in the South Pacific area were then either destroyed or bypassed by Allied forces as the war progressed to its ultimate conclusion.Hough, p. 374, Zimmerman, p. 166.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1fcbb5a68eb924c3401f6fd29945eb01" name="The_High_Command_Assembled_on_Guadalcanal_in_1943" sectnum="21.1#1">../img/1fcbb5a68eb924c3401f6fd29945eb01.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>