<document id="74625027de86d75fb7854b96140e90d8-20" name="Guadalcanal_Campaign" cat="29">
<text>
On January 14, a Tokyo Express run delivered a battalion of troops to act as a rear guard for the ''Ke'' evacuation.  A staff officer from Rabaul accompanied the troops to notify Hyakutake of the decision to withdraw.  At the same time, Japanese warships and aircraft moved into position around the Rabaul and Bougainville areas in preparation to execute the withdrawal operation.  Allied intelligence detected the Japanese movements, but misinterpreted them as preparations for another attempt to retake Henderson Field and Guadalcanal.Miller, p. 338, Frank, p. 540–560, Morison, p. 333–339, Rottman, p. 64, Griffith, p. 269–279, Jersey, p. 384–388, Hayashi, p. 64.

Patch, wary of what he thought to be an imminent Japanese offensive, committed only a relatively small portion of his troops to continue a slow-moving offensive against Hyakutake's forces.  On January 29, Halsey, acting on the same intelligence, sent a resupply convoy to Guadalcanal screened by a cruiser task force.  Sighting the cruiser task force, Japanese naval torpedo bombers attacked the task force that same evening and heavily damaged the U.S. cruiser ''Chicago''.  The next day, more torpedo aircraft attacked and sank ''Chicago''.  Halsey ordered the remainder of the task force to return to base and directed the rest of his naval forces to take station in the Coral Sea, south of Guadalcanal, to be ready to counter the perceived Japanese offensive.Hough, p. 367–368, Frank, p. 568-576, Miller, p. 319–342, Morison, p. 342–350.  After unloading their cargo, the U.S. transports evacuated the 2nd Marine Regiment from the island.  The 2nd Marines had been on Guadalcanal since the beginning of the campaign.

In the meantime, the Japanese 17th Army withdrew to the west coast of Guadalcanal while rear guard units checked the American offensive.  On the night of February 1, 20 destroyers from Mikawa's 8th Fleet under Shintaro Hashimoto successfully extracted 4,935 soldiers, mainly from the 38th Division, from the island.  The Japanese and the Americans each lost a destroyer from air and naval attacks related to the evacuation mission.Frank, p. 582–588, 757–758, Jersey, p. 376–378, Morison, p. 364–368, Miller, p. 343–345, Zimmerman, p. 162, Dull, p. 268.

On the nights of February 4 and 7, Hashimoto and his destroyers completed the evacuation of most of the remaining Japanese forces from Guadalcanal.  Apart from some air attacks, Allied forces, still anticipating a large Japanese offensive, did not attempt to interdict Hashimoto's evacuation runs.  In total, the Japanese successfully evacuated 10,652 men from Guadalcanal.  On February 9, Patch realized that the Japanese were gone and declared Guadalcanal secure for Allied forces, ending the campaign.Frank, p. 589–597, Jersey, p. 378–383, 383, 400–401, Miller p. 342–348.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c38f383f3cafc7fe0e0c08f52ba9a289" name="USS_Chicago_after_Rennell_Island" sectnum="20#1">../img/c38f383f3cafc7fe0e0c08f52ba9a289.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>