<document id="74feb790232e5a7d88fb3caf293672f2-6" name="Chetwynd,_British_Columbia" cat="11">
<text>
The John Hart Highway portion of Highway 97 runs east-west through Chetwynd, connecting the town to Dawson Creek (102 km (67 mi) east) and Prince George (304 km (185 mi) south). Highway 29 (Don Philips Way) runs north-south through Chetwynd, connecting the town to Hudson’s Hope (60 km (34 mi) north) and Tumbler Ridge (89 km (47 mi) southeast). The downtown core lies just west of the intersection of Highway 97 and Highway 29. Chetwynd's internal street network has 28 km (17 mi) of paved road which uses the highway as its main arterial road with parallel frontage roads for local trips. A site plan by the province in 1957 laid out the basic structure of the town. The residential areas are separated from the industry and the highway by the use of natural features, such as contours or creeks, and vegetative buffers.


Chetwynd has rail, air, and bus service for regional and provincial transportation needs. Rail lines enter Chetwynd from three directions: from Fort St. John in the north, from Dawson Creek in the east, and from Prince George in the south. Pacific Great Eastern Railway (later BC Rail) ran passenger service to Chetwynd until 1990. Since then the trains have been used solely for moving resources such as lumber and coal. The District of Chetwynd has operated the unmanned Chetwynd Municipal Airport  since 1970. The runway was paved in 1975 but only handles chartered flights and helicopters. A new airport terminal is expected to open in the spring of 2008, constructed by students at Northern Lights College. The closest airports with commercial airlines are at Fort St. John and Dawson Creek. Greyhound Bus Lines maintain a bus stop in town on their Vancouver-Prince George-Dawson Creek route.

The District uses the northeast-flowing Pine River as both a source of drinking water and an outlet for sewage. The former comes from an intake pipe southwest of town. Its sewerage consists of 28 kilometres (17 mi) of sanitary sewers and 3 kilometres (2 mi) of storm sewers. Raw sewage is processed by a five-cell lagoon system and released into the Pine River south of town. The water supply was briefly shut off in 2000 when oil pipeline along the Pine River ruptured spilling 6200 bbl of oil into the river. Electricity is supplied by BC Hydro from the Bennett and Peace Canyon Dams and natural gas by Pacific Northern Gas.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4d931b4df89b6f492e76c66b8cab98ad" name="Chetwynd_BC_Highway_97" sectnum="6#1">../img/4d931b4df89b6f492e76c66b8cab98ad.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>