<document id="74feb790232e5a7d88fb3caf293672f2-9" name="Chetwynd,_British_Columbia" cat="11">
<text>
The District of Chetwynd's council-manager form of municipal government is headed by a mayor (who represents Chetwynd on the Peace River Regional District's governing board) and a six-member council. These positions, plus two school board trustees, are subject to at-large elections every three years. The current mayor, Evan Saugstad, was first elected in 2003, and re-elected by acclamation in 2005. The city funds a volunteer fire department, which services the town and nearby rural communities. The city maintains the sewer, water, local road, sidewalk, street lighting, animal control, building inspection, park, and recreation services.

The province staffs a government agent office in Chetwynd for access to licenses, permits, and government programs. Through the Northern Health Authority the province operates the five-bed Chetwynd General Hospital. As part of the Peace River South provincial electoral district, it is represented by Blair Lekstrom in the Legislative Assembly of British Columbia. In the 2001 provincial election, he was first elected as Member of the Legislative Assembly with 69% support from Chetwynd polls and re-elected in 2005 with 54% support. Before Lekstrom, Peace River South was represented, between 1986 and 2001, by Jack Weisgerber, a member of the Social Credit Party of British Columbia (1986–1994) and Reform Party of British Columbia (1994–2001). In 1996 as leader of the Reform Party, Weisgerber won re-election despite placing second in the Chetwynd polls to the BC Liberal Party candidate.

Federally, Chetwynd is in the Prince George—Peace River riding, represented in the Canadian House of Commons by Conservative Party Member of Parliament Jay Hill. The closest federal Service Canada office is in Dawson Creek, and Hill's constituency office is in Fort St. John. Before Hill, who was first elected in 1993, the riding was represented by former Chetwynd mayor Frank Oberle of the Progressive Conservative Party. Oberle was elected Chetwynd's mayor in 1968 and its MP in 1972. He became Canada's first German-born minister when he was appointed Minister of Science and Technology in 1985. He also served as Canada's Minister of Forestry in 1989.



| style="width: 150px" |Conservative
| style="width: 90px" |Jay Hill
|align="right"|621
|style="width: 65px" align="right"|61%
|style="width: 65px" align="right"|60%

|NDP
|Malcolm Crockett
|align="right"|179
|align="right"|18%
|align="right"|17%

|Liberal
|Nathan Bauder
|align="right"|144
|align="right"|14%
|align="right"|16%

|Green
|Hilary Crowley
|align="right"|56
|align="right"|5.5%
|align="right"|6.4%

|Independent
|Donna Young
|align="right"|21
|align="right"|2.1%
|align="right"|0.9%

|}


| style="width: 95px" |BC Liberal
| style="width: 120px"|Blair Lekstrom
|align="right"|446
|style="width: 65px" align="right"|54%
|style="width: 65px" align="right"|58%

|NDP
|Pat Shaw
|align="right"|310
|align="right"|37%
|align="right"|33%

|Green
|Ariel Lade
|align="right"|73
|align="right"|8.8%
|align="right"|9.5%

|}
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f2bae101a122823531826dab0b93c40d" name="ChetwyndMunicipalHall" sectnum="9#1">../img/f2bae101a122823531826dab0b93c40d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>