<document id="75147d5121ba793420f1ddfa6aa50d8b-5.8" name="The_Bartered_Bride" cat="20">
<text>
In the years after its first performance the dearth of available Czech operas meant that ''The Bartered Bride'' reappeared in the Provisional Theatre's repertory at regular intervals. Smetana revived it in October 1866, as part of his first season as the theatre's principal conductor. He brought it back again in January 1869 after revision, and again in the summer of that year, by which time it had had been restructured into three acts. Its metamorphosis was complete by September 1870, when Smetana presented the opera in its definitive version, with all spoken dialogue replaced by recitative.

In February 1869 Smetana had the text translated into French, and sent the libretto and score to the Paris Opera with a business proposal for dividing the profits. The management of the Paris Opera did not respond.Large, pp. 168–69 The opera was first performed outside its native land  on 11 January 1871, when Eduard Nápravnik, conductor of the Russian Imperial Opera, gave  a performance at the Mariinsky Theatre in St Petersburg. The work attracted mediocre notices from the critics, one of whom compared the work unfavourably to the Offenbach genre. Smetana was hurt by this remark, which he felt downgraded his opera to operetta status,Large, p. 171 and was convinced that press hostility had been generated by a former adversary, the Russian composer Mily Balakirev. The pair had clashed some years earlier, over the Provisional Theatre's  stagings of Glinka's ''A Life for the Tsar'' and ''Ruslan and Ludmilla''.  Smetana believed that Balakirev had used the Russian premiere of ''The Bartered Bride'' as a means of exacting revenge.Large, p. 210

''The Bartered Bride'' was not performed abroad again until after Smetana's death in 1884.  It was staged by the Prague National Theatre company in Vienna, as part of the Vienna Music and Theatre Exhibition of 1892, where its  favourable reception was the beginning of its worldwide popularity among opera audiences. Since the Czech language was not widely spoken, international performances tended to be in German.  The United States premiere took place at the Haymarket Theatre, Chicago, on 20 August, 1893.  The opera was introduced to Germany in 1894 by Gustav Mahler, then serving as Director of the Hamburg State Opera;Hefling, pp. 111–12 a year later a German company brought a production to the Theatre Royal, Drury Lane in London.Newmarch, pp. 67–68 In 1897, after his appointment as Director of the Vienna State Opera, Mahler brought ''The Bartered Bride'' into the company's repertory, and conducted regular performances of the work between 1899 and 1907. Mahler's enthusiasm for the work was such that he had incorporated a quote from the overture into the final movement of his First Symphony (1888). When he became Director of the Metropolitan Opera in New York in 1907 he added the opera to its repertory. The New York premiere, again in German, took place on 19 February 1909, and was warmly received. The ''New York Times'' commented on the excellence of the staging and musical characterisations, and paid particular tribute to "Mr. Mahler", whose master hand was in evidence throughout. Mahler chose to play the overture between Acts I and II, so that latecomers might hear it. PDF format
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4be2caee4dffd35c5d823728257702e2" name="Metropolitan_opera_1905" sectnum="5.8#1">../img/4be2caee4dffd35c5d823728257702e2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>