<document id="756ea971c47ff2c6f7409444fcec1c09-5.10.8" name="History_of_biology" cat="3">
<text>
By the 1980s, protein sequencing had already transformed methods of scientific classification of organisms (especially cladistics) but biologists soon began to use RNA and DNA sequences as characters; this expanded the significance of molecular evolution within evolutionary biology, as the results of molecular systematics could be compared with traditional evolutionary trees based on morphology. Following the pioneering ideas of Lynn Margulis on endosymbiotic theory, which holds that some of the organelles of eukaryotic cells originated from free living prokaryotic organisms through symbiotic relationships, even the overall division of the tree of life was revised. Into the 1990s, the five domains (Plants, Animals, Fungi, Protists, and Monerans) became three (the Archaea, the Bacteria, and the Eukarya) based on Carl Woese's pioneering molecular systematics work with 16S rRNA sequencing.Sapp, ''Genesis'', chapters 18 and 19

The development and popularization of the polymerase chain reaction (PCR) in mid 1980s (by Kary Mullis and others at Cetus Corp.) marked another watershed in the history of modern biotechnology, greatly increasing the ease and speed of genetic analysis. Coupled with the use of expressed sequence tags, PCR led to the discovery of many more genes than could be found through traditional biochemical or genetic methods and opened the possibility of sequencing entire genomes.Morange, ''A History of Molecular Biology'', chapter 20; see also: Rabinow, ''Making PCR''

The unity of much of the morphogenesis of organisms from fertilized egg to adult began to be unraveled after the discovery of the homeobox genes, first in fruit flies, then in other insects and animals, including humans. These developments led to advances in the field of evolutionary developmental biology towards understanding how the various body plans of the animal phyla have evolved and how they are related to one another.Gould, ''The Structure of Evolutionary Theory'', chapter 10

The Human Genome Project—the largest, most costly single biological study ever undertaken—began in 1988 under the leadership of James D. Watson, after preliminary work with genetically simpler model organisms such as ''E. coli'', ''S. cerevisiae'' and ''C. elegans''. Shotgun sequencing and gene discovery methods pioneered by Craig Venter—and fueled by the financial promise of gene patents with Celera Genomics— led to a public–private sequencing competition that ended in compromise with the first draft of the human DNA sequence announced in 2000.Davies, ''Cracking the Genome'', Introduction; see also: Sulston, ''The Common Thread''
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7587dbfb269122ef2d20447c0e530317" name="Cycler" sectnum="5.10.8#1">../img/7587dbfb269122ef2d20447c0e530317.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>