<document id="756ea971c47ff2c6f7409444fcec1c09-4.5.2" name="History_of_biology" cat="3">
<text>
The most significant evolutionary theory before Darwin's was that of Jean-Baptiste Lamarck; based on the inheritance of acquired characteristics (an inheritance mechanism that was widely accepted until the 20th century), it described a chain of development stretching from the lowliest microbe to humans.Mayr, ''The Growth of Biological Thought'', pp 343–357 The British naturalist Charles Darwin, combining the biogeographical approach of Humboldt, the uniformitarian geology of Lyell, Thomas Malthus's writings on population growth, and his own morphological expertise, created a more successful evolutionary theory based on natural selection; similar evidence led Alfred Russel Wallace to independently reach the same conclusions.Mayr, ''The Growth of Biological Thought'', chapter 10: "Darwin's evidence for evolution and common descent"; and chapter 11: "The causation of evolution: natural selection"; Larson, ''Evolution'', chapter 3

The 1859 publication of Darwin's theory in ''On the Origin of Species by Means of Natural Selection, or the Preservation of Favoured Races in the Struggle for Life'' is often considered the central event in the history of modern biology. Darwin's established credibility as a naturalist, the sober tone of the work, and most of all the sheer strength and volume of evidence presented, allowed ''Origin'' to succeed where previous evolutionary works such as the anonymous ''Vestiges of Creation'' had failed. Most scientists were convinced of evolution and common descent by the end of the 19th century. However, natural selection would not be accepted as the primary mechanism of evolution until well into the 20th century, as most contemporary theories of heredity seemed incompatible with the inheritance of random variation.Larson, ''Evolution'', chapter 5: "Ascent of Evolutionism"; see also: Bowler, ''The Eclipse of Darwinism''; Secord, ''Victorian Sensation''

Wallace, following on earlier work by de Candolle, Humbolt and Darwin, made major contributions to zoogeography. Because of his interest in the transmutation hypothesis, he paid particular attention to the geographical distribution of closely allied species during his field work first in South America and then in the Malay archipelago. While in the archipelago he identified the Wallace line, which runs through the Spice Islands dividing the fauna of the archipelago between an Asian zone and a New Guinea/Australian zone. His key question, as to why the fauna of islands with such similar climates should be so different, could only be answered by considering their origin. In 1876 he wrote ''The Geographical Distribution of Animals'', which was the standard reference work for over half a century, and a sequel, ''Island Life'', in 1880 that focused on island biogeography. He extended the six-zone system developed by Philip Sclater for describing the geographical distribution of birds to animals of all kinds. His method of tabulating data on animal groups in geographic zones highlighted the discontinuities; and his appreciation of evolution allowed him to propose rational explanations, which had not been done before. Larson, ''Evolution'', pp 72-73, 116–117; see also: Browne, ''The Secular Ark''. Bowler ''Evolution: The History of an Idea'' p. 174

The scientific study of heredity grew rapidly in the wake of Darwin's ''Origin of Species'' with the work of Francis Galton and the biometricians. The origin of genetics is usually traced to the 1866 work of the monk Gregor Mendel, who would later be credited with the laws of inheritance. However, his work was not recognized as significant until 35 years afterward. In the meantime, a variety of theories of inheritance (based on pangenesis, orthogenesis, or other mechanisms) were debated and investigated vigorously.Mayr, ''The Growth of Biological Thought'', pp 693–710 Embryology and ecology also became central biological fields, especially as linked to evolution and popularized in the work of Ernst Haeckel. Most of the 19th century work on heredity, however, was not in the realm of natural history, but that of experimental physiology.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e6b53e7bfb570533c30abb79ec622b4c" name="Darwins_first_tree" sectnum="4.5.2#1">../img/e6b53e7bfb570533c30abb79ec622b4c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>