<document id="756fe9011ebbc81c00d59fcd846ef2ca-0.2" name="Dinosaur" cat="3">
<text>
Under phylogenetic taxonomy, dinosaurs are usually defined as the group consisting of "''Triceratops'', Neornithes , their most recent common ancestor, and all descendants." It has also been suggested that Dinosauria be defined with respect to the most recent common ancestor of ''Megalosaurus'' and ''Iguanodon'', because these were two of the three genera cited by Richard Owen when he recognized the Dinosauria.Olshevsky, G. (2000). "An annotated checklist of dinosaur species by continent." ''Mesozoic Meanderings'', '''3''': 1–157 Both definitions result in the same set of animals being defined as dinosaurs, including theropods (mostly bipedal carnivores), sauropodomorphs (mostly large herbivorous quadrupeds with long necks and tails), ankylosaurians (armored herbivorous quadrupeds), stegosaurians (plated herbivorous quadrupeds), ceratopsians (herbivorous quadrupeds with horns and frills), and ornithopods (bipedal or quadrupedal herbivores including "duck-bills").  These definitions are written to correspond with scientific conceptions of dinosaurs that predate the modern use of phylogenetics. The continuity of meaning is intended to prevent confusion about what the term "dinosaur" means.

There is a wide consensus among paleontologists that birds are the descendants of theropod dinosaurs. Using the strict cladistical definition that all descendants of a single common ancestor must be included in a group for that group to be natural, birds would thus ''be'' dinosaurs and dinosaurs are, therefore, not extinct. Birds are classified by most paleontologists as belonging to the subgroup Maniraptora, which are coelurosaurs, which are theropods, which are saurischians, which are dinosaurs.Padian, K. (2004). Basal Avialae. In: Weishampel, D.B., Dodson, P., and Osmólska, H. (eds.). ''The Dinosauria'' (second edition). University of California Press:Berkeley, 210–231. ISBN 0-520-24209-2.

From the point of view of cladistics, birds are dinosaurs, but in ordinary speech the word "dinosaur" does not include birds. Additionally, referring to dinosaurs that are not birds as "non-avian dinosaurs" is cumbersome. For clarity, this article will use "dinosaur" as a synonym for "non-avian dinosaur". The term "non-avian dinosaur" will be used for emphasis as needed.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="12cffb52d307e3b0fe7cdea3f79fe378" name="Triceratops_AMNH_01" sectnum="0.2#1">../img/12cffb52d307e3b0fe7cdea3f79fe378.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>