<document id="756fe9011ebbc81c00d59fcd846ef2ca-0.3" name="Dinosaur" cat="3">
<text>
Using one of the above definitions, dinosaurs (aside from birds) can be generally described as terrestrial archosaurian reptiles with limbs held erect beneath the body, that existed from the Late Triassic (first appearing in the Carnian faunal stage)  to the Late Cretaceous (going extinct at the end of the Maastrichtian). Many prehistoric animals are popularly conceived of as dinosaurs, such as ichthyosaurs, mosasaurs, plesiosaurs, pterosaurs, and ''Dimetrodon'', but are not classified scientifically as dinosaurs. Marine reptiles like ichthyosaurs, mosasaurs, and plesiosaurs were neither terrestrial nor archosaurs; pterosaurs were archosaurs but not terrestrial; and ''Dimetrodon'' was a Permian animal more closely related to mammals. Dinosaurs were the dominant terrestrial vertebrates of the Mesozoic, especially the Jurassic and Cretaceous. Other groups of animals were restricted in size and niches; mammals, for example, rarely exceeded the size of a cat, and were generally rodent-sized carnivores of small prey. One notable exception is ''Repenomamus giganticus'', a triconodont weighing between  and  that is known to have eaten small dinosaurs like young ''Psittacosaurus''.

Dinosaurs were an extremely varied group of animals; according to a 2006 study, over 500 dinosaur genera have been identified with certainty so far, and the total number of genera preserved in the fossil record has been estimated at around 1850, nearly 75% of which remain to be discovered. An earlier study predicted that about 3400 dinosaur genera existed, including many which would not have been preserved in the fossil record. As of September 17, 2008, 1047 different species of dinosaurs have been named. Some were herbivorous, others carnivorous. Some dinosaurs were bipeds, some were quadrupeds, and others, such as ''Ammosaurus'' and ''Iguanodon'', could walk just as easily on two or four legs. Many had bony armor, or cranial  modifications like horns and crests. Although known for large size, many dinosaurs were human-sized or smaller. Dinosaur remains have been found on every continent on Earth, including Antarctica. No dinosaurs are known to have lived in marine or aerial habitats, although it is possible some feathered theropods were flyers.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="62ebe15e4c24c0d4a9964baab854d97b" name="Stegosaurus_at_the_Field_Museum" sectnum="0.3#1">../img/62ebe15e4c24c0d4a9964baab854d97b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>