<document id="75b5ede80779dc02004d7fb3083ad2ea-9.8" name="Imperial_Japanese_Navy" cat="29">
<text>
Japan continued to attribute considerable prestige to battleships and endeavoured to build the largest and most powerful ships of the period. , the largest and most heavily-armed battleship in history, was launched in 1941.

The second half of World War II saw the last battleship duels. In the Battle of Guadalcanal on 15 November 1942, the U.S. battleships  and  fought and destroyed the Japanese battlecruiser , but only after ''South Dakota'' had sustained heavy damage. In the Battle of Leyte Gulf on 25 October 1944 six battleships, led by Rear Admiral Jesse Oldendorf of the U.S. 7th Fleet fired upon and claimed credit for sinking Vice Admiral Shoji Nishimura's battleships  and  during the Battle of Surigao Strait; in fact, both battleships were fatally crippled by destroyer attacks before being brought under fire by Oldendorf's old battleships.

Nevertheless, the Battle off Samar on 25 October 1944 during the Battle of Leyte Gulf showed battleships could still be useful. Only the indecision of Vice Admiral Takeo Kurita and the fight by American destroyers and destroyer escorts saved the American escort carriers of "Taffy 3" from destruction by the gunfire of ''Yamato'', ''Kongō'', ''Haruna'', and ''Nagato'' and their cruiser escort. Miraculously for the Americans, only one escort carrier, two destroyers, and one destroyer escort were lost in this action.

Ultimately, the maturity of air power spelled doom for the battleship. Battleships in the Pacific ended up primarily performing shore bombardment and anti-aircraft defense for the carriers. ''Yamato'' and  were sunk by air attacks long before coming in gun range of the American fleet. As a result of the changing technology, plans for even larger battleships, such as the Japanese Super Yamato class battleship, were cancelled.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e8029e2e56cd21914123c2291b071939" name="Yamatotrials" sectnum="9.8#1">../img/e8029e2e56cd21914123c2291b071939.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>