<document id="75c3c4d04cdf63f677758a7637e65be1-8" name="Tulsa,_Oklahoma" cat="11">
<text>
As of the census of 2006, there were 382,872 people, 165,743 households, and 99,114 families residing in the city, with a population density of 830.9/km² (2,152.0/sq mi). There were 179,405 housing units at an average density of 982.3/sq mi (379.2/km²). Of 165,743 households, 28.5% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 43.1% were married couples living together, 12.9% had a female householder with no husband present, and 40.2% were non-families. Of all households, 33.9% are made up of only one person, and 9.8% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.31 people and the average family size was 2.98. 

In the city proper, the age distribution was 24.8% of the population under the age of 18, 10.9% from 18 to 24, 29.9% from 25 to 44, 21.5% from 45 to 64, and 12.9% who were 65 years of age or older, while the median age was 34 years. For every 100 females there were 93.5 males, while for every 100 females over the age of 17 there were 90.4 males. The median income for a household in the city was $35,316, and the median income for a family was $44,518. Males had a median income of $32,779 versus $25,587 for females, and the per capita income for the city was $21,534. About 10.9% of families and 14.1% of the population were below the poverty line, including 20.5% of those under age 18 and 8.3% of those age 65 or over. In 2006, the racial makeup of the city was 70.09% white, 15.47% African American, 4.72% Native American, 1.82% Asian, 0.05% Pacific Islander, 3.45% from other races, and 4.40% from two or more races. Hispanics or Latinos of any race formed at least 7.15% of the population with possibly more unregistered persons living within the city.

Religiously, Tulsa is overwhelmingly Protestant. The city is located in a geographic strip of high church attendance and widespread beliefs in biblical Christianity often called the "Bible Belt", and its history as a hub for televangelists such as Oral Roberts along with a predominance of Christian beliefs and values often lead Tulsa to be considered the "buckle of the Bible Belt." In 2000, the metropolitan area of Tulsa had 364,533 Protestant Christians, including 166,550 Southern Baptists and 78,221 Methodists. Meanwhile, the area had 43,854 Catholics, 2,650 Jews, 2,200 Muslims, and 1,590 Unitarian-Universalists, which includes the largest Unitarian Universalist one-church congregation in the world.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="47242cd5e9eb0046044f9b129ea27c3c" name="Prayer_Tower_on_the_campus_of_Oral_Roberts_University" sectnum="8#1">../img/47242cd5e9eb0046044f9b129ea27c3c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>