<document id="75c3c4d04cdf63f677758a7637e65be1-4.5" name="Tulsa,_Oklahoma" cat="11">
<text>
Downtown Tulsa is an area of approximately  surrounded by an inner-dispersal loop created by Interstate 244, Highway 64, and Highway 75. The area serves as Tulsa's financial and business district, and is the topic of a large initiative to draw tourism, which includes plans to capitalize on the area's historic architecture. Much of Tulsa's convention space is located in downtown, such as the Tulsa Performing Arts Center and the Tulsa Convention Center, and beginning in 2008, the BOK Center. Prominent downtown sub-districts include the Blue Dome District, the Brady Arts district, and the Greenwood Historical District, the site of ONEOK Field, a new baseball stadium for the Tulsa Drillers, now under construction with a scheduled opening in 2010.


The city's historical residential core lies in an area known as Midtown, containing upscale neighborhoods built in the early 1900s with architecture ranging from art deco to Greek Revival. The University of Tulsa, the Swan Lake neighborhood, Philbrook Museum, and the upscale shopping districts of Utica Square, Cherry Street, and Brookside are located in this region. A large portion of the city's southern half was developed since the 1970s, containing low density housing and retail developments. This region, marked by secluded homes and suburban neighborhoods, contains one of the state's largest shopping malls, Woodland Hills Mall, as well as Southern Hills Country Club and Oral Roberts University.
East of Highway 169, a diverse racial makeup marks the eastern portions of the city, with large Asian and Mexican communities and much of the city's manufacturing industry.

Areas of Tulsa west of the Arkansas River are called West Tulsa, and are marked by large parks, wilderness reserves, and large oil refineries. The northern tier of the city is home to a large percentage of Tulsa's African-American community. Included in the region is OSU-Tulsa, the Gilcrease Museum, the Tulsa International Airport, the Tulsa Zoo, the Tulsa Air and Space Museum, and the nation's third-largest municipal park, Mohawk Park.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="75c3c4d04cdf63f677758a7637e65be1" name="Tulsa,_Oklahoma" sectnum="4.5#1">../img/75c3c4d04cdf63f677758a7637e65be1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>