<document id="75d3c3b4ddd19d9091e606fae5be444b-5" name="Albert,_Prince_Consort" cat="25">
<text>
In 1852, a timely legacy to the Royal Family made it possible for Albert to obtain the freehold of Balmoral, and as usual he embarked on an extensive program of improvements.Hobhouse, p. 145 The same year, he was appointed to several of the offices left vacant by the death of the Duke of Wellington, including the mastership of Trinity House and the colonelcy of the Grenadier Guards.Weintraub, pp. 270–274 and 281–282 With Wellington out of the way, Albert was able to propose and campaign for modernisation of the army, which was long overdue.Hobhouse, pp. 42–43, 47–50 and Weintraub, pp. 274–276 Thinking that the military was unready for war, and that Christian rule was preferable to Islamic rule, Albert counselled a diplomatic solution to conflict between the Russian and Ottoman empires. Palmerston was more bellicose, and favoured a policy which would prevent further Russian expansion.e.g. Fulford, pp. 128, 153–157 Palmerston was manoeuvred out of the cabinet in December 1853, but at about the same time a Russian fleet attacked the Ottoman fleet at anchor at Sinop. The London press depicted the attack as a criminal massacre, and Palmerston's popularity surged as Albert's fell.Weintraub, pp. 288–293 Within two weeks, Palmerston was re-appointed as a minister. Absurd rumours circulated that Albert had been arrested for treason as public outrage at the Russian action continued.Fulford, pp. 156–157 and Weintraub, pp. 294–302 By March 1854, Britain and Russia were embroiled in the Crimean War. Early British optimism soon faded as the press reported that British troops were ill-equipped and mismanaged by aged generals using out-of-date tactics and strategy. The conflict dragged on as the Russians were as poorly prepared as their opponents. The Prime Minister, the Earl of Aberdeen, resigned and Palmerston succeeded him.Weintraub, pp. 303–322, 328 A negotiated settlement eventually put an end to the war with the Treaty of Paris. During the war, Albert arranged to marry his fourteen-year-old daughter, Victoria, to Prince Frederick William of Prussia, though Albert delayed the marriage until Victoria was seventeen. Albert hoped that his daughter and son-in-law would be a liberalising influence in the enlarging Prussian state.Weintraub, pp. 326 and 330

Albert involved himself in promoting many public educational institutions. Chiefly at meetings in connection with these he spoke of the need for better schooling.Hobhouse, p. 63 A collection of his speeches was published in 1857. Recognised as a supporter of education and technological progress, he was invited to speak at scientific meetings, such as the memorable address he delivered as president of the British Association for the Advancement of Science when it met at Aberdeen in 1859.Darby and Smith, p. 84; Hobhouse, pp. 61–62 and Weintraub, p. 232 His espousal of science spawned opposition from the Church. His proposal of a knighthood for Charles Darwin, after the publication of ''On the Origin of Species'', was rejected.Weintraub, p. 232

Albert continued to devote himself to the education of his family and the management of the royal household.Fulford, pp. 71–105 and Hobhouse, pp. 26–43 His children's governess, Lady Lyttelton, thought him unusually kind and patient, and described him joining in family games with enthusiasm.Lady Lyttelton's journal quoted in Fulford, p. 95 and her correspondence quoted in Hobhouse, p. 29 He felt keenly the departure of his eldest daughter for Prussia when she married her fiancé at the beginning of 1858,Fulford, p. 252 and Weintraub, p. 355 but he was disappointed that his eldest son, the Prince of Wales, did not respond well to the intense educational programme that Albert designed for him.Fulford, pp. 253–257 and Weintraub, p. 367 At the age of seven, the Prince of Wales was expected to take six hours of instruction, including an hour of German and an hour of French every day.Fulford, p. 255 When the Prince of Wales failed at his lessons, Albert caned him.Diary of Sir James Clark quoted in Fulford, p. 256 Corporal punishment was common at the time, and was not thought unduly harsh. Albert's biographer Roger Fulford wrote that the relationships between the family members were "friendly, affectionate and normal ... there is no evidence either in the Royal Archives or in the printed authorities to justify the belief that the relations between the Prince and his eldest son were other than deeply affectionate." Philip Magnus wrote in his biography of Albert's eldest son that Albert "tried to treat his children as equals; and they were able to penetrate his stiffness and reserve because they realised instinctively not only that he loved them but that he enjoyed and needed their company."Magnus, Philip (1964) ''King Edward VII'', pp. 19–20, quoted in Hobhouse, pp. 28–29
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="082970aa5254819fc35f80ed6f0bf461" name="Albert_of_Saxe-Coburg-Gotha" sectnum="5#1">../img/082970aa5254819fc35f80ed6f0bf461.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>