<document id="75d3c3b4ddd19d9091e606fae5be444b-2" name="Albert,_Prince_Consort" cat="25">
<text>
By 1836, the idea of marriage between Albert and his cousin, Victoria, had arisen in the mind of their ambitious uncle, Leopold, who had been King of the Belgians since 1831.Hobhouse, pp. 15–16 and Weintraub, pp. 43–49 At this time, Victoria was the heir to the British throne. Her father, Edward Augustus, Duke of Kent, the fourth son of King George III, had died when she was a baby, and her elderly uncle, William IV, was king. Her mother, the Duchess of Kent, Victoria of Saxe-Coburg-Saalfeld, was the sister of both Albert's father, the Duke of Saxe-Coburg and Gotha, and Leopold, King of the Belgians. Leopold arranged for his sister, Victoria's mother, to invite the Duke of Saxe-Coburg and Gotha and his two sons to visit her in May 1836, with the purpose of meeting Victoria. King William IV, however, disapproved of any match with the Coburgs, and instead favoured the suit of Prince Alexander, second son of William II of the Netherlands. Victoria was well-aware of the various matrimonial plans and critically appraised a parade of eligible princes.Weintraub, pp. 43–49 She wrote, " is extremely handsome; his hair is about the same colour as mine; his eyes are large and blue, and he has a beautiful nose and a very sweet mouth with fine teeth; but the charm of his countenance is his expression, which is most delightful."Victoria quoted in Weintraub, p. 49 Alexander, on the other hand, was "very plain".

Victoria wrote to her uncle Leopold to thank him "for the prospect of ''great'' happiness you have contributed to give me, in the person of dear Albert ... He possesses every quality that could be desired to render me perfectly happy."Weintraub, p. 51 Although the parties did not undertake a formal engagement, both the family and their retainers widely assumed that the match would take place.Weintraub, pp. 53, 58, 64, and 65

Victoria came to the throne aged just eighteen on 20 June 1837. Her letters of the time show interest in Albert's education for the role he would have to play, although she resisted attempts to rush her into marriage.Weintraub, p. 62 In the winter of 1838–39 the prince visited Italy, accompanied by the Coburg family's confidential adviser, Baron Stockmar.Hobhouse, pp. 17–18 and Weintraub, p. 67

Albert returned to England with Ernest in October 1839 to visit the Queen, with the object of settling the marriage.Fulford, p. 42 and Weintraub, pp. 77–81 Albert and Victoria felt mutual affection and the Queen proposed to him on 15 October 1839.Fulford, pp. 42–43; Hobhouse, p. 20 and Weintraub, pp. 77–81 Victoria's intention to marry was declared formally to the Privy Council on 23 November,Fulford, p. 45; Hobhouse, p. 21 and Weintraub, p. 86 and the couple married on 10 February 1840 at the Chapel Royal, St. James's Palace.Fulford, p. 52 and Hobhouse, p. 24 Just before the marriage, Albert was naturalised by Act of Parliament, and granted the style of ''Royal Highness'' by an Order-in-Council. At first, he was not popular with the British public. He was perceived to be from an impoverished and undistinguished minor state, barely larger than a small English county.Fulford, p. 45 The British Prime Minister, Lord Melbourne, advised the Queen against granting her husband the title of "King Consort". Parliament even refused to make Albert a peer, partly because of anti-German feeling and a desire to exclude Albert from any political role.Weintraub, p. 88 Melbourne led a minority government and the opposition took advantage of the marriage to weaken his position further. They opposed the ennoblement of Albert and granted him a smaller annuity than previous consorts,Weintraub, pp. 8–9 and 89 £30,000 instead of the usual £50,000.Fulford, p. 47 and Hobhouse, pp. 23–24 Albert claimed that he had no need of a British peerage; he wrote, "It would almost be step downwards, for as a Duke of Saxony, I feel myself much higher than as a Duke of York or Kent."Quoted in Jagow, Kurt (ed.) ''The Letters of the Prince Consort, 1831–61'' (London, 1938). For the next seventeen years Albert was formally titled "HRH Prince Albert" until, on 25 June 1857, Victoria formally granted him the title Prince Consort.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="74c41002f58dc84ff04085493a1e853c" name="Winterhalter_-_Queen_Victoria_1843" sectnum="2#1">../img/74c41002f58dc84ff04085493a1e853c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>