<document id="75d3c3b4ddd19d9091e606fae5be444b-6" name="Albert,_Prince_Consort" cat="25">
<text>
During a trip to Coburg in the autumn of 1860, Albert was driving alone in a carriage drawn by four horses which suddenly bolted. As the horses continued to gallop toward a stationary wagon waiting at a railway crossing, Albert jumped for his life from the carriage. One of the horses was killed in the collision, and Albert was badly shaken, though his only physical injuries were cuts and bruises. He told his brother and eldest daughter that he sensed his time had come.Weintraub, pp. 392–393

In 1861, Victoria's mother and Albert's aunt, the Duchess of Kent, died and Victoria was grief-stricken; Albert took on most of the Queen's duties, despite being ill himself with chronic stomach trouble.Hobhouse, pp. 150–151 and Weintraub, p. 401 Nevertheless, during the autumn of 1861 he stayed as busy as ever. In August, Victoria and Albert visited the Curragh Camp, Ireland, where the Prince of Wales was doing army service. It was there that the Prince of Wales was introduced, by his fellow officers, to Nellie Clifden, an Irish actress.Weintraub, p. 404

By November, Victoria and Albert had returned to Windsor, and the Prince of Wales had returned to Cambridge, where he was a student. Two of Albert's cousins, King Pedro V and Prince Ferdinand of Portugal, died of typhoid fever.Weintraub, p. 405 On top of this sad news, Albert was informed that gossip was spreading in gentlemen's clubs and the foreign press that the Prince of Wales was still involved with Nellie Clifden.Hobhouse, p. 152 and Weintraub, p. 406 Albert and Victoria were horrified by their son's indiscretion, and feared blackmail, scandal or pregnancy.Weintraub, p. 406 Although Albert was at a low ebb, and almost constantly ill, he travelled to Cambridge to see the Prince of WalesHobhouse, p. 154 and Fulford, p. 266 to discuss his indiscreet affair. When the Trent Affair—the forcible removal of Confederate envoys from a British ship by Union forces—threatened war between the United States and Britain, Albert was gravely ill, but intervened quietly to soften the British diplomatic response. Hobhouse, pp. 154–155; Martin, vol. V, pp. 418–426 and Weintraub, pp. 408–424 On 9 December, one of Albert's doctors, William Jenner, diagnosed typhoid fever. Congestion of the lungs supervened, and he died at 10:50 p.m. on 14 December 1861 in the Blue Room at Windsor Castle, in the presence of the Queen and five of their nine children.Darby and Smith, p. 3; Hobhouse, p. 156 and Weintraub, pp. 425–431Though the contemporary diagnosis was typhoid fever, modern writers have pointed out that Albert was ill for at least two years before his death, which may indicate that a chronic disease, such as renal failure or cancer, was the cause of death (see for example, Hobhouse, pp. 150–151).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="270df8800e36444e204c3db767e60b9a" name="Albert_of_Saxe-Coburg_and_Gotha_-_Project_Gutenberg_etext_13103" sectnum="6#1">../img/270df8800e36444e204c3db767e60b9a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>