<document id="75d3c3b4ddd19d9091e606fae5be444b-3" name="Albert,_Prince_Consort" cat="25">
<text>
The position in which the prince was placed by his marriage, while one of distinction, also offered considerable difficulties; in Albert's own words, "I am very happy and contented; but the difficulty in filling my place with the proper dignity is that I am only the husband, not the master in the house."Albert to William von Lowenstein, May 1840, quoted in Hobhouse, p. 26 The Queen's household was run by her former governess,Or more properly "Lady Attendant" Baroness Lehzen. Albert referred to her as the "House Dragon", and manoeuvred to dislodge the Baroness from her position.Fulford, pp. 59–74

Within two months of the marriage, Victoria was pregnant. Albert started to take on public roles; he became President of the Society for the Extinction of Slavery (slavery had been abolished throughout the British Empire already but was still lawful in places such as the United States and the colonies of France), and helped Victoria privately with her government paperwork.Weintraub, pp. 102–105 In June 1840, while on a public carriage ride, Albert and the pregnant Victoria were shot at by Edward Oxford, who was later judged insane. Neither was hurt and Albert was praised in the newspapers for his courage and coolness during the attack.Weintraub, pp. 106–107 Albert was gaining public support as well as political influence, which showed itself practically when, in August, Parliament passed the Regency Act 1840 to designate him Regent in the event of Victoria's death before their child reached the age of majority.Weintraub, p. 107 Their first child, Victoria, named after her mother, was born in November. Eight other children would follow over the next seventeen years. All nine children survived to adulthood, which biographer Hermione Hobhouse credited to Albert's "enlightened influence" on the healthy running of the nursery.Hobhouse, p. 28 In early 1841, he successfully removed the nursery from Lehzen's pervasive control, and in September 1842, Lehzen left England permanently, much to Albert's relief.Fulford, pp. 73–74

After the 1841 general election, Melbourne was replaced as Prime Minister by Sir Robert Peel, who appointed Albert as chairman of the Royal Commission in charge of redecorating the new Palace of Westminster. The Palace had burnt down seven years before, and was being rebuilt. As a patron and purchaser of pictures and sculpture, the commission was set up to promote the fine arts in Britain. The commission's work was slow, and the architect, Charles Barry, took many decisions out of the commissioner's hands by decorating rooms with ornate furnishings which were treated as part of the architecture.Ames, pp. 48–55; Fulford, pp. 212–213 and Hobhouse, pp. 82–88 Albert was more successful as a private patron and collector. Among his notable purchases were early German and Italian paintings, such as Lucas Cranach the Elder's ''Apollo and Diana'' and Fra Angelico's ''St. Peter Martyr'', and contemporary pieces from Franz Xaver Winterhalter and Edwin Landseer.Ames, pp. 132–146, 200–222 and Hobhouse, pp. 70–78. In 1863, the National Gallery, London received 25 paintings (, accessed 4 August 2009) "Presented by Queen Victoria at the Prince Consort's wish". See external links for works in the Royal Collection.

Albert and Victoria were shot at again on both 29 and 30 May 1842, but were unhurt. The culprit, John Francis, was detained and condemned to death, although he was later reprieved.Weintraub, pp. 134–135 Some of their early unpopularity came about because of their stiffness and adherence to protocol in public, though in private the couple were more easy-going.Ames, p. 172; Fulford, pp. 95–104 and Weintraub, p. 141 In early 1844, Victoria and Albert were apart for the first time since their marriage when he returned to Coburg on the death of his father.Ames, p. 60 and Weintraub, p. 154



By 1844, Albert had managed to modernise the royal finances and through various economies had sufficient capital to purchase Osborne House on the Isle of Wight as a private residence for their growing family.Fulford, p. 79; Hobhouse, p. 131 and Weintraub, p. 158 Over the next few years a house modelled in the style of an Italianate villa was built to the designs of Albert and Thomas Cubitt.Ames, pp. 61–71; Fulford, p. 79; Hobhouse, p. 121 and Weintraub, p. 181 Albert laid out the grounds, and improved the estate and farm.Hobhouse, pp. 127, 131 Albert managed and improved the other royal estates; his model farm at Windsor was admired by his biographers,Fulford, pp. 88–89 and Hobhouse, pp. 121–127 and under his stewardship the revenues of the Duchy of Cornwall, the hereditary property of the Prince of Wales, steadily multiplied.Weintraub, Stanley (September 2004; online edition January 2008). . ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography'', Oxford University Press. Accessed 4 August 2009 (Subscription required)

Unlike many landowners who approved of child labour and opposed Peel's repeal of the Corn Laws, Albert supported moves to increase working ages and free up trade.Fulford, p. 116 In 1846, Albert was rebuked by Lord George Bentinck when he attended the debate on the Corn Laws in the House of Commons to give tacit support to Peel.Fulford, p. 116 and Hobhouse, pp. 39–40 During Peel's premiership Albert's authority behind, or beside, the throne became more apparent. He had access to all the Queen's papers, was drafting her correspondenceHobhouse, pp. 36–37 and was present when she met her ministers, or even saw them alone in her absence.Fulford, p. 118 The clerk of the Privy Council, Charles Greville, wrote of him: "He is King to all intents and purposes."Greville's diary volume V, p. 257 quoted in Fulford, p. 117
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e0c2fe914b604c670ae3e57e349d63ba" name="Osborne_House_c1910_-_Project_Gutenberg_eText_17296" sectnum="3#1">../img/e0c2fe914b604c670ae3e57e349d63ba.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>