<document id="777f32cd0973d1c6755cfb654cbf1a4c-8.5" name="Archaea" cat="3">
<text>
Archaea exist in a broad range of habitats, and are a major part of global ecosystems, and may contribute up to 20% of the total biomass on Earth. Multiple archaeans are extremophiles, and historically this was seen as their ecological niche. Indeed, some archaea survive high temperatures, often above 100 °C, as found in geysers, black smokers, and oil wells. Others are found in very cold habitats and others in highly saline, acidic, or alkaline water. However, other archaea are mesophiles that grow in much milder conditions, in marshland, sewage, the oceans, and soils.

Extremophile archaea are members of four main physiological groups. These are the halophiles, thermophiles, alkaliphiles, and acidophiles. These groups are not comprehensive or related to which phylum the organisms belong to, nor are they mutually exclusive, since some archaea belong to several of these groups. Nonetheless, they are a useful starting point for classification. 

Halophiles, including the genus ''Halobacterium'', live in extremely saline environments such as salt lakes and start outnumbering their bacterial counterparts at salinities greater than 20–25%. Thermophiles grow best at temperatures above 45 °C, in places such as hot springs; ''hyperthermophilic'' archaea are defined as those that grow optimally at temperatures greater than 80 °C. The archaeal ''Methanopyrus kandleri'' Strain 116 grows at 122 °C, which is the highest recorded temperature at which any organism will grow. Other archaea exist in very acidic or alkaline conditions. For example, one of the most extreme archaean acidophiles is ''Picrophilus torridus'', which grows at pH 0, which is equivalent to thriving in 1.2 Molar sulfuric acid.

This resistance to extreme environments has made archaea the focus of speculation about the possible properties of extraterrestrial life. This has focused on the possibility that microbial life may exist on Mars, and has even led to the suggestion that viable microbes could be transferred between planets in meteorites.

Recently, several studies have shown that archaea exist not only in mesophilic and thermophilic environments but are also present, sometimes in high numbers, at low temperatures as well. For example, archaea are common in cold oceanic environments such as polar seas. Even more significant are the large numbers of archaea found throughout the world's oceans in the plankton community (as part of the picoplankton). Although these archaea can be present in extremely high numbers (up to 40% of the microbial biomass), almost none of these species have been isolated and studied in pure culture. Consequently, our understanding of the role of archaea in the ecology of the oceans is rudimentary, so their full influence on global biogeochemical cycles remains largely unexplored. Some marine Crenarchaeota are capable of nitrification, suggesting these organisms may be important in the oceanic nitrogen cycle, although these oceanic Crenarchaeota may also use other sources of energy. Vast numbers of archaea are also found in the sediments that cover the sea floor, with these organisms making up the majority of living cells at depths over 1 meter into this sediment.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a4b308f9dbb34ad85cd86b8ae45b9712" name="Plankton_satellite_image" sectnum="8.5#1">../img/a4b308f9dbb34ad85cd86b8ae45b9712.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>