<document id="777f32cd0973d1c6755cfb654cbf1a4c-8.7" name="Archaea" cat="3">
<text>
The well-characterized interactions between archaea and other organisms are either mutualism or commensal. As of 2007, no clear examples of archaeal pathogens or parasites are known. However, a relationship has been proposed between the presence of some species of methanogens and infections in the mouth, and ''Nanoarchaeum equitans'' may be a parasite of another species of archaea, since it only survives and reproduces within the cells of the Crenarchaeon ''Ignicoccus hospitalis'', and appears to offer no benefit to its host.

One well-understood example of mutualism is the interaction between protozoa and methanogenic archaea in the digestive tracts of animals that digest cellulose, such as ruminants and termites. In these anaerobic environments, protozoa break down cellulose from plant material to obtain energy. This process releases hydrogen as a waste product, but high levels of hydrogen will reduce the energy released by this reaction. When methanogens convert the hydrogen to methane, the protozoa benefit as they will gain more energy from breaking down cellulose. 

These associations between methanogens and protozoa are taken a step further in several species of anaerobic protozoa, such as ''Plagiopyla frontata''; here the archaea actually reside inside the protozoa and consume the hydrogen produced in their hydrogenosomes. Similar associations with larger organisms are now being found, with the discovery that the marine archaean ''Cenarchaeum symbiosum'' lives within (it is an endosymbiont of) the sponge ''Axinella mexicana''.

Archaea can also be commensals, benefiting from an association without helping or harming the other organism. For example, the methanogen ''Methanobrevibacter smithii'' is by far the most common archaean in the human flora, with this species making up about one in ten of all the prokaryotes in the human gut. As in termites, these methanogens may in fact be mutualists in humans, interacting with other microbes in the gut to aid the digestion of food. Communities of archaea are also associated with a range of other organisms, such as on the surface of corals, and in the region of soil that surrounds plant roots (the rhizosphere).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8646ec92d5af07e0519a9e4269143363" name="Coptotermes_formosanus_shiraki_USGov_k8204-7" sectnum="8.7#1">../img/8646ec92d5af07e0519a9e4269143363.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>