<document id="777f32cd0973d1c6755cfb654cbf1a4c-1.2" name="Archaea" cat="3">
<text>
The classification of archaea, and of prokaryotes in general, is a rapidly moving and contentious field. Current classification systems aim to organize archaea into groups of organisms that share structural features and common ancestors. These classifications rely heavily on the use of the sequence of ribosomal RNA genes to reveal relationships between organisms (molecular phylogenetics). Most of the culturable and well-investigated species of archaea are members of two main phyla, the Euryarchaeota and Crenarchaeota. Other groups have been tentatively created. For example, the peculiar species ''Nanoarchaeum equitans'', which was discovered in 2003, has been given its own phylum, the Nanoarchaeota. A new phylum Korarchaeota has also been proposed, it contains a small group of unusual thermophilic species that shares features of both of the main phyla, but is most closely related to the Crenarchaeota. Other recently detected species of archaea are only distantly related to any of these groups, such as the Archaeal Richmond Mine Acidophilic Nanoorganisms (ARMAN), which were discovered in 2006.



The classification of archaea into species is also controversial. In biology, a species is a group of related organisms. A popular definition of a species in animals is a set of organisms that can breed with each other and are reproductively isolated from other groups of organisms (''i.e.'' they cannot breed with other species). However, efforts to classify prokaryotes such as archaea into species are complicated by the fact that they are asexual and show high levels of horizontal gene transfer between lineages. The area is contentious; with, for example, some data suggesting that in archaea such as the genus ''Ferroplasma'', individual cells can be grouped into populations that have highly similar genomes and rarely transfer genes with more divergent groups of cells. These groups of cells are argued to be analogous to species. On the other hand, studies in ''Halorubrum'' found significant genetic exchange between such populations. Such results have led to the argument that classifying these groups of organisms as species would have little practical meaning.

Current knowledge on the diversity of archaea is fragmentary and the total number of archaean species cannot be estimated with any accuracy. Even estimates of the total number of phyla in the archaea range from 18 to 23, of which only 8 phyla have representatives that have been grown in culture and studied directly. Many of these hypothetical groups are known from only a single rRNA sequence, indicating that the vast majority of the diversity among these organisms remains completely unknown. The problem of how to study and classify uncultured microbes is also encountered in the Bacteria.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2afe94425610316fe35cbe8890df8902" name="Rio_tinto_river_CarolStoker_NASA_Ames_Research_Center" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/2afe94425610316fe35cbe8890df8902.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>