<document id="777f32cd0973d1c6755cfb654cbf1a4c-1.1" name="Archaea" cat="3">
<text>
Early in the 20th century, prokaryotes were regarded as a single group of organisms and classified based on their biochemistry, morphology and metabolism. For example, microbiologists tried to classify microorganisms based on the structures of their cell walls, their shapes, and the substances they consume. However, a new approach was proposed in 1965, using the sequences of the genes in these organisms to work out which prokaryotes are genuinely related to each other.  This approach, known as phylogenetics, is the main method used today.

Archaea were first classified as a separate group of prokaryotes in 1977 by Carl Woese and George E. Fox in phylogenetic trees based on the sequences of ribosomal RNA (rRNA) genes. These two groups were originally named the Archaebacteria and Eubacteria and treated as kingdoms or subkingdoms, which Woese and Fox termed ''Urkingdoms''. Woese argued that this group of prokaryotes is a fundamentally different sort of life. To emphasize this difference, these two domains were later renamed Archaea and Bacteria. The word ''archaea'' comes from the Ancient Greek , meaning "ancient things".archaea. (2008). In ''Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary''. Retrieved July 1, 2008, from http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/archaea

At first, only the methanogens were placed in this new domain, and the archaea were seen as extremophiles that exist only in habitats such as hot springs and salt lakes.  By the end of the 20th century, microbiologists realized that the archaea are a large and diverse group of organisms that are widely distributed in nature and are common in much less extreme habitats, such as soils and oceans. This new appreciation of the importance and ubiquity of archaea came from using the polymerase chain reaction to detect prokaryotes in samples of water or soil from their nucleic acids alone. This allows the detection and identification of organisms that cannot be cultured in the laboratory, which is often difficult.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c9e348141009072ddb6ce64d831cd178" name="Grand_prismatic_spring" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/c9e348141009072ddb6ce64d831cd178.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>