<document id="77f38d486c4385a25ef04d7accd16ee8-2" name="Banksia_brownii" cat="3">
<text>
''Banksia brownii'' was first collected near King George Sound in 1829 by William Baxter, who named it in honour of botanist Robert Brown. A formal description was published by Brown in his 1830 ''Supplementum Primum Prodromi Florae Novae Hollandiae''; thus the full botanic name of the species is ''Banksia brownii'' Baxter ex R.Br. Under Brown's taxonomic arrangement, ''B. brownii'' was placed in subgenus ''Banksia verae'', the "True Banksias", because its inflorescence is a typical ''Banksia'' flower spike. ''Banksia verae'' was renamed ''Eubanksia'' by Stephan Endlicher in 1847.

Carl Meissner demoted ''Eubanksia'' to sectional rank in his 1856 classification, and divided it into four series, with ''B. brownii'' placed in series ''Dryandroideae''. When George Bentham published his 1870 arrangement in ''Flora Australiensis'', he discarded Meissner's series, placing all the species with hooked styles together in a section that he named ''Oncostylis''. This arrangement would stand for over a century.

In 1891, Otto Kuntze challenged the generic name ''Banksia'' L.f., on the grounds that the name ''Banksia'' had previously been published in 1775 as ''Banksia'' J.R.Forst & G.Forst, referring to the genus now known as ''Pimelea''. Kuntze proposed ''Sirmuellera'' as an alternative, republishing ''B. brownii'' as "''Sirmuellera brownei'' (Baxter)" . The challenge failed, ''Banksia'' L.f. was formally conserved, and ''Sirmuellera brownii'' (Baxter ex R.Br.) Kuntze" is now a nomenclatural synonym of ''B. brownii''.

Alex George published a new taxonomic arrangement of ''Banksia'' in his landmark 1981 monograph ''The genus Banksia L.f. (Proteaceae)''. Endlicher's ''Eubanksia'' became ''B.'' subg. ''Banksia'', and was divided into three sections, one of which was ''Oncostylis''. ''Oncostylis'' was further divided into four series, with ''B. brownii'' placed in series ''Spicigerae'' because its inflorescences are cylindrical.

In 1996, Kevin Thiele and Pauline Ladiges published a new arrangement for the genus, after cladistic analyses yielded a cladogram significantly different from George's arrangement. Thiele and Ladiges' arrangement retained ''B. brownii'' in series ''Spicigerae'', placing it in ''B.'' subser. ''Occidentales'' along with ''B. occidentalis'' (Red Swamp Banksia), ''B. seminuda'' (River Banksia), ''B. verticillata'' (Granite Banksia) and ''B. littoralis'' (Swamp Banksia). This arrangement stood until 1999, when George effectively reverted to his 1981 arrangement in his monograph for the ''Flora of Australia'' series.

Under George's taxonomic arrangement of ''Banksia'', ''B. brownii'''s taxonomic placement may be summarised as follows:
:'''Genus ''Banksia'''''
::'''Subgenus ''Banksia'''''
:::Section ''Banksia''
:::Section ''Coccinea''
:::'''Section ''Oncostylis'''''
::::'''Series ''Spicigerae'''''
:::::''B. spinulosa'' - ''B. ericifolia'' - ''B. verticillata'' - ''B. seminuda'' - ''B. littoralis'' - ''B. occidentalis'' - '''''B. brownii'''''
::::Series ''Tricuspidae''
::::Series ''Dryandroidae''
::::Series ''Abietinae''
::Subgenus ''Isostylis''
''B. brownii'''s closest relative is held to be ''B. occidentalis'', which differs from ''B. brownii'' in having smaller, deep red flowers and narrow, sparsely serrate leaves.

Since 1998, Austin Mast has been publishing results of ongoing cladistic analyses of DNA sequence data for the subtribe Banksiinae, which is comprised of ''Banksia'' and ''Dryandra''. With respect to ''B. brownii'', Mast's results are somewhat at odds with those of both George and Thiele and Ladiges, finding it to be more closely related to ''B. nutans'' (Nodding Banksia) and ''B. quercifolia'' (Oak-leaved Banksia) than to many of the ''Spicigerae''. Overall, the inferred phylogeny is very greatly different from George's arrangement, and provides compelling evidence for the paraphyly of ''Banksia'' with respect to ''Dryandra''. Early in 2007, Mast and Thiele initiated a rearrangement of ''Banksia'' by transferring ''Dryandra'' into it, and publishing ''B.'' subg. ''Spathulatae'' for the species having spoon-shaped cotyledons. They foreshadowed publishing a full arrangement once DNA sampling of ''Dryandra'' was complete; in the meantime, if Mast and Thiele's nomenclatural changes are taken as an interim arrangement, then ''B. brownii'' is placed in ''B.'' subg. ''Spathulatae''.

Three genetically distinct forms of ''B. brownii'' are recognised: the better known forms are a "mountain form" with a shrubby habit, short thin hard leaves, and a squat inflorescence; and a "Millbrook Road form", with a tree habit and longer, wider, soft leaves. Some horticulturists also recognise an intermediate form. Recent genetic testing has confirmed the existence of three distinct forms, but currently these have no taxonomic status.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="90223c59c4c776900f2b9486c98f1d52" name="Banksia_brownii_leaf_variations2" sectnum="2#1">../img/90223c59c4c776900f2b9486c98f1d52.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>