<document id="784da86c783e62cd0d66306ceae713e0-4" name="Casablanca_(film)" cat="19">
<text>
The film premiered at the Hollywood Theater in New York City on November 26, 1942, to coincide with the Allied invasion of North Africa and the capture of Casablanca; it went into general release on January 23, 1943, to take advantage of the Casablanca conference, a high-level meeting between Churchill and Roosevelt in the city. It was a substantial but not spectacular box-office success, taking $3.7 million on its initial U.S. release (making it the seventh best-selling film of 1943).Harmetz, p. 12 Initial critical reaction was generally positive, with ''Variety'' describing it as "splendid anti-Axis propaganda"; as Koch later said, "it was a picture the audiences needed... there were values... worth making sacrifices for. And it said it in a very entertaining way."Sperling, Cass Warner and Millner, Cork (1994). ''Hollywood Be Thy Name: The Warner Bros. Story.'' Rocklin, CA: Prima, p. 249 Other reviews were less enthusiastic: ''The New Yorker'' rated it only "pretty tolerable".Harmetz, pp. 12–13 The Office of War Information prevented screening of the film to troops in North Africa, believing it would cause resentment among Vichy supporters in the region.Harmetz, p. 286

At the 16th Academy Awards, the film won three awards: Best Adapted Screenplay, Best Director, and Best Picture. Wallis was resentful when Jack Warner, rather than he, collected the best picture award; the slight led to Wallis severing his ties with the studio in April that year.Harmetz, pp. 321–24

The film has grown in popularity. Murray Burnett has called it "true yesterday, true today, true tomorrow".Interviewed in  (Turner: 1992) By 1955, the film had brought in $6.8 million, making it only the third most successful of Warners' wartime movies (behind ''Shine On, Harvest Moon'' and ''This is the Army'').Harmetz, p. 283 On April 21, 1957, the Brattle Theater of Cambridge, Massachusetts showed the film as part of a season of old movies. It was so popular that it began a tradition of screening ''Casablanca'' during the week of final exams at Harvard University which continues to the present day, and is emulated by many colleges across the United States. Todd Gitlin, a professor of sociology who himself attended one of these screenings, had said that the experience was, "the acting out of my own personal rite of passage".Harmetz, p. 343 The tradition helped the movie remain popular while other famous films of the 1940s have faded away, and by 1977, ''Casablanca'' was the most frequently broadcast film on American television.Harmetz, p. 346

However, there has been anecdotal evidence that ''Casablanca'' may have made a deeper impression among film-lovers than within the professional movie-making establishment. In the November/December 1982 issue of ''American Film'', Chuck Ross claimed that he retyped the screenplay to Casablanca, only changing the title back to ''Everybody Comes to Rick's'' and the name of the piano player to Dooley Wilson, and submitted it to 217 agencies. Eighty-five of them read it; of those, thirty-eight rejected it outright, thirty-three generally recognized it (but only eight specifically as ''Casablanca''), three declared it commercially viable, and one suggested turning it into a novel.Zinman, David (April 10, 1983). The Magazine (Sunday supplement to ''The Province'' newspaper), p. 12
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="282a7ce52861239657c9e4817e412db3" name="Casablanca,_title" sectnum="4#1">../img/282a7ce52861239657c9e4817e412db3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>