<document id="784da86c783e62cd0d66306ceae713e0-3" name="Casablanca_(film)" cat="19">
<text>
The cast is notable for its internationalism: only three of the credited actors were born in the U.S. The top-billed actors were:
*'''Humphrey Bogart''' as '''Rick Blaine'''. The New York City-born Bogart became a star with ''Casablanca''. Earlier in his career, he had been typecast as a gangster.  ''High Sierra'' (1941) had allowed him to play a character with some warmth, but Rick was his first truly romantic role.
*'''Ingrid Bergman''' as '''Ilsa Lund'''. Bergman's official website calls Ilsa her "most famous and enduring role". The Swedish actress's Hollywood debut in ''Intermezzo'' had been well received, but her subsequent films were not major successes—until ''Casablanca''. Ebert calls her "luminous", and comments on the chemistry between her and Bogart: "she paints his face with her eyes". Other actresses considered for the role of Ilsa had included Ann Sheridan, Hedy Lamarr and Michèle Morgan; Wallis obtained the services of Bergman, who was contracted to David O. Selznick, by loaning Olivia de Havilland in exchange.Harmetz, pp. 88, 89, 92, 95
*'''Paul Henreid''' as '''Victor Laszlo'''. Henreid, an Austrian actor who emigrated in 1935, was reluctant to take the role (it "set  as a stiff forever", according to Pauline KaelHarmetz, p. 99), until he was promised top billing along with Bogart and Bergman. Henreid did not get on well with his fellow actors; he considered Bogart "a mediocre actor", while Bergman called Henreid a "prima donna".Harmetz, p. 97

The second-billed actors were:
*'''Claude Rains''' as '''Captain Louis Renault'''. Rains was an English actor, born in London. He had previously worked with Michael Curtiz on ''The Adventures of Robin Hood''. He later appeared in Alfred Hitchcock's ''Notorious'' with Ingrid Bergman.

*'''Conrad Veidt''' as '''Major Heinrich Strasser'''. He was a German actor who had appeared in ''The Cabinet of Dr. Caligari'' before fleeing from the Nazis and ironically was best-known for playing Nazis in U.S. films.
*'''Sydney Greenstreet''' as '''Signor Ferrari''', a rival clubowner. Another Englishman, Greenstreet had previously starred with Lorre and Bogart in his own film debut in ''The Maltese Falcon''.
*'''Peter Lorre''' as '''Signor Ugarte'''. Lorre was a Hungarian character actor who had left Germany in 1933.

Also credited were:
*'''Dooley Wilson''' as '''Sam'''. He was one of the few American members of the cast. A drummer, he could not play the piano. Hal Wallis had considered changing Sam to a female character (Hazel Scott and Ella Fitzgerald were candidates), and even after shooting had been completed, Wallis considered dubbing over Wilson's voice for the songs.Harmetz, pp. 139–40, 260 and Behlmer, p. 214
*'''Joy Page''' as '''Annina Brandel''', the young Bulgarian refugee. The third credited American, she was studio head Jack Warner's stepdaughter.
*'''Madeleine LeBeau''' as '''Yvonne''', Rick's soon-discarded girlfriend. The French actress was Marcel Dalio's wife until their divorce in 1942.
*'''S. Z. Sakall''' as '''Carl''', the waiter. He was a Hungarian actor who fled from Germany in 1939. His three sisters later died in a concentration camp. A friend of Curtiz's since their days in Budapest, he is billed as "S. K. Sakall".
*'''Curt Bois''' as the '''pickpocket'''. Bois was a German Jewish actor and another refugee. He had one of the longest careers in film, making his first appearance in 1907 and his last in 1987. (He has since been surpassed by Mickey Rooney.)
*'''John Qualen''' as '''Berger''', Laszlo's Resistance contact. He was born in Canada, but grew up in America. He appeared in many of John Ford's movies.
*'''Leonid Kinskey''' as '''Sascha''', whom Rick assigns to escort Yvonne home. He was born in Russia.

Notable uncredited actors were:
* '''Marcel Dalio''' as '''Emil''' the croupier. He had been a star in French cinema, appearing in Jean Renoir's ''La Grande Illusion'' and ''La Regle de Jeu'', but after he fled the fall of France, he was reduced to bit parts in Hollywood. He had a key role in another of Bogart's films, ''To Have and Have Not''.
* '''Helmut Dantine''' as '''Jan Brandel''', the Bulgarian roulette player married to Annina Brandel (Page). Another Austrian, he had spent time in a concentration camp after the Anschluss.
* '''Norma Varden''' as the Englishwoman whose husband has his wallet stolen. She was a famous English character actress.
* '''Jean Del Val''' as the French police radio announcer who (following the opening montage sequence) reports the news of the murder of the two German couriers.
* '''Torben Meyer''' as the Dutch banker who runs "the second largest banking house in Amsterdam." Meyer was a Danish actor.
* '''Dan Seymour''' as '''Abdul''' the doorman. He was an American actor who, at 265 pounds, often played villains.
* '''Gregory Gaye''' as the German banker who is refused entry to the casino by Rick. Gaye was a Russian-born actor who went to the United States in 1917 after the Russian Revolution.

Part of the emotional impact of the film has been attributed to the large proportion of European exiles and refugees among the extras and in the minor roles. A witness to the filming of the "duel of the anthems" sequence said he saw many of the actors crying, and "realized that they were all real refugees".Harmetz, p. 213 Harmetz argues that they "brought to a dozen small roles in ''Casablanca'' an understanding and a desperation that could never have come from Central Casting".Harmetz, p. 214 The German citizens among them nevertheless had to keep curfew as enemy aliens. Ironically, they were frequently cast as the Nazis from whom they had fled.

Some of the exiled foreign actors were:
* '''Wolfgang Zilzer''' who is shot in the opening scene of the movie, was a silent movie actor in Germany who left when the Nazis took over. He later married Casablanca actress Lotte Palfi.
* '''Hans Twardowski''' as a Nazi officer who argues with a French officer over Yvonne. Born in Stettin, Germany (today Szczecin, Poland).
* '''Ludwig Stössel''' as '''Mr. Leuchtag''', the German refugee whose English is "not so good". Born in Austria, the Jewish actor was imprisoned following the Nazi Anschluss. When he was released, he left for England and then America. Stössel became famous for doing a long series of commercials for Italian Swiss Colony wine producers. Dressed in an Alpine hat and lederhosen, Stössel was their spokesman with the slogan, "That Little Old Winemaker, Me!"
* '''Ilka Grünig''' as '''Mrs. Leuchtag'''. Born in Vienna, she was a silent movie star in Germany who came to America after the Anschluss.
* '''Lotte Palfi''' as the refugee trying to sell her diamonds. Born in Germany, she played stage roles at a prestigious theater in Darmstadt, Germany. She journeyed to America after the Nazis came to power in 1933. She later married another Casablanca actor, Wolfgang Zilzer.
* '''Trude Berliner''' as a baccarat player in Rick's. Born in Berlin, she was a famous cabaret performer and film actress. Being Jewish, she left Germany in 1933.
* '''Louis V. Arco''' as another refugee in Rick's. Born Lutz Altschul in Austria, he moved to America shortly after the Anschluss and changed his name.
* '''Richard Ryen''' as Strasser's aide, '''Captain Heinze'''. The Austrian Jew acted in German films, but fled the Nazis.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5fc251627d830a911ef79ad3ae91d619" name="Humphrey_Bogart_and_Sydney_Greenstreet_in_Casablanca_crop_" sectnum="3#1">../img/5fc251627d830a911ef79ad3ae91d619.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>