<document id="784da86c783e62cd0d66306ceae713e0-7" name="Casablanca_(film)" cat="19">
<text>
Almost from the moment ''Casablanca'' became a hit, talk began of producing a sequel. One titled ''Brazzaville'' (in the final scene, Renault recommends fleeing to that Free French-held city) was planned, but never produced. Since then, no studio has seriously considered filming a sequel or outright remake. François Truffaut refused an invitation to remake the film in 1974, citing its cult status among American students as his reason.Harmetz, p. 342 However, it has been reported that Bollywood filmmaker Rajeev Nath is remaking the film, describing it as a "tribute to the original."

The novel, ''As Time Goes By'', written by Michael Walsh and published in , was authorized by Warner. The novel picks up where the movie leaves off, and also tells of Rick's mysterious past in America. The book met with little success. David Thomson provided an unofficial sequel in his  novel ''Suspects''.

There have been two short-lived television series based upon ''Casablanca'', both considered prequels to the movie. The first aired from  to , with Charles McGraw as Rick and Marcel Dalio, who played Emil the croupier in the movie, as Renault; it aired on ABC as part of the wheel series ''Warner Bros. Presents''. It produced a total of 10 hour-long episodes. Another series, briefly broadcast on NBC in , starred David Soul as Rick, Ray Liotta as Sacha and Scatman Crothers as a somewhat elderly Sam. A total of 5 hour-long episodes were produced.

There were several radio adaptations of the film. The two best-known were a thirty-minute adaptation on ''The Screen Guild Theater'' on April 26, 1943, starring Bogart, Bergman and Henreid, and an hour-long version on the ''Lux Radio Theater'' on January 24, 1944, featuring Alan Ladd as Rick, Hedy Lamarr as Ilsa, and John Loder as Victor Laszlo. Two other thirty-minute adaptations were aired: on the ''Philip Morris Playhouse'' on September 3, 1943 and on the ''Theater of Romance'' on December 19, 1944, in which Dooley Wilson reprised his role as Sam.

Julius Epstein made two attempts to turn the film into a Broadway musical, in 1951 and 1967, but neither made it to the stage.Harmetz, p. 338 The original play, ''Everybody Comes to Rick's'', was produced in Newport, Rhode Island in August 1946, and again in London in April 1991, but met with no success.Harmetz, p. 331 The film will be adapted into a musical by Takarazuka Revue, an all-female Japanese musical theater company, and is slated to run from November 2009 through February 2010.

''Casablanca'' was also part of the film colorization controversy during the 1980s, when a colorized version aired on television. This was briefly available on home video, but it was unpopular with purists. Bogart's son Stephen said, "if you're going to colorize ''Casablanca'', why not put arms on the Venus de Milo?"
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0373ab00331ee380c203a66a25410990" name="Casablanca_(colorized)" sectnum="7#1">../img/0373ab00331ee380c203a66a25410990.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>