<document id="79411a31129c20e7ee9eb6aa838cb664-1" name="Mourning_Dove" cat="3">
<text>
The Mourning Dove is closely related to the Eared Dove (''Zenaida auriculata'') and the Socorro Dove (''Zenaida graysoni''). Some authorities describe them as forming a superspecies and these three birds are sometimes classified in the separate genus ''Zenaidura'', but the current classification has them as separate species in the genus ''Zenaida''. In addition, the Socorro Dove has at times been considered conspecific with the Mourning Dove, although several differences in behavior, call, and appearance justify separation as two different species. While the three species do form a subgroup of ''Zenaida'', using a separate genus would interfere with the monophyly of ''Zenaida'' by making it paraphyletic.

There are five subspecies of Mourning Dove:

*Eastern ''Z. m. carolinensis'' (Linnaeus, 1766)
*Clarion Island ''Z. m. clarionensis'' (C.H.Townsend, 1890)
*West Indian ''Z. m. macroura'' (Linnaeus, 1758)
*Western ''Z. m. marginella'' (Woodhouse, 1852)
*Panama ''Z. m. turturilla'' Wetmore, 1956

The ranges of most of the subspecies overlap a little, with three in the United States or Canada. The West Indian subspecies is found throughout the Greater Antilles.NRCS p3 It has recently invaded the Florida Keys. The Eastern subspecies is found mainly in eastern North America, as well as Bermuda and the Bahamas. The Western subspecies is found in western North America and parts of Mexico. The Panamanian subspecies is located in Central America. The Clarion Island subspecies is found only on Clarion Island, just off the Pacific coast of Mexico.

The Mourning Dove is sometimes called the '''American Mourning Dove''' to distinguish it from the distantly related African Mourning Dove (''Streptopelia decipiens''). It was also formerly known as the '''Carolina Turtledove''' or '''Carolina Pigeon'''. The species' scientific name was bestowed in 1838 by French zoologist Charles L. Bonaparte in honor of his wife, Princess Zénaide."100 Birds and How They Got Their Names, by Diana Wells (Algonquin Books of Chapel Hill, 2002) p.193) The "mourning" part of its common name comes from its call.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c022dd5e2e302d0567f7e839e32b94d7" name="Mourning_Dove_Perched" sectnum="1#1">../img/c022dd5e2e302d0567f7e839e32b94d7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>