<document id="7953ebdc3e70b13d25e6fe55762b2a2b-3.1" name="Richard_Williams_(RAAF_officer)" cat="29">
<text>
Appointed an Officer of the Order of the British Empire in the 1919 New Year Honours, Williams served as Staff Officer, Aviation, at Australian Imperial Force (AIF) headquarters in London, before returning to Australia and taking up the position of Director of Air Services at Army Headquarters, Melbourne. The Australian Flying Corps had meanwhile been disbanded at the end of the war, replaced by the Australian Air Corps (AAC) which was, like the AFC, a branch of the Army.Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp.26&ndash;31 


Upon establishment of the Australian Air Board on 9 November 1920, Williams and his fellow AAC officers dropped their army ranks in favour of those based on the Royal Air Force. Williams, now a Wing Commander, personally compiled and tabled the Air Board's submissions to create the Australian Air Force (AAF), a service independent of both the Army and the Royal Australian Navy. The AAF was duly formed on 31 March 1921, the 'Royal' prefix being added five months later.Gillison,  Williams proposed an ensign for the AAF in July 1921, based on the Royal Air Force flag but featuring the five stars of the Southern Cross within the RAF roundel and the Commonwealth Star in the lower hoist quarter. However, this design was not adopted for the RAAF, the Government employing instead a direct copy of the RAF ensign until 1949, when a new design was chosen which included the stars of the Australian Flag.Air Power Development Centre, ''The Australian Experience of Air Power'', pp.32&ndash;35 

As the senior officer of the Air Board, Williams held the title of First Air Member, the fledgling Air Force initially not being deemed suitable for a 'Chief of Staff' appointment equivalent to the Army and Navy.Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp.33&ndash;34 He moved to consolidate the new service's position by expanding its assets and training. Shortly after the AAF's establishment, land was purchased for an air base at Laverton, eight kilometres inland of Point Cook, and in July 1921, Williams made the initial proposal to develop a base at Richmond, New South Wales, the first outside Victoria.Roylance, ''Air Base Richmond'', p.15 He also started a program to second students from the Army and Navy, including graduates of the Royal Military College, Duntroon, to bolster officer numbers; candidates reaped by this scheme included future Air Force chiefs John McCauley, Frederick Scherger, Valston Hancock, and Alister Murdoch, along with other senior identities such as Joe Hewitt and Frank Bladin. As a leader, Williams would gain a reputation for strong will, absorption in administrative minutiae and a "somewhat puritanical" nature. He became known throughout the service as "Dicky".Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp.16,340The spelling "Dickie" is occasionally used, for example in Roylance, ''Air Base Richmond'', p.31, though Roylance also employs "Dicky" on p.36
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8bbdc18f1a26becfc782881e80dd737d" name="AirBoard1928_AWM_128397" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/8bbdc18f1a26becfc782881e80dd737d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>