<document id="7953ebdc3e70b13d25e6fe55762b2a2b-6" name="Richard_Williams_(RAAF_officer)" cat="29">
<text>
For his stewardship of the Air Force prior to World War II, as well as his part in its establishment in 1921, Williams is considered the 'father' of the RAAF.Dennis et al, ''The Oxford Companion to Australian Military History'', pp.670&ndash;671 Between the wars he continually strove for his service's status as a separate branch of the Australian armed forces, seeing off a number of challenges to its independence from Army and Navy interests.Odgers, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp.47&ndash;51 He remains the RAAF's longest-serving Chief, totalling thirteen years over three terms: October to December 1922; February 1925 to December 1932; and June 1934 to February 1939. at RAAF Official Site. Retrieved on 8 September 2007.

In his 1925 paper ''"Memorandum Regarding the Air Defence of Australia"'', Williams defined "the fundamental nature of Australia's defence challenge" and "the enduring characteristics of the RAAF's strategic thinking". Ignored by the government of the day, the study's operational precepts became the basis for Australia's defence strategy in the 1980s, which remains in place in the 21st century. However his input to debate in the 1930s around the 'Singapore strategy' of dependence on the Royal Navy for the defence of the Pacific region has been criticised as limited, and as having "failed to demonstrate the validity of his claims for the central role of air power".


Williams' legacy extends to the very look of the RAAF. He personally chose the colour of the Air Force's winter uniform, a shade "somewhere between royal and navy blue", designed to distinguish it from the lighter Royal Air Force shade.Stephens, ''Going Solo'', p.453 Unique at the time among Commonwealth forces, the uniform was changed to an all-purpose middle blue suit in 1972 but following numerous complaints in the ensuing years reverted to Williams' original colour and style in 2000.MacDougall, ''Australians at War'', p.91Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', p.305 

Memorials to Williams include Sir Richard Williams Avenue at Adelaide Airport, and RAAF Williams in Victoria, established in 1999 after the merger of Point Cook and Laverton bases.. Retrieved on 24 October 2007. In 2005, Williams' Australian Flying Corps wings, usually on display at the RAAF Museum in Point Cook, were carried into space and back on a shuttle flight by Australian-born astronaut Dr Andy Thomas. The Williams Foundation, named in his honour, was launched in February 2009 "to broaden public debate on issues relating to Australian defence and security". at . Retrieved on 8 October 2009.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="979ecb097a21d0380bb076126d56b2c5" name="P02471.001Williams" sectnum="6#1">../img/979ecb097a21d0380bb076126d56b2c5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>