<document id="7953ebdc3e70b13d25e6fe55762b2a2b-4" name="Richard_Williams_(RAAF_officer)" cat="29">
<text>
When war broke out in September 1939, Williams was Air Officer in charge of Administration at RAF Coastal Command, a position he had held since February that year, following a brief posting to the British Air Ministry. Goble had succeeded Williams as Chief of the Air Staff for the last time but clashed with the Federal Government over implementation of the Empire Air Training Scheme and stepped down in early 1940. Williams was recalled from Britain with the expectation of again taking up the RAAF's senior position but Prime Minister Robert Menzies insisted on a British officer commanding the service, over the protest of his Minister for Air, James Fairbairn, and the RAF's Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles Burnett became CAS.Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp.113&ndash;116McKernan, ''The Strength of a Nation'', pp.41&ndash;42 In his volume in the official history of the Air Force in World War II, Douglas Gillison observed that considering Williams' intimate knowledge of the RAAF and its problems, and his long experience commanding the service, "it is difficult to see what contribution Burnett was expected to make that was beyond Williams' capacity".Gillison,  Williams was appointed Air Member for Organisation and Equipment and promoted to Air Marshal, the first man in the RAAF to achieve this rank.Gillison, 

Williams returned to England in October 1941 to set up RAAF Overseas Headquarters, coordinating services for the large number of Australians posted there. He maintained that Australian airmen in Europe and the Mediterranean should serve in RAAF units to preserve their national identity, as per Article XV  of the Empire Air Training Scheme, rather than be integrated into RAF squadrons, but in practice most served in British units.Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp.63&ndash;64 Even nominally 'RAAF' squadrons formed under the Scheme were rarely composed primarily of Australians, and Williams' efforts to establish a distinct RAAF Group within Bomber Command, similar to the Royal Canadian Air Force's No. 6 Group, did not come to fruition.Herington,  He was, however, able to negotiate improvements to conditions of RAAF personnel in Europe, including full Australian pay scales as opposed to the lower RAF rates that were offered initially.Herington,  

When Air Chief Marshal Burnett completed his term in 1942, Williams was once more considered for the role of CAS. However this was vetoed by Prime Minister John Curtin and the appointment unexpectedly went to acting Air Commodore George Jones.Helson, ''"10 Years at the Top"'', pp.64&ndash;68 A mooted Inspector Generalship of the Air Force, which would have seen Williams reporting directly to the Minister for Air, also failed to materialise.Helson, ''"10 Years at the Top"'', p.59 Instead Williams was posted to Washington, D.C. as the RAAF's representative to the Combined Chiefs of Staff in the United States, and remained there until the end of the war.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6113f6b9f14c0f946f4aae5e3bcdda38" name="SUK10301WilliamsMcNamara" sectnum="4#1">../img/6113f6b9f14c0f946f4aae5e3bcdda38.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>