<document id="7953ebdc3e70b13d25e6fe55762b2a2b-5" name="Richard_Williams_(RAAF_officer)" cat="29">
<text>
In 1946, Williams was forced into retirement despite being four years below the mandatory age of 60. All other senior RAAF commanders who were veteran pilots of World War I, with the exception of the-then Chief of the Air Staff, Air Vice Marshal George Jones, were also dismissed, ostensibly to make way for the advancement of younger officers. Williams regarded the grounds for his removal as "specious", calling it "the meanest piece of service administration in my experience". 

Following his completion of duty in the Air Force, Williams was appointed Australia's Director-General of Civil Aviation, serving in the position for almost 10 years. His department was responsible for the expansion of communications and infrastructure to support domestic and international aviation, establishing "an enviable safety record". Williams' tenure coincided with the beginnings of the government carrier Trans Australia Airlines (TAA) and introduction of the Two Airlines Policy, at Australian Parliamentary Library. Retrieved on 24 May 2008. as well as the construction of Adelaide Airport and redevelopment of Sydney Airport as an international facility. at Adelaide Airport. Retrieved on 17 November 2008. at Sydney Airport. Retrieved on 17 November 2008.

William's wife Constance died in 1948 and he married Lois Victoria Cross on 7 February 1950.  He was appointed Knight Commander of the Order of the British Empire (KBE) in the 1954 New Year Honours, the year before he retired from the Director-Generalship of Civil Aviation. He then took up a place on the board of Tasman Empire Airways Limited (TEAL), forerunner of Air New Zealand. In 1977, Williams published his memoirs, ''These Are Facts'', described in 2001 as "immensely important if idiosyncratic ... the only substantial, worthwhile record of service ever written by an RAAF chief of staff". 

Sir Richard Williams died in Melbourne on 7 February 1980. He was accorded an Air Force funeral, with a flypast by seventeen aircraft.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d49f32ee4a97ec75d18f1401112ffbe6" name="A04565Williams" sectnum="5#1">../img/d49f32ee4a97ec75d18f1401112ffbe6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>