<document id="79da66eefbaaa68b2e0875f793d89996-3.3" name="Werner_Mölders" cat="29">
<text>
alt=Black-and-white photograph of four men wearing uniforms sitting on wooden chairs around a table in a living room. An older man is sitting at the head of the table on the left. Two younger men are sitting along the table's side, with their backs towards a tiled fireplace on the room's far wall. A fourth man is sitting at the head of the table on the right, leaning back, his left leg folded over his right. The table is covered by a white table cloth. The right-hand side of the table is empty, except for a large dark ashtray, a spoon and an empty glass; the left and centre of the table is covered by an assortment of empty plates, coffee cups and other dishes; there is also a bowl of fruit. The second man from the left has his hands raised, palms facing the camera, and the fingers of both hands pointing to the left of the image. The heads of the three other men are turned towards him.
Returning to Germany, Mölders was promoted to ''Major'' on 19 July 1940 and took command of Fighter Wing 51 (JG 51) from the recently promoted ''Generalmajor'' Theo Osterkamp the following day.Aders and Held 1993, p. 62. Mölders flew his first combat sortie with JG 51 on 28 July, attacking a Supermarine Spitfire flown by Flying Officer Lovell. On this mission, according to legend, Mölders was hit in a dogfight over Dover by the South African ace Sailor Malan, sustaining three splinter wounds in the lower leg, one in the knee and one in the left foot. ''Oberleutnant'' Richard Leppla shot down the pursuing Spitfire, and Mölders was able to make an emergency landing at Wissant, France.Aders and Held p63Kaplan 2007, p. 56. Recent research suggests Mölders was actually wounded in combat by Flight Lieutenant J.L. Webster&mdash;who was killed in action on 5 September 1940&mdash;in a Spitfire of 41 Squadron.Obermaier and Held 1996, p. 19.Shores and Williams, p. 622. His wounds, although not serious, kept Mölders from further operational flying for a month. ''Generalmajor'' Osterkamp briefly led the'' Geschwader'' again during Mölders' convalescence. Mölders returned to the ''Geschwader'' on 7 August 1940, without medical clearance for combat, to participate in Operation Eagle Attack (code name ''Adlertag''). Adolf Hitler had issued Führer Directive no. 17 (''Weisung Nr.'' 17) on 1 August 1940; the strategic objective was to engage and defeat the Royal Air Force (RAF) so as to achieve air superiority in preparation for Operation Sealion (''Unternehmen Seelöwe''), the proposed amphibious invasion of Great Britain.Aders and Held p. 63.

Mölders returned to approved operational flying status and flew his next two combat missions on 28 August 1940. His aide and wingman, ''Oberleutnant'' Kircheis, was shot down and taken prisoner of war during one of these missions; ''Oberleutnant'' Georg Claus took his place.Aders and Held 1993, p. 67. Mölders claimed two Hurricanes on 31 August and was mentioned again in the ''Wehrmachtbericht''.Obermaier and Held p. 19. ''Oberleutnant'' Victor Mölders, his younger brother, who had been appointed ''Staffelkapitän'' of the 2./JG 51 on 11 September, was shot down and taken prisoner of war on 5 October 1940.Aders and Held 1993, pp. 69, 71. Two Spitfires of the No. 92 Squadron RAF shot down near Dungeness on 20 September increased Mölders' tally of aerial victories to 40. He was the first fighter pilot to reach this number and was awarded the 2nd Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves (''Ritterkreuz des Eisernen Kreuzes mit Eichenlaub'') of the war on 21 September 1941. The award was presented by Adolf Hitler on 23 September in the new ''Reichskanzlei'' in Berlin.  After the award ceremony, Hermann Göring invited Mölders to his hunting lodge in the Rominter Heide.Obermaier and Held 1996, pp. 19&ndash;20, 34, 122.

alt=Black-and-white photograph showing half-length view of two uniformed men outdoors, standing next to each other. The young man on the left is wearing a field cap and a pilot's leather jacket with fur collar, with an Iron Cross displayed at the front of his shirt collar. The middle-aged man on the right is shown in three-quarter profile; he is smiling and wears a jacket with military decorations.
Mölders returned to his unit by the end of September and continued to win aerial victories. On 11 October Mölders claimed his 43rd victory. The No. 66 Squadron RAF Spitfire I ''X4562'' was flown by Pilot Officer J. H. T. Pickering, who bailed out, wounded, over Canterbury.Weal 1999, p. 7. Three Hurricanes on 2 October brought his tally to 51 victories, and he received a preferential promotion to ''Oberstleutnant'' in recognition of his 50 victories on 25 October 1940. While a severe bout of influenza then kept him grounded for a few weeks, his wingman in over 60 aerial combats, ''Oberleutnant'' Georg Claus, was killed over the Thames.Obermaier and Held 1996, pp. 20, 124&ndash;125.  On 1 December, Mölders claimed his last and 55th victory of 1940&mdash;25 of which occurred in the Battle of France and 30 in the Battle of Britain.Obermaier and Held 1996, p. 41. 

Mölders and members of JG 53 spent a couple of weeks of R&R skiing in the Vorarlberg before continuing operations against the RAF over the Channel and occupied France during early 1941.Obermaier and Held 1996, pp. 21, 137&ndash;141. His new wingman from January 1941 was ''Oberleutnant'' Hartmann Grasser.Obermaier and Held 1996, p. 147. Mölders claimed his first aerial victory after the lengthy vacation on 26 February 1941; his tally reached 60 on 26 February and stood at 68 when the ''Geschwader'' was recalled from the Channel front. His logbook showed 238 combat missions plus  an additional 71 reconnaissance flights; he had engaged in aerial combat 70 times.Obermaier and Held 1996, p. 21, 40&ndash;41.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7dafc1dcc3bf3c5c2c7d2cf0910919f5" name="Bf109F-2_Mölders_JG51_kl96" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/7dafc1dcc3bf3c5c2c7d2cf0910919f5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>