<document id="7a006900e36d5321a94712b3b0061ff9-1.2" name="Megadeth" cat="20">
<text>
Early in 1985, the band was given $8,000 by Combat Records to record and produce their debut album. However, after spending half of the album's budget on drugs, alcohol, and food the band was forced to fire their original producer and produce the album themselves. Despite the resulting poor production, ''Killing Is My Business... and Business Is Good!'', released in May 1985, was a well-received effort that blended elements of thrash, and speed metal.Huey, Steve. ''"Killing Is My Business... and Business Is Good! AMG Review"'', at ; last accessed November 16, 2006.Bregman, Adam. ''"Killing Is My Business... and Business Is Good!" Remastered version AMG Review'', at ; last accessed November 16, 2006.

The album features the first of many cover songs performed by Megadeth; a speed metal version of Nancy Sinatra's classic "These Boots Are Made for Walkin'" (), with lyrics altered by Mustaine. The song sparked controversy in later years when the song's original author, Lee Hazlewood, deemed Mustaine's changes to be "vile and offensive", and demanded that the song be removed from the album. Under threat of legal action, the song was removed from all pressings released after 1995. In 2002, however, the album was re-released with a partial version of the song, though with the altered lyrics censored by a "beep". In the ''Killing Is My Business...'' deluxe edition liner notes, Mustaine is strongly critical of Hazlewood, and notes he received royalties for almost 10 years before objecting to the altered version.''"Killing Is My Business... and Business Is Good"'' remastered album notes''. May 2002, Loud Records, 9046-2.

In the summer of 1985, the group toured the United States and Canada for the first time, supporting ''Killing Is My Business...'' with Exciter. During the tour, new guitarist Chris Poland abruptly left the band, and was replaced by touring guitarist Mike Albert. Poland later rejoined Megadeth in October 1985 however, shortly before they began work on their second album with Combat Records.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7872f15963cb43f375424c76c34b0486" name="Megadeth86" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/7872f15963cb43f375424c76c34b0486.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>