<document id="7a006900e36d5321a94712b3b0061ff9-1.12" name="Megadeth" cat="20">
<text>
In May 2004 Mustaine returned to his newest recordings, intended as a solo effort, but due to outstanding contractual obligations with the band's European label EMI, he was forced to release one more album under the "Megadeth" name.Nalbandian, Bob. ''"Dave Mustaine Interview"'', August 28, 2004, ''Hard Radio.com'', reported by ; last accessed November 19, 2006. Mustaine decided to reform the band, and contacted the fan favorite "Rust in Peace line-up" to re-record backing tracks on his latest songs. While drummer Nick Menza initially signed on, Marty Friedman and David Ellefson were both unable to come to an agreement with Mustaine.Nalbandian, Bob. ''"Dave Mustaine Interview"'', August 28, 2004, ''Hard Radio.com'', reported by ; last accessed November 19, 2006. Regarding longtime bassist Ellefson not returning to the band, Mustaine said: "David lied to me in the press, he said that my arm injury was fake, went around town and slandered me. We made him a really good offer (to rejoin the band) and he said no. I mean, if I give you an offer and you don't take it, it means no, right?" ''"Interview with Dave Mustaine of Megadeth"'', July 20, 2004, ''Metal-Temple.com'', reported by ; last accessed November 19, 2006. The new album would be the first ever Megadeth recording not to feature Ellefson. Original lead guitarist Chris Poland (from the 'Killing is My Business' and 'Peace Sells' era) was hired by Mustaine to contribute guitar solos to the new album; the first time the two musicians had worked together since Poland's dismissal from the band in the 1980s. Poland opted to serve as a studio musician only, as he wished to remain focused on his own jazz fusion project OHM.

On September 14, 2004 Megadeth released their comeback album, ''The System Has Failed'' on Sanctuary Records in the US and EMI in Europe. Heralded as a return to form,Birchmeier, Jason. ''"The System Has Failed" AMG Review'', at ; last accessed November 19, 2006. ''Revolver'' magazine gave the album four stars, calling ''The System Has Failed'' "Megadeth's most vengeful, poignant and musically complex offering since ''Countdown to Extinction''".Megadeth's Official website press release ''"Megadeth: Announce dates for "BLACKMAIL THE UNIVERSE TOUR" and band line-up as new CD ‘THE SYSTEM HAS FAILED' hits stores"'', September, 2004, reported by ; last accessed November 19, 2006. The album debuted on the ''Billboard'' 200 chart at #18, and was led by the radio single "Die Dead Enough", () which reached #21 on the US Mainstream Rock charts. Mustaine announced that the album would be the band's last, followed by a farewell tour, after which he would focus on a solo career.

Megadeth began the ''Blackmail the Universe'' world tour in October 2004, enlisting touring bassist James MacDonough (Iced Earth), and guitarist Glen Drover (Eidolon, King Diamond). While in rehearsal for the tour, newly returned drummer Nick Menza once again parted ways with the band, as he was unable to prepare for the physical demands of a full US tour.Brave Words.com ''"MEGADETH Tour Manager Talks About Drummer Nick Menza's Departure"'', November 5, 2004, reported by ; last accessed November 19, 2006. He was replaced just five days before the first show by Shawn Drover (Eidolon), brother to new guitarist Glen Drover, and also a member of the Canadian thrash metal band Eidolon. The band toured the US with Exodus, and later in Europe with Diamond Head and Dungeon.

In June 2005, Capitol Records released a greatest hits album to replace the now out of print ''Capitol Punishment'', entitled ''Greatest Hits: Back to the Start'', which featured the new remixed and remastered versions of songs from the first eight albums.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="facfb69614b9d416b04e76e4f0cbe28a" name="Megadeth_at_Sauna_crop" sectnum="1.12#1">../img/facfb69614b9d416b04e76e4f0cbe28a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>