<document id="7a6650a9ba18c25cd77808b0f2915b97-4" name="Lazare_Ponticelli" cat="29">
<text>
Until his death, Ponticelli lived with his daughter in the Paris suburb of Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, and every 11 November until 2007 he attended Armistice Day ceremonies. An honored citizen of his adopted town, Ponticelli voted in the 2007 presidential and legislative elections. He officially became a supercentenarian on 7 December 2007, and celebrated his 110th birthday at the National History of Immigration Museum. He kept his medals in a shoebox.

When originally offered a state funeral by then French President Jacques Chirac, Ponticelli asserted that he did not want one, although the death of the penultimate recognized soldier, Louis de Cazenave, on 20 January 2008 caused him to reconsider. He eventually accepted a small ceremony "in the name of all those who died, men and women", during World War I.



Ponticelli died at 12:45 PM (11:45 GMT) at his home in Le Kremlin-Bicêtre on 12 March 2008, aged 110. At the time of his death, Ponticelli was the oldest living man of Italian birth and the oldest man living in France. Nicolas Sarkozy, the French president, released a statement and said there would be a day of national remembrance for the war dead of France. Ponticelli was survived by at least one child, his then-78-year-old daughter, Janine Desbaucheron.

His state funeral was held on 17 March 2008. The mass was held at Saint-Louis Cathedral in Les Invalides and was attended by government ministers, soldiers and members of Ponticelli's family. French academic Max Gallo delivered the eulogy. At the mass French ''collégien'' Guillaume Kaleff read a poem written by his class in Ponticelli's honor. Flags were ordered to be flown at half mast while Sarkozy unveiled a plaque dedicated to the veterans of World War I. The French Foreign Legion, the same regiment that Ponticelli fought in, carried his coffin at the funeral. After the procession, he was buried in his family's plot at the Ivry-sur-Seine cemetery, located in the Val-de-Marne. On 11 November 2008, during the first Armistice Day since his death, Rue de Verdun in Le Kremlin-Bicêtre was renamed Rue de Verdun-Lazare-Ponticelli.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ed71a309f4ffbc8a7d1e105ac80c8a24" name="PONTICELLI6" sectnum="4#1">../img/ed71a309f4ffbc8a7d1e105ac80c8a24.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>