<document id="7ab655d8cf28f670524662f2ff4db0c4-7" name="Nashville_Sounds" cat="26">
<text>
In addition to promotions that are synonymous with minor league baseball like theme nights, fireworks night, and discounted ticket or concessions night, the Nashville Sounds also host what is called Faith Night. In 2002, the Sounds became the first sports team to host Faith Night promotions. Third Coast Sports. Retrieved on 30 January 2008. These Christian-based promotional evenings include pre-game concerts from Christian music artists, Bible-themed bobblehead giveaways, and testimonials from players about their faith. Artists performing at Nashville's Greer Stadium in the past include Jars of Clay, Hawk Nelson, and Matthew West. Brent High, then Vice President of Sales for the Sounds, and Mike Snider, the President and owner of Third Coast Sports, an entertainment and sports marketing firm in Nashville, are credited with developing the promotion.

Since their inception, Faith Nights have been among the top-ten most-attended games each season.Cornish, Audie.  National Public Radio. 26 May 2006. Retrieved on 23 October 2007. During Faith Nights in 2004, the Sounds experienced a 93% increase in attendance over their average season attendance for non-Faith Night dates; over 500 church groups attended these games.Cherner, Reid.  ''USA Today''. 21 July 2005. Retrieved on 23 October 2007. That fall, the team partnered with the Nashville Area Habitat for Humanity to build a home for a needy family. The team raised more than $45,000 from 10% of ticket proceeds and collections during Faith Nights. ''Nashville Business Journal''. 25 October 2004. Retrieved on 23 October 2007.

The promotion has since been adopted by at least 40 other minor league teams. It has also been used by major league teams such as the Atlanta Braves and St. Louis Cardinals. Teams from the National Football League and National Basketball Association have also shown interest in holding Faith Night promotions. The program has garnered national media attention for the Sounds from ''The New York Times'' and National Public Radio.St. John, Warren.  ''The New York Times''. 2 June 2006. Retrieved on 30 July 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e499a5c71e7ad58320de1040cba82191" name="NashvilleSoundsFaithNight" sectnum="7#1">../img/e499a5c71e7ad58320de1040cba82191.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>