<document id="7b501415dac82898033c3eb9200cb89d-1.2" name="Joking_Apart" cat="19">
<text>
The pilot, directed by John Kilby, was filmed at Pebble Mill in Birmingham on 9–10 August 1990.Gallagher, William. "Joking Apart", Inlay booklet, Series 2 DVD, ReplayDVD. It is practically identical to the first episode of the series proper; some scenes are even reused, notably the scene with Mark and Becky meeting when he accidentally turns up at a funeral. The reused footage gave rise to the first episode's shared director credit between Spiers and Kilby. The stand-up sequences were shot against a black background. Although this made it clearer that they were not "real", Moffat thought that it looked odd. The pilot was transmitted on BBC2 as part of its ''Comic Asides'' series of pilot shows on 12 July 1991.

Moffat had written all six episodes of the first series before recording commenced. Never again would he be so far in advance of production. With series two, he had written only the first four episodes by the time recording had commenced,Moffat, Steven, ''Joking Apart,'' Series 1, Episode 4 DVD audio commentary only delivering the final episode by the first day of rehearsals. 

All of the location shots were filmed at the beginning of the production block. Recording for the first series of six episodes began on location in the first half of April 1992 and were mainly filmed in Chelsea within a short distance from the director's home. The stand-up sequences were filmed in the ''Café Des Artistes'' on London's Fulham Road, now known as the Valmont Club, and were shot for the benefit of the studio audience, with the intention of reshooting them later for the broadcast version. Robert Bathurst has complained that, in order to save £5,000, this promised reshoot never materialised. The close ups of Bathurst were filmed in the studio for the second series, with stock footage of the club's audience reused. 

After the exterior shots had been filmed, the episodes were recorded at BBC Television Centre in April and May 1992 for the first series, and 12 November until 18 December 1993 for the second. Studio recording sessions were normally completed quickly; Gillies recalls "an hour and a half, tops". To a large extent, the editing occurred live during the studio recording with only tightening later. At the end of the recording on Sunday evenings Spiers would review the show before retiring to the bar, with the bulk of the work complete. Moffat compares this to the editing of modern sitcoms, which, he says, are edited more like film.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="47380ced08b86bbba86e1abd4f367546" name="Joking_Apart_-_Marks_flat" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/47380ced08b86bbba86e1abd4f367546.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>