<document id="7bc60ec21547737798ee0796eaf26829-1" name="Sino-German_cooperation_(1911–1941)" cat="14">
<text>
The earliest Sino-German trading occurred overland through Siberia, and was subject to transit taxes by the Russian government.  In order to make trading more profitable, Germany decided to take the sea route and the first German merchant ships arrived in China, then under the Qing Dynasty, as part of the Royal Prussian Asian Trading Company of Emden, in the 1750s. In 1861, following China's defeat in the Second Opium War, the Treaty of Tientsin was signed, which opened formal commercial relations between various European states, including Prussia, with China.

During the late 19th century, Sino-foreign trade was dominated by the British Empire, and Otto von Bismarck was eager to establish German footholds in China to balance the British dominance. In 1885, Bismarck had the Reichstag pass a steamship subsidy bill which offered direct service to China. In the same year, he sent the first German banking and industrial survey group to evaluate investment possibilities, which led to the establishment of the Deutsch-Asiatische Bank in 1890.  Through these efforts Germany was second to Britain in trading and shipping in China by 1896.

During this period, Germany did not actively pursue imperialist ambitions in China, and appeared relatively restrained compared to Britain and France. Thus, the Chinese government saw Germany as a partner in helping China in its modernization. In 1880s, German shipyard AG Vulcan Stettin built two of the most modern and powerful warships of its day — pre-dreadnought battleships Zhenyuan and  Dingyuan — for the Chinese Beiyang Fleet that would see considerable action during the First Sino-Japanese War.  After China's first modernization efforts apparently failed following its defeat in the First Sino-Japanese War, Yuan Shi-kai requested German help in creating the Self-Strengthening Army () and the  Newly Created Army (新建陸軍; Xīnjìan Lùjūn).  In addition, German assistance not only concerned the military, but also industrial and technical matters.  For example, in the late 1880s, the German company Krupp was contracted by the Chinese government to build a series of fortifications around Port Arthur.

Germany's relatively benign China policy, as shaped by Bismarck, was changed drastically under the reign of Wilhelm II, who assumed a more imperialistic attitude. For example, in the Triple Intervention following the First Sino-Japanese War, Japan was forced to transfer its concessions in Hankow and  Tientsin to Germany. Also, in 1897, Germany obtained a ninety-nine year leasehold on the Kiaochow Bay in Shandong, after a German military attachment was sent in response to the attacks on missionaries by the Chinese in the region. Perhaps the lowest point in Sino-German relations was the Boxer Rebellion of 1900, during which foreign nationals were killed and the German military retaliated with brutality (indeed, Kaiser Wilhelm urged his troops to "fight like Huns," from which the label "Huns" became a derisive term applied to German soldiers in the First and Second World Wars).

During this period, Germany also had a major impact on the development of Chinese law.  In the years preceding the fall of the Qing Dynasty, Chinese reformers began drafting a Civil Code based largely on the German Civil Code, which had already been adopted in neighboring Japan.  Although this draft code was not promulgated before the collapse of the Qing dynasty, it was the basis for the Civil Code of the Republic of China introduced in 1930, which is the current civil law in Taiwan and has influenced current law in mainland China.  The General Principles of Civil Law of the People's Republic of China, drafted in 1985, for example, is modelled after the German Civil Code.

However, in the period preceding World War I, Sino-German relations became less intense.  One reason for this was that Germany was politically isolated, as evident by the 1902 Anglo-Japanese Alliance and the Triple Entente of 1907. Because of this, Germany proposed a German-Chinese-American entente in 1907, but the proposal never came to fruition. In 1912 Germany offered a six million German Goldmark loan to the new Chinese Republican Government and returned to the Chinese railway building rights in Shandong. When World War I broke out in Europe, Germany offered to return Kiaochow Bay to China, in an attempt to keep the concession from falling into Japanese hands. However, the Japanese entered the war on the side of the Allies and proceeded to attack German concessions in China, and seized Tsingtao and Kiaochow Bay. During the war, Germany had no active role or initiative in conducting any meaningful actions in the Far East as it was preoccupied with the war in Europe.  

On August 14, 1917, China declared war on Germany and recovered German concessions in Hankow and Tientsin, and was promised the return of other German spheres of influence following the defeat of Germany. However, instead of China, Japan acquired these concessions in the Treaty of Versailles. The feeling of betrayal by the Allied powers sparked the nationalistic May Fourth Movement. As a result, World War I dealt a severe blow to Sino-German relations, particularly in trade. For example, of the almost three hundred German firms in China in 1913, only two remained in 1919.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c3be7b79eba9840f736bacc27d85e91d" name="Beiyang_Army" sectnum="1#1">../img/c3be7b79eba9840f736bacc27d85e91d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>