<document id="7c7c03df56a5ee44e8c25bd34743e061-2.1" name="USS_West_Bridge_(ID-2888)" cat="29">
<text>
At 17:40, ''West Bridge''s engine broke down once again and her crew was unable to repair it. ''West Bridge'', falling off the back of the convoy and adrift, signaled ''Marseillaise'' to request a tow. At sundown, shortly before 18:00, ''Montanan''—still in the convoy, which was by now some  ahead of ''West Bridge''—was hit by one of three torpedoes launched by German submarine . ''Montanan'' began to settle and was quickly abandoned. On ''West Bridge'', Lieutenant Commander Hawkins realized the potential for another submarine attack and ordered his crew to general quarters and reduced the number of men in the mechanical spaces below decks. ''Noma'' sailed back to ''West Bridge'', ordered the freighter to extinguish her lights, and stood by. At nearly the same time,  approached and launched two torpedoes at the stationary cargo ship, scoring hits with both. The first struck near the No. 3 cargo hold in the front of the ship, while the second hit amidships near the engine room. ''West Bridge'' immediately began listing to starboard, and Hawkins ordered the crew to abandon the vessel. He and two crewmen remained behind until they felt sure that everyone else had departed. By the time they left the stricken ship, water was up to the gunwales and lapping at the well deck.

Immediately after the attack, ''Noma'' sped off to depth charge the submarine while sending an SOS for ''West Bridge'', since the initial explosion destroyed the cargo ship's wireless. Destroyer ''Burrows'' arrived to take on ''West Bridge''s survivors, who had situated themselves about a mile (2 km) from the still-floating ''West Bridge''. After boarding the destroyer, a head count revealed that four men were missing, but it also turned up two female stowaways.


By the morning of 16 August, both ''Montanan'' and ''West Bridge'' were still afloat, albeit with decks awash. Despite attempts to get ''Montanan'' under tow, she foundered later in the morning. Meanwhile, Hawkins and his executive officer were taken by boat to ''West Bridge'' to assess her situation. After boarding the ship and finding three cargo holds and her engineering spaces completely flooded, Hawkins advised ''Burrows'' captain that the situation was hopeless and he would only be endangering his ship, crew, and the ''West Bridge'' survivors by remaining alongside. Consequently, ''Burrows'' departed for Brest, France, leaving destroyer ''Smith'' to stand by ''West Bridge''.

A volunteer work and salvage party from ''Smith'', led by Lieutenant Richard L. Conolly, and which included Chief Boatswain's Mate John Henry Claudell,Stringer, p. 54. and Construction Mechanic, 3rd class Walter Homer Todd,Stringer, p. 137. boarded ''West Bridge'' and awaited four tugs which had been dispatched from Brest: the U.S. Navy tug ,Stringer, p. 147. two French tugs, and one British tug. Over the course of the next five days, the tugs, joined by patrol yacht , slowly made their way to the French coast, eventually arriving at Brest. ''West Bridge'' was towed over  with only 1% buoyancy remaining. Conolly, Claudell, and Todd were each awarded the Navy Cross for their efforts in saving ''West Bridge''; W. W. Wotherspoon, the fleet salvage officer on ''Favorite'' was also honored with a Navy Cross, in part for his salvage efforts for ''West Bridge''.In addition to his salvage work on ''West Bridge'', Wotherspoon was honored for his efforts for , , ''Conner'', and ''Murray''. See: Stringer, p. 147.

The extent of the damage and the condition of ''West Bridge'' led to some erroneous reports of her loss. News articles on 24 August in both ''The New York Times'' and the ''Chicago Daily Tribune'' reported the loss of ''West Bridge'',  and the mistaken information also made it into book form. Authors Benedict Crowell and Robert Forrest Wilson, in their work ''The Road to France: The Transportation of Troops and Military Supplies, 1917–1918'', repeat the misinformation about the loss of ''West Bridge''.Crowell and Wilson, p. 530.

After ''West Bridge'' underwent seven months of repairs, the ship resumed service with the  through 1 December 1919, at which time she was decommissioned and handed over to the .
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a05c632604b20463f8ac0c4c517b16f8" name="USS_West_Bridge_torpedo_damage,_boiler" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/a05c632604b20463f8ac0c4c517b16f8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>