<document id="7c8419e9eba6b27378b7bfa131283673-7.9" name="German_occupation_of_Luxembourg_in_World_War_I" cat="29">
<text>
Despite the armistice ending the war, and the end of the revolts, Luxembourg's own future was still uncertain.  Belgium was one of the countries hit hardest by the war; almost the whole of the country was occupied by Germany, and over 43,000 Belgians, including 30,000 civilians, had died as a result.  Belgium sought compensation, and had its eye on any and all of its neighbours; in November 1918, Lord Hardinge, the Permanent Secretary at the Foreign Office, told the Dutch ambassador in London, "The Belgians are on the make, and they want to grab whatever they can."

  From early 1919, Belgium engaged in a propaganda campaign to promote its vision of annexation.  At the Paris Peace Conference, the Belgian delegation argued in favour of the international community allowing Belgium to annex Luxembourg.  However, fearing loss of influence over the left bank of the Rhine, France rejected Belgium's overtures out of hand, thus guaranteeing Luxembourg's continued independence.

The resulting Treaty of Versailles set aside two articles (ยง40 and ยง41) to address concerns for  Luxembourg's status.  The main article, ยง40, revoked all special privileges that Germany had acquired in Luxembourg, with Germany specifically renouncing advantages gained in the treaties of 1842, 1847, 1865, 1866, February 1867, May 1867, 1871, 1872, and 1902., Article 40.  28 June 1919.  Retrieved on 2006-07-23.  The effects of these treaties' revocation were then explicitly stated; Luxembourg would withdraw from the ''Zollverein'', Germany would lose its right to use the Luxembourgian railways, and Germany was obligated to recognise the termination of Luxembourg's neutrality, thus validating the actions of the Luxembourgian government since the armistice.  Furthermore, to prevent economic embargo after the end of the customs union, the treaty allowed Luxembourg an indefinite option on German coal,Treaty of Versailles, Annex V(5), 28 June 1919 and prohibited Germany from levying duty on Luxembourgian exports until 1924.Treaty of Versailles, Article 268(c), 28 June 1919
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f03d2282700296c04fa1712ea7e51764" name="Treaty_of_Versailles_Signing,_Hall_of_Mirrors" sectnum="7.9#1">../img/f03d2282700296c04fa1712ea7e51764.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>