<document id="7c8419e9eba6b27378b7bfa131283673-5.6" name="German_occupation_of_Luxembourg_in_World_War_I" cat="29">
<text>
Discontent amongst the population grew constantly, particularly in the country's industrialised south.  The autumn of 1916 had seen the first unionisation within the iron and steel industries, with trade unions springing up in both Luxembourg City and Esch-sur-Alzette.  Despite the war demand, iron production had slumped, leading to greater employment insecurity.  In March and April, three independents were elected as deputies from the canton of Esch-sur-Alzette, where the economy was dominated by iron and steel.  As independents, these newly-elected deputies were the only legislative opposition to the National Union Government.

For many Luxembourgers, particularly the miners, expression of disgust at the government could not be directed through the ballot box alone.  Sensing the threat of civil disobedience or worse, von Tessmar threatened any individual committing an act of violence (in which he included strike action) with the death penalty.Proclamation by Tessmar to steel workers at Differdange (in German), 10 May 1917  However, on 31 May 1917, the workers sought to use their most potent weapon, by defying von Tessmar's ultimatum and downing tools.Telegram from Thorn to Arendt (in German), 2 June 1917  Germany was dependent upon Luxembourgian iron, as the British Royal Navy's naval blockade forced Germany to look to accessible local supplies; in 1916, Luxembourg produced over one-seventh of the Zollverein's pig iron..  National Bureau of Economic Research.  Retrieved on 2006-07-23.  As such, Germany simply could not afford a strike, lest it be deprived of critical raw materials.

In putting down the strike, von Tessmar was ruthlessly efficient, but he was not required to resort to the executions that he had threatened.  Within nine days, the strike was defeated and the leaders arrested.Letter from Kauffmann to Zimmerman (in German), 3 August 1917  The two ringleaders were then sentenced by German court-martial in Trier to ten years imprisonment, to the disgust of the government.  The continued refusal of the German authorities to respect the Luxembourgian government, and the humiliating manner in which the strike was put down by German military muscle rather than the Luxembourgian gendarmerie, were too much for Thorn.  On 19 June 1917, the government resigned.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0fff57a6da7a5b94eedc66b43b7b7a66" name="Von_Tessmar_caricature" sectnum="5.6#1">../img/0fff57a6da7a5b94eedc66b43b7b7a66.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>