<document id="7c8419e9eba6b27378b7bfa131283673-3" name="German_occupation_of_Luxembourg_in_World_War_I" cat="29">
<text>
Just as the war was in the balance on the Western Front, so the fate of Luxembourg was see-sawing back and forth.  It was clear to all that the good conduct of the Luxembourgian government, if fully receptive to the needs of the German military administrators, could guarantee Luxembourg's continued self-government, at least in the short-term.  Eyschen was a familiar and overwhelmingly popular leader, and all factions put their utmost faith in his ability to steer Luxembourg through the diplomatic minefield that was occupation.  On 4 August 1914, he expelled the French minister in Luxembourg at the request of the German minister,Telegram from Eyschen to Mollard (in French), 4 August 1914 followed by the Belgian minister four days later and the Italian minister when his country entered the war.  To the same end, Eyschen refused to speak ill of the German ''Zollverein'', even though he had talked openly of exiting the customs union before the war began.Letter from Eyschen to Nyssens (in French), 28 December 1882.

On occasions, Eyschen's principles got the better of him.  On 13 October 1914, a Luxembourgian journalist named Karl Dardar was arrested by the German army for publishing anti-German stories.  He was then taken to Koblenz, and tried and sentenced by court-martial to three months imprisonment.  Eyschen was outraged that the Germans had kidnapped a Luxembourgian citizen and tried him for an extraterritorial offence, and Eyschen did nothing to hide his indignation.  Eyschen told the German minister in Luxembourg that the action was a 'direct injury to the Grand Duchy's national sovereignty'.Telegram from Eyschen to Buch (in German), 8 December 1914.

Such vexatious complaints were repeated, by both Eyschen and Victor Thorn, when a railway worker was arrested in January 1915 for allegedly working for French military intelligence, and subsequently tried and sentenced in Trier.  As Minister for Justice, Thorn was incensed that the Luxembourgian legal system had been treated with such disdain.Telegram from Thorn to Berg (in German), 1 February 1915.  Such objections were not received well by the German authorities.  Although they tired of Eyschen's stubborn ways, he remained a useful tool to unite the various Luxembourgian political factions.

Eyschen was not alone in letting his principles obstruct government business.  In the summer of 1915, Eyschen pushed to further reduce the role of the Catholic Church in the state school system.  Grand Duchess Marie-Adélaïde objected.  A fervently religious Catholic (as was most of the country, but not her late father, who was Protestant), she was reputed to have said, "I will not allow their most precious heritage  to be stolen while I have the key."O'Shaughnessy (1932), pp. 134–135  Marie-Adélaïde refused to budge, inviting Eyschen to resign if he could not accept her decision.  Eyschen nearly did, but decided to control himself.Calmes (1989), p. 93  Nevertheless, he would not be long in the job.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b5a28b29010e8cef947ffa4b1eb0fd4a" name="Paul_Eyschen_photograph_by_Grieser" sectnum="3#1">../img/b5a28b29010e8cef947ffa4b1eb0fd4a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>