<document id="7c8419e9eba6b27378b7bfa131283673-7.7" name="German_occupation_of_Luxembourg_in_World_War_I" cat="29">
<text>
By the autumn of 1918, Germany's position in the war was becoming untenable.  The massive Spring Offensive had been an unmitigated disaster, whereas the Allied counter-attack, the Hundred Days Offensive, had driven Germany back towards its own borders.  On 6 November, von Tessmar announced the full withdrawal of German soldiers from Luxembourg.Letter from Tessmar to Reuter (in German), 6 November 1918.  Five days after von Tessmar's announcement, Germany signed an armistice treaty, which brought an end to the war of four years.  One of the terms of the armistice involved the withdrawal of German soldiers from Luxembourg, along with the other occupied countries. , Article A(I).  11 November 1918.  Retrieved on 2006-07-23.

The Allied Powers agreed that the German withdrawal from Luxembourg would be observed by the United States, and that the USA would receive the honour of liberating the captive country.  On 18 November, General John Pershing issued a proclamation to the people of Luxembourg, stating that the United States' newly-formed Third Army would move through Luxembourg to occupy the German Rhineland, but that the Americans would come as allies and as liberators:



The following day, American soldiers crossed the Franco-Luxembourgian border.  Everywhere, they were fêted as liberators, in the spirit that Pershing had intended to inspire, and were met by bands and civilians waving flags, and were adorned with flowers..  US Third Army, 14 July 2004.  Retrieved on 2006-07-23.  Luc Housse, the Mayor of Luxembourg City, told the advancing American army that the Germans had, on the whole, been disciplined and well-behaved in the previous three weeks: a marked improvement upon his numerous complaints earlier in the conflict.  Finally, on 22 November 1918, the German army completed its withdrawal from Luxembourg, ending its occupation.

Germany's defeat created the perfect opportunity for the Allied powers to resolve the Luxembourgian question once and for all.  By removing Luxembourg from Germany's sphere of influence, they hoped to guarantee its continued independence, and thus preserve the peace they had won. On 19 December, at the instigation of the British and French governments, the Luxembourgian government announced its withdrawal from the ''Zollverein'' and an end to the railway concessions that Luxembourg had previously granted Germany.Thewes (2003), p. 79.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3b2f9a793ed3482634adc7f32bd349e6" name="US_Infantry_crossing_Echternach_bridge,_1918" sectnum="7.7#1">../img/3b2f9a793ed3482634adc7f32bd349e6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>