<document id="7c8419e9eba6b27378b7bfa131283673-2" name="German_occupation_of_Luxembourg_in_World_War_I" cat="29">
<text>
On 1 August 1914, Germany declared war on Russia.  On the outbreak of war with its eastern neighbour, Germany put the Schlieffen Plan into action, and Luxembourg's government's fears were realised.  Initially, Luxembourg was only a transit point for Albrecht von Württemberg's Fourth Army.  One of the railways from the northern Rhineland into France passed through Troisvierges, in the far north of Luxembourg, and Germany's first infringement of Luxembourg's sovereignty and neutrality was the unauthorised use of Troisvierges station.Telegram from Eyschen to Jagow (in German), 1 August 1914. Eyschen protested, but could do nothing to prevent Germany's incursion.

The next day, Germany launched a full invasion.  German soldiers began moving through south-eastern Luxembourg, crossing the Moselle River at Remich and Wasserbillig, and headed towards the capital, Luxembourg City.Telegram from Eyschen to assorted foreign ministers (in French), 2 August 1914.  Tens of thousands of German soldiers had been deployed to Luxembourg in those twenty-four hours (although the Grand Duchy's government refuted any precise number that was suggested).Speech by Eyschen to the Luxembourg Chamber of Deputies (in French), 3 August 1914.  Grand Duchess Marie-Adélaïde ordered that the Grand Duchy's small army, which numbered under 400, not resist, and, on the afternoon of the 2 August, she and Eyschen met the German commander, ''Oberst'' Richard Karl von Tessmar, on Luxembourg City's Adolphe Bridge, the symbol of Luxembourg's modernisation.  They protested mildly, but both the young Grand Duchess and her aging statesman accepted German military rule as inevitable.O'Shaughnessy (1932), p. 155 

On 2 August, German Chancellor Theobald von Bethmann Hollweg justified the complete occupation of Luxembourg in terms of military necessity, arguing that France was ready to invade Luxembourg itself.Telegram from Bethmann-Hollweg to Eyschen (in German), 2 August 1914.  The French minister in Luxembourg dismissed this argument, claiming that it would not have considered violating Luxembourg's neutrality unless Germany had done so first.Letter from Mollard to Eyschen (in French), 3 August 1914.  Bethmann Hollweg attempted to prove his country's regret by offering Luxembourg compensation for the losses due to the military presence.  On 4 August, Bethmann Hollweg told the Reichstag: 

However, when it seemed that Germany was on the verge of victory, the Chancellor began to revise his statements.  In his ''Septemberprogramm'', Bethmann Hollweg called for Luxembourg to become a German federal state, and for that result to be forced upon the Luxembourgian people once Germany achieved victory over the Triple Entente. .  9 September 1914.  Retrieved on 2006-07-23.  Given this promise, it came as a great relief to most Luxembourgers that the British and French halted the German advance at the Battle of the Marne in mid-September.  The result for the combatant nations was trench warfare, but, for Luxembourg, it was the indefinite continuation of German occupation.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bd1950f7ebafc150d0746141bf1bc369" name="Theobald_von_Bethmann-Hollweg" sectnum="2#1">../img/bd1950f7ebafc150d0746141bf1bc369.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>