<document id="7c8419e9eba6b27378b7bfa131283673-8" name="German_occupation_of_Luxembourg_in_World_War_I" cat="29">
<text>
Thousands of Luxembourgers overseas, unconstrained by the Luxembourgian government's need to remain neutral, signed up to serve with foreign armies.  3,700 Luxembourgian nationals served in the French Army, of whom over 2,000 died.  As Luxembourg's pre-war population was only 266,000, the loss of life solely in the service of the French army amounted to almost 1% of the entire Luxembourgian population, relatively greater than the totals for many combatant countries (see: ''World War I casualties'').  The Luxembourgian volunteers are commemorated by the Gëlle Fra (literally '' 'Golden Lady' '') war memorial, which was unveiled in Luxembourg City on 27 May 1923.  The original memorial was destroyed on 20 October 1940, during the Nazi occupation, as it symbolised the rejection of German identity and active resistance against Germanisation.  After World War II, it was gradually rebuilt, culminating in its second unveiling, on 23 June 1985.

The Luxembourgian community in the United States found itself confronted  by a crisis of identity.  Traditionally, they had identified themselves as ethnically German, rather than as a separate community of their own.  As such, they read German language newspapers, attended German schools, and lived amongst German Americans.  Nonetheless, when it became apparent that the war would not be over quickly, the opinions of Luxembourg Americans changed; on 2 May 1915, the Luxemburger Brotherhood of America's annual convention decided to adopt English as its only official language.  Other organisations were less inclined to change their ways; the ''Luxemburger Gazette'' opposed President Woodrow Wilson's supposed 'favouritism' towards the United Kingdom as late in the war as 1917.  However, when the United States entered the war in April of that year, the wavering members of the community supported the Allies, changing forever the relationship between the German and Luxembourgian communities in the USA.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="63f29aa3e2d77a631974e2b848e9a72a" name="Gëlle_Fra_whole_1" sectnum="8#1">../img/63f29aa3e2d77a631974e2b848e9a72a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>