<document id="7dbb4d7bdd41cb2f00b70479a0c12082-1.3" name="Film_Booking_Offices_of_America" cat="19">
<text>
The advent of sound film would drastically alter the studio's course: Negotiations that began in late 1927 with the Radio Corporation of America (RCA) on a deal for sound conversion led to RCA purchasing a major interest in FBO in January 1928. Four months later, as part of a strategy conceived with RCA head David Sarnoff, Kennedy acquired control of Keith-Albee-Orpheum (KAO), a vaudeville exhibition chain with approximately one hundred theaters across the United States and the Pathé (U.S.)–De Mille filmmaking operations under its charge."Cinemerger" (1927); Lasky (1989), pp. 24–26. Note that the statement in Jewell (1982) referring to "the 700 K-A-O Theatres in the US and Canada" (p. 10) is wildly inaccurate and may well be a typo. Lasky (1989) says "several hundred theaters" (p. 25), Beauchamp (1998), citing Lasky, says "three hundred theaters" (quote: p. 228, cite: p. 414 n. 41)—figures belied by ''Time'' magazine's contemporary data (see "Cinemerger"). On June 17, 1928, FBO's ''The Perfect Crime'', directed by Bert Glennon and starring Clive Brook and Irene Rich, debuted.For a description of the film, see the anonymous ''New York Times'' review, August 6, 1928 (available ). According to Crafton (1997), ''The Perfect Crime'' "premiered June 17, 1928 and opened at the Rivoli on August 4" (p. 140). It was the first feature-length "talkie" to appear from a studio other than Warner Bros. since the epochal premiere of Warners' ''The Jazz Singer'' eight months before. ''The Perfect Crime'', which went into general release on August 4, had been shot silently; using RCA's sound-on-film Photophone system, the dialogue was dubbed in afterward—a process then known as "synthetic sound."Crafton (1997), pp. 140, 304. On August 22, Kennedy signed a contract with RCA for live Photophone recording; more importantly, he also tendered the company an option to buy his governing share of FBO. Two months later, RCA had acquired controlling stock interests in both the studio and KAO. 

On October 23, 1928, RCA announced it was merging Film Booking Offices and Keith-Albee-Orpheum to form the new motion picture business Radio-Keith-Orpheum (RKO), with Sarnoff as chairman.While all other latter-day published sources give October as the date of the merger, Crafton (1997) states, "The new holding company, Radio-Keith-Orpheum, was formed on 21 November 1928" (p. 142). Kennedy, who retained Pathé, was paid $150,000 for arranging the merger on top of the millions of dollars in profit he made from selling off his stock.Lasky (1989), pp. 33–34. Joseph I. Schnitzer, ranking FBO vice-president, was elevated to president of the new company's production arm, replacing Kennedy.Jewell (1982), p. 10. William LeBaron, the last FBO production chief, retained his position after the merger, but the new studio, dedicated to full sound production, cut ties with most of FBO's roster of silent-screen performers. Movies that Film Booking Offices had either produced or arranged to distribute were released under the FBO banner through the end of 1929. The last official FBO production to reach American theaters was ''Pals of the Prairie'', directed by Louis King and starring Buzz Barton and Frank Rice, released July 1, 1929.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="45aa0cce65bb11a40e39baed03404cf7" name="FBOlogo1928" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/45aa0cce65bb11a40e39baed03404cf7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>