<document id="7dbddef77f080d64ce953783dd7b76dd-3" name="Battle_of_the_Eastern_Solomons" cat="29">
<text>
The battle is generally considered to be more or less a tactical and strategic victory for the U.S. because the Japanese lost more ships, aircraft, and aircrew, and Japanese troop reinforcements for Guadalcanal were delayed.Hara, ''Japanese Destroyer Captain'', 114–115  Summing up the significance of the battle, historian Richard B. Frank states,
The Battle of the Eastern Solomons was unquestionably an American victory, but it had little long-term result, apart from a further reduction in the corps of trained Japanese carrier aviators. The (Japanese) reinforcements that could not come by slow transport would soon reach Guadalcanal by other means.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', 193

The U.S. lost only seven aircrew members in the battle.  However, the Japanese lost 61 veteran aircrew, who were hard for the Japanese to replace because of an institutionalized limited capacity in their naval aircrew training programs and an absence of trained reserves.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', 191–193.  The troops in Tanaka's convoy were later loaded onto destroyers at the Shortland Islands and delivered piecemeal, without most of their heavy equipment, to Guadalcanal beginning on August 29, 1942.Hara, ''Japanese Destroyer Captain'', 118–119, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', 201–203, Peattie, p. 180 & 339.  Of the aircrew losses, 27 were from ''Shokaku'', 21 from ''Zuikaku'', and 13 from ''Ryūjō''

Emphasizing the strategic value of Henderson Field, in a separate reinforcement effort, Japanese destroyer ''Asagiri'' was sunk and two other Japanese destroyers heavily damaged on August 28, 70 miles (130 km) north of Guadalcanal in "The Slot" by U.S. aircraft based at the airfield.Evans, ''Japanese Navy'', p. 171, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', 199–200.  The battle for the island settled into a two-month-long stalemate, punctuated by an intense land battle at Edson's Ridge on September 13 and a large surface naval engagement at Cape Esperance in early October.

''Enterprise'' traveled to Pearl Harbor for extensive repairs, which were completed on October 15, 1942.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', 191.  She returned to the South Pacific on October 24, just in time for the Battle of the Santa Cruz Islands and her rematch with ''Shōkaku'' and ''Zuikaku''.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', 370–371.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d56a28aeb7dd415847d9ebbf0636356b" name="EasternSolomons5inchGallery" sectnum="3#1">../img/d56a28aeb7dd415847d9ebbf0636356b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>