<document id="7dbddef77f080d64ce953783dd7b76dd-1" name="Battle_of_the_Eastern_Solomons" cat="29">
<text>
On August 7, 1942, Allied forces (primarily U.S.) landed on Guadalcanal, Tulagi, and Florida Islands in the Solomon Islands.  The landings on the islands were meant to deny their use by the Japanese as bases for threatening the supply routes between the U.S. and Australia, and secure the islands as starting points for a campaign with the eventual goal of isolating the major Japanese base at Rabaul while also supporting the Allied New Guinea campaign.  The landings initiated the six-month-long Guadalcanal campaign.Hogue, ''Pearl Harbor to Guadalcanal'', p. 235–236.

The Allied landings were directly supported by three U.S. aircraft carrier task forces: TF 11 (USS ''Saratoga''), TF 16 (USS ''Enterprise''), and TF 18 (USS ''Wasp''), their respective air groups, and supporting surface warships, including a battleship, cruisers, and destroyers.Hammel, ''Carrier Clash'', 150. Not all of the ships were U.S. warships; attached to TF 18 was TF 44, commanded by Victor Alexander Charles Crutchley, and included the Australian navy cruisers HMAS ''Australia'' and HMAS ''Hobart'' (source:  Lundstrom, ''Guadalcanal campaign'', p. 96 and 99). The overall commander of the three carrier task forces was Vice Admiral Frank Jack Fletcher who flew his flag on ''Saratoga''.Hammel, ''Carrier Clash'', 41–42.  The aircraft from the three carriers provided close air support for the invasion forces and defended against Japanese air attacks from Rabaul.Hammel, ''Carrier Clash'', 43–99. After a successful landing, they remained in the south Pacific area charged with guarding the line of communication between the major Allied bases at New Caledonia and Espiritu Santo, supporting the Allied ground forces at Guadalcanal and Tulagi against any Japanese counteroffensives, covering the movement of supply ships to Guadalcanal, and engaging and destroying any Japanese warships, that came within range.Lundstrom, ''Guadalcanal Campaign'', 89 and Hammel, ''Carrier Clash'', 106.

Between August 15 and August 20, the U.S. carriers covered the delivery of fighter and bomber aircraft to the newly opened Henderson Field on Guadalcanal.Hammel, ''Carrier Clash'', 111–129. Henderson Field and the aircraft based there soon began having a telling effect on the movement of Japanese forces in the Solomon Islands and in the attrition of Japanese air forces in the South Pacific Area. In fact, Allied control of Henderson Field became the key factor in the entire battle for Guadalcanal.Hammel, ''Guadalcanal: Decision at Sea'', 400

Taken by surprise by the Allied offensive in the Solomons, Japanese naval (under Admiral Isoroku Yamamoto) and army forces prepared a counteroffensive, with the goal of driving the Allies out of Guadalcanal and Tulagi. The counteroffensive was called ''Operation Ka'' (''Ka'' comes from the first syllable for ''Guadalcanal'' as pronounced in Japanese) with the naval portion having an additional objective of destroying Allied warship forces in the South Pacific area, specifically the U.S. carriers.Hammel, ''Carrier Clash'', 121.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="540d4f8b5e506a555ef2c53784c50315" name="SolomonsThreeCarriers" sectnum="1#1">../img/540d4f8b5e506a555ef2c53784c50315.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>