<document id="7dde4239baf7365dbedb1a0503f9d322-3" name="Fun_Home" cat="17">
<text>
''Fun Home'' was first printed in hardcover by Houghton Mifflin (Boston, New York) on June 8, 2006. This edition appeared on the ''New York Times''' Hardcover Nonfiction bestseller list for two weeks, covering the period from June 18–July 1, 2006. It continued to sell well, and by February 2007 there were 55,000 copies in print. A trade paperback edition was published in the United Kingdom by Random House under the Jonathan Cape imprint on September 14, 2006; Houghton Mifflin published a paperback edition under the Mariner Books imprint on June 5, 2007.


In the summer of 2006, a French translation of ''Fun Home'' was serialized in the Paris newspaper ''Libération'' (which had previously serialized ''Persepolis'' by Marjane Satrapi). This translation, by Corinne Julve and Lili Sztajn, was subsequently published by Éditions Denoël on October 26, 2006. In January 2007, ''Fun Home'' was an official selection of the Angoulême International Comics Festival. In the same month, the Anglophone Studies department of the Université François Rabelais, Tours sponsored an academic conference on Bechdel's work, with presentations in Paris and Tours. At this conference, papers were presented examining ''Fun Home'' from several perspectives: as containing "trajectories" filled with paradoxical tension; as a text interacting with images as a paratext; and as a search for meaning using drag as a metaphor. These papers and others on Bechdel and her work were later published in the peer-reviewed journal ''GRAAT'' (''Groupe de Recherches Anglo-Américaines de Tours'', or Tours Anglo-American Research Group).

An Italian translation was published by Rizzoli in January 2007.
A German translation was published by Kiepenheuer & Witsch in January 2008. The book has also been translated into Hungarian, Korean, and Polish, and a Chinese translation has been scheduled for publication.

In October 2006, a resident of Marshall, Missouri attempted to have ''Fun Home'' and Craig Thompson's ''Blankets'', both graphic novels, removed from the city's public library. Supporters of the books' removal characterized them as "pornography" and expressed concern that they would be read by children. Marshall Public Library Director Amy Crump defended the books as having been well-reviewed in "reputable, professional book review journals," and characterized the removal attempt as a step towards "the slippery slope of censorship". On October 11, 2006, the library's board appointed a committee to create a materials selection policy, and removed ''Fun Home'' and ''Blankets'' from circulation until the new policy was approved. The committee "decided not to assign a prejudicial label or segregate  by a prejudicial system", and presented a materials selection policy to the board. On March 14, 2007, the Marshall Public Library Board of Trustees voted to return both ''Fun Home'' and ''Blankets'' to the library's shelves. Bechdel described the attempted banning as "a great honor", and described the incident as "part of the whole evolution of the graphic-novel form.", p. 39.  Retrieved on August 6, 2007.

In 2008, an instructor at the University of Utah placed ''Fun Home'' on the syllabus of a mid-level English course, "Critical Introduction to English Literary Forms".  One student objected to the assignment, and was given an alternate reading in accordance with the university's religious accommodation policy.  The student subsequently contacted a local organization called "No More Pornography", which started an online petition calling for the book to be removed from the syllabus.  Vincent Pecora, the chair of the university's English department, defended ''Fun Home'' and the instructor. The university said that it had no plans to remove the book.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7350ae799517987f0345a60b62d8011c" name="Fun_Home_French_cover" sectnum="3#1">../img/7350ae799517987f0345a60b62d8011c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>