<document id="7dde4239baf7365dbedb1a0503f9d322-3.2" name="Fun_Home" cat="17">
<text>
''Fun Home'' was positively reviewed in many publications. ''The Times'' of London described ''Fun Home'' as "a profound and important book;" Salon.com called it "a beautiful, assured piece of work;" and ''The New York Times'' ran two separate reviews and a feature on the memoir. In one ''New York Times'' review, Sean Wilsey called ''Fun Home'' "a pioneering work, pushing two genres (comics and memoir) in multiple new directions" and "a comic book for lovers of words". Jill Soloway, writing in the ''Los Angeles Times'', praised the work overall but commented that Bechdel's reference-heavy prose is at times "a little opaque".  Similarly, a reviewer in ''The Tyee'' felt that "the narrator's insistence on linking her story to those of various Greek myths, American novels and classic plays" was "forced" and "heavy-handed". By contrast, the ''Seattle Times''' reviewer wrote positively of the book's use of literary reference, calling it "staggeringly literate". ''The Village Voice'' said that ''Fun Home'' "shows how powerfully—and economically—the medium can portray autobiographical narrative. With two-part visual and verbal narration that isn't simply synchronous, comics presents a distinctive narrative idiom in which a wealth of information may be expressed in a highly condensed fashion."

Several publications listed ''Fun Home'' as one of the best books of 2006, including ''The New York Times'', Amazon.com, ''The Times'' of London, ''New York'' magazine and Publishers Weekly, which ranked it as the best comic book of 2006.
 Salon.com named ''Fun Home'' the best nonfiction debut of 2006, admitting that they were fudging the definition of "debut" and saying, "''Fun Home'' shimmers with regret, compassion, annoyance, frustration, pity and love—usually all at the same time and never without a pervasive, deeply literary irony about the near-impossible task of staying true to yourself, and to the people who made you who you are." ''Entertainment Weekly'' called it the best nonfiction book of the year, and ''Time'' named ''Fun Home'' the best book of 2006, describing it as "the unlikeliest literary success of 2006" and "a masterpiece about two people who live in the same house but different worlds, and their mysterious debts to each other."


''Fun Home'' was a finalist for the 2006 National Book Critics Circle Award, in the memoir/autobiography category. In 2007, ''Fun Home'' won the GLAAD Media Award for Outstanding Comic Book, the Stonewall Book Award for non-fiction, the Publishing Triangle-Judy Grahn Nonfiction Award, and the Lambda Literary Award in the "Lesbian Memoir and Biography" category. ''Fun Home'' was nominated for the 2007 Eisner Awards in two categories, Best Reality-Based Work and Best Graphic Album, and Bechdel was nominated as Best Writer/Artist. ''Fun Home'' won the Eisner for Best Reality-Based Work. In 2008, ''Entertainment Weekly'' placed ''Fun Home'' at #68 in its list of "New Classics" (defined as "the 100 best books from 1983 to 2008"). ''The Guardian'' included ''Fun Home'' in its series "1000 novels everyone must read", noting its "beautifully rendered" details.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="702d4e9bd7f604f54c0902a0350b6cc7" name="Alison_Bechdel_in_London" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/702d4e9bd7f604f54c0902a0350b6cc7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>