<document id="7e912013738ebe632e69811ea23a5438-2.2" name="History_of_the_Philippines" cat="14">
<text>
The Philippines had trade relations with southern China and cultural ties with India through neighboring present-day Malaysia, and Indonesia as early as the 9th to the 12th centuries. The social and political organization of the population in the widely scattered islands evolved into a generally common pattern. Only the permanent-field rice farmers of northern Luzon had any concept of territoriality. The basic unit of settlement was the barangay, originally a kinship group headed by a Datu (chief). Within the barangay the broad social divisions consisted of the maharlika (nobles), including the datu; timawa (freemen); and a group described before the Spanish period as dependents. Dependents included several categories: landless agricultural workers; those who had lost freeman status because of indebtedness or punishment for crime; and alipin (slaves), most of whom appear to have been war captives.

In the period between the 7th century to the beginning of the 1400s, numerous prosperous centers of trade had emerged, including the Kingdom of Namayan which flourished alongside Manila Bay,, the Rajahnate of Cebu, the Confederation of Panay, Remains of ancient barangays in many parts of Iloilo testify to the antiquity and richness of these pre-colonial settlements. Pre-hispanic burial grounds were found in many towns of Iloilo. These burial grounds contained antique porcelain burial jars and coffins made of hard wood, where the dead were put to rest with abundance of gold, crystal beads, Chinese potteries, and golden masks. These Philippine national treasures are sheltered at the Museo de Iloilo and in the collections of many Ilonngo old families. Early Spanish colonizers took note of the ancient civilizations in Iloilo and their organized social structure ruled by nobilities. 
In the late 16th Century, Fray Gaspar de San Agustin in his chronicles about the ancient settlements in Panay says: ''“También fundó convento el Padre Fray Martin de Rada en Araut- que ahora se llama el convento de Dumangas- con la advocación de nuestro Padre San Agustín...Está fundado este pueblo casi a los fines del río de Halaur, que naciendo en unos altos montes en el centro de esta isla (Panay)...Es el pueblo muy hermoso, ameno y muy lleno de palmares de cocos. Antiguamente era el emporio y corte de la más lucida nobleza de toda aquella  isla.”'' Gaspar de San Agustin, O.S.A., ''Conquistas de las Islas Filipinas (1565-1615)'', Manuel Merino, O.S.A., ed., Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cientificas: Madrid 1975, pp. 374-375. the Rajahnate of Butuan, the Kingdom of Sanfotsi situated in Pangasinan, the Kingdoms of Zabag and Wak-Wak situated in Pampanga and Aparri (which specialized in trade with  Japan and the Kingdom of Ryukyu in Okinawa).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a20caa51bac92c31b96a73c28c5378bd" name="Boxer_codex" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/a20caa51bac92c31b96a73c28c5378bd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>