<document id="7ec724230401f4a030b6a752ef5749db-1.1" name="2005_Sugar_Bowl" cat="26">
<text>
The Virginia Tech Hokies entered the 2004 college football season having gone 8&ndash;5 in 2003, culminating with a 52&ndash;49 loss to California in the 2003 Insight Bowl. Virginia Tech Athletics Department, Hokiesports.com. Accessed May 26, 2008. The 2003 season had also been Virginia Tech's final year in the Big East Conference, and Tech began the new season in the Atlantic Coast Conference. The Associated Press, MSNBC.com. July 2, 2004. Accessed March 13, 2008. Tech started the season unranked for the first time since 1998, and was picked to finish sixth (out of 11 ACC teams) in the annual ACC preseason poll, held in July.
The Hokies' first game in their new conference was a non-conference contest in Washington, D.C. against the top-ranked USC Trojans. Tech lost, 24&ndash;13, The Associated Press, ESPN.com. August 28, 2004. Accessed May 26, 2008. but recovered to win its next game—against lightly regarded Western Michigan—in blowout fashion, 63&ndash;0. SportsTicker, ESPN.com. September 11, 2004. Accessed May 26, 2008. In its first conference game in the ACC, the Hokies beat Duke, 47&ndash;17, to improve to a 2&ndash;1 record. The Associated Press, ESPN.com. September 18, 2004. Accessed May 26, 2008. Their first win in the ACC was followed by their first loss, however, as the Hokies lost the next week to North Carolina State, 17&ndash;16, when Tech kicker Brandon Pace missed a last-second field goal. SportsTicker, ESPN.com. September 25, 2004. Accessed May 26, 2008.

Following the loss, Virginia Tech was 2&ndash;2 on the season, and faced the potential of being ineligible for a postseason bowl game if it did not improve its winning percentage. Those fears were for naught as the Hokies won their next eight games, finishing the season with a 10&ndash;2 record. Virginia Tech Athletics Department, Hokiesports.com. Accessed May 26, 2008. With late-season wins over perennial rival, 16th-ranked Virginia, The Associated Press, ESPN.com. November 27, 2004. Accessed May 26, 2008. and fellow ACC newcomer, ninth-ranked Miami, The Associated Press, ESPN.com. December 4, 2004. Accessed May 26, 2008. Virginia Tech clinched the ACC football championship (the last year in which it would be decided without a conference championship game) and a bid to a Bowl Championship Series game. Because the ACC's normal bowl destination, the Orange Bowl, was hosting the national championship game, Virginia Tech was selected to attend the Sugar Bowl in New Orleans, Louisiana, instead.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="39ce96b1b6591295b56d9c299c042132" name="FedexField-2004BCAclassic" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/39ce96b1b6591295b56d9c299c042132.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>