<document id="7ec724230401f4a030b6a752ef5749db-2.7" name="2005_Sugar_Bowl" cat="26">
<text>
At the conclusion of the regular season, Virginia Tech's defense was ranked third nationally in scoring defense (12.6 points allowed per game), fourth in total defense (269.5 total yards allowed per game) and fifth in pass defense (149.8 passing yards allowed per game). Andy Gardiner, USA Today. December 28, 2004. Accessed June 22, 2008. The Tech defense featured two highly regarded cornerbacks, Jimmy Williams and Eric Green, who finished the regular season with 50 tackles and 31 tackles, respectively. Williams also had four interceptions (the most on the team), including one returned for a touchdown, (PDF) "Eric Green" Virginia Tech Sports Information, December 2004. Blacksburg, Virginia. Page 31 and was named first-team All-ACC. Green, meanwhile, had one interception. (PDF) "Eric Green" Virginia Tech Sports Information, December 2004. Blacksburg, Virginia. Page 17 Auburn wide receiver Courtney Taylor praised the two players highly in an interview before the game, saying, "Those cornerbacks are amazing to me every time I look at them. I think, 'God, those guys are very athletic.' We're going to have our hands full." 

Linebacker Mikal Baaqee was first on the team in tackles, recording 63 during the regular season. (PDF) "Eric Green" Virginia Tech Sports Information, December 2004. Blacksburg, Virginia. Page 11 Fellow linebacker Vince Hall ranked second, with 62.

On the defensive line, defensive tackle Jonathan Lewis was considered a key player. Though limited by a cast protecting a broken pinky finger suffered during Virginia Tech's game against Virginia, Lewis was expected to continue to perform well. Heading into the Sugar Bowl, Lewis had 38 tackles, including 10 tackles for loss and four sacks. Randy King, ''The Roanoke Times''. December 30, 2004. Accessed June 21, 2008. Also on the defensive line was Darryl Tapp, who led the team in sacks, tackles for loss, and quarterback hurries. (PDF) "Eric Green" Virginia Tech Sports Information, December 2004. Blacksburg, Virginia. Pages 29–30 Tapp earned first-team All-ACC honors and had 55 tackles and one interception during the regular season.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fa643cc80e0c08641d6b6dc26ceb2e2e" name="Vince_Hall" sectnum="2.7#1">../img/fa643cc80e0c08641d6b6dc26ceb2e2e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>