<document id="80b9b49b9ce9711acc51f6515426c9ed-2.4" name="Ulysses_(poem)" cat="17">
<text>
Tennyson penned "Ulysses" after the death of his close Cambridge friend, the poet Arthur Henry Hallam (1811–1833), with whom Tennyson had a strong emotional bond. The two friends had spent much time discussing poetry and philosophy, writing verse, and travelling in southern France, the Pyrenees, and Germany. Tennyson considered Hallam destined for greatness, perhaps as a statesman.Hughes, p. 197.

When Tennyson heard on 1 October 1833 of his friend's death, he was living in Somersby, Lincolnshire, in cramped quarters with his mother and nine of his ten siblings. His father had died in 1831, requiring Tennyson to return home and take responsibility for the family. Tennyson's friends were becoming increasingly concerned about his mental and physical health during this time. The family had little income, and three of Tennyson's brothers were mentally ill. Just as Tennyson's outlook was improving—he was adjusting to his new domestic duties, regaining contact with friends, and had published his 1832 book of poems—the news of Hallam's death arrived. Tennyson shared his grief with his sister, Emily, who had been engaged to Hallam.

According to Victorian scholar Linda Hughes, the emotional gulf between the state of his domestic affairs and the loss of his special friendship informs the reading of "Ulysses"—particularly its treatment of domesticity.Hughes. At one moment, Ulysses' discontent seems to mirror that of Tennyson, who would have been frustrated with managing the house in such a state of grief. At the next, Ulysses is determined to transcend his age and his environment by travelling again. It may be that Ulysses' determination to defy circumstance attracted Tennyson to the myth;Hughes, p. 199. he said that the poem "gave my feeling about the need of going forward and braving the struggle of life".Widely quoted; see for example, A. T. Tennyson and A. Roberts (2000). ''Alfred Tennyson. The Oxford authors.'' Oxford: Oxford University Press. ISBN 0192100165. p. 567. On another occasion, the poet stated, "There is more about myself in ''Ulysses'', which was written under the sense of loss and that all had gone by, but that still life must be fought out to the end. It was more written with the feeling of  loss upon me than many poems in ''In Memoriam''."Quoted in Hughes, p. 195. Hallam's death influenced much of Tennyson's poetry, including perhaps his most highly regarded work, ''In Memoriam A.H.H.'', begun in 1833 and completed seventeen years later.

Other critics find stylistic incongruities between the poem and its author that make "Ulysses" exceptional. W. W. Robson writes, "Tennyson, the responsible social being, the admirably serious and 'committed' individual, is uttering strenuous sentiments in the accent of Tennyson the most un-strenuous, lonely and poignant of poets."Robson, W. W. (1957). "The Dilemma of Tennyson". In Killham (1960), p. 159. He finds that Tennyson's two widely noted personae, the "responsible social being" and the melancholic poet, meet uniquely in "Ulysses", yet seem not to recognize each other within the text.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9dae18ad9e0e1d80de82678e1c58981f" name="Arthur_Henry_Hallam" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/9dae18ad9e0e1d80de82678e1c58981f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>