<document id="80b9b49b9ce9711acc51f6515426c9ed-2.6" name="Ulysses_(poem)" cat="17">
<text>
The degree to which Tennyson identifies with Ulysses has provided one of the great debates among scholars of the poem. Critics who find that Tennyson identifies with the speaker read Ulysses' speech "affirmatively", or without irony. Many other interpretations of the poem have developed from the argument that Tennyson does not identify with Ulysses, and further criticism  has suggested that the purported inconsistencies in Ulysses' character are the fault of the poet himself.

Key to the affirmative reading of "Ulysses" is the biographical context of the poem.  Such a reading takes into account Tennyson's statements about writing the poem—"the need of going forward"—and considers that he would not undermine Ulysses' determination with irony when he needed a similar stalwartness to face life after Hallam's death. Ulysses is thus seen as an heroic character whose determination to seek "some work of noble note" (52) is courageous in the face of a "still hearth" (2) and old age.Tennyson, however, discouraged an autobiographical interpretation of his monologues. (Campbell, p. 130.)Hughes, p. 194. The passion and conviction of Tennyson's language—and even his own comments on the poem—signify that the poet, as was typical in the Victorian age, admired courage and persistence. Read straightforwardly, "Ulysses" promotes the questing spirit of youth, even in old age, and a refusal to resign and face life passively.

Until the early twentieth century, readers reacted to "Ulysses" sympathetically. The meaning of the poem was increasingly debated as Tennyson's stature rose. After  Paull F. Baum criticized Ulysses' inconsistencies and Tennyson's conception of the poem in 1948,Baum, Paull F. (1948). ''Tennyson Sixty Years After.'' Chapel Hill: Univ. of North Carolina Press. the ironic interpretation became dominant.Hughes, p. 200. Baum finds in Ulysses echoes of Lord Byron's flawed heroes, who similarly display conflicting emotions, self-critical introspection, and a rejection of social responsibility. Even Ulysses' resolute final utterance—"To strive, to seek, to find, and not to yield"—is undercut by irony, when Baum and later critics compare this line to Satan's "courage never to submit or yield" in John Milton's ''Paradise Lost'' (1667).Baum 1948, cited in Pettigrew (1963).

Ulysses' apparent disdain for those around him is another facet of the ironic perspective. He declares that he is "matched with an aged wife" (3), indicates his weariness in governing a "savage race" (4), and suggests his philosophical distance from his son Telemachus. A sceptical reading of the second paragraph finds it a condescending tribute to Telemachus and a rejection of his "slow prudence" (36). However, the adjectives used to describe Telemachus—"blameless", "discerning", and "decent"—are words with positive connotations in other of Tennyson's poetry and within the classical tradition, where "blameless" is an attribute of gods and heroes.

Critic E. J. Chiasson argued in 1954 that Ulysses is without faith in an afterlife, and that Tennyson uses a "method of indirection" to affirm the need for religious faith by showing how Ulysses' lack of faith leads to his neglect of kingdom and family. Chiasson regards the poem as "intractable" in Tennyson's canon, but finds that the poem's meaning resolves itself when this indirection is understood: it illustrates Tennyson's conviction that "disregarding religious sanctions and 'submitting all things to desire' leads to either a sybaritic or a brutal repudiation of responsibility and 'life'."E. J. Chiasson, "Tennyson's 'Ulysses'—A Re-Interpretation". In Killham (1960), 164–173.

Other ironic readings have found Ulysses longing for withdrawal, even death, in the form of his proposed quest.  In noting the sense of passivity in the poem, critics highlight Tennyson's tendency toward the melancholic. T. S. Eliot opines that "Tennyson could not tell a story at all". He finds Dante's treatment of Ulysses exciting, while Tennyson's piece is "an elegiac mood".T. S. Eliot, "In Memoriam". In Killham (1960), 210. "Ulysses" is found lacking in  narrative action; the hero's goal is vague, and by the poem's famous last line, it is not clear for what he is "striving", or to what he refuses to yield. According to Victorian scholar Herbert Tucker, Tennyson’s characters "move" through time and space to be moved inwardly.Tucker, p. 11. 
To Ulysses, experience is "somewhere out there",


      … an arch wherethro'
     Gleams that untravell'd world whose margin fades
     For ever and for ever when I move. (19–21)
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a6e43d99bc60a6a780417ed36d8b5bc9" name="Paradise_Lost_2" sectnum="2.6#1">../img/a6e43d99bc60a6a780417ed36d8b5bc9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>