<document id="80b9b49b9ce9711acc51f6515426c9ed-2.5" name="Ulysses_(poem)" cat="17">
<text>
Tennyson adopts aspects of the Ulysses character and narrative from many sources; his treatment of Ulysses is the first modern account.Stanford, p. 202. The ancient Greek poet Homer introduced Ulysses (Odysseus in GreekThe word "Ulysses" (more correctly "Ulixes") is the Latin form of the Greek "Odysseus", source of the word "odyssey".), and many later poets took up the character, including Euripides,Tennyson wrote in the margin of Euripedes' ''Hecabe'', "Ulysses is, as usual, crafty  unfeeling." (Markley, p. 123). Horace, Dante, William Shakespeare, and Alexander Pope.  Homer's ''Odyssey'' provides the poem's narrative background: in its eleventh book the prophet Tiresias foretells that Ulysses will return to Ithaca after a difficult voyage, then begin a new, mysterious voyage, and later die a peaceful, "unwarlike" death that comes vaguely "from the sea". At the conclusion of Tennyson's poem, his Ulysses is contemplating undertaking this new voyage.



Tennyson's character, however, is not the lover of public affairs seen in Homer's poems. Rather, "Ulisse" from Dante's ''Inferno'' is Tennyson's main source for the character,Pettigrew, p. 31. which has an important effect on the poem's interpretation. Ulisse recalls his voyage in the ''Inferno'''s 26th canto, in which he is condemned to the Eighth Circle of false counsellors for misusing his gift of reason. Dante treats Ulisse, with his "zeal …/ T'explore the world", as an evil counselor who lusts for adventure at the expense of his family and his duties in Ithaca.Rowlinson (1994), p. 241. Tennyson projects this zeal into Ulysses' unquenched desire for knowledge:Schwarz, D. R. (1987). ''Reading Joyce's Ulysses.'' New York: St. Martin's Press, p. 39. ISBN 0312664583. 


     And this gray spirit yearning in desire
     To follow knowledge like a sinking star,
     Beyond the utmost bound of human thought. (30–32)


The poet's intention to recall the Homeric character remains evident in certain passages. "I am become a name" (11) recalls an episode in the ''Odyssey'' in which Demodocus sings about Odysseus' adventures in the king's presence, acknowledging his fame. With phrases such as "There gloom the dark broad seas" (45) and "The deep / Moans round with many voices" (55–56), Tennyson seems to be consciously invoking Homer.Markley, p. 124.

Critics have also noted the influence of Shakespeare in two passages. In the early movement, the savage race "That hoard, and sleep, and feed, and know not me" (5) echoes Hamlet's soliloquy: "What is a man, / If his chief good and market of his time / Be but to sleep and feed? A beast, no more."IV, iv. 32 ff., quoted in Bush, Douglas (Jan 1943). "Tennyson's 'Ulysses' and 'Hamlet'." ''The Modern Language Review'', 38(1), 38. Tennyson's "How dull it is to pause, to make an end, / To rust unburnish’d, not to shine in use!" (22–23) recalls Shakespeare's Ulysses in ''Troilus and Cressida'' (c. 1602):''Troilus and Cressida'', Act III, Scene III, quoted in Stanford, p. 203.

     Perserverance, my dear lord,
     Keeps honour bright: to have done is to hang
     Quite out of fashion, like a rusty mail,
     In monumental mockery.


The last movement of "Ulysses", which is among the most familiar passages in nineteenth-century English-language poetry, presents decisive evidence of the influence of Dante.i) Robson, W. W. (1957). "The Dilemma of Tennyson". In Killham (1960). ii) Stanford.  Ulysses turns his attention from himself and his kingdom and speaks of ports, seas, and his mariners. The strains of discontent and weakness in old age remain throughout the poem, but Tennyson finally leaves Ulysses "To strive, to seek, to find, and not to yield" (70), recalling the Dantesque damnable desire for knowledge beyond all bounds. The words of Dante's character as he exhorts his men to the journey find parallel in those of Tennyson's Ulysses, who calls his men to join him on one last voyage. Quoting Dante's Ulisse:


     'O brothers', said I, 'who are come despite
     Ten thousand perils to the West, let none,
     While still our senses hold the vigil slight
     Remaining to us ere our course is run,
     Be willing to forgo experience
     Of the unpeopled world beyond the sun.
     Regard your origin,—from whom and whence!
     Not to exist like brutes, but made were ye
     To follow virtue and intelligence'.Dante, ''Inferno'' XXVI; quoted in Robson, W. W. (1957). "The Dilemma of Tennyson". In Killham (1960).


However, critics note that in the Homeric narrative, Ulysses' original mariners are dead. A significant irony therefore develops from Ulysses' speech to his sailors—"Come, my friends, / 'Tis not too late to seek a newer world" (56–57). Since Dante's Ulisse has already undertaken this voyage and recounts it in the ''Inferno'', Ulysses' entire monologue can be envisioned as his recollection while situated in Hell.Rowlinson (1994), p. 132.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2e0630bafd5d46d02db2466bc23bd655" name="Blake_Dante_Hell_XXVI_Ulisses" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/2e0630bafd5d46d02db2466bc23bd655.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>