<document id="8100cfc420911fc0f9b198fb9bd234ba-3" name="Kinetoscope" cat="19">
<text>
The Kinetophone (aka Phonokinetoscope) was an early attempt by Edison and Dickson to create a sound-film system. Reports suggest that in July 1893, a Kinetoscope accompanied by a cylinder phonograph had been presented at the Chicago World's Fair. The first known movie made as a test of the Kinetophone was shot at Edison's New Jersey studio in late 1894 or early 1895; now referred to as the Dickson Experimental Sound Film, it is the only surviving movie with live-recorded sound made for the Kinetophone. In March 1895, Edison offered the device for sale; involving no technological innovations, it was a Kinetoscope whose modified cabinet included an accompanying cylinder phonograph. Kinetoscope owners were also offered kits with which to retrofit their equipment. The first Kinetophone exhibitions appear to have taken place in April.Robinson (1997), p. 51; Musser (1994), p. 87. Though a Library of Congress educational website states, "The picture and sound were made somewhat synchronous by connecting the two with a belt," part of the Library of Congress/''Inventing Entertainment'' educational website. Retrieved 10/22/06. this is incorrect. As historian David Robinson describes, "The Kinetophone...made no attempt at synchronization. The viewer listened through tubes to a phonograph concealed in the cabinet and performing approximately appropriate music or other sound." Historian Douglas Gomery concurs, " did not try to synchronize sound and image." Leading production sound mixer Mark Ulano writes, "nly 45 Kinetophones were made. They did NOT play synchronously other than the phonograph turned on when viewing and off when stopped."Robinson (1997), p. 51; Gomery (1985), p. 54;  by Mark Ulano, C.A.S., part of the ''FilmSound.org'' website. Retrieved 10/22/06. See also Hendricks (1966), pp. 48–50, 118–125; Millard (1990), p. 169. Though the surviving Dickson test involves live-recorded sound, certainly most, and probably all, of the films marketed for the Kinetophone were shot as silents, predominantly march or dance subjects; exhibitors could then choose from a variety of musical cylinders offering a rhythmic match.Altman (2004), pp. 81–83; Hendricks (1966), pp. 124–125. For example, three different cylinders with orchestral performances were proposed as accompaniments for ''Carmencita'': "Valse Santiago", "La Paloma", and "Alma-Danza Spagnola".''Guida practica'' (1895–96), p. 126 .

Even as Edison followed his dream of securing the Kinetoscope's popularity by adding sound to its allure, many in the field were beginning to suspect that film projection was the next step that should be pursued. When Norman Raff communicated his customers' interest in such a system to Edison, the great inventor summarily rejected the notion:

No, if we make this screen machine that you are asking for, it will spoil everything. We are making these peep show machines and selling a lot of them at a good profit. If we put out a screen machine there will be a use for maybe about ten of them in the whole United States. With that many screen machines you could show the pictures to everybody in the country—and then it would be done. Let's not kill the goose that lays the golden egg.Quoted in Ramsaye (1986), ch. 9.

Under continuing pressure from Raff, Edison eventually conceded to investigate the possibility of developing a projection system. He seconded one of his lab's technicians to the Kinetoscope Company to initiate the work, without informing Dickson. Dickson's ultimate discovery of this move appears to have been one of the central factors leading to his break with Edison that occurred in spring 1895.Ramsaye (1986), ch. 9.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bdb34b957bcfffea8dc695df085e8d4a" name="Kinetophonebis1" sectnum="3#1">../img/bdb34b957bcfffea8dc695df085e8d4a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>