<document id="82175cb2cc39a1bd4d1b8e20c79c4155-2.6.5" name="Kannada_literature_in_the_Western_Chalukya_Empire" cat="17">
<text>
The meteoric rise of Veerashaivism (a religious sect which preaches devotion to the god Shiva, also called "Lingayatism") in caste-ridden 12th-century Karnataka has historic significance because it involved commoners from the lower strata of society, people who had hitherto been denied access to even basic education.Shiva Prakash (1997), p. 167 The essence of the movement, also seen in the resulting ''Vachana'' poems, was the rejection of temple-based ritual worship and the hegemony of mainstream Sanskritic texts and scriptures. The movement encouraged a monotheistic belief in the god Shiva which, according to Kannada scholar H.S. Shiva Prakash, is a possible influence of the 63 Nayanmars (poets devoted to the god Shiva, 5th&ndash;10th century) of the Tamil-speaking region. The followers of the faith prayed not to a conventional image of a God but rather wore a ''linga'' (symbol of the god Shiva) on their body.Shiva Prakash (1997), pp. 168&ndash;169Kloppenborg and Hanegraaff (1995), p. 124 The beginnings of the ''Vachana'' poetry (called ''Vachana Sahitya'' &ndash; "Vachana literature", or ''Anubhava Sahitya'' &ndash; "mystic literature" and sometimes ''Sharana Sahitya'' &ndash; "literature of the devotees"), a unique form of expression in the Kannada language, can however be traced back to the 11th century.Shiva Prakash (1997), p. 168&ndash;169Sahitya Akademi (1987), pp. 199&ndash;200  

Names of three poets from the 11th century and some of their poems are available. Madara Chennaiah, a cobbler turned saint, is considered by H.S. Shiva Prakash as the first ''Vachana poet'', and was held in high esteem by latter day poets of the 12th century, including Basavanna. Only ten of Chennaiah's poems, expressing his resentment of the caste system in metaphors taken from the cobblers' trade, are extant today.Shiva Prakash (1997), p. 171&ndash;172 Dohara Kakkaiah is the second poet. A dalit by birth, his six available poems are confessional in nature, a theme seen in the later poems of Basavanna.Shiva Prakash (1997), pp. 172&ndash;173 Devara Dasimaiah (or Jedara Dasimaiah, 1040) is better known because a hundred and fifty of his poems are available. Written in a deft and concise language of proverbs and metaphors, his poems encourage monotheistic belief in the god Shiva. Dasimaiah's wife Duggale qualifies as Kannada's first women poet, though only a few of her poems are available.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="07eb4540c2aa683fdad3b3c43aee979d" name="Kudalasangama_9" sectnum="2.6.5#1">../img/07eb4540c2aa683fdad3b3c43aee979d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>