<document id="82175cb2cc39a1bd4d1b8e20c79c4155-1.4" name="Kannada_literature_in_the_Western_Chalukya_Empire" cat="17">
<text>
At about this time, adding to pressure from the popularity of the ''Vachana'' canon in the northern Kannada-speaking region,Nagaraj (2003), p. 355 the noted Hoysala king Vishnuvardhana (1108&ndash;1152) of the southern Kannada-speaking region converted from Jainism to the Hindu sect of Vaishnavism. The popularity of Ramanujacharya's philosophy had spread in the Hoysala lands and Srivaishnavism, a sub-sect of Vaishnavism, was in the ascendant.Kamath (2001), p. 132 By the late 13th century, the Veerashaiva writers, who were by now writing allegorical inscriptions and biographies of famous ''Vachanakaras'' of the 12th century, were in stiff competition with the Jains. The earliest attempts by the Jains to veer away from traditional ''puranic'' (philosophical) themes of renunciation are seen in the writings of Hoysala writers Nemichandra and Andayya. ''Lilavati Prabhandam'', a novel written by Nemichandra (1170) on the topic of love, erotica, and of the victory of Kamadeva (god of love) over his arch-rival Shiva, is the first among such writings. It was followed by  ''Kabbigara Kava'' ("Poets defender", 1215&ndash;1237) by Andayya, also a work depicting a war between Kamadeva and the god Shiva.Nagaraj (2003), pp. 355&ndash;356, 366; Rice E.P. (1921), pp. 43&ndash;44 Despite these efforts, the Jain literary influence was to recede in the coming decades and centuries, being relegated mostly to the coastal Kannada-speaking region.Sastri (1955), pp. 359&ndash;360 Works of enduring quality were still produced by maverick authors such as Ratnakaravarni (1557), though their numbers were fewer.Shiva Prakash (1997), pp. 210&ndash;211Sahitya Akademi (1987), pp. 453&ndash;454 
 
Contemporaneous to these developments, Nagavarma II wrote his Kannada grammar ''Karnataka bhashabhushana'' ("Ornament of Karnataka language", 1042 or 1145). A milestone in the history of Kannada literature, it helped consolidate the language as competitor to established languages such as Sanskrit and Prakrit, bringing the local language within the realm of literary cosmopolitanism.Nagaraj (2003), p. 327 Writing a Kannada grammar in Sanskrit language was essential to Nagavarma II, a subtle rebuttal to Sanskritic scholars of the day who may have considered Kannada a language of the common man and its grammar as underdeveloped. In addition to the Chalukya patronage, Kannada poets and writers of this period were popular in the courts of neighbouring kingdoms of the western Deccan. The Hoysalas, the southern Kalachuris, the Seunas, the Gangas and the Silharas are some of the ruling families who enthusiastically used Kannada in inscriptions and promoted its literature.Sen (1999), p. 409Narasimhacharya (1988), p. 68Kamath (2001) pp. 49&ndash;50, 132&ndash;134, 143&ndash;144
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ab5c6ccebc1280e354d8550082643dac" name="Chavundaraya_Poet_Handwriting" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/ab5c6ccebc1280e354d8550082643dac.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>