<document id="822116cc0f6a0a81d8a83d13ae6d35f4-3" name="Bath_School_disaster" cat="14">
<text>
The American Red Cross, setting up operations at the Crum drugstore, took the lead in providing aid and comfort to the victims. The Lansing Red Cross headquarters were kept open until 11:30 that night to answer telephone calls, update the list of dead and injured and provide information and planning services for the following day.


The Red Cross also managed donations sent to pay for both the medical expenses of the survivors and the burial costs of the deceased. In a few short weeks, $5,284.15 was raised through donations, including $2,500 from the Clinton County board of supervisors and $2,000 from the Michigan legislature. Unlike the Columbine High School massacre later that century, there was no legislative response, either by the state or federal governments, aimed at preventing a recurrence, although pyrotol was quietly taken off the market.

Over the next few days there were multiple funerals, with the most, eighteen, held on Saturday, May 22. The disaster made the front pages of national newspapers and remained there until news of  Michigan native Charles Lindbergh's completion of first solo transatlantic flight broke on May 23, 1927.

Vehicles from outlying areas and surrounding states descended upon Bath by the thousands. Over 100,000 vehicles passed through on Saturday alone, an enormous amount of traffic for the area. Some Bath citizens regarded this armada as an unwarranted intrusion into their time of grief, but most accepted it as a show of sympathy and support from surrounding communities. The Ku Klux Klan interjected that as a Roman Catholic, Kehoe's actions were the result of his adherence to the stance of the Roman Catholic Church against "Protestant or godless schools."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c889bf2d69d871b8c9ff5ce0e0cb3d0d" name="Bath_School_clean-up_crew" sectnum="3#1">../img/c889bf2d69d871b8c9ff5ce0e0cb3d0d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>