<document id="823f992256bb21ac8266c72d23e2119d-2.4" name="k-os" cat="20">
<text>
On February 20, 2007, he performed "Sunday Morning" on the Late Show With David Letterman.

''Crabbuckit'' can be heard in the trailer for the 2007 blockbuster ''Shrek the Third''.

In 2007, k-os toured with P.O.S., RX Bandits, and Gym Class Heroes on The Darryl Hall For President Tour

His 2007 single "Born To Run" was featured in the soundtrack for FIFA 08.

His song CatDieseL is featured in the opening of an episode of CSI: Miami titled Bloodline.

Instrumental versions of 'Sunday Morning' and 'Black Ice (Hymn 4 Disco) were featured in the soundtrack for Tiger Woods PGA Tour 08 

His 4th studio album, entitled ''Yes!'', was released on April 14, 2009. The first single off the album, , was released in December 2008. The second single, "Burning Bridges", was released in April 2009. While "I Wish I Knew Natalie Portman" was released as the third single in July 2009.

K-Os also held an online contest in 2008-2009 at http://www.indabamusic.com/ in which he provided the public with 11 tracks from the album "Yes!" to be remixed. At the end of the contest, the most voted remixes of each song were selected to be on a remix album of "Yes!" entitled, "Yes It's Yours (Fan Remix Album)" which is set to be released in the Spring of 2009. The 11 contest winners were also awarded $1000 each. 
http://www.indabamusic.com/studio_access/kos?utm_source=Indaba+Members&utm_campaign=c4d93199a8-K_OS_Blast_11_18_2008&utm_medium=email.

In April 2009, k-os began the groundbreaking Karma Tour across Canada. For this tour, no advance tickets are sold. Fans are simply asked to donate what they think the show was worth as they leave the venue. Entry is on a first-come, first-serve basis.http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20090429.AKOS29ART1630/TPStory/TPEntertainment/Music/

In October 2009, k-os is pairing up with the Stephen Lewis Foundation and their campaign  to raise money for HIV/AIDS affected families in Africa. The musician will return to his old job at The Bay and will help customers select toys in the store's toy department.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ab0f5199c48f0346921200763424f215" name="K-os07" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/ab0f5199c48f0346921200763424f215.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>