<document id="829442aa166ca0372f66113c5c0d775d-5.11" name="Robert_Falcon_Scott" cat="14">
<text>
Scott's reputation survived the period after World War II, beyond the 50th anniversary of the disaster in 1962.Jones, pp. 287–89 A few years after that, Reginald Pound, the first biographer given access to Scott's original sledging journal, revealed personal failings which cast a new light on Scott, although Pound continued to endorse his heroism, writing of "a splendid sanity that would not be subdued".Pound, pp. 285–86 Within the following decade further books appeared, each of which to some degree challenged the prevailing public perception. The most critical of these was  David Thomson's ''Scott's Men'' (1977); in Thomson's view Scott was not a great man, "at least, not until near the end";Thomson, Preface, p. xiii his planning is described as "haphazard" and "flawed",Thomson, p. 153 and p. 218 his leadership characterized by lack of foresight.Thomson, p. 233 Thus by the late 1970s, in Jones's words: "Scott's complex personality had been revealed and his methods questioned." 
 
In 1979 came the most sustained attack on Scott, from Roland Huntford's dual biography ''Scott and Amundsen'' in which Scott is depicted as a "heroic bungler".Huntford, p. 527 Huntford's thesis had an immediate impact, becoming the new orthodoxy.Jones, p. 8 Even Scott's heroism in the face of death is challenged; Huntford sees Scott's Message to the Public as a deceitful self-justification from a man who had led his comrades to their deaths. After Huntford's book, debunking Captain Scott became commonplace; Francis Spufford, in a 1996 history  not wholly antagonistic to Scott, refers to "devastating evidence of bungling",Spufford, p. 5 concluding that  "Scott doomed his companions, then covered his tracks with rhetoric".Spufford, pp. 104–05 Travel writer Paul Theroux summarised Scott as "confused and demoralised ... an enigma to his men, unprepared and a bungler".Quoted in Barczewski, p. 260 This decline in Scott's reputation was accompanied by a corresponding rise in that of his erstwhile rival Shackleton, at first in the United States but eventually in Britain as well.Barczewski, p. 283. A 2002 nationwide poll in the United Kingdom to discover the "100 Greatest Britons" showed Shackleton in eleventh place, Scott well down the list at 54th. 

However, the early years of the 21st century have seen a shift of opinion in Scott's favour, in what cultural historian Stephanie Barczewski calls "a revision of the revisionist view."Barczewski, pp. 305–311  Meteorologist Susan Solomon's 2001 account ''The Coldest March'' ties the fate of Scott's party to the extraordinarily adverse Barrier weather conditions of February and March 1912 rather than to personal or organizational failings, although Solomon accepts the validity of some of the criticisms of Scott.Solomon, pp. 309–327; see also Barczewski, p. 306 In 2004 polar explorer Sir Ranulph Fiennes published a biography which was a strong defence of Scott and an equally forthright rebuttal of Huntford; the book is dedicated "To the Families of the Defamed Dead".Fiennes's book was published in the United States as ''Race to the Pole: Tragedy, Heroism and Scott's Antarctic Quest''. Barczewski, p. 378. Fiennes was later criticised for the personal nature of his attacks on Huntford, and for his apparent assumption that his own experiences as a polar explorer gave him unique authority. 

In 2005 David Crane published a new Scott biography which, according to Barczewski, goes some way towards an assessment of Scott "free from the baggage of earlier interpretations." What has happened to Scott's reputation, Crane argues, derives from the way the world has changed since the heroic myth was formed: "It is not that we see him differently from the way they  did, but that we see him the same, and instinctively do not like it."Crane, p. 11 Crane's main achievement, according to Barczewski, is the restoration of Scott's humanity, "far more effectively than either Fiennes's stridency or Solomon's scientific data." ''Daily Telegraph'' columnist Jasper Rees, likening the changes in explorers' reputations to climatic variations, suggests that "in the current Antarctic weather report, Scott is enjoying his first spell in the sun for twenty-five years."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="42ac249aa3c950daf06e56cb1804e7b4" name="Scott_memorial_binton" sectnum="5.11#1">../img/42ac249aa3c950daf06e56cb1804e7b4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>