<document id="829442aa166ca0372f66113c5c0d775d-1.2" name="Robert_Falcon_Scott" cat="14">
<text>
In July 1883 Scott passed out of ''Britannia'' as a midshipman, seventh overall in a class of 26.Crane, p. 23 By October he was en route to South Africa to join HMS ''Boadicea'', the flagship of the Cape squadron, the first of several ships on which he served during his midshipman years. While stationed in St Kitts, West Indies, on HMS Rover, he had his first encounter with Sir Clements Markham, then Secretary of the Royal Geographical Society (RGS), who would loom large in Scott's later career. On this occasion, 1 March 1887, Markham observed Midshipman Scott's cutter winning that morning's race across the bay.  Markham's habit was to "collect" likely young naval officers with a view to their undertaking polar exploration work in the future. He was impressed by Scott's intelligence, enthusiasm and charm, and the 18-year-old midshipman was duly noted.Crane, p. 82
 
Later that year, Scott attended the Royal Naval College at Greenwich and in March 1888 passed his examinations for Sub-Lieutenant, with four First Class certificates out of five.Crane, p. 34  His career progressed smoothly, with service on various ships and promotion to Lieutenant in 1889. In 1891, after a long spell in foreign waters, he applied for the two-year torpedo training course on HMS ''Vernon'', an important career step. He graduated with First Class certificates in both the theory and practical examinations. A small blot occurred in the summer of 1893 when, while commanding a torpedo boat, Scott managed to run it aground, which earned him a mild rebuke.Crane, p.50

During the research for his dual biography of Scott and Roald Amundsen,''Scott and Amundsen'', later republished as ''The Last Place On Earth''. See '''Sources''' section. Roland Huntford got wind of a possible scandal in Scott's early naval career, but was unable to pin it down. He focuses on the period 1889&ndash;90 when Scott was a lieutenant on HMS ''Amphion''. According to him Scott "disappears from naval records" for eight months, from mid-August 1889 until 24 March 1890. Huntford hints at involvement with a married American woman, of cover-up, and protection from senior officers. David Crane reduces the missing period to eleven weeks, but is unable to throw much more light other than scorning the notion of protection by senior officers, on the grounds that Scott was not important or well-connected enough to warrant this. Documents that may have offered explanations are missing from Admiralty records.Huntford, pp. 121&ndash;23, and Crane, footnote pp. 39&ndash;40

In 1894, while serving as Torpedo Officer on the depot ship HMS ''Vulcan'', Scott learned of the financial calamity that had overtaken his family. John Scott, having sold the brewery and invested the proceeds unwisely, had lost all his capital and was now virtually bankrupt. Fiennes, p. 21 At the age of 63, and in poor health, he was forced to take a job as a brewery manager and move his family to Shepton Mallet, Somerset. Just three years later, while son Robert was serving as torpedo lieutenant aboard the Channel squadron flagship HMS Majestic, John Scott died of heart disease, creating a fresh family crisis.Fiennes, p. 22  The family &ndash; mother and two unmarried daughters &ndash; now relied entirely on the service pay of Scott and the salary of younger brother Archie, who had left the army for a post in the colonial service in order to increase his income. Archie's own death in the autumn of 1898, after contracting typhoid fever, thrust the whole financial responsibility for the family on to Scott.Fiennes, p. 23 

An ambitious officer, Scott now had an additional weight of domestic responsibility. The main thing that concerned him now was promotion, and the extra income this would bring.Crane, p. 59 Early in June 1899, while home on leave, he had a chance encounter in a London street with Sir Clements Markham (now the RGS President), and learned for the first time of a pending Antarctic expedition. It was an opportunity for early command and a chance to distinguish himself. Markham remembered him from St Kitts, and presumably said something encouraging, because a few days later, on 11 June, Scott appeared at the Markham residence and volunteered to lead the expedition.Crane, p. 82
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="69a6a606d3613e3edda522b6e6d15ce1" name="HMS_Britannia_Chambers_mg_0529" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/69a6a606d3613e3edda522b6e6d15ce1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>