<document id="829442aa166ca0372f66113c5c0d775d-4.6" name="Robert_Falcon_Scott" cat="14">
<text>
It was the expressed hope of the RGS that this expedition would be "scientific primarily, with exploration and the Pole as secondary objects"Crane, pp. 397&ndash;99  but, unlike the Discovery Expedition, neither they nor the Royal Society were in charge this time. In his expedition prospectus Scott stated plainly that its main objective was "to reach the South Pole, and to secure for the British Empire the honour of this achievement".In the narration, Ponting says that Scott set out from the London docks with "enthusiasm for achievement for the honour of his country." Scott had, as Markham observed, been "bitten by the Pole mania". Thus, despite its having "the largest and most efficient scientific staff that ever left England",Cherry-Garrard, p. 608 Scott had made it clear that, on this second expedition, the priority lay with the Pole, and with getting there first. Later, however, claims would be made that the race to the pole was lost because Scott refused to compromise his scientific programme For example, Cherry-Garrard, p. 608, says: "We were primarily a great scientific expedition", and, p. 275, "We travelled for science". See also Markham's preface to L. Huxley, Vol. I 


Scott did not know that he would be in a race for the Pole until he received Amundsen's telegram in Melbourne, in October 1910.Crane, pp. 425&ndash;28  Before this he had set about fashioning the expedition according to his own preferences, without the restraints of a joint committee. In the decisions that he made with regard to the expedition's methods of travel on the ice he showed that his prejudices against dogs had not faded. They were to be merely one element in a complicated transport strategy that also involved horses and motor sledges and much man-hauling. Scott knew nothing of horses, but felt that as they had seemingly served Shackleton well, he ought to use them.Preston, p. 107. Also Crane, pp. 432&ndash;33  Dogs expert Cecil Meares was going to Siberia to select the dogs, and Scott ordered that, while he was there, he should deal with the purchase of Manchurian ponies. Huntford, on p. 305, implies that Oates, who had much experience with horses, should have been sent to choose them. But Meares left England for Siberia in January 1910, and Oates was not available to the expedition until May Huntford, p.262 Meares was not an experienced horse-dealer, and the ponies he chose proved mostly of poor quality, and ill-suited to prolonged Antarctic work.Preston, p. 113 Meanwhile Scott spent time in France and Norway, testing motor-sledges, and recruited Bernard Day, from Shackleton's expedition, as his motor expert.Preston, p. 112
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="46183d183099d69e004f77ad3bb6e8c5" name="Cape_Evans_-_Antarctica" sectnum="4.6#1">../img/46183d183099d69e004f77ad3bb6e8c5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>