<document id="829442aa166ca0372f66113c5c0d775d-4.8" name="Robert_Falcon_Scott" cat="14">
<text>
The march south began on 1 November 1911, a complex caravan of mixed transport groups (motors, dogs, horses), with loaded sledges, travelling at different rates, all designed to support a final group of four men who would make a dash for the Pole. Scott had earlier outlined his plans for the southern journey to the entire shore party,Huxley, Vol I, p. 407 without being specific as to precise roles – no one knew, for instance, who would form the final polar team. There was continuing uncertainty about how he proposed to use the dogs, a variety of different orders being issued which left it unclear whether they were to be saved for future scientific journeys, or were to assist the polar party home.In his foreword to the 1965 edition of Cherry-Garrard's ''Worst Journey'', George Seaver gives a concise account of the muddle that arose from the conflicting orders given at different times concerning the use of dogs. Cherry-Garrard, pp. 30&ndash;32 The consequence was that his subordinates back at base were confused and uncertain as to how they should act, and failed to use the dogs in a concerted attempt to relieve the returning polar party when the need arose.See Atkinson's account in L. Huxley, Vol II, pp. 298&ndash;306

The southbound party continued, steadily reducing in size as the support teams turned back. By 4 January 1912 the last two four-man groups had reached 87°34'S.L. Huxley, Vol I, p. 528  Scott announced his decision: five men (Scott, Edward Wilson, H. R. Bowers, Lawrence Oates and Edgar Evans) would go forward, the other three (Teddy Evans, William Lashly and Tom Crean) would return.Exactly when Scott decided on a five-man polar party is uncertain. On the first page of the fresh journal started on 22 December 1911 &ndash;two weeks before the polar party was chosen &ndash; Scott lists the five names of those eventually selected, but the list is not itself dated and could have been written later. L. Huxley, Vol I p. 514  The chosen group marched on, reaching the Pole on 17 January 1912, only to find that Amundsen had preceded them by five weeks. Scott's anguish is indicated in his diary: "The worst has happened";  "All the day dreams must go"; "Great God! This is an awful place".L. Huxley, Vol I, pp. 543&ndash;44
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6c1f8577e0f87c8d720da5dc3a50a952" name="Robert_Falcon_Scott_by_Herbert_Ponting" sectnum="4.8#1">../img/6c1f8577e0f87c8d720da5dc3a50a952.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>