<document id="82d3769219f0f4935fd9424d352132bc-5" name="Hugh_Trumble" cat="26">
<text>
Trumble joined the National Bank of Australasia in 1887 to begin a career in banking. While the bank often allowed him time to practice, his frequent absences with cricket meant his career progression was slow; after each of his five tours of England he returned to find junior bank officers promoted over him.  Nevertheless, he was appointed accountant at the Richmond branch in 1903 and after his retirement from cricket in 1908, manager of the Kew branch.

A loyal clubman, Trumble served on the committee of the Melbourne Cricket Club (MCC) from 1900–01 to 1910–11 and was made a life member in 1904. In 1911 he resigned from the bank to become MCC club secretary; a position he held for 27 years until his death.  In this role, he played a leading part in reconciling the club and the Victorian Cricket Association after a period of some friction between the two bodies.  He was instrumental in attracting quality cricketers to the club including Bert Ironmonger, whom Trumble saw play on a visit to Queensland. During his term as secretary, the Melbourne Cricket Ground was expanded to a capacity of over 70,000 spectators.

Trumble was a prominent writer about and elder statesman of the game and was conspicuous in his support for journalists calling at any hour.  From time to time, Trumble acted as a selector of the Victorian cricket team.Haigh, p. 200.  In 2001, Trumble was selected in the Melbourne Cricket Club Team of the Century, and in 2004 he was inducted into the Australian Cricket Hall of Fame for his contribution to the sport in Australia.

In 1899, aged 31, Trumble met and fell in love with Florence Christian, aged 19 from Queensland.  The couple were married in 1902, with the wedding timed to allow a honeymoon trip accompanying the Australian cricket tour of England.  An injury to his thumb freed Trumble from cricket commitments for a while, to his new wife's delight. Together, the couple had eight children; six sons and two daughters. One son, Robert, a renowned musician and writer, dedicated his first book, ''The Golden Age of Cricket'', to his father. Trumble died aged 71, from a heart attack in his home in the Melbourne eastern suburb of Hawthorn.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="478c23d73c8f77b44e96d3cfeca05ed6" name="HughTrumbleOlder" sectnum="5#1">../img/478c23d73c8f77b44e96d3cfeca05ed6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>