<document id="82d3769219f0f4935fd9424d352132bc-2.3" name="Hugh_Trumble" cat="26">
<text>
At the age of 34, Trumble was chosen to captain the Australian team against England in 1901–02 when Joe Darling withdrew to manage his farm in Tasmania after the first three Tests.  Australia won the two remaining Tests—the only occasions that Trumble would captain his country in Test cricket—to win the series four Tests to one.  Earlier, in the Second Test at the Melbourne Cricket Ground, Trumble took a "hat-trick"; only five hat-tricks had been taken in the previous 24 years of Test cricket. He dismissed Arthur Jones, John Gunn and Sydney Barnes in successive balls to complete an Australian victory by 229 runs.Meher-Homji, p. 28.  In the Third Test in Adelaide, Trumble captured 6 wickets for 74 runs in the England second innings and made 62 not out to help the Australians win the match by 4 wickets. After this success with the bat, Trumble&mdash;in his new role as captain&mdash;promoted himself to open the batting alongside Victor Trumper.  He made only 6 runs, handing the opening batsman role to Reggie Duff for the second innings. Australia won the Test by 7 wickets with Trumble not required to bat a second time.  In the Fifth Test, again in Melbourne, Trumble took 5 wickets for 62 runs to help restrict England to a lead of 45 runs after the first innings.  In the second innings Trumble took another 3 wickets and, combined with Noble's 6 wickets, helped Australia win by 32 runs. Trumble and Noble were the most successful Australian bowlers during the series. Together they took 60 wickets in the Tests: Noble 32 at an average of 19.00 and Trumble 28 at an average of 20.03.


Trumble's last cricketing tour of England was in 1902, with Darling returning to captain the Australian team.  Early in the tour, Trumble broke his thumb at practice, causing him to miss the first month of the English season.  Despite this, when he returned for the final three Tests he took 26 wickets.  In the Fourth Test at Old Trafford, Trumble took 10 wickets. This included 6 wickets in the second innings when he combined with Jack Saunders to bowl England out for 120; securing an Australian victory by 3 runs.  Trumble, recalling his final over of the match, said "With the ball greasy  and my boots unable to get a proper foothold on slippery turf, it was the most trying over I ever bowled."   In the Fifth Test at The Oval, Trumble made 64 runs in the first innings and followed this with 8 wickets for 65 runs in the English first innings.  He took another 4 wickets in the English second innings, but this was not sufficient to prevent an English victory by one wicket.  Darling bowled Trumble unchanged from the Pavilion end throughout both innings of the match.  ''Wisden'' praised Trumble's bowling saying "Trumble, paying us his fifth visit, bowled perhaps better than ever", but remarked that "it must be said that the wet weather and soft wickets were all in his favour"

After playing in one Test match against the South African team on a stopover when returning from England to Australia, Trumble retired from Test cricket, aged 35.  When Australia lost to the English tourists in the First Test in Sydney in 1903–04, Trumble was persuaded to return for the Second Test under the captaincy of Noble.  He was immediately successful taking 4 wickets for 107 runs in the first innings and 5 for 34 in the second, but was unable to prevent England from winning the Test by 185 runs Selected for the remaining four Tests, his 24 wickets in four Tests made Trumble the most successful Australian bowler in the series. The writer Roland Perry described Trumble's final Test match as "the most dramatic and memorable farewell performance ever by a bowler". In front of his home town supporters in Melbourne, he took 7 wickets for 28 runs, including a hat-trick, to bowl Australia to victory; ''Wisden'' describing his bowling in the second innings as "practically unplayable".  The hat-trick, his second in Test cricket, consisted of the dismissals of Bernard Bosanquet, Plum Warner and Dick Lilley.  He went on to take the wicket of Ted Arnold, ending the match and his career in international cricket.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6b2a6f92ccf77be15de9cb3f12bbbb95" name="1902AusTeam" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/6b2a6f92ccf77be15de9cb3f12bbbb95.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>