<document id="82d3769219f0f4935fd9424d352132bc-3" name="Hugh_Trumble" cat="26">
<text>
Trumble was tall and thin,  in height. His long face featured prominent ears and a large nose, while his long arms and uncommonly long and strong fingers assisted his bowling.Pollard (1988), pp. 1069–1071.  The cricket writer Ray Robinson said of Trumble: "El Greco, with his lengthening touch would have liked to draw Trumble.  Hugh's lantern shaped head set on a column of a neck would have given the Spaniard a halfway start."  English cricketer and author Plum Warner called him "That great camel, Hughie Trumble."


When bowling, Trumble made the most of his height, bringing the ball over the full extent of his right arm.  His action was described by his team-mate and bowling partner, Monty Noble, as "sidelong and insinuating, with his neck craned like a gigantic bird". He bowled off spinners with an impeccable length at medium pace and was able to swing the new ball.  He had a well-disguised slower ball, hoodwinking batsmen such as Stanley Jackson, who said, "You old devil. You get me caught-and-bowled whenever you like but I'll pick that slow one sooner or later."  He preferred English pitches, saying he hardly saw one on which he could not get some turn and the temperate weather allowed him to bowl all day.  In Australia, Trumble had to work harder for his wickets on firmer pitches, relying on his change of pace and consistent accuracy; he claimed he could land the ball on a saucer  away five times out of six.  Johnnie Moyes named him as an "immortal of the art" who succeeded by "attacking the batsman's strength".  W. G. Grace called him "the best bowler Australia has sent us".  While Trumble was able to score 1,183 runs during the 1899 tour of England, the demands of bowling did not allow him to consistently score heavily.  His long,  prehensile fingers helped him make a reputation as a fine slips fieldsman and he was the first to take 20 catches in an Australian season. English cricketer Johnny Douglas said, "Trumble should not be allowed on the cricket field—his natural place would be up trees in the bush."  He practised slip fielding by catching a tennis ball thrown against a brick wall; he believed this practise trained him not to "snatch" at the ball but allow it to fall into his safe hands. 

Trumble was known for his cleverness on the field.  C. B. Fry said of him, "He is the most long-headed, observant and acute judge of the game, a perfect master of the whole art of placing fieldsmen and changing bowlers."  On one occasion when captaining his state side, Victoria, he deliberately bowled two wides that his fieldsmen allowed to roll to the boundary to score four runs for his opponents. This was done in order to save his tired bowlers from having to bowl again immediately, as his opponents would have been required to follow-on (bat twice in a row), at the time compulsory.  When questioned by an onlooker about the dubious sportmanship of the action, he replied, "I had to do it, old chap, but I wonder what my father will think of it?"  Trumble was respected by his teammates and opponents; New Zealand cricketer, Dan Reese, who played against and alongside Trumble said, "His subtle humour, his fund of cricket stories, his kindness, and, above all, his judgment, made him a man of exceptional character."

He was popular with team-mates and opponents alike, with a weakness for practical jokes.  On board a ship travelling to England, Trumble offered to coach unsuspecting fellow travellers in various deck sports such as quoits.  Accepting Trumble's advice, they were made to contort themselves into a number of ludicrous positions to the amusement of his team-mates and other onlookers in the know.  To prolong the joke, in his own games Trumble would adopt the same peculiar stance and method he advocated.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="70fa2da2084e4eb7b46def49b5404375" name="TrumbleinAction" sectnum="3#1">../img/70fa2da2084e4eb7b46def49b5404375.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>