<document id="82d3769219f0f4935fd9424d352132bc-2.2" name="Hugh_Trumble" cat="26">
<text>
Trumble was selected in the Australian team to tour England in 1896, despite a poor domestic season in 1895–96 that saw his place in the touring squad seriously questioned by pundits.  The leading cricket journalist, Tom Horan said that as much as he personally liked Trumble, he could not see him as a member of a team for the England tour that season. It was, however, during this tour that Trumble finally established a permanent place in the Australian line up. ''Wisden'' said of Trumble when listing him as one of its Cricketers of the Year, "...it was not until his third visit, during the past season, that Trumble convinced Englishmen he was entitled to rank among the great bowlers of Australia".  In that season, Trumble took 148 wickets at an average of 15.81. He was seen as Australia's leading bowler who "was able to inspire  batsmen with a feeling of apprehension".  ''Wisden's'' summary of the 1896 Australian tour said of Trumble, "His great strength lay in the combination of spin with extreme accuracy" and "he was on all wickets distinctly the best bowler on the  side".

England won the First Test at Lord's by 6 wickets, Trumble taking one wicket in each innings. The Second Test at Old Trafford was more closely fought.  Despite K. S. Ranjitsinhji scoring a "marvellous" 154 and Tom Richardson "bowling in his finest form" the Australians managed to hold on for a 3 wicket victory. The Australians required 125 runs to win in their second innings and were expected to make this target easily.  Richardson's skilful bowling however saw Trumble and Kelly batting together with only 3 wickets in hand but with 25 runs still to make.  Against excellent bowling and in a tense atmosphere, the pair managed to bat Australia home with the last runs taking an hour to score, mainly in singles.  Trumble made 17 not out to follow his 24 runs in the first innings and his 4 wickets.  With the series tied at one Test apiece, the Third and final Test was played at The Oval in London.  On a pitch damaged by rain, the English batted first and were dismissed for 145.  Trumble took 6 wickets for 59 runs, including a 9-over spell of 5 wickets for 10 runs.  England fought back to bowl the Australians out for 119.  In turn, the Australians restricted England to 84 runs with Trumble taking 6 wickets for 30, to leave Australia requiring 111 runs in their second innings to win the match. Bobby Peel and Jack Hearne combined to bowl Australia out for 44 runs to win the Test by 66 runs and retain the Ashes for England .  In the three Tests, Trumble took 18 wickets at an average of 18.83 runs per wicket.

Trumble played in every Test of the 1897–98 series against the touring English, who were again captained by Stoddart.  England won the First Test in Sydney by 9 wickets with Trumble's 70 runs the highest score in the Australian first innings.  Under the captaincy of Harry Trott, Australia fought back to win the Second Test in Melbourne by an innings and 55 runs. Trumble took 8 wickets in the match and in partnership with Monty Noble bowled the English out for 150 runs in the second innings. Australia won the Third Test in Adelaide by an innings and 13 runs; Trumble made 37 runs in the Australian innings and took 1 wicket for the match. In the Fourth Test, Trumble combined with Clem Hill in a 165 run partnership for the seventh wicket, described by ''Wisden'' as the turning point in the innings.  Australia won the match by 8 wickets.  Australia won the Fifth Test and the series four Tests to one.  For the series overall, Trumble took 19 wickets at an average of 28.15 runs per wicket and scored 170 runs at an average of 36.20.

The 1899 Australian tour saw Trumble score 1,183 runs and take 142 wickets; he was only the second Australian, after George Giffen, to score 1,000 runs and take 100 wickets in an English season as part of a touring team.  In the Test series, Trumble took 15 wickets at an average of 25.00 and made 232 runs at an average of 38.66.  ''Wisden'' said of Trumble's batting that season, " played so consistently well as to make it clear that if he had not been a bowler he would have been a great batsman".  Dry pitches saw his bowling average fall off a little from the 1896 tour but ''Wisden'' stated that he "bowled quite as well as in 1896" and " never seemed easy to hit, and whenever the ground gave him least advantage ... he was deadly".  Australia won the Second Test by 10 wickets and with the other Tests finishing in draws, they retained the Ashes in a one Test to nil series victory.  Trumble played particularly well in the Third Test at Headingley, where he took 5 wickets for 60 runs and was the highest run-scorer in the Australian second innings with 56.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="30458054759212a176f088d1356b1bb6" name="HughTrumble1907" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/30458054759212a176f088d1356b1bb6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>