<document id="82dcb3edb6f2118f21c73bdbfd020c70-3.1" name="Deinonychus" cat="3">
<text>
In 1974 Ostrom published another monograph on the shoulder of ''Deinonychus'' in which he realized that the pubis that he had described was actually a coracoid – a shoulder element.Ostrom, John H. (1974). " The Pectoral Girdle and Forelimb Function of ''Deinonychus'' (Reptilia: Saurischia) : A Correction". '' Postilla, Peabody Museum of Natural History Bulletin '', 165:1-11. In that same year, another specimen of ''Deinonychus'' was excavated in Montana by a Harvard University expedition headed by Farish Jenkins. This discovery added several new elements; well preserved femurs, pubes, a sacrum, and better ilia, as well as elements of the pes and metatarsus. Ostrom described this specimen and revised his skeletal restoration of ''Deinonychus''. This time it showed the very long pubes, and Ostrom began to suspect that they may have even been a little retroverted like those of birds.

A skeleton of ''Deinonychus'' including bones from the original (and most complete) specimen can be seen on display at the American Museum of Natural History, with another specimen on display at the Museum of Comparative Zoology at Harvard University. The American Museum and Harvard specimens are from a different locality than the Yale specimens. Even these two skeletal mounts are lacking elements including the sterna, sternal ribs, furcula, and gastralia.

Even after all of Ostrom’s work, several small blocks of lime-encased material remained unprepared in storage at the American Museum. These consisted mostly of isolated bones and bone fragments, including the original matrix, or surrounding rock in which the specimens were initially buried. An examination of these unprepared blocks by Gerald Grellet-Tinner and Peter Makovicky in 2000 revealed an interesting, overlooked feature. Several long, thin bones identified on the blocks as ossified tendons (structures which helped stiffen the tail of ''Deinonychus'') turned out to actually represent gastralia (abdominal ribs). More significantly, a large number of previously unnoticed fossilized eggshells were discovered in the rock matrix which had surrounded the original ''Deinonychus'' specimen.

In a subsequent, more detailed report on the eggshells, Grellet-Tinner and Makovicky concluded that the egg almost certainly belonged to ''Deinonychus'', representing the first dromaeosaurid egg to be identified. Moreover, the external surface of one eggshell was found in close contact with the gastralia suggesting that ''Deinonychus'' might have brooded its eggs. This implies that ''Deinonychus'' used body heat transfer as a mechanism for egg incubation, and indicates an endothermy similar to modern birds. Further study by Gregory Erickson and colleagues finds that this individual was 13 or 14 years old at death and its growth had plateaued.  Unlike other theropods in their study of specimens found associated with eggs or nests, it had finished growing at the time of its death.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d02126341af84700344b3d77da822d00" name="Deinonychus_im_NHM_Wien" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/d02126341af84700344b3d77da822d00.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>