<document id="82dcb3edb6f2118f21c73bdbfd020c70-4.3" name="Deinonychus" cat="3">
<text>
''Deinonychus'' teeth found in association with fossils of the ornithopod dinosaur ''Tenontosaurus'' are quite common in the Cloverly Formation. Two quarries have been discovered that preserve fairly complete ''Deinonychus'' fossils near ''Tenontosaurus'' fossils. The first, the Yale quarry in the Cloverly of Montana, includes numerous teeth, four adult ''Deinonychus'' and one juvenile ''Deinonychus''. The association of this number of ''Deinonychus'' skeletons in a single quarry suggests that ''Deinonychus'' may have fed on that animal, and perhaps hunted it. Ostrom and Maxwell have even used this information to speculate that ''Deinonychus'' might have lived and hunted in packs. () The second such quarry is from the Antlers formation of Oklahoma. The site contains six partial skeletons of ''Tenontosaurus'' of various sizes, along with one partial skeleton and many teeth of ''Deinonychus''. One tenontosaur humerus even bears what might be ''Deinonychus'' tooth marks. Brinkman ''et al.'' (1998) point out that ''Deinonychus'' had an adult mass of 70-100 kilograms, whereas adult tenontosaurs were 1-4 metric tons. A solitary ''Deinonychus'' could not kill an adult tenontosaur, suggesting that pack hunting is possible.

A recent study by Roach and Brinkman has called into question the cooperative pack hunting behavior of ''Deinonychus'', based on what is known of modern carnivore hunting and the taphonomy of tenontosaur sites. Modern archosaurs (birds and crocodiles) and komodo dragons display little cooperative hunting; instead, they are usually either solitary hunters, or are drawn to previously killed carcasses, where much conflict occurs between individuals of the same species. For example, in situations where groups of komodo dragons are eating together, the largest individuals eat first and will attack smaller komodos that attempt to feed; if the smaller animal is killed, it is cannibalized. When this information is applied to the tenontosaur sites, it appears that what is found is consistent with ''Deinonychus'' having a komodo- or crocodile-like feeding strategy.  ''Deinonychus'' skeletal remains found at these sites are from subadults, with missing parts consistent with having been eaten by other ''Deinonychus''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3d503bd8630d9e74e4c7ddb9af621ca8" name="Deinonychus_NT" sectnum="4.3#1">../img/3d503bd8630d9e74e4c7ddb9af621ca8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>