<document id="82dcb3edb6f2118f21c73bdbfd020c70-4.5" name="Deinonychus" cat="3">
<text>
The identification in 2000 of a probable ''Deinonychus'' egg associated with one of the original specimens allowed comparison with other theropod dinosaurs in terms of egg structure, nesting, and reproduction. In their 2006 examination of the specimen, Grellet-Tinner and Makovicky examined the possibility that the dromaeosaurid had been feeding on the egg, or that the egg fragments had been associated with the ''Deinonychus'' skeleton by coincidence. They dismissed the idea that the egg had been a meal for the theropod, noting that the fragments were sandwiched between the belly ribs and forelimb bones, making it impossible that they represented contents of the animal's stomach. In addition, the manner in which the egg had been crushed and fragmented indicated that it had been intact at the time of burial, and was broken by the fossilization process. The idea that the egg was randomly associated with the dinosaur were also found to be unlikely; the bones surrounding the egg had not been scattered or disarticulated, but remained fairly intact relative to their positions in life, indicating that the area around and including the egg was not disturbed during preservation. The fact that these bones were belly ribs (gastralia), which are very rarely found articulated, supported this interpretation. All the evidence, according to Grellet-Tinner and Makovicky, indicates that the egg was intact beneath the body of the ''Deinonychus'' when it was buried. It is possible that this represents brooding or nesting behavior in ''Deinonychus'' similar to that seen in the related troodontids and oviraptorids, or that the egg was in fact inside the oviduct when the animal died.

Examination of the ''Deinonychus'' egg's microstructure confirms that it belonged to a theropod, since it shares characteristics with other known theropod eggs and shows dissimilarities with ornithischian and sauropod eggs. Compared to other maniraptoran theropods, the egg of ''Deinonychus'' is more similar to those of oviraptorids than to those of troodontids, despite studies which show the latter are more closely related to dromaeosaurids like ''Deinonychus''. While the egg was too badly crushed to accurately determine its size, Grellet-Tinner and Makovicky estimated a diameter of about 7 cm (2.7 in) based on the width of the pelvic canal through which the egg had to have passed. This size is similar to the 7.2 cm diameter of the largest ''Citipati'' (an oviraptorid) eggs; ''Citipati'' and ''Deinonychus'' also shared the same overall body size, supporting this estimate. Additionally, the thicknesses of ''Citipati'' and ''Deinonychus'' eggshells are almost identical, and since shell thickness correlates with egg volume, this further supports the idea that the eggs of these two animals were about the same size.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9c05d37771c4b163b5ad46eaa0a9034b" name="Deinonychus_Steveoc" sectnum="4.5#1">../img/9c05d37771c4b163b5ad46eaa0a9034b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>