<document id="82f0be3ca0030e751d8b527656a926df-2.7" name="Robert_Peake_the_Elder" cat="1">
<text>
In 1598, Francis Meres, in his ''Palladis Tamia'', included Peake on a list of the best English artists.Strong, "An Approach Through Inscriptions," 53. In 1612, Henry Peacham wrote in "The Gentlemans Exercise" that his "good friend Mr Peake", along with Marcus Gheeraerts, was outstanding "for oil colours".He also judged that Nicholas Hilliard and Isaac Oliver were "inferior to none in Christendom for the countenance in small" (miniature portraits). Edmond, ''Hilliard & Oliver'', 168. Ellis Waterhouse suggested that the genre of elaborate costume pieces was as much a decorative as a plastic art. He notes that these works, the "enamelled brilliance" of which has become apparent through cleaning, are unique in European art and deserve respect. They were produced chiefly by the workshops of Peake, Gheeraerts the Younger, and De Critz.Waterhouse, ''Painting in Britain'',  41. Sheeran detects the influence of Hilliard’s brightly patterned and coloured miniatures in Peake’s work and places Peake firmly in the "iconic tradition of late Elizabethan painting".

Sheeran believes that Peake's creativity waned into conservatism, his talent "dampened by mass production". He describes Peake's Cambridge portrait of "Prince Charles, as Duke of York" as poorly drawn, with a lifeless pose, in a stereotyped composition that "confirms the artist's reliance on a much repeated formula in his later years". Art historian and curator Karen Hearn, on the other hand, praises the work as "magnificent" and draws attention to the naturalistically rendered note pinned to the curtain. Peake painted the portrait to mark Charles’s visit to Cambridge on 3 and 4 March 1613, during which he was awarded an M.A.—four months after the death of his brother.Edmond, “New Light on Jacobean Painters”, 74. Depicting Prince Charles wearing the Garter and Lesser George, Peake here reverts to a more formal, traditional style of portraiture.Hearn calls it "a return to the frozen grandeur of mainstream continental court portraiture". Hearn, ''Dynasties'', 188. The note pinned to a curtain of cloth of gold, painted in trompe-l'œil fashion, commemorates Charles’s visit in Latin.The Latin inscription translates: "Charles, we the Muses, since you deigned to agree to both, have both welcomed you as our guest and painted you in humble duty. Visiting the University in the 10th year of his father's reign over England, on 4 March, he was enrolled in the ranks of the Masters and admitted in this Senate House by Valentine Carey Vice-Chancellor". Hearn, ''Dynasties'', 188. X-rays of the portrait reveal that Peake painted it over another portrait. Pentimenti, or signs of alteration, can be detected: for example, Charles’s right hand originally rested on his waist.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5872ddc698bf219cd991ab1a75e7acf6" name="Prince_Charles_the_Future_Charles_I_by_Robert_Peake,_1613._(University_of_Cambridge)" sectnum="2.7#1">../img/5872ddc698bf219cd991ab1a75e7acf6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>