<document id="82f0be3ca0030e751d8b527656a926df-1.1" name="Robert_Peake_the_Elder" cat="1">
<text>
Peake was born to a Lincolnshire family in about 1551.Hearn, ''Dynasties'', 186. He began his training on 30 April 1565 under Laurence Woodham,Edmond, ''Hilliard & Oliver'', 153. who lived at the sign of “The Key” in Goldsmith’s Row, Westcheap;"The Key" would have been a sign, identifying Woodham's shop and house, as was usual before street-numbering. he was apprenticed, three years after the miniaturist Nicholas Hilliard, to the Goldsmiths’ Company in London.It was once assumed that Peake was much younger than Hilliard: in 1969, art historian Roy Strong called him Hilliard’s “most important follower among the younger generation” (''The English Icon,'' 19). Edmond, "New Light on Jacobean Painters", 74. He became a freeman of the company on 20 May 1576. His son, William, later followed in his father's footsteps as a freeman of the Goldsmiths' Company and a portrait painter.Edmond, ''Hilliard & Oliver,'' 153. Peake’s training would have been similar to that of John de Critz and Marcus Gheeraerts the Younger, who may have been pupils of the Flemish artist Lucas de Heere.Waterhouse, ''Painting in Britain'', 43. 
 
Peake is first heard of professionally in 1576 in the pay of the Office of the Revels, the department that oversaw court festivities for Elizabeth I. When Peake began practising as a portrait painter is uncertain,Weiss (2001 and 2006) judges Peake's earliest attributed works to be the portraits of Arthur, Lord Grey de Wilton, and Humphrey Wingfield, dated 1587, following Strong's ''English Icon'' of 1969. The portrait of Anne Knollys attributed to Peake in the Berger Collection at the Denver Art Museum, however, bears Peake's characteristic inscription and is dated 1582. According to art historian Roy Strong, he was "well established" in London by the late 1580s, with a "fashionable clientèle".Strong, ''English Icon'', 225. Payments made to him for portraits are recorded in the Rutland accounts at Belvoir in the 1590s.Strong, "An Approach Through Inscriptions", 53.  A signed portrait from 1593, known as the “Military Commander”, shows Peake’s early style. Other portraits have been grouped with it on the basis of similar lettering. Its three-quarter-length portrait format is typical of the time.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="aab0525d60ef66fe90e3e89005ad8b92" name="Elizabeth_I,_Procession_Portrait." sectnum="1.1#1">../img/aab0525d60ef66fe90e3e89005ad8b92.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>