<document id="83b93b12ac43a2534833fd381cee2b85-4.5" name="Psittacosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
The integument, or body covering, of ''Psittacosaurus'' is known from a Chinese specimen, which most likely comes from the Yixian Formation of Liaoning. The specimen, which is not yet assigned to any particular species, was illegally exported from China, in violation of Chinese law, but was purchased by a German museum and arrangements are being made to return the specimen to China.Mayr, Gerald, Peters, D. Stephan, Plodowski, Gerhard & Vogel, Olaf. (2002). Bristle-like integumentary structures at the tail of the horned dinosaur ''Psittacosaurus''. ''Naturwissenschaften'' 89: 361–365.

Most of the body was covered in scales. Larger scales were arranged in irregular patterns, with numerous smaller scales occupying the spaces between them, similarly to skin impressions known from other ceratopsians, such as ''Chasmosaurus''. However, a series of what appear to be hollow, tubular bristles, approximately 16 centimeters (6.4 in) long, were also preserved, arranged in a row down the dorsal (upper) surface of the tail. However, according to some scientists "t present, there is no convincing evidence which shows these structures to be homologous to the structurally different ''Repenomamus giganticus'' preying on a juvenile ''Psittacosaurus''.}}} 
Another fossil from the Yixian Formation provides direct evidence of ''Psittacosaurus'' as a prey animal. One skeleton of ''Repenomamus robustus'', a large triconodont mammal, is preserved with the remains of a juvenile ''Psittacosaurus'' in its abdominal cavity. Several of the juvenile's bones are still articulated, indicating that the carnivorous mammal swallowed its prey in large chunks. This specimen is notable in that it is the first known example of Mesozoic mammals preying on live dinosaurs.Hu Yaoming, Meng Jin, Wang Yuanqing & Li Chuankui. (2005). Large Mesozoic mammals fed on dinosaurs. ''Nature'' 433: 149–152. Heavy predation on juvenile ''Psittacosaurus'' may have resulted in R-selection, the production of more numerous offspring to counteract this loss.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c2b3869bcb2c6c445b381fc4793479b4" name="Psittacosaurus_sibiricus_whole_BW" sectnum="4.5#1">../img/c2b3869bcb2c6c445b381fc4793479b4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>