<document id="83b93b12ac43a2534833fd381cee2b85-2.2" name="Psittacosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
''Psittacosaurus'' is the type genus of the family Psittacosauridae, which was also named by Osborn in 1923. Only one other genus, ''Hongshanosaurus'', is currently classified in this family alongside ''Psittacosaurus''.You Hailu, Xu Xing & Wang Xiaolin. (2003). A new genus of Psittacosauridae (Dinosauria: Ornithopoda) and the origin and early evolution of marginocephalian dinosaurs. ''Acta Geologica Sinica'' (English edition) 77(1): 15–20. Psittacosaurids were basal to almost all known ceratopsians except ''Yinlong'' and perhaps Chaoyangsauridae.Xu Xing, Forster, Catherine A., Clark, James M. & Mo Jinyou. (2006). A basal ceratopsian with transitional features from the Late Jurassic of northwestern China. ''Proceedings of the Royal Society of London: Biological Sciences''. 273: 2135–2140. doi:10.1098/rspb.2006.3566  While Psittacosauridae was an early branch of the ceratopsian family tree, ''Psittacosaurus'' itself was probably not directly ancestral to any other groups of ceratopsians. All other ceratopsians retained the fifth digit of the hand, a plesiomorphy or primitive trait, whereas all species of ''Psittacosaurus'' had only four digits on the hand. In addition, the ''antorbital fenestra'', an opening in the skull between the eye socket and nostril, was lost during the evolution of Psittacosauridae, but is still found in most other ceratopsians and in fact most other archosaurs. It is considered highly unlikely that the fifth digit or antorbital fenestra would evolve a second time.

Although many species of ''Psittacosaurus'' have been named, their relationships to each other have not yet been fully explored and no scientific consensus exists on the subject. The most recent and most detailed cladistic analysis was published by Alexander Averianov and colleagues in 2006:



It has been suggested that ''P. lujiatunensis'' is basal to all other species. This would be consistent with its earlier appearance in the fossil record.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fb069bab761fa4a35725c1b7a86554a5" name="Psittacosaurus_holotype" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/fb069bab761fa4a35725c1b7a86554a5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>