<document id="83b93b12ac43a2534833fd381cee2b85-1" name="Psittacosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
Different species of ''Psittacosaurus'' varied in size and specific features of the skull and skeleton, but shared the same overall body shape. The best-known species, ''P. mongoliensis'', reached 2 meters (6.5 ft) in length.Sereno, Paul C. (1997). Psittacosauridae. In: Currie, Philip J. & Padian, Kevin P. (Eds.). ''The Encyclopedia of Dinosaurs''. San Diego: Academic Press. Pp. 611–613. The maximum adult body weight was most likely over 20 kilograms (44 lb) in ''P. mongoliensis''.Erickson, Gregory M. & Tumanova, Tatyana A. (2000). Growth curve of ''Psittacosaurus mongoliensis'' Osborn (Ceratopsia: Psittacosauridae) inferred from long bone histology. ''Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society'' 130: 551–566. Several species approached ''P. mongoliensis'' in size (''P. major'', ''P. neimongoliensis'', ''P. xinjiangensis''),Sereno, Paul C, Zhao Xijin, Brown, Loren & Tan Lin. (2007). New psittacosaurid highlights skull enlargement in horned dinosaurs.  ''Acta Palaeontologica Polonica'' 52(2): 275-284.Russell, Dale A. & Zhao Xijin. (1996). New psittacosaur occurrences in Inner Mongolia. ''Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences'' 33: 637–648.Brinkman, Donald B., Eberth, David A., Ryan, M.J. & Chen Peiji. (2001). The occurrence of ''Psittacosaurus xinjiangensis'' Sereno and Chao, 1988 in the Urho area, Junggar basin, Xinjiang. ''Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences'' 38: 1781–1786. while others were somewhat smaller (''P. sinensis'', ''P. meileyingensis'').Sereno, Paul C., Zhao Xijin, Chang Zhengwu & Rao Chenggang. (1988). ''Psittacosaurus meileyingensis'' (Ornithischia: Ceratopsia), a new psittacosaur from the Lower Cretaceous of northeastern China. ''Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology'' 8: 366–377. ''P. ordosensis'' was the smallest known species, 30% smaller than ''P. mongoliensis''. The largest were ''P. lujiatunensis'' and ''P. sibiricus'', although neither was significantly larger than ''P. mongoliensis''.Zhou Changfu, Gao Keqin, Fox, Richard C. & Chen Shuihua. (2006). A new species of ''Psittacosaurus'' (Dinosauria: Ceratopsia) from the Early Cretaceous Yixian Formation, Liaoning, China. ''Palaeoworld'' 15: 100–114.Averianov, Alexander O., Voronkevich, Alexei V., Leshchinskiy, Sergei V. & Fayngertz, Alexei V. (2006). A ceratopsian dinosaur ''Psittacosaurus sibiricus'' from the Early Cretaceous of West Siberia, Russia and its phylogenetic relationships. ''Journal of Systematic Paleontology'' 4(4): 359–395.

The skull of ''Psittacosaurus'' was highly modified compared to other ornithischian dinosaurs of its time. The skull was extremely tall and short, with an almost round profile in some species. The portion in front of the orbit (eye socket) was only 40% of total skull length, shorter than any other known ornithischian. The lower jaws of psittacosaurs are characterized by a bulbous vertical ridge down the center of each tooth. Both upper and lower jaws sported a pronounced beak, formed from the ''rostral'' and ''predentary'' bones, respectively. The bony core of the beak may have been sheathed in keratin to provide a sharp cutting surface for cropping plant material. As the generic name suggests, the short skull and beak superficially resembled those of modern parrots. ''Psittacosaurus'' skulls shared several adaptations with more derived ceratopsians, such as the unique rostral bone at the tip of the upper jaw, and the flared jugal (cheek) bones. However, there was still no sign of the bony neck frill or prominent facial horns which would develop in later ceratopsians.*You Hailu & Dodson, Peter. (2004). Basal Ceratopsia. In: Weishampel, David B., Dodson, Peter, & Osmolska, Halszka (Eds.). ''The Dinosauria'' (2nd Edition). Berkeley: University of California Press. Pp. 478–493. Bony horns did protrude from the skull of ''P. sibiricus'', but these are thought to be an example of convergent evolution.

''Psittacosaurus'' postcranial skeletons were more typical of a 'generic' bipedal ornithischian. In ''P. mongoliensis'', similarly to other species, the forelimbs were only 58% as long as the hindlimbs, indicating that these animals were almost totally bipedal in life. There were only four digits on the manus ('hand'), as opposed to the five found in most other ornithischians (including all other ceratopsians). Overall, the four-toed hindfoot was very similar to many other small ornithischians.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="643af9f1ff65c0cceab700c58b395701" name="Psittacosaurus_mongoliensis_whole_BW" sectnum="1#1">../img/643af9f1ff65c0cceab700c58b395701.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>