<document id="841486c6b97c7bbf63661217b9d1c803-2" name="Jurassic_Park_(film)" cat="19">
<text>
*'''Sam Neill''' as '''Dr. Alan Grant''': A world renowned paleontologist excavating ''Velociraptor'' fossils in the Montana Badlands. He dislikes children, frightening one with a talon of a raptor, but he soon has to protect Hammond's grandchildren. Neill was Spielberg's original choice, but he was too busy. Spielberg then met Richard Dreyfuss and Kurt Russell, who were too expensive, and William Hurt turned down the role. Spielberg then pushed back filming a month to let Neill play the character: he wound up only having a weekend's break between filming ''Family Pictures'' and ''Jurassic Park''. Neill prepared for the role by meeting paleontologist Jack Horner.Shay, Duncan, p.71–5 Neill scarred his wrist filming the ''T. rex'' attack when the flare he held went off.
*'''Laura Dern''' as '''Dr. Ellie Sattler''': A paleobotanist and graduate student of Grant. Dern also met Horner and visited the Natural History Museum of Los Angeles County, learning to prepare a fossil. Sigourney Weaver was reportedly Spielberg's first choice, before landing with Dern.
*'''Jeff Goldblum''' as '''Dr. Ian Malcolm''': A mathematician and chaos theorist. He warns of the danger of resurrecting dinosaurs and becomes Hammond's main opposition. He also falls for Sattler, another in a long line of romantic interests. Goldblum was Spielberg's first choice, and he is a big fan of dinosaurs.Shay, Duncan, p.110–1 To prepare for his role, Goldblum met with James Gleick and Ivar Ekeland to discuss chaos theory.Jones, Alan. ''Cinefantastique'' Magazine, Vol.24, No.2, pg. 9, "Jurassic Park: Computer Graphic Dinosaurs"
*'''Ariana Richards''' as '''Alexis "Lex" Murphy''': Hammond's granddaughter, a vegetarian and self-professed computer hacker.
*'''Joseph Mazzello''' as '''Timothy "Tim" Murphy''': Lex's younger brother, into dinosaurs. He has read Grant's book.
*'''Richard Attenborough''' as '''John Hammond''': CEO of InGen and architect of Jurassic Park. ''Jurassic Park'' was Attenborough's first acting role since 1979's ''The Human Factor''.
*'''Wayne Knight''' as '''Dennis Nedry''': The disgruntled architect of Jurassic Park's computer systems. He is bribed by Biosyn agent Lewis Dodgson for $1.5 million to deliver frozen dinosaur embryos. For his character's death, Knight was shot with an air gun filled with K-Y Jelly to simulate the ''Dilophosaurus''s venomous spit. The jelly dyed the actor's hair purple, something which the actor would reminisce with the technician who shot the jelly at him when they discovered they were neighbours.
*'''Samuel L. Jackson''' as '''Ray Arnold''': The park's chief engineer. He switches off the main power to reboot the mainframe but unwittingly unleashes the raptors in doing so.
*'''Bob Peck''' as '''Robert Muldoon''': The park's game warden. He is concerned about the intelligence of the raptors and would have them all destroyed.
*'''Martin Ferrero''' as '''Donald Gennaro''': A lawyer who represents Hammond's concerned investors.
*'''B. D. Wong''' as '''Dr. Henry Wu''': The park's chief geneticist, who is responsible for making all the dinosaurs female and lysine deficient. He leaves during the storm.
*'''Gerald R. Molen''', the film's producer, cameoed as '''Gerry Harding''', the park's veterinarian, who appears to take care of the ''Triceratops''.
*'''Cameron Thor''' as '''Lewis Dodgson''': The head of InGen's rival corporation Biosyn in the novel. He only appears in the film to give Nedry a shaving cream can to put stolen embryos in before he goes to Jurassic Park.
*'''Dean Cundey''', the film's cinematographer, cameoed as the '''Dockworker''' to whom Nedry talks on the computer.
*'''Richard Kiley''', the voice of the car tour guide.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5fb1a68ed0ae9f4cc865dfaed2e264b7" name="JurassicParkcast" sectnum="2#1">../img/5fb1a68ed0ae9f4cc865dfaed2e264b7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>