<document id="84295419d9d180f246c38560d66adf8f-1.2" name="Chalukya_dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
Inscriptions are the main source of information about the Badami Chalukya history. Among them, the Badami cave inscriptions of Mangalesa (578), Kappe Arabhatta record of c. 700, Peddavaduguru inscription of Pulakesi II, the Kanchi Kailasanatha Temple inscription and Pattadakal Virupaksha Temple inscription of Vikramaditya II (all in  Kannada language) provide more evidence of the Chalukya language.Kamath (2001), p. 6, p. 10, p. 57, p. 59, p. 67Ramesh (1984), p. 76, p. 159, pp. 161&ndash;162 The Badami cliff inscription of Pulakesi I (543), the Mahakuta Pillar inscription of Mangalesa (595) and the Aihole inscription of Pulakesi II (634) are examples of important Sanskrit inscriptions written in old Kannada script.Kamath (2001), p. 59
The reign of the Chalukyas saw the arrival of Kannada as the predominant language of inscriptions along with Sanskrit, in areas of the Indian peninsula outside what is known as Tamilaham (Tamil country).Thapar, (2003), p. 326 Several coins of the Badami Chalukyas with Kannada legends have been found. All this indicates that Kannada language flourished during this period.Kamath (2001), pp. 12, 57, 67

Travelogues of contemporary foreign travellers have provided useful information about the Chalukyan empire. Hiuen-Tsiang, a Chinese traveller had visited the court of Pulakesi II. At the time of this visit, as mentioned in the Aihole record, Pulakesi II had divided his empire into three ''Maharashtrakas'' or great provinces comprising of 99,000 villages each. This empire possibly covered present day Karnataka, Maharashtra and coastal Konkan.Pulakesi II's ''Maharashtra'' extended from Nerbudda (Narmada river) in the north to Tungabhadra in the south (Vaidya 1924, p. 171)Kamath (2001), p. 60 Hiuen-Tsang, impressed with the governance of the empire observed that the benefits of king's efficient administration was felt far and wide. Later, Persian emperor Khosrau II exchanged ambassadors with Pulakesi II.From the notes of Arab traveller Tabari (Kamath 2001, p. 60)Chopra (2003), p. 75, part 1
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2a6ec535cd7871aadc810312cb2c0f8e" name="Xuanzang_w" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/2a6ec535cd7871aadc810312cb2c0f8e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>