<document id="84295419d9d180f246c38560d66adf8f-4" name="Chalukya_dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
The Aihole inscription of Pulakesi II (634) written by his court poet Ravikirti in Sanskrit language and Kannada script is considered as an excellent piece of poetry.Quote:"He deemed himself the peer of Bharavi and Kalidasa". An earlier inscription in Mahakuta, in prose is comparable to the works of Bana (Sastri, 1955, p. 312)Kamath (2001), p. 59 A few verses of a poetess named Vijayanaka who describes herself as the "dark Sarasvati" has been preserved. It is  possible that she may have been a queen of prince Chandraditya (a son of Pulakesi II).Sastri, 1955, p. 312 Famous writers in Sanskrit from the Western Chalukya period are Vijnaneshwara who achieved fame by writing Mitakshara, a book on Hindu law, and King Somesvara III, a noted scholar, who compiled an encyclopedia of all arts and sciences called ''Manasollasa''.The writing is on various topics including traditional medicine, music, precious stones, dance etc. (Kamath 2001, p.106)

From the period of the Badami Chalukyas, references are made to the existence of Kannada literature, though not much has survived.Sen (1999), p. 366 Inscriptions however refer to Kannada as the "natural language".Thapar (2003), p. 345 The Kappe Arabhatta record of c. 700 in ''tripadi'' (three line) metre is the earliest available work in Kannada poetics.Sahitya Akademi (1988), p. 1717 ''Karnateshwara Katha'', which was quoted later by Jayakirti, is believed to be a eulogy of Pulakesi II and to have belonged to this period.Chidananda Murthy in Kamath (2001), p. 67 Other probable Kannada writers, whose works are not extant now but titles of which are known from independent referencesSuch as Indranandi's ''Srutavatara'', Devachandra's ''Rajavalikathe'' (Narasimhacharya, 1934, pp. 4&ndash;5); Bhattakalanka's ''Sabdanusasana'' of 1604 (Sastri 1955, p.355) are Syamakundacharya (650), who is said to have authored the ''Prabhrita'', and Srivaradhadeva (also called Tumubuluracharya, 650 or earlier), the possible author of the ''Chudamani'' ("Crest Jewel"), a lengthy commentary on logic.Sastri (1955), p. 355Mugali (1975), p. 13Narasimhacharya (1988), p. 4

The rule of the Western and Eastern Chalukyas, however, is a major event in the history of Kannada and Telugu literatures respectively. By the 9th&ndash;10th centuries, Kannada language had already seen some of its most notable writers. The "three gems" of Kannada literature, Adikavi Pampa, Sri Ponna and Ranna belonged to this period.Sastri 1955, p. 356Chopra (2003), p. 196, part 1 In the 11th century, Telugu literature was born under the patronage of the Eastern Chalukyas with Nannaya Bhatta as its first writer.Sastri (1955), p. 367
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a1496f052d79d04c319c205fe69e6eb1" name="Aihole_inscription_of_Ravi_Kirti" sectnum="4#1">../img/a1496f052d79d04c319c205fe69e6eb1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>