<document id="848a7fe4308208dcc81794c133f2c0cc-4.7" name="Tanks_in_the_Spanish_Army" cat="29">
<text>
In 1943, the Spanish Army and government decided to replace much of its armor.  Tanks such as the Panzer I and T-26 were obsolete, as compared to newer tanks such as the Soviet T-34 and German Panther tank.  As a result, on 15 March 1943 Spain began to negotiate with the Wehrmacht over the acquisition of up to date materiel.  The petition asked for 250 Panzer IIIs and 100 Panzer IVs.  In return, the Germans instead offered a sale of 20 Panzer IVs and 10 Sturmgeschütz IIIs.  On 29 April, Spain accepted Germany's offer.Caballero (2006), p. 76  The Panzer IVs sold were of the ''Ausf.'' H variant, and arrived in Spain on 6 December 1943.Caballero (2006), pp. 77–78  The Panzer IV ''Ausf.'' H included the longer  tank gun, and the homogeneous  steel plate on the glacis.Jentz (2001), p. 13  As early as January 1944, Spain again began to negotiate with Germany for more equipment.  The new program revolved around the sale of 33 Panzer IVs, three of which would be of the command variant.  Another offer was made for 67 more Panzer IVs at a later date; a result, the two programs together summed up to a potential procurement of 100 Panzer IVs.Caballero (2006), pp. 79–80  Spain also suggested the purchase of a number of Tiger tanks, although this offer never amounted to anything serious.  Regardless, the program to acquire another 100 Panzer IVs never materialized.Caballero (2006), p. 82  The 20 Panzer IVs received in late 1943 were organized into two companies, distributed among two battalions in the armored regiment of the Brunete Armored Division.Manrique, ''La Brunete'', pp. 26–27

At the end of World War II, the Spanish Army counted on a tank force composed of 20 Panzer IVs, 10 StuG IIIs, 116 T-26s, 93 Panzer Is (including command vehicles), 60 CV-33s and 80 armored cars.  In 1949 the armored regiment was reorganized into two battalions of 60 T-26s, with two command Panzer Is, six combat versions of the Panzer I and two CV-33, which were used for reconnaissance, each.  A third battalion was composed of the 20 Panzer IVs, plus six Panzer Is.  The regiment numbered an estimated 1,500 personnel and 100 tanks.Manrique, ''La Brunete'', p. 31
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f1a8d308c5c21403f0fd3962f1feb0f1" name="Pz_IV_turret_zoomed" sectnum="4.7#1">../img/f1a8d308c5c21403f0fd3962f1feb0f1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>