<document id="848a7fe4308208dcc81794c133f2c0cc-2.1" name="Tanks_in_the_Spanish_Army" cat="29">
<text>
The first prototype development began in 1925.García (2008), p. 56  Produced in the Trubia Artillery Factory (''Fábrica de Artillería Trubia''), in Asturias,García (2008), p. 54 the tank was powered by a four cylinder Hispano-Suiza 40/50 engine, the same engine the Spanish Army's military trucks had been equipped with since 1915. Given the Spanish Army's opinion that the FT-17 was limited in firepower, the Trubia tank featured a special turret.  The turret was designed in two articulated halves, which could traverse independently, each armed with a machine gun.  Theoretically, if one of the machine guns jammed, the tank would still have another one to defend itself with.  Furthermore, the vehicle's hull was provided with firing ports, to allow the crew to fire from within the tank.García (2008), pp. 55–56  This prototype was put through a series of tests, and its success brought about the decision to continue development on a Spanish tank, leading to an improved Trubia tank design, known as the ''Modelo Trubia 75HP, tipo rápido, serie A'' (Model Trubia 75hp, fast tank, series A).de Mazarrasa (1998), pp. 99–101

While touring Europe for a second time, in an attempt to integrate foreign design trends into the new Trubia, Captain Ruiz de Toledo found a new type of track system in Germany.  Designed to avoid having problems with the tracks coming off the vehicle, the new design substituted the traditional tracks with a system which was held together by a lateral metal wall, with the roadwheels suspended from the chassis.García (2008), pp. 56–57  The track system was the most innovative and unique part of the new Trubia light tank.de Mazarrasa (1998), p. 101  Apart from the new tracks, the Trubia was to have a greater velocity (at least ) and greater road range than the FT-17.  While a new machine gun was installed on the glacis plate, the tank's crew was increased from two to three, which caused the hull to be enlarged; this also allowed the engine to be maintained from inside the vehicle, allowing the crew to fix small breakdowns in the field.García (2008), p. 57  To refrigerate the engine and the crew, a compressed air dispenser was installed inside the chassis.  This solved problems dealing with the crew's claustrophobia and the intake of gasses originating from the engine found in the FT-17, and made crewing the tank much more ergonomic.García (2008), pp. 57–58  The original  was replaced with a more powerful  Daimler four cylinder engine.  The transmission had four forward gears and four reverse gears.de Mazarrasa (1998), p. 102  The new tank proved satisfactory—and even bettered the French FT-17 in some aspects—and the Spanish Army ordered the construction of four prototypes.Manrique (2006), p. 292

The first prototype was manufactured in 1926.García (2008), pp. 58–59  A total of four prototypes were ordered, but production was slow and by 1928 only one of the tanks had been completed, while the other three prototypes were not armed.  The completed vehicle, called the Trubia A4, was sent to the Firing School where it was put through a series of tests.de Mazarrasa (1998), pp. 102–103  In 1931, a second prototype was completed, while the final two were completed in 1934.García (2008), p. 59  The original prototype was returned to the factory in 1935, to integrate a number of modernizations and to repair any damage which was done to the vehicle during the testing process.  The other three tanks were issued to the Milan Infantry Regiment, in Oviedo, where they continued testing.de Mazarrasa (1998), p. 103
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a5f23b7cf50c457506f94eda86d83e0c" name="Trubia" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/a5f23b7cf50c457506f94eda86d83e0c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>