<document id="848a7fe4308208dcc81794c133f2c0cc-3.4" name="Tanks_in_the_Spanish_Army" cat="29">
<text>
The first 50 T-26 tanks which arrived in Spain, under the command of Krivoshein, were crewed by Soviet personnel.  Nevertheless, the Soviet lieutenant colonel opened a training school in the town of Archena, near Cartagena, recruiting mainly truck and bus drivers from cities such as Madrid and Barcelona.  The next month, he opened a second school in Alcalá de Henares, north of Madrid.Candil (March 1999), p. 32  However, only Communist soldiers were allowed to crew Soviet tanks, and as a result the pool of soldiers to recruit from was narrow and often less adept drivers were picked over better ones, due to their political ideologies.  For example, in one instance a tank commander broke contact with the enemy because he had not learned how to fire his main gun.  Furthermore, at first, the Soviet trainers did not have interpreters to communicate with their Spanish students.Daley (March 1999), p. 43

With training underway, and the tanks quickly put into combat, the first 50 vehicles were organized into the Popular Army's first tank battalion.  The battalion was equipped with three tank companies (each company containing ten tanks) and a headquarters company; each company had three platoons, with three tanks a piece, and a command tank.  By mid-November a second battalion was organized.  Later that month, Krivoshein and his deputy (Major Greisser) were recalled to the Soviet Union and replaced by General Dmitry Pavlov.Candil (March 1999), pp. 32–33  In December 1936, General Pavlov organized new Soviet armored vehicles into an armored brigade, made up of four tank battalions and a reconnaissance company.Candil (March 1999), p. 33  This brigade, known as ''Brigada de Carros de Combate'' (Tank Brigade), was composed of 56 tanks and 68 other armored vehicles, and immediately saw combat around Madrid, including in the battles of Jarama and Guadalajara.  However, the brigade was used to support Republican infantry forces and not as a mobile armored group, and as a result its strategic role during the war was limited by its misuse.Pedraza (2003), p. 9  In July 1937, the brigade took part in the Battle of Brunete, the largest tank battle to that date in the war,Muñoz (2008), p. 55 with some 150 Republican tanks taking part.Pedraza (2003), p. 10  The battle was also one of the few examples during the Spanish Civil War of the use of tanks to exploit a penetration along the front.Manrique, ''La Brunete'', p. 5  However, the battle cost the Popular Army around 159 armored fighting vehicles.Pedraza (2003), pp. 10–11



After the Battle of Brunete, the brigade was reorganized into a new Spanish division, known as the ''División de Ingenios Blindados'' (Armored Vehicles Division).  This was composed of a tank brigade and an armored brigade; the latter was made up of lighter armored fighting vehicles, such as the BA-6.  It was put under the command of Spanish Colonel Sánchez Paredes.  By this time, most of the Soviet tankers had returned to the Soviet Union to provide information on mechanized warfare in Spain.  The only Soviet unit left was the heavy tank regiment, armed with brand new BT-5s which had not been used in combat yet.Pedraza (2003), p. 11  This regiment was crewed by both Soviet and veteran Spanish tankers, and was put under the command of Soviet Colonel Kondriatev.Candil (1999), p. 33; by the end of the war the heavy tank regiment lost all but one BT-5 tank.  It is said that the sole survivor was presented to Italian leader Benito Mussolini as a trophy after the Spanish Civil War.  Finally, the division also disposed of an infantry brigade and an anti-tank artillery company.  However, by this time the Republican military command had relegated the tank to the role of merely infantry support, dissuaded by the poor performance of Republican armor to that date.  The last major battle Republican armor would take part in was the Battle of the Ebro, in 1938.Pedraza (2003), p. 13

The Soviets deducted that although tank formations in Spain were not large enough to perform an ideal mechanized penetration of an enemy's lines,Daley (May 1999), p. 36 too large tank formations were also not ideal due to uneven terrain preventing their use en masse.  As a result, armored commanders like Pavlov considered the tank's best role to be infantry support.Hofmann (1998), p. 120  The Republican use of armor during the Spanish Civil War was not a good demonstration of deep mechanized battle.Hofmann (1998), p. 121
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6d89f4de3c08eb755ff1873c7eff10bc" name="Spanish_CV33_at_El_Goloso" sectnum="3.4#1">../img/6d89f4de3c08eb755ff1873c7eff10bc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>