<document id="8490d3b1a0d072e7c0cc913b6c5a36d9-2" name="Lince_(tank)" cat="29">
<text>
In 1984, the Spanish Ministry of Defense declared its intent to set aside 120 billion ''pesetas'' (1.1 billion dollars) for a future tank program and attracted interest from five foreign companies.El País, ''Cinco empresas compiten para cofabricar un carro de combate en España''  German company Krauss-Maffei and Spanish company Santa Bárbara presented a joint bid in mid-1984 that would produce a tank based on 1970s technology.  The French government proposed to cooperate with Spain in designing a tank complete with new technology&mdash;they would later develop this program on their own as the AMX-Leclerc. However, the French admitted that there would be restrictions placed on Empresa Nacional Santa Bárbara when it came to exporting the tank.Yarnóz, ''Francia propone a España la construcción conjunta de un nuevo carro de combate'', El País  The Italian government proposed a similar deal for a cooperative tank design. The American company General Dynamics and British company Vickers offered the M1 Abrams and Valiant, respectively; the Spanish government rejected their offers the following year because of the low likelihood of local production and export of the tank.  By late 1985, the only offers still under consideration were those from the German-Spanish collaboration and the French and Italian governments.Yarnóz, ''Serra descarta a EE UU y Reino Unido para cofabricar los nuevos carros'', El País



Krauss-Maffei's Lince bid provided the clearest technical designs.  The tank would be forty-nine tonnes and equipped with a 120-millimeter main gun.  It could fire this gun on the move and aim at targets with effectiveness in day and night operations.  Fitted with a 1,200 horsepower (894.84 kW) engine, the Lince could travel as fast as 70 kilometers per hour (43.50 mph) on the roads.Yarnóz, ''Técnicos españoles y alemanes han presentado el diseño del futuro carro de combate para el Ejército'', El País  Although heavily based on the Leopard 2A4, the Lince was smaller and lighter, trading protection for mobility.  Specifically, the Lince prioritised enhanced mobility over the irregular Spanish terrain.  Furthermore, size restrictions were imposed due to the existing capabilities of Spain's railroad and highway network.Candil, ''Carros de Combate'', p. 166  Although the reduced armor conflicted with the problems that the Spanish had with AMX-30E's thin armor,de Mazarrasa, ''Carro de Combate AMX-30E'', p. 77 the Lince used a multi-layer armor similar to that of the German Leopard 2A4, providing greater protection than standard armor for a similar weight.  The protection was further enhanced by the low profile turret, again similar to that of the Leopard 2A4.

In early 1986, the Ministry of Defense declared that it would choose a contract within a matter of months. News sources cited that Krauss-Maffei would most likely gain the contract, although the French might get it due to past and existing French armament contracts with Spain.Yarnóz, ''El Gobierno elegirá el mes próximo el carro de combate de los noventa'', El País  Apart from producing the French-designed AMX-30, the Spanish government also had a contract for Mirage F1 fighter planes and Puma utility helicopters in 1979.Kolodziej, ''France and the Arms Trade'',p. 59  In early 1987, France again offered Spain the contract to co-develop and co-produce the AMX-Leclerc. This time they added the lucrative term of joint export.Bassets, ''Francia ofrece a España la fabricación conjunta de un moderno carro de combate'', El País  Despite the offer and ongoing collaboration with the Italians,C., ''El INI y un ente público italiano firmarán un protocolo de colaboración'', El País Spanish investment in the German-Spanish Lince program grew up to 200 billion pesetas (1.8 billion dollars).  However, the Spanish government did not announce any winner for the contract. This indecision led Krauss-Maffei to freeze their bid for the Lince.  Krauss-Maffei also cited the loss of millions of dollars due to failures on part of Santa Bárbara Sistemas, who would manufacture the Lince.Yarzón, ''Fabricantes alemanes de armas critican el programa del futuro tanque español'', El País
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6969a35e47d309159080ead944cf8217" name="AMX30_afar" sectnum="2#1">../img/6969a35e47d309159080ead944cf8217.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>