<document id="84951c943faa2db40140ee004db22a25-1.2" name="Abbey_Theatre" cat="17">
<text>
Encouraged by the St Theresa's Hall success, Yeats, Lady Gregory, Æ, Martyn, and John Millington Synge founded the Irish National Theatre Society in 1903 with funding from Horniman.  At first, they staged performances in the Molesworth Hall.Mikhail, E. H. ''The Abbey Theatre: Interviews and Recollections', Rowman & Littlefield Publishers, October 1987. p. 97. ISBN 0-3892-0616-4 When the Hibernian Theatre of Varieties in Lower Abbey Street and an adjacent building in Marlborough Street became available after fire safety authorities closed the Hibernia, Horniman and William Fay agreed to buy and refit the space to meet the society's needs.McCormack, W. J. (ed.). ''The Blackwell Companion to Modern Irish Culture'', Blackwell Publishing, 28 January 2002. p. 7. ISBN 0-6312-2817-9 

On 11 May 1904, the society formally accepted Horniman's offer of the use of the building. As Horniman did not usually reside in Ireland, the royal letters patent required were granted in the name of Lady Gregory, although paid for by Horniman.  The founders appointed William Fay theatre manager, responsible for training the actors in the newly established repertory company. They commissioned Yeats' brother Jack to paint portraits of all the leading figures in the society for the foyer, and hired Sarah Purser to design stained glass for the same space.Frazier, p. 172.

On 27 December, the curtains went up on opening night. The bill consisted of three one-act plays, ''On Baile's Strand'' and ''Cathleen Ní Houlihan'' by Yeats, and ''Spreading the News'' by Lady Gregory.  On the second night, ''In the Shadow of the Glen'' by Synge replaced the second Yeats play.  These two bills alternated over a five-night run. Frank Fay, playing Cúchulainn in ''On Baile's Strand'', was the first actor on the Abbey stage.Hunt, p. 61.  Although Horniman had designed the costumes, neither she nor Lady Gregory were present. Horniman had returned to England.  In addition to providing funding, her chief role with the Abbey over the coming years was to organise publicity and bookings for their touring productions in London and provincial England. 

In 1905 without properly consulting Horniman, Yeats, Lady Gregory and Synge decided to turn the theatre into a limited liability company, the National Theatre Society Ltd.Richards, Shaun. ''The Cambridge Companion to Twentieth-Century Irish Drama'', Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, February, 2004. p. 63. ISBN 0-5210-0873-5  Annoyed by this treatment, she hired Ben Iden Payne, a former Abbey employee, to help run a new repertory company which she founded in Manchester.Butler Yeats, William. ''The Collected Letters of W. B. Yeats: Volume IV: 1905-1907'', Oxford: Oxford University Press, Republished 1996. p. 616. ISBN 0-1981-2684-0
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="71e113639475c968cb41919aa6c1cf1f" name="Lady_gregory" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/71e113639475c968cb41919aa6c1cf1f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>