<document id="84951c943faa2db40140ee004db22a25-1.3" name="Abbey_Theatre" cat="17">
<text>
The new Abbey Theatre found great popular success, and large crowds attended many of its productions. The Abbey was fortunate in having Synge as a key member, as he was then considered one of the foremost English-language dramatists.  The theatre staged many plays by eminent or soon-to-be eminent authors, including Yeats, Lady Gregory, Moore, Martyn, Padraic Colum, George Bernard Shaw, Oliver St John Gogarty,  F. R. Higgins, Thomas MacDonagh, Lord Dunsany, T. C. Murray, James Cousins and Lennox Robinson.  Many of these authors served on the board, and it was during this time that the Abbey gained its reputation as a writers' theatre.



The Abbey's fortunes worsened in January 1907 when the opening of Synge's ''The Playboy of the Western World'' resulted in civil disturbance.  The troubles (since known as the ''Playboy Riots'') were encouraged, in part, by nationalists who believed the theatre was insufficiently political and who took offence at Synge's use of the word 'shift', as it was known at the time as a symbol representing Kitty O'Shea and adultery, and hence was seen as a slight on the virtue of Irish womanhood.Price, Alan ''Synge and Anglo-Irish Drama'', London: Methuen, 1961. pp. 15, 25. Much of the crowd rioted loudly, and the actors performed the remainder of the play in dumbshow.Isherwood, Charles. "A Seductive Fellow Returns, but in a Darker Mood", ''New York Times'', 28 October 2004.  The theatre's decision to call in the police further roused anger of the nationalists.  Although press opinion soon turned against the rioters and the protests faded, management of the Abbey was shaken.  They chose not to stage Synge's next&mdash;and last completed&mdash;play, ''The Tinker's Wedding'' (1908), for fear of further disturbances.  That same year, the Fay brothers' association with the theatre ended when they emigrated to the United States; Lennox Robinson took over the Abbey's day-to-day management. 

In 1909, Shaw's ''The Shewing-Up of Blanco Posnet'' led to further protests.  The subsequent discussion occupied a full issue of the theatre's journal ''The Arrow''.  Also that year, the proprietors decided to make the Abbey independent of Annie Horniman, who had indicated a preference for this course.  Relations with Horniman had been tense, partly because she wished to be involved in choosing which plays were to be performed and when. As a mark of respect for the death of King Edward VII, an understanding existed that Dublin theatres were to close on the night of 7 May 1910.  Robinson, however, kept the Abbey open.Leland, Mary. ''The Lie of the Land: Journeys Through Literary Cork'', Cork: Cork University Press, 2000. p. 238. ISBN 1-8591-8231-3  When Horniman heard of Robinson's decision, she severed her connections with the company.Welch, Robert, Stewart, Bruce. ''The Oxford Companion to Irish Literature'', Oxford: Oxford University Press, January, 1996. p. 3. ISBN 0-1986-6158-4 By her own estimate, she had invested  £10,350&mdash;worth approximately $1 million in 2007 US dollars&mdash;on the project.

With the loss of Horniman, Synge, and the Fays, the Abbey under Robinson tended to drift, suffering from falling public interest and box office returns.  This trend was halted for a time by the emergence of Sean O'Casey as an heir to Synge.Kavanagh, pp. 118, 127, 137. O'Casey's career as a dramatist began with ''The Shadow of a Gunman'', staged by the Abbey in 1923. This was followed by ''Juno and the Paycock'' in 1924, and ''The Plough and the Stars'' in 1926. Theatergoers arose in riots over the last play, in a way reminiscent of those that had greeted the ''Playboy'' 19 years earlier.Kavanagh, p. 135. Concerned about public reaction, the Abbey rejected O'Casey's next play.  He emigrated to London shortly thereafter.Collins, Glenn. ", ''New York Times'', 13 November 1989. Retrieved on 21 January 2008.

In 1924, Yeats and Lady Gregory offered the Abbey to the government of the Free State as a gift to the Irish people.  Although the government refused, the following year Minister of Finance Ernest Blythe arranged an annual government subsidy of £850 for the Abbey. This made the company the first state-supported theatre in the English-speaking world.Kavanagh, pp. 125&ndash;126. The subsidy allowed the theatre to avoid bankruptcy, but the amount was too small to rescue it from financial difficulty. 

The Abbey School of Acting and the Abbey School of Ballet were set up that year. The latter was led by Ninette de Valois&mdash;who had provided choreography for a number of Yeats' plays&mdash;and ran until 1933.Sorley Walker, Kathrine. "The Festival and the Abbey: Ninette de Valois' Early Choreography, 1925-1934, Part One". ''Dance Chronicle'', Volume 7, No. 4, 1984&ndash;85. pp. 379&ndash;412.

Around this time the company acquired additional space, allowing them to create a small experimental theatre, the ''Peacock'', in the ground floor of the main theatre. In 1928, Hilton Edwards and Micheál MacLiammoir launched the Gate Theatre, initially using the Peacock to stage works by European and American dramatists.Welsh (1999), p. 108.  The Gate primarily sought work from new Irish playwrights and, despite the new space, the Abbey entered a period of artistic decline. 

This is illustrated by the story of how one new work was said to have come to the Gate Theatre. Denis Johnston reportedly submitted his first play, ''Shadowdance'', to the Abbey; however, Lady Gregory rejected it, returning it to the author with “The Old Lady says No” written across the title page.Welch, Robert, and Stewart, Bruce. ''The Oxford Companion to Irish Literature'', Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1996. p. 275. ISBN 0-1986-6158-4  Johnston decided to re-title the play.  The Gate staged ''The Old Lady Says 'No' '' in ''The Peacock'' in 1928.  (Note: academic critics Joseph Ronsley and Christine St. Peter have questioned the veracity of this story.Bartlett, Rebecca Ann. ''Choice's Outstanding Academic Books, 1992-1997: Reviews of Scholarly Titles'', Association of College & Research Libraries, 1998. p. 136. ISBN 0-8389-7929-7
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c77cec853cb661bf3d74178746ca1a8d" name="John_Millington_Synge" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/c77cec853cb661bf3d74178746ca1a8d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>