<document id="84c8fa2341f7d052a1ee3a36ff043798-7" name="Peru" cat="11">
<text>
With about 29 million inhabitants, Peru is the fourth most populous country in South America as of 2007.United Nations, , pp. 44–48. Retrieved on July 29, 2007 Its demographic growth rate declined from 2.6% to 1.6% between 1950 and 2000; population is expected to reach approximately 42 million in 2050.Instituto Nacional de Estadística e Informática, ''Perú: Estimaciones y Proyecciones de Población, 1950–2050'', pp. 37–38, 40. As of 2007, 75.9% lived in urban areas and 24.1% in rural areas.Instituto Nacional de Estadística e Informática, ''Perfil sociodemográfico del Perú'', p. 13. Major cities include Lima, home to over 8 million people, Arequipa, Trujillo, Chiclayo, Piura, Iquitos, Cusco, Chimbote, and Huancayo, all of which reported more than 250,000 inhabitants in the 2007 census.Instituto Nacional de Estadística e Informática, ''Perfil sociodemográfico del Perú'', p. 24. In the Amazonian region, there are 16 ethno-linguistic families and more than 65 different ethnic groups.  After Brazil and New Guinea, Peru has the largest number of uncontacted tribes in the world.. National Geographic News. October 6, 2008.

Peru is a multiethnic country formed by the combination of different groups over five centuries. Amerindians inhabited Peruvian territory for several millennia before Spanish Conquest in the 16th century; their population decreased from an estimated 9 million in the 1520s to around 600,000 in 1620 mainly because of infectious diseases.Noble David Cook, ''Demographic collapse: Indian Peru, 1520–1620'', p. 114. Spaniards and Africans arrived in large numbers under colonial rule, mixing widely with each other and with indigenous peoples. After independence, there has been a gradual European immigration from England, France, Germany, Italy, and Spain.Mario Vázquez, "Immigration and mestizaje in nineteenth-century Peru", pp. 79–81. Chinese arrived in the 1850s as a replacement for slave workers and have since become a major influence in Peruvian society.Magnus Mörner, ''Race mixture in the history of Latin America'', p. 131. Other immigrant groups include Arabs and Japanese. Peru's racial structure can be classified as 45% Amerindian, 37% mestizo (mixed Amerindian and European), 15% European, and 3% African, Japanese, Chinese, and other., U.S. Department of State

Spanish, the first language of 83.9% of Peruvians age 5 and older in 2007, is the primary language of the country. It coexists with several indigenous languages, the most important of which is Quechua, spoken by 13.2% of the population. Other native and foreign languages were spoken at that time by 2.7% and 0.1% of Peruvians, respectively.Instituto Nacional de Estadística e Informática, ''Perfil sociodemográfico del Perú'', p. 111. In the 2007 census, 81.3% of the population over 12 years old described themselves as Catholic, 12.5% as Evangelical, 3.3% as of other denominations, and 2.9% as non-religious.Instituto Nacional de Estadística e Informática, ''Perfil sociodemográfico del Perú'', p. 132. Literacy was estimated at 92.9% in 2007; this rate is lower in rural areas (80.3%) than in urban areas (96.3%).Instituto Nacional de Estadística e Informática, ''Perfil sociodemográfico del Perú'', p. 93. Primary and secondary education are compulsory and free in public schools.''Constitución Política del Perú'', Article N° 17.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ee50abb2e585b2d680972bf9a4377f4e" name="Quechuawomanandchild" sectnum="7#1">../img/ee50abb2e585b2d680972bf9a4377f4e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>