<document id="84c8fa2341f7d052a1ee3a36ff043798-6" name="Peru" cat="11">
<text>
Peru's economy has experienced significant growth in the last 15 years. It is consired an Emerging Market   according to the MSCI  MSCI Barra. Peru has a high Human Development Index score of 0.806.United Nations Development Programme, . Retrieved on April 28, 2009. Its 2008 per capita was US$8,594; 36.2% of its total population is poor, including 12.6% that is extremely poor.Instituto Nacional de Estadística e Informática, . Retrieved on June 12, 2009. Historically, the country's economic performance has been tied to exports, which provide hard currency to finance imports and external debt payments.Rosemary Thorp and Geoffrey Bertram, ''Peru 1890–1977'', p. 4. Although exports have provided substantial revenue, self-sustained growth and a more egalitarian distribution of income have proven elusive.Rosemary Thorp and Geoffrey Bertram, ''Peru 1890–1977'', p. 321.

Buildings in the financial district of San Isidro
Peruvian economic policy has varied widely over the past decades. The 1968–1975 government of Juan Velasco Alvarado introduced radical reforms, which included agrarian reform, the expropriation of foreign companies, the introduction of an economic planning system, and the creation of a large state-owned sector. These measures failed to achieve their objectives of income redistribution and the end of economic dependence on developed nations.Rosemary Thorp and Geoffrey Bertram, ''Peru 1890–1977'', pp. 318–319. Despite these adverse results, most reforms were not reversed until the 1990s, when the liberalizing government of Alberto Fujimori ended price controls, protectionism, restrictions on foreign direct investment, and most state ownership of companies.John Sheahan, ''Searching for a better society'', p. 157. Reforms have permitted sustained economic growth since 1993, except for a slump after the 1997 Asian financial crisis. Banco Central de Reserva, . Retrieved on May 15, 2007.

Services account for 53% of Peruvian gross domestic product, followed by manufacturing (22.3%), extractive industries (15%), and taxes (9.7%).2006 figures.  Banco Central de Reserva, , p. 204. Retrieved on June 25, 2007. Recent economic growth has been fueled by macroeconomic stability, improved terms of trade, and rising investment and consumption. Banco Central de Reserva, , pp. 15, 203. Retrieved on June 25, 2007. Trade is expected to increase further after the implementation of a free trade agreement with the United States signed on April 12, 2006.Office of the U.S. Trade Representative, , April 4, 2006. Retrieved on May 15, 2007. Peru's main exports are copper, gold, zinc, textiles, and fish meal; its major trade partners are the United States, China, Brazil, and Chile.2006 figures.  Banco Central de Reserva, , pp. 60–61. Retrieved on July 3, 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c50f4f1960426cf2b75774029040aef9" name="Callao" sectnum="6#1">../img/c50f4f1960426cf2b75774029040aef9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>