<document id="84c8fa2341f7d052a1ee3a36ff043798-3" name="Peru" cat="11">
<text>
Peru is a presidential representative democratic republic with a multi-party system. Under the current constitution, the President is the head of state and government; he or she is elected for five years and cannot seek immediate re-election, he or she must stand down for at least one full constitutional term before reelection.''Constitución Política del Perú'', Article N° 112. The President designates the Prime Minister and, with his advice, the rest of the Council of Ministers.''Constitución Política del Perú'', Article N° 122. There is a unicameral Congress with 120 members elected for a five-year term.''Constitución Política del Perú'', Article N° 90. Bills may be proposed by either the executive or the legislative branch; they become law after being passed by Congress and promulgated by the President.''Constitución Política del Perú'', Articles N° 107–108. The judiciary is nominally independent,''Constitución Política del Perú'', Articles N° 146. though political intervention into judicial matters has been common throughout history and arguably continues today.Jeffrey Clark, . Retrieved on July 24, 2007.

The Peruvian government is directly elected, and voting is compulsory for all citizens aged 18 to 70.''Constitución Política del Perú'', Article N° 31. General elections held in 2006 ended in a second round victory for presidential candidate Alan García of the Peruvian Aprista Party (52.6% of valid votes) over Ollanta Humala of Union for Peru (47.4%). Oficina Nacional de Procesos Electorales, . Retrieved on May 15, 2007. Congress is currently composed of the Peruvian Aprista Party (36 seats), Peruvian Nationalist Party (23 seats), Union for Peru (19 seats), National Unity (15 seats), the Fujimorista Alliance for the Future (13 seats), the Parliamentary Alliance (9 seats) and the Democratic Special Parliamentary Group (5 seats). Congreso de la República del Perú, . Retrieved on January 5, 2008.

Peruvian foreign relations have been dominated by border conflicts with neighboring countries, most of which were settled during the 20th century.Ronald Bruce St John, ''The foreign policy of Peru'', pp. 223–224. There is still an ongoing dispute with Chile over maritime limits in the Pacific Ocean.BBC News, . Retrieved on May 16, 2007. Peru is an active member of several regional blocs and one of the founders of the Andean Community of Nations. It is also a participant in international organizations such as the Organization of American States and the United Nations. The Peruvian military is composed of an army, a navy and an air force; its primary mission is to safeguard the independence, sovereignty and territorial integrity of the country.Ministerio de Defensa, ''Libro Blanco de la Defensa Nacional'', p. 90. The armed forces are subordinate to the Ministry of Defense and to the President as Commander-in-Chief. Conscription was abolished in 1999 and replaced by voluntary military service.''Ley N° 27178, Ley del Servicio Militar'', Articles N° 29, 42 and 45.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3d1bfd8dbecce837df8e2f8f75b334bd" name="Peru_Lima_Congreso_Detail_centre" sectnum="3#1">../img/3d1bfd8dbecce837df8e2f8f75b334bd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>