<document id="84deb303629e4deb7fe218ced51eaac2-4" name="Dreadnought" cat="29">
<text>
The First World War was almost an anticlimax for the great dreadnought fleets. There was no decisive clash of modern battlefleets to compare with Tsushima. The role of battleships was marginal to the great land struggle in France and Russia; it was equally marginal to the First Battle of the Atlantic.Kennedy, ''Rise and Fall of British Naval Mastery'', p.250&ndash;1

By virtue of geography, the Royal Navy could keep the German High Seas Fleet bottled up in the North Sea with relative ease, but was on the other side unable to break the German superiority in the baltic sea. Both sides were aware, because of the greater number of British dreadnoughts, a full fleet engagement would result in a British victory. The German strategy was therefore to try to provoke an engagement on favourable terms: either inducing a part of the Grand Fleet to enter battle alone, or to fight a pitched battle near the German coast, where friendly minefields, torpedo boats, and submarines could even the odds.Keegan, ''The First World War'', p. 289

The first two years of war saw conflict in the North Sea limited to skirmishes by battlecruisers at the Battle of Heligoland Bight and Battle of Dogger Bank, and raids on the English coast. In the summer of 1916, a further attempt to draw British ships into battle on favourable terms resulted in a clash of the battlefleets at Jutland; it was indecisive.Ireland, ''Jane's War At Sea'', p.88&ndash;95

In the other naval theatres, there were no decisive pitched battles. In the Black Sea, Russian and Turkish battleships skirmished, but nothing more. In the Baltic Sea, action was largely limited to convoy raiding and the laying of defensive minefields.Keegan, ''The First World War'', p.234&ndash;5 The Adriatic was in a sense the mirror of the North Sea: the Austro-Hungarian dreadnought fleet remained bottled up by British and French blockading fleets. And in the Mediterranean, the most important use of battleships was in support of the amphibious assault at Gallipoli.Kennedy, ''Rise and Fall of British Naval Mastery'', p.256&ndash;7

The course of the war also illustrated the vulnerability of battleships to cheaper weapons. In September 1914, the U-boat threat to capital ships was demonstrated by successful attacks on British cruisers, including the sinking of three elderly British armored cruisers by the German submarine ''U-9'' in less than an hour. Mines continued to prove a threat when a month later the recently commissioned British super-dreadnought ''Audacious'' struck one. By the end of October, British strategy and tactics in the North Sea had changed to reduce the risk of U-boat attack.Massie, Robert. ''Castles of Steel'', London, p127&ndash;145 While Jutland was the only major clash of battleship fleets in history, the German plan for the battle relied on U-boat attacks on the British fleet; and the escape of the German fleet from the superior British firepower was affected by the German cruisers and destroyers closing on British battleships, causing them to turn away to avoid the threat of torpedo attack. Further near-misses from submarine attacks on battleships and casualties amongst cruisers led to growing paranoia in the Royal Navy about the vulnerability of battleships.Kennedy, ''Rise and Fall of British Naval Mastery'', p.245&ndash;8

For the German part, the High Seas Fleet determined not to engage the British without the assistance of submarines, and since submarines were more needed for commerce raiding, the fleet stayed in port for much of the remainder of the war.Kennedy, ''The Rise and Fall of British Naval Mastery'', p. 247&ndash;249 Other theatres also showed the role of small craft in damaging or destroying dreadnoughts. The two Austrian dreadnoughts lost in 1918 were the casualties of torpedo boats and of frogmen.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a8fd9fa1272aee4db6fe6bfa94a1825d" name="HMS_Audacious_crew_take_to_lifeboats" sectnum="4#1">../img/a8fd9fa1272aee4db6fe6bfa94a1825d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>