<document id="84deb303629e4deb7fe218ced51eaac2-3.8" name="Dreadnought" cat="29">
<text>
The building of ''Dreadnought'' coincided with increasing tension between Britain and Germany. Germany had begun to build a large battlefleet in the 1890s, as part of a deliberate policy to challenge British naval supremacy. With the conclusion of the Entente Cordiale between Britain and France in April 1904, it became increasingly clear that Britain's principal naval enemy would be Germany, which was building up a large, modern fleet under the 'Tirpitz' laws. This rivalry gave rise to the two largest dreadnought fleets of the pre-war period.Breyer, ''Battleships and Battlecruisers of the World'', p.59

The first German response to ''Dreadnought'' came with the ''Nassau'' class, laid down in 1907. This was followed by the ''Helgoland'' class in 1909. Together with two battlecruisers&mdash;a type for which the Germans had less admiration than Fisher, but which could be built under authorisation for armored cruisers, rather than capital ships&mdash;these classes gave Germany a total of ten modern capital ships built or building in 1909. While the British ships were somewhat faster and more powerful than their German equivalents, a 12:10 ratio fell far short of the 2:1 ratio that the Royal Navy wanted to maintain.Sondhaus, ''Naval Warfare 1815–1914'', p.203

In 1909, the British Parliament authorized an additional four capital ships, holding out hope Germany would be willing to negotiate a treaty about battleship numbers. If no such solution could be found, an additional four ships would be laid down in 1910. Even this compromise solution meant (when taken together with some social reforms) raising taxes enough to prompt a constitutional crisis in Britain in 1909&ndash;10. In 1910, the British eight-ship construction plan went ahead, including four ''Orion''-class super-dreadnoughts, and augmented by battlecruisers purchased by Australia and New Zealand. In the same period of time, Germany laid down only three ships, giving Britain a superiority of 22 ships to 13. The British resolve demonstrated by their construction program led the Germans to seek a negotiated end to the arms race. While the Admiralty's new target of a 60% lead over Germany was near enough to Tirpitz's goal of cutting the British lead to 50%, talks foundered on the question on whether British Commonwealth battlecruisers should be included in the count, as well as non-naval matters like the German demands for recognition of her ownership of Alsace-Lorraine. Sondhaus, ''Naval Warfare 1815&ndash;1914'', p.203&ndash;4

The dreadnought race stepped up in 1910 and 1911, with Germany laying down four capital ships each year and Britain five. Tension came to a head following the German Naval Law of 1912. This proposed a fleet of 33 German battleships and battlecruisers, outnumbering the Royal Navy in home waters. To make matters worse for Britain, the Imperial Austro-Hungarian Navy was building four dreadnoughts, while the Italians had four and were building two more. Against such threats, the Royal Navy could no longer guarantee vital British interests. Britain was faced with a choice of building more battleships, withdrawing from the Mediterranean, or seeking an alliance with France. Further naval construction was unacceptably expensive at a time when social welfare provision was making calls on the budget. Withdrawing from the Mediterranean would mean a huge loss of influence, weakening British diplomacy in the Mediterranean and shaking the stability of the British Empire. The only acceptable option, and the one recommended by First Lord of the Admiralty Winston Churchill, was to break with the policies of the past and make an arrangement with France. The French would assume responsibility for checking Italy and Austria-Hungary in the Mediterranean, while the British would protect the north coast of France. In spite of some opposition from British politicians, the Royal Navy organised itself on this basis in 1912.Kennedy ''The Rise and Fall of British Naval Mastery'' p. 224&ndash;8

In spite of these important strategic consequences, the 1912 Naval Law had little bearing on the battleship force ratios. Britain responded by laying down ten new super-dreadnoughts in her 1912 and 1913 budgets&mdash;ships of the ''Queen Elizabeth'' and ''Revenge'' classes, which introduced a further step change in armament, speed and protection&mdash;while Germany laid down only five, focusing resources on the Army. Sondhaus, ''Naval Warfare 1815&ndash;1914'', p.204&ndash;5
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="455bdc0abb27206649347a3cf7384e20" name="George_V_and_Admiral_Callaghan_onboard_HMS_Iron_Duke" sectnum="3.8#1">../img/455bdc0abb27206649347a3cf7384e20.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>