<document id="84deb303629e4deb7fe218ced51eaac2-3.11" name="Dreadnought" cat="29">
<text>
Compared to the other major naval powers, France was slow to start building dreadnoughts, instead finishing the planned ''Danton'' class of pre-dreadnoughts, laying down five in 1907 and 1908. It was not until September 1910 that the first of the  was laid down, making France the eleventh nation to enter the dreadnought race.Sondhaus, ''Naval Warfare 1815–1914'', p.214&ndash;5 In the Navy Estimates of 1911, Paul Bénazet asserted that over the period of 1896 to 1911, France dropped from being the world's second-largest naval power to fourth; he attributed this to problems in maintenance routines and neglect.Gardiner and Gray, ''Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships 1906&ndash;1921'', p.190 However, the closer alliance with Britain made these reduced forces more than adequate for French needs.

The Italian navy had received proposals for an all-big-gun battleship from Cuniberti well before ''Dreadnought'' was launched, but it took until 1909 for Italy to lay down one of her own. The construction of ''Dante Alighieri'' was prompted by rumours of Austro-Hungarian dreadnought building. A further five dreadnoughts of the ''Cavour'' class and ''Andrea Doria'' class followed as Italy sought to maintain its lead over Austria-Hungary. These ships remained the core of Italian naval strength until World War II. The subsequent ''Caracciolo'' class were cancelled on the outbreak of WWI.Sondhaus, ''Naval Warfare 1814–1915'', p.209&ndash;11

In January 1909, Austro-Hungarian admirals circulated a document calling for a fleet of four dreadnoughts. However, a constitutional crisis in 1909&ndash;10 meant no construction could be approved. In spite of this, two dreadnoughts were laid down by shipyards on a speculative basis, and later approved along with an additional two. The resulting ships, all ''Tegetthoff'' class, were to be accompanied by a further four ships, but these were cancelled on the outbreak of World War I.Sondhaus, ''Naval Warfare 1815&ndash;1914'', p.211&ndash;3

In June 1909, the Imperial Russian Navy began construction of four  dreadnoughts for the Baltic Fleet, and in October 1911, three more  class dreadnoughts for the Black Sea were laid down. Of seven ships, only one was completed within four years of being laid down, and the ''Gangut'' ships were "obsolescent and outclassed" upon commissioning.Gardiner and Gray, ''Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships 1906&ndash;1921'', p.302&ndash;3Gibbons, ''The Complete Encyclopedia of Battleships and Battlecruisers'', p.205 Taking lessons from Tsushima, and influenced by Cuniberti, they ended up more closely resembling slower versions of Fisher's battlecruisers than ''Dreadnought'', and they proved badly flawed due to their smaller guns and thinner armor when compared with contemporary dreadnoughts.Breyer, ''Battleships and Battlecruisers of the World'', p.393

Spain commissioned three ships of the , with the first being laid down in 1909. The three ships were the smallest dreadnoughts ever built. While built in Spain, the construction was reliant on British assistance; for example, construction on the third ship, ''Jaime I'', took nine years from her laying down date to completion because of non-delivery of critical material, especially armament, from Great Britain.Gibbons, ''The Complete Encyclopedia of Battleships and Battlecruisers'' p.195Gardiner and Gray, ''Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships 1906&ndash;1921'', p.378

Brazil's  at sea in early 1910, soon after her commissioning
Brazil was the third country to begin construction on a dreadnought.Sondhaus, ''Naval Warfare, 1815–1914'', p.216 Although three pre-dreadnoughts had been ordered from Britain, construction was halted in favor of a much improved designWhitley, ''Battleships of World War II'', p.24&mdash;new plans called for a dreadnought mounting a heavier main battery than any other battleship afloat at the time (twelve /45 caliber guns).  was laid down on by Armstrong (Elswick) on 17 April 1907, and her sister, , followed thirteen days later at Vickers (Barrow).Gardiner and Gray, ''Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships, 1906–1921'', p.403 Although many naval journals in Europe and the US speculated that the ships were really acting as a proxy for one of the naval powers and would hand the ships over to them as soon as they were complete, both ships were commissioned into the Brazilian Navy in 1910; the US commissioned the first ''South Carolina'', , on 4 January, just one day before ''Minas Geraes''.Friedman, ''US Battleships'', p.419 The Brazilian dreadnoughts sparked a small-scale arms race in South America, as Argentina and Chile ordered dreadnoughts from the US and Britain, respectively. Both of Chile's two battleships were purchased by the British on the outbreak of the First World War. One, , was later returned to the Chilean government.Sondhaus, ''Naval Warfare 1815&ndash;1914'', p.214&ndash;6

The Netherlands intended by 1912 to replace its fleet of pre-dreadnought armored ships with a modern fleet comprising at least five dreadnoughts. Constant fiddling with the designs and slow political decision making meant the ships were not ordered until the summer of 1914, when the outbreak of World War I put an end to the ambitious fleet plan.Breyer, ''Battleships and Battlecruisers of the World, p.450&ndash;5Gardiner and Gray, ''Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships 1906&ndash;1921'', p.363&ndash;4, 366

Turkey ordered two dreadnoughts from British yards, which were seized by the British on the outbreak of World War I, in order to reinforce the Royal Navy and prevent the ships falling into enemy hands. The ships ''Reshadiye'' and ''Sultan Osman I'' became HMS ''Erin'' and ''Agincourt'' respectively. The seizure of the ships was followed by Germany's gift to Turkey of two warships, the battlecruiser ''Goeben'' and the cruiser ''Breslau''. This became an important factor in the decision of the Ottoman Empire to join the Central Powers.Greger, ''Schlachtschiffe der Welt'', p. 252

Greece had ordered a dreadnought from Germany, but work stopped on the outbreak of war. The main armament for the Greek ship had been ordered in the United States, and the guns consequently equipped a class of British monitors. Greece in 1914 purchased two pre-dreadnoughts from the United States Navy, renaming them ''Kilkis'' and ''Limnos'' in Royal Hellenic Navy service.Sondhaus, ''Naval Warfare 1815–1914'', p.220
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5f5df9a7648c76794f628a572a3498b8" name="Provence-3" sectnum="3.11#1">../img/5f5df9a7648c76794f628a572a3498b8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>