<document id="84deb303629e4deb7fe218ced51eaac2-3.12" name="Dreadnought" cat="29">
<text>
Within five years of the commissioning of ''Dreadnought'', a new generation of more powerful "super-dreadnoughts" were being built. The arrival of the super-dreadnought is commonly held to start with the British . What made them 'super' was the unprecedented 2,000-ton jump in displacement, the introduction of the heavier 13.5-inch (343 mm) gun, and the placement of all the main armament on the centerline. In the four years between ''Dreadnought'' and ''Orion'', displacement had increased by 25%, and weight of broadside had doubled.Breyer, ''Battleships and Battlecruisers of the World'', p.126

British super-dreadnoughts were joined by other nations as well. The U.S. Navy ''New York'' class, laid down in 1911, carried 14-inch (356 mm) guns in response to the British move and this caliber became standard. In Japan, two  super-dreadnoughts were laid down in 1912, followed by the two s in 1914, with both classes carrying twelve 14-inch (356 mm) guns. In 1917, the  was ordered, the first dreadnoughts to mount  guns, making them the arguably most powerful warships in the world. All were increasingly built from Japanese rather than imported components. In France, the ''Courbet''s were followed by three super-dreadnoughts of the , carrying 340 mm (13.4 in) guns; another five s were canceled on the outbreak of World War One.Sondhaus, ''Naval Warfare 1815&ndash;1914'', p.214

Later British super-dreadnoughts, principally the , dispensed with one turret, so weight and volume were freed up for larger, oil-fired boilers. The new 15-inch (381-mm) gun gave greater firepower in spite of the loss of a turret, and there was a thicker armor belt and improved underwater protection. The class had a 25-knot (46-km/h) design speed, and they were considered the first fast battleships.Breyer, ''Battleships and Battlecruisers of the World'', p.140&ndash;4

The stern of the US' first super-dreadnought, , during World War I

The design weakness of super-dreadnoughts, which distinguished them from post-World War I designs, was armor disposition. Their design emphasized the vertical protection needed in short-range battles. These ships could engage the enemy at , but were vulnerable to the high-angle ('plunging') fire at such ranges. Post-war designs typically had 5 to 6 inches (130 to 150 mm) of deck armor to defend against this. The concept of zone of immunity became a major part of the thinking behind battleship design. Lack of underwater protection was also a weakness of these pre-World War I designs which were developed only as the threat of the torpedo became real.Breyer, ''Battleships and Battlecruisers of the World'', p.75&ndash;79

The United States Navy's 'Standard type battleships', beginning with the , were designed with long-range engagements and plunging fire in mind; the first of these was laid down in 1912, four years before Jutland taught the dangers of long-range fire to European navies. Important features of the standard battleships were 'all or nothing' armor and 'raft' construction, a philosophy under which only the parts of the ship worth giving the thickest possible protection were worth armoring at all, and enough reserve buoyancy should be contained within the resulting armored "raft" to keep afloat the entire ship in the event the unarmored bow and stern were thoroughly riddled and flooded. This design was proven in battle at the Naval Battle of Guadalcanal, when an ill-timed turn by  silhouetted her to Japanese guns. In spite of receiving 26 heavy hits, her armored raft remained untouched and she remained both afloat and operational at the end of action.Friedman, ''U.S. Battleships'', p.202&ndash;3
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="33d3eb4dcc1801d93a31ecfe7b76cebf" name="2nd_Battle_Squadron" sectnum="3.12#1">../img/33d3eb4dcc1801d93a31ecfe7b76cebf.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>