<document id="84f98075bd8d75d5dfe71edde86191d7-1.3" name="Armament_of_the_Iowa_class_battleship" cat="29">
<text>
The large caliber guns were designed to fire two different 16 inch shells: an armor piercing round for anti-ship and anti-structure work and a high explosive round designed for use against unarmored targets and shore bombardment. A third type of ammunition for delivering tactical nuclear warheads was developed subsequently.

The Mk. 8 APC (Armor-Piercing, Capped) shell weighs 2,700 lb (1225 kg) and was designed to penetrate the hardened steel armor carried by foreign battleships. At 20,000 yards (18 km) the Mk. 8 could penetrate 20 inches (500 mm) of steel armor plate.William H. Garzke and Robert O. Dulin, Jr. ''Battleships: United States Battleships 1935–1992'' At the same range, the Mk. 8 could penetrate 21 feet (6.4 m) of reinforced concrete. 

For unarmored targets and shore bombardment, the 1,900 lb (862 kg) Mk. 13 HC (High-Capacity—referring to the large bursting charge) shell was available. The Mk. 13 shell would create a crater 50 feet (15 m) wide and 20 feet (6 m) deep upon impact and detonation, and could defoliate trees 400 yards (360 m) from the point of impact.

The final type of ammunition developed for the ''Iowa'' class were "Katie" shells. These shells were born from the concept of nuclear deterrence that had begun to shape the United States armed forces as the Cold War began. To compete with the Air Force and the Army, which had developed nuclear bombs and nuclear shells for use on the battlefield, the United States Navy began a top-secret program to develop Mk. 23 nuclear naval shells with an estimated yield of 15 to 20 kilotons. These shells were designed to be launched from the best seaborne artillery platform available, which at the time were the four ships of the ''Iowa'' class. The shells entered development around 1953, and were reportedly ready by 1956; however, it is not known whether they were ever actually deployed on the ''Iowa''-class battleships because the United States Navy does not confirm or deny the presence of nuclear weapons aboard its ships. In 1991 the U.S. unilaterally withdrew its nuclear artillery shells from service, and Russia responded in kind in 1992. The U.S. removed around 1,300 nuclear shells from Europe and reportedly dismantled its last shells by 2003.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="69db9a2783f0fcc1d2445afa2d5af0dc" name="16-in_Battleship_Ammunition" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/69db9a2783f0fcc1d2445afa2d5af0dc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>