<document id="84f98075bd8d75d5dfe71edde86191d7-3.7" name="Armament_of_the_Iowa_class_battleship" cat="29">
<text>
Arguably the best light anti-aircraft weapon of World War II, the Bofors 40 mm anti-aircraft gun was used on almost every major warship in the U.S. and UK fleet during World War II from about 1943 to 1945. Although a descendant of German and Swedish designs, the Bofors mounts used by the United States Navy during World War II had been heavily "Americanized" to bring the guns up to the standards placed on them by the US Navy. This resulted in a guns system set to English standards (now known as the Standard System) with interchangeable ammunition, which simplified the logistics situation for World War II. When coupled with electric-hydraulic drives for greater speed and the Mark 51 Director (''pictured'') for improved accuracy, the Bofors 40 mm gun became a fearsome adversary, accounting for roughly half of all Japanese aircraft shot down between 1 October 1944 and 1 February 1945.

When the ''Iowa''-class battleships were launched in 1943 and 1944 they carried twenty quad Bofors 40 mm gun mounts, which they used for defense against enemy aircraft. These heavy guns were also employed in the protection of allied aircraft carriers operating in the Pacific Theater of World War II. These guns remained on the battleships ''Iowa, Missouri,'' and ''Wisconsin'' from the time they were commissioned until they were reactivated for service in the 1980s.USS ''New Jersey'' had her 40 mm guns removed in 1968 when she was called into action for the Vietnam War. -  Retrieved 30 March 2007 As each battleship arrived for modernization during the early and mid 1980s the Bofors mounts that remained aboard were removed due in large part to the ineffectiveness of such manually aimed weapons against modern day jet fighters and enemy missiles. The replacement for the Bofors guns was the US Navy's Phalanx Close-in weapon system (CIWS).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1e7b46d907ab3d6396a33020c564576f" name="Mk51_Director" sectnum="3.7#1">../img/1e7b46d907ab3d6396a33020c564576f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>