<document id="84f98075bd8d75d5dfe71edde86191d7-3.8" name="Armament_of_the_Iowa_class_battleship" cat="29">
<text>
During their modernization in the 1980s, each ''Iowa''-class battleship was equipped with four of the United States Navy's Phalanx CIWS mounts, two which sat just behind the bridge and two which were next to the after ship's funnel. , , and  were equipped with the Block 0 version of the Phalanx, while  received the first operational Block 1 version in 1988.

Developed as the final line of defense (terminal defense or point defense) against anti-ship missiles, the Phalanx Close in Weapon System (CIWS, pronounced "see-whiz") is the anti-aircraft/anti-missile gun currently in use in the United States Navy. Due to their distinctive shape, they have been nicknamed "R2D2s", in reference to the droid R2-D2 from the Star Wars universe. Designed in the early 1970s by General Dynamics, and currently produced by Raytheon, the Phalanx CIWS mount utilizes a 20 mm M61 Vulcan gatling gun to destroy enemy missiles and aircraft that manage to escape anti-missile and anti-aircraft missiles fired from friendly ships.

The Phalanx guns work by using a search radar and a tracking radar to follow targets that come within 1 to . When a target comes within this range the CIWS mount physically moves to track the target while simultaneously evaluating the target against several preset criteria to determine the next course of action. Depending on whether the target criteria are met, the Phalanx mount may automatically engage the incoming target if it is judged to be hostile in nature, or the system may recommend that the Phalanx operator engage a target. 

Phalanx CIWS mounts were used by ''Missouri'' and ''Wisconsin'' during the 1991 Gulf War; ''Wisconsin'' alone fired 5,200 20 mm Phalanx CIWS rounds. ''Missouri'' also received Phalanx fire during a "friendly fire" incident in which the ''Perry''-class guided missile frigate  mistook chaff fired off by ''Missouri'' for a legitimate target and shot at ''Missouri''. Rounds from this attack struck the ship in the bulkhead above the famed "surrender deck" and bounced off the armor, one round penetrated the forward funnel and passed completely through it, and another round penetrated a bulkhead and embedded in an interior passageway of the ship.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="76db79029cc7c8c557b3fcba283703b4" name="Close-In_Weapon_System" sectnum="3.8#1">../img/76db79029cc7c8c557b3fcba283703b4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>