<document id="84f98075bd8d75d5dfe71edde86191d7-4.9" name="Armament_of_the_Iowa_class_battleship" cat="29">
<text>
The BGM-109 Tomahawk Land Attack Missile (TLAM) was first introduced in the 1970s, and entered service with the United States in 1983. Designed as a long-range, all-weather, subsonic cruise missile, the Tomahawk is capable of reaching targets at a much greater range than the  guns on the ''Iowa''-class ships. When added to the battleships in the 1980s the Tomahawk became the longest-ranged weapon carried by the battleships.The maximum range for the Tomahawk Land Attack Missile is 675 nautical miles (nm), the maximum range for the Harpoon is 85 nm, ( battleship.org, Retrieved on 2007-03-25) and the maximum range for the  guns is 24 nautical miles (nm).( factplace.com, Retrieved on 2007-03-25)

Owing to the original 1938 design of the battleships, the Tomahawk missiles could not be fitted to the ''Iowa''-class unless the battleships were physically rebuilt in such a way as to accommodate the missile mounts that would be needed to store and launch the Tomahawks. This realization prompted the removal of the anti-aircraft guns previously installed on the ''Iowas'' and the removal of four of each of the battleships ten 5"/38 DP mounts. The mid and aft end of the battleships were then rebuilt to accommodate the missile magazines. This resulted in the construction of two separate platforms, one located between the first and second funnel and one located behind the second funnel, to which MK-143 Armored Box Launcher (ABL) canisters could be attached. Each Armored Box Launcher carries four missiles, and each of the battleships were outfitted with eight canisters, enabling the ''Iowa''-class to carry and fire a total of 32 Tomahawk missiles.

The type of Tomahawk carried by the battleships varies, as there are three basic configurations for the Tomahawk: the Anti-Ship Missile (TASM); the Land-Attack Missile-Conventional (TLAM-C); and the Land-Attack Missile-Nuclear (TLAM-N). Each version is similar in appearance and uses the same airframe body and launcher. The conventional Tomahawk missile can carry a  explosive warhead or submunitions which use the missile body to reach their destination. The nuclear variant carries a 200 kt W80 nuclear warhead.

The TLAM can be equipped with an inertial and terrain contour matching (TERCOM) radar guidance package to find and destroy its target. The TERCOM radar uses a stored map reference to compare with the actual terrain to determine the missile's position. If necessary, a course correction is then made to place the missile on course to the target. Terminal guidance in the target area is provided by the optical Digital Scene Matching Area Correlation (DSMAC) system, which compares a stored image of target with the actual target image.

The firing weight of the Tomahawk is  plus a  booster. It has a cruising speed of 0.5 Mach and an attack speed of 0.75 Mach. The anti-ship version of the Tomahawk has an operating range of 250 nautical miles (nm) and a maximum range of 470 nm, while the conventional land attack missile version has a maximum range of 675 nm and TLAM-N has maximum range of 1,500 nm.

During the 1991 Gulf War, USS ''Missouri'' and USS ''Wisconsin'' used ABL launchers to fire Tomahawk missiles at Iraqi targets during Operation Desert Storm. ''Wisconsin'' served as the Tomahawk Land Attack Missile (TLAM) strike commander for the Persian Gulf, directing the sequence of launches that marked the opening of Operation Desert Storm and firing a total of 24 of her own TLAMs during the first two days of the campaign.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4ded763ec3ed252347225c8aa6f4a2c3" name="USSNewJersey_tomohawk" sectnum="4.9#1">../img/4ded763ec3ed252347225c8aa6f4a2c3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>