<document id="8580588096a57b352e094fbaf9152304-1.1" name="El_Greco" cat="1">
<text>
Born in 1541 in either the village of Fodele or Candia (the Venetian name of Chandax, present day Heraklion) in Crete, El Greco was descended from a prosperous urban family, which had probably been driven out of Chania to Candia after an uprising against the Venetians between 1526 and 1528.M. Lambraki-Plaka, ''El Greco—The Greek'', 40–41 El Greco's father, Geórgios Theotokópoulos (d. 1556), was a merchant and tax collector. Nothing is known about his mother or his first wife, a Greek woman.M. Scholz-Hansel, ''El Greco'', 7* M. Tazartes, ''El Greco'', 23 El Greco's older brother, Manoússos Theotokópoulos (1531 – December 13, 1604), was a wealthy merchant and spent the last years of his life (1603–1604) in El Greco's Toledo home.M. Scholz-Hansel, ''El Greco'', 7* 



El Greco received his initial training as an icon painter of the Cretan school, the leading centre of post-Byzantine art. In addition to painting, he probably studied the classics of ancient Greece, and perhaps the Latin classics also; he left a "working library" of 130 books at his death, including the Bible in Greek and an annotated Vasari.Richard Kagan in, J. Brown, ''El Greco of Toledo'', 45 Candia was a center for artistic activity where Eastern and Western cultures co-existed harmoniously, where around two hundred painters were active during the 16th century, and had organized a painters' guild, based on the Italian model. In 1563, at the age of twenty-two, El Greco was described in a document as a "master" ("maestro Domenigo"), meaning he was already a master of the guild and presumably operating his own workshop.J. Brown, ''El Greco of Toledo'', 75 Three years later, in June 1566, as a witness to a contract, he signed his name as  (''Master Menégos Theotokópoulos, painter'').

Most scholars believe that the Theotokópoulos "family was almost certainly Greek Orthodox",X. Bray, ''El Greco'', 8* M. Lambraki-Plaka, ''El Greco—The Greek'', 40–41 although some Catholic sources still claim him from birth. Like many Orthodox emigrants to Europe, he apparently transferred to Catholicism after his arrival, and certainly practiced as a Catholic in Spain, where he described himself as a "devout Catholic" in his will. The extensive archival research conducted since the early 1960s by scholars, such as Nikolaos Panayotakis, Pandelis Prevelakis and Maria Constantoudaki, indicates strongly that El Greco's family and ancestors were Greek Orthodox. One of his uncles was an Orthodox priest, and his name is not mentioned in the Catholic archival baptismal records on Crete.P. Katimertzi,  Prevelakis goes even further, expressing his doubt that El Greco was ever a practicing Roman Catholic.H.E. Wethey, ''Letters to the Editor'', 125–127
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6cc637c4fc3536f8463d6a4529d77d8b" name="Dormition_El_Greco" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/6cc637c4fc3536f8463d6a4529d77d8b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>