<document id="86152a2926dba76c312e7f4b365dbe77-3" name="Real_Love_(John_Lennon_song)" cat="20">
<text>
The first problem The Beatles had to confront was the low quality of the demo, as Lennon had not used professional recording equipment on the take they were using, but a handheld tape recorder. George Martin had suffered a hearing loss, so the Beatles brought in Electric Light Orchestra's Jeff Lynne (who had worked with Harrison as part of The Traveling Wilburys) to co-produce. Lynne, who had already co-produced "Free as a Bird" said:



Although "Real Love" was comparatively more complete than "Free as a Bird," which had required the addition of some lyrics by McCartney, the song also suffered from problems with Lennon's timing. Lynne said:



This complicated job was a large part of the reason why George Martin, the traditional Beatles producer, did not produce any of the new, original Beatles songs. McCartney said:



Nevertheless, Lynne and the remaining Beatles did their best to make the song appear very "Beatles-y." Lynne said:



Therefore, The Beatles gathered once more in Sussex, England at McCartney's studio to produce another single. Added to the demo (which was now a full step higher because Lynne and The Beatles had it sped up) were the sounds of a double bass (originally owned by Elvis Presley's bassist, Bill Black), Fender Jazz bass guitar, a couple of Stratocaster guitars, one a modern "Clapton-style one" as Lynne described it, and George Harrison's psychedelically-painted "Rocky" strat (as seen in the ''I Am The Walrus'' video), as well as a Ludwig drum kit. McCartney did not use his traditional Höfner bass guitar, as he did during much of his career as a Beatle. Other than their traditional instruments, a Baldwin Combo Harpsichord (used by Lennon on The Beatles song "Because") and a harmonium (which appeared on The Beatles hit single "We Can Work It Out") were also used.. Retrieved June 24, 2005.

The Beatles used sound engineer Geoff Emerick, who had not only worked with them to a great extent in the 60s, but is often credited with many of The Beatles' audio inventions. McCartney said, "e's solid, really great. He knows how Ringo's snare should sound." The attitude in the studio was very relaxed, according to Lynne, "Paul and George would strike up the backing vocals—and all of a sudden it's The Beatles again! ... I'd be waiting to record and normally I'd say, 'OK, Let's do a take', but I was too busy laughing and smiling at everything they were talking about." Starr said that they had to be, in order to avoid being overwhelmed by the thought of being too reverent towards "a fallen hero" (as McCartney put it): "We just pretended that John had gone on holiday or out for tea and had left us the tape to play with. That was the only way we could deal with it, and get over the hurdle, because  was really very emotional."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e4dee8a3d92258f9d7f6b28ea9eadf24" name="REALLUV1" sectnum="3#1">../img/e4dee8a3d92258f9d7f6b28ea9eadf24.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>