<document id="86240e212b464c82c1f79eac4d1287d2-2" name="Natalie_Clifford_Barney" cat="17">
<text>
In November 1899 Barney met the poet Pauline Tarn, better known by her pen name Renée Vivien. For Vivien it was love at first sight, while Barney became fascinated with Vivien after hearing her recite one of her poems,Rodriguez, 105–106. which she described as "haunted by the desire for death."Barney, ''A Perilous Advantage'', 15. Their romantic relationship was also a creative exchange that inspired both of them to write. Barney provided a feminist theoretical framework which Vivien explored in her poetry. They adapted the imagery of the Symbolist poets along with the conventions of courtly love to describe love between women, also finding examples of heroic women in history and myth.Jay, xii-xiv. Sappho was an especially important influence and they studied Greek so as to read the surviving fragments of her poetry in the original. Both wrote plays about her life.Jay, 63, 67.



Vivien saw Barney as a muse and as Barney put it, "she had found new inspiration through me, almost without knowing me." Barney felt Vivien had cast her as a ''femme fatale'' and that she wanted "to lose herself... entirely in suffering" for the sake of her art.Barney, ''A Perilous Advantage'', 19, 24–25. Vivien also believed in fidelity, which Barney was unwilling to agree to. While Barney was visiting her family in Washington, D.C. in 1901, Vivien stopped answering her letters. Barney tried to get her back for years, at one point persuading a friend, operatic mezzo-soprano Emma Calvé, to sing under Vivien's window so she could throw a poem (wrapped around a bouquet of flowers) up to Vivien on her balcony. Both flowers and poem were intercepted and returned by a governess.Jay, 11–15.

In 1904 she wrote ''Je Me Souviens'' (''I Remember''), an intensely personal prose poem about their relationship which was presented as a single handwritten copy to Vivien in an attempt to win her back. They reconciled and traveled together to Lesbos, where they lived happily together for a short time and talked about starting a school of poetry for women like the one which Sappho, according to tradition, had founded on Lesbos some 2,500 years before. However, Vivien soon got a letter from her lover Hélène (the Baroness de Zuylen de Nyevelt) and went to Constantinople thinking she would break up with her in person. Vivien planned to meet Barney in Paris afterward but instead stayed with the Baroness and this time, the breakup was permanent.  

Vivien's health declined rapidly after this. According to Vivien's friend and neighbor Colette, she ate almost nothing and drank heavily, even rinsing her mouth with perfumed water to hide the smell.Colette, 83–103. Colette's account has led some to call Vivien an anorexicJay, 19. but this diagnosis did not yet exist at the time. Vivien was also addicted to the sedative chloral hydrate. In 1908 she attempted suicide by overdosing on laudanumRodriguez, 116, 186–187. and died the following year. In a memoir written fifty years later Barney said "She could not be saved. Her life was a long suicide. Everything turned to dust and ashes in her hands."Barney, ''Souvenirs Indiscrets'', quoted in Souhami (2005), 52.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d27615bb62136d38ebb360d0d9a276db" name="Natalie_Barney_and_Renee_Vivien" sectnum="2#1">../img/d27615bb62136d38ebb360d0d9a276db.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>