<document id="86240e212b464c82c1f79eac4d1287d2-7" name="Natalie_Clifford_Barney" cat="17">
<text>
Barney's attitudes during World War II have been controversial.  In 1937, Una, Lady Troubridge had complained that Barney "talked a lot of half-baked nonsense about the tyranny of fascism".Souhami (1999), 332.  Barney herself was one-eighth Jewish, and since she spent the war in Italy with Romaine Brooks, risked deportation to a concentration camp—a fate she avoided only by wiring her sister Laura for a notarized document attesting to her confirmation.  Nevertheless, having no other source of information about the war, she believed Axis propaganda that portrayed the Allies as the aggressors, so that pro-Fascism seemed to her to be a logical consequence of her pacifism.  An unpublished memoir she wrote during the war years is  pro-Fascist and anti-Semitic, quoting speeches by Hitler, apparently with approval.Livia (1992), 192–193

It is possible that the anti-Semitic passages in her memoir were intended to be used as evidence that she was not Jewish;Livia (1992), 191.  Rodriguez, 315, calls this a plausible theory. alternatively, she may have been influenced by Ezra Pound's anti-Semitic radio broadcasts.Rodriguez, 317.  Whatever the case, she did help a Jewish couple escape Italy, providing passage on a ship to the United States.  By the end of the war her sympathies had again changed, and she saw the Allies as liberators.Rodriguez, 326–327.

''Villa Trait d'Union'' was destroyed by bombing.  After the war, Brooks declined to live with Barney in Paris; she remained in Italy, and they visited each other frequently.Secrest, 368.  Their relationship remained monogamous until the mid-1950s, when Barney met her last new love, Janine Lahovary, the wife of a retired Romanian ambassador.  Lahovary made a point of winning Romaine Brooks's friendship, Barney reassured Brooks that their relationship still came first, and the triangle appeared to be stable.Rodriguez, 341–344.



The salon resumed in 1949 and continued to attract young writers for whom it was as much a piece of history as a place where literary reputations were made.  Truman Capote was an intermittent guest for almost ten years; he described the decor as "totally turn-of-the-century" and remembered that Barney introduced him to the models for several characters in Marcel Proust's ''In Search of Lost Time''.Wickes, 255–256  Alice B. Toklas became a regular after Gertrude Stein's death in 1946.  Fridays in the 1960s honored Mary McCarthy and Marguerite Yourcenar, who in 1980—eight years after Barney's death—became the first female member of the French Academy.Rodriguez, 336, 353–4.

Barney did not return to writing epigrams, but did publish two volumes of memoirs about other writers she had known, ''Souvenirs Indiscrets'' (''Indiscreet Memories'', 1960) and ''Traits et Portraits'' (''Traits and Portraits'', 1963).  She also worked to find a publisher for Brooks's memoirs and to place her paintings in galleries.Souhami, 194.

In the late 1960s Brooks became increasingly reclusive and paranoid; she sank into a depression and refused to see the doctors Barney sent.  Bitter at Lahovary's presence during their last years, which she had hoped they would spend exclusively together, she finally broke off contact with Barney.  Barney continued to write to her, but received no replies.  Brooks died in December 1970, and Barney on 2 February 1972 of heart failure.Rodriguez, 362–365.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="698e1a898b818cc04a3df36ce3471e88" name="Carolus-Duran---Natalie-at-" sectnum="7#1">../img/698e1a898b818cc04a3df36ce3471e88.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>