<document id="86a8e2d1fc7d097075cca2b875e396c0-3.7" name="Maria:_or,_The_Wrongs_of_Woman" cat="17">
<text>
Sensibility in the second half of the eighteenth century was considered both a physical and a moral phenomenon. Physicians and anatomists believed that the more sensitive people's nerves, the more emotionally affected they would be by their surroundings. Since women were thought to have keener nerves than men, it was also believed that women were more emotional than men.Barker-Benfield, 9. The emotional excess associated with sensibility also theoretically produced an ethic of compassion: those with sensibility could easily sympathize with people in pain. Thus historians have credited the discourse of sensibility and those who promoted it with the increased humanitarian efforts, such as the movement to abolish the slave trade, of the eighteenth century.Barker-Benfield, 224. But sensibility was also thought to paralyze those who had too much of it; they were weakened by constant vicarious suffering.

By the time Wollstonecraft was writing ''The Wrongs of Woman'', sensibility had already been under sustained attack for a number of years.Todd, ''Sensibility'', 144. Sensibility, which had initially promised to draw individuals together through sympathy, was now viewed as "profoundly separatist"; novels, plays, and poems that employed the language of sensibility asserted individual rights, sexual freedom, and unconventional familial relationships based only upon feeling.Todd, ''Sensibility'', 136. Sensibility seemed to many, particularly during a time of political reaction, to offer too much political power to women and to emasculate British men needed for fighting France.Todd, ''Sensibility'', 133.

All of Wollstonecraft's writings betray a tortured relationship with the language of sensibility and ''The Wrongs of Woman'' is no exception. As feminist scholar Mitzi Myers has observed, Wollstonecraft is usually described as an "enlightened philosopher strenuously advocating the cultivation of reason as the guide to both self-realization and social progress", but her works do not unambiguously support such a model of selfhood. Her emphasis on "feeling, imagination, and interiority" mark her as a Romantic, particularly in ''Letters Written in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark'' (1796). Repeatedly, in both her fiction and non-fiction, Wollstonecraft argues that the proper understanding of one's emotions leads to a transcendent virtue.Myers, "Unfinished Business", 108; 111.

However, because Wollstonecraft herself is contradictory and vague in the unfinished ''Wrongs of Woman'', there is no real scholarly consensus on what exactly the novel says about sensibility. Wollstonecraft is intentionally breaking the conventions of sentimental fiction, but exactly what her goals are in doing so is unclear.  For example, Maria and Jemima can seemingly be identified with the traditional categories of "reason" (Jemima) and "sensibility" (Maria), but since such couples were usually male and female, Wollstonecraft's characterization challenges conventional definitions of gender.Todd, ''Women's Friendships'', 208.

Some critics interpret Maria's story ironically, arguing that the juxtaposition of Maria's sentimental and romantic narrative with Jemima's harsh and bleak narrative encourages such a reading. In this interpretation, Maria's narrative is read as a parody of sentimental fiction that aims to demonstrate the "wrongs" that women inflict upon themselves when they overindulge in sensibility.Mellor, 415–17. Although Wollstonecraft promotes sensibility in this text, it is not the same kind that she condemns in the ''Rights of Woman''; proper sensibility, she contends, rests on sympathy and, most importantly, is controlled by reason.Mellor, 418. A woman with this kind of sensibility would not be "blown about by every gust of momentary feeling".Wollstonecraft, ''Vindication of the Rights of Woman'', 177. Other critics see ''The Wrongs of Woman'' as a "negation" of the anti-sentimental arguments offered in the ''Rights of Woman''. Citing Jemima's infrequent appearances in the narrative and the narrator's own use of the language of sensibility, they have difficulty in accepting the claim that the novel is undercutting or questioning the rhetoric of sensibility.Poovey, 104–105.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a0e1387d65a6581a8fabaf7c1def95e4" name="HighmorePamelaFainting" sectnum="3.7#1">../img/a0e1387d65a6581a8fabaf7c1def95e4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>