<document id="86a8e2d1fc7d097075cca2b875e396c0-3.7.1" name="Maria:_or,_The_Wrongs_of_Woman" cat="17">
<text>
One of the key differences between Wollstonecraft's novels and her philosophical treatises, as feminist critic Cora Kaplan has argued, is that her fiction values female emotion while her treatises present it as "reactionary and regressive, almost counter-revolutionary".Kaplan, "Wild Nights", 35. The ''Rights of Woman''  portrays sexuality as a masculine characteristic, and while Wollstonecraft argues that some masculine characteristics are universal, this is not one of them. In the ''The Wrongs of Woman'', however, she accepts, relishes, and uses the sexualized female body as a medium of communication: Maria embraces her lust for Darnford and establishes a relationship with him. While in the ''Rights of Woman'' she had emphasized companioniate relationships, arguing that passions should cool between lovers, in ''The Wrongs of Woman'', she celebrates those passions.Johnson, 58–59; see also, Todd, ''A Revolutionary Life'', 430. Challenging contemporary moralists such as John Gregory and Rousseau, Wollstonecraft claimed that women could be fully sexualized beings.Johnson, 63; Kelly, ''Revolutionary Feminism'', 215.

Initially, Maria wants to marry Venables because of his charitable nature; she believes him to be the romantic hero that she has read about in novels.Poovey, 99. However, she later realizes his duplicity:

 continued to single me out at the dance, press my hand at parting, and utter expressions of unmeaning passion, to which I gave a meaning naturally suggested by the romantic turn of my thoughts. … When he left us, the colouring of my picture became more vivid—Whither did not my imagination lead me? In short, I fancied myself in love—in love with the disinterestedness, fortitude, generosity, dignity, and humanity, with which I had invested the hero I dubbed.Wollstonecraft, ''The Wrongs of Woman'' (Kelly), 130.
 
One of the important questions raised by the novel is whether Maria is deluded in her relationship with Darnford. Maria writes an autobiography for her daughter in which she admits that she was misled by Venables, but critics disagree over the extent to which she is also misled by Darnford. Some suggest that Maria repeats her mistake and imagines Darnford as a hero, citing as evidence Maria's refusal to leave the madhouse, when she is free to do so, because she wants to remain with him, as well as her infatuation with Rousseau's novel ''Julie, or the New Heloise''. She imagines Darnford as its "hero", St. Preux, the sometime lover but not husband of Julie.  Maria's reading and the plots she conjures in her imagination as a result of that reading are the cause of her downfall in this interpretation: unable or unwilling to separate fiction from reality, she incorporates Darnford into her romantic fantasies.Poovey, 99; see also Taylor, 135 and Todd, ''Women's Friendship'', 210–11; Maurer, 48; Johnson, 65–66. Other critics, while agreeing that Maria is led astray by Darnford, argue that it is not her sexuality and eroticism that are the problem, but her choice of partner. They argue that Wollstonecraft is not portraying female sexuality as inherently detrimental, as she had in ''Mary'' and the ''Rights of Woman'', rather she is criticizing the directions it often takes.Taylor, 136–37.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f490b6c3a46a17bdbd37ff35ce16e5f7" name="The-First-Kiss-of-Love-La-Nouvelle-Heloise" sectnum="3.7.1#1">../img/f490b6c3a46a17bdbd37ff35ce16e5f7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>