<document id="86a8e2d1fc7d097075cca2b875e396c0-3.9" name="Maria:_or,_The_Wrongs_of_Woman" cat="17">
<text>
While some scholars emphasize ''The Wrongs of Woman'''s criticism of the institution of marriage and the laws restricting women in the eighteenth century, others focus on the work's description of "the experience of ''being'' female, with the emotional violence and intellectual debilitation" that accompanies it (emphasis in original).Taylor, 56; see also Sapiro, 265–66; Myers, "Unfinished Business", 110. It is in Wollstonecraft's depiction of a female mind educating itself and creating a specifically feminine sense of self that she "breaks new ground".Myers, "Unfinished Business", 111. Maria's role as mother allows her to instruct herself, thereby creating her own sense of self; in advising her daughter through the manuscript she is writing, Maria learns about herself and realizes her past errors. Her ability to formulate her own selfhood can be contrasted to the heroine of Wollstonecraft's first novel, ''Mary: A Fiction'', who transfers her maternal cravings from character to character.Maurer, 37.

Furthermore, while patriarchal marriages are one of the great wrongs perpetrated upon women, Wollstonecraft argues that a greater wrong is women's lack of independence. Because they are unable to find respectable, well-paid work, they are reliant upon men. Women such as Jemima are reduced to hard physical labor, stealing, begging, or prostituting themselves in order to survive; they are demeaned by this work and think meanly of themselves because of it.Mellor, 414–15; Taylor, 56.

Because male-female relationships are inherently unequal in her society, Wollstonecraft endeavours to formulate a new kind of friendship in ''The Wrongs of Woman'': motherhood and sisterhood. It is Maria's pathetic story regarding the kidnapping of her child that first interests Jemima in her plight. The novel fragments also suggest that the tale might not end with a marriage, but rather with the creation of a new kind of family, one constituted by two mothers for Maria's child. With Jemima's rescue of Maria, Wollstonecraft appears to reject the traditional romantic plot and invent a new one, necessitated by the failure of society to grant women their natural rights.Johnson, 67–68; see also Mellor, 420; Taylor, 243–44; Sapiro, 155. 

While more recent critics have emphasized the revolutionary aspects of the cross-class friendship between Jemima and Maria, others have questioned the extent of that radicalism, arguing that Jemima's story occupies a small section of the novel and is abruptly truncated.Poovey, 104. Mary Poovey also maintains that Wollstonecraft fails to extend her critique of marriage and society from the individual to the systemic level.Poovey, 108–109.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="177823d70c5a9aad1b1cdfb0b631fa01" name="Henriette_Browne_Mutter_Kind" sectnum="3.9#1">../img/177823d70c5a9aad1b1cdfb0b631fa01.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>