<document id="872a277b6367beeebd2da26b171df854-1.5" name="Uncle_Tupelo" cat="20">
<text>
With the addition of Stirratt, Coomer, and Johnston just prior to the recording of ''Anodyne'', Farrar and Tweedy's relationship became more tumultuous and led to verbal altercations between Tweedy and Farrar after concerts. In one account, Tweedy recalled:Kot 2004. p. 77

Around this time, I would say something into a microphone onstage, and afterward  pull me aside and say, "Don't you ever fucking talk into that microphone again."  He would misconstrue me talking into the microphone as more evidence of my out-of-control, rampant ego, more evidence of me feeling like I didn't have to be so fucking afraid anymore.

Tweedy felt the new members gave him a new opportunity to contribute to the band, but Farrar felt disdain for Tweedy's new carefree attitude. Years later, Farrar would claim that he had been tempted to quit the band after seeing Tweedy stroking the hair of Farrar's girlfriend, an act which he believed to have been a proposition. Last accessed June 8, 2007. In January 1994, Farrar called manager Tony Margherita to inform him of his decision to leave the band. Farrar told Margherita that he was no longer having fun, and didn't want to work with Tweedy anymore.Kot 2004. p. 81–82 Soon after the breakup, Farrar explained his departure: "It just seemed like it reached a point where Jeff and I really weren't compatible. It had ceased to be a symbiotic songwriting relationship, probably after the first record." Last accessed June 8, 2007.

Tweedy was enraged that he heard the news secondhand from Margherita, since Farrar decided not to tell him in person. The following day, the two singers engaged in a barbarous verbal confrontation.Kot 2004. p. 82–83 As a favor to Margherita—who had spent a substantial amount of money to keep the band running—Farrar agreed to a final tour with Uncle Tupelo in North America. Tweedy and Farrar again engaged in a shouting match two weeks into the tour, due to Farrar's refusal to sing harmony on any of Tweedy's songs. The band made its first appearance on national television during the tour when they were featured on ''Late Night with Conan O'Brien''. Sire had requested that the band perform "The Long Cut" on the show, which further irked Farrar since the song was written and sung by Tweedy. Uncle Tupelo's last concert was May 1, 1994 at Mississippi Nights in St. Louis, Missouri. Tweedy and Farrar each performed nine songs during the concert, and Mike Heidorn performed as drummer during the encore.Kot 2004. p. 84
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0f788ac4ca0c46653e93bbdccadb57dc" name="Utposter-lg" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/0f788ac4ca0c46653e93bbdccadb57dc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>