<document id="873bcc274003298160f330f1cbed9e8f-3.7" name="Paul_Collingwood" cat="26">
<text>
Following a successful summer, Collingwood was selected later in 2006 for both the 2006 ICC Champions Trophy squad and Ashes touring party. However, after two lacklustre defeats to India and Australia, critics such as Geoffrey Boycott and some fans began to question the coaching staff's placement of him in the batting order.

The return of Andrew Flintoff following an injury would reignite the ongoing debate about which two of Cook, Bell and Collingwood should be included in the team, with many speculating that Collingwood would be the man to miss out. With the sudden departure of Marcus Trescothick from the tour just over a week before the First Test, the debate was settled for the time being.

The first ball of the First Test, at the Gabba in Brisbane, bowled wildly wide by Steve Harmison set the tone for the series.  However, on the fourth day, England seemed to be batting towards a draw, when Collingwood, who had worked his way to a hard&ndash;earned 96 was stumped "...skipping miles down the pitch and trying to smack Warne over his head to reach a hundred". This was a pivotal moment: England went on to lose the next six wickets for 126 runs, and so lost the Test match.  In the Second Test at Adelaide, Collingwood made a career-best 206 in England's first innings, sharing in a 310&ndash;run fourth&ndash;wicket stand with Pietersen; he became only the eighth English double centurion against Australia in Ashes history, and the first in Australia since Wally Hammond scored 251 and 200 in consecutive innings during the 1928–29 Ashes.  Hopefully we can replace this with a reputbale pundit (not a tabloid)--> In the second innings he added an unbeaten 22 from 119 balls, but England collapsed to 129 all out and so went 2&ndash;0 down.  Collingwood received both praise and criticism from commentators on the manner in which he batted with the tail-enders.

England fared no better in the Third and Fourth Tests, losing them both, with Collingwood picking up only 60 with the bat in his four innings.  During the Fifth Test at the Sydney Cricket Ground in January 2007, Australia's Shane Warne revived the controversy of Collingwood's MBE with clearly audible "sledging" at Collingwood's expense.  Collingwood's performance during this Test was mediocre, scoring 27 and 17 with the bat and not being called upon to bowl a single ball, while Warne scored a quick-fire 71 (including nine 4's and two 6's) as Australia won comfortably by ten wickets.

Despite the series ending with a 5&ndash;0 whitewash by Australia, Collingwood finished the series ranked 14th in the LG ICC World Rankings for Test batsmen.

The Commonwealth Bank One-Day International series began on a low note for Collingwood, with a loss in the opening game against Australia at the Melbourne Cricket Ground.  Despite the defeat being followed by a narrow win over New Zealand in Hobart, the team and Collingwood went into a rapid decline, losing a string of four matches.  He missed England's 92&ndash;run victory over Australia  due to food poisoning, but returned to make 106 and capture two wickets in the decisive 14&ndash;run victory over New Zealand in the final group stage match.  He then hit a century and scored the winning runs as England won the first of three finals in Melbourne, against Australia, becoming the eighth Englishman to hit centuries in consecutive ODIs. His innings of 120 not out was the highest ever by an English ODI player against Australia in Australia.
In the second of the finals, he was Man of the Match for the third consecutive game, top&ndash;scoring for England with 70 and taking two wickets, as well another difficult catch off the bowling of Sajid Mahmood to once again dismiss Matthew Hayden.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9bb10cffe89c0ec416494426b23466f4" name="Paul_Collingwood_bowl" sectnum="3.7#1">../img/9bb10cffe89c0ec416494426b23466f4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>