<document id="876eea12931dd4a72f4c87817b19cfbb-3.3" name="John_Douglas_(architect)" cat="1">
<text>
Douglas designed some 500 buildings. He built at least 40 new churches or chapels, restored, altered or made additions to many other churches, and designed fittings and furniture for the interiors of churches.  He designed new houses, altered or made additions to others, and built various structures associated with those houses.  Douglas' works also included farms, shops, offices, hotels, a hospital, drinking fountains, clocks, schools, public baths, a library, a bridge, an obelisk, cheese factories, and public conveniences.  As his office was in Chester, most of his works were in Cheshire and North Wales, although some were further afield, in Lancashire, Staffordshire, Warwickshire and Scotland.

Throughout his career Douglas attracted commissions from wealthy and important patrons. His first-known independent work was an ornament, which is no longer in existence, for the garden of the Honourable Mrs Cholmondeley.  She was the sister-in-law of Hugh Cholmondeley, 2nd Baron Delamere, and it was from the 2nd Baron that Douglas received his first major commission, a considerable rebuilding of the south wing of his seat at Vale Royal Abbey in 1860.  Around the same time, Lord Delamere commissioned him to build the church of St John the Evangelist at Over, Winsford, as a memorial to his first wife.  

Douglas' most important patrons were the Grosvenor family of Eaton Hall, Cheshire.  In 1865 he was commissioned to design the entrance lodge and other structures for Grosvenor Park in Chester, and St John's Church in the village of Aldford in the Eaton Hall estate for Richard Grosvenor, 2nd Marquess of Westminster.  When the marquess died in 1869 he was succeeded by his son Hugh Grosvenor, 1st Duke of Westminster.  Douglas received a large number of commissions from the 1st Duke and from his son, the 2nd Duke, throughout his career.  It is estimated that for the 1st Duke alone he designed four churches and chapels, eight parsonages and large houses, about 15 schools, around 50 farms (in whole or in part), about 300 cottages, lodges and smithies, two factories, two inns and about 12 commercial buildings on the Eaton Hall estate alone.  He also designed buildings on the duke's Halkyn estate in Flintshire, including another church.

Other wealthy landowners who commissioned work from Douglas included William Molyneux, 4th Earl of Sefton, Francis Egerton, 3rd Earl of Ellesmere, George Cholmondeley, 5th Marquess of Cholmondeley, Rowland Egerton-Warburton of Arley Hall, Cheshire, and in Wales, the family of Lord Kenyon, and the Gladstone family, including W. E Gladstone.  He also received commissions from industrialists, including John & Thomas Johnson, soap and alkali manufacturers from Runcorn, Richard Muspratt, a chemical industrialist from Flint, Flintshire, and W. H. Lever, soap manufacturer and creator of the village of Port Sunlight.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6e4dce88b584b0eb9835fdfcbf5ca2fa" name="Vale-Royal-Abbey-Douglas" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/6e4dce88b584b0eb9835fdfcbf5ca2fa.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>