<document id="882786b8ff6b3b9233c7afde899f7590-2.2" name="Ronald_Niel_Stuart" cat="29">
<text>
Following the action Stuart remained with Campbell and Loveless as Inspectors of Shipping, choosing those vessels they believed to be best suited to Q-ship work for naval service. After some time ashore all three returned to sea in a vessel they had personally chosen, an old, battered tramp steamer named SS ''Vittoria''. Renaming it HMS ''Pargust'', they armed their vessel with a 4" gun, two twelve pounders, two machine guns, torpedo tubes and depth charges. P.126, ''The Naval VCs'', Stephen Snelling  Thus armed the ''Pargust'' departed on her first patrol to the same grounds where ''U-83'' had been sunk, in the waters south of Ireland. For the first few days her duties consisted only of rescuing survivors from sunken cargo ships but with increasing German activity, an attack was expected at any moment. On the 7 June 1917, ''Pargust'' was suddenly struck by a torpedo fired at very close range from an unseen German submarine. P.304, ''Symbol of Courage'', Max Arthur Unlike the ''Farnborough'' action, the damage done to the ''Pargust'' was immense. The ship was holed close to the waterline, and its cover was almost blown when one of the twelve pounder gun ports was blasted free from its mounting; it was only the quick thinking of sailor William Williams, who took the full weight of the gun port on himself, that prevented the gun being exposed. One petty officer was killed and a number wounded. P.127, ''The Naval VCs'', Stephen Snelling 

By this stage in the war, the German submarine authorities had become aware of the existence of Q-ships and Captain Ernst Rosenow of the UC-29 was taking no risks with his target, remaining at 400 yards (366m) distance watching the staged panicked evacuation of the ship. While the hidden gun crews watched the enemy approach the lifeboats, the officer in charge of the boats, Lieutenant Francis Hereford, realised that the submarine would follow his movements, as its commander assumed him to be the captain. Hereford therefore ordered his men to row back towards the ship, thus luring the enemy into range. This made the submarine commander believe that the ship’s crew were planning to regain their vessel and he immediately closed to just 50 yards (46m), surfaced and began angrily semaphoring to the "survivors" in the boats. This was exactly what the gun crews had been waiting for and a volley of fire was directed at the U-boat. P.128, ''The Naval VCs'', Stephen Snelling  Numerous holes were blown in the conning tower and the submarine desperately attempted to flee on the surface before slowing down and heeling over, trailing oil. The gun crews then stopped firing only for the submarine to suddenly restart its engines and attempt to escape. In a final barrage of fire the submarine was hit fatally, a large explosion blowing the vessel in two. Rosenow and 22 of his crew were killed, whilst two survivors were rescued by the panic party.

The wrecked ''Pargust'' was taken in tow by HMS ''Crocus'', USS ''Cushing'' and HMS ''Zinnia'' and reached Queenstown barely afloat nearly two days later. The port's admiral congratulated the crew personally on their arrival. As before, the crew were awarded £1,000 prize money and several awards were promised. Unusually, the Admiralty were unable to decide who amongst the ship's crew should receive the Victoria Cross as all were deemed to have participated in the action with equal valour. It was thus decided for the first time, under article 13 of the Victoria Cross's royal warrant, that one officer and one enlisted man would be granted the award following a ballot by the ship's company. P.129, ''The Naval VCs'', Stephen Snelling  After the vote, from which Campbell abstained, the Victoria Crosses were awarded to Stuart and William Williams. Fourteen other crew members were awarded medals, including DSOs for Campbell and Hereford. In addition, every sailor had his participation in the action and subsequent ballot noted on his service records.

Due to the official secrecy surrounding the activities of the Q-ships, Stuart's and Williams's Victoria Crosses were announced without fanfare or explanation of their actions; even the ''Pargust's'' name was omitted from the citation. The full account of the action was not published until after the armistice in November 1918. Stuart was noted as the first Anglo-Canadian to receive the Victoria Cross and his obituary later stated that in the action, "his gallantry stood out". The medal was presented to him in a ceremony at Buckingham Palace by King George V on the 23 July 1917.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2951032ee63200ca40084209e49c26b1" name="CharingRNStuartVC-2" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/2951032ee63200ca40084209e49c26b1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>