<document id="88315ba1db2f60ceaa8e869dd3c935da-1.2" name="Waterfall_Gully,_South_Australia" cat="11">
<text>
One of the earliest accounts of Waterfall Gully comes from a "Mr Kent" who, along with Captain Collet Barker and Barker's servant, Miles, climbed Mount Lofty in 1831. In making their ascent the party skirted a ravine—described by Mr Kent as possessing "smooth and grassy sides"—which is believed by Anne Hardy to have been Waterfall Gully. Subsequent to Barker's ascent, the first settlers who were recorded as having climbed Mount Lofty were Bingham Hutchinson and his servant, William Burt. The pair made three attempts to scale the mount before succeeding, and for their first attempt they attempted to traverse Waterfall Gully.Hardy (1989), p. 6. The attempt was unsuccessful, but in July, 1837, Hutchinson wrote about the gully though which they had travelled. Waterfall Gully he wrote, had proven difficult, as the plants were so thickly grown as to provide a significant barrier to their progress. Near the point of surrender, Hutchinson described how they were "agreeably surprised by seeing a wall of rock about fifty or sixty feet  high, which stretched across the ravine, and from the top of it leapt the brook which had so long been  companion".Hutchinson, in Warburton (1981), pp. 187-188. Hutchinson reported that they continued the climb, but surrendered after being faced with another steep ravine separating them from their goal. The brook was First Creek, and the waterfall they sighted is today known as First Falls.Warburton (1977), p. 28.

Nevertheless, Hutchinson was not the first to see First Falls. The first known recorded sighting of the waterfall by a colonial was that of John William Adams, an emigrant of H.M.S. ''Buffalo'' in early January 1837, who named it "Adams' Waterfall". He was traveling with his wife, Susanna and a party consisting of Nicholson's and Breaker's who had the use of a dray to go into the hills. Adams states "we were opposite the spot where the Eagle on the Hill now is, and the question was put, who would volunteer to go down the hillside to try for water".Stringer (1980)
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="27c9b41e08347d367086b8a66024594a" name="Waterfall_Gully_1866" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/27c9b41e08347d367086b8a66024594a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>