<document id="88315ba1db2f60ceaa8e869dd3c935da-5" name="Waterfall_Gully,_South_Australia" cat="11">
<text>
The main attraction of Waterfall Gully is the waterfall, First Falls. It is at the south-eastern end of the road, in land owned by Cleland Conservation Park. The weir at the bottom of the Waterfall was constructed in the late 1800s and was part of Adelaide's early water supply. Development in the area has continued since the construction of a restaurant in 1912.Melbourne (1956b), p. 156. Developments over recent decades have included improving access to the site, upgrading the bridges, and the addition of new signage."Waterfall Gully facelift" (4 June 1998), p. 14.

The Waterfall Gully Restaurant was constructed between 1911 and 1912 by South Australian architects Albert Selmar Conrad and his brother Frank,"Place Details: Dr Helen Mayos House, 176&ndash;180 Mackinnon Pde, North Adelaide, SA, Australia" and was formally opened by Sir Day Bosanquet on 9 November 1912. Built in the style of a Swiss chalet, the building has been heritage listed since 1987,"Heritage Places Database Details: Waterfall Gully Kiosk/Restaurant, Cleland Conservation Park" and is reputedly haunted by the ghost of a firefighter who died from burns suffered in 1926.Hardy (1989), p. 12.

Other fire tracks and walking trails wind around the hills that surround Waterfall Gully, branching off from Chambers Gully, Woolshed Gully or the area around First Creek. Destinations include Crafers, Eagle on the Hill, Mount Lofty, Mount Osmond and the Cleland Wildlife Park, located in the Cleland Conservation Park. The tracks have been completely rebuilt and resurfaced in the past ten years, and a number of older and more perilous routes have been sealed because of the difficult terrain. Many offer views of the city of Adelaide as well as the Gully itself. One of these is notable for connecting to the  Heysen Trail, and the trails are highly frequented.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e371548dc98008d6f797e68a68a0c1f2" name="Waterfall_Gully_Restaurant" sectnum="5#1">../img/e371548dc98008d6f797e68a68a0c1f2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>