<document id="88eae6f1a75d2f5ec6c493900a63d4e7-1.1" name="2007_USC_Trojans_football_team" cat="26">
<text>
The Trojans ended the 2006 season with a victory in the 2007 Rose Bowl Game and a No. 4 ranking in both AP and Coaches polls, their fifth straight year winning the Pac-10 Championship and finishing in the top 4.  During that 5-year period, the team won two national championships (2003, 2004)., ESPN.com, Accessed July 7, 2008., ESPN.com, Accessed July 7, 2008.  Prior to the 2007 season, the Trojans were ranked No. 1 in all national pre-season polls and were expected to challenge for the National Championship.Mark Schlabach, , ESPN.com, February 23, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.Stewart Mandel, , CNNSI.com, April 24, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.  The team received a boost in the offseason when many draft-eligible juniors decided to return to school for their senior seasons; the holdover of talented veterans was a major factor in the Trojans being considered preeminent favorites for a national championship.  As expected, USC was at the top of the first Coaches Poll of the season, released on August 3, 2007, with 45 of a possible 60 first-place votes; other teams receiving first-place votes were No. 2 Louisiana State University (LSU) with 4 votes, No. 3 Florida with 6 votes, and No. 5 Michigan with 2 votes., ESPN.com, August 3, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.  USC was also at the top of the first AP Poll, released on August 18, with 62 of 65 first-place votes, with No. 2 LSU receiving 2 votes and No. 3 West Virginia receiving one., Associated Press, August 18, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.  In mid-August, all twelve experts polled by ESPN picked USC to win the season's BCS Championship Game.  On August 29, 2007, the day before the season began, three of four experts at SI.com predicted USC would win the BCS Championship Game, attributing the decision to the Trojans defense.



In terms of overall talent, Carroll stated that the 2007 squad is the "most competitive team we've had" during his six-year tenure as coach.Bill Plaschke, , ''Los Angeles Times'', May 25, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.  Senior starting quarterback John David Booty entered the season as a front-runner for the Heisman Trophy.Gene Menez, , CNNSI.com, April 24, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.  Booty, along with returning senior tackle Sam Baker, were ranked as two of the "Top 20 Players Heading Into 2007" by ''Sports Illustrated''., CNNSI.com, April 24, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.

The Trojans entered pre-season fall camp well stocked at the running back position, with 10 former high school Super Prep All-Americans, nine of whom were Prep Star all-Americans and seven were Parade all-Americans.Lee Jenkins, , ''The New York Times'', August 26, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.  The exceptional running back situation at USC was a major factor in ''Sports Illustrated'' forecasting the 2007 season as "The Year of the Running Back."Austin Murphy, , ''Sports Illustrated'', August 14, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.  In judging USC as a pre-season favorite, particular emphasis was made on the defense.  Considered to be one of the best defenses during the 2006 season, the Trojans entered 2007 with 10 returning starters and key backups.  After a one-season experiment with the 3-4 defense formation, the defense returned to using the 4-3.  The highlight of the defense was the linebacking corp, led by Brian Cushing, Keith Rivers and Rey Maualuga.Arash Markazi, , SI.com, August 14, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.Barker Davis, , ''Washington Times'', August 28, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.

At the Pacific-10 Conference media day, the Trojans were the unanimous pre-season pick to win the conference; this was USC's fifth year in a row as the favorite to win the conference title, and only the third time in conference history that a team had been picked unanimously (the other two were USC in 2004 and 2005)., Associated Press, July 26, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6576f8976f8dccf4707f2954154dca3f" name="091507-USCNeb-CushingWilliams" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/6576f8976f8dccf4707f2954154dca3f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>