<document id="88eae6f1a75d2f5ec6c493900a63d4e7-5.8" name="2007_USC_Trojans_football_team" cat="26">
<text>
USC opened Pac-10 conference play by hosting the Washington State Cougars. Entering the game, Trojans quarterback John David Booty and the receiver corp remained unproven after an uninspiring performance against Idaho and a run-dominated game against Nebraska.  Hoping to take advantage, Washington State elected to go into the game using a man-to-man pass coverage to allow more focus on stopping the Trojans running game.Lonnie White, , ''Los Angeles Times'', September 22, 2007, Accessed July 2, 2008.  The Cougars had given the then-No. 3 Trojans a scare in their 2006 meeting, with the game coming down to the final seconds.Gregg Bell, , Associated Press, October 1, 2006, Accessed July 2, 2008.

In the end, USC routed the Cougars 47–14, with a primarily aerial attack.  Booty reestablished his presence, completing 28 of 35 passes for 279 yards and four touchdowns before leaving the game early in the fourth quarter.  Tight end Fred Davis had a career night with nine receptions for 124 yards and two touchdowns.John Nadel, , Associated Press, September 22, 2007, Accessed July 2, 2008. Davis' performance marked the most yards receiving ever in a game by a Trojans tight end.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', September 24, 2007, Accessed July 2, 2008.  The Trojans' first offensive drive set the tone with 13 plays, 83 yards and a touchdown on fourth down; mostly coming from the air.Lonnie White, , ''Los Angeles Times'', September 22, 2007, Accessed July 2, 2008.  Receivers Patrick Turner and Vidal Hazelton were able to find a groove and make plays after sputtering against Nebraska.  In the rushing game, Chauncey Washington started and rushed for 84 of USC's 207 yards.  Stafon Johnson, who led the Trojans ground game against Nebraska, had nine carries and finished with 48 yards.  Joe McKnight also got his first extended work and gained 48 yards in seven carries.  USC built a 27–7 halftime lead and then scored on its first three possessions in the second half.  The Trojans defense kept the Cougars in check, putting pressure on quarterback Alex Brink and limiting Washington State to 64 yards rushing.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', September 23, 2007, Accessed July 2, 2008.

Junior cornerback Cary Harris dislocated his right shoulder during the game and was replaced by Shareece Wright.  Linebacker Brian Cushing reinjured the ankle he sprained in the opener against Idaho.  Sixth-year senior running back Hershel Dennis played for the first time since the 2004 season during the fourth quarter, gaining 14 yards in four carries; he had sat out the two previous seasons due to injury.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', September 23, 2007, Accessed July 2, 2008.

The victory continued the Trojans' domination of the series, 55–8–4; it also extended the record of top-ranked USC teams against the Cougars to 5–0.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', September 22, 2007, Accessed July 2, 2008.  The game marked the first time it had ever rained during a USC game in September; as a result the attendance was 86,876, the first time in 16 home games that the Trojans failed to draw at least 90,000.  USC extended its home winning streak to 35 games.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c92542c75c92552430d12ec9cc41d2fc" name="091507-USCNeb-KeithRivers" sectnum="5.8#1">../img/c92542c75c92552430d12ec9cc41d2fc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>