<document id="88eae6f1a75d2f5ec6c493900a63d4e7-5.11" name="2007_USC_Trojans_football_team" cat="26">
<text>
After the previous week's upset loss to Stanford, the Trojans hosted the Arizona Wildcats, led by head coach Mike Stoops, aiming to correct mistakes and demonstrate that they were still in contention for the Pac-10 title and to remain an outside candidate for the national title game.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', October 13, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.Matt Becker, , ''Associated Press'', October 13, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.  Matters were complicated when it was announced that starting quarterback John David Booty would not start due to a broken middle finger on his throwing hand, suffered during the previous week's loss.  As a result, redshirt sophomore Mark Sanchez made his first start for the Trojans; previously he had only played during garbage time.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', October 12, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.  The Trojans also remained without offensive linemen Chilo Rachal and Kris O'Dowd, as well as leading rusher Stafon Johnson, who remained idle for a second week after bruising his left foot during the game against Washington.  The Trojans entered the game a 21-point favorite.John Nadel, , ''Associated Press'', October 13, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.



The Trojans again showed inconsistency for most of the game before coming alive in the fourth quarter and pulling away to a 20–13 victory.  USC started out well, going ahead 10–0 in the second quarter after running back Chauncey Washington's 18-yard touchdown run and David Buehler's 27-yard field goal.  However, the offense began to sputter; the Trojans amassed only 12 total yards in the second quarter and 50 in the third.  Part of the offense's problems were turnovers; Sanchez threw two interceptions in the second quarter, allowing Arizona to tie the game going into halftime.  The Wildcats kicked another field goal early in the third quarter to go up 13–10, raising speculation that USC was going to be upset for the second consecutive week.  The momentum of the game quickly changed in the fourth quarter after freshman running back Joe McKnight, touted as the next great Trojans tailback but yet to meet expectations, made a 45-yard punt return that Sanchez followed up on the next play with a 25-yard touchdown pass to tight end Fred Davis.  After a defensive stop, Arizona punter Keenyn Crier kicked an 83-yard punt to the Trojans one-yard line.  The Trojans pushed forward with fullback Stanley Havili before McKnight again made a big play, running 59 yards and setting up what would be a Trojans field goal.  The USC defense then forced an Arizona turn-over on downs to preserve the victory.John Nadel, , October 13, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', October 14, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.  Sanchez recovered from his poor first half performance with a strong performance in the second, where he completed 11 of 15 passes for 74 yards and a touchdown while later making a key 10-yard scramble on third and seven late in the fourth quarter.Ben Bloch, , ''Los Angeles Times'', October 14, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.

The injuries that had plagued USC throughout the season continued as All-American tackle Sam Baker left the game because of a hamstring strain and freshman guard Zack Heberer, already substituting for an injured Chilo Rachal, suffered a shoulder bruise.  On the defense, linebacker Rey Maualuga suffered a hip injury and safety Kevin Ellison broke his nose.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', October 14, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.  An uncommon number of injuries, especially along the offensive line, depleted reserve players and forced Trojans to reach out to the general student population in order to find students with previous lineman experience to help on the scout team's offensive line; however, none were officially added to the roster.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', October 19, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.

In light of the Trojans close victory, USC dropped in both major polls, falling to No. 13 in the AP Poll and No. 9 in the Coaches Poll, tied with previously No. 2 California, which had just lost an upset to Oregon State., ESPN.com, Accessed July 3, 2008.  The Trojans debuted at No. 14 in the Bowl Championship Series standings., ESPN.com, Accessed July 3, 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b529834e8f54604b577c92ee9336fe8b" name="091507-USCNeb-MarkSanchez_v2" sectnum="5.11#1">../img/b529834e8f54604b577c92ee9336fe8b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>