<document id="88eae6f1a75d2f5ec6c493900a63d4e7-1.5" name="2007_USC_Trojans_football_team" cat="26">
<text>
On January 6, 2007, Shortly after the Trojans ended their 2006 season with a win at the 2007 Rose Bowl, two-year starting placekicker Mario Danelo was found dead at the bottom of a cliff in San Pedro, California.  Danelo had been expected to start during the 2007 season.  For the 2007 season, USC players wore a #19 sticker on their helmets in honor of Danelo; in addition the Kennedy-Jones practice field had the number "19" sprayed onto its end zones and the Coliseum hung a banner above the player's tunnel with Danelo's name and also paid tribute to him on the goal-post pads.Scott Wolf, , ''Daily News'', August 12, 2007, ''Accessed August 12, 2007''.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', March 26, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.


The Trojans lost their offensive coordinator, Lane Kiffin, on January 23, 2007, when he was hired to  be the new head coach of the Oakland Raiders; the 31-year-old Kiffin became the youngest head coach in Raiders history, and the youngest head coach since the formation of the modern NFL., Associated Press, January 22, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008. The following week, Pete Carroll named Steve Sarkisian as his team's new offensive coordinator.  Sarkisian had interviewed with the Raiders for their vacant head coach position but withdrew from the process to stay at USC, where he had been the assistant head coach and quarterbacks coach.Steve Corkran, , ''Oakland Tribune'', January 19, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.

Intra-conference controversy arose in March 2007, when Stanford coach Jim Harbaugh was quoted as saying "'s only got one more year, though. He'll be there one more year. That's what I've heard. I heard it inside the staff."  Upon further questions, Harbaugh claimed he had heard it from staff at USC.Ted Miller, , ESPN.com, April 6, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.  At the Pac-10 Conference media day (July 26, 2007), Harbaugh praised the Trojans, stating "There is no question in my mind that USC is the best team in the country and may be the best team in the history of college football"; the declaration, especially in light of his earlier comment, garnered more media attention., Associated Press, July 26, 2007.Pat Forde, , ESPN.com, July 27, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.

In early July, LSU coach Les Miles stirred inter-conference controversy when he publicly criticized USC's 2007 schedule in front of LSU boosters; though the two schools had not played each other since 1984, the LSU Tiger faithful maintained a strong grudge against the Trojans after they shared the national title in the controversial 2003 season.Stewart Mandel, , SI.com, July 6, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.  LSU and Michigan were ranked as the pre-season No. 2 team in various polls.  Coincidentally, by week five of the 2007 season, there were questions as to whether USC's schedule was actually harder than LSU's, given their opponents' early-season performances.Mark Schlabach, , ESPN.com, September 24, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fca546976d15c82da6d3f413b43cef42" name="2008-0808-USC19-SteveSarkisian" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/fca546976d15c82da6d3f413b43cef42.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>