<document id="88eae6f1a75d2f5ec6c493900a63d4e7-5.10" name="2007_USC_Trojans_football_team" cat="26">
<text>
USC continued Pac-10 play by hosting the struggling Stanford Cardinal, under first-year coach Jim Harbaugh.  In a major upset, USC stumbled at home to the 41 point underdog, losing 24–23.

Harbaugh made headlines prior to the season by claiming 2007 would be Carroll's last year with USC before departing to the NFL, drawing a terse rebuke from Carroll; Harbaugh later called the 2007 Trojans one of the best teams in history at the Pac-10 Media Day, reiterating the position in the week before their game.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', October 6, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008. However, there were no hard feelings between the coaches. The two kept in cordial phone contact and Carroll made light of Harbaugh's comments several times during the season.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', October 3, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.



The Stanford starting quarterback, redshirt senior T. C. Ostrander, suffered a seizure on the afternoon of September 30, one day after their game against Arizona State; he was released from Stanford Hospital after a few hours, but as a precautionary measure he was held out of the game against USC.  The starting quarterback position fell to Tavita Pritchard, a redshirt sophomore with three passes in his college career.Thomas Bonk, , ''Los Angeles Times'', October 3, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.  Stanford was also without two other key starters: defensive lineman Ekom Udofia (ankle) and offensive lineman Allen Smith (knee).Ray Ratto, , ''San Francisco Chronicle'', October 5, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.  On October 3 it was announced that USC running back C.J. Gable, who was averaging a team-best 11 yards a carry, would undergo season-ending abdominal surgery to correct a nagging sports hernia that had limited his ability since the previous season; because he had only played in the first three games, he would seek a medical redshirt season.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', October 4, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.  Gable's fellow running back, Stafon Johnson, was also held out of the game due to a foot bruise suffered the previous week.

Stanford was the last team to beat USC at the Coliseum, doing so on September 29, 2001 under Tyrone Willingham (now the coach of Washington) against then-first year coach Carroll.  By game week, the line for the game favored the Trojans by 39.5 points, and reached 41 points by gametime.Lonnie White, , ''Los Angeles Times'', October 4, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.Arash Markazi, , SI.com, October 7, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.  The loss ended multiple USC streaks, including a five-game win streak against Stanford and a 35-game home winning streak.John Nadel, , Associated Press, October 7, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.  For sportsbooks, the loss to a 41-point underdog marked the biggest upset in their history.Stewart Mandel, , SI.com, October 7, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.

There were a few positive efforts for the Trojans: Tight end Fred Davis caught five passes for a career-best 152 yards, including a 63-yard touchdown; and nose tackle Sedrick Ellis had three sacks.  However, there were many more errors and substandard performances: quarterback John David Booty, who broke a bone in the middle finger of his throwing hand in the first half, had four passes intercepted in the second half.  The offensive line had been suffering since losing two starters in one play during the previous week's game at Washington, but the effect was severe against Stanford; the offensive line gave up four sacks, one more than the Trojans had surrendered all season, and USC gained only 95 yards rushing.  Key receiver Patrick Turner dropped several passes, the defense gave up 17 points in the fourth quarter and USC had an extra-point attempt blocked, a point which became a crucial difference.  Like their previous game against Washington, USC out-gained Stanford by 224 yards (459 to 235) but made many crucial turnovers and penalties.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', October 8, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', October 8, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.  In the press conference following the game, Coach Carroll summarized his concerns: "It's real clear that we have fallen out of line with our philosophy that has guided this program for years; we're turning the ball over too much."

Opinions in the sports press ranged from proclaiming the end of the USC's era of dominance in college football to calling the loss a major, but not fatal set-back to any hopes for a Trojans run at the national championship.Mark Schlabach, , ESPN.com, October 8, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008., ESPN.com, October 8, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.  The Trojans fell to No. 10 in the AP Poll; however, USC only fell to No. 7 in both the Coaches Poll and Harris Poll, both of which are the human components for determining who the BCS chooses for the National Championship Game., ESPN.com, Accessed July 3, 2008., ESPN.com, Accessed July 3, 2008.  As a result, USC remained in outside title contention with upcoming games against consensus-No. 2 California and top-10 Oregon.Chris Dufresne, , ''Los Angeles Times'', October 8, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.  The upset landed the Trojans in ESPN.com's Bottom 10.David Duffey, , ESPN.com, October 9, 2007, Accessed August 4, 2008.

In an interview the following month, Carroll assessed the mistakes that led to the loss as his own:


At the end of the regular season, ''Sports Illustrated'' chose Stanford's upset of USC as the second "Biggest Upset of 2007" after Division I FCS Appalachian State's upset of No. 5 Michigan.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="70bb6a83414a86b34a4e1d1b579a467d" name="JimHarbaugh2007" sectnum="5.10#1">../img/70bb6a83414a86b34a4e1d1b579a467d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>