<document id="88eae6f1a75d2f5ec6c493900a63d4e7-1.3" name="2007_USC_Trojans_football_team" cat="26">
<text>
In May, the Trojans were joined by former Arkansas quarterback Mitch Mustain, who was a 8–0 win/loss record as a starter during his freshman (and only) year with the team., Associated Press, May 21, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.  Mustain joined fellow Arkansas teammate and wide receiver Damian Williams, who transferred from Arkansas before the 2006 bowl season. Due to NCAA transfer rules all would be unable to compete until 2008, although they would be allowed on the scout team.

In early summer, Jordan Cameron, a former freshman basketball player from Brigham Young University, also transferred to USC to play football as a wide receiver., USC Athletic Department, July 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.  However, when USC refused to accept some of Cameron's credits from Brigham Young, he was forced to withdraw and attend Ventura College.  He missed the football season but was given the option to try and rejoin the team in 2008.  Even if he had stayed at USC, due to NCAA transfer rules he would have been ineligible to play in 2007.Scott Wolf, , ''San Bernardino Sun'', July 26, 2007, Accessed July 26, 2007.

With the late 2006 dismissal of Troy Van Blarcom (academics) and the death of Mario Danelo, USC was left with only one experienced kicker:Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', November 8, 2008, Accessed February 2, 2009.Garry Paskwietz, , WeAreSC.com, July 23, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008. David Buehler, a 2006 junior college transfer from Santa Ana College who competed mainly at fullback and safety, but was used for one successful field goal attempt the previous season.Mark Saxon, , ''The Orange County Register'', August 23, 2007, Accessed May 30, 2008.  In July 2007, Joe Houston, a junior college kicker from El Camino College, joined the team as a "preferred walk-on", guaranteed a non-scholarship spot on the team.  As a junior college transfer, Houston would be able to  play for the Trojans immediately.  USC also recruited former University of Nebraska kicker, Jordan Congdon, who was not eligible for the 2007 season; and Brad Smith, formerly of Davidson College.  Smith was able to play immediately under an NCAA rule that permits non-scholarship players who have already received a degree to transfer once with immediate eligibility.Gary Klein, , ''Los Angeles Times'', August 12, 2007, Accessed July 3, 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b0befe4491f4289d6ba5e50de2d6c842" name="MitchMustain-HS" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/b0befe4491f4289d6ba5e50de2d6c842.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>