<document id="8918c5402b82d897801a43959bdbb02e-5.3" name="Prince's_Palace_of_Monaco" cat="1">
<text>
By the time of Charles III's death in 1889, Monaco and Monte Carlo were synonymous as one and the same place, and had acquired, through gambling, a reputation as a louche and decadent playground of the rich. It attracted everyone from Russian grand dukes and railway magnates, often with their mistresses, to adventurers, causing the small country to be derided by many including Queen Victoria.''Edwards'', p. 155-157 In fact so decadent was Monaco considered that from 1882, when she first began visiting the French Riviera, Queen Victoria refused to make a courtesy social call at the palace.''Edwards'', p. 169 The contemporary writer Sabine Baring-Gould described the habituées of Monaco as: "....the moral cesspool of Europe." 

The successive rulers of Monaco tended to live elsewhere and visit their palace only occasionally. Charles III was succeeded in 1889 by Albert I. Albert married the daughter of a Scottish aristocrat. The couple had one son, Louis, before divorcing in 1880. Albert was a keen scientist and founded the Oceanographic Institute in 1906; as a pacifist he then founded the International Institute of Peace in Monaco. Albert's second wife, Alice Heine, did much to turn Monte Carlo into a cultural centre, establishing both ballet and the opera in the city. Having brought a large dowry into the family she contemplated turning the casino into a convalescent home for the poor who would benefit from recuperation in warm climes.''de Fontenoy'', p. 87. The couple separated before she was able to put her plan into action.  

Albert was succeeded in 1922 by his son Louis II. Louis II had been brought up by his mother and stepfather in Germany, and did not know Monaco at all until he was 11. He had a distant relationship with his father and served in the French Army. While posted abroad, he met his mistress Marie Juliette Louvet, by whom he had a daughter, Charlotte Louise Juliette, born in Algeria in 1898. As Prince of Monaco, Louis II spent much time elsewhere, preferring to live on the family estate of Le Marchais close to Paris. In 1911 Prince Louis had a law passed legitimising his daughter so that she could inherit the throne, in order to prevent its passing to a distant German branch of the family. The law was challenged and developed into what became known as  Monaco succession crisis. Finally in 1919 the prince formally adopted his illegitimate daughter Charlotte, who became known as Princess Charlotte, Duchess of Valentinois.''Glatt'', p.55 Louis II's collection of artefacts belonging to Napoleon I form the foundation of the Napoleon Museum at the palace, which is open to the public.

During World War II, Louis attempted to keep Monaco neutral, although his sympathies were with the Vichy French Government.''Taraborrelli'', p.202  This caused a rift with his grandson Rainier, his daughter's son, and the heirPrincess Charlotte ceded her succession rights to her son, Rainier, in 1944. to Louis' throne, who strongly supported the Allies against the Nazis.

Following the liberation of Monaco by the Allied forces, the 75-year-old Prince Louis did little for his principality and it began to fall into severe neglect. By 1946 he was spending most of his time in Paris, and on 27 July of that year, he married for the first time. Absent from Monaco during most of the final years of his reign, he and his wife lived on their estate in France. Prince Louis died in 1949 and was succeeded by his grandson, Prince Rainier III.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1fbe654acd8bac02f5de2e69cae80a98" name="Monte_Carlo_Casino" sectnum="5.3#1">../img/1fbe654acd8bac02f5de2e69cae80a98.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>