<document id="8936418508263cd8fa6b35d114ca7957-4" name="Homer_Simpson" cat="19">
<text>
Homer Simpson is one of the most popular and influential television characters in a variety of standards. ''USA Today'' cited the character as being one of the "top 25 most influential people of the past 25 years" in 2007, adding that Homer "epitomized the irony and irreverence at the core of American humor." Robert Thompson, director of Syracuse University's Center for the Study of Popular Television believes that "three centuries from now, English professors are going to be regarding Homer Simpson as one of the greatest creations in human storytelling." Animation historian Jerry Beck described Homer as one of the best animated characters, saying, "you know someone like it, or you identify with (it). That's really the key to a classic character." Homer has been described by ''The Sunday Times'' as "the greatest comic creation of  time". The article remarked, "every age needs its great, consoling failure, its lovable, pretension-free mediocrity. And we have ours in Homer Simpson."

Homer has been cited as a bad influence on children; for example, in 2005 a survey conducted in the United Kingdom found that 59% of parents felt that Homer promoted an unhealthy lifestyle. A five-year study of more than 2,000 middle-aged people in France found a possible link between weight and brain function, the findings of which were dubbed the "Homer Simpson syndrome". Results from a word memory test showed that people with a Body mass index (BMI) of 20 (considered to be a healthy level) remembered an average of nine out of 16 words. Meanwhile, people with a BMI of 30 (inside the obese range) remembered an average of just seven out of 16 words.

Despite Homer's embodiment of American culture, his influence has spread to other parts of the world. In 2003, Matt Groening revealed that his father, after whom Homer was named, was Canadian, and said that this made Homer himself a Canadian. The character was later made an honorary citizen of Winnipeg, Canada, in real life because Homer Groening was believed to be from the Manitoba capital, although sources say the senior Groening was actually born in Saskatchewan. In 2007, an image of Homer was painted next to the Cerne Abbas giant in Dorset, England as part of a promotion for ''The Simpsons Movie''. This caused outrage among local neopagans who performed "rain magic" to try to get it washed away. In 2008, a fake Spanish euro coin was found in Avilés, Spain, with the face of Homer replacing the figure of King Juan Carlos I. On April 9, 2009, the United States Postal Service unveiled a series of five 44 cent stamps featuring Homer and the four other members of the Simpson family. They are the first characters from a television series to receive this recognition while the show is still in production. The stamps, designed by Matt Groening, were made available for purchase on May 7, 2009.

Homer has appeared, voiced by Castellaneta, in several other television shows, including the sixth season of ''American Idol'' where he opened the show; ''The Tonight Show with Jay Leno'' where he performed a special animated opening monologue for the July 24, 2007 edition; and the 2008 fundraising television special ''Stand Up to Cancer'' where he was shown having a colonoscopy.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c74d12fadf186c19d4f406a127d1b535" name="Homer_Simpson_in_Cerne_Abbans" sectnum="4#1">../img/c74d12fadf186c19d4f406a127d1b535.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>