<document id="8a3d167afbb4e753445afa4e2b4cc7b8-2.11" name="Walter_Model" cat="29">
<text>
Following the end of Market Garden, Hitler decided that the Germans should launch an offensive in the west, which would catch the Western Allies by surprise. The objective he had in mind was to split the Allied front and capture Antwerp. This operation, codenamed ''Wacht am Rhein'' (Watch on the Rhine), would force the British and Americans to sue for peace, leaving Germany free to concentrate on fighting the Soviet Union.

Model, along with all the other commanders involved, believed the idea was unachievable given the scarce resources available in 1944. At the same time, both he and von Rundstedt felt that a purely defensive posture&mdash;as had been adopted since retreating from Normandy&mdash;could only delay Germany's defeat, not prevent it. Thus he prepared Operation Herbstnebel, a less ambitious attack that did not attempt to cross the Meuse, but would still have inflicted a severe setback on the Allies. A similar plan had been developed by von Rundstedt at OB West, and the two field marshals combined their plans to present a joint "small solution" to Hitler. It was rejected, and the "big solution" of aiming for Antwerp went ahead.Parker (1999), pp.95–100.Mitcham (2006), p.38.Newton (2006), pp.329–334.

For this operation, Model had at his disposal Sixth SS Panzer Army, Fifth Panzer Army and Seventh Army, including a dozen panzer and panzergrenadier divisions, representing the last strategic reserve of the Third Reich. Despite his misgivings, Model threw himself into the task with his usual energy, cracking down on any defeatism he might find. A staff officer complained about shortages, causing him to snap: "If you need anything, take it from the Americans".von Mellenthin (1977), p.154.Newton (2006), p.334. He remained acutely aware of both the operation's significance, and its most likely outcome. When Colonel Friedrich August von der Heydte, ordered to lead a parachute drop as part of the operation, said that the jump had no more than a 10 per cent chance of success, he replied: "Well, then it is necessary to make the attempt, since the entire offensive has no more than a 10 per cent chance of success. It must be done, since this offensive is the last remaining chance to conclude the war favourably."Newton (2006), p.336.Mitcham (2006), p.49.

The operation was launched on 16 December 1944 and enjoyed initial success, but it lacked air cover and infantry, and most critically, fuel. Sixth SS Panzer Army ran into stiff resistance, and while Fifth Panzer Army managed to make a deep thrust into Allied lines, Model was unable to exploit the breakthrough. The Germans had failed to capture the vital road junction at Bastogne; combined with the poor weather and impassable terrain, this caused the German columns to bank up into huge traffic jams on the roads behind the front. Starved of fuel and ammunition, the attack had ground to a halt by 25 December, and was called off on 8 January.Mitcham (2006), pp.155–158.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="679f5c368734f9579fca7905c694c2b7" name="Model-5" sectnum="2.11#1">../img/679f5c368734f9579fca7905c694c2b7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>