<document id="8a3d167afbb4e753445afa4e2b4cc7b8-2.9" name="Walter_Model" cat="29">
<text>
On 17 August 1944, Model received from a grateful Hitler the Diamonds to go with his Knight's Cross with Oakleaves and Swords, a reward for patching up the Eastern Front. Simultaneously, he was transferred to the west, replacing von Kluge as commander-in-chief of Army Group B and OB West. The front in Normandy had collapsed after nearly two months of severe fighting, the U.S. Third Army was driving for the Seine, and the army group was in danger of being completely annihilated in the Falaise pocket.

Model's first order was that Falaise be defended, which did not impress his staff.Speidel (1950), pp.130–131.Newton (2006), p.308. However he quickly changed his mind, convincing Hitler to authorize the immediate escape of the German Seventh Army and Panzer Group Eberbach&mdash;something that von Kluge, with his limited political clout, had not been able to do. He was thus able to salvage a remarkable proportion of his units, albeit at the cost of nearly all his armour and heavy materiel. When Hitler demanded that Paris be held, Model replied that he could do so, but only if given an extra 200,000 men and several panzer divisions&mdash;an act that has been described as naivety by some,Speidel (1950), pp.134–135. and canny bargaining by others.Newton (2006), p.309. The reinforcements were not forthcoming, and the city's liberation took place on 25 August. Meanwhile, Model fell back to the German border.

By early September, Model was finding the task of juggling his responsibilities at Army Group B and OB West increasingly difficult, in the face of Allied air superiority and his own predilection for roaming the front lines. Thus he was happy to relinquish OB West in that month to Field Marshal Gerd von Rundstedt. He retained command of Army Group B, a post he would keep until the army group's final dissolution in April 1945.Newton (2006), pp.313–314.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="abbbf88902ebd580c9a489dae4857407" name="AmbushedGermanconvoy" sectnum="2.9#1">../img/abbbf88902ebd580c9a489dae4857407.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>