<document id="8a3d167afbb4e753445afa4e2b4cc7b8-2.12" name="Walter_Model" cat="29">
<text>
The failure of ''Wacht am Rhein'' marked the end of Model's special relationship with Hitler, who on 21 January 1945, issued an order that all the divisions of Army Group B would thenceforth be personally responsible to him. Withdrawing to the Rhine was forbidden, and the army group was directed to conduct its defence without giving up an inch of ground.Newton (2006), pp.348–349.


It was an impossible task, and by mid-March Model had been forced back to the Ruhr. On 1 April, Army Group B was encircled there by the U.S. First and Ninth Armies. Hitler's response was to declare the Ruhr a fortress, from which surrender or escape were denied (much like Stalingrad had been); he further ordered its industries to be destroyed to prevent them falling into Allied hands. Model ignored these orders.Newton (2006), pp.352–353.D'Este (1989), p.329.

On 15 April, after the Allies had split the pocket in two, Major General Matthew Ridgway, commanding the U.S. XVIII Airborne Corps, urged Model to surrender rather than throw the lives of his soldiers away. The reply was that Model, still bound by his oath to Hitler and his sense of honour as a field marshal, considered surrender out of the question. Rather than continue fighting, however, he ordered the army group dissolved. The oldest and youngest soldiers were discharged, and the remainder given the option of surrendering or attempting to break out on their own. In fact, he could do little else: the Fifth Panzer Army had already laid down its arms, and German command and communications in the pocket had all but disintegrated. On 20 April, Joseph Goebbels' Propaganda Ministry denounced Army Group B as traitors, marking the final break between Model and the collapsing Nazi regime.Newton (2006), p.356–357.Mitcham (2006), p.165.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8f51c8a75e93786833ccc55b67f07362" name="Bruecke_von_Remagen_1945_2" sectnum="2.12#1">../img/8f51c8a75e93786833ccc55b67f07362.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>