<document id="8a3d167afbb4e753445afa4e2b4cc7b8-3.14" name="Walter_Model" cat="29">
<text>
What Model possessed was an excellent tactical mind, especially on the defensive, and an "outstanding talent for improvisation".D'Este (1989), p.330. At 3rd Panzer Division he was a pioneer in the use of Kampfgruppen, which would soon become standard practice for the Germans. He had a formidable memory and eye for detail, which allowed him to dominate his staff officers, especially those in charge of specialist areas such as artillery, transport and communications.Parker (1999), p.196. 

Before the war, when he was put in charge of analyzing technical advances at home and abroad, his enthusiasm for innovation earned him the nickname ''Armee Modernissimus'' ("the army modernization fanatic"). To some extent, this was a product of their respective experiences. Model fought nearly all his battles in the northern and central parts of the Eastern Front; he was never tested on the steppes of southern Russia, where the open terrain would have made mobile warfare a more attractive proposition. Nevertheless, his defensive record indicated the value of his approach. At Rzhev, Orel, in Galicia and in Estonia he stymied opponents who expected to overwhelm him, and as late as November 1944, he gave the U.S. 12th Army Group a bloodied nose in the Hürtgen Forest.

His approach was not pretty. Model was a ruthless commander, willing to inflict and take casualties to stabilize his front.Newton (2006), pp.259, 274, 362. The splitting up of units was continually practised by Model and took place on the regimental and divisional level.The objective was always to give necessary reinforcements to the centers of gravity, when no reserves were available. From an operational viewpoint this allowed Model to achieve defensive successes, which would not have been possible otherwise. According to Newton the  sending of theatre or operational reserves into the line where the fighting was toughest, was meant to preserve the units Model saw as organic to his own command.Newton (2006), pp.200–201. For example, he was given the elite ''Grossdeutschland'' Division in September 1942, when his Ninth Army was under heavy attack during Operation Mars. Told that the division was not to be broken up, Model nonetheless split it into battalions and companies, which he used to plug any gaps that appeared. ''Grossdeutschland'' took nearly 10,000 casualties out of a strength of 18,000 men, and at one point was reportedly close to mutiny; but from Model's viewpoint, these losses were acceptable because they meant that Ninth Army's own troops did not have to suffer them.Newton (2006), pp.201–204. That said, he did not simply treat these units as disposable either. In early 1942, the ''Der Führer'' Regiment of the 2nd SS Division ''Das Reich'' was infamously reduced to a handful of men in three weeks of bitter fighting&mdash;but in that time it also received reinforcements including  88 mm guns, artillery pieces, and StuG III assault guns, and Model himself visited the sector daily, calculating the minimum support that would be needed to hold off the Soviet attacks.Newton (2006), pp.189–192.Carell (1966), pp.402–407. 
Model was aware of the negative effects of the splitting up of units. For example, on 7 October 1944 he forbade among others the splitting up of regiments in autonomous battalions to be used outside the division.Model/Bradley,Generalfeldmarshall Walter Model Dokumentation eines Soldatenlebens p 317.

Allied to this were his boundless determination and vigour, and stubborn refusal to countenance defeat. He held himself to the same high standard as he held those around him, saying: "He who leads troops has no right to think about himself". His visits to the front may not have helped operational efficiency, but they energized his men, who consistently held him in much higher regard than did his officers. As commanding general of Ninth Army he was once recorded as personally leading a battalion attack against a Soviet position, pistol in hand.Mitcham (2006), p.15.Carrell (1966), p.398. His peers respected his ability and iron will, even though they may have detested his personality. Guderian thought him the best choice to command Army Group Centre during the crisis of Operation Bagration;D'Este (1989), p.319.  the Ninth Army's War Diary recorded, after he arrived at army group headquarters in Minsk: "The news of Field Marshal Model's arrival is noted with satisfaction and confidence."Adair (1994), p.118.
Model was the master of the type of defense which can be called 'defense limited in time'; in which you defend as long as possible but then retreat to avoid breakthrough and destruction. He was always at the critical points and in his merciless, hard and often risky but brilliant leadership he took away battlegroups or even single battalions from less threatened sectors, with which at other locations holes were plugged or short counterattacks were executed and so opportunities were created for bigger solutions. Hereby a closed front was guaranteed. The mixing and tearing apart of units was the smaller evil in this.Niepold ,Mittlere Ostfront Juni 1944, p.257.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b9276b1c0041d1eb77163c6637890e8c" name="Model-nehring" sectnum="3.14#1">../img/b9276b1c0041d1eb77163c6637890e8c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>