<document id="8a3d167afbb4e753445afa4e2b4cc7b8-2.10" name="Walter_Model" cat="29">
<text>
After the debacle of Normandy, Model established his headquarters at Oosterbeek, near Arnhem in the Netherlands, where he set about the massive task of rebuilding Army Group B. In mid-August 1944, von Kluge committed suicide and Model was  given command of OB West for eighteen days before he was relieved of duty and Gerd von Rundstedt was once again placed in command in the west.
150px
On 17 September, his lunch was rudely interrupted when the British 1st Airborne Division dropped into the town: Operation Market Garden, the Allied attempt to capture the bridges on the lower Rhine, Maas and Waal, was under way. Model initially thought they were trying to capture him and his staff, but the size of the assault quickly disabused him of that notion.Newton (2006), p.317.

When Model perceived what the Allies' real objective was, he ordered the II SS Panzer Corps into action. The corps, containing the 9th SS Panzer and 10th SS Panzer Divisions refitting after Normandy, had been overlooked by Allied intelligence: while still seriously understrength, it was composed of veteran troops and a deadly threat to lightly equipped paratroopers. 9th SS Panzer took on the British at Arnhem, while the 10th moved south to defend the bridge at Nijmegen.

Model believed that the situation represented not just a threat, but also an opportunity to counterattack and possibly clear the Allies out of the southern Netherlands. Towards this end, he forbade SS General Willi Bittrich and SS Lieutenant General Heinz Harmel, commanding II SS Panzer Corps and 10th SS Panzer respectively, from destroying the Nijmegen bridge. With the exception of this tactical error, Model is considered to have fought an outstanding battle and handed the Allies a sharp defeat. The bridge at Arnhem was held and the 1st Airborne Division destroyed, dashing the Allies' hopes for a foothold over the Rhine before the end of the year.Newton (2006), pp.319–321.

Arnhem restored much of Model's self-confidence, which had been shaken by the experience of Normandy.Newton (2006), p.322. From September to December he fought another Allied thrust to a standstill, this time by Omar Bradley's U.S. 12th Army Group into the Hürtgen Forest and Aachen. While he interfered less in the day-to-day movements of his units than at Arnhem, he still kept himself fully informed on the situation, slowing the Allies' progress, inflicting heavy casualties and taking full advantage of the fortifications of the ''Westwall'', known to the Allies as the Siegfried Line.

The Hürtgen Forest cost the U.S. First Army at least 33,000 killed and incapacitated, including both combat and noncombat losses; Germans casualties were between 12,000 and 16,000. Aachen eventually fell on 22 October, again at high cost to the U.S. Ninth Army. The Ninth Army's push to the Roer River fared no better, and did not manage to cross the river or wrest control of its dams from the Germans. Hürtgen was so costly that it has been called an Allied "defeat of the first magnitude", with specific credit being assigned to Model.Whiting (1989), pp.xi–xiv, 271–274.MacDonald (1963), pp.102–103.Newton (2006), pp.323–326.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="25571e4ba2c45a1c1b57e0fcd9658161" name="Westwall01" sectnum="2.10#1">../img/25571e4ba2c45a1c1b57e0fcd9658161.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>