<document id="8a5e28d1b5f28bc5d1a88afbad5a96f5-6.8" name="Princess_Helena_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
Edward VII died in 1910, and the First World War began four years after his death. Helena devoted her time to nursing, and her daughter, Princess Marie Louise, recorded in her memoirs that requests for news of loved ones reached Helena and her sisters. It was decided that the letters should be forwarded to Crown Princess Margaret of Sweden, as Sweden was neutral during the war. It was during the war that Helena and Christian celebrated their golden wedding anniversary in 1916, and despite the fact that Britain and Germany were at war, the Kaiser sent a congratulatory telegram to his aunt and uncle through the Crown Princess of Sweden.Marie Louise, pp. 141–142 George V and Queen Mary were present when the telegram was received, and the King remarked to Helena's daughter, Marie Louise, that her former husband, Prince Aribert of Anhalt, did her a service when he turned her out. When Marie Louise said she would have run away to Britain if she was still married, the King said, “with a twinkle in his eye”, that he would have had to intern her.Marie Louise, p. 142



In 1917, in response to the wave of anti-German feeling that surrounded the war, George V changed the family name from Saxe-Coburg and Gotha to Windsor. He also disposed of his family's German titles and styles, so Christian, Helena and their daughters simply became ''Prince and Princess Christian; Princess Helena Victoria and Marie Louise'' with no territorial designation. Helena's surviving son, Albert, fought on the side of the Prussians, though he made it clear that he would not fight against his mother's country.Marie Louise, p. 43 In the same year, on 8 October, Prince Christian died at Schomberg House. Her last years were spent arguing with Commissioners, who tried to turn her out of Schomberg and Cumberland Lodge because of the expense of running her households. They failed, as clear evidence of her right to live in those residences for life was shown.Chomet, pp. 143–144

Princess Helena, Princess Christian of Schleswig-Holstein, died at Schomberg House on 9 June 1923.Chomet, p. 149 Her funeral, described as a “magnificently stage-managed scene” by her biographer Seweryn Chomet, was headed by King George V. The regiment of her favourite son, Prince Christian Victor, lined the steps of St. George's Chapel at Windsor Castle. Although originally interred in the Royal Vault at St George's, on 15 June 1923 her body was reburied at the Royal Burial Ground at Frogmore, a few miles from Windsor, after its consecration on 23 October 1928.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="25039e93a6bfad26f4baa64335b3c0f1" name="Schleswig-Holstein_plot_at_Royal_Burial_Ground,_Frogmore" sectnum="6.8#1">../img/25039e93a6bfad26f4baa64335b3c0f1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>