<document id="8a5e28d1b5f28bc5d1a88afbad5a96f5-3.3" name="Princess_Helena_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
Helena and Christian were devoted to each other, and led a quiet life in comparison to Helena's sisters.Chomet, p. 55 Following their marriage, they took up residence at Cumberland Lodge in Windsor Great Park, the traditional residence of the Ranger of Windsor Great Park, the honorary position bestowed on Christian by the Queen. When staying in London, they lived at the Belgian Suite in Buckingham Palace.Chomet, p. 133 The couple had six children: Christian Victor in 1867, Albert in 1869, and Princesses Helena Victoria and Marie Louise in 1870 and 1872 respectively. Their last two sons died early; Frederick Harold died eight days after his birth in 1876, and an unnamed son was stillborn in 1877. Princess Louise, Helena's sister, commissioned the French sculptor Jules Dalou to sculpt a memorial to Helena's dead infants.Packard, p. 192

The Christians were granted a parliamentary annuity of £6000 a year, which the Queen requested in person.Chomet, p. 52 In addition, a dower of £30,000 was settled upon, and the Queen gave the couple £100,000 which yielded an income of about £4000 a year.Chomet, p. 54 As well as that of Ranger of Windsor Park, Christian was given the honorary position of High Steward of Windsor, and was made a Royal Commissioner for the Great Exhibition of 1851. However, he was often an absentee figurehead at the meetings, instead passing his time playing with his dog Corrie, feeding his numerous pigeons, and embarking on hunting excursions.Chomet, p. 59

Helena, as promised, lived close to the Queen, and both she and Beatrice performed duties for her. Beatrice, whom Victoria had groomed for the main role at her side, carried out the more important duties, and Helena took on the more minor matters that Beatrice did not have time to do.Packard, p. 194 Helena was assisted by her unmarried daughter, Helena Victoria, to whom the Queen dictated her journal in the last months of her life.Benson, p. 300

Helena's health was not robust, and she was addicted to the drugs opium and laudanum.Packard, pp. 269–270 However, the Queen did not believe that Helena was really ill, accusing her of hypochondria encouraged by an indulgent husband.Packard, p. 193 Queen Victoria wrote to Victoria, Crown Princess of Prussia complaining that Helena was inclined to “coddle herself (and Christian too) and to give way in everything that the great object of her doctors and nurse is to rouse her and make her think less of herself and of her confinement”.Quoted in Chomet, p. 128 Not all of her health scares were brought on by hypochondria; in 1869, she had to cancel her trip to Balmoral Castle when she became ill at the railway station. In 1870, she was suffering from severe rheumatism and problems with her joints. In July 1871, she suffered from congestion in her lungs, an illness severe enough to appear in the Court Circular, which announced that her illness caused “much anxiety to members of the royal family”.Quoted in Chomet, p. 129 In 1873, she was forced to recuperate in France as a result of illness, and in the 1880s she travelled to Germany to see an oculist for her eyes.Chomet, p. 130
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="aac3323ef1c304ac771d31da1c8343c0" name="Prince_Christian_of_Schleswig-Holstein" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/aac3323ef1c304ac771d31da1c8343c0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>