<document id="8a5e28d1b5f28bc5d1a88afbad5a96f5-3.1" name="Princess_Helena_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
Princess Helena began an early flirtation with her father's former librarian, Carl Ruland, following his appointment to the Royal Household on the recommendation of Baron Stockmar in 1859. He was trusted enough to teach German to Helena's brother, the young Prince of Wales, and was described by the Queen as “useful and able”.Chomet, p. 17 When the Queen discovered that Helena had grown romantically attached to a royal servant, he was promptly dismissed back to his native Germany, and he never lost the Queen's hostility.Chomet, p. 19
Princess Helena
Following Ruland's departure in 1863, the Queen looked for a husband for Helena. However, as a middle child, the prospect of a powerful alliance with a European royal house was low.Chomet, p. 37 Her appearance was also a concern, as by the age of fifteen she was described by her biographer as chunky, dowdy and double-chinned.Packard, p. 99 Furthermore, Victoria insisted that Helena's future husband had to be prepared to live near the Queen, thus keeping her daughter nearby.Van der Kiste, p. 61 Her choice eventually fell on Prince Christian of Schleswig-Holstein; however, the match was politically awkward, and caused a severe breach within the royal family. Schleswig and Holstein were two territories fought over between Prussia and Denmark during the First and Second Schleswig Wars. In the latter, Prussia and Austria defeated Denmark, but the duchies were claimed by Austria for the Prince Christian's family. However, following the Austro-Prussian War, in which Prussia invaded and occupied the duchies, they became Prussian, but the title Duke of Schleswig-Holstein was still claimed by Prince Christian's family.Packard, p. 121 The marriage, therefore, horrified King Christian IX of Denmark's daughter, Alexandra, Princess of Wales, who exclaimed: “The Duchies belong to Papa.” Alexandra found support in the Prince of Wales and Princess Alice, who openly accused her mother of sacrificing Helena's happiness for the Queen's convenience.Battiscombe, p. 77 She also argued that it would reduce the already low popularity of her sister, the Crown Princess of Prussia, at the German court in Berlin.Van der Kiste, p. 65 Among the other opposers were Prince Alfred and Prince George, Duke of Cambridge, but the Queen was ardently supported by her eldest daughter Victoria, who had been a personal friend of Christian's family for many years.Packard, p. 113



Despite the political controversies and their age difference—he was fifteen years her senior—Helena was happy with Christian and was determined to marry him.Packard, p. 114 As a younger son of a reigning duke, the absence of any foreign commitments allowed him to remain permanently in Britain—the Queen's primary concern—and she declared the marriage would go ahead.Van der Kiste, p. 64 Helena and Christian were actually 3rd cousins in descent from Frederick, Prince of Wales. Relations between Helena and Alexandra remained strained, and Alexandra was unprepared to accept Christian (who was also a third cousin to Alexandra in descent from Frederik V of Denmark) as either a cousin or brother.Battiscombe, p. 76 The Queen never forgave Alice for accusations of possessiveness, and wrote of the Waleses shortly afterwards: “Bertie is most affectionate and kind but Alix  is by no means what she ought to be. It will be long, if ever, before she regains my confidence.”Van der Kiste, p. 181
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="130ff1f60996a5f9d301160b6eb0c1f4" name="Christian_and_helena" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/130ff1f60996a5f9d301160b6eb0c1f4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>