<document id="8a5e28d1b5f28bc5d1a88afbad5a96f5-1" name="Princess_Helena_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
Helena was born at Buckingham Palace, the official royal residence in London, on 25 May 1846.Chomet, p. 9 She was the third daughter and fifth child of the reigning British monarch, Queen Victoria, and her husband Prince Albert of Saxe-Coburg and Gotha. Albert reported to his brother, Ernest II, the Duke of Saxe-Coburg and Gotha, that Helena “came into this world quite blue, but she is quite well now”.Bennet, p. 89 He added that the Queen “suffered longer and more than the other times and she will have to remain very quiet to recover.”Quoted in Chomet, p. 10 Albert and Victoria chose the names ''Helena Augusta Victoria''. The German name for Helena was ''Helenchen'', later shortened to ''Lenchen'', the name by which members of the royal family invariably referred to Helena. As the daughter of the sovereign, Helena was styled ''Her Royal Highness The Princess Helena'' from birth. Helena was baptised on 25 July 1846 at the private chapel at Buckingham Palace. Her godparents were The Hereditary Grand Duke of Mecklenburg-Strelitz, her first cousin once-removed by marriage; The Duchess of Orléans (Hélène, for whom The Queen's mother The Duchess of Kent stood proxy); and The Duchess of Cambridge.

Helena was a lively and outspoken child, and reacted against brotherly teasing by punching the bully on the nose.
 Her early talents included drawing. Lady Augusta Stanley, a lady-in-waiting to the Queen, commented favourably on the three-year-old Helena's artwork.Chomet, p. 11 Like her other sisters, she could play the piano to a high standard at an early age. Other interests included science and technology, shared by her father Prince Albert, and horseback riding and boating, two of her favourite childhood occupations.Chomet, p. 10 However, Helena became a middle daughter following the birth of Princess Louise in 1848, and her abilities were overshadowed by her more artistic sisters.Chomet, p. 12
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="502a3a36294517496b2c0b2bfc9dffda" name="Princess_Elena_and_Prince_Albert_of_England,_1843" sectnum="1#1">../img/502a3a36294517496b2c0b2bfc9dffda.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>