<document id="8a5e28d1b5f28bc5d1a88afbad5a96f5-4.4" name="Princess_Helena_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
Helena had a firm interest in nursing, and became President of the British Nurses' Association (RBNA) upon its foundation in 1887. In 1891, it received the prefix “Royal”, and received the Royal Charter the following year. She was a strong supporter of nurse registration, an issue that was opposed by both Florence Nightingale and leading public figures.Chomet, p. 119 In a speech Helena made in 1893, she made clear that the RBNA was working towards “improving the education and ''status'' of those devoted and self-sacrificing women whose whole lives have been devoted to tending the sick, the suffering, and the dying”. In the same speech, she warned about opposition and misrepresentation they had encountered. Although the RBNA was in favour of  registration as a means of enhancing and guaranteeing the professional status of trained nurses, its incorporation with the Privy Council allowed it to maintain a list rather than a formal register of nurses.Chomet, p. 120

Following the death of Queen Victoria in 1901, the new Queen, Alexandra, insisted on replacing Helena as President of the Army Nursing Service. This gave rise to a further breach between the royal ladies, with King Edward VII caught in the middle between his sister and his wife.Battiscombe, p. 234 Lady Roberts, a courtier, wrote to a friend: “matters were sometimes ''very'' difficult and not always pleasant.” However, in accordance with rank, Helena agreed to resign in Alexandra's favour, and she retained presidency of the Army Nursing Reserve.Chomet, p. 122 Though thought to be merely an artefact created by society ladies, Helena exercised an efficient and autocratic regime—“if anyone ventures to disagree with Her Royal Highness she has simply said, ‘It is my wish, that is sufficient.’”Quoted in Battiscombe, p. 233

The RBNA gradually went into decline following the Nurses Registration Act 1919; after six failed attempts between 1904 and 1918, the British parliament passed the bill allowing formal nurse registration. What resulted was the Royal College of Nursing (RCN), and the RBNA lost membership and dominance. Helena supported the proposed amalgamation of the RBNA with the new RCN, but that proved unsuccessful when the RBNA pulled out of the negotiations.Chomet, p. 123 However, she remained active in other nursing organisations, and was president of the Isle of Wight, Windsor and Great Western Railway branches of the Order of St. John. In this position, she personally signed and presented many thousands of certificates of proficiency in nursing.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="23a619d0bacd4dd036427c33a9a746f5" name="Florence_Nightingale_1920_reproduction" sectnum="4.4#1">../img/23a619d0bacd4dd036427c33a9a746f5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>