<document id="8b3edb8e7ecf995bb1257eef9b43ffc8-2.4" name="Jackie_Chan" cat="19">
<text>
In 1998, Chan released his final film for Golden Harvest, ''Who Am I?'' After leaving Golden Harvest in 1999, he produced ''Gorgeous'', a romantic comedy that focused on personal relationships. Chan then helped create a PlayStation game in 2000 called ''Jackie Chan Stuntmaster'', to which he lent his voice and performed the motion capture.



Despite further success with ''Shanghai Noon'' in 2000, ''Rush Hour 2'' in 2001 and ''Shanghai Knights'' in 2003, Chan became frustrated with Hollywood over the limited range of roles and lack of control over the film-making process. In response to Golden Harvest's withdrawal from the film industry in 2003, Chan started his own film production company, JCE Movies Limited (Jackie Chan Emperor Movies Limited) in association with Emperor Multimedia Group (EMG). His films have since featured an increasing number of dramatic scenes while continuing to succeed at the box office; examples include ''New Police Story'' (2004), ''The Myth'' (2005) and ''Rob-B-Hood'' (2006).

Chan's next release was ''Rush Hour 3'' in August 2007. It grossed US$255 million. However, it performed poorly in Hong Kong, grossing only HK$3.5 million during its opening weekend. The filming of ''The Forbidden Kingdom'', Chan's first onscreen collaboration with fellow Chinese actor Jet Li, was completed on 24 August 2007 and the film was released in April 2008. Chan voiced the character Master Monkey in the DreamWorks Animation film, ''Kung Fu Panda'', released in June 2008, appearing with stars Jack Black, Dustin Hoffman and Angelina Jolie.
 In addition, he has signed up to assist Anthony Szeto in an advisory capacity for the writer-director's upcoming film ''Wushu'', which is currently in pre-production. The film will star Sammo Hung and Wang Wenjie as father and son.


In November 2007, Chan began filming ''Shinjuku Incident'' with director Derek Yee, which sees Chan take on the role of a Chinese immigrant in Japan. The film was released on 2 April 2009. According to his blog, Chan wishes to direct a film after completing ''Shinjuku Incident'', something he has not done for a number of years. The film is expected to be the third in the Armour of God series, and has a working title of ''Armour of God III: Chinese Zodiac''. Chan originally stated that he would start filming on 1 April 2008, but that date had passed. Because the Screen Actors Guild did not go on strike, Chan started shooting his next movie ''The Spy Next Door'' at the end of October in New Mexico, leaving the status of ''Armour of God III: Chinese Zodiac'' up in the air. In ''The Spy Next Door'', Chan plays an undercover agent whose cover is blown when he looks after the children of his neighbor.

On 22 June 2009, Chan told a Los Angeles Chinatown concert crowd that he is leaving for Beijing to film "The Karate Kid" remake title ''The Kung Fu Kid'' with Jaden Smith. And also appear in an Indian  Bollywood film for the first time called  ''Acid Factory'' where he plays a merciless killer from Sikkim.Brian Warmoth, , ''MTV Movie Blog'', May 6, 2009 (Chan sang the inspirational popular song ''“Yeah Dosti hum nahi torenge”'' at the concert.)
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="62a24e0069a90b567cbadb6c2fbcf768" name="Jackie_Chan_Burglar" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/62a24e0069a90b567cbadb6c2fbcf768.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>