<document id="8b3edb8e7ecf995bb1257eef9b43ffc8-2.3" name="Jackie_Chan" cat="19">
<text>
In 1988 Chan starred alongside Hung and Yuen for the last time to date, in the film ''Dragons Forever''. Hung co-directed with Corey Yuen, and the villain in the film was played by Yuen Wah, both of whom were fellow graduates of the China Drama Academy.

In the late 1980s and early 90s, Chan starred in a number of successful sequels beginning with ''Police Story 2'', which won the award for Best Action Choreography at the 1989 Hong Kong Film Awards. This was followed by ''Armour of God II: Operation Condor'', and ''Police Story 3'', for which Chan won the Best Actor Award at the 1993 Golden Horse Film Festival. In 1994, Chan reprised his role as Wong Fei Hung in ''Drunken Master II'', which was listed in ''Time Magazine's'' All-Time 100 Movies. Another sequel, ''Police Story 4: First Strike'', brought more awards and domestic box office success for Chan, but did not fare as well in foreign markets.
Jackie Chan rekindled his Hollywood ambitions in the 1990s, but refused early offers to play villains in Hollywood films to avoid being typecast in future roles. For example, Sylvester Stallone offered him the role of Simon Phoenix, a criminal in the futuristic film ''Demolition Man''. Chan declined and the role was taken by Wesley Snipes.

Chan finally succeeded in establishing a foothold in the North American market in 1995 with a worldwide release of ''Rumble in the Bronx'', attaining a cult following in the United States that was rare for Hong Kong movie stars.
The success of ''Rumble in the Bronx'' led to a 1996 release of ''Police Story 3'' in the United States under the title ''Supercop'', which grossed a total of US $16,270,600. Jackie then co-starred with Chris Tucker in the 1998 buddy cop action comedy ''Rush Hour'', grossing US$130 million in the United States alone.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0a0cf3523d8b5fda55653226ec3242fa" name="Rumble_In_The_Bronx" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/0a0cf3523d8b5fda55653226ec3242fa.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>