<document id="8b3edb8e7ecf995bb1257eef9b43ffc8-3" name="Jackie_Chan" cat="19">
<text>
Jackie Chan performs most of his own stunts, which are choreographed by the Jackie Chan Stunt Team.  He has stated in interviews that the primary inspiration for his more comedic stunts were films such as ''The General'', starring and directed by Buster Keaton, who was also known to perform his own stunts without doubles. Since the team's establishment in 1983, Chan has used it in all his subsequent films to make choreographing easier, given his understanding of each member's abilities. Chan and his team undertake many of the stunts performed by other characters in his films, shooting the scenes such that their faces are obscured.

The dangerous nature of his stunts makes it difficult for Chan to get insurance, especially in the United States, where his stunt work is contractually limited. Chan holds the Guinness World Record for "Most Stunts By A Living Actor", which emphasizes "no insurance company will underwrite Chan's productions, in which he performs all his own stunts". In addition, he holds an unrecognised record for the most number of takes for a single shot in a film, having shot over 2900 retakes for a complex scene involving a badminton game in ''Dragon Lord''.

Chan has been injured numerous times attempting stunts; many of them have been shown as outtakes or as bloopers during the closing credits of his films. He came closest to death filming ''Armour of God'', when he fell from a tree and fractured his skull. Over the years, Chan has dislocated his pelvis and broken his fingers, toes, nose, both cheekbones, hips, sternum, neck, ankle and ribs on numerous occasions. Promotional materials for ''Rumble in the Bronx'' emphasized that Chan performed all of the stunts, and one version of the movie poster even diagrammed his many injuries.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9fd0b8c7141d689c1a035d52ebb53ea3" name="Jackie_Chan_Stunt" sectnum="3#1">../img/9fd0b8c7141d689c1a035d52ebb53ea3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>