<document id="8b3edb8e7ecf995bb1257eef9b43ffc8-2.2" name="Jackie_Chan" cat="19">
<text>
Willie Chan had become Jackie's personal manager and firm friend, and has remained so for over 30 years. He was instrumental in launching Chan's international career, beginning with his first forays into the American film industry in the 1980s. His first Hollywood film was ''Battle Creek Brawl'' in 1980. Chan then played a minor role in the 1981 film ''The Cannonball Run'', which grossed US$100 million worldwide. Despite being largely ignored by audiences in favour of established American actors like Burt Reynolds, Chan was impressed by the outtakes shown at the closing credits, inspiring him to include the same device in his future films. 

After the commercial failure of ''The Protector'' in 1985, Chan temporarily abandoned his attempts to break into the US market, returning his focus to Hong Kong films.

Back in Hong Kong, Chan's films began to reach a larger audience in East Asia, with early successes in the lucrative Japanese market including ''The Young Master'' (1980) and ''Dragon Lord'' (1982).
Chan produced a number of action comedy films with his opera school friends Sammo Hung and Yuen Biao. The three co-starred together for the first time in 1983 in ''Project A'', which won the Best Action Design Award at the third annual Hong Kong Film Awards. Over the following two years, the "Three Brothers" appeared in ''Wheels on Meals'' and the original ''Lucky Stars'' trilogy. In 1985, Chan made the first ''Police Story'' film, a US-influenced action comedy in which Chan performed his own stunts. It was named the "Best Movie" at the 1986 Hong Kong Film Awards.
In 1987, Chan played "Asian Hawk", an Indiana Jones-esque character, in the film ''Armour of God''. The film was Chan's biggest domestic box office success to date, grossing over HK $35 million.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6c3a09ee42fa2a2a4cab691a4be3829d" name="Jcpmall" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/6c3a09ee42fa2a2a4cab691a4be3829d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>