<document id="8b7fbfcbcb9b6c016e824efa998b4233-4.4" name="Mary_Martha_Sherwood" cat="17">
<text>
While in India, Sherwood wrote a series of texts based on colonial life. Her most popular work, ''The History of Little Henry and his Bearer'' (1814), tells the story of a young British boy who, on his deathbed, converts Boosy, the Indian man who has taken care of him throughout his childhood. The book was enormously successful; it reached 37 editions by 1850 and was translated into French, German, Spanish, Hindustani, Chinese, and Sinhalese. Sherwood's tale blends the realistic with the sentimental and introduces her readers to Hindustani words and descriptions of what she felt was authentic Indian life.Cutt, 17-18. As Cutt explains, "with this work, the obituary tract (which invariably stressed conversion and a Christian death) had assumed the colouring of romance."  Sherwood also wrote a companion story titled  ''Little Lucy and her Dhaye'' (1825) that told a similar tale but from a little girl's perspective.


In ''The Indian Pilgrim'' (1818) Sherwood tried to adapt ''Pilgrim's Progress'' for the Indian context; the work focused on "the supposed depravity and pagan idolatry of Brahmans, fakirs, nautch (dance) girls, and soldiers' temporary wives." This text demonstrates Sherwood's religious biases: "Muslims and Jews receive better treatment than Hindus because of their belief in one God, but Roman Catholics fare little better than the Hindu idolaters."Dawson, 274–275. ''The Indian Pilgrim'', although never published in India, was popular in Britain and America. Sherwood also wrote texts for Indian servants of British families in the style of British writings for the poor. One of these was ''The Ayah and Lady'' (1813) in which the ayah, or maid, is "portrayed as sly, selfish, lazy, and untrustworthy. Her employers are well aware of her faults, yet they tolerate her." A more culturally sensitive and realistic portrayal of Indians appears in ''The Last Days of Boosy'' (1842), a sequel to ''The History of Little Henry and his Bearer'', in which the converted Boosy is cast out of his family and community because of his conversion to Christianity. 

Colonial themes were a constant thread in Sherwood's texts; ''The History of Henry Milner'' (1822–37), its sequel ''John Marten'' (1844), and ''The Indian Orphans'' (1839) all evince Sherwood's interest in these topics. Her writings on India reveal her strong sense of European, if not specifically British, superiority; India therefore appears in her works as a morally corrupt land in need of reformation.Cutt, 20; Dawson, 273; Demers, "Mrs. Sherwood and Hesba Stretton," 134. She wrote ''The History of George Desmond'' (1821) to warn young men of the dangers of emigrating to India.  Sherwood's books shaped the minds of several generations of young Britons. According to Cutt, Sherwood's depictions of India were among the few available to young British readers; such children "acquired a strong conviction of the rightness of missions, which, while it inculcated sincere concern for, and a genuine kindness towards an alien people for whom Britain was responsible, quite destroyed any latent respect for Indian tradition."Cutt, 21. Cutt attributes the growing paternalism of nineteenth-century British polices on India in part to the widespread popularity of Sherwood's books.

Using a postcolonial analysis, Nandini Bhattacharya emphasizes the complex relationship between Sherwood's evangelicalism and her colonialism. She argues that Sherwood's evangelical stories demonstrate the deep colonial "mistrust of feminized agency," represented by a dying child in ''Little Henry and his Bearer''. Henry "subvert the colonialist's fantasy of universal identity by generating a subaltern identity that mimics and explodes that fantasy."  But, ultimately, Bhattacharya argues, Sherwood creates neither a completely colonialist text nor a subaltern text; the deaths of children such as Henry eliminate any possibility for an alternative consciousnesses to mature.Bhattacharya, 383.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0d6f0c194846f68676a6c12eb3619b39" name="SherwoodHenryIllustration" sectnum="4.4#1">../img/0d6f0c194846f68676a6c12eb3619b39.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>