<document id="8bd84a5663be440d632d3ba1ff917cf1-2.7" name="History_of_American_football" cat="26">
<text>
As a result of the 1905–1906 reforms, mass formation plays became illegal and forward passes legal. Bradbury Robinson, playing for visionary coach Eddie Cochems at St. Louis University, threw the first legal pass in a September 5, 1906 game against Carroll College at Waukesha. Other important changes, formally adopted in 1910, were the requirements that at least seven offensive players be on the line of scrimmage at the time of the snap, that there be no pushing or pulling, and that interlocking interference (arms linked or hands on belts and uniforms) was not allowed.  These changes greatly reduced the potential for collision injuries.John S. Watterson, , ''American Heritage'' magazine, June 1988 Several coaches emerged who took advantage of these sweeping changes. Amos Alonzo Stagg introduced such innovations as the huddle, the tackling dummy, and the pre-snap shift. Vancil (2000), pp 17   Other coaches, such as Pop Warner and Knute Rockne, introduced new strategies that still remain part of the game.

Besides these coaching innovations, several rules changes during the first third of the twentieth century had a profound impact on the game, mostly in opening up the passing game. In 1914, the first roughing-the-passer penalty was implemented. In 1918, the rules on eligible receivers were loosened to allow eligible players to catch the ball anywhere on the field—previously strict rules were in place only allowing passes to certain areas of the field. Vancil (2000) pp 22  Scoring rules also changed during this time: field goals were lowered to three points in 1909 and touchdowns raised to six points in 1912. 

Star players that emerged in the early twentieth century include Jim Thorpe, Red Grange, and Bronko Nagurski; these three made the transition to the fledgling NFL and helped turn it into a successful league. Sportswriter Grantland Rice helped popularize the sport with his poetic descriptions of games and colorful nicknames for the game's biggest players, including Grange, whom he dubbed "The Galloping Ghost," Notre Dame's "Four Horsemen" backfield, and Fordham University's linemen, known as the "Seven Blocks of Granite".Vancil (2000) pp 24
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d97a1c2b2d7ea80f217c32f8f8db6115" name="RobinsonThrowing" sectnum="2.7#1">../img/d97a1c2b2d7ea80f217c32f8f8db6115.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>