<document id="8be4d536659a057935da0a90e28e7dfc-1" name="Northern_Bald_Ibis" cat="3">
<text>
The ibises are gregarious, long-legged wading birds with long down-curved bills; along with the spoonbills they form one subfamily within the Threskiornithidae. del Hoyo ''et al.'' (1992) p.472 "Threskiornithidae (Ibises and Spoonbills)" The Northern Bald Ibis's closest relative, and the only other member of the genus, is the Southern Bald Ibis, ''G. calvus'', of southern Africa. The two ''Geronticus'' species differ from other ibises in that they have unfeathered faces and heads, breed on cliffs rather than in trees, and prefer arid habitats to the wetlands used by their relatives.

The Northern Bald Ibis was described and illustrated by Swiss naturalist Conrad Gessner in his ''Historiae animalium'' in 1555, Gessner (1551) pp.337&ndash;8 "Corvo sylvatico"  and given the binomial name ''Upupa eremita'' by Carolus Linnaeus in his 1758 ''Systema naturae''. Linnaeus (1758) p.118 ''U. viridis, capite flavo, cervice jubata. Corvus sylvaticus'' It was moved to its current genus by the German herpetologist Johann Georg Wagler in 1832. Wagler (1832) volume 25 column 1232

The species probably split into two distinct populations at least 400 years ago and, since then, the two populations have been diverging morphologically, ecologically, and genetically; nevertheless, the Turkish and Moroccan populations of this ibis are not currently classed as separate subspecies. One consistent difference between the eastern and western birds is a single mutation in the cytochrome b gene of their mitochondrial DNA. 

Fossils of the Northern Bald Ibis have been found at a Holocene (c. 10,000 years ago) site in southern France, in middle Pleistocene (c. 900,000 ago) strata in Sicily, and in Pliocene-Pleistocene boundary (c. 1.8 million years ago) deposits on the Mediterranean coast of Spain. What appears to be an ancestral form, ''Geronticus balcanicus'', was found in the late Pliocene of Bulgaria, further illustrating the early widespread presence of this genus in Europe, and suggesting that ''Geronticus eremita'' may have originated in southeastern Europe or the Middle East.   

The genus name, ''Geronticus'', is derived from the Ancient Greek , meaning ''old man'' and refers to the bald head of the aged. Brook (2006) p. 507 ''Eremita'' is Late Latin for ''hermit'', from the Greek , meaning ''desert'', Brook (2006) p. 621 and refers to the arid habitats inhabited by this species. The alternative common name ''Waldrapp'' is German for ''forest crow'', Brook (2006) p. 1713 the equivalent of the Latin ''Corvo sylvatico'' of Gesner, adapted as ''Corvus sylvaticus'' by Linnaeus.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="39907eba37c7fdba9d8a94dd8792f52f" name="Nbibis0371crop" sectnum="1#1">../img/39907eba37c7fdba9d8a94dd8792f52f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>