<document id="8be4d536659a057935da0a90e28e7dfc-4.1" name="Northern_Bald_Ibis" cat="3">
<text>
The Northern Bald Ibis breeds in loosely spaced colonies, nesting on cliff ledges or amongst boulders on steep slopes, usually on the coast or near a river. Volunteer climbers have created extra ledge spaces in the Souss-Massa colonies to ensure that breeding population is not limited by the availability of nest ledges, and artificial nest boxes are used in the managed colony at Birecik. Topak, Muzaffer (Coordinator)  (PDF) Republic of Turkey Ministry of Forestry General Directorate of National Parks and Game In the past, the birds also nested in buildings.

This ibis starts breeding at 3&ndash;5 years of age, and pairs for life. The male chooses a nest site, cleans it, and then advertises for a female by waving his crest and giving low rumbling calls. Once the birds have paired, the bond is reinforced through bowing displays and mutual preening. The nest is a loose construction of twigs lined with grass or straw. ''G. eremita'' normally lays 2&ndash;4 rough-surfaced eggs, which weigh an average of 50.16 g (1.8 oz), retrieved 28 December 2008. Also available to subscribers at .  and are initially blue-white with brown spots, becoming brown during incubation. An egg in the collection of the British Museum was marked more thickly at the broad end, with "spots and very small blotches of yellowish brown and pale rufous". It was 0.93 cm long and 0.68 cm wide (2.37 × 1.73 in).Oates (1902) p.100 The clutch is incubated for 24&ndash;25 days to hatching, the chicks fledge in another 40&ndash;50 days, and the first flight takes place at about two months. (Arabic and English) Hulme, Diana; Tabbaa, Darem; Bright, Alastair '''' (PDF) Syrian Arab Republic Ministry of Education and Al Baath University Faculty of Veterinary Medicine Animal Protection Project. (English version half way through document) Both parents incubate and feed the chicks.

The Northern Bald Ibis lives in captivity for an average of 20&ndash;25 years (oldest recorded male 37 years, oldest recorded female 30 years).Böhm (1999) pp.52&ndash;64  "Northern Bald Ibis ''Geronticus eremita''" The average age in the wild has been estimated as 10&ndash;15 years.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a01d61637b96da8b925b89a57c63d09c" name="Geronticus_eremita_Waldrapp" sectnum="4.1#1">../img/a01d61637b96da8b925b89a57c63d09c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>