<document id="8be4d536659a057935da0a90e28e7dfc-5.3" name="Northern_Bald_Ibis" cat="3">
<text>
For the first time in the species' recorded history, there is now evidence of population growth in the wild, and the population in Morocco increased to 100 breeding pairs in the decade prior to 2008. Simple site and species protection has facilitated this growth. Quantitative assessments of the importance of sites for breeding, roosting and foraging have guided actions to prevent disturbance and the loss of key areas to mass tourism development. Wardening by members of the local community has reduced human intrusion and increased the perceived value of the birds. The provision of drinking water and the removal and deterrence of predators and competitors enhances breeding prospects, and monitoring has confirmed that steppe and two-year fallows are key feeding habitats.

Maintaining such non-intensive land uses in future may present major management challenges, and the recovery in the Souss-Massa region remains precarious because the population is concentrated in just a few places. However, it could provide opportunities for natural extension of the range to formerly occupied sites further north in Morocco. 


The main cause of breeding failure at the Souss-Massa National Park is the loss of eggs to predators, especially the Common Raven which nest monitoring has shown to have had a serious impact at one sub-colony. The effects of predators on adult birds have not been studied, but the very similar Southern Bald Ibis, ''Geronticus calvus'', is hunted by large raptors, particularly those that share its breeding cliffs. Harrison (1997) p.104 "" There is evidence of chick starvation in some years, but the main threats to breeding birds are human disturbance and the loss of feeding habitat. There was a dramatic mortality incident at the Moroccan colonies in May 1996, when 40 adults died or disappeared over a period of nine days. Although analyses have not identified the cause, an obscure virus, a toxin, or botulism are thought to be the most likely causes of the deaths.

The Syrian Ministry of Agriculture and Agrarian Reform has now put protection measures in place to protect the tiny breeding population in that country, and Yemen and Ethiopia, which provide migration stop-offs and wintering areas, have a good record for conservation. However, young birds do not winter nor return with the adults and their wintering grounds are still unknown. Although the wild Syrian population is very small, the discovery that semi-wild Turkish birds on a migration trial visited the Palmyra colony has led to hopes that some migrants may join the Syrian breeding population and boost the numbers in that country.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b5aac07af19afa00090c2a16ef953200" name="Waldrapp_Ibis_is_feeding_a_chick" sectnum="5.3#1">../img/b5aac07af19afa00090c2a16ef953200.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>