<document id="8be4d536659a057935da0a90e28e7dfc-5.5.2" name="Northern_Bald_Ibis" cat="3">
<text>
The Northern Bald Ibis became one of the world's earliest officially protected species in 1504, thanks to a decree by Archbishop Leonhard of Salzburg, but died out in Austria as elsewhere in Europe. There are now two ibis reintroduction projects in the country; a research station at Grünau has a breeding colony managed, like the Turkish population, as a free-flying flock which is caged at migration time. The aim here is to investigate flock interactions and hormonal status, behavioural and ecological aspects of natural foraging, and the establishment of traditions via social learning.   Retrieved 26 November 2008 

The Scharnstein Project is an attempt to establish a migratory Waldrapp colony by using ultralight planes to teach a migration route. The scheme builds on the Grünau rearch by developing a method to control and guide the autumn migration of a founder population, which then can pass this migration tradition to subsequent generations. In May 2002, 11 birds from the Vienna Zoo and the Grünau colony were trained to follow two microlight planes, and in 2003, a first attempt was made to lead a group of birds from Scharnstein to southern Tuscany. Due to adverse weather and technical problems, the birds had to be transported by road over a considerable part of the distance. The subsequent releases were more successful, with birds wintering in Tuscany, and, from 2005, returning to northern Austria. In 2008, a female ibis named Aurelia flew 930 km (580 mi) back to Austria for her fourth return to the breeding site. The hazards of the journey are shown by the loss of her two offspring and her mate while on the southern journey in the autumn of 2007.  Retrieved 26 November 2008

''Proyecto Eremita'' is a Spanish reintroduction involving the release of nearly 30 birds in the Ministry of Defence training ground in La Janda district, Barbate (Cádiz Province). It had its first success in 2008, when a pair laid two eggs. This is the probably the first attempt to breed in the wild in Spain for 500 years; the last definite reference to the Northern Bald Ibis breeding in Spain is from a 15th-century falconry book.  Retrieved 24 November 2008 This effort has been undertaken by the Andalusian government’s Environmental Ministry, the Spanish Ministry of Defence, and the Jerez Zoo and Botanical Gardens, with the assistance of the Doñana National Park and volunteers from the Cádiz Natural History Society.  Retrieved 24 November 2008  Retrieved 24 November 2008 Previously, two birds left the area in 2005 and 14 in 2006, but nothing is known of their whereabouts other than that a ringed bird from Spain was seen in the Middle Atlas, Morocco in 2005.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c98c6a902635fb79481950e3c4c4f93e" name="Graz_Schlossberg_Waldrapp_Infotafel" sectnum="5.5.2#1">../img/c98c6a902635fb79481950e3c4c4f93e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>