<document id="8c98ce7dbdf61f9adad46a6d0dbd17fe-5" name="Selena" cat="20">
<text>
Jennifer Lopez played Selena in a film about her life. Directed by Gregory Nava, the biopic opened with mostly positive reviews.. ''Rotten Tomatoes'', Retrieved on July 20, 2006. Over 20,000 people auditioned for the leading role in the movie.. ''Houston Chronicle'', April 28, 1996. Retrieved on June 5, 2006. The film stirred some controversy in the Mexican-American community, since Lopez is Puerto Rican-American and played the role of a singer of Mexican descent. But Selena's fans supported the movie, and Lopez's acting in the film helped elevate her career.. Thompson Gale (Gale.com). Retrieved on July 20, 2006. Although Lopez succeeded as a pop star a few years later, Selena's voice was dubbed in for all the songs in the movie.. ''Roger Ebert'', Retrieved on July 20, 2006. For her role, Lopez was nominated for a Golden Globe award for Best Actress in a Musical.. IMDb.com. Retrieved on May 17, 2006.

Reliant Stadium in Houston hosted a tribute concert, ''Selena ¡VIVE!'', on April 7, 2005. Held a week after the 10th anniversary of her death, over 65,000 fans attended the concert, which featured high-profile artists including Gloria Estefan, Pepe Aguilar, Thalía, Paulina Rubio, Ana Barbara, Alejandra Guzmán, Ana Gabriel, and Fey. The artists performed renditions of Selena's music, as did her brother, A.B. Quintanilla, who performed with his band Kumbia Kings backed with footage of Selena singing "Baila Esta Cumbia". Broadcast live on the Univision network, ''Selena ¡VIVE!'' is the highest-rated and most-viewed Spanish-language show in American television history. The show, which lasted over three hours, scored a 35.9 Nielsen household rating.. Univision, November 4, 2005. Retrieved on June 6, 2006.

The American Bank Center in Corpus Christi named their 2,526-seat concert auditorium, Selena Auditorium, in her memory.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="84fb8e56c1e675a8ca30ea557f13eca9" name="Mirador200109" sectnum="5#1">../img/84fb8e56c1e675a8ca30ea557f13eca9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>