<document id="8cdf0b127987ca891e9e8931c4519622-1" name="Latter_Days" cat="19">
<text>
Elder Aaron Davis (Steve Sandvoss), a young Mormon missionary from Pocatello, Idaho, is sent to Los Angeles with three other missionaries to spread the Mormon faith. They move into a bungalow apartment next to the apartment of openly gay party boy Christian Markelli (Wes Ramsey), an aspiring actor, and his roommate Julie, an aspiring singer. Christian works as a waiter at ''Lila's'', a trendy restaurant owned by retired actress Lila Montagne (Jacqueline Bisset).

Intrigued by his new, sober Mormon neighbors, Christian makes a $50 bet with his cynical co-workers that he can seduce one of them. Christian soon realizes that Aaron, the most inexperienced missionary, is a closeted homosexual.

Aaron and Christian become acquainted after several encounters in the apartment complex. When Christian accidentally cuts himself on a piece of metal and faints, Aaron helps him indoors and cleans his wound. Christian seizes the opportunity to seduce Aaron and nearly succeeds. However, the hesitant Mormon becomes upset by Christian's standard patter that sex "doesn't have to mean anything." Aaron angrily replies that Christian "equates sex with a handshake", and after accusing him of being superficial and shallow, walks out. Worried that Aaron is right, Christian joins Project Angel Food to deliver meals to people with AIDS.

Later, Aaron's fellow missionary, Paul Ryder (Joseph Gordon-Levitt), has a cycling accident. On returning to his apartment, a distraught Aaron encounters Christian, who tries to comfort him with a hug. Both men are overwhelmed by their feelings and end up kissing. Lost in the moment, they fail to notice the return of Aaron's roommates. Christian is ordered to leave. He returns to the missionaries' apartment the next day to explain himself, but is told that Aaron has been sent home in disgrace. This leads to a confrontation with Elder Ryder, who is angry that Christian has corrupted a decent young man for no apparent purpose. Christian admits that he initially just wanted to win a bet, but says "it's not about that" anymore.

Recognizing Christian's genuine distress, Ryder softens enough to tell him that Aaron has a five-hour layover in Salt Lake City. Christian catches the next flight there and eventually finds Aaron standing in the snow outside the terminal. Christian confesses his love, and despite his profound misgivings, Aaron admits his own feelings of love. With all flights cancelled due to a snowstorm, Christian and Aaron are able to spend a loving and intimate night together in a nearby motel. However, when Christian awakes in the morning, he finds Aaron gone, his pocketwatch, which had been handed down in his family for generations left behind accidentally (or possibly as a gift). Christian returns sadly to Los Angeles.

Aaron's kissing another man violated the rules of the Mormon Church regarding homosexuality. On arriving home in Idaho, Aaron is excommunicated by the church elders, led by his own father, Farron (Jim Ortlieb), who is the Stake President (regional leader). Aaron is rejected by his father and scolded by his mother (Mary Kay Place) when he said that Christian told him he loved him. She informs him of the $50 bet she is told about by the Mission President. She states that he needs to pray for forgiveness, though Aaron disagrees and says that what if it isn't something he did, but who he is. For that statement, Aaron's mother slaps him, causing him (and her) to cry. Before Aaron left Idaho for Los Angeles, his mother, Gladys, gave him a family picture, tearfully stating how much she loved him and that he will always be her baby. This relationship was extremely important to Aaron, and he now feels like it's gone forever. Overwhelmed by despair, he tries to commit suicide. He is saved just in time by his older sister Susan, who, while trying to convince Aaron that their relationship will never change, sees blood coming from the bottom of the closed bathroom door, and becomes hysterical (in a deleted scene). Aaron is subsequently sent by his parents to a treatment facility to undergo aversion therapy to "cure" him of his homosexuality.

Christian is desperate to find Aaron and eventually locates his home address and phone number. On phoning, he is devastated to be told by Aaron's mother that "Thanks to you, my son took a razor to his wrists; thanks to you I have ''lost'' my son." Although the statement was likely figurative, Christian is under the impression it is literal (as Gladys might have hoped, given her anger over the situation). Believing that Aaron is dead, Christian spends the next few days thinking non-stop about Aaron, as he constantly holds his pocket watch. One morning at 3AM, his roommate Julie comes home from work in the studio and finds Christian awake, sitting on the couch. When Christian brushes off her concerns and heads back to bed, Julie discovers a poem in his cellphone (which he also uses as a journal). She decides to use it as the base of her new song.

Aaron is from Pocatello, Idaho.
Christian seeks out the family home in Idaho, where he tearfully returns Aaron's family heirloom watch to his mother. She recognizes that she may have been too harsh in her judgment, but is too late to stop Christian before he drives off (She hurries out the door, yelling "Wait!" but he had already driven too far to hear her). During an encounter with Julie, she hesitatingly shows him her new video, which stuns Christian, realizing that part of the lyrics had come from his journal. Julie tries to convince Christian that she had only hoped that something good would come out of it. However, Christian feels betrayed because Julie read and used his (most painful) personal journal entry without his consent.

Late one night in the treatment facility, Aaron hears a female voice singing and goes to investigate. He discovers a music video playing on television, the song performed by Julie. Coincidentally, it is the same video that Julie had shown Christian. As it plays, Aaron sees an on-screen message stating that the song describes a roommate of the performer, not a boyfriend. The video prompts Aaron to return to Los Angeles in search of Christian. Upon arriving at Christian's apartment, Aaron is heartbroken to find a shirtless stranger answering the door. Thinking that this is just another one-night stand answering the door, that Christian has returned to his party boy ways and has moved on, and having nowhere else to go, Aaron makes his way to Lila's restaurant. By chance, he had befriended Lila while on missionary work after her life partner died, though he did not realize that she owned the restaurant where Christian worked. Christian is shocked but overjoyed at seeing Aaron alive, and their reconciliation ends the film on a happy note. Together with Christian's co-workers, they celebrate Thanksgiving and look forward to a happy future together. Lila makes an extremely selfless toast, telling everyone present, including Julie, who is currently passing through Los Angeles on a tour, that no matter what, they will always have "a place at my table, and a place in my heart".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6093326c028f6f3d1d5f32b717adcce2" name="Latterdays_001" sectnum="1#1">../img/6093326c028f6f3d1d5f32b717adcce2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>