<document id="8cf4a40460024864e77c72d54cd7c2dd-4" name="Red_Barn_Murder" cat="14">
<text>
On 11 August, 1828 Corder was taken to the gallows in Bury St. Edmunds, apparently too weak to stand without support.Gatrell p.13
He was hanged shortly before noon in front of a huge crowd; one newspaper claimed there were 7,000 spectators, another as many as 20,000.Gatrell p.32 At the prompting of the prison governor, just before the hood was drawn over his head he weakly asserted:Cairns p.18

After an hour his body was cut down by Foxton, the hangman, who according to his rights claimed Corder's trousers and stockings. The body was taken back to the courtroom at Shire Hall where it was slit open along the abdomen to expose the muscles. The crowds were allowed to file past until six o'clock when the doors were shut. According to the ''Norwich and Bury Post'', over 5,000 people queued to see the body.Curtis p.210 

The following day the dissection and autopsy were carried out in front of an audience of students from Cambridge and physicians. A battery was attached to Corder's limbs to demonstrate the contraction of the muscles, the sternum was opened and the internal organs examined. There was some discussion as to whether the cause of death was suffocation, but since it was reported that Corder's chest was seen to rise and fall for several minutes after he had dropped, it was thought probable that pressure on the spinal cord had killed him. Since the skeleton was to be reassembled after the dissection, it was not possible to examine the brain, so instead the surgeons contented themselves with a phrenological examination of the skull. Corder's skull was asserted to be profoundly developed in the areas of "secretiveness, acquisitiveness, destructiveness, philoprogenitiveness, and imitativeness" with little evidence of "benevolence or veneration". The bust of Corder held by Moyse's Hall Museum in Bury St. Edmunds is an original made by Child of Bungay, Suffolk, as a tool for the study of Corder's phrenology. The skeleton was reassembled, exhibited and used as a teaching aid in the West Suffolk Hospital.Gatrell pp.256–7 Several copies of his death mask were made, a replica of one is held at Moyse's Hall Museum. Artifacts from the trial and some which were in Corder's possession are also held at the museum. Corder's skin was tanned by the surgeon George Creed, and used to bind an account of the murder. 

Corder's skeleton was put on display in the Hunterian Museum in the Royal College of Surgeons of England, where it hung beside that of Jonathan Wild.  In 2004, Corder's bones were removed from display and cremated.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="06a1060d02c315203464660cb05183f0" name="WilliamCorder-hanging" sectnum="4#1">../img/06a1060d02c315203464660cb05183f0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>