<document id="8cf4a40460024864e77c72d54cd7c2dd-3" name="Red_Barn_Murder" cat="14">
<text>
Corder was taken back to Suffolk where he was tried at Shire Hall, Bury St. Edmunds. The trial started on 7 August 1828, having been put back several days because of the interest the case had generated. The hotels in Bury St. Edmunds began to fill up from as early as 21 July and, because of the large numbers that wanted to view the trial, admittance to the court was by ticket only. Despite this the judge and court officials still had to push their way bodily through the crowds that had gathered around the door to gain entry to the court room.

The judge, Chief Baron Alexander, was unhappy with the coverage given to the case by the press "to the manifest detriment of the prisoner at the bar".''The Times'' 9 August 1828 p.3 quoted in Wiener p.138
''The Times'', nevertheless, congratulated the public for showing good sense in aligning themselves against Corder.''The Times'' 12 August 1828 p.3 quoted in Wiener p.138

Corder entered a plea of not guilty. The exact cause of death could not be established. It was thought that a sharp instrument, possibly Corder's short sword, had been plunged into Marten's eye socket, but this wound could also have been caused by her father's spade when he was exhuming the body. Strangulation could not be ruled out as Corder's handkerchief had been discovered around her neck, and, to add to the confusion, the wounds to her body suggested she had been shot. The indictment charged Corder with "…murdering Maria Marten, by feloniously and wilfully shooting her with a pistol through the body, and likewise stabbing her with a dagger." To avoid any chance of a mistrial, he was indicted on nine charges, including one of forgery. 

Ann Marten was called to give evidence of the events of the day of Maria's disappearance and her later dreams. Thomas Marten then told the court how he had dug up his daughter, and George Marten, Maria's 10-year-old brother, revealed that he had seen Corder with a loaded pistol before the alleged murder and later had seen him walking from the barn with a pickaxe. Lea gave evidence concerning Corder's arrest and the objects found during the search of his house. The prosecution suggested that Corder had never wanted to marry Maria, but that her knowledge of some of his criminal dealings had given her a hold over him, and that his theft previously of the money sent by her child's father had been a source of tension between them.Cairns p.40

Corder then gave his own version of the events. He admitted to being in the barn with Maria but said he had left after they argued. He claimed that while he was walking away he heard a pistol shot and running back to the barn found Maria dead with one of his pistols beside her. He pleaded with the jury to give him the benefit of the doubt, but after they retired it took them only 35 minutes to return with a guilty verdict. Baron Alexander sentenced him to hang and afterwards be dissected:


Corder spent the next three days in prison agonising over whether to confess to the crime and make a clean breast of his sins before God. After several meetings with the prison chaplain, entreaties from his wife, and pleas from both his warder and John Orridge, the governor of the prison, he finally confessed.Langbein p.270 He strongly denied stabbing Maria, claiming instead he had accidentally shot her in the eye after they argued while she was changing out of her disguise.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a7855019cb246f52958b280db9159bf4" name="WilliamCorder-awaitingtrial" sectnum="3#1">../img/a7855019cb246f52958b280db9159bf4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>