<document id="8cf4a40460024864e77c72d54cd7c2dd-6" name="Red_Barn_Murder" cat="14">
<text>
The case had all the elements to ignite a fervent popular interest: the wicked squire and the poor girl, the iconic murder scene, the supernatural element of the stepmother's prophetic dreams, the detective work by Ayres and Lea (who later became the detective Pharos Lee in stage versions of the events) and Corder's new life which was the result of a lonely hearts advertisement. As a consequence, the case created its own small industry.


Plays were being performed while Corder was still awaiting trial and, after the execution, an anonymous author published a melodramatic version of the murder—a precursor of the Newgate novels—which quickly became a best-seller. Along with the story of Jack Sheppard and other highwaymen, thieves and murderers, the Red Barn Murder was a popular subject for penny gaffs, cheap plays performed for the entertainment of the lower classes in the gin-soaked atmosphere of the back rooms of public houses.Picard p.198 After the execution, James Catnach managed to sell over a million broadsides (sensationalist single sheet newspapers).Gatrell p.159 Catnach's sheets gave details of Corder's confession and the execution, and included a sentimental ballad supposedly penned by Corder himself, but more likely to have been the work of Catnach or somebody in his employ.Neuberg p.138Hindley p.79 It was one of at least five ballads about the crime that appeared directly following the execution.

Owing to the excitement around the trial and the public demand for entertainments based on the murder, many different versions of the events were set down and distributed, making it hard for modern readers to discern fact from melodramatic embellishment. Good records of the trial exist from the official records, and the best record of the events surrounding the case is generally considered to be that of James Curtis, a journalist who spent time with Corder and two weeks in Polstead interviewing those concerned. Curtis was apparently so connected with the case that when asked to produce a picture of the accused man, an artist for one of the newspapers drew him rather than Corder.Caulfield p.55

Pieces of the rope which was used to hang Corder sold for a guinea each. Part of Corder's scalp with an ear still attached was displayed in a shop in Oxford Street.Gatrell p.258 A lock of Maria's hair sold for two guineas. Polstead became a tourist venue with visitors travelling from as far afield as Ireland;Mackay p.700 Curtis estimated that 200,000 people visited Polstead in 1828 alone. The Red Barn and the Martens' cottage excited particular interest. The barn was stripped for souvenirs, down to the planks being removed from the sides, broken up and sold as toothpicks.Gatrell p.43 It was planned to be demolished after the trial, but it was left standing and eventually burnt down in 1842. Even Maria's gravestone was eventually chipped away to nothing by souvenir hunters. Pottery models and sketches were sold and songs composed, including one mentioned in the Vaughan Williams opera ''Hugh the Drover''.

Corder's skeleton was put on display in a glass case in the West Suffolk Hospital, and apparently rigged with a mechanism that made its arm point to the collection box when approached. Eventually, the skull was replaced by a Dr. Kilner who wanted to add Corder's skull to his extensive collection of Red Barn memorabilia. After a series of unfortunate events, Kilner became convinced the skull was cursed and handed it on to his friend Hopkins. Further disasters plagued both men and they finally paid for the skull to be given a Christian burial in an attempt to lift the supposed curse.Storey p.118

Interest in the case did not quickly fade. ''Maria Marten; or The Murder in the Red Barn'', which existed in various anonymous versions, was a sensational hit throughout the mid-1800s and may have been the most performed play of the 19th century; Victorian fairground peepshows were forced to add extra apertures to their viewers when exhibiting their shows of the murder to cope with the demand. The plays of the Victorian era tended to portray Corder as a cold-blooded monster and Maria as the innocent he preyed upon; her reputation and her children by other fathers were airbrushed out,Wiener pp. 138–9 and Corder was made into an older man.Richards p.136 Charles Dickens published an account of the murder in his magazine ''All The Year Round'' after initially rejecting it because he felt the story to be too well known and the account of the stepmother's dreams rather far-fetched.Letters of Charles Dickens p.371 

Although diminished, the fascination continued into the 20th century with five film versions, including the 1935 ''Maria Marten or Murder in the Red Barn'', starring Tod Slaughter, which was only released in the US after some scenes were cut. A fictionalized account of the murder was produced in 1953 for the CBS radio series "Crime Classics". The incident has inspired a number of contemporary musicians: ''No Roses'' by the Albion Country Band, released in 1971, included the traditional song "Murder of Maria Martin"; more recently, "Murder in the Red Barn", a song by Tom Waits (co-written with his wife Kathleen Brennan) from his 1992 album ''Bone Machine'', and Kathryn Roberts and Sean Lakeman's "The Red Barn" on the 2004 album ''2'' have referred to the event. The song "Maria Martin" included on the folk album ''White Swans Black Ravens'' was recorded live in Moyse's Hall Museum. Swavesey Village College Theatre Company produced a stage adaptation in 2000, and later revived the production in 2006. The latest revival toured theatres and received critical acclaim.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="307b796531d3b36c07cf270d1f007bd8" name="Corder-broadside2" sectnum="6#1">../img/307b796531d3b36c07cf270d1f007bd8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>