<document id="8d05be7493a43d76c350102946d85cba-4.2.1" name="Antbird" cat="3">
<text>
Many species participate in mixed-species feeding flocks, forming a large percentage of the participating species within their range. Some of these are core or "nuclear species". These nuclear species share territories with other nuclear species but exclude conspecifics (members of the same species) and are found in almost all flocks; these are joined by "attendant species".  Loud and distinctive calls and conspicuous plumage are important attributes of nuclear species as they promote cohesion in the flock. The composition of these flocks varies geographically; in Amazonia species of ''Thamnomanes'' antshrike are the leading nuclear species; elsewhere other species, such as the Dot-winged Antwrens and Checker-throated Antwrens, fill this role. Other species of antwren and antbird join them along with woodcreepers, ant-tanagers, foliage-gleaners and greenlets. The benefits of the mixed flock are thought to be related to predation, since many eyes are better for spotting predatory hawks and falcons. Comparisons between multi-species feeding flocks in different parts of the world found that instances of flocking were positively correlated with predation risk by raptors.Thiollay, J. (1999)  ''Journal of Avian Biology''. '''30''' (3): 282&ndash;294  For example, where ''Thamnomanes'' antshrikes lead the group they give loud warning calls in the presence of predators. These calls are understood and reacted to by all the other species in the flock. The advantage to the ''Thamnomanes'' antshrikes is in allowing the rest of the flock, which are typically gleaners, to act as beaters, flushing prey while foraging which the antshrikes can obtain by sallying. Similar roles are filled in other flocks by other antbird species or other bird families, for example the shrike-tanagers. Within the feeding flocks competition is reduced by microniche partitioning; where Dot-winged Antwrens, Checker-throated Antwrens and White-flanked Antwrens feed in flocks together, the Dot-wings feed in the densest vines, the White-flank in less dense vegetation, and the Checker-throats in the same density as the latter but in dead foliage only.Wiley, R.H. (1971)  ''Auk'' '''88''' (4): 881&ndash;892
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="160f7b3364ec5a8af51a39fbd57dba3f" name="Dotted_winged_antwren_(Drake_Bay)" sectnum="4.2.1#1">../img/160f7b3364ec5a8af51a39fbd57dba3f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>