<document id="8ddce5ac766087aa7b06de57e25956bd-3.1" name="Seabird" cat="3">
<text>
Seabirds have made numerous adaptations to living on and feeding in the sea. Wing morphology has been shaped by the niche an individual species or family has evolved, so that looking at a wing's shape and loading can tell a scientist about its life feeding behaviour. Longer wings and low wing loading are typical of more pelagic species, whilst diving species have shorter wings.Gaston, Anthony J. (2004). ''Seabirds: A Natural History'' New Haven:Yale University Press, ISBN 0-300-10406-5 Species such as the Wandering Albatross, which forage over huge areas of sea, have a reduced capacity for powered flight and are dependent on a type of gliding called dynamic soaring (where the wind deflected by waves provides lift) as well as slope soaring.Pennycuick, C. J. (1982). "The flight of petrels and albatrosses (Procellariiformes), observed in South Georgia and its vicinity". ''Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London B'' '''300''': 75–106. Seabirds also almost always have webbed feet, to aid movement on the surface as well as assisting diving in some species. The Procellariiformes are unusual amongst birds in having a strong sense of smell, which is used to find widely distributed food in a vast ocean,Lequette, B., Verheyden, C., Jowentin, P. (1989) "Olfaction in Subantarctic seabirds: Its phylogenetic and ecological significance" ''The Condor'' '''91''': 732-135.  and possibly to locate their colonies.

Salt glands are used by seabirds to deal with the salt they ingest by drinking and feeding (particularly on crustaceans), and to help them osmoregulate.Harrison, C. S. (1990) ''Seabirds of Hawaii, Natural History and Conservation'' Ithica:Cornell University Press, ISBN 0-8014-2449-6 The excretions from these glands (which are positioned in the head of the birds, emerging from the nasal cavity) are almost pure sodium chloride.

With the exception of the cormorants and some terns, and in common with most other birds, all seabirds have waterproof plumage. However, compared to land birds, they have far more feathers protecting their bodies. This dense plumage is better able to protect the bird from getting wet, and cold is kept out by a dense layer of down feathers. The cormorants possess a layer of unique feathers that retain a smaller layer of air (compared to other diving birds) but otherwise soak up water.Grémillet, D, Chauvin, C, Wilson, R.P., Le Maho, Y. & Wanless, S. (2005) Unusual feather structure allows partial plumage wettability in diving great cormorants ''Phalacrocorax carbo''." ''Journal of Avian Biology'' '''36'''(1): 57–63. This allows them to swim without fighting the buoyancy that retaining air in the feathers causes, yet retain enough air to prevent the bird losing excessive heat through contact with water.

The plumage of most seabirds is less colourful than that of land birds, restricted in the main to variations of black, white or grey. A few species sport colourful plumes (such as the tropicbirds or some penguins), but most of the colour in seabirds appears in the bills and legs. The plumage of seabirds is thought in many cases to be for camouflage, both defensive (the colour of US Navy battleships is the same as that of Antarctic Prions, and in both cases it reduces visibility at sea) and aggressive (the white underside possessed by many seabirds helps hide them from prey below).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="485d525f867dc12e17173b706a3abc4e" name="Phalacrocorax-auritus-007" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/485d525f867dc12e17173b706a3abc4e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>