<document id="8ddce5ac766087aa7b06de57e25956bd-3.2.1" name="Seabird" cat="3">
<text>
Many seabirds feed on the ocean's surface, as the action of marine currents often concentrates food such as krill, forage fish, squid or other prey items within reach of a dipped head.

Surface feeding itself can be broken up into two different approaches, surface feeding while flying (for example as practiced by gadfly petrels, frigatebirds and  storm-petrels), and surface feeding whilst swimming (examples of which are practiced by fulmars, gulls, many of the shearwaters and gadfly petrels). Surface feeders in flight include some of the most acrobatic of seabirds, which either snatch morsels from the water (as do frigate-birds and some terns), or "walk", pattering and hovering on the water's surface, as some of the storm-petrels do.Withers, P.C (1979) "Aerodynamics and Hydrodynamics of the ‘Hovering’ Flight of Wilson'S Storm Petrel" ''Journal of Experimental Biology'' '''80''': 83–91 Many of these do not ever land in the water, and some, such as the frigatebirds, have difficulty getting airborne again should they do so.Metz, V. G., and E. A. Schreiber. 2002. Great Frigatebird (''Fregata minor''). In ''The Birds of North America'', No. '''681''' (A. Poole and F. Gill, eds.). The Birds of North America, Inc., Philadelphia, PA. Another seabird family that does not land while feeding is the skimmer, which has a unique fishing method: flying along the surface with the lower mandible in the water—this shuts automatically when the bill touches something in the water. The skimmer's bill reflects its unusual lifestyle, with the lower mandible uniquely being longer than the upper one.

Surface feeders that swim often have unique bills as well, adapted for their specific prey. Prions have special bills with filters called lamellae to filter out plankton from mouthfuls of water,Brooke, M. (2004).  ''Albatrosses And Petrels Across The World'' Oxford University Press, Oxford, UK ISBN 0-19-850125-0  and many albatrosses and petrels have hooked bills to snatch fast-moving prey. Gulls have more generalised bills that reflect their more opportunistic lifestyle.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="79caceb2536e72ccf77fd885296788bb" name="Wilson's_storm_petrel" sectnum="3.2.1#1">../img/79caceb2536e72ccf77fd885296788bb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>