<document id="8ddce5ac766087aa7b06de57e25956bd-3.2.2" name="Seabird" cat="3">
<text>
Pursuit diving exerts greater pressures (both evolutionary and physiological) on seabirds, but the reward is a greater area in which to feed than is available to surface feeders. Propulsion underwater can be provided by wings (as used by penguins, auks, diving petrels, and some other species of petrel) or feet (as used by cormorants, grebes, loons and several types of fish-eating ducks). Wing-propelled divers are generally faster than foot-propelled divers. In both cases, the use of wings or feet for diving has limited their utility in other situations: loons and grebes walk with extreme difficulty (if at all), penguins cannot fly, and auks have sacrificed flight efficiency in favour of underwater diving. For example, the razorbill (an Atlantic auk) requires 64% more energy to fly than a petrel of equivalent size.Gaston, Anthony J. & Jones, Ian L. (1998). ''The Auks'' Oxford:Oxford University Press, ISBN 0-19-854032-9 Many shearwaters are intermediate between the two, having longer wings than typical wing-propelled divers but heavier wing loadings than the other surface-feeding procellariids, leaving them capable of diving to considerable depths while still being efficient long-distance travellers. The most impressive diving exhibited by shearwaters is found in the Short-tailed Shearwater, which has been recorded diving below 70 m.Weimerskirch, H., Cherel, Y., (1998) Feeding ecology of short-tailed shearwaters: breeding in Tasmania and foraging in the Antarctic? ''Marine Ecology Progress Series'' '''167''': 261–274  Some albatross species are also capable of some limited diving, with Light-mantled Sooty Albatrosses holding the record at 12 m.Prince, P.A., Huin, N., Weimerskirch, H., (1994) "Diving depths of albatrosses" ''Antarctic Science'' '''6''': (''3'') 353–354. Of all the wing-propelled pursuit divers, the most efficient in the air are the albatrosses, and it is no coincidence that they are the poorest divers. This is the dominant guild in polar and subpolar environments, as it is energetically inefficient in warmer waters. With their poor flying ability, many wing-propelled pursuit divers are more limited in their foraging range than other guilds, especially during the breeding season when hungry chicks need regular feeding.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f9a74295f5634acba3106b82730ffa16" name="Penguinu" sectnum="3.2.2#1">../img/f9a74295f5634acba3106b82730ffa16.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>