<document id="8ddce5ac766087aa7b06de57e25956bd-4.11" name="Seabird" cat="3">
<text>
Many seabirds are little studied and poorly known, due to living far out to sea and breeding in isolated colonies.  However, some seabirds, particularly, the albatrosses and gulls, have broken into popular consciousness.  The albatrosses have been described as "the most legendary of birds",Carboneras, C. (1992) "Family Diomedeidae (Albatrosses)" in ''Handbook of Birds of the World'' Vol 1. Barcelona:Lynx Edicions, ISBN 84-87334-10-5 and have a variety of myths and legends associated with them, and today it is widely considered unlucky to harm them, although the notion that sailors believed that is a mythCocker, M., & Mabey, R., (2005) ''Birds Britannica'' London:Chatto & Windus, ISBN 0-7011-6907-9 which derives from Samuel Taylor Coleridge's famous poem, "The Rime of the Ancient Mariner", in which a sailor is punished for killing an albatross by having to wear its corpse around his neck.

''Instead of the Cross the Albatross''
''About my neck was hung''

Sailors did, however, consider it unlucky to touch a storm-petrel, especially one that has landed on the ship.Carboneras, C. (1992) "Family Hydrobatidae (Storm-petrels)" in ''Handbook of Birds of the World'' Vol 1. Barcelona:Lynx Edicions, ISBN 84-87334-10-5

Gulls are one of the most commonly seen seabirds, given their use of human-made habitats (such as cities and dumps) and their often fearless nature. They therefore also have made it into the popular consciousness - they have been used metaphorically, as in ''Jonathan Livingston Seagull'' by Richard Bach, or to denote a closeness to the sea, such as their use in the ''The Lord of the Rings'' both in the insignia of Gondor and therefore Númenor (used in the design of the films), and to call Legolas to (and across) the sea. Other species have also made an impact; pelicans have long been associated with mercy and altruism because of an early Western Christian myth that they split open their breast to feed their starving chicks.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7d89bf2c8e21cfcfb926169157933319" name="Pelican_in_its_piety" sectnum="4.11#1">../img/7d89bf2c8e21cfcfb926169157933319.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>