<document id="8ddce5ac766087aa7b06de57e25956bd-3.3" name="Seabird" cat="3">
<text>
Seabirds' life histories are dramatically different from those of land birds. In general, they are K-selected, live much longer (anywhere between twenty and sixty years), delay breeding for longer (for up to ten years), and invest more effort into fewer young.Robertson, C.J.R. (1993). "Survival and longevity of the Northern Royal Albatross ''Diomedea epomophora sanfordi'' at Taiaroa Head" 1937–93. ''Emu'' '''93''': 269–276. Most species will only have one clutch a year, unless they lose the first (with a few exceptions, like the Cassin's Auklet),Manuwal, D. A. and A. C. Thoresen. 1993. Cassin’s Auklet (''Ptychoramphus aleuticus''). In The Birds of North America, No. 50 (A. Poole and F. Gill, Eds.). Philadelphia: The Academy of Natural Sciences; Washington, D.C.: The American Ornithologists’ Union. and many species (like the tubenoses and sulids), only one egg a year.

Care of young is protracted, extending for as long as six months, among the longest for birds. For example, once Common Guillemot chicks fledge, they remain with the male parent for several months at sea. The frigatebirds have the longest period of parental care of any bird, with the chicks fledging after four to six months and with continued assistance after that for up to fourteen months.Metz, V.G. & Schreiber, E.A. (2002) "Great Frigatebird (''Fregata minor'')" In ''The Birds of North America, No 681'', (Poole, A. & Gill, F., eds) The Birds of North America Inc:Philadelphia Due to the extended period of care, breeding occurs every two years rather than annually for some species. This life-history strategy has probably evolved both in response to the challenges of living at sea (collecting widely scattered prey items), the frequency of breeding failures due to unfavourable marine conditions, and the relative lack of predation compared to that of land-living birds.

Because of the greater investment in raising the young and because foraging for food may occur far from the nest site, in all seabird species except the phalaropes, both parents participate in caring for the young, and pairs are typically at least seasonally monogamous. Many species, such as gulls, auks and penguins, retain the same mate for several seasons, and many petrel species mate for life. The albatrosses and procellariids which mate for life can take many years to form a pair bond before they breed, and the albatrosses have an elaborate breeding dance that is part of pair-bond formation.Pickering, S.P.C., & Berrow, S.D., (2001) "Courtship behaviour of the Wandering Albatross ''Diomedea exulans'' at Bird Island, South Georgia" ''Marine Ornithology'' '''29''': 29–37
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="68845ba9f5d6a446d12104acda70a5d1" name="Morus_bassanus_billing" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/68845ba9f5d6a446d12104acda70a5d1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>