<document id="8ddce5ac766087aa7b06de57e25956bd-4.9" name="Seabird" cat="3">
<text>
Other human factors have led to declines and even extinctions in seabird populations, colonies and species. Of these, perhaps the most serious are introduced species. Seabirds, breeding predominantly on small isolated islands, have lost many predator defence behaviours. Feral cats are capable of taking seabirds as large as albatrosses, and many introduced rodents, such as the Pacific Rat, can take eggs hidden in burrows. Introduced goats, cattle, rabbits and other herbivores can lead to problems, particularly when species need vegetation to protect or shade their young.Carlile, N., Proiddel, D., Zino, F., Natividad, C. & Wingate, D.B. (2003) "A review of four successful recovery programmes for threatened sub-tropical petrels" ''Marine Ornithology'' '''31''': 185–192 Disturbance of breeding colonies by humans is often a problem as well—visitors, even well-meaning tourists, can flush brooding adults off a colony leaving chicks and eggs vulnerable to predators.


The build-up of toxins and pollutants in seabirds is also a concern. Seabirds, being apex predators, suffered from the ravages of DDT until it was banned; among other effects, DDT was implicated in embryo development problems and the skewed sex ratio of Western Gulls in southern California.Fry, D. & Toone, C. (1981) "DDT-induced feminization of gull embryos" ''Science'' '''213'''(4510): 922–924 Oil spills are also a threat to seabird species, as both a toxin and because the feathers of the birds become saturated by the oil, causing them to lose their waterproofing.Dunnet, G., Crisp, D., Conan, G., Bourne, W. (1982) "Oil Pollution and Seabird Populations " ''Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London. B'' '''297'''(1087): 413–427 Oil pollution threatens species with restricted ranges or already depressed populations.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b0a1873345899d30c5f4ae734f8b69c7" name="Oiledcrestedauklet" sectnum="4.9#1">../img/b0a1873345899d30c5f4ae734f8b69c7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>