<document id="8e01095fbce66ebe95129a0c1f844f77-4.11" name="Yagan" cat="14">
<text>
From the mid-1970s, members of the Noongar community lobbied for the erection of a statue of Yagan as part of the WAY 1979 sesquicentennial celebrations. Their requests were refused, however, after then Premier of Western Australia Sir Charles Court was advised by one prominent historian that Yagan was not important enough to warrant a statue  Colbung claims "Court was more interested in spending tax payers' money on refurbishing the badly neglected burial place of Captain James Stirling, WA's first governor." Despite this setback, the Noongar community persisted, establishing a Yagan Committee and running a number of fund-raising drives. Eventually, sufficient funds were collected to allow the commissioning of Australian sculptor Robert Hitchcock to create a statue. The result was a life-size statue in bronze, depicting Yagan standing naked with a spear held across his shoulders. Hitchcock's statue of Yagan was officially opened by Yagan Committee chairperson Elizabeth Hanson on 11 September 1984. It stands on Heirisson Island in the Swan River near Perth.

In 1997, within a week of the return of Yagan's head to Perth, vandals beheaded the statue and stole the head. After restoration, it was beheaded again. Credit for the act was anonymously claimed by a "British loyalist" as an act of retaliation for Colbung's comments about Princess Diana. The Western Australia Police did not succeed in identifying the vandals, nor in recovering the heads, and deemed it infeasible to have the status fenced off or placed under guard. Western Australian media coverage found humour in the beheadings; Stephen Muecke, for example, has identified what he calls the "satirical trivialising of Aboriginal concerns" in ''The West Australian'''s coverage, which in one article referred to the head as a "bonce" and a "noggin", and finished with a pun on "skullduggery". Speaking of the same piece, Adam Shoemaker writes "This is the stuff of light humour and comic relief. There is no sense of the decapitation as being an act of vandalism, even less that it could have been motivated by malevolence. And, as an editorial, the piece has a definite authorising function...." On the other hand, academic analysis has treated the act with much more gravity. In 2007, for example, David Martin described the decapitation as "an act which speaks not only to the continuance of white settler racism, but also to the power of mimesis to invigorate our modern memorials and monuments with a life of their own."

In 2002 Member of the Western Australian Legislative Assembly Janet Woollard called for the statue's private parts to be covered up, but nothing was done. In November 2005 Richard Wilkes again called for the statue's private parts to be covered, on the grounds that such a depiction would be more historically accurate as Yagan would have worn a covering for most of the year. Also under consideration is the creation of a new statue with a head shape that accords better with the forensic reconstruction of Yagan's head.Kent, Melissa (2005). Yagan centre of cover-up bid. ''The West Australian'', 24 November 2005.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ab6baca3cada84fd7bb6699eaf96c68d" name="Yagan_Statue_2005" sectnum="4.11#1">../img/ab6baca3cada84fd7bb6699eaf96c68d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>