<document id="8ea1526ee1fcfad1bd285f2c48117b6a-3.9" name="Fightin'_Texas_Aggie_Band" cat="20">
<text>
The halftime drill always begins with the band running into place at the command of the drum major's whistle. The announcer (Lieutenant Colonel Jay Brewer) then states, usually in unison with the crowd, "Now forming at the north end of Kyle Field, the nationally famous Fightin' Texas Aggie Band." A whoop and cheers come from the audience. The drum majors then march out in front of the band and the head drum major calls the band to attention and vocally gives directions to the band, referencing the composition of the Aggie War Hymn, by shouting, "Recall! Step off on Hullabaloo!" (Recall is a traditional Army bugle call - the first 34 notes, and intro of the Aggie War Hymn. "Hullabaloo" is the first word sung in the Aggie War Hymn.) These directions are not amplified in any way, but can be heard across the entire stadium. After another whoop, the drum majors signal for the horns to be lifted into playing position with two quick whistle blasts and the bugle rank does a flourish.

The drill then begins with the band playing the opening notes of the War Hymn and stepping off into the initial formation. At some point in the drill, the band converts from Spread formation to Block formation. With no cessation of the music until the band leaves the field, the drill continues and often stops with the band playing the last stanza in place in the center of the field before moving into the signature "Block T" or "Block ATM". When done playing, the band runs off the field. Specific maneuvers in the drill can include:

*The Criss Cross &mdash; the band files split into two halves and march through each other at 90° angles
*The Four-way Cross Through (and many variations on it) &mdash; The band splits into four groups of three files and march through each other from each of the corners of the field
*Minstrel Turns &mdash; band members pass through each other by stepping between each others' feet.
*Spread-to-Block &mdash; the band moves from being 30 files wide by 12 ranks deep to 12 files wide by 30 ranks deep
*Block-to-Spread &mdash; the opposite of Spread-to-Block
*Continuous Countermarch &mdash; the bugle rank leads two successive countermarches following the back of the band through the maneuver
*Wheel Turns (also known as a Gate Turn) &mdash; A turn of a block of the band where the people on the inside of the turn reduce their step size. This is also done during parades when going around corners.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="272e0d2687c18e28c3972e2052fcc334" name="AggieBandFormation" sectnum="3.9#1">../img/272e0d2687c18e28c3972e2052fcc334.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>