<document id="8eb55bad0c2703126e6d4575db9f8f81-4.1" name="Plunketts_Creek_(Loyalsock_Creek)" cat="11">
<text>
The clear-cutting of forests in the 19th century adversely affected the ecology of the Plunketts Creek watershed and its water quality. Polluting industries on the creek and its tributaries then included a coal mine and tannery (which are long since departed).''For a historical perspective on pollution from both mining and tanneries, see:''  In the autumn of 1897, three men working with hides at the Proctor tannery were stricken with anthrax, two fatally. Another four deaths originally blamed on pneumonia were suspected of being due to pulmonary anthrax, and some cattle drinking from Plunketts Creek downstream from the tannery were also infected. As late as 1959, the sludge pile from the tannery was still visible in Proctor, but was not disturbed for fear of anthrax spores. ''The article has a note that it was written in 1959, but the author's name was lost prior to publication in 1966.'' No acid mine drainage is reported in the watershed.

As of 1984, the mean annual precipitation for the Loyalsock Creek watershed (which Plunketts Creek is part of) was 42 to 48 inches (1067 to 1219 mm). Pennsylvania receives the greatest amount of acid rain of any state in the United States. Because Plunketts Creek is in a sandstone and shale mountain region, it has a relatively low capacity to neutralize added acid. This makes it especially vulnerable to increased acidification from acid rain, which poses a threat to the long term health of the plants and animals in the creek. The total alkalinity (TA) is a measure of the capacity of water to neutralize acid, with a larger TA corresponding to a greater capacity. In 2007, the TA of two subtributaries was known: Engle Run, a 4.9-mile (7.9 km) tributary of King Run, had a TA of 5, and the Noon Branch, a 1.9-mile (3.1 km) tributary of Wolf Run, had a TA of 9.

The 2002 Pennsylvania Department of Conservation and Natural Resources (DCNR) report on "State Forest Waters with Special Protection" rated Plunketts Creek (from its source to mouth) and two of it tributaries, Wolf Run and Mock Creek (from the county line to the mouth), as "High Quality-Cold Water Fisheries". Two subtributaries were rated as "Exceptional Value" streams for fishing: Engle Run and the Noon Branch of Wolf Run. ''Note:'' What is now Loyalsock State Forest in the Plunketts Creek watershed was then divided into Tiadaghton State Forest in Lycoming County and Wyoming State Forest in Sullivan County.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="04e2a30a0d7bfba7518f4d3e3c9e2dd1" name="Proctor,_Pennsylvania_Panorama" sectnum="4.1#1">../img/04e2a30a0d7bfba7518f4d3e3c9e2dd1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>