<document id="8eb55bad0c2703126e6d4575db9f8f81-4" name="Plunketts_Creek_(Loyalsock_Creek)" cat="11">
<text>
The Plunketts Creek watershed drains parts of Cascade, McNett, and Plunketts Creek townships in Lycoming County, and Fox and Hillsgrove Townships in Sullivan County (with most of the watershed in Plunketts Creek Township). The drainage basin area is 23.6 square miles (61.1 km²), accounting for 4.78% of the 494 square mile (1,279 km²) Loyalsock Creek watershed. Bear Creek, whose mouth is also within the village of Barbours but on the opposite (left) bank, is the nearest major creek at 0.52 miles (0.84 km) downstream, as measured along Loyalsock Creek. (It is also known as "Big Bear Creek" as it is the watershed upstream of "Little Bear Creek".) The neighboring major watersheds on the same bank are Wallis Run (9.56 miles (15.39 km) downstream) and Mill Creek (at the village of Hillsgrove, 9.16 miles (14.74 km) upstream). Pleasant Stream, a tributary of Lycoming Creek, is the watershed to the north.

The named tributaries together account for 70.6% of the Plunketts Creek watershed. The largest tributary is Wolf Run, with an area of 7.39 square miles (19.14 km²), accounting for 31.3% of the total. The Wolf Run drainage basin includes both the Noon Branch (4.26 square miles (11.03 km²)) and the Brian Branch (1.60 square miles (4.14 km²)). The next largest tributary of Plunketts Creek is King Run with 5.56 square miles (14.40 km²) or 23.6% of the watershed. The King Run watershed includes Engle Run, with 2.90 square miles (7.51 km²). The third largest tributary is Dry Run with 1.79 square miles (4.64 km²) or 7.6%, followed by the unnamed tributary in Coal Mine Hollow with 1.08 square miles (2.80 km²) or 4.6%. All other named tributaries are less than 1.00 square mile (2.59 km²) and account for less than 5% of the drainage basin individually. Plunketts Creek does not have its own watershed association, but is part of the larger Loyalsock Creek Watershed Association. and
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0d3b1c70b4620baa9d0880fa0bacca13" name="Plunketts_Creek_Hoppestown_1" sectnum="4#1">../img/0d3b1c70b4620baa9d0880fa0bacca13.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>