<document id="8ef95695c1880fd9838f8ff05c01a68a-3.6" name="2006_Chick-fil-A_Bowl" cat="26">
<text>
Because Virginia Tech had received the opening kickoff, Georgia received the ball to open the second half. Stafford was able to connect with wide receiver Mario Raley for a 24-yard gain, taking Georgia to the 50-yard line, but Virginia Tech's defense stiffened and Georgia was forced to punt. Pinned at their ten-yard line by the Georgia punt, Virginia Tech went three-and-out and was itself forced to punt.  

A 19-yard punt return by Mikey Henderson put Georgia into good field position. Stafford capitalized on the opportunity, completing a 26-yard pass to put Georgia into field-goal range. After three unsuccessful plays, kicker Brandon Coutu connected on a 51-yard field goal to cut the Virginia Tech lead to 21&ndash;6. 

On the kickoff following the field goal, Georgia head coach Mark Richt ordered an unorthodox onside kick. Surprised by the unexpected play, the Virginia Tech coverage team was unable to recover the ball, which was leapt upon by the kicker, Brian Mimbs. With a new chance at offense and a sense of optimism triggered by the successful onside kick, Georgia drove down the field. Aided by 20 yards in penalties against Virginia Tech, the drive resulted in a six-yard touchdown pass to Martrez Milner. The touchdown and extra point boosted Georgia's morale and cut the score to 21&ndash;13, Virginia Tech leading by eight. 

The third quarter came to a close as Virginia Tech struggled to answer the two Georgia scores. Tech quarterback Sean Glennon connected on a 29-yard pass to Eddie Royal, driving the Hokies to the Bulldog 47-yard line as the clock hit zero. 

At the end of the third quarter, Virginia Tech still led Georgia, 21&ndash;13. ESPN.com 3rd Quarter Play-by-Play. Accessed October 10, 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="691a07c08c6ddff38ba2a917bdfaa14a" name="2006_VT_UGA_Chick_fil_A_action" sectnum="3.6#1">../img/691a07c08c6ddff38ba2a917bdfaa14a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>