<document id="8fc84d237456da58e358f5dc4e767a08-2.1" name="Rudolph_Cartier" cat="19">
<text>
Cartier and Kneale's first major production was the six-part serial ''The Quatermass Experiment'', broadcast in the summer of 1953. A science-fiction story, it relates the sending of the first humans into space by Professor Bernard Quatermass and the consequences when an alien presence invades the crew's rocket during its flight and returns to Earth in the body of the one remaining crewmember, having absorbed the consciousnesses and shredded the bodies of the other two. A critical and popular success, ''The Quatermass Experiment'' has been described by the British Film Institute's "Screenonline" website as "one of the most influential series of the 1950s." Cartier's contribution to the serial's success was highlighted in his 1994 obituary in ''The Times'' newspaper, which also called the serial "a landmark in British television drama as much for its visual imagination as for its ability to shock and disturb."

The success of ''The Quatermass Experiment'' led to two sequels, ''Quatermass II'' (1955) and ''Quatermass and the Pit'' (1958–59), both produced and directed by Cartier and written by Kneale. Both were successful and critically-acclaimed, and Cartier's production work on them became increasingly ambitious. For ''Quatermass II'', he pre-filmed a significant amount of material on location, using 35 mm film, opening the drama out from a confined studio setting with the most ambitious location shooting yet attempted in British television.Pixley, p. 19. Cartier, with his previous experience as a film director, particularly enjoyed working on these cinema-style filmed scenes.Pixley, p. 20.

The appeal of the ''Quatermass'' serials has been attributed by the Museum of Broadcast Communications to the depiction of "A new range of gendered fears about Britain's postwar and post-colonial security. As a result, or perhaps simply because of Kneale and Cartier's effective combination of science fiction and poignant melodrama, audiences were captivated." The Screenonline website suggests that the visual impact of Cartier's interpretation of Kneale's scripts was a major factor in their success, which it attributes to their "originality, mass appeal and dynamism... ''The Quatermass Experiment'' became a landmark of science fiction and the cornerstone of the genre on British television."

Aside from the ''Quatermass'' serials, Cartier and Kneale collaborated on several one-off dramas, including literary and theatrical adaptations of ''Wuthering Heights'' (6 December 1953) and ''The Moment of Truth'' (10 March 1955), as well as Kneale's own ''The Creature'' (30 January 1955).Pixley, p. 16. Of particular note was their collaboration on an adaptation of George Orwell's novel ''Nineteen Eighty-Four'', originally broadcast on 12 December 1954, regarded as Cartier's most famous work. ''The Times'''s review the day after its broadcast noted its "vividness... the two minutes' hate was, for instance, a wonderfully riotious orgy of vindictiveness." The production also attracted considerable controversy. There were questions asked in the House of Commons concerning some of the graphic scenes of horror in the play, and the BBC received several telephone calls threatening Cartier's life if the second live performance, scheduled for 16 December, went ahead.Cooke, p. 27. The BBC took these threats seriously enough to assign him bodyguards. Cartier appeared live on television himself to defend the production in a studio debate, and eventually the Board of Governors of the BBC voted that the second performance should go ahead as planned.Murray, p. 39. The production had by this time received the backing of the Duke of Edinburgh, who commented during a speech to the Royal Society of Arts that he and the Queen had watched and enjoyed the first performance.Murray, pp. 38–39.

''Nineteen Eighty-Four'' had been a success, but it was also one of the most expensive television dramas ever made in the UK. Cartier often spent large amounts of money on his productions. Earlier in 1954, Michael Barry had heavily criticised him for the money and resources he had expended in an adaptation of ''Rebecca''. In a memo written after that production's transmission, Barry admonished Cartier for his over-ambitious production:
The performance of ''Rebecca'' seems to me to have taken us further into the danger area instead of showing any improvement. I am unable to defend at a time when departmental costs and scene loads are in an acute state the load imposed by ''Rebecca'' on Design and Supply and the expenditure upon extras and costumes... the vast area of the hall and the stairway never justified the great expenditure of effort required in building and one is left with a very clear impression of reaching a point where the department must be accused of not knowing what it is doing.Jacobs, p. 134.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5a8245bba31b6c0c0cdf652f573c2381" name="Quat2pic" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/5a8245bba31b6c0c0cdf652f573c2381.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>