<document id="9039c3a87f4c2f7855e006764aed9b4f-1.1" name="Geography_and_ecology_of_the_Everglades" cat="11">
<text>
At only 5,000 years of age, the Everglades is a young region in geological terms. Its ecosystems are in constant flux due to three factors: the type and amount of water present, the geology of the region, and the frequency and severity of fires.


Water is the dominant element in the Everglades, and it shapes the land, vegetation, and animal life of South Florida. The South Florida climate was once arid and semi-arid, interspersed with wet periods. Between 10,000 and 20,000 years ago, sea levels rose, submerging portions of the Florida peninsula and causing the water table to rise. Fresh water saturated the limestone, eroding some of it and creating springs and sinkholes. The abundance of fresh water allowed new vegetation to take root, and through evaporation formed thunderstorms. Limestone was dissolved by the slightly acidic rainwater. The limestone wore away, and groundwater came into contact with the surface, creating a massive wetland ecosystem.McCally, pp. 9–10. Although the region appears flat, the wearing away of the limestone in some areas created slight valleys and plateaus—a difference of inches in elevation—that affected not only the flow of water, but also types of vegetation present. 

The Everglades are unique; no other wetland system in the world is nourished primarily from the atmosphere.Lodge, p.14. Before the first attempt at draining the Everglades in 1882, the entire watershed extended from Orlando to Florida Bay comprising the Kissimmee&ndash;Lake Okeechobee&ndash;Everglades (KLOE) watershed. Kissimmee River outlets flow into Lake Okeechobee, which sits  above sea level.Lodge, pp. 18–19. Only two seasons exist in the Everglades: wet (May to November) and dry (December to April). Average annual rainfall in the Everglades is approximately , though fluctuations of precipitation are normal.
 Droughts, floods, and tropical storms are normal occurrences in the area.
  When Lake Okeechobee exceeds its water storage capacity during the wet season, it pours slowly over the southern rim and flows for  to Florida Bay. The gradient change is so slight that the river moves only  a minute.Lodge, p. 21. Sawgrass thrives in this river, dominates freshwater marshes and sloughs, and is the main characteristic of the region.

Severe weather, in the form of tropical storms and hurricanes, also affects the structure of the Everglades. Between 1871 and 2003, 40 tropical cyclones struck the Everglades, usually every one to three years.Lodge, p. 89. These storms alter the coastline, flush decaying vegetation from estuaries, strip weakened branches from trees, and disperse seeds, pollen, and plant material.Jewell, p. 35. Hurricane Donna in 1960 affected  of mangrove forests by depositing marl over the roots and depriving the trees of oxygen. It also eradicated orchids, bromeliads, and other epiphytes that once flourished in the mangroves; their reappearance may take a century or more. Donna also significantly spread buttonwood, saltwort, and glasswort, and epiphytes began to grow in new areas.Lodge, pp. 89–93. Although the lasting effects remain to be seen, Hurricane Andrew in 1992 also destroyed mangrove forests and snapped slash pines in half. However, regrowth occurred quickly, and sand deposited by the storm surge improved nesting conditions for crocodiles and sea turtles.Toops, p. 95.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="04abc708cd2fb0c5773279aa60f96d55" name="Storm_at_Shark_River_in_Everglades" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/04abc708cd2fb0c5773279aa60f96d55.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>