<document id="907ca7121de0ce762dae71a3e8a8f658-2.2" name="Jake_Gyllenhaal" cat="19">
<text>
''Donnie Darko'', Gyllenhaal's second major film, was not a box office success upon its initial 2001 release, but eventually became a cult favorite.Snider, Mike (February 2, 2005), ,''USA Today''. Retrieved September 19, 2006. The film, directed by Richard Kelly, is set in 1988 and stars Gyllenhaal as a troubled teenager who, after narrowly escaping death, experiences visions of a 6 foot (1.8 m) tall rabbit named Frank who tells him that the world is coming to an end. Gyllenhaal's performance was well-received by critics; Gary Mairs of culturevulture.net claimed that "Gyllenhaal manages the difficult trick of seeming both blandly normal and profoundly disturbed, often within the same scene."Kois, Dan (July 23, 2004), ,''Salon.com''. Retrieved September 19, 2006Mairs, Gary, ,''CultureVulture.net''. Retrieved September 21, 2006.


After the critical success of ''Donnie Darko'', Gyllenhaal's next role was as the lead character in 2002's ''Highway'', a film ignored by audiences and critics alike. His performance was described by one critic as "silly, cliched and straight to video."Wills, Dominic (2006), , ''Tiscali.com'', page 7. Retrieved September 16, 2006. Gyllenhaal had more success starring opposite Jennifer Aniston in ''The Good Girl'', which premiered at the 2002 Sundance Film Festival; he also starred in ''Lovely & Amazing'' with Catherine Keener.Hubbell, Anne (January 16, 2002), , CNN Entertainment. Retrieved September 16, 2006. In both films he plays an unstable character who begins a reckless affair with an older woman. Gyllenhaal later described these as "teenager in transition" roles.Michael, David (October 21, 2002), . Retrieved September 19, 2006. Gyllenhaal later starred in the Touchstone Pictures romantic comedy ''Bubble Boy'', which was loosely based on the story of David Vetter. The film portrays the title character's adventures as he pursues the love of his life before she marries the wrong man.Gonzalez, Ed (2001), . Retrieved September 19, 2006. The film was panned by critics, with one calling it an "empty-headed, chaotic, utterly tasteless atrocity".Swietek, Frank, , oneguysopinion.com. Retrieved September 21, 2006.

Following ''Bubble Boy'', Gyllenhaal starred opposite Dustin Hoffman, Susan Sarandon and Ellen Pompeo in ''Moonlight Mile'', as a young man coping with the death of his fiancée and the grief of her parents. The story, which received mixed reviews,. Retrieved September 21, 2006. is loosely based on writer/director Brad Silberling's personal experiences following the murder of girlfriend Rebecca Schaeffer.Murray, Rebecca (2006), , ''About.com''. Retrieved September 19, 2006.

Gyllenhaal was almost cast as Spider-Man for ''Spider-Man 2'' due to director Sam Raimi's concerns about original ''Spider-Man'' star Tobey Maguire`s health.Otto, Jeff. "" ''IGN'', July 23, 2003. Retrieved on 2007-08-14. Maguire recovered, however, and the sequel was shot without Gyllenhaal.Morales, Wilson (June 2004), , Blackfilm.com. Retrieved September 19, 2006. Instead, Gyllenhaal starred in the blockbuster ''The Day After Tomorrow'' in 2004, co-starring Dennis Quaid as his father.Mottram, James (May 12, 2004), . Retrieved September 19, 2006.Schruers, Fred (October 30, 2005), ,''The Guardian''. Retrieved September 19, 2006.

In his theatrical debut Gyllenhaal starred on the London stage in Kenneth Lonergan's revival of ''This is Our Youth''.Billington, Michael (March 18, 2002), , ''The Guardian''. Retrieved September 19, 2006. Gyllenhaal said, "Every actor I look up to has done theatre work, so I knew I had to give it a try."Gritten, David (April 13, 2002), , ''The Telegraph''. Retrieved September 19, 2006. The play, which had been a critical sensation on Broadway, ran for eight weeks in London's West End. Gyllenhaal received favorable critical reviews and an Evening Standard Theatre Award in the category "Outstanding Newcomer."Loveridge, Lizzie (March 2002), , CurtainUp.com. Retrieved September 21, 2006.Albemarle-London, . Retrieved September 19, 2006.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8e7995ce76375412d14b24a831762d91" name="Donniedarkoskelcostume" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/8e7995ce76375412d14b24a831762d91.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>