<document id="9098410a05683f8373815299ffd2889e-3.6" name="Night_of_the_Living_Dead" cat="19">
<text>
Romero revolutionized the horror film genre with ''Night of the Living Dead''; per Almar Haflidason, of the BBC, the film represented "a new dawn in horror film-making".Almar Haflidason, review of ''Night of the Living Dead'', March 20, 2001, at ; last accessed June 24, 2006. The film has also effectively redefined the use of the term Zombie. Early zombie films like Victor Halperin's ''White Zombie'' (1932) and Jacques Tourneur's ''I Walked with a Zombie'' (1943) concerned living people enslaved by a Voodoo witch doctor; many were set in the Caribbean.

The film and its successors spawned countless imitators that borrowed elements instituted by Romero: ''Tombs of the Blind Dead'', ''Zombie'', ''Hell of the Living Dead'', ''The Evil Dead'', ''Night of the Comet'', ''Return of the Living Dead'', ''Night of the Creeps'', ''Braindead'', ''Children of the Living Dead'', and the video game series ''Resident Evil'' (later adapted as films in 2002, 2004, and 2007), ''Dead Rising'', and ''House of the Dead''. ''Night of the Living Dead'' is parodied in films such as ''Night of the Living Bread'' and ''Shaun of the Dead'', and in episodes of ''The Simpsons'' ("Treehouse of Horror III", 1992), ''South Park'' ("Pink Eye", 1997; "Night of the Living Homeless", 2007) and ''Invader Zim'' (''Halloween Spectacular of Spooky Doom'', 2001;).Rockoff, ''Going to Pieces'', p. 36."Treehouse of Horror III", episode 64, ''The Simpsons'', October 29, 1992, at the ; last accessed June 24, 2006."Pink Eye", episode 107, ''South Park'', October 29, 1997, on ''South Park: The Complete First Season'' (DVD, Warner Bros., 2002) The word ''zombie'' is never used, but Romero's film introduced the theme of zombies as reanimated, flesh-eating cannibals.Collum, ''Assault of the Killer B's'', p. 3.Andrew Tudor, ''Monsters and Mad Scientists: A Cultural History of the Horror Movie'' (Oxford, Eng.: Blackwell Publishing, 1989), p. 101, ISBN 0-631-16992-X .

''Night of the Living Dead'' ushered in the splatter film sub-genre. As one film historian points out, horror prior to Romero's film had mostly involved rubber masks and costumes, cardboard sets, or mysterious figures lurking in the shadows. They were set in locations far removed from rural and suburban America.Jones, ''Rough Guide to Horror'', p. 117. Romero revealed the power behind exploitation and setting horror in ordinary, unexceptional locations and offered a template for making an "effective and lucrative" film on a "minuscule budget". Slasher films of the 1970s and 80s such as John Carpenter's ''Halloween'' (1978), Sean S. Cunningham's ''Friday the 13th'' (1980), and Wes Craven's ''A Nightmare on Elm Street'' (1984), for example, "owe much to the original ''Night of the Living Dead''".Grant, "Taking Back the ''Night of the Living Dead''", p. 201.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7e1210171d83cb0d283c1e8de1dd12e6" name="Nightofthelivingdead_screenshot" sectnum="3.6#1">../img/7e1210171d83cb0d283c1e8de1dd12e6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>