<document id="9098410a05683f8373815299ffd2889e-2.2" name="Night_of_the_Living_Dead" cat="19">
<text>
The lead role of Ben was played by unknown stage actor Duane Jones. His performance depicted Ben as a "comparatively calm and resourceful Negro", according to a contemporary (1969) movie reviewer.Kevin Thomas, review of ''Night of the Living Dead'', Los Angeles ''Times'', January 10, 1969, reprinted in ''The A-List: The National Society of Film Critics' 100 Essential Films'', ed. Jay Carr (Cambridge, Mass.: Da Capo Press, 2002), p. 199, ISBN 0-306-81096-4 . Casting Jones as the hero was, in 1968, potentially controversial. At the time, it was not typical for a black man to be the hero of a film the cast of which included white actors and actresses. Social commentators saw that casting as significant; on the other hand, Romero said that Jones "simply gave the best audition".George A. Romero, quoted in Jones, ''Rough Guide to Horror Movies'', p. 118. After ''Night of the Living Dead'', he co-starred in ''Ganja and Hess'' (1973), ''Vampires'' (1986), ''Negatives'' (1988) and ''To Die For'' (1989) before his death in 1988.Duane Jones at the ; last accessed June 24, 2006. Despite his other film roles, Jones worried that people only recognized him as Ben.Duane Jones interview, Bonus Materials, ''Night of the Living Dead'', Millennium Edition (DVD, Elite Entertainment, 2002).

Judith O'Dea, a 23-year-old commercial and stage actress, played Barbra. She had once worked for Hardman and Eastman in Pittsburgh, so they called her to audition. O'Dea was in Hollywood seeking to enter the movie business. She remarked in an interview that starring in the film was a positive experience for her, although she admitted that horror movies terrified her, particularly Vincent Price's ''House of Wax'' (1953). Besides acting, O'Dea performed her own stunts, which she jokingly says amounted to "lots of running". Assessing ''Night of the Living Dead'', she states "I honestly had no idea it would have such a lasting impact on our culture". She was just as surprised by the renown the film brought her: "People treat you differently.  ho-hum Judy O'Dea until they realize  Barbra from ''Night of the Living Dead''. All of a sudden  not so ho-hum anymore!" Following ''Night of the Living Dead'', O'Dea appeared in the television film ''The Pirate'' in 1978 and feature films ''Claustrophobia'', ''October Moon'', and ''The Ocean''.Judith O'Dea at the ; last accessed June 24, 2006.

The supporting cast had no experience in the film industry prior to ''Night of the Living Dead''. The role of Tom remained Keith Wayne's only film role (he committed suicide in 1995),Keith Wayne at the ; last accessed June 24, 2006. but Judith Ridley co-starred in Romero's ''There's Always Vanilla'' (1971).Judith Ridley at the ; last accessed June 24, 2006. The cemetery zombie who kills Johnny in the first scene was played by S. William Hinzman, in a role that launched his horror film career. Hinzman was later involved in the films ''Season of the Witch'' (1973), ''Flesheater'' (1988), ''Legion of the Night'' (1995), ''Santa Claws'' (1996), and ''Evil Ambitions'' (1996).S. William Hinzman at the ; last accessed June 24, 2006.

Cast members Karl Hardman, Marilyn Eastman and Russell Streiner performed prominent acting roles. Hardman and Eastman co-starred as Harry and Helen Cooper (Eastman also played the female zombie who plucks an insect off a tree and eats it) while Streiner played Johnny, Barbra's brother. Hardman's 11-year-old daughter, Kyra Schon, played Karen Cooper. Image Ten's production manager, George Kosana, played Sheriff McClelland.Full Cast and Crew for ''Night of the Living Dead'' at the ; last accessed June 24, 2006. Romero's friends and acquaintances were recruited as zombie extras. Romero stated, "We had a film company doing commercials and industrial films so there were a lot of people from the advertising game who all wanted to come out and be zombies, and a lot of them did". He adds amusingly, "Some people from around Evans City who just thought it was a goof came out to get caked in makeup and lumber around".George A. Romero interview, quoted at ; last accessed June 24, 2006.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="55c425d2cae51a53a316614b948a5b0b" name="Duane_Jones_as_Ben_in_Night_of_the_Living_Dead_bw" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/55c425d2cae51a53a316614b948a5b0b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>