<document id="9098410a05683f8373815299ffd2889e-3" name="Night_of_the_Living_Dead" cat="19">
<text>
''Night of the Living Dead'' premiered on October 1, 1968 at the Fulton Theater in Pittsburgh. Nationally, it was shown as a Saturday afternoon matinée — as was typical for horror films at the time — and attracted an audience consisting of pre-teens and adolescents.Stephen King, ''Danse Macabre'' (New York: Berkley Books, 1983), pp. 1–9, ISBN 0-425-10433-8 .Roger Ebert, review of ''Night of the Living Dead'', Chicago ''Sun-Times'', January 5, 196, at ; last accessed June 24, 2006. The MPAA film rating system was not in place until November 1968, so even young children were not prohibited from purchasing tickets. Roger Ebert of the ''Chicago Sun-Times'' chided theater owners and parents who allowed children access to the film. "I don't think the younger kids really knew what hit them," he said. "They were used to going to movies, sure, and they'd seen some horror movies before, sure, but this was something else." According to Ebert, the film affected the audience immediately:




One commentator asserts that the film garnered little attention from critics, "except to provoke argument about censoring its grisly scenes".Higashi, "''Night of the Living Dead''", p. 175. Despite the controversy, five years after the premiere Paul McCullough of ''Take One'' observed that ''Night of the Living Dead'' was the "most profitable horror film ever  produced outside the walls of a major studio".Paul McCullough, "A Pittsburgh Horror Story", ''Take One'' 4 (No. 6, July-August 1973), p. 8. The film had earned between $12 and $15 million at the American box office after a decade. It was translated into more than 25 languages and released across Europe, Canada and Australia. ''Night of the Living Dead'' grossed $30 million internationally, and the ''Wall Street Journal'' reported that it was the top grossing film in Europe in 1969.''Wall Street Journal'' (New York), quoted in Dillard, "''Night of the Living Dead''", p. 15.

''Night of the Living Dead'' was awarded two distinguished honors 30 years after the debut. The Library of Congress added it to the National Film Registry in 1999 with other films deemed "historically, culturally or aesthetically important in any way"."Librarian of Congress Names 25 More Films to National Film Registry", November 16, 1999, at ; last accessed June 24, 2006. In 2001, the American Film Institute named the film to a list of one hundred important horror and thriller films, ''100 Years...100 Thrills''.''AFI's 100 Years...100 Thrills'', at ; last accessed June 24, 2006. This film was #9 on Bravo's ''100 Scariest Movie Moments''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f84f9fd33e8e5a5a4cb9b8ed8b7f62fb" name="NightoftheLivingDeadPosterSpanish" sectnum="3#1">../img/f84f9fd33e8e5a5a4cb9b8ed8b7f62fb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>