<document id="90edde4ecc403ea91eaa3443872111dc-8" name="Mangalore" cat="11">
<text>
The pre-collegiate medium of instruction in schools is predominantly Kannada, while English and Kannada are predominant languages in private schools. Additionally, other media of instruction exist in Mangalore. The medium of instruction in educational institutions after matriculation in colleges is English. Recently, a committee of experts constituted by the Tulu Sahitya Academy recommended the inclusion of Tulu (in Kannada script) as a medium of instruction in education.

Schools and colleges in Mangalore are either government-run or run by private trusts and individuals. The schools are affiliated with either the Karnataka State Board, Indian Certificate of Secondary Education (ICSE), or the Central Board for Secondary Education (CBSE) boards. After completing 10 years of schooling in secondary education, students enroll in Higher Secondary School, specializing in one of the three streams – Arts, Commerce or Science. Since the 1980s, there have been a large number of professional institutions established in a variety of fields including engineering, medicine, dentistry, business management and hotel management. The earliest schools established in Mangalore were the Basel Evangelical School (1838) and Milagres School (1848). The Kasturba Medical College established in 1953, was India's first private medical college. Popular educational institutions in the city are  National Institute of Technology (Karnataka), KS Hegde Medical Academy,Father Muller Medical College, St. Aloysius College, Canara College,Canara Engineering College, S.D.M. College and St. Joseph Engineering College. The Bibliophile's Paradise, a hi-tech public library run by the Corporation Bank, is located at Mannagudda in Mangalore. Mangalore University was established on September 10, 1980. It caters to the higher educational needs of Dakshina Kannada, Udupi and Kodagu districts and is a National Assessment and Accreditation Council (NAAC) accredited four-star level institution.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="be55c1037bdebe7847a618f13095949d" name="NITK_mangalore" sectnum="8#1">../img/be55c1037bdebe7847a618f13095949d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>