<document id="90edde4ecc403ea91eaa3443872111dc-10" name="Mangalore" cat="11">
<text>
Major national English language newspapers such as ''The New Indian Express'', ''The Hindu'', ''Times of India'' and ''Deccan Herald'' publish localised Mangalore editions. The ''Madipu'', ''Mogaveera'', ''Samparka'' and ''Saphala'' are well-known Tulu periodicals in Mangalore. Popular Konkani language periodicals published in the city are ''Rakno'', ''Konknni Dirvem'' and ''Kannik''. Beary periodicals like ''Jyothi'' and ''Swatantra Bharata'' are also published from Mangalore. Among Kannada newspapers, ''Udayavani'', ''Vijaya Karnataka'', ''Prajavani'', ''Kannada Prabha'' and ''Varthabharathi'' are popular. Evening newspapers such as ''Karavali Ale'', ''Mangalooru Mitra'', ''Sanjevani'', and ''Jayakirana'' are also published in the city. The first Kannada language newspaper ''Mangalore Samachara'' was published from Mangalore in 1843.

The state run, nationally broadcast Doordarshan provides both national and localised television coverage. Cable television also provides broadcast cable channels of independently owned private networks. Canara Tv transmits daily video news channels from Mangalore. Mangalore is not covered by the Conditional access system (CAS); however, a proposal to provide CAS to television viewers in Mangalore sometime in the future has been initiated by V4 Media, the local cable service provider. Direct-to-Home (DTH) services, although nascent, are available in Mangalore via Dish TV, Sun Direct and Tata Sky. All India Radio (AIR) has a studio at Kadri that airs program during scheduled hours. Mangalore's private FM stations include Radio Mirchi 98.3 FM, Big 92.7 FM, Superhitz 93.5 FM and 94.3 Century FM.

Mangalore is home to the Tulu Film Industry, which has a catalogue of 31 films, and releases one film annually, on average. Popular Tulu films are ''Kadala Mage'' and ''Suddha''. Tulu dramas, mostly played in the Town Hall at Hampankatta, are very popular. In 2006, a Tulu film festival was organized in Mangalore.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5723e3d67c37fa749ba098775731b26b" name="AIR_FM_Tower_Mangalore_0203" sectnum="10#1">../img/5723e3d67c37fa749ba098775731b26b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>