<document id="90edde4ecc403ea91eaa3443872111dc-1" name="Mangalore" cat="11">
<text>
Mangalore was named after the local Hindu deity Mangaladevi, the presiding deity of the Mangaladevi temple. According to local legend, Matsyendranath, the founder of the Nath tradition, arrived in the area with a princess from Kerala named Parimala or Premaladevi. Having converted Premaladevi to the Nath sect, Matsyendranath renamed her ''Mangaladevi''. After her death, the Mangaladevi temple was consecrated in her honour at Bolar in Mangalore. The city got its name from the Mangaladevi temple.

One of the earliest references to the city's name was made in 715 CE by the Pandyan King Chettian, who called the city ''Managalapuram''. The 11th-century Arabian traveler Ibn Battuta referred to Mangalore as ''Manjarur'' in his chronicles. In Kannada, the city is called ''Mangal큰ru'', a reference to Mangaladevi (the suffix ''큰ru'' means ''town'' or ''city'' in Kannada). During the British occupation in 1799, ''Mangalore'' (anglicized from ''Mangal큰ru''), stuck as the official appellation. However, according to Mangalorean Historian George M. Moraes, the word "Mangalore" is the Portuguese corruption  of ''Mangal큰ru''.

Mangalore's diverse communities have different names for the city in their languages. In Tulu, the primary spoken language, the city is called ''Kudla'' meaning ''junction'', since the city is situated at the confluence of the Netravati and Phalguni rivers. In Konkani, Mangalore is referred to as ''Kodial''. The Beary name for the city is ''Maikala'', meaning ''wood charcoal'', an attribution to the early practice of producing charcoal from wood on the banks of the Netravati river. On the occasion of ''Suvarna Karnataka'' (Golden Karnataka) in 2006, the Government of Karnataka stated that the city would be renamed ''Mangalooru'', though this change in name is not implemented.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="80f00f5a751976780a3db66daad5561c" name="Mangaladevi_(Commons)" sectnum="1#1">../img/80f00f5a751976780a3db66daad5561c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>