<document id="90edde4ecc403ea91eaa3443872111dc-3" name="Mangalore" cat="11">
<text>
Mangalore is located at  in the Dakshina Kannada district of Karnataka. It has an average elevation of  above mean sea level. It is the administrative headquarters of the Dakshina Kannada district, the largest urban coastal center of Karnataka, and the fourth largest city in the state. Mangalore is situated on the west coast of India, and is bounded by Arabian Sea to its west and the Western Ghats to its east. Mangalore city, as a municipal entity, spans an area of . Mangalore experiences moderate to gusty winds during day time and gentle winds at night. The topography of the city ranges from plain to undulating, with several hills, valleys and flat areas within the city. The geology of the city is characterized by hard laterite in hilly tracts and sandy soil along the seashore. The Geological Survey of India has identified Mangalore as a moderately earthquake-prone urban centre and categorized the city in the Seismic III Zone.

Mangalore lies on the backwaters of the Netravati and Gurupura rivers. These rivers effectively encircle the city, with the Netravti flowing at the south of the city, and the Gurupura flowing at the north of the city. The rivers form an estuary at the southern region of the city and subsequently  flow into the Arabian sea. The city is often used as a staging point for traffic along the Malabar Coast. The coastline of the city is dotted with several beaches, such as Mukka, Panambur, Tannirbavi, Suratkal, and Someshwara. Coconut trees, palm trees, and Ashoka trees comprise the primary vegetation of the city.


Mangalore has a tropical climate; summer and winter months experience similar temperate conditions, with average temperatures ranging from  to . Humidity is approximately 78% on average, and peaks during May, June and July. The maximum average humidity is 93% in July and average minimum humidity is 56% in January. Under the Köppen climate classification, Mangalore has a Tropical monsoon climate and is under the direct influence of the Arabian Sea branch of the South-West monsoon. It receives about 90% of its total annual rainfall within a period of about six months from May to October, while remaining extremely dry from December to March. The annual precipitation in Mangalore is .

The most pleasant months in Mangalore are from December to February, during which time the humidity and heat are at their lowest. During this period, temperatures during the day stay below  and drop to about  at night. This season is soon followed by a hot summer, from March to May, when temperatures rise as high as . The summer gives way to the monsoon season, when the city experiences more precipitation than most urban centres in India, due to the Western Ghats. Rainfall up to  could be recorded during the period from June to September. The rains subside in September, with the occasional rainfall in October.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1b772a792e1c2991f493a612370b64fa" name="Panamburbeach057" sectnum="3#1">../img/1b772a792e1c2991f493a612370b64fa.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>