<document id="90edde4ecc403ea91eaa3443872111dc-5" name="Mangalore" cat="11">
<text>
Mangalore has a population of 398,745 per the 2001 census of India. The urban area has a population of 538,560, while the metropolitan area has a population of 419,306 (2001). According to World Gazetteer, Mangalore's estimated population in 2008 was 431,976, making it the 101st most populous city in India. As of the same extrapolations, the World Gazetteer estimated the population of the Mangalore urban area to be 603,269, making it the 61st most populated urban area in India. The number of males was 200,234, constituting 50% of the population, while the number of females were 198,511. The decadal growth rate was 45.90. Male literacy was 86%, while female literacy was 79%. About 6% population was under six years of age. Mangalore's literacy rate is 83% &ndash; significantly higher than the national average of 59.5%.  Birth rate was 13.72%, while death rate and infant mortality rate were at 3.71% and 1.24% respectively. The Mangalore urban area had 32 recognised slums, and nearly 22,000 migrant labourers lived in slums within the city limits. According to the ''Crime Review Report'' (2006) by the Dakshina Kannada Police, Mangalore registered a drop in the crime rate in 2005, compared with 2003.

The four main languages in Mangalore are Tulu, Konkani, Kannada, and Beary with Tulu language being the mother tongue of the majority. Malayalam, Hindi, Urdu and English are also spoken in the city. A resident of Mangalore is known as a ''Mangalorean'' in English, ''Kudladaru'' in Tulu, ''Kodialgharano'' in Catholic Konkani, ''Kodialchi'' or ''Manglurchi'' in Goud Saraswat Brahmin Konkani, ''Manglurnavaru'' in Kannada, and ''Maikaaltanga'' in Beary. Hinduism is followed by a large number of the population, with Mogaveeras, Billavas, Ganigas and Bunts forming the largest groups. Kota Brahmins, Shivalli Brahmins, Sthanika Brahmins, Havyaka Brahmins, Goud Saraswat Brahmins (GSBs), Daivajna brahmins, and Rajapur Saraswat Brahmins also form considerable sections of the Hindu population. Christians form a sizable section of Mangalorean society, with Konkani-speaking Catholics, popularly known as Mangalorean Catholics, accounting for the largest Christian community. Protestants in Mangalore known as Mangalorean Protestants typically speak Tulu or Kannada. Most Muslims in Mangalore are Bearys, who speak a dialect called Beary bashe. There is also a sizeable group of landowners following Jainism.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5fc8b4e35632dcfe3465c9da71647f71" name="St._Aloyscus_Church_Mangalore" sectnum="5#1">../img/5fc8b4e35632dcfe3465c9da71647f71.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>