<document id="9153a0666f7172ff17b5a5f89d9d9e88-5" name="Capture_of_Fort_Ticonderoga" cat="29">
<text>
Ethan Allen and his men eventually drifted away from Ticonderoga, especially once the alcohol began to run out, and Arnold largely controlled affairs from a base at Crown Point.J. Nelson (2006), p. 53  He oversaw the fitting of the two large ships, eventually taking command of ''Enterprise'' due to a lack of knowledgeable seamen.  His men began rebuilding Ticonderoga's barracks, and worked to extract armaments from the rubble of the two forts and build gun carriages for them.

Connecticut sent about 1,000 men under Colonel Benjamin Hinman to hold Ticonderoga, and New York also began to raise militia to defend Crown Point and Ticonderoga against a possible British attack from the north.  When Hinman's troops arrived in June, there was once again a clash over leadership.  None of the communications to Arnold from the Massachusetts committee indicated that he was to serve under Hinman; when Hinman attempted to assert authority over Crown Point, Arnold refused to accept it, as Hinman's instructions only included Ticonderoga.J. Nelson (2006), p. 61  The Massachusetts committee eventually sent a delegation to Ticonderoga.  When they arrived on June 22 they made it clear to Arnold that he was to serve under Hinman.  Arnold, after considering for two days, disbanded his command, resigned his commission, and went home, having spent more than £1,000 of his own money in the effort to capture the fort.Randall (1990), pp. 128–129


Congress, when it received news of the events, drafted a second letter to the inhabitants of Quebec, which was sent north in June with James Price, another sympathetic Montreal merchant.  This letter, and other communications from the New York Congress, combined with the activities of vocal American supporters, stirred up the Quebec population in the summer of 1775.Lanctot (1967), pp. 55–60

When news of the fall of Ticonderoga reached England, Lord Dartmouth wrote that it was "very unfortunate; very unfortunate indeed".Jellison (1969), p. 120
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a2207a15700bd376b81497362620f741" name="Ruins_of_Fort_Frederick_Crown_Point_N.Y" sectnum="5#1">../img/a2207a15700bd376b81497362620f741.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>