<document id="9153a0666f7172ff17b5a5f89d9d9e88-5.4" name="Capture_of_Fort_Ticonderoga" cat="29">
<text>
Beginning on the day of the fort's capture, Allen and Arnold began a war of words, each attempting to garner for himself as much credit for the operation as possible.  Arnold, unable to exert any authority over Allen and his men, began to keep a diary of events and actions, which was highly critical and dismissive of Allen.  Allen, in the days immediately after the action, also began to work on a memoir. Published several years later (see Further reading), the memoir fails to mention Arnold at all.  Allen also wrote several versions of the events, which John Brown and James Easton, one of the Connecticut men, brought to a variety of Congresses and committees in New York, Connecticut, and Massachusetts.  Randall (1990) claims that Easton took accounts written by both Arnold and Allen to the Massachusetts committee, but conveniently lost Arnold's account on the way, ensuring that Allen's version, which greatly glorified his role in the affair, would be preferred.Randall (1990), p. 99  Smith (1907) indicates that it was highly likely that Easton was interested in claiming Arnold's command for himself.Smith (1907), p. 184  There was clearly no love lost between Easton and Arnold. Allen and Easton returned to Crown Point on June 10 and called a council of war while Arnold was with the fleet on the lake, a clear breach of military protocol.  When Arnold, whose men now dominated the garrison, asserted his authority, Easton insulted Arnold, who responded by challenging Easton to a duel. Arnold later reported, "On refusing to draw like a gentleman, he having a  by his side and cases of loaded pistols in his pockets, I kicked him very heartily and ordered him from the Point."Randall (1990), p. 121
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e80b99236d1b66ce23e6401aaef82882" name="Benedict_arnold_illustration" sectnum="5.4#1">../img/e80b99236d1b66ce23e6401aaef82882.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>