<document id="9153a0666f7172ff17b5a5f89d9d9e88-2" name="Capture_of_Fort_Ticonderoga" cat="29">
<text>
Arnold departed immediately after receiving his instructions.  He was accompanied by two captains, Eleazer Oswald and Jonathan Brown, who were charged with raising the necessary men.  Arnold reached the border between Massachusetts and the Grants on May 6,  where he learned of the recruitment efforts of the Connecticut Committee, and that Ethan Allen and the Green Mountain Boys were already on their way north.  Riding furiously northward (his horse was subsequently destroyed), he reached Allen's headquarters in Bennington the next day.Randall (1990), p. 86–89  Upon arrival, Arnold was told that Allen was in Castleton, fifty miles to the north, awaiting supplies and more men.  He was also warned that, while Allen's effort had no official sanction, his men were unlikely to serve under anyone else.  Leaving early the next day, Arnold arrived in Castleton in time to join a war council, where he made a case to lead the expedition based on his formal authorization to act from the Massachusetts Committee.Randall (1990), p. 90

The force that Allen had assembled in Castleton included about 100 Green Mountain Boys, about 40 men raised by James Easton and John Brown at Pittsfield, Massachusetts, and an additional 20 men from Connecticut.Smith (1907), pp. 124–125  Allen was elected colonel, with Easton and Seth Warner as his lieutenants.  When Arnold arrived on the scene, Samuel Herrick had been sent to Skenesboro and Asa Douglas to Panton with detachments to secure boats. Captain Noah Phelps, a member of the "Committee of War for the Expedition against Ticonderoga and Crown Point", had reconnoitered the fort disguised as a peddler seeking a shave. He saw that the fort walls were dilapidated, learned from the garrison commander that the soldiers' gunpowder was wet, and that they expected reinforcements at any time.Randall (1990), p. 91Phelps (1899), p. 204  He reported this intelligence to Allen, following which they planned a dawn raid.

Many of the Green Mountain Boys objected to Arnold's wish to command, insisting that they would go home rather than serve under anyone other than Ethan Allen. Arnold and Allen worked out an agreement, but no documented evidence exists concerning the deal. According to Arnold, he was given joint command of the operation. Some historians have supported Arnold's contention, while others suggest he was merely given the right to march next to Allen.Pell (1929), p. 81 claims there is no documentary evidence.  Boatner (1974) (pp. 1101–1102) notes that while Ward believes Arnold merely had the right to march next to Allen, Allen French argues otherwise in ''The Taking of Ticonderoga in 1775''. Bellesiles (1995), p. 117 claims that Allen offered Arnold the right to march at the head of the column to placate Arnold.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bfe832c1a5d5ef89145f7933ecfa890d" name="Fort_Ticonderoga,_Ticonderoga,_NY" sectnum="2#1">../img/bfe832c1a5d5ef89145f7933ecfa890d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>