<document id="917c8e96fbaa4c6999a8d530654bcb66-7" name="Roman–Persian_Wars" cat="29">
<text>
The sources for the history of Parthia and the wars with Rome are scant and scattered. The Parthians followed the Achaemenid tradition and favored oral historiography that assured the corruption of their history once they had been vanquished. The main sources of this period are thus Roman (Tacitus, Marius Maximus, and Justin) and Greek historians (Herodian, Cassius Dio and Plutarch). The 13th book of the Sibylline Oracles narrates the effects of the Roman&ndash;Persian Wars in Syria from the reign of Gordian III to the domination of the province by Odaenathus of Palmyra. With the end of Herodian's record we lose all contemporary chronological narratives of Roman history, until the narratives of Lactantius and Eusebius at the beginning of the fourth century, both from a Christian perspective.Dodgeon&ndash;Greatrex&ndash;Lieu (2002), I, 5; Potter (2004), 232&ndash;233 

The principal sources for the early Sassanid period are not contemporary. Among them the most important are the Greeks Agathias and Malalas, the Persians Tabari and Ferdowsi, the Armenian Agathangelos, and the Syriac Chronicles of Edessa and Arbela, most of whom depended on late Sassanid sources, especially Khoday Namag. The Augustan History is neither contemporary nor reliable, but it is the chief narrative source we have for Severus and Carus. The trilingual (Greek, Parthian, and Middle Persian) inscriptions of Shapur are prime sources.Frye (2005), 461&ndash;463; Shahbazi,  These were isolated attempts at approaching written historiography however, and by the end of the fourth century AD, even the practice of carving rock reliefs and leaving short inscriptions was abandoned by the Sassanids.Shahbazi, 

For the period between 353 and 378, there is an eyewitness source to the main events on the eastern frontier in the ''Res Gestae'' of Ammianus Marcellinus. For the events covering the period between the fourth and the sixth century, the works of Sozomenus, Zosimus, Priscus, and Zonaras are especially valuable.Dodgeon&ndash;Greatrex&ndash;Lieu (2002), I, 7 Theophylact Simocatta is the main source for the reign of Maurice,Boyd (1999), 160 while Theophanes, Chronicon Paschale and the poems of George of Pisidia are useful sources for the last Roman&ndash;Persian war. In addition to Byzantine sources, two Armenian historians, Sebeos and Movses, contribute to the coherent narrative of Heraclius' war and are regarded by Howard-Johnston as "the most important of extant non-Muslim sources".Howard-Johnston (2006), 42&ndash;43
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c216a83f3ef99ff588f84382331a529d" name="HumiliationValerianusHolbein" sectnum="7#1">../img/c216a83f3ef99ff588f84382331a529d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>