<document id="917c8e96fbaa4c6999a8d530654bcb66-3.5" name="Roman–Persian_Wars" cat="29">
<text>
In 524&ndash;525 AD, Kavadh proposed that Justin I adopt his son, Khosrau, but the negotiations soon broke down.Procopius, ''Wars'', I.11.23&ndash;30* Greatrex (2005), 487; Greatrex&ndash;Lieu (2002), II, 81&ndash;82 Tensions between the two powers erupted into conflict when Iberia under King Gourgen defected to the Romans in 524&ndash;525.Greatrex&ndash;Lieu (2002), II, 82 Overt Roman&ndash;Persian fighting had broken out in the Transcaucasus region and upper Mesopotamia by 526&ndash;527.Greatrex&ndash;Lieu (2002), II, 84 The early years of war favored the Persians: by 527, the Iberian revolt had been crushed, a Roman offensive against Nisibis and Thebetha in that year was unsuccessful, and forces trying to fortify Thannuris and Melabasa were prevented from doing so by Persian attacks.Zacharias Rhetor, ''Historia Ecclesiastica'', IX, 2* Greatrex&ndash;Lieu (2002), II, 83, 86 Attempting to remedy the deficiencies revealed by these Persian successes, the new Roman emperor, Justinian I, reorganized the eastern armies.Greatrex&ndash;Lieu (2002), II, 85



In 530 a major Persian offensive in Mesopotamia was defeated by Roman forces under Belisarius at Dara, while a second Persian thrust in the Caucasus was defeated by Sittas at Satala. Belisarius was defeated by Persian and Lakhmid forces at the Battle of Callinicum in 531. In the same year the Romans gained some forts in Armenia, while the Persians had captured two forts in eastern Lazica.Greatrex&ndash;Lieu (2002), II, 92&ndash;96 Immediately after the failure at Callinicum the Persians and Romans negotiated without success.Greatrex&ndash;Lieu (2002), II, 93 The two sides re-opened talks in spring 532 and finally signed the Eternal Peace in September 532, which lasted less than eight years. Both powers agreed to return all occupied territories, and the Romans agreed to make a one-time payment of 110 ''centenaria'' (11,000 lbs of gold). Iberia remained in Persian hands, and the Iberians who had left their country were given the choice of remaining in Roman territory or returning to their native land.Evans (2000), 118; Greatrex&ndash;Lieu (2002), II, 96&ndash;97
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e12eca6f22a371866a00e534173bf09b" name="Roman-Empire_477ad" sectnum="3.5#1">../img/e12eca6f22a371866a00e534173bf09b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>