<document id="917c8e96fbaa4c6999a8d530654bcb66-3.7" name="Roman–Persian_Wars" cat="29">
<text>
War broke out again when Armenia and Iberia revolted against Sassanid rule in 571 AD, following clashes involving Roman and Persian proxies in Yemen and the Syrian desert, and Roman negotiations for an alliance with the Turks against Persia.John of Epiphania, ''History'', , gives an additional for the outbreak of the war: " contentiousness increased even further  when Justin did not deem to pay the Medians the five hundred pounds of gold each year previously agreed to under the peace treaties and let the Roman State remain forever a tributary of the Persians." See also, Greatrex (2005), 503&ndash;504 Justin II brought Armenia under his protection, while Roman troops under Justin's nephew Marcian raided Arzanene and invaded Persian Mesopotamia, where they defeated local forces.Treadgold (1997), 222 Marcian's sudden dismissal and the arrival of troops under Khosrau resulted in a ravaging of Syria, the failure of the Roman siege of Nisibis and the fall of Dara.The great bastion of the Roman frontier was in Persian hands for the first time (Whitby , 92&ndash;94). At a cost of 45,000 ''solidi'', a one-year truce in Mesopotamia (eventually extended to five years)Greatrex&ndash;Lieu (2002), II, 152; Louth (2005), 113 was arranged, but in the Caucasus and on the desert frontiers the war continued.Theophanes, ''Chronicle'', 246.11&ndash;27* Whitby (2000), 92&ndash;94 In 576, Khosrau I attempted to combine aggression in Armenia with discussion of a permanent peace. He invaded Anatolia and sacked Sebasteia, but after a clash near Melitene the Persian army suffered heavy losses while fleeing across the Euphrates under Roman attack.Theophylact, ''History'', I,  (PDF) Treadgold (1997), 224; Whitby (2000), 95 


The Romans exploited Persian disarray by invading deep into Persian territory and raiding Atropatene. Khosrau sought peace, but abandoned this initiative after Tamkhusro won a victory in Armenia, where Roman actions had alienated local inhabitants.Treadgold (1997), 224; Whitby (2000), 95&ndash;96 In the spring of 578 the war in Mesopotamia resumed with Persian raids on Roman territory. The Roman general Maurice retaliated by raiding Persian Mesopotamia, capturing the stronghold of Aphumon, and sacking Singara. Khosrau again opened peace negotiations but he died early in 579 and his successor Hormizd IV preferred to continue the war.Soward,  (PDF); Treadgold (1997), 225; Whitby (2000), 96 


During the 580s, the war continued inconclusively with victories on both sides. In 582, Maurice won a battle at Constantia over Adarmahan and Tamkhusro, who was killed, but the Roman general did not follow up his victory; he had to hurry to Constantinople to pursue his imperial ambitions.Soward,  (PDF); Treadgold (1997), 226; Whitby (2000), 96 

The Persians captured Martyropolis through treachery in 589, but that year the stalemate was shattered when the Persian general Bahram Chobin, having been dismissed and humiliated by Hormizd IV, raised a rebellion. Hormizd was overthrown in a palace coup in 590 and replaced by his son Khosrau II, but Bahram pressed on with his revolt regardless and the defeated Khosrau was soon forced to flee for safety to Roman territory, while Bahram took the throne as Bahram VI. With support from Maurice, Khosrau raised a rebellion against Bahram, and in 591 the combined forces of his supporters and the Romans restored Khosrau II to power. In exchange for their help, Khosrau not only returned Dara and Martyropolis but also agreed to cede the western half of Iberia and more than half of Persian Armenia to the Romans.Theophylact, V, ''History'', I,  (PDF) and  (PDF)* Louth (2005), 115; Treadgold (1997), 231&ndash;232
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b3d393a7359abdb78f1a97209b7a4cc2" name="Persia_600ad" sectnum="3.7#1">../img/b3d393a7359abdb78f1a97209b7a4cc2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>