<document id="917c8e96fbaa4c6999a8d530654bcb66-3.3" name="Roman–Persian_Wars" cat="29">
<text>
Conflict resumed shortly after the overthrow of Parthian rule and Ardashir I's foundation of the Sassanid empire. Ardashir raided Mesopotamia and Syria in 230 AD and demanded the cession of all the former territories of the Achaemenid Empire.Herodian, ''Roman History'', VI, ; Cassius Dio, ''Roman History'', LXXX, * Dodgeon&ndash;Greatrex&ndash;Lieu (2002), I, 16 After fruitless negotiations, Alexander Severus set out against Ardashir in 232 and finally repulsed him.Herodian, ''Roman History'', VI, * Dodgeon&ndash;Greatrex&ndash;Lieu (2002), I, 24&ndash;28; Frye (1993), 124 In 238&ndash;240, towards the end of his reign, Ardashir attacked again, taking several cities in Syria and Mesopotamia, including Carrhae and Nisibis.Frye (1993), 124&ndash;125; Southern (2001), 234&ndash;235 The struggle resumed and intensified under Ardashir's successor Shapur I, who invaded Mesopotamia. His forces were defeated at a battle near Resaena in 243 and the Romans regained Carrhae and Nisibis.Frye (1993), 125 Encouraged by this, the Roman Emperor Gordian III advanced down the Euphrates but was repelled near Ctesiphon at the Battle of Misiche in 244.Aurelius Victor, ''Liber de Caesaribus'', 27.; Sibylline Oracles, XIII, * Frye (1993), 125; Southern (2001), 235 

In the early 250s, the emperor Philip was involved in a struggle over the control of Armenia. Shapur had the Armenian king murdered and re-opened hostilities against the Romans, defeating them at the Battle of Barbalissos, and then probably taking and plundering Antioch.Frye (1993), 125; Southern (2001), 235&ndash;236 Between 258 and 260, Shapur captured the Emperor Valerian I after defeating his army at the Battle of Edessa, and advanced into Anatolia. However, defeats at the hands of Roman forces there and attacks from Odaenathus of Palmyra forced the Persians to withdraw from Roman territory.Lactantius, ''De Mortibus Persecutorum'', ; Sibylline Oracles, XIII, * Frye (1993), 126; Southern (2001), 238


The Emperor Carus launched a successful invasion of Persia in 283, sacking Ctesiphon, the Sassanid capital. The Romans would probably have extended their conquests if Carus had not died in December of that year.Aurelius Victor, ''Liber de Caesaribus'', 38.; Eutropius, ''Abridgment of Roman History'', IX, * Frye (1993), 128; Southern (2001), 241 
After a brief peace early in Diocletian's reign, the Persians renewed hostilities when they invaded Armenia and defeated the Romans outside Carrhae in either 296 or 297.Frye (1993), 130; Southern (2001), 242 However, Galerius crushed the Persians in battle in 298, capturing the treasury and the royal harem, an utter disgrace for the Persian monarch. The resulting peace settlement gave the Romans control of the area between the Tigris and the Greater Zab. This was the most decisive Roman victory for many decades; all the territories that had been lost, all the debatable lands, and control of Armenia lay in Roman hands.Aurelius Victor, ''Liber de Caesaribus'', 39.; Eutropius, ''Abridgment of Roman History'', IX, * Frye (1993), 130&ndash;131; Southern (2001), 243

The arrangements of 299 lasted until the mid-330s, when Shapur II began a series of offensives against the Romans. Despite a string of victories in battle, his campaigns achieved little lasting effect: three Persian sieges of Nisibis were repulsed, and while Shapur succeeded in taking Amida and Singara, both cities were soon regained by the Romans. Following a lull during the 350s while Shapur fought off nomad attacks on Persia's northern frontier, he launched a new campaign in 359 and again captured Amida. This provoked a major offensive in 363 by the Roman Emperor Julian, who advanced down the Euphrates to Ctesiphon.Frye (1993), 137 Julian won the Battle of Ctesiphon but was unable to take the Persian capital and retreated along the Tigris. Harried by the Persians, Julian was killed in a skirmish. With the Roman army stuck on the eastern bank of the Euphrates, Julian's successor Jovian made peace, agreeing major concessions in exchange for safe passage out of Sassanid territory. The Romans surrendered their former possessions east of the Tigris, as well as Nisibis and Singara, and Shapur soon conquered Armenia.Frye (1993), 138 In 384, a definitive peace treaty was signed by Shapur III and Theodosius I, which divided Armenia between the two states. Meanwhile, the northern territories of the Roman empire were invaded by Germanic, Alanic, and Hunnic peoples, while Persia's northern borders were threatened by Hephthalites. With both empires preoccupied by these threats, a largely peaceful period followed, interrupted only by two brief wars, the first in 421&ndash;422 and the second in 440.Bury (1923), ; Frye (1993), 145; Greatrex-Lieu (2002), II, 37&ndash;51
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7a18acf520c0549406c3d637d4a55bf5" name="Bas_relief_nagsh-e-rostam_al" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/7a18acf520c0549406c3d637d4a55bf5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>