<document id="919a312983a42b0b6a7d0f29ca09e757-2.4" name="Her_Majesty's_Theatre" cat="17">
<text>
The theatre was designed as a symmetrical pair with the Carlton Hotel and restaurant on the adjacent site, now occupied by New Zealand House.The Carlton Hotel, opened in 1899 by the chef Auguste Escoffier and hotelier César Ritz after they left the Savoy Hotel, introduced the ''à la carte menu''. The frontage formed three parts, each of nine bays. The hotel occupied two parts, the theatre one, and the two buildings were unified by a cornice above the ground floor. The buildings rose to four storeys, with attic floors above, surmounted by large squared domes in a style inspired by the French Renaissance. The theatre has a Corinthian colonnade at the first floor, rising to the second, forming a loggia in front of the circle foyer. This is above a canopy over the main ground floor entrances. The theatre lies on an east–west axis. The stage at the western end was  deep and  wide, and reputedly the first to be flat, rather than raked. The interior was designed by the consulting architect, W. H. Romaine-Walker (1854–1940), after the Opera at Versailles by Gabriel. Stalls and the pit were entered at ground level, with two partly cantilevered tiers above accommodating dress and family circles on the first level, and upper circle, amphitheatre and gallery on the tier above. In all, there were 1,319 seats. Contemporary opinion was critical of the project. Edwin Sachs wrote in his 1897 guide to theatres, "The treatment is considered to be in the French Renaissance style and stone has been used throughout. The detail cannot, however, be termed satisfactory, nor does the exterior architecturally express the purpose of the building."Sachs, Edwin O. ''Modern Opera Houses and Theatres'' vol. ii, p. 36 (London, 1897) (Reprint Ayer Co Pub., 1968) ISBN 0405089066

Modern opinion of the theatre is more generous, with English Heritage describing the building as both Phipps' finest work and one of the best planned theatres in London. The building was Grade II* listed in January 1970. Appreciation of the buildings came too late to save the adjacent hotel from redevelopment as the new High Commission for New Zealand, completed in 1963 by British architects Robert Matthew, Johnson Marshall and Partners, who also designed the Commonwealth Institute. In 1995, this too was Grade II listed as a fine example of 1960s architecture. The 20th century Society, accessed 31 January 2008 The 200-year-old Royal Opera Arcade, built by Nash and Repton, is all that survives of the second theatre and is the earliest example of a London arcade.Jones, Edward, and Christopher Woodward. ''A Guide to the Architecture of London'' (London: Weidenfeld and Nicolson, 1992) ISBN 1841880124
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="97a1dab748d45d3ca64d1921300e2637" name="her.majestys.theatre.london.arp" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/97a1dab748d45d3ca64d1921300e2637.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>