<document id="919a312983a42b0b6a7d0f29ca09e757-1" name="Her_Majesty's_Theatre" cat="17">
<text>
The end of the 17th century was a period of intense rivalry amongst London's actors, and in 1695 there was a split in the United Company, who had a monopoly on the performance of drama at their two theatres. Dramatist and architect John Vanbrugh saw this as an opportunity to break the duopoly of the patent theatres, and in 1703 he acquired a former stable yard, at a cost of £2000, for the construction of a new theatre on the Haymarket. In the new business, he hoped to improve the share of profits that would go to playwrights and actors. He raised the money by subscription, probably amongst members of the Kit-Cat Club:
To recover them , therefore, to their due Estimation, a new Project was form'd of building them a stately theatre in the Hay-Market, by Sir John Vanbrugh, for which he raised a Subscription of thirty Persons of Quality, at one hundred Pounds each, in Consideration whereof every Subscriber, for his own Life, was to be admitted to whatever Entertainments should be publickly perform'd there, without farther Payment for his Entrance.—John Vanbrugh's notice of subscription for the new theatre, accessed 18 December 2007 He was joined in the enterprise by his principal associate and manager William Congreve and an actors' co-operative led by Thomas Betterton.Downes, Kerry. ''Sir John Vanbrugh: A Biography'' (London: Sidgwick and Jackson 1987) ISBN 0-283-99497-5 

The theatre provided the first alternative to the Theatre Royal, Drury Lane, built in 1663 and the Lincoln's Inn, founded in 1660 (forerunner of the Theatre Royal, Covent Garden, built in 1728). The theatre's site is the second oldest such site in London that remains in use. These three post-interregnum theatres defined the shape and use of modern theatres.Earl, John and Michael Sell. ''Guide to British Theatres 1750–1950'', p. 117 (Theatres Trust, 2000) ISBN 0-7136-5688-3. Sadler's Wells Theatre was founded as a music room in 1683, and a theatre was built on the site in 1765.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d1311b5ff3a14c19c56345d694cbf0df" name="John_Vanbrugh" sectnum="1#1">../img/d1311b5ff3a14c19c56345d694cbf0df.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>