<document id="92416f269ed8cfdc68a4ba246c06b939-6.1" name="Amchitka" cat="11">
<text>
A few days after the ''Milrow'' test, the Don't Make A Wave Committee was organized at a meeting in Vancouver. On the agenda was whether to fight another blast at the island, or whether to expand their efforts to fight all perceived threats against the environment. As he was leaving, one man gave the traditional farewell of the peace-activist movement, "Peace." "Make it a green peace." replied another member. The Committee would later become Greenpeace.The Greenpeace Story in: 

The Committee's name referred to predictions made by a Vancouver journalist named Bob Hunter, later to become Greenpeace member 000. He wrote that the test would cause earthquakes and a tsunami. The AEC considered the likelihood of the test triggering a severe earthquake "very unlikely", unless one was already imminent on a nearby fault, and considered a tsunami "even more unlikely".

Others disagreed. Russell Train, then Chairman of the Council on Environmental Quality, argued that "experience with ''Milrow'' ... does not provide a sure basis for extrapolation. In the highly nonlinear phenomena involved in earthquake generation, there may be a threshold value of the strain that must be exceeded prior to initiation of a large earthquake. ... The underground explosion could serve as the first domino of the row of dominoes leading to a major earthquake. ... as in the case of earthquakes it is not possible at this time to assess quantitatively the probability of a tsunami following the explosion."



In July 1971, a group called the ''Committee for Nuclear Responsibility'' filed suit against the AEC, asking the court to stop the test. The suit was unsuccessful, with the Supreme Court denying the injunction by 4 votes to 3, and Richard Nixon personally authorized the $200 million test, in spite of objections from Japan, Peru, and Sweden. The ''Don't Make A Wave Committee'' chartered a boat, in which they had intended to sail to the island in protest, but due to weather conditions they were unable to reach their destination.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="cb6ed68348bf8bfcc3337cd0d3a97983" name="Cannikin_test_stills" sectnum="6.1#1">../img/cb6ed68348bf8bfcc3337cd0d3a97983.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>