<document id="926940896fa0910af77989b5093a8023-3" name="Omaha_Beach" cat="29">
<text>
An officer anxiously observes Omaha Beach as his landing craft approaches the Norman coast.

With the initial assault missions unaccomplished the second and larger wave of assault landings, designed to bring in reinforcements, support weapons and headquarter elements, started coming ashore at 07:00 to similar conditions experienced by the first. Some relief against the largely unsuppressed defensive fire was gained simply by virtue of the fact that with more troops landing the concentration of fire was spread more about the many targets available. The survivors amongst the initial forces were not, however, able to give much covering fire, and the landing troops still suffered in places the same high casualty rates as those in the first wave. The failure to clear sufficient paths through the beach obstacles added to the difficulties of the second wave now that the tide was beginning to cover those obstacles. The loss of landing craft as they hit these defenses before they reached the shore began to feature in the rate of attrition. As in the initial landings, difficulties in navigation and the consequent mis-landings proved most disruptive, serving to scatter the infantry and to separate headquarters elements from their units.

On the 116th RCT front the remainder of the 1st battalion; B/116, C/116 and D/116, were due to land in support of A/116 at Dog Green. Three boats carrying the battalion’s headquarters elements and Dog Green beach master group landed too far west, under the cliffs. There are no exact details of the casualties they took getting across the beach, but the one-third to one-half that did make it spent the rest of day pinned down by snipers. Dog Green remained a lethal sector. Not all sections of the badly scattered B/116 landed there, but those that did quickly joined the survivors of A/116 in their fight for survival at the water’s edge. Two companies of 2nd Rangers coming in later on the edge of Dog Green did manage to reach the sea wall, but it cost them half their strength to do so.

To the left of Dog Green the Dog White sector sitting between the Vierville and Les Moulins strongpoints (defending the draws codenamed D-1 and D-3 respectively) was a different story. As a result of earlier mis-landings and now because of their own mis-landing, the troops of C/116 found themselves alone there, only a handful of tanks from the first wave in sight. The smoke from the grass fires covered their advance up the beach, and they gained the sea wall with few casualties and in better shape than any unit on the 116th RCT front so far. Whilst the 1st battalion was effectively disarmed of its heavy weapons when D/116 suffered a disastrous landing, the build up at Dog White continued when C/116 was joined by the 5th Ranger battalion pretty much in its entirety. The Ranger commander, recognizing the situation at Dog Green on the run in, ordered the assault craft to divert into Dog White (the 2nd Rangers still got caught out on the right flank of the Ranger landing). This was also the sector where the 116th RCT regimental command group, including the 29th Division assistant commander Brigadier General Norman Cota, was able to land relatively unscathed.

Further east a similar picture of the effectiveness of the strongpoint defenses emerges. On the Dog Red/Easy Green boundary the defenses around the Les Moulins strongpoint took a heavy toll as the remainder of the 2nd battalion; H/116 and headquarters elements, struggled ashore there. The survivors joined the remnants of F/116 behind the shingle where the battalion commander was able to organize 50 men in an improvised advance across the shingle. A further advance up the bluffs just east of Les Moulins was too weak to have any effect and was forced back down. To their left, mainly between the draws on the Easy Green/Easy Red boundary, the 116th RCT support battalion landed without too much loss, though in the process becoming scattered and too disorganized to play any immediate part in an assault against the bluffs.

On the 16th RCT front, the eastern end of Easy Red was another area between strongpoints that allowed G/16 and the support battalion to escape destruction in the advance up the beach. Nevertheless, most of G/16’s 63 casualties for the day were suffered before this company reached the shingle. The other 2nd battalion company landing in the second wave; H/16 came in a few hundred yards to the left opposite the E-3 draw and suffered for it, being put out of action for the next few hours.

The situation on the eastern most beach (Fox Green) where elements of five different companies had become mixed up was little improved by the equally disorganized landings of the second wave. Two more companies of the third battalion joined the melee, and I/16, part of the first wave that had drifted east, finally made a traumatic landing there at 08:00. A captain from this company found himself senior officer in charge of the badly out of shape 3rd battalion.Two of I/16’s six boats were swamped on their detour to the east. As they eventually came in under fire at Fox Green, three of the four remaining boats were damaged by artillery or mines whilst the fourth got hung up on an obstacle.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1433b72b3815784180fe534ccf3d0ad5" name="Omaha_Beach_1944_Second_Assault" sectnum="3#1">../img/1433b72b3815784180fe534ccf3d0ad5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>