<document id="926940896fa0910af77989b5093a8023-4.9" name="Omaha_Beach" cat="29">
<text>
The only artillery support available to the troops in making these tentative advances came from the navy. With targets difficult to spot, and because of the fear of hitting their own troops, the big guns of the battleships and cruisers concentrated on targets at each flank of the Omaha beaches. The destroyers, however, were able to get in close and from 08:00 were engaging their own targets. At 09:50, two minutes after the ''McCook'' destroyed a 75 mm gun position in WN-74, the destroyers were ordered to get as close in as possible. Some approached as close as 1000 yards (900 m) several times, scraping bottom and risking running aground. An engineer who had landed in the first wave at Fox Red watched the ''Frankford'' steaming in to shore, thinking she had been hit and was being subsequently beached. Instead, she turned parallel to the beach and cruised westwards, guns blazing at targets of opportunity. Thinking she was going to turn back out to sea, the engineer realized that she had started to back up, still firing. At one point the gunners aboard the ''Frankford'' observed an immobilized tank at the water’s edge still firing. They watched its fall of shot and followed it up with a salvo of their own. For the next few minutes the tank acted in this manner as the ship’s fire control party. The official history attributes a similar action to the ''Carmick'': “

Later analysis of the naval support provided to the pre-landing phase concluded that there had been inadequate gunfire provided by the navy for the size and extent of the planned assault.  http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USN/rep/Normandy/Cominch/ Amphibious Operations Invasion of Northern France Western Task Force June 1944 Chapter 2-27. From Hyperwar, retrieved 2008-06-04
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="922be0359da2099dca4569a48d5b05a5" name="USS_Frankford_0549703" sectnum="4.9#1">../img/922be0359da2099dca4569a48d5b05a5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>