<document id="927ccb87605fdbc73a6898f423cbc96e-4" name="Second_Ostend_Raid" cat="29">
<text>
Despite German claims that the blockage did not impede their operations, the operation to close the Ostend canal seemed to have been at least partially successful. The channel was largely blocked and so Bruges was ostensibly closed off from the open sea, even if the position of the blockship meant that smaller ships could get through. In fact, however, the entire operation had been rendered moot before it even began, due to events at the wider canal in Zeebrugge. British assessments of that operation had ultimately proven optimistic and the channel there had not been properly closed. Small coastal submarines of the UC Class had been able to pass through the channel as early as the morning after the Zeebrugge Raid and German naval engineers were able to dredge channels around the blockages at both ports over the coming weeks.Tarrant, p.62 

At Ostend, the ''Vindictive'' did prevent larger warships passing through the channel, although smaller craft could still come and go at will. Ultimately, the larger warships in Bruges were trapped there for the remaining months of the war; the town was captured  by the Allies in October 1918. Ultimately the blockages at Ostend and Zeebrugge took several years to clear completely, not being totally removed until 1921. On a strategic scale however, the effects of the raids at Ostend and Zeebrugge on the battle of the Atlantic were negligible. Despite this ultimate failure, in Britain the Ostend Raid was feted as a success. Three Victoria Crosses and a host of lesser awards were given to the men involved. The Admiralty presented it as a fine example of daring and careful planning from the Royal Navy, providing a valuable morale boost at one of the most critical moments of the war.Bennett, p.278
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c5442585634cc81c2d9da63a164a5033" name="Vindictivewreck2" sectnum="4#1">../img/c5442585634cc81c2d9da63a164a5033.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>