<document id="92fdd2ecb9e00982a766e42085dbe674-8" name="Malcolm_X" cat="14">
<text>
After leaving the Nation of Islam, Malcolm X spoke before a wide variety of audiences in the United States. He spoke at regular meetings of Muslim Mosque, Inc., and the Organization of Afro-American Unity. He was one of the most sought-after speakers on college campuses,Terrill, p. 9. and one of his top aides later wrote that he "welcomed every opportunity to speak to college students."Karim, p. 128. Malcolm X also spoke before political groups such as the Militant Labor Forum.Perry, pp. 277–278.

Tensions increased between Malcolm X and the Nation of Islam. As early as February 1964, a member of Temple Number Seven was given orders by the Nation of Islam to wire explosives to Malcolm X's car.Karim, pp. 159–160. On March 20, 1964, ''Life'' published a photograph of Malcolm X holding an M1 Carbine and peering out a window. The photo was intended to illustrate his determination to defend himself and his family against the death threats he was receiving.


The Nation of Islam and its leaders began making threats against Malcolm X both in private and in public. On March 23, 1964, Elijah Muhammad told Boston minister Louis X (later known as Louis Farrakhan) that hypocrites like Malcolm should have "their heads cut off."Kondo, p. 170. The April 10 edition of ''Muhammad Speaks'' featured a cartoon in which his severed head was shown bouncing. On July 9, John Ali, a top aide to Muhammad, answered a question about Malcolm X by saying that "anyone who opposes the Honorable Elijah Muhammad puts their life in jeopardy."Evanzz, p. 248. The December 4 issue of ''Muhammad Speaks'' included an article by Louis X that railed against Malcolm X and said that "such a man as Malcolm is worthy of death."Evanzz, p. 264.

Some threats were made anonymously. During the month of June 1964, FBI surveillance recorded two such threats. On June 8, a man called Malcolm X's home and told Betty Shabazz to "tell him he's as good as dead."Carson, p. 473. On June 12, an FBI informant reported getting an anonymous telephone call from somebody who said "Malcolm X is going to be bumped off."Carson, p. 324.

In June 1964, the Nation of Islam sued to reclaim Malcolm X's residence in Queens, New York, which they claimed to own. The suit was successful, and Malcolm X was ordered to vacate.Perry, pp. 290–292. On February 14, 1965, the night before a scheduled hearing to postpone the eviction date, the house burned to the ground. Malcolm X and his family survived. No one was charged with any crime.Perry, pp. 352–356.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4cef52d4380ffabb3e4dfb94f4f746af" name="Malcolm-x" sectnum="8#1">../img/4cef52d4380ffabb3e4dfb94f4f746af.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>