<document id="92fdd2ecb9e00982a766e42085dbe674-11.11" name="Malcolm_X" cat="14">
<text>
The Malcolm X House Site, at 3448 Pinkney Street in North Omaha, Nebraska, marks the place where Malcolm Little first lived with his family. The house where the Little family lived was torn down in 1965 by owners who did not know of its connection with Malcolm X. The site was listed on the National Register of Historic Places in 1984 and a historic marker identifies the site because of the importance of Malcolm X to American history and national culture. In 1987 the site was added to the Nebraska register of historic sites and marked with a state plaque.

Lansing, Michigan, where Malcolm Little spent his early, formative years, is home to a Michigan Historical Marker erected in 1975 marking his homesite.  The city is also home to El-Hajj Malik El-Shabazz Academy, a public charter school with an Afrocentric focus. The Academy is located in the building where Little attended elementary school.


The city of Berkeley, California has recognized Malcolm X's birthday as a citywide holiday since 1979.

There have been dozens of schools named after Malcolm X, including Malcolm X Shabazz High School in Newark, New Jersey, Malcolm Shabazz City High School in Madison, Wisconsin, and Malcolm X College in Chicago, Illinois.

Many cities have renamed streets after Malcolm X. In New York City, Lenox Avenue was renamed Malcolm X Boulevard in the late 1980s. The name of Reid Street in Brooklyn, New York, was changed to Malcolm X Boulevard in 1985.Rickford, p. 419. In 1997, Oakland Avenue in Dallas, Texas, was renamed Malcolm X Boulevard.

In 2005, Columbia University announced the opening of the Malcolm X and Dr. Betty Shabazz Memorial and Educational Center. The memorial is located in the Audubon Ballroom, where Malcolm X was assassinated.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="196e468bb1a872870856dff4ce62a02d" name="Malcolm_X_Blvd" sectnum="11.11#1">../img/196e468bb1a872870856dff4ce62a02d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>