<document id="937a8bc3a5df97d25c9aa61d2425c173-2.1" name="Christopher_Smart's_asylum_confinement" cat="17">
<text>
Few details are known about Smart's time at St Luke's Hospital for Lunatics. He was admitted to St Luke's on 6 May 1757 as a "Curable Patient".Sherbo 1967 p. 112 It is possible that Smart was confined at Newbery's behest over old debts and a poor relationship that existed between the two; Newbery had previously mocked Smart's immorality in ''A Collection of Pretty Poems for the Amusement of Children six Foot High.''Mounsey 2001 p. 181 Regardless of Newbery's exact reasons, there is evidence suggesting that Newbery’s admittance of Smart into the mental asylum was not based on madness. In order to have Smart admitted, Newbery probably provided a small bribe, although bribes were against St Luke's policy.

There is little information about Smart's condition during his stay at St Luke's, possibly because Battie's denied his patients from being visited, including by their own family members. One of the few records that survive of Smart's time at St Luke's was an entry in ''St Luke's Minute Book'', which read:

12 May 1758Dr. Battie having acquainted this Committee that Christopher Smart (who was admitted on the 6th day of May 1757) continues disordered in his Senses notwithstanding he has been admitted into this Hospital above 12 Calendar Months and from the present Circumstances of his Case there is not Suffit. reason to expect his speedy Recovery And he being brought up and examined. Ordered. That he be discharged and that Notice be sent to his Securities to take him away.

During Smart's confinement at St Luke's, not even other doctors were allowed to see Smart unless they had received personal permission from Battie.Mounsey 2001 p. 210 It was improbable that Smart could have left the asylum without being released by Battie. Even if Smart would have attempted to obtain release via legal means, the rules for subpoenaing release would have been almost impossible to follow based on the system that Battie had in place, which isolated the individual from all contact. Eventually, Smart was deemed "incurable" and would not have been released by the hospital but for its lack of funds.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3ed9bc0fa79e8f82be653ba8e487d481" name="Jubilate_Agno_let" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/3ed9bc0fa79e8f82be653ba8e487d481.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>