<document id="938db156ad9b67fa1d4276ac67649940-4.1" name="Ant" cat="3">
<text>
In the colonies of a few ant species, there are physical castes&mdash;workers in distinct size-classes, called minor, median, and major workers. Often the larger ants have disproportionately larger heads, and correspondingly stronger mandibles. Such individuals are sometimes called "soldier" ants because their stronger mandibles make them more effective in fighting, although they are still workers and their "duties" typically do not vary greatly from the minor or median workers. In a few species the median workers are absent, creating a sharp divide between the minors and majors. Weaver ants, for example, have a distinct bimodal size distribution.
 Some other species show continuous variation in the size of workers. The smallest and largest workers in ''Pheidologeton diversus'' show nearly a 500-fold difference in their dry-weights. Workers cannot mate; however, because of the haplodiploid sex-determination system in ants, workers of a number of species can lay unfertilised eggs that become fully fertile haploid males. The role of workers may change with their age and in some species, such as honeypot ants, young workers are fed until their gasters are distended, and act as living food storage vessels. These food storage workers are called ''repletes''. This polymorphism in morphology and behaviour of workers was initially thought to be determined by environmental factors such as nutrition and hormones which led to different developmental paths; however, genetic differences between worker castes have been noted in ''Acromyrmex'' sp. These polymorphisms are caused by relatively small genetic changes; differences in a single gene of ''Solenopsis invicta'' can decide whether the colony will have single or multiple queens. The Australian jack jumper ant (''Myrmecia pilosula''), has only a single pair of chromosomes (males have just one chromosome as they are haploid), the lowest number known for any animal, making it an interesting subject for studies in the genetics and developmental biology of social insects.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0cdedb0c77fbf826eee662d9bbff1fc8" name="Atta.cephalotes.gamut.selection" sectnum="4.1#1">../img/0cdedb0c77fbf826eee662d9bbff1fc8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>