<document id="93f3cbb0350f9a2ba3048af0131f525a-3" name="Jesus_College_Boat_Club_(Oxford)" cat="26">
<text>
D. W. Griffith, the stroke of the Jesus College boat, was present at the inaugural meeting of the Oxford University Boat Club on 23 April 1839.Sherwood, pp. 20–21  However, Jesus College oarsmen played an infrequent part in university rowing in the nineteenth century.  No Jesus College student served on the OUBC committee between 1839 and 1899, the last year for which Sherwood gives records.Sherwood, pp. 361–369 Two students from the college (W. S. Thompson and E. W. Davies (cox)) were part of the losing Oxford crew in the second Oxford–Cambridge boat race in 1836.Sherwood, p. 349 Between 1858 and 1899, seven others trialled, unsuccessfully, for places in the Oxford University crew.Sherwood, pp. 287–302  Since then, college representation in the Boat Race has been more frequent: M. L. Thomas and D. R. Glynne Jones (1952);Baker, p.145 Boris Mavra (1992, 1993 and 1995); the Canadian 2004 Olympic rowing silver medallist Barney Williams (2005 and 2006); and Brodie Buckland (2007). Justin Hutchinson rowed for Oxford's reserve crew, known as Isis, in the 2002 and 2003 Boat Races, as did Tim Farquharson, an undergraduate studying Engineering Science, in 2009. Various women have won their "Blue" for competing in the Women's Boat Race against Cambridge: Anna Bean and Ann Bevitt (1989); Louise Sanford (1997); and Claire Weaver (1998).

Some prominent individuals rowed while they were students at the college.  The historian Albert Pollard was Captain of Boats in 1890, having rowed in the boat that was last on the river in 1889. Alwyn Williams (later Bishop of Durham), who was a student from 1906 to 1911, was captain of the Boat Club, Baker, p. 108 as was James Page, who went on to become secretary of the Amateur Rowing Association from 1952 to 1972 and a rowing coach for both Oxford and Cambridge Boat Clubs. Maurice Jones (later Principal of St David's College, Lampeter) was a cox, as were Gordon Roe (later Bishop of Huntingdon) and the chemist Frank Greenaway. John Sankey (later Lord Chancellor) rowed in a Torpid boat that went down four places,Baker, p. 84 whilst the boat in which the baritone David Ffrangcon Davies rowed went up five places in Torpids and four in Eights Week.Baker, p. 106  Angus Buchanan, who won the Victoria Cross in 1916 during the First World War, rowed in a college four in 1919, despite having been blinded in 1917.Baker, p. 116 Anton Muttukumaru (later Commander of the Ceylon Army) rowed at bow in a college four.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6e48c437d7895710505856fc25a21efd" name="Four_Colleges_Barge" sectnum="3#1">../img/6e48c437d7895710505856fc25a21efd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>