<document id="94517872ca8756e01371963760040e5e-6" name="Act_of_Independence_of_Lithuania" cat="14">
<text>
The Act of February 16 proclaimed the ''re''-establishment (''atstatyti'') of the Lithuanian state, making it the successor to the Lithuanian historical state, the Grand Duchy of Lithuania.   In this respect the Council deviated from the resolution adopted by the Vilnius Conference which called for establishment (''sudaryti'') of a Lithuanian state. However, it was made clear that the new state would be quite different from the old Duchy: it was to be organized only in ethnic Lithuanian lands and was to be governed by democratic principles, as opposed to the multi-ethnic Duchy that had been ruled by aristocracy. The termination of the ties binding Lithuania to other states was addressed to Germany, Russia, and Poland, all of which had their own plans for the country. Even though not addressed directly, the Act renounced any attempt to resurrect the former Polish-Lithuanian union.

The Act of February 16, 1918, is the legal basis for the existence of present-day Lithuania, both during the interwar period and since 1990. The Act became one of the key elements during the restoration of Lithuania's independence from the Soviet Union in 1990. A paragraph in the Act of the Re-Establishment of the State of Lithuania, delivered on March 11, 1990, stated:



This formulation emphasized the continuity of the two legal Acts. The Act of February 16, 1918 and its successor, the Act of March 11, 1990, are regarded as two of the most important developments of Lithuanian society in the 20th century.  

February 16 in Lithuania is now an official holiday. , Žin., 1990, Nr. 31-757. Seimas (2001-05-24). Retrieved on 2007-02-07. On this day various ceremonies are hosted all across Lithuania, but the main commemoration is held in the House of Signatories in Vilnius where the Act was signed in 1918. During this observance the Flag of Lithuania is hoisted, and Lithuanian cultural activists and politicians deliver speeches from its balcony to the people gathered below. Special masses in churches and cathedrals are also delivered. Honoring the Act's legacy, the President of Lithuania hosts a reception for the signatories of the Act of March 11, 1990, in the Presidential Palace.

In 1992, an award was established in honor of Jonas Basanavičius, who led the Council of Lithuania when the Act of February 16 was signed. The Jonas Basanavičius Prize is bestowed for distinguished work within the previous five years in the fields of ethnic and cultural studies.  The prize is awarded in the House of Signatories, in homage to its history.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4fc12ae6f3ffadbfee455ece290cecab" name="House_of_Signatories" sectnum="6#1">../img/4fc12ae6f3ffadbfee455ece290cecab.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>