<document id="94517872ca8756e01371963760040e5e-5.4" name="Act_of_Independence_of_Lithuania" cat="14">
<text>
Soon after the signing, the Act was taken to Germany and handed to parties in the Reichstag. On February 18, the text was reprinted in German newspapers, including ''Das Neue Litauen'', ''Vossische Zeitung'', ''Taegliche Rundschau'' and ''Kreuzzeitung''. In Lithuania a text of the proclamation was prepared for printing in newspapers, particularly in ''Lietuvos aidas'', the Council's newspaper established by Antanas Smetona; but the German authorities prohibited this publication. Although the majority of the copies of the issue were confiscated, the newspaper's editor, Petras Klimas, managed to hide about 60 of them. This censorship meant that the distribution and dissemination of the Act was illegal in Lithuania.

On March 3, 1918, Germany and the now-Bolshevik Russia signed the Treaty of Brest-Litovsk. It declared that the Baltic nations were in the German interest zone and that Russia renounced any claims to them. On March 23, Germany recognized independent Lithuania on the basis of the December 11 declaration. However, in substance, nothing had changed either in Lithuania or in the Council's status: any efforts to establish an administration were hindered. This situation changed when the German Revolution started and Germany lost the war in the fall of 1918 – it was no longer in a position to dictate terms. The Council of Lithuania adopted the first provisional constitution on November 2. The functions of government were entrusted to a three-member presidium, and Augustinas Voldemaras was invited to form the first Cabinet of Ministers of Lithuania.  The first government was formed on November 11, 1918, on the day that Germany signed the armistice in Compiègne. The Council immediately began to organize an army, police, municipalities, and other institutions. The proclaimed independence was established.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="58d1a28e37ce5b81bdc7d74966cf6a32" name="Lietuvos_aidas_independence" sectnum="5.4#1">../img/58d1a28e37ce5b81bdc7d74966cf6a32.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>