<document id="9515f8a169b7fb0d5d75718df2e9219d-3" name="William_Butler_Yeats" cat="17">
<text>
In 1889, Yeats met Maud Gonne, then a 23-year-old heiress and ardent Nationalist.Gonne claimed they first met in London three years earlier. Foster notes how Gonne was "notoriously unreliable on dates and places (1997, 57) Gonne was eighteen months younger than Yeats and later claimed she met the poet as a "paint-stained art student."Foster (1997), 57 Gonne had admired "The Isle of Statues" and sought out his acquaintance. Yeats developed an obsessive infatuation with her beauty and outspoken manner, and she was to have a significant and lasting effect on his poetry and his life thereafter.Uddin Khan, Jalal. "Yeats and Maud Gonne: (Auto)biographical and Artistic Intersection". ''Alif: Journal of Comparative Poetics'', 2002. 


Looking back in later years, he admitted "it seems to me that she  brought into my life those days&mdash;for as yet I saw only what lay upon the surface&mdash;the middle of the tint, a sound as of a Burmese gong, an over-powering tumult that had yet many pleasant secondary notes."Foster (1997), 86–87 Yeats' love remained unrequited, in part due to his reluctance to participate in her nationalist activism."". BBC Four. Retrieved on 20 June 2007. His only other love affair during this period was with Olivia Shakespear, whom he had first met in 1896, and parted with one year later. In 1891, he visited Gonne in Ireland and proposed marriage, but was rejected. He later admitted that from that point "the troubling of my life began."Cahill, Christopher. "Second Puberty: The Later Years of W. B. Yeats Brought His Best Poetry, along with Personal Melodrama on an Epic Scale". ''The Atlantic Monthly'', December 2003. Yeats proposed to Gonne three more times: in 1899, 1900 and 1901. She refused each proposal, and in 1903, to his horror, married the Irish nationalist Major John MacBride.Ó Corráin, Donnchadh. "". University College Cork. Retrieved on 15 July 2007.

Yeats' friendship with Gonne persisted, and in Paris in 1908 they finally consummated their relationship. "The long years of fidelity rewarded at last" was how another of his lovers described the event. Yeats was less sentimental and later remarked that "the tragedy of sexual intercourse is the perpetual virginity of the soul." The relationship did not develop into a new phase after their night together, and soon afterwards Gonne wrote to the poet indicating that despite the physical consummation, they could not continue as they had been: "I have prayed so hard to have all earthly desire taken from my love for you & dearest, loving you as I do, I have prayed & I am praying still that the bodily desire for me may be taken from you too."Foster (1997), 394 By January 1909, Gonne was sending Yeats letters praising the advantage given to artists who abstain from sex. Nearly twenty years later, Yeats recalled the night with Gonne in his poem "A Man Young and Old":

My arms are like the twisted thornAnd yet there beauty lay;The first of all the tribe lay thereAnd did such pleasure take;She who had brought great Hector downAnd put all Troy to wreck.

In 1896, Yeats was introduced to Lady Gregory by their mutual friend Edward Martyn. Gregory encouraged Yeats' nationalism, and convinced him to continue focusing on writing drama. Although he was influenced by French Symbolism, Yeats concentrated on an identifiably Irish content and this inclination was reinforced by his involvement with a new generation of younger and emerging Irish authors. Together with Lady Gregory, Martyn, and other writers including J. M. Synge, Sean O'Casey, and Padraic Colum, Yeats was one of those responsible for the establishment of the "Irish Literary Revival" movement.Corcoran, Neil. ''After Yeats and Joyce: Reading Modern Irish Literature''. (Oxford), Oxford University Press, 1997. viii Apart from these creative writers, much of the impetus for the Revival came from the work of scholarly translators who were aiding in the discovery of both the ancient sagas and Ossianic poetry and the more recent folk song tradition in Irish. One of the most significant of these was Douglas Hyde, later the first President of Ireland, whose ''Love Songs of Connacht'' was widely admired.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3f9daa2f7d7084ce3b4ca2c0e715bfd9" name="maudgonne" sectnum="3#1">../img/3f9daa2f7d7084ce3b4ca2c0e715bfd9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>