<document id="9515f8a169b7fb0d5d75718df2e9219d-4" name="William_Butler_Yeats" cat="17">
<text>
In 1899, Yeats, Lady Gregory, Edward Martyn, and George Moore established the Irish Literary Theatre for the purpose of performing Celtic and Irish plays.Foster (2003), 486; 662 The ideals of the Abbey were derived from the avant-garde French theatre, which sought to express the "ascendancy of the playwright rather than the actor-manager ''à l'anglais''."Foster (1997), 183Text reproduced from Yeats' own handwritten draft. The group's manifesto, which Yeats himself wrote, declared "We hope to find in Ireland an uncorrupted & imaginative audience trained to listen by its passion for oratory... & that freedom to experiment which is not found in the theatres of England, & without which no new movement in art or literature can succeed."Foster (1997), 184

The collective survived for about two years and was not successful. However, working together with two Irish brothers with theatrical experience, William and Frank Fay, Yeats' unpaid-yet-independently wealthy secretary Annie Elizabeth Fredericka Horniman, and the leading West End actress Florence Farr, the group established the Irish National Theatre Society. This group of founders was able, along with J.M. Synge, to acquire property in Dublin and open the Abbey Theatre on 27 December, 1904. Yeats' play ''Cathleen Ní Houlihan'' and Lady Gregory's ''Spreading the News'' were featured on the opening night. Yeats continued to be involved with the Abbey until his death, both as a member of the board and a prolific playwright. In 1902, he helped set up the Dun Emer Press to publish work by writers associated with the Revival. This became the Cuala Press in 1904, and inspired by the Arts and Crafts movement, sought to "find work for Irish hands in the making of beautiful things.""". Trinity College, Dublin, 12 February 2004. Retrieved on 2 June 2007. From then until its closure in 1946, the press&mdash;which was run by the poet's sisters&mdash;produced over 70 titles; 48 of them books by Yeats himself.

 
In 1913, Yeats met the American poet Ezra Pound. Pound had travelled to London at least partly to meet the older man, whom he considered "the only poet worthy of serious study."Monroe, Harriet (1913). "Poetry". (Chicago) Modern Poetry Association. 123 From that year until 1916, the two men wintered in the Stone Cottage at Ashdown Forest, with Pound nominally acting as Yeats' secretary. The relationship got off to a rocky start when Pound arranged for the publication in the magazine ''Poetry'' of some of Yeats' verse with Pound's own unauthorised alterations. These changes reflected Pound's distaste for Victorian prosody. A more indirect influence was the scholarship on Japanese Noh plays that Pound had obtained from Ernest Fenollosa's widow, which provided Yeats with a model for the aristocratic drama he intended to write. The first of his plays modeled on Noh was ''At the Hawk's Well'', the first draft of which he dictated to Pound in January 1916.Sands, Maren. "". Colorado State University. Retrieved on 15 July 2007.

In his early work, Yeats' aristocratic pose led to an idealisation of the Irish peasant and a willingness to ignore poverty and suffering. However, the emergence of a revolutionary movement from the ranks of the urban Catholic lower-middle class made him reassess his attitudes. His new direct engagement with politics can be seen in the poem ''September 1913'', with its well-known refrain "Romantic Ireland's dead and gone / It's with O'Leary in the grave." The poem is an attack on the Dublin employers who were involved in the 1913 Dublin Lockout of workers and supports James Larkin's attempts to organise the Irish labour movement. In the refrain of "Easter 1916" ("All changed, changed utterly / A terrible beauty is born"), Yeats faces his own failure to recognise the merits of the leaders of the Easter Rising, due to his attitude towards their humble backgrounds and lives.Foster (2003), 59–66
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d0b62adecb81e50a89f66d795f25a37f" name="Abbey_Theatre_exterior" sectnum="4#1">../img/d0b62adecb81e50a89f66d795f25a37f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>