<document id="9622129f4a5397c15998d296c4f9c269-2.4" name="2008_Humanitarian_Bowl" cat="26">
<text>
The site of the game was Bronco Stadium in Boise, Idaho, the home field of Boise State University. The field's blue artificial turf has the distinction of being the only non-green playing field in use by a Division I Football Bowl Subdivision team. Due to the color of its field, the stadium is nicknamed "The Blue" and the field itself is sometimes colloquially referred to as "smurf turf"., Bronco Sports.com, Boise State University Broncos official website, retrieved January 4, 2009., Hometown Annapolis, ''The Capital'', December 17, 2008, retrieved 2009.

Pundits and opponents have asserted that Boise State benefits from an added advantage by wearing their blue home uniforms to match the playing field., ''USA Today'', September 24, 2004, retrieved January 9, 2009., ''The Daily Orange'', October 14, 2004, retrieved January 9, 2009., CBS College Sports, September 14, 2006, retrieved January 9, 2009. Boise State possessed a 64–2 record at Bronco Stadium from 1998 to 2008.Ron Snyder, , Baltimore Examiner.com, ''The Examiner'', December 12, 2008, retrieved January 4, 2009. Nevada, designated as the home team, likewise wore blue uniforms during the Humanitarian Bowl., ''Reno Gazette-Journal'', December 28, 2008, retrieved January 9, 2009.

ACC teams viewed a berth in the Humanitarian Bowl as undesirable due to its location. Aside from being one of the lower priority tie-ins, the destination is far outside the conference's geographic footprint. Travel costs from the East Coast are prohibitively expensive and historically caused low turnout among ACC fans. In addition, the game is hosted at a cold-weather venue, which is a disadvantage in comparison with ACC bowl games in places such as Florida, California, and Georgia., ''The Diamondback'', December 30, 2008, retrieved January 17, 2009., Scout.com, December 29, 2008, retrieved January 17, 2009.Eric Prisbell, , ''The Washington Post'', December 8, 2008, retrieved January 17, 2009.

The game historically relied on local ticket sales, and the participating schools struggled to sell their alloted tickets. On December 8, a Boise-area television news station reported that Maryland and Nevada had sold just sixteen and eight tickets, respectively., 2News.TV, December 8, 2008, retrieved January 21, 2009. The story was widely circulated by sports-related blogs, but the figures were discredited by a Maryland official.Jeff Barker, , ''The Baltimore Sun'', December 17, 2008, retrieved January 21, 2009. On December 18, the Reno Gazette-Journal reported that 100 tickets had been sold by Nevada., ''Reno Gazette-Journal'', December 18, 2008, retrieved January 21, 2009. Maryland officials admitted that ticket sales among its fans were expected to be low, with one stating they were in the "mid-hundreds" a week and a half from the game date.Patrick Stevens, , ''The Washington Times'', December 20, 2008, retrieved January 21, 2009., ''The Baltimore Sun'', December 18, 2008, retrieved January 21, 2009. According to a ''Baltimore Sun'' reporter, Maryland's final ticket figure was about 800.Jeff Barker, , ''The Baltimore Sun'', December 30, 2008, retrieved January 21, 2009. By comparison, Clemson sold about 3,500 tickets for the 2001 Humanitarian Bowl, and Georgia Tech sold about 250 tickets for the 2007 Humanitarian Bowl., ''The Baltimore Sun'', December 30, 2008, retrieved February 8, 2009.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="10ccd78f6c0491f04f13d362e1a8393a" name="Broncostadiumoct108" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/10ccd78f6c0491f04f13d362e1a8393a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>