<document id="9646b7998c0120200405906417f07c93-2.3" name="Frederick_III,_German_Emperor" cat="25">
<text>
When his father succeeded to the Prussian throne as King William I on 2 January 1861, Frederick became the Crown Prince. Already twenty-nine years old, he would be Crown Prince for a further twenty-seven years. The new king was initially considered politically neutral; Frederick and Prussia's liberal elements hoped that he would usher in a new era of liberal policies. The liberals managed to greatly increase their majority in the Prussian Diet, but William soon showed that he preferred the conservative ways.  On the other hand, Frederick declared himself in complete agreement with the "essential liberal policy for internal and foreign affairs".Van der Kiste, p. 68.

Because William was a dogmatic soldier and unlikely to change his ideas at the age of sixty-four,Van der Kiste, p. 61. he regularly clashed with the Diet over policies.  In September 1862, one such disagreement almost led to Frederick being crowned and replacing his father as king; William threatened to abdicate when the Diet refused to fund his plans for the army's reorganization.  Frederick was appalled by this action, and said that an abdication would "constitute a threat to the dynasty, country and Crown".Pakula, p. 168.  William reconsidered, and instead appointed Otto von Bismarck as Minister-President. The appointment of Bismarck, an authoritarian who often ignored or overruled the Diet, set Frederick on a collision course with his father and led to his exclusion from affairs of state for the rest of William's reign.  Frederick insisted on bloodless "moral conquests", unifying Germany by liberal and peaceful means, but it was Bismarck's policy of blood and iron that prevailed.

Frederick was severely reproached by his father for his liberal ideas, so he spent a large portion of time in England where Queen Victoria frequently allowed him to represent her at ceremonies and social functions.Pakula, p. 69.


Frederick experienced his first combat in the Second Schleswig War.  Appointed to supervise the supreme German Confederation commander Field Marshal Wrangel and his staff, the Crown Prince tactfully managed disputes between Wrangel and the other officers.  The Prussians and their Austrian allies defeated the Danes and conquered the southern part of Jutland, but after the war they spent two years politicking to assume leadership of the German states. This culminated in the Austro-Prussian War, and although Frederick had opposed a war against Austria, he accepted command of one of Prussia's three armies, with General Leonhard Graf von Blumenthal as his chief of staff.  The timely arrival of his II Army was crucial to the Prussian victory in 1866 at the decisive Battle of Königgrätz, which won the war for Prussia.Lord, p. 125.  After the battle, William presented Frederick with the Order Pour le Mérite for his personal gallantry on the field and leadership of the II Army. A few days before Königgrätz, Frederick had written to his wife, expressing his hope that this would be the last war he would have to fight. On the third day of the battle he wrote to her again: "Who knows whether we may not have to wage a third war in order to keep what we have now won?"Pakula, p. 98.

Four years later Frederick was in action again, this time during the Franco-Prussian War of 1870, in which he commanded the III Army, consisting of troops from the southern German states.Howard, p. 60.Kollander, p. 92.  He was praised for his leadership after defeating the French at the battles of Wörth and Wissembourg,  and met with further successes at the Battle of Sedan and during the Siege of Paris.  Frederick's humane treatment of his country's foes earned him their respect and the plaudits of neutral observers.Kollander, p. 109.  After the Battle of Wörth, a London journalist witnessed the Crown Prince's many visits to wounded Prussian soldiers and lauded his deeds, extolling the love and respect the soldiers held for Frederick.  Following his victory, Frederick had remarked to two Paris journalists, "I do not like war gentlemen. If I should reign I would never make it." One French journalist remarked that "the Crown Prince has left countless traits of kindness and humanity in the land that he fought against."  For his behaviour and accomplishments, the ''London Times'' wrote a tribute to Frederick in July 1871, stating that "the Prince has won as much honour for his gentleness as for his prowess in the war".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="776ff548adfb47d41fedd6ad9668b464" name="Kronprinz_Friedrich_Wilhelm_auf_dem_Hofball_1878" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/776ff548adfb47d41fedd6ad9668b464.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>