<document id="9649610dbce420e3eddd1b58072aa8b2-7.1" name="Anna_Laetitia_Barbauld" cat="17">
<text>
Barbauld’s poetry, which addresses a wide range of topics, has been read primarily by feminist literary critics interested in recovering women writers who were important in their own time but who have been forgotten by literary history. Isobel Armstrong's work represents one way to do such scholarship; she argues that Barbauld, like other Romantic women poets:


In her subsequent analysis of “Inscription for an Ice-House” she points to Barbauld’s challenge of Edmund Burke's characterization of the sublime and the beautiful and Adam Smith's economic theories in the ''Wealth of Nations'' as evidence for this interpretation.Armstrong, 18; 22–3.

The work of Marlon Ross and Anne K. Mellor represents a second way to apply the insights of feminist theory to the recovery of women writers. They argue that Barbauld and other Romantic women poets carved out a distinctive feminine voice in the literary sphere. As a woman and a Dissenter, Barbauld had a unique perspective on society, according to Ross, and it was this specific position that "obligated" her to publish social commentary.Ross, Marlon B. “Configurations of Feminine Reform: The Woman Writers and the Tradition of Dissent.” ''Re-visioning Romanticism: British Women Writers, 1776–1837''. Eds. Carol Shiner Wilson and Joel Haefner. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press (1994), 93. But, Ross points out, women were in a double bind: “they could choose to speak politics in nonpolitical modes, and thus risk greatly diminishing the clarity and pointedness of their political passion, or they could choose literary modes that were overtly political while trying to infuse them with a recognizable ‘feminine’ decorum, again risking a softening of their political agenda.”Ross, 94. Therefore Barbauld and other Romantic women poets often wrote “occasional poems.” These poems had traditionally commented, often satirically, on national events, but by the end of the eighteenth century they were increasingly serious and personal. Women wrote sentimental poems, a style then much in vogue, on personal occasions such as the birth of a child and argued that in commenting on the small occurrences of daily life, they would establish a moral foundation for the nation.Ross, 96–97. Scholars such as Ross and Mellor maintain that this adaptation of existing styles and genres is one way that female poets created a feminine Romanticism.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f310e644e9d6e438abeddc59fc74bd95" name="BarbauldMouse" sectnum="7.1#1">../img/f310e644e9d6e438abeddc59fc74bd95.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>