<document id="9649610dbce420e3eddd1b58072aa8b2-5" name="Anna_Laetitia_Barbauld" cat="17">
<text>
In 1802, the Barbaulds moved to Stoke Newington where Rochemont took over the pastoral duties of the Chapel at Newington Green. Barbauld herself was happy to be nearer her brother, John, because her husband’s mind was rapidly failing.Rodgers, 128–9. Rochemont developed a “violent antipathy to his wife and he was liable to fits of insane fury directed against her. One day at dinner he seized a knife and chased her round the table so that she only saved herself by jumping out of the window.”Rodgers, 136; Le Breton, 121–2. Such scenes repeated themselves to Barbauld’s great sadness and real danger, but she refused to leave him. Rochemont drowned himself in the nearby New River in 1808 and Barbauld was overcome with grief. When Barbauld returned to writing, she produced the radical poem ''Eighteen Hundred and Eleven'' (1812) that depicted England as a ruin. It was reviewed so viciously that Barbauld never published another work within her lifetime, although it is now often viewed by scholars as her greatest poetic achievement.Rodgers, 139–141. Barbauld died in 1825, a renowned writer, and was buried in the family vault in St Mary's, Stoke Newington. After Barbauld’s death, a marble tablet was erected in the Newington Green Chapel with the following inscription:




''In Memory of'' 
''ANNA LETITIA BARBAULD,''
''Daughter of John Aikin, D.D.''
''And Wife of''
''The Rev. Rochemont Barbauld,''
''Formerly the Respected Minister of this Congregation.''
''She was born at Kibworth in Leicesterhsire, 20th June, 1743,''
''and died at Stoke Newington, 9th March, 1825.''
''Endowed by the Giver of all Good''
''With Wit, Genius, Poetic Talent, and a Vigorous Understanding''
''She Employed these High Gifts''
''in Promoting the Cause of Humanity, Peace, and Justice,''
''of Civil and Religious Liberty,''
''of Pure, Ardent, and Affectionate Devotion.''
''Let the Young, Nurtured by her Writings in the Pure Spirit''
''of Christian Morality;''
''Let those of Maturer Years, Capable of Appreciating''
''the Acuteness, the Brilliant Fancy, and Sound Reasoning''
''of her Literary Compositions;''
''Let the Surviving few who shared her Delightful''
''and Instructive Conversation,''
''Bear Witness''
''That this Monument Records''
''No Exaggerated Praise.''Le Breton, 197.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7d6fb018c2e26c85e369eb94dc3e39d6" name="Barbauld1811" sectnum="5#1">../img/7d6fb018c2e26c85e369eb94dc3e39d6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>