<document id="9649610dbce420e3eddd1b58072aa8b2-2" name="Anna_Laetitia_Barbauld" cat="17">
<text>
In 1773, Barbauld brought out her first book of poems, after her friends had praised them and convinced her to publish.Rodgers, 57. The collection, entitled simply ''Poems'', went through four editions in just one year and surprised Barbauld by its success. Barbauld became a respected literary figure in England on the reputation of ''Poems'' alone. The same year she and her brother, John Aikin, jointly published ''Miscellaneous Pieces in Prose'', which was also well-received. The essays in it (most of which were by Barbauld) were favorably compared to Samuel Johnson's.Rodgers, 61–2.

In May 1774, despite some "misgivings", Barbauld married Rochemont Barbauld, the grandson of a French Huguenot and a former pupil at Warrington. According to Barbauld's niece, Lucy Aikin:


After the wedding, the couple moved to Suffolk, near where Rochemont had been offered a congregation and a school for boys.Rodgers, 63–4. Barbauld took this time and rewrote some of the psalms, a common pastime in the eighteenth century, publishing them as ''Devotional Pieces Compiled from the Psalms and the Book of Job''. Attached to this work is her essay “Thoughts on the Devotional Taste, on Sects and on Establishments”, which explains her theory of religious feeling and the problems inherent in the institutionalization of religion.

It seems that Barbauld and her husband were concerned that they would never have a child of their own and in 1775, after only a year of marriage, Barbauld suggested to her brother that they adopt one of his children:

Eventually her brother conceded and the couple adopted Charles; it was for him that Barbauld wrote her most famous books: ''Lessons for Children'' (1778–9) and ''Hymns in Prose for Children'' (1781).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="11615b2bb3e6a6aab6e3b5d19bfa7354" name="PriestleyLeeds" sectnum="2#1">../img/11615b2bb3e6a6aab6e3b5d19bfa7354.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>