<document id="9664d8622a9bb86983b15a3de54868fd-5" name="Wallis,_Duchess_of_Windsor" cat="25">
<text>
On 20 January 1936, George V died and Edward ascended the throne as Edward VIII. The next day, he broke royal protocol by watching the proclamation of his accession from a window of St. James's Palace, in the company of the still-married Wallis.The Duke of Windsor, p. 265 It was becoming apparent to Court and Government circles that Edward meant to marry her.Ziegler, pp. 277–278 The King's behaviour and his relationship with Wallis made him unpopular with the Conservative-led British government, as well as distressing his mother and brother.Ziegler, pp. 289–292 Although the pre-war British media remained deferential to the monarchy, and no stories of the affair were reported in the domestic press, foreign media widely reported their relationship.

The monarch of the United Kingdom is Supreme Governor of the Church of England—at the time of the proposed marriage, and until 2002, the Church of England did not permit the re-marriage of divorced people with living ex-spouses. Accordingly, while there was no civil law barrier to Edward marrying Wallis, the constitutional position was that the King could not marry a divorcée and remain as King (for to do so would conflict with his role as Supreme Governor).Beaverbrook, pp. 39–44 and p. 122 Furthermore, the British government and the governments of the Dominions were against the idea of marriage between the King and an American divorcée for other reasons.Ziegler, pp. 305–307 She was perceived by many in the British Empire as a woman of "limitless ambition",Sir Horace Wilson writing to Neville Chamberlain quoted in Higham, p. 191 who was pursuing the King because of his wealth and position.Ziegler, p. 234 and p. 312

Wallis had already filed for divorce from her second husband and the decree nisi was granted on 27 October 1936. Her relationship with the King had become public knowledge in the United Kingdom by early December. Wallis decided to flee the country as the scandal broke, being driven to the south of France in a dramatic race to outrun the press. For the next three months, she was under siege by the press at the Villa Lou Viei, near Cannes, the home of her close friends Herman and Katherine Rogers.The Duke of Windsor, p. 359

Back in the United Kingdom, the King consulted with the Prime Minister, Stanley Baldwin, on a way to marry Wallis and keep the throne. The King suggested a morganatic marriage, where the King would remain King but Wallis would not be Queen, but this was rejected by Baldwin and the Prime Ministers of Australia and South Africa. If the King were to marry Wallis against Baldwin's advice, the Government would be required to resign, causing a constitutional crisis.Beaverbrook, p. 57

At her hideaway in the south of France, Wallis was pressured by the King's Lord-in-Waiting, Peregrine Cust, 6th Baron Brownlow, to renounce the King. On 7 December 1936, Lord Brownlow read to the press her statement, which he had helped her draft, indicating Wallis's readiness to give up the King. However, Edward was determined to marry Wallis. As the issue of abdication gathered strength, John Theodore Goddard, Wallis's solicitor, stated: " client was ready to do anything to ease the situation but the other end of the wicket  was determined." This seemingly indicated that the King had decided he had no option but to abdicate if he wished to marry Wallis.

The King signed the Instrument of Abdication on 10 December 1936, in the presence of his three surviving brothers, the Duke of York (who would ascend the throne the following day as George VI), the Duke of Gloucester and the Duke of Kent. Special laws passed by the Parliaments of the Dominions finalised Edward's abdication the following day, or in Ireland's case one day later. On 11 December 1936, Edward made a broadcast to the people, saying of Wallis, "I have found it impossible to carry the heavy burden of responsibility, and to discharge my duties as King as I would wish to do, without the help and support of the woman I love."The Duke of Windsor, p. 413

Afterwards, Prince Edward left Britain and went to Austria, staying at Schloss Enzesfeld, the home of Baron Eugen and Baroness Kitty de Rothschild. Edward had to remain apart from Wallis until there was no danger of compromising the granting of a decree absolute in her divorce proceedings. Upon her divorce being made final in May 1937, she resumed her maiden name of Wallis Warfield. The couple were reunited at the Château de Candé, Monts, France, on 4 May 1937.Higham, p. 224
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6efc76068cae08e5124e060039305fa7" name="Wallis_Time" sectnum="5#1">../img/6efc76068cae08e5124e060039305fa7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>