<document id="9675857922e83b87794d738af9d70e24-6" name="One_Hot_Minute" cat="20">
<text>
The ''One Hot Minute'' tour began several days after the release of the album. The band opened the tour with a European leg. Kiedis felt that as a musician, he was becoming somewhat lackluster.Kiedis, Sloman, 2004. pp.350-363 The short European leg ended in early November, and the U.S. portion was scheduled to begin ten days later. It was however, postponed until early February. A few shows into the commencement of the U.S. leg, Kiedis badly injured his leg while engaging in what he calls "eyes-closed robotic dancing". He tripped over a monitor and fell off the stage ending up hanging by his calf from his microphone cable, resulting in a cast which he wore for the next two months. Kiedis reflected that it "was nice to see that people were still interested in coming out to see what we do", as there had been a four year gap since the release of ''Blood Sugar Sex Magik''. Following the conclusion of the U.S. tour, the Chili Peppers took two weeks off before several Australia and New Zealand performances. The band then played at the Tibetan Freedom Concert in San Francisco, before finishing the tour in Europe.

Kiedis had remained sober the entire tour and maintained positive disposition during shows. Navarro however, was growing tired of touring, and that was beginning to grate on his fellow band-mates. Kiedis received an additional injury in Prague after falling off the stage while attempting to execute a back flip. He was forced to wear a back brace for the next few shows, which immobilized his actions to area around his microphone. After shows in Paris and London, the band returned home to Los Angeles. Kiedis began taking drugs once again, though he forced himself to discontinue after several weeks. The band was then asked to play in the North Pole for roughly one hundred contest winners of a concert set up by Molson, a Canadian beer company. While the show was mildly motivating to the band, they returned home after two days.Kiedis, Sloman, 2004. p. 364

Months went by without any scheduled concerts due to the album's poor sales.Kiedis, Sloman, 2004. p. 376 Following another relapse and a stint in rehab, Kiedis and the rest of the band prepared for a summer tour—their first in almost seven months. Unfortunately, before the tour could begin, Kiedis had an accident on his motorcycle, and was rushed to the hospital after severely injuring his hand. Due to his drug addiction, it took seven doses of morphine before the pain was assuaged. Following discharge from the hospital, he was forced to wear a full-arm cast for several months, resulting in the cancellation of all remaining scheduled concerts. Half way through Kiedis's recovery, the band was asked to play the Fuji Rock Festival in July 1997. By that time, Kiedis's cast had receded down to the elbow and he felt well enough to play.Kiedis, Sloman, 2004. pp.280-282 A large typhoon had been forecast to hit the festival several hours before the show. The concert took place anyway, and when the Chili Peppers got on stage to play, the audience was being soaked in torrential rains, and the band found it virtually impossible to play their instruments. After eight songs, the lighting and sound equipment was torn from the stage and the band was obliged to an impromptu finish.Kiedis, Sloman, 2004. pp. 384-390

Returning home, the Chili Peppers parted ways and, for the most part, remained secluded from each other through the rest of 1997. No new material was written during that time, and it was not until the beginning of 1998 that the band began rehearsal. At this point, Navarro had become dependent on drugs, with Kiedis also struggling to remain clean. The band decided they would have a talk with Navarro and attempt to convince him to enter rehab. The discussion escalated into a heated dispute, and Navarro fell over an amplifier in a drug-induced daze. By April 1998, the band had not written any new material; Kiedis and Flea decided it was time to fire their guitarist. Navarro was furious when confronted by Kiedis and Flea, but eventually accepted his termination.Kiedis, Sloman, 2004. pp. 390-395 The Chili Peppers were fighting, and on the verge of breaking up. Flea was beginning to question the band's future, and thought it may be necessary to break the band up. He made one last attempt to keep the band together, asking Frusciante to rejoin. Frusciante had recently completed a drug rehabilitation program after more than five years of heroin addiction, and gladly accepted the invitation.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9dd8f6721767625bcdfb28b0e8b92670" name="Kiedis1996" sectnum="6#1">../img/9dd8f6721767625bcdfb28b0e8b92670.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>