<document id="969730fc679ebe5aa50e263392331c94-5" name="Ivan_Alexander_of_Bulgaria" cat="25">
<text>
During Ivan Alexander's rule, the Second Bulgarian Empire entered a period of cultural renaissance, which is sometimes referred to as the "Second Golden Age of Bulgarian culture", the original one being the rule of Simeon the Great.
 A large number of Bulgarian monasteries and churches were constructed or renovated on the order of Ivan Alexander.''Sinodik na Car Boril'', additions from the 13th and 14th century, cited in Canev, ''Bǎlgarski hroniki'', p. 456. Mural portraits of him as a donor can be seen in the Bachkovo Monastery's ossuary and in the Rock-hewn Churches of Ivanovo.
 Donor's deeds of Ivan Alexander prove that the monasteries of the Holy Mother of God Eleoussa and St Nicholas in Nesebǎr were reconstructed during that period, as was the St Nicholas monastery near Pernik, according to a Hilandar monastery deed. In addition, the tsar also initiated the construction of the Dragalevci and Kilifarevo monasteries.

Literary activity also flourished during the reign of Ivan Alexander. Several important literary works were created in the period, such as the Middle Bulgarian translation of the Manasses Chronicle (1344–1345), currently preserved in the Vatican Secret Archives in Rome, the richly illustrated Tetraevangelia of Ivan Alexander (1355–1356), now exhibited in the British Library, the Tomić Psalter (1360), today in Moscow, and the Sofia Psalter (1337).

Ivan Alexander's rule was also marked by efforts to strengthen the position of the Bulgarian Orthodox Church by pursuing heretics and Jews. He organized two anti-heretical church councils, in 1350 and 1359–1360, that condemned various sects such as the Bogomils, the Adamites and the Judaizers.Canev, ''Bǎlgarski hroniki'', p. 457.

The spiritual practice of hesychasm, a form of incantatory prayer, deeply influenced certain areas of the Eastern Orthodox world of the 14th century. A notable Bulgarian representative of the movement during Ivan Alexander's reign was Theodosius of Tǎrnovo.

During this time, the Bulgarian Empire had trade relations with the Mediterranean maritime powers Venice, Genoa and Ragusa. In 1353, Ivan Alexander issued a charter allowing Venetian merchants to buy and sell goods throughout Bulgaria after Doge Andrea Dandolo assured him they would observe the prior treaties between the two countries.Bakalov, ''Istorija na Bǎlgarija'', "Venecianska gramota"

In modern times, the rule of Ivan Alexander inspired Bulgarian national writer Ivan Vazov to write the novelette ''Ivan-Aleksandǎr'' and the drama ''Kǎm propast'' (''Towards an Abyss''), in both of which the tsar is the main character.

A piece of a garment signed by Ivan Alexander and interwoven with gold was discovered in a noble's grave near Pirot in the 1970s; today it is preserved in the National Museum of Serbia in Belgrade. It is the first find of its kind, demonstrating a medieval tradition attested in writing according to which Orthodox rulers would present their most eminent dignitaries with a piece of a garment they had worn.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8f00ef9228e4b6a28d1542992cc72656" name="Ioal_backovo" sectnum="5#1">../img/8f00ef9228e4b6a28d1542992cc72656.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>