<document id="96a6d281f40487c4fda06ba271f24fb8-3" name="Myxobolus_cerebralis" cat="3">
<text>
''Myxobolus cerebralis'' has a two-host life-cycle involving a salmonid fish and a tubificid oligochaete. So far, the only worm known to be susceptible to ''M. cerebralis'' infection is ''Tubifex tubifex'', though what scientists currently call ''T. tubifex'' may in fact be more than one species.  First, myxospores are ingested by tubificid worms. In the gut lumen of the worm, the spores extrude their polar capsules and attach to the gut epithelium by polar filaments. The shell valves then open along the suture line and the binucleate germ cell penetrates between the intestinal epithelial cells of the worm. This cell multiplies, producing many amoeboid cells by an asexual cell fission process called merogony. As a result of the multiplication process, the intercellular space of the epithelial cells in more than 10 neighbouring worm segments may become infected.El-Matbouli, M., and Hoffmann, R.W. (1998). Light and electron microscopic studies on the chronological development of Myxobolus cerebralis to the Actinosporean stage in Tubifex Tubifes. International Journal For Parasitology 28: 195–217.

Around 60&ndash;90 days post-infection, sexual cell stages of the parasite undergo sporogenesis, and develop into pansporocysts, each of which contains eight triactinomyxon-stage spores. These spores are released from the oligochaete anus into the water.  Alternatively, a fish can become infected by eating an infected oligochaete. Infected tubificids can release triactinomyxons for at least 1 year. The triactinomyxon spores swim through the water to infect a salmonid through the skin.  Penetration of the fish by these spores takes only a few seconds. Within five minutes, a sac of germ cells called a sporoplasm has entered the fish epidermis, and within a few hours, the sporoplasm splits into individual cells that will spread through the fish.

Within the fish, there are both intracellular and extracellular stages that reproduce in its cartilage by asexual endogeny, meaning that new cells grow from within old cells.  The final stage within fish is the myxospore, which is formed by sporogony.  They are released into the environment when the fish decomposes or is eaten.  Some recent research indicates that some fish may expel viable myxospores while still alive.Nehring, R. B. Thompson, K. G. Taurman, K. A. & Shuler, D.L. (2002). Laboratory studies indicating that living brown trout Salmo trutta expel viable Myxobolus cerebralis myxospores. American Fisheries Society Symposium 29: 125–134.

Myxospores are extremely tough: "it was shown that ''Myxobolus cerebralis'' spores can tolerate freezing at ­-20°C for at least 3 months, aging in mud at 13°C for at least 5 months, and passage through the guts of northern pike ''Esox lucius'' or mallards ''Anas platyrhynchos'' without loss of infectivity" to worms.El-Matbouli, M., and Hoffmann, R.W. (1991). Effects of freezing, aging, and passage through the alimentary canal of predatory animals on the viability of Myxobolus cerebralis spores. Journal of Aquatic Animal Health 3: 260–262.  Triactinomyxons are much shorter lived, surviving 34 days or less, depending on temperature.Markiw, M.E. (1992). Experimentally induced whirling disease. II. Determination of longevity of the infective triactinomyxon stage of Myxobolus cerebralis by vital staining. Journal of Aquatic Animal Health 4 (1): 44–47.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="12082fb28c69e17398ca89cb003d9472" name="LifeCycle(Myxobolus_cerebralis)" sectnum="3#1">../img/12082fb28c69e17398ca89cb003d9472.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>