<document id="970eed35cee1a20ccae4e529b5683276-3.2" name="Candide" cat="17">
<text>
The trio arrive in Buenos Aires, where Governor Don Fernando de Ibaraa y Figueora y Mascarenes y Lampurdos y Sousa asks to marry Cunégonde. Just then, an alcaide (a Portuguese fortress commander) arrives,  pursuing Candide for killing the Grand Inquisitor. Leaving the women behind, Candide flees to Paraguay with his practical and heretofore unmentioned manservant, Cacambo.

At a border post on the way to Paraguay, Cacambo and Candide speak to the commandant, who turns out to be Cunégonde's unnamed brother. He explains that after his family was slaughterd, the Jesuits' preparation for his burial revived him, and he has since joined the order. When Candide proclaims he intends to marry Cunégonde, her brother attacks him, and Candide stabs him through with his rapier. After lamenting all the people (mainly priests) he's killed, he and Cacambo flee.  


After a few more adventures, Candide and Cacambo wander into El Dorado, a geographically isolated utopia where the streets are covered with precious stones, there exist no priests, and all of the king's jokes are funny.Aldridge (1975), p. 254 Candide and Cacambo stay a month in El Dorado, but Candide is still in pain without Cunégonde, and expresses to the king his wish to leave. The king points out that this is a foolish idea, but generously helps them do so. The pair continue their journey, now accompanied by one hundred red pack sheep carrying provisions and incredible sums of money, which they slowly lose or have stolen over the next few adventures.

Candide and Cacambo eventually reach Suriname, where they split up: Cacambo travels to Buenos Aires to retrieve Lady Cunégonde, while Candide prepares to travel to Europe to await the two. Before leaving Surinam, Candide feels in need of companionship, so he interviews a number of local men who have been through various ill-fortunes and settles on a man named Martin.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bfb63c246d939b28bead4e635ac375d6" name="Moreau_Sucre_crop" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/bfb63c246d939b28bead4e635ac375d6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>