<document id="970eed35cee1a20ccae4e529b5683276-5.7" name="Candide" cat="17">
<text>
The conclusion of the novella, in which Candide finally dismisses his tutor's optimism, leaves unresolved what philosophy the protagonist is to accept in its stead. This element of ''Candide'' has been written about voluminously, perhaps above all others. The conclusion is enigmatic and its analysis is contentious.Leister (1985), p. 29


Voltaire develops no formal, systematic philosophy for the characters to adopt.Bottiglia (1951), pp. 723–724 The conclusion of the novel may be thought of not as a philosophical alternative to optimism, but as a prescribed practical outlook (though ''what'' it prescribes is in dispute). Many critics have concluded that one minor character or another is portrayed as having the right philosophy. For instance, a number believe that Martin is treated sympathetically, and that his character holds Voltaire's ideal philosophy—pessimism. Others disagree, citing Voltaire's negative descriptions of Martin's principles and the conclusion of the work in which Martin plays little part.Bottiglia (1951), p. 726

Within debates attempting to decipher the conclusion of ''Candide'' lies another primary ''Candide'' debate. This one concerns the degree to which Voltaire was advocating a pessimistic philosophy, by which Candide and his companions give up hope for a better world. Critics argue that the group's reclusion on the farm signifies Candide and his companions' loss of hope for the rest of the human race. This view is to be compared to a reading that presents Voltaire as advocating a melioristic philosophy and a precept committing the travellers to improving the world through metaphorical gardening. This debate, and others, focuses on the question of whether or not Voltaire was prescribing passive retreat from society, or active industrious contribution to it. Leister (1985), p. 26
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3baf9f1cb89163a6ef27918a9001f73d" name="Voltaire's_chateau,_Ferney" sectnum="5.7#1">../img/3baf9f1cb89163a6ef27918a9001f73d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>