<document id="97396873b31037b0370923527843dd80-3.3" name="Polish–Soviet_War" cat="29">
<text>
According to the British historian A.J.P. Taylor, the Polish–Soviet War "largely determined the course of European history for the next twenty years or more.  Unavowedly and almost unconsciously, Soviet leaders abandoned the cause of international revolution." It would be twenty years before the Bolsheviks would send their armies abroad to 'make revolution'.Davies, Norman, ''White Eagle, Red Star: the Polish-Soviet War, 1919–20'', Pimlico, 2003, ISBN 0-7126-0694-7. (First edition: New York, St. Martin's Press, inc., 1972.)Page ix. According to American sociologist Alexander Gella "the Polish victory had gained twenty years of independence not only for Poland, but at least for an entire central part of Europe.Aleksander Gella, ''Development of Class Structure in Eastern Europe: Poland and Her Southern Neighbors'', SUNY Press, 1988, ISBN 0-88706-833-2, 

After the peace negotiations Poland did not maintain all the territories it had controlled at the end of hostilities. Due to their losses in and after the Battle of Warsaw, the Soviets offered the Polish peace delegation substantial territorial concessions in the contested borderland areas, closely resembling the border between the Russian Empire and the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth before the first partition of 1772.Norman Davies, ''God's Playground. Vol. 2: 1795 to the Present''. Columbia University Press, 1982. ISBN 0-231-05352-5.  Polish resources were exhausted, however, and Polish public opinion was opposed to a prolongation of the war. The Polish government was also pressured by the League of Nations, and the negotiations were controlled by Dmowski's National Democrats: Piłsudski might have controlled the military, but parliament (Sejm) was controlled by Dmowski due in part because much of the territories in the East whose population would have voted for Pilsudski were controlled by the Bolsheviks at the time of the elections.  Timothy Snyder. (2003). ''The Reconstruction of Nations.'' New Haven: Yale University Press, pg. 68.   The peace negotiations were of a political nature. National Democrats, like Stanisław Grabski, who earlier had resigned his post to protest the Polish–Ukrainian alliance and now wielded much influence over the Polish negotiators, cared little for Piłsudski's Międzymorze; this post-war situation proved a death blow to Piłsudski's vision of reviving the multicultural Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth in the form of the Międzymorze.  Many of the hundreds of thousands of Poles left to live under Soviet rule by the Treaty of Riga were friendly to Pilsudski's ideas, and leaving them the national minorities within Soviet territory was the only way for the National Democrats, whose electoral heartland was in central and western Poland, to win elections.   

The National Democrats in charge of the state also had few concerns about the fate of their Ukrainian ally, Petlura, and cared little that their political opponent, Piłsudski, felt honor-bound by his treaty obligations;Norman Davies, ''God's Playground. Vol. 2: 1795 to the Present''. Columbia University Press, 1982. ISBN 0-231-05352-5. ) his opponents did not hesitate to scrap the treaty. The National Democrats wanted only the territory that they viewed as 'ethnically or historically Polish' or possible to polonize.Manfred F. Boemeke, Gerald D. Feldman, Elisabeth Glaser, ''The Treaty of Versailles: A Reassessment After 75 Years'', Cambridge University Press, 1998, ISBN 0-521-62132-1,  Despite the Red Army's crushing defeat at Warsaw and the willingness of Soviet chief negotiator Adolf Joffe to concede almost all disputed territory, National Democrats ideology allowed the Soviets to regain certain territories. The Peace of Riga was signed on March 18, 1921, splitting the disputed territories in Belarus and Ukraine between Poland and Russia.Snyder, op cit,  The treaty, which Piłsudski called an ''act of cowardice'', and for which he apologized to the Ukrainians, actually violated the terms of Poland's military alliance with the Directorate of Ukraine, which had explicitly prohibited a separate peace; Ukrainian allies of Poland suddenly found themselves interned by the Polish authorities. The internment worsened relations between Poland and its Ukrainian minority: those who supported Petliura felt that Ukraine had been betrayed by its Polish ally, a feeling that grew stronger due to the assimilationist policies of nationalist inter-war Poland towards its minorities. To a large degree, this inspired the growing tensions and eventual violence against Poles in the 1930s and 1940s.Snyder, op cit, 

The war and its aftermath also resulted in other controversies, such as the situation of prisoners of war of both sides, Karpus, Zbigniew, Alexandrowicz Stanisław, Waldemar Rezmer, ''Zwycięzcy za drutami. Jeńcy polscy w niewoli (1919–1922). Dokumenty i materiały'' (Victors Behind Barbed Wire: Polish Prisoners of War, 1919–1922: Documents and materials), Toruń, Wydawnictwo Uniwersytetu Mikołaja Kopernika w Toruniu, 1995, ISBN 83-231-0627-4. Karpus, Zbigniew, '''' Toruń 1997, ISBN 8371740204. English translation available: ''Russian and Ukrainian Prisoners of War and Internees in Poland, 1918–1924'', Wydawn. Adam Marszałek, 2001, ISBN 8371749562 treatment of the civilian population (in Russian).''‘Having burst through the front, Budyonny's cavalry would devastate the enemy's rear - burning, killing and looting as they went. These Red cavalrymen inspired an almost numbing sense of fear in their opponents  the very names Budyonny and Cossack terrified the Ukrainian population, and they moved into a state of neutrality or even hostility toward Petliura and the Poles..."’''from Richard Watt, 1979. Bitter Glory: Poland and its fate 1918–1939. New York: Simon & Shuster. ISBN 0-671-22625-8 Courtois, Stephane; Werth, Nicolas; Panne, Jean-Louis; Paczkowki, Andrzej; Bartosek, Karel; Margolin, Jean-Louis (1999). The Black Book of Communism. Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard University Press. ISBN 0-674-07608-7 and behaviour of some commanders like Stanisław Bułak-Bałachowicz  at modern Russian pro-White movement All-Russian military Union site. or Vadim Yakovlev.Isaac Babel, ''1920 Diary'', , Yale, 2002, ISBN 0-300-09313-6 The Polish military successes in the autumn of 1920 allowed Poland to capture the Vilnius region, where a Polish-dominated Governance Committee of Central Lithuania (''Komisja Rządząca Litwy Środkowej'') was formed. A plebiscite was conducted, and the Vilnius Sejm voted on February 20, 1922, for incorporation into Poland. This worsened Polish-Lithuanian relations for decades to come. However the loss of Vilnius might have safeguarded the very existence of the Lithuanian state in the interwar period. Despite an alliance with Soviets (Soviet-Lithuanian Treaty of 1920) and the war with Poland, Lithuania was very close to being invaded by the Soviets in summer 1920 and having been forcibly converted into a socialist republic. It was only the Polish victory against the Soviets in the Polish-Soviet War (and the fact that the Poles did not object to some form of Lithuanian independence) that derailed the Soviet plans and gave Lithuania an experience of interwar independence.Alfred Erich Senn, ''The Formation of the Lithuanian Foreign Office, 1918-1921'', Slavic Review, Vol. 21, No. 3. (Sep., 1962), pp. 500-507.: ''"A Bolshevik victory over the Poles would have certainly meant a move by the Lithuanian communists, backed by the Red Army, to overthrow the Lithuanian nationalist government... Kaunas, in effect, paid for its independence with the loss of Vilna."''Alfred Erich Senn, ''Lietuvos valstybes...'' p. 163: ''"If the Poles didn't stop the Soviet attack, Lithuania would fell to the Soviets... Polish victory costs the Lithuanians the city of Vilnius, but saved Lithuania itself."''Antanas Ruksa, ''Kovos del Lietuvos nepriklausomybes'', t.3, p.417: ''"In summer 1920 Russia was working on a communist revolution in Lithuania... From this disaster Lithuania was saved by the miracle at Vistula."''Jonas Rudokas,  (Polish translation of a Lithuanian article) "Veidas", 25 08 2005: '' "defended both Poland and Lithuanian from Soviet domination"'' Another controversy concerned the pogroms of Jews, which have caused the United States to send a commission lead by Henry Morgenthau, Sr. to investigate the matter.Joanna Beata Michlic, ''Poland's Threatening Other: The Image of the Jew from 1880 to the Present'', University of Nebraska Press, 2006, ISBN 0803232403


Military strategy in the Polish–Soviet War influenced Charles de Gaulle, then an instructor with the Polish Army who fought in several of the battles. He and Władysław Sikorski were the only military officers who, based on their experiences of this war, correctly predicted how the next one would be fought. Although they failed in the interbellum to convince their respective militaries to heed those lessons, early in World War II they rose to command of their armed forces in exile.Stanley S.Seidner, ''Marshal Edward Śmigły-Rydz Rydz and the Defense of Poland'', New York, 1978, ch, 5. The Polish–Soviet War also influenced Polish military doctrine, which for the next 20 years would place emphasis on the mobility of elite cavalry units.

In 1943, during the course of World War II, the subject of Poland's eastern borders was re-opened, and they were discussed at the Tehran Conference. Winston Churchill argued in favor of the 1920 Curzon Line rather than the Treaty of Riga's borders, and an agreement among the Allies to that effect was reached at the Yalta Conference in 1945. The Western Allies, despite having alliance treaties with Poland and despite Polish contribution also left Poland within the Soviet sphere of influence. This became known in Poland as the Western Betrayal.

Until 1989, while Communists held power in the People's Republic of Poland, the Polish–Soviet War was omitted or minimized in Polish and other Soviet bloc countries' history books, or was presented as a foreign intervention during the Russian Civil War to fit in with Communist ideology.Marc Ferro, ''The Use and Abuse of History: Or How the Past Is Taught to Children'', Routledge, 2004, ISBN 0-415-28592-5,
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="dfb53e7ae3763c60e5379854718a01bc" name="Powazki_1920" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/dfb53e7ae3763c60e5379854718a01bc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>