<document id="97c85e123d3e6bb5c4c2da98a1e3e0e5-4" name="Leo_Ornstein" cat="20">
<text>
In the early 1930s, Ornstein gave his last public performance.Pollack (2000) confirms Ornstein performed at a 1930 Copland–Sessions concert (p. 44). Stepner (1997), in his well-sourced notes, gives 1933 as the date of Ornstein's last public concert, though he does give the incorrect 1913 for ''Suicide in an Airplane.'' A few years later, he and his wife—the former Pauline Mallet-Prèvost, also a pianist—founded the Ornstein School of Music in Philadelphia.Broyles (2004) writes that the school was founded in 1934 (p. 81). Broyles and Von Glahn (2007) indicate that it was 1935 (p. 4). Anderson (2002a) says it was 1940. Among the students there, John Coltrane and Jimmy Smith would go on to major careers in jazz.Porter (1999), p. 33; Mathieson (2002), p. 53. The Ornsteins directed and taught at the school until it closed with their retirement in 1953. They essentially disappeared from public view until the mid-1970s, when they were tracked down by music historian Vivian Perlis: the couple was spending the winter in a Texas trailer park (they also had a home in New Hampshire). ''NewMusicBox'', April 1, 2002; web magazine of the American Music Center. Retrieved 1/30/07. Ornstein had continued to compose music; equipped with a powerful memory, he was not diligent about writing it all down and had not sought to publicize it for decades. Though his style had tempered greatly since the 1910s, it retained its unique character, and with his rediscovery came a new burst of productivity. In Gann's description, piano works composed by Ornstein in his eighties, such as ''Solitude'' and ''Rendezvous at the Lake'', featured melodies that "sprang through endless ornate curlicues that brought no other composer to mind."


 
In 1988, the ninety-five-year-old Ornstein wrote his Seventh Piano Sonata. With this composition Ornstein became, by a couple of years, the oldest published composer ever to produce a substantial new work.Broyles (2004), p. 81; Anderson (2002a). In 1990, at the age of ninety-seven, Ornstein's final work, the Eighth Piano Sonata, was completed and given its world premiere.  The names of the sonata's movements reflect not only the passage of a remarkable span of time, but an undimmed sense of humor and exploratory spirit: I. "Life's Turmoil and a Few Bits of Satire" / II. "A Trip to the Attic—A Tear or Two for a Childhood Forever Gone" (a. "The Bugler" / b. "A Lament for a Lost Boy" / c. "A Half-Mutilated Cradle—Berceuse" / d. "First Carousel Ride and Sounds of a Hurdy-Gurdy")Note that  for Marc-André Hamelin's performance of the Eighth Piano Sonata mistakenly refers to "Sources of a Hurdy-Gurdy"; the liner notes by Anderson (2002b) correctly state "Sounds of a Hurdy-Gurdy." / III. "Disciplines and Improvisations." Reviewing the work's New York debut, critic Anthony Tommasini wrote, "Between the roaring craziness of the first and third movements, the middle movement is a suite of four short musical musings on childhood mementos discovered in an attic. Though completely incongruous, the shift in tone is audacious and the music disarming. The audience listened raptly, then erupted in applause."

In early 2002, Ornstein died in Green Bay, Wisconsin.  At the age of 108, he was among the longest-lived of composers.Midgette (2002).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f062e6fbf7b5e4e66e6af781136aa4b3" name="Leo_Ornstein_around_90" sectnum="4#1">../img/f062e6fbf7b5e4e66e6af781136aa4b3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>