<document id="985118344ef3adb3e3806ce6694da609-6" name="Edward_VII_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
King Edward VII in coronation robes. Note the Royal Sceptre in its original form, shortly before the addition of the Cullinan I Diamond.
When Queen Victoria died on 22 January 1901, Edward became King of the United Kingdom, Emperor of India and, in an innovation, King of the British Dominions.Middlemas, p. 104 He chose to reign under the name Edward VII, instead of Albert Edward—the name his mother had intended for him to use,No English or British sovereign has ever reigned under a double name. declaring that he did not wish to "undervalue the name of Albert" and diminish the status of his father with whom among royalty the name Albert should stand alone. The number VII was occasionally omitted in Scotland, even by the national church, in deference to protests that the previous Edwards were English kings who had "been excluded from Scotland by battle". J. B. Priestley recalled, "I was only a child when he succeeded Victoria in 1901, but I can testify to his extraordinary popularity. He was in fact the most popular king England had known since the earlier 1660's."Priestley, p. 9

He donated his parents' house, Osborne on the Isle of Wight, to the state and continued to live at Sandringham.The Duke of Windsor, p. 14 He could afford to be magnanimous; it was claimed that he was the first heir to succeed to the throne in credit. Edward's finances had been ably managed by Sir Dighton Probyn, Comptroller of the Household, and had benefited from advice from Edward's Jewish financier friends, such as Ernest Cassel, Maurice de Hirsch and the Rothschild family.Middlemas, pp. 38, 84, 96; Priestley, p. 32 At a time of widespread anti-Semitism, Edward attracted criticism for openly socialising with Jews.



Edward VII and Alexandra were crowned at Westminster Abbey on 9 August 1902 by the 80-year-old Archbishop of Canterbury, Frederick Temple, who died only four months later. Edward's coronation had originally been scheduled for 26 June, but two days before on 24 June, Edward was diagnosed with appendicitis. Thanks to developments in anaesthesia and antisepsis in the preceding 50 years, he underwent a life-saving operation, performed by Sir Frederick Treves. This was at a time when appendicitis was generally not treated operatively and carried a high mortality rate. Treves, with the support of Lord Lister, performed a then-radical operation of draining the infected appendix through a small incision. The next day, Edward was sitting up in bed, smoking a cigar.The Duke of Windsor, p. 20 Two weeks later, it was announced that the King was out of danger. Treves was honoured with a baronetcy (which Edward had arranged before the operation)Bentley-Cranch, p. 127 and appendix surgery entered the medical mainstream.

Edward refurbished the royal palaces, reintroduced the traditional ceremonies, such as the State Opening of Parliament, that his mother had foregone, and founded new orders of decorations, such as the Order of Merit, to recognise contributions to the arts and sciences.Bentley-Cranch, pp. 122–139 The Shah of Persia, Mozzafar-al-Din, visited England in 1902, expecting to receive the Order of the Garter. Edward refused to give this high honour to the Shah because the order was meant to be his personal gift and the Foreign Secretary, Lord Lansdowne, had promised the order without his consent. Edward also objected to inducting a Muslim into a Christian order of chivalry. His refusal threatened to damage British attempts to gain influence in Persia,Hattersley, pp. 39–40 but Edward resented his ministers' attempts to reduce the King's traditional powers. Eventually, he relented and Britain sent a special embassy to the Shah with a full Order of the Garter the following year.Middlemas, pp. 125–126
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4629721531052c5ef6a5254670c6d60c" name="Edward_VII_UK_and_successors" sectnum="6#1">../img/4629721531052c5ef6a5254670c6d60c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>