<document id="985118344ef3adb3e3806ce6694da609-10" name="Edward_VII_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
Statue of Edward VII in Queen Victoria Gardens, Melbourne


Statues of Edward can be found throughout the former empire, such as those in Waterloo Place, London, Union Street, Aberdeen, Queen's Park, Toronto, Franklin Square, Hobart, Queen Victoria Gardens, Melbourne, and outside the Royal Botanic Gardens, Sydney.

The lead ship of a new class of battleships, launched in 1903, was named in his honour. Many schools in England are named after Edward; two of the largest are in Melton Mowbray and Sheffield. King Edward Memorial (KEM) Hospital in India, the King Edward Medical University in Pakistan, King Edward Memorial Hospital for Women in Subiaco, Western Australia, and the King Edward VII College of Medicine student hostel in Singapore (part of Yong Loo Lin School of Medicine) carry King Edward's name. The Parque Eduardo VII in Lisbon, King Edward Avenue in Vancouver and King Edward Cigars are also named after him.

As king, Edward VII proved a greater success than anyone had expected, but he was already an old man and had little time left to fulfil the role. In his short reign, he ensured that his second son and heir, George V, was better prepared to take the throne. Contemporaries described their relationship as more like affectionate brothers than father and son,Bentley-Cranch, p. 155 and on Edward's death George wrote in his diary that he had lost his "best friend and the best of fathers ... I never had a  word with him in my life. I am heart-broken and overwhelmed with grief".King George V's diary, 6 May 1910. Royal Archives Edward received criticism for his apparent pursuit of self-indulgent pleasure but he received great praise for his affable and kind good manners, and his diplomatic skill. As his grandson wrote, "his lighter side ... obscured the fact that he had both insight and influence."The Duke of Windsor, p. 69 "He had a tremendous zest for pleasure but he also had a real sense of duty", wrote J. B. Priestley.Priestley, p. 25 Lord Esher wrote that Edward was "kind and debonair and not undignified – but too human".Hattersley, p. 17 Edward VII is buried at St. George's Chapel, Windsor Castle. As Barbara Tuchman noted in ''The Guns of August'', his funeral marked "the greatest assemblage of royalty and rank ever gathered in one place and, of its kind, the last".

Edward had been afraid that his nephew, the German Emperor Wilhelm II, would tip Europe into war.Middlemas, pp. 176, 179 Four years after Edward's death, World War I broke out. The naval reforms and the Anglo-French alliance he had supported, as well as the relationships between his extended royal family, were put to the test. The war marked the end of the Edwardian way of life.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="21c7b7808096a303bafefb477af67604" name="Parque_Eduardo_Setimo" sectnum="10#1">../img/21c7b7808096a303bafefb477af67604.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>