<document id="985118344ef3adb3e3806ce6694da609-4" name="Edward_VII_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
Once widowed, Queen Victoria effectively withdrew from public life. Shortly after Prince Albert's death, she arranged for Edward to embark on an extensive tour of the Middle East, visiting Egypt, Jerusalem, Damascus, Beirut and Constantinople.Bentley-Cranch, pp. 40–42 As soon as he returned to Britain, preparations were made for his engagement, which was sealed at Laeken in Belgium on 9 September 1862.Bentley-Cranch, p. 44 Edward and Alexandra married at St. George's Chapel, Windsor, on 10 March 1863. Edward was 21; Alexandra was 18.



Edward and his wife established Marlborough House as their London residence and Sandringham House in Norfolk as their country retreat. They entertained on a lavish scale. Their marriage met with disapproval in certain circles because most of Queen Victoria's relations were German, and Denmark was at loggerheads with Germany over the territories of Schleswig and Holstein. When Alexandra's father inherited the throne of Denmark in November 1863, the German Confederation took the opportunity to invade and annex Schleswig-Holstein. Queen Victoria was of two minds whether it was a suitable match given the political climate.Middlemas, p. 35 After the couple's marriage, she expressed anxiety about their socialite lifestyle and attempted to dictate to them on various matters, including the names of their children.

Edward had mistresses throughout his married life. He socialised with actress Lillie Langtry; Lady Randolph Churchill (mother of Winston Churchill);Letters written by Edward to Lady Randolph may have "signified no more than a flirtation" but were "ritten in a strain of undue familiarity" (). Daisy Greville, Countess of Warwick; actress Sarah Bernhardt; Alice Keppel; singer Hortense Schneider; prostitute Giulia Barucci; and wealthy humanitarian Agnes Keyser. At least fifty-five liaisons are conjectured.. They are listed at http://anthonyjcamp.com/page9.htm. How far these relationships went is not always clear. Edward always strove to be discreet, but this did not prevent society gossip or press speculation.Middlemas, pp. 74–80

In 1869, Sir Charles Mordaunt, a British Member of Parliament, threatened to name Edward as co-respondent in his divorce suit. Ultimately, he did not do so but Edward was called as a witness in the case in early 1870. It was shown that Edward had visited the Mordaunts's house while Sir Charles was away sitting in the House of Commons. Although nothing further was proven and Edward denied he had committed adultery, the suggestion of impropriety was damaging.

The story that Queen Alexandra invited Edward's last mistress, society beauty Alice Keppel, to the King's death-bed in 1910Priestley, pp. 18, 180 is a myth that Alice herself propagated. In reality Alice was, most reluctantly, asked at the King's request and, in a wild fit of hysterics, she was ejected shrieking, "I never did any harm, there was nothing wrong between us. What is to become of me?";  One of Alice Keppel's great-granddaughters, Camilla Parker Bowles, became the wife of Charles, Prince of Wales, one of Edward's great-great grandsons. It was rumoured that Camilla's grandmother, Sonia Keppel (born in May 1900), was the illegitimate daughter of Edward, but she was "almost certainly" the daughter of George Keppel, whom she resembled. Edward never acknowledged any illegitimate children. Alexandra is believed to have been aware of many of his affairs and to have accepted them.Middlemas, p. 89
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="06071102f78422f117f8b865b971ce27" name="King_Edward_VII_and_Queen_Alexandra_-_Wedding_-1863_-cropped" sectnum="4#1">../img/06071102f78422f117f8b865b971ce27.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>