<document id="986888cdb8ad13a17ffa780663d5a490-3" name="Margate_F.C." cat="26">
<text>
The stadium in Hartsdown Park has been Margate's home since 1929, the same year the park itself opened to the public.  Little development of the stadium took place until 2002, when the club launched an ambitious scheme to completely redevelop the site.  The club moved out and the old stadium, which was constructed mainly from timber and corrugated iron, was demolished in early 2003, but the local council disputed the plans submitted.  Although planned to be completed by August 2003, the redevelopment dragged on for three years, mired in issues regarding planning permission for the commercial facilities the club wanted to build in addition to the stadium itself.   The team spent three years ground-sharing with other Kent clubs, but club officials' failure to confirm a return date to Hartsdown led to Margate's expulsion from the Conference National in 2004.  In 2005 the club was finally able to return to the ground, albeit with pre-fabricated stands and temporary buildings in place. 

The club's ultimate plan involves a stadium with a capacity of 5,000 forming part of a complex incorporating a hotel, fitness centre, conference centre, all-weather pitch and ten 5-a-side pitches.  Although it was announced that work on the 5-a-side pitch complex was to begin in May 2007, ground was not in fact broken for a further four months.  The Hartsdown Football 5s officially opened on 9 December 2007, with a 32 team tournament.  Former Premier League players Paul Merson, Ray Parlour, Kenny Sansom, Kerry Dixon, Neville Southall, Clayton Blackmore, Mark Bright, and Steve Sedgley were guests as the centre opened. The Hartsdown Football 5s will see an income stream to the football club, as well as a community use scheme which gives access to the centre for local schools.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="02237a16510bd8b2e4091be714505724" name="HartsdownPark" sectnum="3#1">../img/02237a16510bd8b2e4091be714505724.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>