<document id="987ec21d72f5bb93667b003c5d351772-1.3" name="Blackburn_Olympic_F.C." cat="26">
<text>
The following season, Olympic again reached the semi-finals of the FA Cup, as did Blackburn Rovers.  When the draw for the semi-finals was made, the club was paired with Queen's Park in one match and Rovers with Notts County in the other, setting up the possibility of the two teams meeting in the final.  The Olympic team, however, were outclassed and defeated 4&ndash;0 by their Scottish opponents.  The club lodged an appeal with the FA based on the encroachment onto the pitch of some of the 16,000 spectators, but to no avail.Phythian, p. 61  Rovers went on to defeat Queen's Park in the final.

The club was never again able to achieve this level of success.  In the 1884&ndash;85 season, Olympic lost in the second round of the FA Cup to rivals Rovers, who went on to cement their position as the town's leading team by winning the competition for the second consecutive season.  The threat of a schism within the sport was averted in 1885 when the FA agreed to legalise professionalism.  In a town the size of Blackburn, however, Olympic found it hard to compete for spectators and sponsors with the longer-established and more successful Rovers, and as a result could not pay wages on a par with those offered by that club or by other professional clubs in Lancashire.  In 1886 the club's committee was forced to reduce the players' wages to a quarter of what was being offered by Preston North End.  Many of the team's key players walked out in response and were quickly signed by wealthier clubs.Phythian, p. 71

The Football League, the world's first association football league, was formed in 1888 by the leading clubs of the Midlands and North.  Aston Villa chairman William McGregor, the driving force behind the new competition, put in place a rule stating that only one club from each town or city could join, and chose Rovers, rather than Olympic, to be Blackburn's entrant.  Some of the clubs not invited to join the League, including Olympic, formed The Combination, but this was a poorly organised competition which attracted only small crowds and collapsed before the end of the 1888&ndash;89 season.  Beset by heavy debts, the club's committee announced in early 1889 that all professional players were being released from their contracts with immediate effect and that henceforth the club would employ only amateur players.Phythian, p. 79  This desperate measure came too late to save the club, which closed down in September 1889.  Blackburn Olympic's last match was a defeat away to Everton.  An unrelated amateur club based in the town adopted the name Blackburn Olympic in 1959.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0e6e9c158efea51a76dfb9ceb3ced272" name="Blackburnrovers_facup-1883-84" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/0e6e9c158efea51a76dfb9ceb3ced272.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>