<document id="98fbb43a04146f28f65e9a6b0f5a144f-2.1" name="Joel_Selwood" cat="26">
<text>
Selwood was drafted by the Geelong Football Club with their first selection, and was the seventh overall draft pick in the 2006 AFL Draft.Walls, R, , ''The Age'', 23 June 2007, accessed 3 October 2007 Although many recruiting scouts viewed him as "the finest pure footballer in the draft",Gleeson, M, , ''The Age'', 26 November 2007, accessed 19 September 2007 and a potential top pick, there was still concern surrounding the durability of his knee. Nonetheless, as the equal highest-ever draft pick for the Cats,Slattery, p. 18. Selwood made his debut in the opening round of the 2007 AFL premiership season and missed only four games during the regular season., footywire.com, accessed 21 July 2009


Selwood's transition to the AFL drew positive comments throughout the footballing community;Slattery, p. 81. former Brisbane coach Leigh Matthews noted how "from  first game ... he looked like he had played 200 of them".Morton, J. , Australian Football League & Bigpond, 13 August 2007. accessed 22 May 2008 Geelong coach Mark Thompson labelled the 18-year-old Selwood the best youngster to have come under his tutelage during his time at the club.Gullan, S, , ''The Herald Sun'', 14 July 2007, accessed 19 September 2007Witham, J, , Australian Football League & Bigpond, 5 September 2007, accessed 19 September 2007 From the beginning, Selwood showed an ability to influence games; in just his fourth appearance he led his older and more experienced teammates with a game of 25 disposals and nine tackles. This achievement, described as inspiring,Gullan, p. 70. earned him an AFL Rising Star Award nomination. The Geelong coaching staff had a highlights package made of this performance, to screen to the rest of the team during the match review later that week.Gullan, p. 79. Selwood's impact on the game as a first–year player prompted numerous comparisons to Chris Judd, who a few years earlier had been lauded for his first-year success as an 18-year-old.

At the conclusion of the home and away period, Selwood's regular contributions resulted in several individual accolades. Polling 44 out of a possible 45 votes, he was awarded the inaugural Ron Evans Medal as the winner of the AFL Rising Star Award.Shields, J ", ''The Geelong Advertiser'', 6 September 2007, accessed 5 December 2007 Selwood earned the maximum five votes from eight of the nine judges, the other awarding him four out of five. This meant that eight of the nine judges rated him as the best nominee., Australian Football League & Bigpond, 5 September 2007, accessed 19 September 2007 Selwood was also awarded the prestigious AFLPA Best First Year Player Award, winning  over 70% of all votes from his peers. He became only the fourth player to win both the major awards for first–year players., ''The Herald Sun'', 29 September 2007, accessed 29 September 2007



Having helped Geelong finish first on the ladder and win the McClelland Trophy, Selwood made his finals debut in the 2nd Qualifying Final against the Kangaroos (now North Melbourne) at the Melbourne Cricket Ground (MCG).Boulon, M, , ''The Age'', 6 September 2007, accessed 5 December 2007 In front of nearly 80,000 spectators, Selwood amassed 22 disposals, five marks, five clearances, six inside 50s, five tackles, and five score assists, helping Geelong to a club finals record 106 point victory.Lienert, S. , ''Perth Now'', 9 September 2008, accessed 26 May 2008 Although Selwood struggled to contribute in the Preliminary Final against Collingwood two weeks later,Townley, p. 101. he returned to form for the 2007 AFL Grand Final at the MCG against Port Adelaide., ''The Geelong Advertiser'', 29 September 2007, accessed 5 December 2007 With 18 disposals, five marks, five clearances&mdash;the most of any Geelong player&mdash;seven inside 50s, four tackles, and an equal game-high four score assists,, ''The Bendigo Advertiser'', 1 October 2007, accessed 9 February 2008 Selwood helped the Cats to a record 119 point win., Australian Football League & Bigpond, 30 September 2007, accessed 5 December 2007 At 19 years of age, Selwood became the youngest person to play in a winning Grand Final team in 10 years.Williams, R, , Fox Sports, 1 October 2007, accessed 1 October 2007 He was also the first to win the AFL Rising Star Award and play in a premiership side within the same season, making him one of the most accomplished first year players in league history.Sherwood, M, , ''The Canberra Times'', 3 October 2007, accessed 8 November 2007Slattery, p. 48. Selwood's debut year achievements resulted in his becoming AFL's highest-paid first–year player.Barrett, D. , ''The Herald Sun'', 1 October 2007, accessed 26 May 2008

Selwood finished the season ranked first among all first–year players in several major statistical categories; total possessions (405), disposals per game (19.3), kicks (216), handpasses (189), marks (109), tackles (94)&mdash;the most ever by any first–year AFL player, Australian Football League & Bigpond, accessed 13 May 2008&mdash;and tackles per game (4.5). His 23 score assists during the season also ranked him within the top ten in the league. Selwood added to his list of first year honours at season's end with the Geelong Football Club Best First Year Player Award, along with a top 20 placing in the Club Champion award., Australian Football League & Bigpond, accessed 4 November 2007 He also received several media end of year sporting awards., ''The Bendigo Advertiser'', 13 October 2007, accessed 4 November 2007
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="de09cb9c6aee829e8ce67948a2392028" name="Joel_Selwood_in_2007" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/de09cb9c6aee829e8ce67948a2392028.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>