<document id="996f1b5fcfba69355c2c8b35a42fd71e-1" name="Choe_Bu" cat="14">
<text>
Choe Bu of the Jeonju Choe clan was born in 1454 in the prefectural town of Naju in Jeollanam-do, Korea.Goodrich (1976), 257. Choe passed the ''jinsa'' examinations in 1477, which was a lower examination that did not immediately ensure a post in government; rather, it permitted enrollment in the National Academy, or ''Seonggyungwan'', where he could study further for the higher ''mungwa'' examinations.Choe (1974), 614. In preparation for the exams, he studied the Five Classics as Confucian students had for centuries, but he also was taught the emphasis of the Four Books of Zhu Xi (1130&ndash;1200),Khair et al. (2006), 161. which was in line with the Neo-Confucian doctrine first accepted in mainstream Chinese education during the mid-13th century.Ebrey et al. (2006), 169. He passed his first civil service examination in 1482 and a second civil service examination in 1486, qualifying him for an immediate post in government. In a career as a graduate scholar-official that spanned 18 years, Choe was privileged with various positions. He held posts in the Hodang Library, printing office, and the National Academy. He also held posts involving the military, such as on the military supplies commission, with the office of the inspector-general, and with the Yongyang garrison. The culmination of his career was his promotion as a minister of the Directorate of Ceremonies in the capital, a distinguished office. Choe Bu was also one of the scholars who aided in the compilation of the ''Dongguk Tonggam'' in 1485, a history of Korea from ancient times. Choe was learned in Confucian ethics, Chinese letters, Chinese poetry, and well versed in Korean history, geography, and famous people; all this later helped him to dispel the notion of Chinese that he was a Japanese pirate instead of a Korean official who had unfortunately shipwrecked in China. In 1487, Choe Bu was sent to Jeju Island to check the registers for escaped slaves from the mainland.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="62cb7169904518894020d2709808a15f" name="Daegu_hyanggyo_myeongnyundang" sectnum="1#1">../img/62cb7169904518894020d2709808a15f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>