<document id="9a40681bcb7c5225af47b19f5c8b8ed2-1.7" name="Pixies" cat="20">
<text>
The Pixies performing in Seattle (2004).
In the 11 years following the break-up, rumors frequently circulated regarding a reunion. Though Frank Black steadfastly dismissed them, he did begin to incorporate an increasing number of Pixies songs in his sets with the Catholics, and occasionally included Santiago and Lovering in his solo work. In late 2003 a press release from Black's publicist officially confirmed a reunion would occur in the spring of 2004.  The Pixies played their first reunion concert on April 13, 2004 at The Fine Line Music Cafe in Minneapolis, Minnesota, and a warmup tour through the U.S. and Canada was followed by an appearance at the Coachella Valley Music and Arts Festival.  The band then spent much of 2004 touring throughout Brazil, Europe, Japan, and the U.S.

The 2004 reunion of the Pixies was the subject of the 2006 documentary,  ''LoudQUIETloud.''

In June 2004, the band released a new single, "Bam Thwok" () exclusively on the iTunes Music Store. The song reached number one in the British download chart.  4AD released ''Wave of Mutilation: The Best of the Pixies'', along with a companion DVD.  The band also contributed a rendition of "Ain't That Pretty At All" to the Warren Zevon tribute album ''Enjoy Every Sandwich''.

2005 saw the band make appearances at the Lollapalooza and Sasquatch! music festivals. The band also played at European events such as the Reading and Leeds Festivals, and in Fife, Scotland as part of the T in the Park music festival, as well as V festival in Stafford and Chelmsford.  In August, the band performed an entirely acoustic set (after a warm-up acoustic set in Albany, New York) at the Newport Folk Festival. Also has a complete list of the band's summer 2004 tour dates

The band continued to make appearances through 2006 and 2007, culminating in their first-ever appearances in Australia.  By early 2008, however, following abortive attempts to record a new album, Black began stating in interviews that the reunion was over.

In late August 2008, Black Francis told NME.com that he may be willing to return to the recording with his former bandmates, saying "It's just a waiting game right now. Whatever we do in the future is gonna have to be fresh. I have to see if the band as a whole wants to go into the recording studio for a new record. That makes sense on some level. For us, there's gotta be an angle. It can't be just playing our old songs over and over."

On March 13, 2009, they were announced as playing the 2009 Isle of Wight Festival, appearing before Sunday night headliner Neil Young.
On March 26, 2009, they were announced as playing the 2009 Where The Action Is festival in Stockholm, Sweden.

On April 21, 2009, the band confirmed that a new release would be available for pre-order on June 15., ''NME'', 21 April 2009  The release, ''Minotaur'', will be a box set of the band's previous albums plus bonus artwork, available both in Deluxe and Limited editions. The artworks will be created by Vaughan Oliver and Simon Larbalestier, the men responsible for the original album designs and artworks. ''Minotaur'' will be available through the Artists in Residence website.

In order to celebrate the 20th anniversary of the release of ''Doolittle'', the Pixies announced a small European tour in October 2009 taking in London, Glasgow, Amsterdam, Dublin and Frankfurt where they will be playing the album and all relevant B-sides from the singles.  Tickets sold out almost instantaneously. At the end of August 2009, it was announced that the Doolittle tour would be extended to Australasia in early 2010, including a first ever visit to New Zealand. 

In June 2009 Black Francis was quoted as saying in the ''NME'' that the Pixies would return to the studio to record their sixth full length album some time during 2010. In addition, he stated that he would like it to be a film and music tie-in project involving a big Hollywood director such as Quentin Tarantino, but would be open to the idea of recording a more conventional album should this project fall through., ''NME'', 25 June 2009
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6642ca622bc6e1b2afe813e24ff22e97" name="Pixies_in_Kansas_City,_October_1,_2004" sectnum="1.7#1">../img/6642ca622bc6e1b2afe813e24ff22e97.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>