<document id="9a820165ebf67ce8e19ab5b503a276a3-2.2" name="Turkish_literature" cat="17">
<text>
The folk poetry tradition in Turkish literature, as indicated above, was strongly influenced by the Islamic Sufi and Shi'a traditions. Furthermore, as partly evidenced by the prevalence of the still existent ''aşık''/''ozan'' tradition, the dominant element in Turkish folk poetry has always been song. The development of folk poetry in Turkish—which began to emerge in the 13th century with such important writers as Yunus Emre, Sultan Veled, and Şeyyâd Hamza—was given a great boost when, on 13 May 1277, Karamanoğlu Mehmet Bey declared Turkish the official state language of Anatolia's powerful Karamanid state;Karamanoğlu Mehmet Bey's declaration is as follows: ''Şimden gerü dîvânda, dergâhta, bârgâhta, mecliste ve meydanda Türkçeden başka dil kullanılmayacaktır'' ("From this day forward, no language other than Turkish will be used in the court, in the ''tekke'', in the palace, in the government, or in public") (Selçuk Üniversitesi Uzaktan Eğitim Programı (SUZEP). As a measure of the extent of the influence against which Karamanoğlu Mehmet Bey was fighting, his declaration itself contains three words of Arabic origin (دیوان ''dîvân'' or "court", مجلس ''meclis'' or "government", and ميدان ''meydân'' or "public") and two of Persian origin (درگاه ''dergâh'' or "''tekke''" and بارگاه ''bârgâh'' or "palace"). subsequently, many of the tradition's greatest poets would continue to emerge from this region. 

There are, broadly speaking, two traditions of Turkish folk poetry:

* the ''aşık''/''ozan'' tradition, which—although much influenced by religion, as mentioned above—was for the most part a secular tradition;
* the explicitly religious tradition, which emerged from the gathering places (''tekke''s) of the Sufi religious orders and Shi'a groups.

Much of the poetry and song of the ''aşık''/''ozan'' tradition, being almost exclusively oral until the 19th century, remains anonymous. There are, however, a few well-known ''aşık''s from before that time whose names have survived together with their works: the aforementioned Köroğlu (16th century); Karacaoğlan (1606?–1689?), who may be the best-known of the pre-19th century ''aşık''s; Dadaloğlu (1785?–1868?), who was one of the last of the great ''aşık''s before the tradition began to dwindle somewhat in the late 19th century; and several others. The ''aşık''s were essentially minstrels who travelled through Anatolia performing their songs on the ''bağlama'', a mandolin-like instrument whose paired strings are considered to have a symbolic religious significance in Alevi/Bektashi culture. Despite the decline of the ''aşık''/''ozan'' tradition in the 19th century, it experienced a significant revival in the 20th century thanks to such outstanding figures as Aşık Veysel Şatıroğlu (1894–1973), Aşık Mahzuni Şerif (1938–2002), Neşet Ertaş (1943– ), and many others.


The explicitly religious folk tradition of ''tekke'' literature shared a similar basis with the ''aşık''/''ozan'' tradition in that the poems were generally intended to be sung, generally in religious gatherings, making them somewhat akin to Western hymns (Turkish ''ilahi''). One major difference from the ''aşık''/''ozan'' tradition, however, is that—from the very beginning—the poems of the ''tekke'' tradition were written down. This was because they were produced by revered religious figures in the literate environment of the ''tekke'', as opposed to the milieu of the ''aşık''/''ozan'' tradition, where the majority could not read or write. The major figures in the tradition of ''tekke'' literature are: Yunus Emre (1240?–1320?), who is one of the most important figures in all of Turkish literature; Süleyman Çelebi (?–1422), who wrote a highly popular long poem called ''Vesîletü'n-Necât'' (وسيلة النجاة "The Means of Salvation", but more commonly known as the ''Mevlid''), concerning the birth of the Islamic prophet Muhammad; Kaygusuz Abdal (1397–?), who is widely considered the founder of Alevi/Bektashi literature; and Pir Sultan Abdal (?–1560), whom many consider to be the pinnacle of that literature.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a1f8252870454d6b49a6e01ee0ea7735" name="Kaygusuz_Abdal" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/a1f8252870454d6b49a6e01ee0ea7735.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>