<document id="9a820165ebf67ce8e19ab5b503a276a3-4.9" name="Turkish_literature" cat="17">
<text>
In 1908, Sultan Abdülhamid II had instituted a constitutional government, and the parliament subsequently elected was composed almost entirely of members of the Committee of Union and Progress (also known as the "Young Turks"). The Young Turks (ژون تورکلر ''Jön Türkler'') had opposed themselves to the increasingly authoritarian Ottoman government, and soon came to identify themselves with a specifically Turkish national identity. Along with this notion developed the idea of a Turkish and even pan-Turkish nation (Turkish: ''millet''), and so the literature of this period came to be known as "National Literature" (Turkish: ''millî edebiyyât''). It was during this period that the Persian- and Arabic-inflected Ottoman Turkish language was definitively turned away from as a vehicle for written literature, and that literature began to assert itself as being specifically Turkish, rather than Ottoman.

At first, this movement crystallized around the magazine ''Genç Kalemler'' (کنج قلملر; "Young Pens"), which was begun in the city of Selânik in 1911 by the three writers who were most representative of the movement: Ziya Gökalp (1876–1924), a sociologist and thinker; Ömer Seyfettin (1884–1920), a short-story writer; and Ali Canip Yöntem (1887–1967), a poet. In ''Genç Kalemler'''s first issue, an article entitled "New Language" (Turkish: "''Yeni Lisan''") pointed out that Turkish literature had previously looked for inspiration either to the East as in the Ottoman Divan tradition, or to the West as in the ''Edebiyyât-ı Cedîde'' and ''Fecr-i Âtî'' movements, without ever turning to Turkey itself.Muhtar, et al. This latter was the National Literature movement's primary aim.

The intrinsically nationalistic character of ''Genç Kalemler'', however, quickly took a decidedly chauvinistic turn,Viz. Elif Şafak's characterization of Ömer Seyfettin's story "''Primo Türk Çocuğu''" ("Primo: The Turkish Lad"), Şafak 2005. and other writers—many of whom, like Yakup Kadri Karaosmanoğlu, had been a part of the ''Fecr-i Âtî'' movement—began to emerge from within the matrix of the National Literature movement to counter this trend. Some of the more influential writers to come out of this less far-rightist branch of the National Literature movement were the poet Mehmet Emin Yurdakul (1869–1944), the early feminist novelist Halide Edip Adıvar (1884–1964), and the short-story writer and novelist Reşat Nuri Güntekin (1889–1956).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="31f28c909fe9c161d7093d2903c2253b" name="Genc_Kalemler" sectnum="4.9#1">../img/31f28c909fe9c161d7093d2903c2253b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>