<document id="9a820165ebf67ce8e19ab5b503a276a3-3.6" name="Turkish_literature" cat="17">
<text>
By the early 19th century, the Ottoman Empire had become moribund. Attempts to right this situation had begun during the reign of Sultan Selim III, from 1789 to 1807, but were continuously thwarted by the powerful Janissary corps. As a result, only after Sultan Mahmud II had abolished the Janissary corps in 1826 was the way paved for truly effective reforms (Ottoman Turkish: تنظيمات ''tanzîmât'').

These reforms finally came to the empire during the Tanzimat period of 1839–1876, when much of the Ottoman system was reorganized along largely French lines. The Tanzimat reforms "were designed both to modernize the empire and to forestall foreign intervention".Mansel, 266

Along with reforms to the Ottoman system, serious reforms were also undertaken in the literature, which had become nearly as moribund as the empire itself. Broadly, these literary reforms can be grouped into two areas:

* changes brought to the language of Ottoman written literature;
* the introduction into Ottoman literature of previously unknown genres.

The reforms to the literary language were undertaken because the Ottoman Turkish language was thought by the reformists to have effectively lost its way. It had become more divorced than ever from its original basis in Turkish, with writers using more and more words and even grammatical structures derived from Persian and Arabic, rather than Turkish.This view of Ottoman Turkish and its works as derivative of Arabic and, especially, Persian has begun to be challenged in recent years. In an essay on Şeyh Gâlib, for example, Victoria Holbrook states: "The slur that Ottoman poetry in general imitated the Persian ... is based on a misunderstanding of Ottoman poetical conventions and a confounding of notions of 'imitation'." (Holbrook, 442) Meanwhile, however, the Turkish folk literature tradition of Anatolia, away from the capital Constantinople, came to be seen as an ideal. Accordingly, many of the reformists called for written literature to turn away from the Divan tradition and towards the folk tradition; this call for change can be seen, for example, in a famous statement by the poet and reformist Ziya Pasha (1829–1880):

''Our language is not Ottoman; it is Turkish. What makes up our poetic canon is not ''gazel''s and ''kasîde''s, but rather ''kayabaşı''s, ''üçleme''s, and ''çöğür''s''''Kayabaşı'', ''üçleme'', and ''çöğür'' were all seen as part of the Turkish folk tradition: a ''kayabaşı'' was a sort of rural ballad or shepherd's song; an ''üçleme'' was a three-part tale or narrative song; and a ''çöğür'' was a mandolin-like musical instrument associated with the ''aşık''/''ozan'' tradition.'', which some of our poets dislike, thinking them crude. But just let those with the ability exert the effort on this road , and what powerful personalities will soon be born!''"Bizim dilimiz Osmanlıca değil, Türkçedir. Şiirimizde divanları dolduran gazelle kaside değil, bazılarının vezinsiz diye beğenmedikleri 'kayabaşı', 'üçleme' ve 'çöğür'lerdir. İstidat sahiplerimiz hele bu yola bir kere himmet etsinler, az vakitte ne kudretli şahsiyetler yetişir" (Karaalioğlu, ''Ziya Paşa'', 39).
At the same time as this call—which reveals something of a burgeoning national consciousness—was being made, new literary genres were being introduced into Ottoman literature, primarily the novel and the short story. This trend began in 1861, with the translation into Ottoman Turkish of François Fénelon's 1699 novel ''Les aventures de Télémaque'', by Yusuf Kâmil Pasha, Grand Vizier to Sultan Abdülaziz. What is widely recognized as the first Turkish novel, ''Taaşuk-u Tal'at ve Fitnat'' (تعشق طلعت و فطنت; "Tal'at and Fitnat In Love") by Şemsettin Sami (1850–1904), was published just ten years later, in 1872.There had actually been, according to , five other earlier or contemporaneous works of fiction that were clearly distinct from earlier prose traditions in both Divan and folk literature, and that approximate novelistic form. Among these five works is the ''Muhayyelât'' of Ali Aziz Efendi, cited above. Another, 1851's ''Akabi Hikâyesi'' ("''Akabi's Story''"), written by the Armenian Vartan Pasha (Hovsep Vartanian) using the Armenian script and for an Armenian audience was, according to Andreas Tietze, "the first genuine modern novel written and published in Turkey" (cited in Gökalp 188). The introduction of such new genres into Turkish literature can be seen as part of a trend towards Westernization that continues to be felt in Turkey to this day.

Due to historically close ties with France—strengthened during the Crimean War of 1854–1856—it was French literature that came to constitute the major Western influence on Turkish literature throughout the latter half of the 19th century. As a result, many of the same movements prevalent in France during this period also had their equivalents in the Ottoman Empire: in the developing Ottoman prose tradition, for instance, the influence of Romanticism can be seen during the Tanzimat period, and that of the Realist and Naturalist movements in subsequent periods; in the poetic tradition, on the other hand, it was the influence of the Symbolist and Parnassian movements that became paramount.

Many of the writers in the Tanzimat period wrote in several different genres simultaneously: for instance, the poet Nâmık Kemal (1840–1888) also wrote the important 1876 novel ''İntibâh'' (انتباه; "Awakening"), while the journalist Şinasi (1826–1871) is noted for writing, in 1860, the first modern Turkish play, the one-act comedy "''Şair Evlenmesi''" (شاعر اولنمسى; "The Poet's Marriage").An earlier play, a farce entitled "''Vakâyi`-i `Acibe ve Havâdis-i Garibe-yi Kefşger Ahmed''" (وقایع عجیبه و هوادث غریبۀ کفشگر احمد; "The Strange Events and Bizarre Occurrences of the Cobbler Ahmed"), dates from the beginning of the 19th century, but there remains some doubt about its authenticity. In a similar vein, the novelist Ahmed Midhat Efendi (1844–1912) wrote important novels in each of the major movements: Romanticism (حسن ملاح ياخود سر ايچيكده اسرار ''Hasan Mellâh yâhud Sırr İçinde Esrâr'', 1873; "''Hasan the Sailor, or The Mystery Within the Mystery''"), Realism (هﻨﻮز اون يدى يشکده ''Henüz On Yedi Yaşında'', 1881; "''Just Seventeen Years Old''"), and Naturalism (مشاهدات ''Müşâhedât'', 1891; "''Observations''"). This diversity was, in part, due to the Tanzimat writers' wish to disseminate as much of the new literature as possible, in the hopes that it would contribute to a revitalization of Ottoman social structures.Moran, 19
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="77149c009d4d59cc8b4b2ef272c0e2eb" name="Ziya" sectnum="3.6#1">../img/77149c009d4d59cc8b4b2ef272c0e2eb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>