<document id="9ac85a7a3df90af5b88aec75e569e1ae-4.8" name="Rudolf_Vrba" cat="14">
<text>
Vrba moved to Canada in 1967, serving on the Medical Research Council of Canada from 1967 to 1973,Proudfoot, Shannon. "Auschwitz escapee alerted world to horrors of the Holocaust", ''Ottawa Citizen'', March 31, 2006. and becoming a Canadian citizen in 1972. He spent 1973 to 1975 on sabbatical as a research fellow at Harvard Medical School; there he met his second wife Robin. They returned to Vancouver, British Columbia, where she became a successful real estate dealer, and he became an associate professor of pharmacology at the University of British Columbia from 1976 until the early 1990s,Martin, Douglas. "Rudolf Vrba, 82, Auschwitz Witness, Dies", ''The New York Times'', April 7, 2006. specializing in neurology."", no byline, ''BC BookWorld Author Bank'', retrieved April 01, 2006. He became known internationally for more than 50 research papers on the chemistry of the brain, and for his work on diabetes and cancer.

Impressed with Vrba's heroism, in 1992 British historian Sir Martin Gilbert supported a campaign to have him awarded the Order of Canada, and solicited letters from well-known Canadians on his behalf. One of them was law professor (and later Minister of Justice and Attorney General) Irwin Cotler, who, in a handwritten letter to Gilbert said "I fully concur with you that Vrba is a 'real hero'. Indeed, there are few more deserving of the Order of Canada than Vrba, and few, anywhere, who have exhibited his moral courage. Canada will honour itself—and redeem itself somewhat—by awarding him the order of Canada." Gilbert's efforts were, however, unsuccessful.

In 1998, at the instigation of Ruth Linn, he received the title of Doctor of Philosophy ''Honoris Causa'' from the University of Haifa "in recognition of his heroism and daring in exposing, during the war itself, the horrors of Auschwitz, which action led to the saving of Jewish lives; and in profound appreciation of his educational contribution and devotion to spreading knowledge about the Holocaust."

Vrba died of cancer on March 27, 2006 in Vancouver; he was survived by his first wife Gerta, second wife Robin, younger daughter Zuza Vrbová Jackson, granddaughter Hannah, and grandson Jan.Medoff, Rafael. , ''The Jewish Tribune'', April 20, 2006, p. 4., ''The Jerusalem Post'', April 1, 2006. He was pre-deceased by his older daughter Dr. Helena Vrbová, who died doing malaria research in Papua-New Guinea in 1982., Helena Vrbová Scholarship. London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, University of London, retrieved September 7, 2006. His fellow escapee, Alfréd Wetzler, died in Slovakia in 1988.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8cdc68e7fc30fd2b0c7b3d0e24e9ceb6" name="1975_wedding_picture_of_Rudi_and_Robin_Vrba" sectnum="4.8#1">../img/8cdc68e7fc30fd2b0c7b3d0e24e9ceb6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>