<document id="9ac85a7a3df90af5b88aec75e569e1ae-3.4" name="Rudolf_Vrba" cat="14">
<text>
On June 6, 1944, the day of the Normandy landing or D-Day, Arnost Rosin (prisoner no. 29858) and Czesław Mordowicz (prisoner no. 84216) arrived in Slovakia, having escaped from Auschwitz on May 27. Hearing about the Battle of Normandy, and believing the war was over, they got drunk to celebrate, using dollars they'd smuggled out of Auschwitz. They were promptly arrested for violating the currency laws, and spent eight days in prison, before the Jewish Council paid their fines.

Rosin and Mordowicz already knew Vrba and Wetzler. Vrba wrote in his memoir that any inmate who managed to survive more than a year in Auschwitz was regarded as a senior member of what he called the "old hands Mafia", and all were known to each other.Vrba (2002), p. 406. On June 15, the men were interviewed by Oscar Krasniansky, the engineer who had translated the Vrba-Wetzler report into German.The text of the Vrba-Wetzler report, under the title "German Extermination Camps—Auschwitz and Birkenau", was first published in full in an English translation on November 26, 1944 by the Executive Office of the U.S. War Refugee Board. It was this document that combined the testimony of Vrba and Wetzler with two other reports, and these came to be known jointly as the Auschwitz Protocols. (John Conway. "The Significance of the Vrba-Wetzler Report on Auschwitz-Birkenau", in Vrba (2002), Appendix I, pp. 292–293, footnote 3.) The protocols consisted of the Vrba-Wetzler report, and an earlier two-part report from August 10 and August 12, 1943 written by Witold Pilecki who was a member of the Polish underground in Auschwitz, and sent to the Office of Strategic Services (OSS) in London. The August 1943 Polish report included details about the gas chambers, about "selection", and about the sterilization experiments. It stated that there were three crematoria in Birkenau with the capacity to incinerate 10,000 bodies daily, and that 30,000 people had been gassed in one day. The author wrote: "History knows no parallel of such destruction of human life." Raul Hilberg writes that the report was filed away with a note that there was no indication as to the reliability of the source. (Hilberg (2003), p. 1212). The four-to-seven page report based on information from Arnost Rosin and Czesław Mordowicz, who escaped from Auschwitz on May 27, 1944, shortly after Vrba and Wetzler, was also attached. All three reports were submitted in evidence at the Nuremberg Trials and were assigned the document number 022-L. The full text is held in the archives of the War Refugee Board at the F.D. Roosevelt Library in New York. It is not known when the reports were first called the Auschwitz Protocols. R. Braham referred to them as the Auschwitz Protocols in ''The Politics of Genocide. The Holocaust in Hungary'', volume 2, 1981, pp. 708–716. (John Conway. "The Significance of the Vrba-Wetzler Report on Auschwitz-Birkenau", in Vrba (2002), Appendix I, pp. 292–293, footnote 3). They told Krasniansky that, between May 15 and May 27, 100,000 Hungarian Jews had arrived at Birkenau, and that most of them were killed on arrival, apparently with no knowledge of what was about to happen to them. The men reported that Jews were being killed at an unprecedented rate, with human fat being used to accelerate the burning. 

John Conway, professor emeritus of history at the University of British Columbia, and a friend of Vrba, has written that, because Rosin and Mordowicz were saying Hungarian Jews arriving at Auschwitz still had no idea what awaited them, Vrba and Wetzler concluded that their information had been suppressed. According to Conway, Vrba remained convinced until the end of his life that "if the intended victims had been warned, they would have resisted or hid or fled." In his memoir, Vrba wrote: "I only learned after the war that more than 400,000 Hungarian Jews were brought to Auschwitz after our escape and died a terrible death there up to mid-July, 1944 without ever having been warned by the Hungarian Jewish Council about the true nature of 'resettlement'."Vrba (2002), p. 407.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="eb27a4addc3b8b1aa3bfdb7c9c074433" name="RudolfVrbawithArnostRosin" sectnum="3.4#1">../img/eb27a4addc3b8b1aa3bfdb7c9c074433.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>