<document id="9ac85a7a3df90af5b88aec75e569e1ae-2.2" name="Rudolf_Vrba" cat="14">
<text>
On arrival at Birkenau, Vrba was "selected" to go to the right rather than the left, which meant he had been chosen to work rather than be sent to the gas chambers.Lungen 2005. He was tattooed as prisoner no. 44070.

He was described by those who knew him as possessing a photographic memory, and during his time at Auschwitz I and II, he tried to commit to memory the numbers of Jews arriving and the place of origin of each transport. Because his job involved being present when most of the Jewish deportees arrived, and sorting out the belongings of the ones who were gassed, he was able to calculate how many had been sent to Auschwitz, and how many were killed. He noticed that many of them had packed as though for the long term. He saw clothes for different seasons and utensils for a variety of uses, which convinced him that the Jews believed the Nazis' stories about resettlement in the East.Linn (2004), p. 19. This strengthened his conviction that he had to escape. For two years he had thought about it, but now, he wrote, "It was no longer a question of reporting a crime, but of preventing one; of warning the Hungarians, of rousing them, of raising an army one million strong, an army that would fight rather than die."Vrba 2006.

In the summer of 1943, he was given the job of registrar (''Blockschreiber'') in the quarantine section for men, Birkenau sector BIIa. From his barracks, he could see the lorries driving towards the gas chambers. This allowed him to estimate the number of Jews arriving daily, and the percentage gassed. His estimate was that only 10 percent of each transport was selected to go to the right, and the rest were killed.Linn (2004), p. 18. By April 1944, he calculated that 1,750,000 Jews had already been killed, a figure significantly higher than those now accepted by mainstream historians, but which even decades later he insisted was accurate.In March 1990 Vrba stated "Hilberg's estimate of 1 million killed is a gross error bordering on ignorance... According to my observations there were 1,765,000 victims which I counted." (Nueman, Elena. "New List of Holocaust Victims Reignites Dispute over Figures", ''Jewish Telegraphic Agency'', March 5, 1990).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a48e88a59b700125c51415591dbb530b" name="Selection_Birkenau_ramp" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/a48e88a59b700125c51415591dbb530b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>