<document id="9ac85a7a3df90af5b88aec75e569e1ae-4.7" name="Rudolf_Vrba" cat="14">
<text>
Vrba moved to Prague in 1945, attending and working at the Prague Technical University, where he received his doctorate in chemistry and biochemistry (Dr. Tech. Sc.) in 1951 for a thesis entitled "On the metabolism of butyric acid."Vrba, Rudolf. , University of British Columbia. This was followed by post-doctoral research at the Czechoslovak Academy of Science, where he received his C. Sc. in 1956. According to friends, Vrba was initially a staunch supporter of the Communist Party, which had helped him and Wetzler escape from Auschwitz, and for whom he had fought with the Czech partisans.  However, "anti-semitic purges in Stalinist Czechoslovakia, culminating in the 1952 trial of Rudolph Slansky, the Czechoslovak Communist party secretary" drove him to want to emigrate.

In the summer of 1944 he had re-acquainted himself with a childhood friend Gerta, another Slovak Jew, who survived the war by moving from Slovakia to Hungary and back under assumed names, eventually escaping the Gestapo, and living as a refugee in Russian controlled Budapest. After the war she too moved to Prague and became a medical doctor; they married (she took the surname Vrbová, the female version of Vrba), and they had two daughters, one in 1952, and one in 1954.Martin, Sandra. "Rudolf Vrba, Scientist and Professor 1924–2006", ''The Globe and Mail'', April 8, 2006. Soon after that the marriage failed; Vrbová escaped with her daughters to Copenhagen via Poland in 1958, reaching England in 1959., no byline, UCL News, University College London, June 9, 2006, retrieved September 7, 2006.

In 1958, Vrba received an invitation to present at an international conference in Israel, and while there, he also defected, working for the next two years at the Weizmann Institute of Science in Rehovot.Barkat, Amiran. , ''Haaretz'', April 2, 2006. He found he could not continue to live in Israel, because the same men who had, in his view, betrayed the Jewish community in Hungary were now in positions of power there, so he decided to move to England in 1960, becoming a British citizen in 1966. In England, he worked for two years in the Neuropsychiatric Research Unit in Carshalton, Surrey, and seven years for the British Medical Research Council.Sanderson, David & Smith, Lewis. "", ''The Times'', April 01, 2006.

On May 11, 1960, Adolf Eichmann was captured by the Mossad in Buenos Aires and taken to Jerusalem to stand trial. Vrba wrote in his memoir that the British newspapers were suddenly full of stories about Auschwitz. He contacted Alan Bestic, a journalist with the British newspaper, the ''Daily Herald'', to ask whether the newspaper would be interested in his story. They were, and it was published in five installments of 1,000 words each over one week in March 1961, on the eve of Eichmann's trial. Vrba also submitted a statement in evidence against Eichmann. With Bestic's help, he wrote up the rest of his story in August 1963 for his memoir, ''Escape from Auschwitz: I cannot forgive'', which was published in English in 1963.It was also published in German (1964), French (1988), Dutch (1996), Czech (1998), and Hebrew (1998).

He appeared as a witness at one of the Frankfurt Auschwitz trials in 1964, and testified at the seven-week trial for Holocaust denial of Ernst Zündel in Canada in 1985.Hume, Mark. "", ''The Globe and Mail'', March 31, 2006.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="23c41b2910e19fc2781f144e6322a874" name="RudolfVrba1960-1" sectnum="4.7#1">../img/23c41b2910e19fc2781f144e6322a874.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>