<document id="9b6a2aa6838121f6b90e41886e91e976-4" name="Fritz_the_Cat_(film)" cat="19">
<text>
''Fritz the Cat'' was released on April 12, 1972, opening in Hollywood and Washington, D.C., and went on to become a worldwide hit, grossing over $100 million worldwide, and was the most successful independent animated feature of all time. Critical reaction to the film was positive. Vincent Canby of ''The New York Times'' wrote that the film is "constantly funny   something to offend just about everyone." ''New York'' magazine film critic Judith Crist wrote that "Like Crumb, Bakshi and producer Steve Krantz have captured the funk and the fraud and the foible and resorted to outrageous laughter to stifle the scream.  ''Fritz the Cat'' is a ball for the open mind." Paul Sargent Clark in ''The Hollywood Reporter'' called the film "powerful and audacious", while ''Newsweek'' called it "a harmless, mindless, pro-youth saga calculated to shake up only the box office." ''The Wall Street Journal'' and ''Cue'' both gave the film mixed reviews. Film website Rotten Tomatoes, which compiles reviews from a wide range of critics, gives the film a score of 53%. 

In Michael Barrier's 1972 article on the film's production, Bakshi gives his accounts of two separate screenings of the film. Of the reactions to the film by audiences at a preview screening in Los Angeles, Bakshi stated "They forget it's animation. They treat it like a film.  This is the real thing, to get people to take animation seriously." Bakshi was also present at a showing of the film at the Museum of Modern Art and remembers "Some guy asked me why I was against the revolution. The point is, animation was making people get up off their asses and get mad."

Robert Crumb first saw the film in February 1972, during a visit to Los Angeles in the company of fellow underground cartoonists Spain Rodriguez, S. Clay Wilson, Robert Williams, and Rick Griffin.  Crumb disliked the film, saying that he felt that the film was "really a reflection of Ralph Bakshi's confusion, you know. There's something real repressed about it. In a way, it's more twisted than my stuff. It's really twisted in some kind of weird, unfunny way.  I didn't like that sex attitude in it very much. It's like real repressed horniness; he's kind of letting it out compulsively." Crumb also took issue with the film's condemnation of the radical left, denouncing Fritz's dialogue in the final sequences of the film as "red-neck and fascistic"  and stating that "They put words into his mouth that I never would have had him say." 

Reportedly, Crumb filed suit to have his name removed from the film's credits. San Francisco copyright attorney Albert L. Morse claims that no suit was filed, but an agreement was reached to remove Crumb's name from the credits. However, as Crumb's name has remained in the final film since its original theatrical release, both of these claims are highly unlikely. Crumb later drew a comic in which the Fritz character was killed off, and claimed that he "wrote them a letter telling them not to use any more of my characters in their films." Crumb later stated that the film is "one of those experiences I sort of block out. The last time I saw it was when I was making an appearance at a German art school in the mid-1980s, and I was forced to watch it with the students. It was an excruciating ordeal, a humiliating embarrassment. I recall Victor Moscoso was the only one who warned me, 'if you don't stop this film from being made, you are going to regret it for the rest of your life'—and he was right."

In a 2008 interview, Bakshi referred to Crumb as a "hustler" and stated that "He goes in so many directions that he’s hard to pin down. I spoke to him on the phone. We both had the same deal, five percent. They finally sent Crumb the money and not me. Crumb always gets what he wants, including that château of his in France.  I have no respect for Crumb. Is he a good artist? Yes, if you want to do the same thing over and over. He should have been my best friend for what I did with ''Fritz the Cat''. I drew a good picture, and we both made out fine." Bakshi also stated that Crumb threatened to disassociate himself from any cartoonist that worked with Bakshi, which would have hurt their chances at getting work published.

The film also sparked negative reactions because of its content. "A lot of people got freaked out", says Bakshi. "The people in charge of the power structure, the people in charge of magazines and the people going to work in the morning who loved Disney and Norman Rockwell, thought I was a pornographer, and they made things very difficult for me. The younger people, the people who could take new ideas, were the people I was addressing. I wasn't addressing the whole world. To those people who loved it, it was a huge hit, and everyone else wanted to kill me."

Michael Barrier, an animation historian, described ''Fritz the Cat'' as one of two films that were "not merely provocative, but highly ambitious." Barrier described the films as an effort "to push beyond what was done in the old cartoons, even while building on their strengths."Barrier, Michael. ''Hollywood Cartoons: American Animation in Its Golden Age''. Oxford University Press US, 2003. . Retrieved on October 15, 2009. ISBN 0195167295, 9780195167290. Bakshi said that "for all its faults, I at least enjoy Bakshi's ''Fritz the Cat'', for reasons. I suspect have  more to do with Crumb's original stories than Bakshi's gifts as a  director.""." Michael Barrier. April 2, 2009. Retrieved on October 15, 2009.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ae88596600d9be519ff6bfc6db946c91" name="Fritz_the_Cat_promo" sectnum="4#1">../img/ae88596600d9be519ff6bfc6db946c91.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>