<document id="9b785800f815749afd346fc4c5a7077d-3" name="Joan_of_Arc" cat="14">
<text>
Joan of Arc wore men's clothing between her departure from Vaucouleurs and her abjuration at Rouen.Condemnation trial, pp. 78–79. (Accessed 12 February 2006) This raised theological questions in her own era and raised other questions in the twentieth century. The technical reason for her execution was a biblical clothing law.Deuteronomy 22:5. (Accessed 22 March 2006). The nullification trial reversed the conviction in part because the condemnation proceeding had failed to consider the doctrinal exceptions to that stricture.

Doctrinally speaking, she was safe to disguise herself as a page during a journey through enemy territory and she was safe to wear armor during battle. The ''Chronique de la Pucelle'' states that it deterred molestation while she was camped in the field. Clergy who testified at her rehabilitation trial affirmed that she continued to wear male clothing in prison to deter molestation and rape.Nullification trial testimony of Guillaume de Manchon. (Accessed 12 February 2006) Preservation of chastity was another justifiable reason for crossdressing: her apparel would have slowed an assailant, and men would be less likely to think of her as a sex object in any case.According to medieval clothing expert Adrien Harmand, she wore two layers of pants (trousers in British-English) attached to the doublet with 20 fastenings. The outer pants were made of a boot-like leather. "Jeanne d'Arc, son costume, son armure." (Accessed 23 March 2006)

She referred the court to the Poitiers inquiry when questioned on the matter during her condemnation trial. The Poitiers record no longer survives but circumstances indicate the Poitiers clerics approved her practice. In other words, she had a mission to do a man's work so it was fitting that she dress the part.Condemnation trial, p. 78. (Accessed 12 February 2006) Retrial testimony of Brother Seguin de Seguin, Professor of Theology at Poitiers, does not mention clothing directly, but constitutes a wholehearted endorsement of her piety. (Accessed 12 February 2006) She also kept her hair cut short through her military campaigns and while in prison. Her supporters, such as the theologian Jean Gerson, defended her hairstyle, as did Inquisitor Brehal during the Rehabilitation trial.Fraioli, "Joan of Arc: The Early Debate," p. 131.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b4ed112b9fafdd2a18be4f71a6355a65" name="ingres_coronation_charles_vii" sectnum="3#1">../img/b4ed112b9fafdd2a18be4f71a6355a65.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>