<document id="9b785800f815749afd346fc4c5a7077d-2" name="Joan_of_Arc" cat="14">
<text>
Joan was the daughter of Jacques d'Arc and Isabelle RoméeJacques d'Arc (1380–1440) was a farmer in Domremy who held the post of ''doyen'' a local tax-collector and organiser of village defenses. He married Isabelle de Vouthon (1387–1468), called Romée, in 1405. Their other children were Jacquemin, Jean, Pierre and Catherine. Charles VII ennobled Jacques and Isabelle's family on 29 December 1429; the Chamber of Accounts registered the family's designation to nobility on 20 January 1430. The grant permitted the family to change their surname to du Lys. in Domrémy, a village which was then in the duchy of Bar (later annexed to the province of Lorraine and renamed Domrémy-la-Pucelle).Condemnation trial, p. 37. (Accessed 23 March 2006) Her parents owned about 50 acres (0.2 square kilometers) of land and her father supplemented his farming work with a minor position as a village official, collecting taxes and heading the local watch.Pernoud and Clin, p. 221. They lived in an isolated patch of northeastern territory that remained loyal to the French crown despite being surrounded by Burgundian lands. Several local raids occurred during her childhood and on one occasion her village was burned.

Joan said she was about 19 at her trial, so she was born about 1412; she later testified that she experienced her first vision around 1424 at the age of 12 years when she was out alone in a field and heard voices. She had said she cried when they left as they were so beautiful. She would report that Saint Michael, Saint Catherine, and Saint Margaret told her to drive out the English and bring the Dauphin to Reims for his coronation.Condemnation trial, pp. 58–59. (Accessed 23 March 2006)

At the age of 16, she asked a kinsman, Durand Lassois, to bring her to nearby Vaucouleurs where she petitioned the garrison commander, Count Robert de Baudricourt, for permission to visit the royal French court at Chinon. Baudricourt's sarcastic response did not deter her.DeVries, pp. 37–40. She returned the following January and gained support from two men of standing: Jean de Metz and Bertrand de Poulengy.Nullification trial testimony of Jean de Metz. (Accessed 12 February 2006) Under their auspices, she gained a second interview where she made a remarkable prediction about a military reversal near Orléans.Oliphant, ch. 2. (Accessed 12 February 2006)
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b2fe357889f6bc047d0ecda9e49b0a27" name="Maison_J_dArc" sectnum="2#1">../img/b2fe357889f6bc047d0ecda9e49b0a27.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>