<document id="9b80a63df52f88f7cc11b9b2649d3df6-1.2" name="Toronto_Raptors" cat="26">
<text>
In the team's first official NBA game, Alvin Robertson scored the first NBA points in Raptors history,, cbc.ca, 1 February 2007, accessed 25 April 2007. while Stoudamire recorded 10 points and 10 assists in a 94–79 victory over the New Jersey Nets., basketball-reference.com, 3 November 1995, accessed 16 June 2007. The Raptors concluded their inaugural season with a 21–61 win–loss record, although they were one of the few teams to defeat the Chicago Bulls,, basketball-reference.com, 24 March 1996, accessed 16 June 2007. who set an all-time NBA best 72–10 win–loss regular season record. With averages of 19.0 points and 9.3 assists per game, Stoudamire also won the 1995–96 Rookie of the Year Award., nba.com, accessed 16 June 2007.

In the 1996–97 season the team improved on its win record by nine games., nba.com, accessed 16 June 2007. They selected centre Marcus Camby with the second overall pick in the 1996 NBA Draft., nba.com/raptors, accessed 23 April 2007. By the end of the season, Camby earned a berth on the NBA's All-Rookie Team while Stoudamire continued to play well, averaging 20.2 points and 8.8 assists per game. As in the previous season, the Raptors were one of only 11 teams to topple the eventual 1997 Champions, the Chicago Bulls., basketball-reference.com, 8 December 1996, accessed 16 June 2007. The Raptors also defeated the Houston Rockets, Utah Jazz and Miami Heat, all of whom were eventual Conference finalists., basketball-reference.com, accessed 21 April 2007. However, the Raptors struggled against teams who were not of championship calibre, including three losses to the 15–67 Boston Celtics.

Early in the 1997–98 season John Bitove had sold his ownership interest in the team and the team suffered numerous injuries and slid into a 17-game losing streak., nba.com/raptors, accessed 16 June 2007. GM Isiah Thomas resigned after his ownership bid for the Raptors failed and was replaced by Glen Grunwald.Beck, Howard, , nytimes.com, 1 November 2006, accessed 12 April 2007 With Thomas gone, Stoudamire immediately sought a trade.Grange, Michael , globesports.com, 3 March 2007, accessed 21 April 2007. On 13 February 1998, he was shipped to the Portland Trail Blazers along with Walt Williams and Carlos Rogers for Kenny Anderson, Alvin Williams, Gary Trent, two first-round draft choices, a second-round draft choice and cash. Anderson refused to report to Toronto and was traded to the Celtics with Zan Tabak and Popeye Jones for Chauncey Billups, Dee Brown, Roy Rogers and John Thomas. When the trading deadline was over, the Raptors became the youngest team in the league with an average age of 24.6. They had five rookies on their roster, including the 18-year-old Tracy McGrady, who at the time was the youngest player in the NBA. The inexperienced Raptors struggled throughout the season and their regular season record regressed to 16–66., nba.com/history, accessed 16 June 2007.

During the 1998 NBA Draft, in what became a defining move for the franchise, Grunwald traded the team's 4th overall pick Antawn Jamison to the Golden State Warriors for Vince Carter, who was selected 5th overall., nba.com, accessed 16 June 2007. To bring further credibility to the Raptors, Grunwald traded Camby to the New York Knicks for Charles Oakley,, nba.com/raptors, accessed 16 June 2007. a veteran with playoff experience. Kevin Willis, another veteran acquired from the trade, solidified the centre position, while the coaching staff temporarily rotated Dee Brown, Alvin Williams and Doug Christie to play point guard. Both Christie and Williams became talented players in their own right; Christie developed into one of the elite defenders in the NBA, while Williams improved his play on the offensive end. New coach Butch Carter was also credited with much of the team's turnaround during the lockout shortened 1998–99 season. Although the team did not make the playoffs, many were optimistic with the impressive performances of Rookie of the Year Carter and a much improved McGrady.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c959dd9dbb2297e4dc20636abdafc879" name="RogersCentre_Toronto_Sept1-05" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/c959dd9dbb2297e4dc20636abdafc879.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>