<document id="9b80a63df52f88f7cc11b9b2649d3df6-1.5" name="Toronto_Raptors" cat="26">
<text>
The 2006–07 season represented a watershed year for the Raptors franchise. The roster was overhauled, including the selection of 2006 NBA Draft number one pick Andrea Bargnani, the acquisition of point guard T. J. Ford in exchange for Charlie Villanueva, and the signing of shooting guard Anthony Parker and small forward Jorge Garbajosa.Ewing, Lori, , cbc.ca, 14 July 2006, accessed 17 June 2007. Bosh was given a three-year contract extension, while Maurizio Gherardini of Benetton Treviso was hired as the club's vice-president and assistant general manager., nba.com/raptors, 22 June 2006, accessed 17 June 2007.

The first half of the season produced mixed results as Toronto struggled towards the .500 mark.Smalls, Anthony, , nba.com, 12 April 2007, accessed 16 June 2007. However, Toronto ended the regular season with a 47–35 record, securing the third seed in the Eastern Conference for the 2007 NBA Playoffs along with the Atlantic Division title, as well as homecourt advantage for the first time in franchise history., nba.com/raptors, 15 April 2007, accessed 17 June 2007., nba.com, accessed 22 April 2007. Bosh recorded career-highs in ppg and rpg and was voted to start in the 2007 NBA All-Star Game. cbc.ca, 25 January 2007, accessed 16 June 2007. The Raptors were also praised for their improved defense, ball-sharing and tremendous team chemistry.Schuhmann, John, , nba.com, 23 March 2007, accessed 16 June 2007. Colangelo, Gherardini and Mitchell were credited with Toronto's turnaround this season,Feschuk, Dave, , thestar.com, 21 April 2007, accessed 16 June 2007. which was one of the best in NBA history in terms of league standing and defensive ranking.Pelton, Kevin, , nba.com/sonics, 11 March 2007, accessed 16 June 2007. Mitchell was subsequently named the 2006–07 NBA Coach of the Year, the first coach in Raptors history to receive the honour,, nba.com/raptors, 24 April 2007, accessed 16 June 2007. while Colangelo was named 2006–07 Executive of the Year., nba.com/raptors, 14 May 2007, accessed 16 May 2007. On 24 April 2007, the Raptors won their first playoff game in five seasons, with an 89–83 victory over the New Jersey Nets,, nba.com/raptors, 24 April 2007, accessed 16 June 2007. but lost the series 4–2., 4 May 2007, accessed 16 June 2007.

Several changes to the roster were made before the 2007–08 campaign as Toronto sought to reproduce the same form as the previous campaign. Most notably, the Raptors acquired Carlos Delfino in a trade with Detroit for two second round draft picks,, nba.com/raptors, 15 June 2007, accessed 22 July 2007. and signed Jamario Moon, nba.com/raptors, 10 July 2007, accessed 22 July 2007. and three-point specialist Jason Kapono as free agents.Ulmer, Mike, , nba.com/raptors, 12 July 2007, accessed 13 July 2007. On the other hand, veteran swingman Morris Peterson joined the New Orleans Hornets., cbc.ca, 23 July 2007, accessed 9 August 2007. Despite being defending division champions, the Raptors were widely tipped as outside contenders for the division and conference titles.Feschuk, Dave, , thestar.com, 31 October 2007, accessed 1 November 2007. Bargnani's inability to play well consistently, coupled with injuries to Garbajosa (75 games), Bosh (15 games) and Ford (31 games) derailed the possibility of a smooth campaign as the Raptors chalked up six fewer wins than the previous season. The Raptors ceded the division title to Boston, and qualified for the 2008 NBA Playoffs as the sixth seed where they were pitted against the Orlando Magic, but were eliminated in five games., basketball-reference.com, accessed 4 May 2008.Ulmer, Mike, , nba.com/raptors, 30 April 2008, accessed 4 May 2008. Whereas the preceding season was considered a success, the 2007–08 campaign was considered a disappointment. Weaknesses in Toronto's game—rebounding, defence, and a lack of a swingman—were brought into sharp focus during the playoffs, and changes were expected to be made to the roster.

As it turned out, a blockbuster trade was agreed in principle before the 2008–09 campaign: six-time All-Star Jermaine O'Neal was acquired from the Indiana Pacers in exchange for Ford (who had become expendable with the emergence of Calderón), Rasho Nesterovič, Maceo Baston, and Roy Hibbert, the 17th pick in the 2008 NBA Draft, giving the Raptors a potential boost in the frontcourt.Smith, Doug, , thestar.com, 26 June 2008, accessed 27 June 2008. Meanwhile, Bargnani, who had spent the summer working on his interior game, was projected to come off the bench. The Raptors also introduced a black alternate road jersey for the season similar to the earlier purple design that was dropped a few seasons ago. It had a maple leaf featured on the back neck of the jersey, symbolizing the Raptors as "Canada's team"., thestar.com, 25 Sept 2008, accessed 14 Oct 2008. Despite the introduction of O'Neal, who brought home the rebounds and the blocks, and a much improved Bargnani, the Raptors were too inconsistent. Following a 8–9 start to the season, Mitchell was fired and replaced by long-time assistant Jay Triano., nba.com/raptors, 3 December 2008, accessed 3 December 2008. Triano tweaked with the starting line-up to no avail as the Raptors fell to 21–34 prior to the All-Star break. O'Neal and Moon were then traded to Miami for Shawn Marion and Marcus Banks,Aldridge, David, , nba.com, 13 February 2009, accessed 14 February 2009. but with the losses mounting, the Raptors soon fell out of the playoffs picture, and were eliminated from contention with seven games of the regular season remaining., nba.com, 5 April 2009, accessed 11 April 2009. The Raptors eventually finished with a 33–49 record, basketball-reference.com, accessed 16 April 2009. and headed into the next season with a potential overhaul of the core: Marion could become a free agent; Bosh could become one after 2009–10; Parker would soon turn 35; and Bargnani had his breakthrough season. On 12 May 2009, Triano was given a three-year term for the position of head coach.Smith, Doug, , 12 May 2009, accessed 13 May 2009.

The inevitable roster shakeup for the 2009–10 season began when Kapono was traded to the Philadelphia 76ers for the aggressive veteran forward Reggie Evans., nba.com accessed 15 June 2009. Toronto then drafted DeMar DeRozan‎ with the ninth pick, enabling them to fill a spot on the wings., sports.espn.go.com, 26 June 2009, accessed 27 June 2009. This was followed by the signing of free agent Hedo Türkoğlu, which in turn led to a sign-and-trade agreement involving four teams, with Toronto landing wing players Devean George (later traded for Marco Belinelli) and Antoine Wright, while releasing Marion, Kris Humphries and Nathan Jawai.Stein, Marc, , sports.espn.go.com, 9 July 2009, accessed 10 July 2009. Around the same time, Parker headed for the Cleveland Cavaliers,, news-hearld.com, 10 July 2009, accessed 12 July 2009. while Indiana point guard Jarrett Jack was added and Nesterovič brought back to provide cover for the big men. Finally, Delfino and Ukić were moved to the Milwaukee Bucks for Amir Johnson and Sonny Weems., sports.espn.go.com, accessed 24 August 2009. It became increasingly clear that Colangelo, in securing a credible nucleus for the future, was doing this to persuade Bosh to stay beyond 2010.Grange, Michael, "Jack could provide fringe benefits for struggling Raptors ", ''The Globe and Mail'', 12 July 2009.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f1bcdb815771cfd0bf6af33e0db1e341" name="raptors_0607" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/f1bcdb815771cfd0bf6af33e0db1e341.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>