<document id="9b8fb60c62039c918644d599afcabc63-6" name="Melodifestivalen" cat="20">
<text>
Before the introduction of the current voting system in 1999, a group of regional or age-based juries decided the winner of Melodifestivalen. In 1993, televoting was used experimentally, but proved unsuccessful. The Swedish telephone network collapsed due to the number of calls, and claims by the Swedish tabloid press suggested the use of televoting had drastically altered the results. Evening newspapers released what they claimed to be the back-up juries' votes, which showed that the winner, Arvingarna's "Eloise", would have finished fourth had the juries' votes counted. SVT never confirmed the accuracy of these claims.The tabloid's "winner" was Nick Borgen's "We are All the Winners". Thorsson, p. 233. 

The current voting format is a positional voting system similar to that used at the Eurovision Song Contest. The international jury award 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, and 12 points to seven songs, as do eleven juries based in towns and cities around Sweden. Televotes are given an equivalent weighting; 12, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, and 144 points are awarded. The song with the highest number of points at the end of all three sets of results is the winner.

Telephone lines open immediately after the radio preview for the final and do not close until the juries have voted that night.  . SR.se (March 2006) Retrieved on 16 May 2007. Two telephone numbers are used, giving voters the option of whether to donate money to SVT's ''Radiohjälpen''  charity appeal or not as they vote. Viewers can also vote by text message, and televoting is only possible in Sweden.  . Blupp.nu (February 2007). Retrieved on 4 May 2007. . SVT.se. Retrieved on 14 March 2009. 

The regional juries' votes are announced by spokespeople who are not members of the juries. The votes are read in ascending order, beginning with one point and finishing with twelve. When read, they are repeated by the host, for example:

Spokesperson: "Ett poäng för melodi nummer två." (''One point for melody number two.'')
Presenter: "Melodi nummer två får ett poäng." (''Melody number two gets one point.'')

As the votes are announced, they are collated on a graphic scoreboard. SVT varies the way the jury votes are announced from year to year. For example, the finalists of ''Expedition: Robinson'' acted as spokespeople in 2004, and in 2006 Fredrik Lindström announced jury tallies using the dialects of each region.  . SVT.se (March 2004). Retrieved on 28 April 2007. Johanna Melén (18 March 2006).   . Aftonbladet.se. Retrieved on 28 April 2007. Televoting results are announced by the hosts in ascending order. The final of Melodifestivalen has broken Nordic voting records; figures exceeded two million for the first time in 2007.  . SVT.se (13 March 2007). Retrieved on 4 May 2007. 

If there is a tie, the song that received more votes from the public receives the higher position.  . SR.se (13 March 2005). Retrieved on 28 April 2007. There have been two ties for first place in the festival's history. In 1969, Tommy Körberg tied for first place with Jan Malmsjö before winning after juries voted for their favourite out of the two. In 1978, Björn Skifs tied for first place with Lasse Holm, Kikki Danielsson and Wizex (performing together); a similar tie-break process made Skifs the winner.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="aa37e5ab403b113723c0fe4bd23f5f01" name="Melodifestivalen_voting_2005" sectnum="6#1">../img/aa37e5ab403b113723c0fe4bd23f5f01.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>