<document id="9bae22cc2ee5cd5bfd302a7d18694f31-3.1" name="Battle_of_Moscow" cat="29">
<text>
For Hitler, Moscow was the most important military and political target, as he anticipated that the city's surrender would shortly afterwards lead to the general collapse of the Soviet Union. As Franz Halder, head of the ''Oberkommando des Heeres'' (Army General Staff), wrote in 1940, "The best solution would be a direct offensive towards Moscow."''Moscow Encyclopedia'', ed. Great Russian Encyclopedia, Moscow, 1997, entry "Battle of Moscow" Therefore, the city was a primary target for the large and well-equipped Army Group Center. The forces committed to Operation ''Typhoon'' included three armies (the 2nd, 4th and 9th) supported by three Panzer Groups (the 2nd, 3rd and 4th) and by the Luftwaffe's Luftflotte 2. Overall, more than one million men were committed to the operation, along with 1,700 tanks and 14,000 guns. German aerial strength had been radically reduced. Since the 22 June the Luftwaffe had lost 1,603 aircraft and 1,028 damaged. As a result ''Luftflotte 2'' had only 549 serviceable machines, including 158 medium and dive-bombers and 172 fighters.Bergstöm 2007, p. 90. The attack relied on standard blitzkrieg tactics, using Panzer groups rushing deep into Soviet formations and executing double-pincer movements, pocketing Red Army divisions and destroying them.Guderian, pp. 307–9.

The initial Wehrmacht plan called for two initial movements. The first would be a double-pincer performed around the Soviet Western Front and Reserve Front forces located around Vyazma. The second would be a single-pincer around the Bryansk Front to capture the city of Bryansk. From that point, the plan called for another quick pincer north and south of Moscow to encircle the city. However, the German armies were already battered and experiencing some logistical issues. Guderian, for example, wrote that some of his destroyed tanks had not been replaced, and that his mechanized troops lacked fuel at the beginning of the operation.Guderian, p. 307

Facing the Wehrmacht were three Soviet fronts formed from exhausted armies that had already been involved in heavy fighting for several months. The forces committed to the city's defense totaled 1,250,000 men, 1,000 tanks, 7,600 guns. The Soviet Air Force/''Voenno-Vozdushnye Sily'' (VVS) had suffered appalling losses of some 7,500Hardesty, 1991, p.61. or 21,200Bergström 2007, p.118. aircraft. Extraordinary industrial achievements had begun to replace losses, and the VVS had 936 aircraft, 578 of which were bombers for the defense of the capital.Bergström 2007, p.90-91. Even with reinforcements, air strength was down to about a quarter of pre-war strength. Troops and weaponry, while presenting a significant threat to the Wehrmacht based on their numbers alone, were poorly located, with most of the troops deployed in a single line, and had little or no reserves to the rear. In his memoirs, Vasilevsky pointed out that while immediate Soviet defenses were quite well prepared, these errors in troop placement were largely responsible for the Wehrmacht's initial success. Furthermore, many Soviet defenders were seriously lacking in combat experience and some critical equipment (such as anti-tank weapons), while their tanks were obsolete models.Glantz, chapter 6, sub-ch. "Viaz'ma and Briansk", pp. 74 ff.



The Soviet command began constructing extensive defenses around the city. The first part, the Rzhev-Vyazma defense setup, was built on the Rzhev-Vyazma-Bryansk line. The second, the Mozhaisk defense line, was a double defense stretching between Kalinin and Kaluga. Finally, a triple defense ring surrounded the city itself, forming the Moscow Defense Zone.  These defenses were still largely unprepared by the beginning of the operation because of the speed of the German advance. Furthermore, the German attack plan had been discovered quite late, and Soviet troops were ordered to assume a total defensive stance only on September 27, 1941. However, new Soviet divisions were being formed on the Volga, in Asia and in the Urals, and it would only be a matter of a few months  before these new troops could be committed,Vasilevsky, p. 138. making the battle a race against time as well.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9bae22cc2ee5cd5bfd302a7d18694f31" name="Battle_of_Moscow" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/9bae22cc2ee5cd5bfd302a7d18694f31.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>