<document id="9be5a2722b8b603104dcfff5b4414f95-7.14.2" name="David_I_of_Scotland" cat="25">
<text>
In the modern period there has been more of an emphasis on David's statebuilding and on the effects of his changes on Scottish cultural development. Lowland Scots tended to trace the origins of their culture to the marriage of David's father Máel Coluim III to Saint Margaret, a myth which had its origins in the medieval period.See, for instance, Steve Boardman, "Late Medieval Scotland and the Matter of Britain", in Edward J. Cowan and Richard J. Finlay (eds.), Scottish History: The Power of the Past, (Edinburgh, 2002), pp. 65–71. With the development of modern historical techniques in the mid-19th century, responsibility for these developments appeared to lie more with David than his father. David assumed a principal place in the alleged destruction of the Celtic Kingdom of Scotland. Andrew Lang, in 1900, wrote that "with Alexander , Celtic domination ends; with David, Norman and English dominance is established".Quoted in Oram, ''David'', p. 219, citing Lang, ''A History of Scotland'', vol. 1, pp. 102–9; Lang did not neglect the old myth about Margaret, writing of the Northumbrian refugees arriving in Scotland "where they became the sires of the sturdy Lowland race", Lang, ''A History of Scotland'', vol. 1, p. 91.

The ages of Enlightenment and Romanticism had elevated the role of races and "ethnic packages" into mainstream history, and in this context David was portrayed as hostile to the native Scots, and his reforms were seen in the light of natural, perhaps even justified, civilised Teutonic aggression towards the backward Celts.See Matthew H. Hammond, "Ethnicity and the Writing of Medieval Scottish history", pp. 1&ndash;27.; see also, Murray G.H. Pittock's work, ''Celtic Identity and the British Image'', (Manchester, 1999), and Oram, ''David'', pp. 219&ndash;20.

In the 20th century, several studies were devoted to Normanisation in 12th century Scotland, focusing upon and hence emphasising the changes brought about by the reign of David I. Græme Ritchie's ''The Normans in Scotland'' (1954), Archie Duncan's ''Scotland: The Making of the Kingdom'' (1974) and the many articles of G. W. S. Barrow all formed part of this historiographical trend.Græme Ritchie, ''The Normans in Scotland'', (Edinburgh, 1954); Duncan, ''Scotland: The Making of the Kingdom'', pp. 133–73; most of Barrow's most important essays have been collected in two volumes, ''Scotland and Its Neighbours In the Middle Ages'', (London, 1992) and ''The Kingdom of the Scots: Government, Church and Society from the eleventh century to the fourteenth century'', 2nd edn. (Edinburgh, 2003).

In the 1980s, Barrow sought a compromise between change and continuity, and argued that the reign of King David was in fact a "Balance of New and Old".Barrow, "The Balance of New and Old", ''passim''. Such a conclusion was a natural incorporation of an underlying current in Scottish historiography which, since William F. Skene's monumental and revolutionary three-volume ''Celtic Scotland: A History of Ancient Alban'' (1876–80), had been forced to acknowledge that "Celtic Scotland" was alive and healthy for a long time after the reign of David I.William Forbes Skene, ''Celtic Scotland: A History of Ancient Alban'', 3 vols. (Edinburgh, 1876–80); see also, Edward J. Cowan, "The Invention of Celtic Scotland", pp. 1&ndash;23. Michael Lynch followed and built upon Barrow's compromise solution, arguing that  as David’s reign progressed, his kingship became more Celtic.Lynch, ''Scotland: A New History'', pp. 82&ndash;83. Despite its subtitle, in 2004 in the only full volume study of David I's reign yet produced, ''David I: The King Who Made Scotland'', its author Richard Oram further builds upon Lynch's picture, stressing continuity while placing the changes of David's reign in their context.Oram, ''David I'', (Stroud, 2004).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="920b5870582f5502a638c8a2c320af3d" name="David_Seal_(rev)" sectnum="7.14.2#1">../img/920b5870582f5502a638c8a2c320af3d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>