<document id="9be5a2722b8b603104dcfff5b4414f95-5.14" name="David_I_of_Scotland" cat="25">
<text>
One of the first problems David had to deal with as king was an ecclesiastical dispute with the English church. The problem with the English church concerned the subordination of Scottish sees to the archbishops of York and/or Canterbury, an issue which since his election in 1124 had prevented Robert of Scone from being consecrated to the see of St Andrews (Cell Ríghmonaidh). It is likely that since the 11th century the bishopric of St Andrews functioned as a ''de facto'' archbishopric. The title of "Archbishop" is accorded in Scottish and Irish sources to Bishop GiricDauvit Broun, "Recovering the Full Text of Version A of the Foundation Legend", pp. 108–14. and Bishop Fothad II.AU 1093.2,  &  ; see also Alan Orr Anderson, ''Early Sources '', p. 49



The problem was that this archiepiscopal status had not been cleared with the papacy, opening the way for English archbishops to claim overlordship of the whole Scottish church. The man responsible was the new aggressively assertive Archbishop of York, Thurstan. His easiest target was the bishopric of Glasgow, which being south of the river Forth was not regarded as part of Scotland nor the jurisdiction of St Andrews. In 1125, Pope Honorius II wrote to John, Bishop of Glasgow ordering him to submit to the archbishopric of York.A.O. Anderson, ''Scottish Annals'', pp. 160–1. David ordered Bishop John of Glasgow to travel to the Apostolic See in order to secure a pallium which would elevate the bishopric of St Andrews to an archbishopric with jurisdiction over Glasgow.Duncan, ''Scotland: The Making of the Kingdom'', p. 259; Oram, ''David'', p. 49.

Thurstan travelled to Rome, as did the Archbishop of Canterbury, William de Corbeil,  and both presumably opposed David's request. David however gained the support of King Henry, and the Archbishop of York agreed to a year's postponement of the issue and to consecrate Robert of Scone without making an issue of subordination.Duncan, ''Making of the Kingdom'', p. 260; John Dowden, ''Bishops of Scotland'', (Glasgow, ), ed. J. Maitland Thomson, (Glasgow, 1912) pp. 4–5. York's claim over bishops north of the Forth were in practice abandoned for the rest of David's reign, although York maintained her more credible claims over Glasgow.Duncan, ''Scotland: The Making of the Kingdom'', pp. 60–1.

In 1151, David again requested a pallium for the Archbishop of St Andrews. Cardinal John Paparo met David at his residence of Carlisle in September 1151. Tantalisingly for David, the Cardinal was on his way to Ireland with four ''pallia'' to create four new Irish archbishoprics.  When the Cardinal returned to Carlisle, David made the request. In David's plan, the new archdiocese would include all the bishoprics in David's Scottish territory, as well as bishopric of Orkney and the bishopric of the Isles. Unfortunately for David, the Cardinal does not appear to have brought the issue up with the papacy. In the following year the papacy dealt David another blow by creating the archbishopric of Trondheim, a new Norwegian archbishopric embracing the bishoprics of the Isles and Orkney.Oram, ''David'', p. 155.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="650b31b3181789b821b58db9ac33db48" name="St_Rules_Tower" sectnum="5.14#1">../img/650b31b3181789b821b58db9ac33db48.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>