<document id="9be5a2722b8b603104dcfff5b4414f95-2.4" name="David_I_of_Scotland" cat="25">
<text>
In the later part of 1113, King Henry gave David the hand of Matilda of Huntingdon, daughter and heiress of Waltheof, Earl of Northumberland. The marriage brought with it the "Honour of Huntingdon", a lordship scattered through the shires of Northampton, Huntingdon, and Bedford; within a few years, Matilda de Senlis bore a son, whom David named Henry after his patron.G. W. S. Barrow, "David I (c. 1085–1153)".

The new territories which David controlled were a valuable supplement to his income and manpower, increasing his status as one of the most powerful magnates in the Kingdom of the English. Moreover, Matilda's father Waltheof had been Earl of Northumberland, a defunct lordship which had covered the far north of England and included Cumberland and Westmorland, Northumberland-proper, as well as overlordship of the bishopric of Durham. After King Henry's death, David would revive the claim to this earldom for his son Henry.For all this, see Duncan, ''Scotland: The Making of the Kingdom'', pp. 134, 217–8, 223; see also, for Durham and part of the earldom of Northumberland in the eyes of Earl Henry, Paul Dalton, "Scottish Influence on Durham, 1066–1214", in David Rollason, Margaret Harvey & Michael Prestwich (eds.), ''Anglo-Norman Durham, 1093–1193'', pp. 349–351; see also G. W. S. Barrow, "The Kings of Scotland and Durham", in Rollason ''et al.'' (eds.), ''Anglo-Norman Durham'', p. 318.

David's activities and whereabouts after 1114 are not always easy to trace. He spent much of his time outside his principality, in England and in Normandy. Despite the death of his sister on 1 May 1118, David still possessed the favour of King Henry when his brother Alexander died in 1124, leaving Scotland without a king.Oram, ''David'', pp. 69–72.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="370e1ef11afebe04ba0dae4bf15a9dc0" name="Henry1" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/370e1ef11afebe04ba0dae4bf15a9dc0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>