<document id="9c01415166cb80bd49d1dcb3b484b628-6.5" name="Trafford" cat="11">
<text>
Trafford is the home of several major sports teams, including Manchester United Football Club and Lancashire County Cricket Club (LCCC). Manchester United began as Newton Heath L&YR F.C. in 1878.Shurry (2005), pp. 6–8. The team plays at Old Trafford football ground, which is sometimes used as a stadium for international matches. Manchester United have won the Premier League 18 times and the FA Cup 11 times. They last won the Premier League in 2008–09. Retrieved on 13 December 2007. LCCC started as the Manchester Cricket Club, Retrieved on 13 December 2007. and represents the historic county of Lancashire. The club contested the original 1890 County Championship. Retrieved on 13 December 2007. Old Trafford Cricket Ground – Lancashire's home ground – stages international matches, including Test matches and One Day Internationals. Retrieved on 13 December 2007. The team has won the county championship eight times and in 2008 finished in fifth place.

Also in the top division of their sports are Sale Sharks, who play rugby union. From 2009, Manchester Phoenix, who play home games at the Altrincham Ice Dome, are members of the English Premier Ice Hockey Leaguethe unofficial 2nd teir of British Ice Hockey. The club was formed in 2003 as the successor to Manchester Storm and was one of the founder members of the Elite Ice Hockey League. Retrieved on 29 July 2009. Retrieved on 29 July 2009. In 2008–09 they finished sixth in the Elite Ice Hockey League. The Trafford Metros are the Phoenix's junior side and are also based at the Altrincham Ice Dome. Retrieved on 15 September 2009. Rugby Union side Sale Sharks were formerly based in Trafford and although they now play at Edgeley Park in Stockport, they retain their name from when they were based at Heywood Road in Sale; their former home-ground Road is still used as the team's training ground. Retrieved on 7 May 2007. Sale Sharks won the Guinness Premiership in 2006; in 2008–09 they finished fifth.

As well as being home to several clubs in the top echelon of their sports, Trafford plays host to smaller clubs, including Altrincham F.C., Flixton F.C., and Trafford F.C.. Both Flixton F.C. and Trafford F.C. play in the North West Counties Football League Division One. Flixton F.C. was formed in 1960 and earned promotion to NWCF Division One at the end of the 2006–07 season. Trafford F.C. was formed in 1990 and finished fifth in the 2006–07 season. Retrieved on 13 December 2007. Altrincham F.C. was founded in 1903 and plays in the Football Conference.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a012fe3f2f92ac6c21f275d344be8ae4" name="Bridgewater_Canal_and_Old_Trafford_footballl_stadium" sectnum="6.5#1">../img/a012fe3f2f92ac6c21f275d344be8ae4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>