<document id="9c76a07ab62cceeb85527b63f8b09800-3.5" name="Manzanar" cat="14">
<text>
The camp site was situated on  at Manzanar, leased from the City of Los Angeles, with the developed portion covering approximately . The residential area was about one square mile (2.6 km²), and consisted of 36 blocks of hastily constructed,  by  tarpaper barracks, with each prisoner family living in a single  by  “apartment” in the barracks. These apartments consisted of partitions with no ceilings, eliminating any chance of privacy.  Lack of privacy was a major problem for the prisoners, especially since the camp had communal men's and women's latrines.

“…One of the hardest things to endure was the communal latrines, with no partitions; and showers with no stalls,” said former Manzanar prisoner Rosie Kakuuchi.

Each residential block also had a communal mess hall, a laundry room, a recreation hall, an ironing room, and a heating oil storage tank, although Block 33 lacked a recreation hall.  In addition to the residential blocks, Manzanar had 34 additional blocks that had staff housing, camp administration offices, two warehouses, a garage, a camp hospital, and 24 firebreaks.  The camp also had school facilities, a high school auditorium, staff housing, chicken and hog farms, churches, a cemetery, a post office, a cooperative store, other shops, a camp newspaper, and other necessary amenities that one would expect to find in most American cities.  

Manzanar also had a camouflage net factory, an experimental plantation for producing natural rubber from the Guayule plant, and an orphanage called Children's Village, which housed 101 Japanese American orphans.  The camp perimeter had eight watchtowers manned by armed Military Police, and it was enclosed by five-strand barbed wire.  There were sentry posts at the main entrance.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0f6d3e1bf806cd202ad5a65e13c747a7" name="Manzanar_calisthenics_0016u" sectnum="3.5#1">../img/0f6d3e1bf806cd202ad5a65e13c747a7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>