<document id="9c76a07ab62cceeb85527b63f8b09800-3.8" name="Manzanar" cat="14">
<text>
On November 21, 1945, the WRA closed Manzanar, the sixth camp to be closed. Although the prisoners had been brought to the Owens Valley by the United States Government, they had to leave the camp and travel to their next destinations on their own.  The WRA gave each person $25, one-way train or bus fare, and meals to those who had less than $600.  While many left the camp voluntarily, a significant number refused to leave because they had no place to go after having lost everything when they were forcibly uprooted and removed from their homes.  As such, they had to be forcibly removed once again, this time from Manzanar. Indeed, those who refused to leave were generally removed from their barracks, sometimes by force, even if they had no place to go.

146 prisoners died at Manzanar.  Fifteen prisoners were buried there, but only five graves remain, as most were later reburied elsewhere by their families.

The Manzanar cemetery site is marked by a monument that was built by prisoner stonemason Ryozo Kado in 1943.  An inscription in Japanese on the front of the monument reads,  (Soul Consoling Tower). The inscription on the back reads "Erected by the Manzanar Japanese" on the left, and "August 1943" on the right.  Today, the monument is often draped in strings of ''origami'', and sometimes survivors and other visitors leave offerings of personal items as mementos.  The National Park Service periodically collects and catalogues such items.

After the camp was closed, the site eventually returned to its original state.  Within a couple of years all the structures had been removed, with the exception of the two sentry posts at the entrance, the cemetery monument, and the former Manzanar High School auditorium, which was purchased by the County of Inyo.  The County leased the auditorium to the Independence Veterans of Foreign Wars, who used it as a meeting facility and community theater until 1951. After that, the building was used as a maintenance facility by the Inyo County Road Department.

As of 2007, the site also retains numerous building foundations, portions of the water and sewer systems, the outline of the road grid, remains of the landscaping constructed by prisoners, and much more.  Despite four years of use by the prisoners, the site also retains evidence of the ranches and of the town of Manzanar, as well as artifacts from the days of the Owens Valley Paiute settlement.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1a6014d4dec93ee524464fad3f17ddac" name="SueEmbrey" sectnum="3.8#1">../img/1a6014d4dec93ee524464fad3f17ddac.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>