<document id="9c8debc2a043288f03297d2455aa7b56-4" name="Supernature_(Goldfrapp_album)" cat="20">
<text>
"Ooh La La", ''Supernature'''s opening track, inspired by  T.Rex Timmermans, Arjan. . ArjanWrites. 9 December 2005. Retrieved 29 November 2008., was chosen as its lead single "because it was up and in your face and it carried on the theme of the glammy, discoey beat from the last album".van den Boogert, Kate. . ''GoGo Paris in England''. 6 July 2005. Retrieved 30 May 2007. It was the duo's first song to feature the electric guitar, and received positive reviews, often being noted as a highlight of the album.Hubbard, Michael. . MusicOMH.com. 8 August 2005. Retrieved 16 June 2007. In the United Kingdom, "Ooh La La" was Goldfrapp's most successful single release, reaching the top five. It was also promoted in US dance clubs, and peaked in the top ten of the ''Billboard'' Hot Dance Club Play chart. The  second track, "Lovely 2 C U", received mixed reviews from critics, with one reviewer stating that it was the "worst offender of sounding by-numbers, its lazy glam affectations sounding all the worse amid a chorus striking only in its complete dullness".Vernon, Polly. . ''The Guardian''. 17 July 2005. Retrieved 16 June 2007.



"Ride a White Horse", the third single, was inspired by the disco era.Timmermans, Arjan. . ArjanWrites. 9 December 2005. Retrieved 13 June 2007. Like previous singles from the album, the song was another top-twenty single in the UK. The ballads "You Never Know" and "Let it Take You" have minimal background electronics, and were generally well-received by critics, who drew comparisons to Goldfrapp's debut album ''Felt Mountain''.Empire, Kitty. . ''The Guardian''. 14 August 2005. Retrieved 30 May 2007. "Fly Me Away", another synth ballad, had an associated music video which featured Goldfrapp as an animated doll; the video, however, was never released.. Mute Records. Retrieved 31 May 2007. The song was not heavily promoted and was less commercially successful than the other singles. "Slide In", an electroclash song about sex, and "Koko" were compared to Gary Numan's early compositions.Doran, John. . PlayLouder. 26 August 2005. Retrieved 16 June 2007.Lynskey, Dorian. . ''The Guardian''. 12 August 2005. Retrieved 16 June 2007. A remix of "Slide In" by DFA was released as a promotional single in the UK in early 2006.. Goldfrapp.free.fr. Retrieved 30 May 2007.

"Satin Chic" is a disco song with glam rock and cabaret influences, similar to early Elton John. Cited by Goldfrapp and Gregory as their favourite song on ''Supernature'', it was remixed by The Flaming Lips and issued as a limited edition single in September 2006. The tenth track, "Time Out from the World", features an orchestra and whispered vocals by Goldfrapp. Critics liked the song, writing that it was an "exception to the prevailing style of ''Supernature''" due to its "haunting, yet glamorous, atmospherics". The album's closing track and second single, "Number 1", is about the importance and meaning of relationships. The song, which is based around a synth and bass arrangement, reached the top ten in the UK and number one on the US Dance Chart.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="22610cd33064f283f619b28adf2d1702" name="Goldfrapp112" sectnum="4#1">../img/22610cd33064f283f619b28adf2d1702.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>