<document id="9ca6f5bdbe9e94435985bfd81d63e8b3-6" name="George_VI_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
Albert assumed the style and title King George VI to emphasise continuity with his father and restore confidence in the monarchy.Howarth, p. 66 The beginning of George VI's reign was taken up by questions surrounding his predecessor and brother, whose titles, style and position were uncertain. He had been introduced as "His Royal Highness Prince Edward" for the Abdication broadcast, but George VI felt that by abdicating and renouncing the succession Edward had lost the right to bear Royal titles, including "Royal Highness".Howarth, p. 143 In settling the issue, George's first act as King was to confer upon his brother the title HRH The Duke of Windsor, but the Letters Patent creating the dukedom prevented any wife or children from bearing royal styles. George VI was also forced to buy the royal residences of Balmoral Castle and Sandringham House from Prince Edward, as these were private properties and did not pass to George VI automatically.Ziegler, p. 326 Three days after his accession, on his 41st birthday, he invested his wife, the new Queen, with the Order of the Garter.Bradford, p. 223

George VI's coronation took place on 12 May 1937, the date previously intended for Edward's coronation. In a break with tradition, Queen Mary attended the ceremony as a show of support for her son.Bradford, p. 214 There was no Durbar held in Delhi for George VI, as had occurred for his father, as the cost would have been a burden to the government of India.Vickers, p. 175 Rising Indian nationalism made the welcome that the royal couple would have received likely to be muted at best,Bradford, p. 209 and a prolonged absence from Britain would have been undesirable in the tense period before World War II. Two overseas tours were undertaken, to France and North America, both of which promised greater strategic advantages in the event of war.Bradford, pp. 269, 281

The growing likelihood of war in Europe dominated the early reign of George VI. The King was constitutionally bound to support Prime Minister Neville Chamberlain's appeasement of Hitler. However, when the King and Queen greeted Chamberlain on his return from negotiating the Munich Agreement in 1938, they invited him to appear on the balcony of Buckingham Palace with them. This public association of the monarchy with a politician was exceptional, as balcony appearances were traditionally restricted to the royal family.


In May and June 1939, the King and Queen toured Canada and the United States. From Ottawa, the royal couple were accompanied throughout the trip by the Prime Minister of Canada, and not a British minister, meaning they were present in both Canada and the US as King and Queen of Canada. George was the first reigning Monarch of Canada to visit North America, though he had been to Canada previously as Prince Albert and as Duke of York. The Canadian Prime Minister, Mackenzie King, hoped that the King's presence in Canada would allow him to demonstrate in reality the principles of the Statute of Westminster 1931, which gave full self-government to the Dominions and recognised each Dominion as having a separate crown. Thus, at his Canadian residence, Rideau Hall, George VI personally accepted and approved the Letter of Credence of the newly appointed U.S. Ambassador to Canada, Daniel Calhoun Roper. The official Royal Tour historian, Gustave Lanctot, stated: "When Their Majesties walked into their Canadian residence, the Statute of Westminster had assumed full reality: the King of Canada had come home."

The entire trip was a measure intended to soften the strong isolationist tendencies among the North American public with regard to the developing tensions in Europe. Although the aim of the tour was mainly political, to shore up Atlantic support for Britain in any future war, the King and Queen were enthusiastically received by the public.Rhodes James, pp. 154–168; Vickers, p. 187 The fear that George would be unfavourably compared to his predecessor, Edward VIII, was dispelled.Bradford, pp. 298–299 They visited the 1939 New York World's Fair and stayed with President Franklin D. Roosevelt at the White House and at his private estate at Hyde Park, New York.''The Times'' Monday, 12 June 1939 p. 12 col. A
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e426fce4c76e4c389f0570e4dc8388b4" name="RoyalVisitSenate" sectnum="6#1">../img/e426fce4c76e4c389f0570e4dc8388b4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>