<document id="9d28c804bde9a6d04b496c72095d65b5-3" name="Battle_of_Cape_Esperance" cat="29">
<text>
Captain Kikunori Kijima, Gotō's chief of staff and commander of the bombardment force during the return trip to the Shortland Islands after Gotō's death in battle, claimed that his force had sunk two American cruisers and one destroyer.  ''Furutaka's'' captain, who survived the sinking of his ship, blamed the loss of his cruiser on bad air reconnaissance and poor leadership from the 8th fleet staff under Admiral Mikawa.  Although Gotō's bombardment mission failed, Jojima's reinforcement convoy was successful in delivering the crucial men and equipment to Guadalcanal.  ''Aoba'' journeyed to Kure, Japan, for repairs that were completed on February 15, 1943.  ''Kinugasa'' was sunk one month later during the Naval Battle of Guadalcanal.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 309–312, Hackett, ''HIJMS Aoba'', Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 169–171.

Scott claimed that his force sank three Japanese cruisers and four destroyers.  News of the victory was widely publicized in the American media.  ''Boise'', which was damaged enough to require a trip to the Philadelphia Naval Shipyard for repairs, was dubbed the "one-ship fleet" by the press for her exploits in the battle, although this was mainly because the names of the other involved ships were withheld for security reasons.  ''Boise'' was under repair until March 20, 1943.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 311, Cook, ''Cape Esperance'', p. 140–144, Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 170–171.

Although a tactical victory for the U.S., Cape Esperance had little immediate, strategic effect on the situation on Guadalcanal.  Just two days later on the night of October 13, the Japanese battleships ''Kongō'' and ''Haruna'' bombarded and almost destroyed Henderson Field.  One day after that, a large Japanese convoy successfully delivered 4,500 troops and equipment to the island.  These troops and equipment helped complete Japanese preparations for the large land offensive, scheduled to begin on October 23.  The convoy of U.S. Army troops reached Guadalcanal on October 13 as planned and were key participants for the Allied side in the decisive land battle for Henderson Field that took place October 23, 1942 &ndash; October 26, 1942.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 313–324, Cook, ''Cape Esperance'', p. 150–151, Dull, ''Imperial Japanese Navy'', p. 230, and Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 171.

The Cape Esperance victory helped prevent an accurate U.S. assessment of Japanese skills and tactics in naval night fighting.  The U.S. was still unaware of the range and power of Japanese torpedoes, the effectiveness of Japanese night optics, and the skilled fighting ability of most Japanese destroyer and cruiser commanders.  Incorrectly applying the perceived lessons learned from this battle, U.S. commanders in future naval night battles in the Solomons consistently tried to prove that American naval gunfire was more effective than Japanese torpedo attacks.  This belief was severely tested just two months later during the Battle of Tassafaronga, in which Japanese torpedoes inflicted one of the worst defeats suffered by the U.S. Navy in its history.  In retrospect, it appears that luck may have had as much to do with Scott's victory at Cape Esperance as the complacency that allowed Gotō's ships to be surprised by Scott's force.  A junior officer on ''Helena'' later wrote, "Cape Esperance was a three-sided battle in which chance was the major winner."Cook, ''Cape Esperance'', p. 59, 147–151, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 310–312, Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 170–171.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7123b72df23bb9834a6300fcf8b40e54" name="CapeEsperanceBoise2" sectnum="3#1">../img/7123b72df23bb9834a6300fcf8b40e54.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>