<document id="9d28c804bde9a6d04b496c72095d65b5-2.3" name="Battle_of_Cape_Esperance" cat="29">
<text>
During the battle between Scott's and Gotō's ships, Jojima's reinforcement group completed unloading at Guadalcanal and began its return journey unseen by Scott's warships, using a route that passed south of the Russell Islands and New Georgia.  Despite extensive damage, ''Aoba'' was able to join ''Kinugasa'' in retirement to the north through the Slot.  ''Furutaka's'' damage caused her to lose power around 00:50, and she sank at 02:28, 22 miles (35 km) northwest of Savo Island.  ''Hatsuyuki'' picked up ''Furutaka's'' survivors and joined the retreat northward.Cook, ''Cape Esperance'', p. 58, 97–98, 111, 120, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 306–307, D'Albas, ''Death of a Navy'', p. 187, Dull, ''Imperial Japanese Navy'', p. 229, and Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 168–169.

''Boise'' extinguished her fires by 02:40 and at 03:05 rejoined Scott's formation.  ''Duncan'', on fire, was abandoned by her crew at 02:00.  Unaware of ''Duncan's'' fate, Scott detached ''McCalla'' to search for her and retired with the rest of his ships towards Nouméa, arriving in the afternoon of October 13.  ''McCalla'' located the burning, abandoned ''Duncan'' about 03:00, and several members of ''McCalla's'' crew made an attempt to keep her from sinking.  By 12:00, however, they had to abandon the effort as interior bulkheads within ''Duncan'' collapsed causing the ship to finally sink 6 miles (10 km) north of Savo Island.  American servicemen in boats from Guadalcanal as well as ''McCalla'' picked up ''Duncan's'' scattered survivors from the sea around Savo.  In total, 195 ''Duncan'' sailors survived; 48 did not.  As they rescued ''Duncan's'' crew, the Americans came across the more than 100 ''Fubuki'' survivors, floating in the same general area.  The Japanese initially refused all rescue attempts but a day later allowed themselves to be picked up and taken prisoner.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 307–308, Cook, ''Cape Esperance'', p. 95–96, 108–110, 114–130, 135–138, Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 166–169.

Jojima, learning of the bombardment force's crisis, detached destroyers ''Shirayuki'' and ''Murakumo'' to assist ''Furutaka'' or her survivors and ''Asagumo'' and ''Natsugumo'' to rendezvous with ''Kinugasa'', which had paused in her retreat northward to cover the withdrawal of Jojima's ships.  At 07:00, five CAF SBD Dauntless dive bombers attacked ''Kinugasa'' but inflicted no damage.  At 08:20, 11 more SBDs found and attacked ''Shirayuki'' and ''Murakumo''.  Although they scored no direct hits, a near miss caused ''Murakumo'' to begin leaking oil, marking a trail for other CAF aircraft to follow.  A short time later, seven more CAF SBDs plus six TBF Avengers accompanied by 14 Wildcats found the two Japanese destroyers 170 miles (274 km) from Guadalcanal.  In the ensuing attack, ''Murakumo'' was hit by a torpedo in her engineering spaces, leaving her without power.  In the meantime, ''Aoba'' and ''Hatsuyuki'' reached the sanctuary of the Japanese base in the Shortland Islands at 10:00.Cook, ''Cape Esperance'', p. 111, 120–122, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 308–309, Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 169.

Rushing to assist ''Murakumo'', ''Asagumo'' and ''Natsugumo'' were attacked by another group of 11 CAF SBDs and TBFs escorted by 12 fighters at 15:45.  An SBD placed its bomb almost directly amidships on ''Natsugumo'' while two more near misses contributed to her severe damage.  After ''Asagumo'' took off her survivors, ''Natsugumo'' sank at 16:27.  The CAF aircraft also scored several more hits on the stationary ''Murakumo'', setting her afire.  After her crew abandoned ship, ''Shirayuki'' scuttled her with a torpedo, picked up her survivors, and joined the rest of the Japanese warships for the remainder of their return trip to the Shortland Islands.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 309, Cook, ''Cape Esperance'', p. 130–131, Dull, ''Imperial Japanese Navy'', p. 230, and Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 169.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c2431e8d2c5cc5762dec3afce459aa7a" name="Murakumo" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/c2431e8d2c5cc5762dec3afce459aa7a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>