<document id="9d81c44af8fef8e928720bd2ee5bcb01-1" name="Meerkat_Manor" cat="19">
<text>
''Meerkat Manor'' was created by Caroline Hawkins, executive producer and series editor at Oxford Scientific Films, and commissioned for Animal Planet International by executive producer and commissioning editor Mark Wild. Filming for a 13-episode series takes seven to eight months, and is limited to the Kalahari spring and summer seasons, as meerkats are less active during winter. Series three was filmed from November 2006 through April 2007, and Series four began filming in October 2007. Most scenes are filmed on location at the Kuruman River Reserve, where the Kalahari Meerkat Project that the meerkats are a part of is based.  However, the meerkats seen in commercials and on the show's website are not the same animals portrayed in ''Meerkat Manor''.  Instead, tamer rescued meerkats from the Fellow Earthlings Wildlife Center are filmed against a green screen.


The show is primarily filmed using Sony DSR570 cameras, although special equipment is needed for some unique footage. For scenes inside the animals' burrows, mini fibre-optic infra-red cameras are employed; wide-angle shots are filmed with a seven-metre crane and a remote-controlled camera platform.  An off-camera wireless microphone is also used to record many meerkat vocalizations, only partially audible to cameras' on-board systems. Most filming is done by a single cameraman and a single sound engineer; researchers have required a minimal human presence to avoid stressing the animals. Eye-level shots are difficult to achieve at times, due to the meerkats' small size and the limited height of even the smallest tripods. 

For tracking purposes, the dominant female of each group is fitted with a radio collar, as are some dominant and roaming males.  The meerkats – especially younger animals – are marked with dye to differentiate them. As the meerkats are habituated, they will usually ignore the camera crew as long as their "personal space" is respected.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ad666100ba68a3fb9fd7b90e00f05e9d" name="Filming_Meerkat_Manor" sectnum="1#1">../img/ad666100ba68a3fb9fd7b90e00f05e9d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>