<document id="9d81c44af8fef8e928720bd2ee5bcb01-2" name="Meerkat_Manor" cat="19">
<text>
The show follows several groups of meerkats, who act communally for the benefit of the groups in which they live. These groups are typically led by a dominant female and male, who maintain almost exclusive rights to have offspring.  The group followed most closely is known as the Whiskers family.  This group was chosen because of its matriarch Flower, an unusually successful dominant female who led the group for five years.  During series three, Flower died from a snake bite and was succeeded by her daughter Rocket Dog.

Animals in neighbouring groups are highlighted in each series as well.  In the first series, a group called the Lazuli were shown frequently in competition with the Whiskers family, and the opening credits referred to them as the "neighbours from hell". Although their dominant male Big Si died between series, the Lazuli appeared in the second series, mostly as a source of roving males. Another group called the Commandoes, led by a one-eyed male named Hannibal, introduced themselves by attacking the Lazuli burrow, killing a pup and badly wounding the babysitting adult. The Commandoes became the new major rivals in the area, killing the pups of evicted Whiskers female Mozart and taking over some of the Whiskers' territory.

The Whiskers' new neighbours were the Zappa and the Starsky.  Although smaller than the Whiskers, the Zappa attacked frequently, and when they fled after one attack, the Whiskers – in a rare occurrence – adopted an abandoned Zappa pup. The Starsky group, on the other hand, was no threat to the Whiskers.  Formed by a trio of Flower's daughters permanently evicted from the Whiskers, the small group was ravaged by illness, predators, and a lack of new pups.  The constantly struggling Starsky succumbed in the penultimate episode, with the death of the last survivor, Mozart, who was killed by a jackal.

Former Whiskers female Maybelline broke away from group at the end of the third series, forming a new group called the Aztecs which became the Whiskers' rivals in the fourth series.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ce673bf2cbf7554c1605a2036da10bf9" name="Meerkat_Manor_-_Meerkat_with_pups_in_burrow" sectnum="2#1">../img/ce673bf2cbf7554c1605a2036da10bf9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>