<document id="9db5265677ab7fc67158baedecb1ed5d-5" name="Óengus_I_of_the_Picts" cat="25">
<text>
The story of the foundation of St Andrews, originally ''Cennrígmonaid'', is not contemporary and may contain many inventions. The Irish annals report the death of "Tuathalán, abbot of Cinrigh Móna", in 747, making it certain that St Andrews had been founded before that date, probably by Óengus or by Nechtan son of Der-Ilei.Anderson, ''ESSH'', p. 238; Forsyth, pp. 21–22; Foster, "Discovery", pp. 42–43; Woolf, "Ungus". The most recent study, Yorke, ''Conversion'', favours Óengus. It is generally presumed that the St Andrews Sarcophagus was executed at the command of Óengus.Henderson, pp. 155–156; MacLean, pp. 200–201; Woolf, "Ungus". It is less certain whose remains the sarcophagus contained. Woolf and MacLean argue for Óengus while Henderson favours Nechtan mac Der Ilei. Clancy, "Caustantín", favours a 9th century date. Later generations may have conflated this king Óengus with the 9th century king of the same name.Foster, "Discovery", p. 42; Broun, pp. 80–81. The choice of David as a model is, as Alex Woolf notes, an appropriate one: David too was an usurper.Woolf, "Carnifex tyrannus", p. 40.

The cult of Saint Andrew may have come to Pictland from Northumbria, as had the cult of Saint Peter which had been favoured by Nechtan, and in particular from the monastery at Hexham which was dedicated to Saint Andrew. This apparent connection with the Northumbrian church may have left a written record. Óengus, like his successors and possible kinsmen Caustantín and Eógan, is recorded prominently in the ''Liber Vitae Ecclesiae Dunelmensis'', a list of some 3000 benefactors for whom prayers were said in religious institutions connected with Durham.Forsyth, pp. 25–26; Yorke, ''Conversion'', p. 167. Óengus is listed 43rd, Caustantín 80th and Eógan 100th.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1791aa9567eafe585db4cee058103432" name="Standrewssarcophagus" sectnum="5#1">../img/1791aa9567eafe585db4cee058103432.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>