<document id="9db5265677ab7fc67158baedecb1ed5d-4" name="Óengus_I_of_the_Picts" cat="25">
<text>
In 740, a war between the Picts and the Northumbrians is reported, during which Æthelbald, King of Mercia, took advantage of the absence of Eadberht of Northumbria to ravage his lands, and perhaps burn York.Anderson, ''SAEC'', pp. 55–56. The reason for the war is unclear, but it has been suggested that it was related to the killing of Earnwine son of Eadwulf on Eadberht's orders. Earnwine's father had been an exile in the north after his defeat in the civil war of 705–706, and it may be that Óengus, or Æthelbald, or both, had tried to place him on the Northumbrian throne.Woolf, "Carnifex tyrannus", p. 37. For Earnwine, see Kirby, p. 150; Yorke, ''Kings and Kingdoms'', p. 90. 

Battles between the Picts and the Britons of Alt Clut, or Strathclyde, are recorded in 744 and again in 750, when Kyle was taken from Alt Clut by Eadberht of Northumbria. The 750 battle between the Britons and the Picts is reported at a place named Mocetauc (perhaps Mugdock, near Milngavie) in which Talorgan the brother of Óengus was killed.Anderson, ''ESSH'', pp. 238–239; Anderson, ''SAEC'', p. 56. Following the defeat in 750, the ''Annals of Ulster'' record "the ebbing of the sovereignty of Óengus".Anderson, ''ESSH'', p. 240. This is thought to refer to the coming to power of Áed Find, son of Eochaid mac Echdach, in all or part of Dál Riata, and his rejection of Óengus's overlordship.Woolf, "Carnifex tyrannus", p. 38; M.O. Anderson, ''Kings and Kingship'', pp. 186–187. The entry for 752 in the ''Annals of Tigernach'', recording "the battle of Asreth in Circinn", is thought to be misplaced.

Unlike the straightforward narrative of the attacks on Dál Riata, a number of interpretations have been offered of the relations between Óengus, Eadberht and Æthelbald in the period from 740 to 750. One suggestion is that Óengus and Æthelbald were allied against Eadberht, or even that they exercised a joint rulership of Britain, or bretwaldaship, Óengus collecting tribute north of the River Humber and Æthelbald south of the Humber. This rests largely on a confused passage in Symeon of Durham's ''Historia Regum Anglorum'', and it has more recently been suggested that the interpretation offered by Frank Stenton—that it is based on a textual error and that Óengus and Æthelbald were not associated in any sort of joint overlordship—is the correct one.Woolf, "Carnifex tyrannus", p. 38; Anderson, ''SAEC'', p. 56.

In 756, Óengus is found campaigning alongside Eadberht of Northumbria. The campaign is reported as follows: In the year of the Lord's incarnation 756, king Eadberht in the eighteenth year of his reign, and Unust, king of Picts led armies to the town of Dumbarton. And hence the Britons accepted terms there, on the first day of the month of August. But on the tenth day of the same month perished almost the whole army which he led from Ouania to Niwanbirig.After Forsyth, p. 29. See also Anderson, ''SAEC'', p. 57.

That Ouania is Govan is now reasonably certain,Forsyth, pp. 29–30; Woolf, "Carnifex tyrannus", p. 39. but the location of Newanbirig is less so. Although there are very many Newburghs, it is Newburgh-on-Tyne near Hexham that has been the preferred location.Kirby, p. 150. An alternative interpretation of the events of 756 has been advanced: it identifies Newanbirig with Newborough by Lichfield in the kingdom of Mercia. A defeat here for Eadberht and Óengus by Æthelbald's Mercians would correspond with the claim in the Saint Andrews foundation legends that a king named Óengus son of Fergus founded the church there as a thanksgiving to Saint Andrew for saving him after a defeat in Mercia.Woolf, "Carnifex tyrannus", pp. 39–40. This version of the St Andrews foundation legend is given in M.O. Anderson, ''Kings and Kingship'', pp. 258–260.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2bacbd075c8c3c5fe9f0c1d43631c8a2" name="Escomb_Church_(John_Phillips)" sectnum="4#1">../img/2bacbd075c8c3c5fe9f0c1d43631c8a2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>