<document id="9dbc51776b953711c3a354f81571277e-3" name="Baby_Boy_(song)" cat="20">
<text>
"Baby Boy" was released as the second single from the album ''Dangerously in Love''. It is dedicated to Beyonce's first and true love; Darien Reyes. It was released as a CD in Canada on May 4, 2003, in Australia on September 9, and in the United States on October 14, 2003 as a 12" single. The track appeared in the revamped version of Sean Paul's 2003 second album, ''Dutty Rock''.

"Baby Boy" was well-received by critics. ''Rolling Stone'' magazine reviewer Anthony DeCurtis wrote that Knowles‎ sounded like she was "having fun" on the song, while Stephen Thomas Erlewine of Allmusic, an online music database, described Knowles' vocals as "assured and sexy". Mark Anthony Neal of the international webzine PopMatters, regarded the song as one of the "high-profile collaborations" from ''Dangerously in Love''. Lisa Verrico of the daily US newspaper ''The Times'' described the song a "Latino-tinged collaboration ... set to clicky beats that sound like castanets". She concluded that "Paul does a reggae rap in the middle, but it's when he chats while Beyoncé half raps that the pair have real chemistry". Yancey Strickler of the ''Flak'' magazine wrote that "'Baby Boy''s diwali stutter is enhanced by Sean Paul's dancehall monotone". ''Entertainment Weekly'' magazine's Neil Drumming said that "'Baby Boy' goes full-tilt Bollywood 'n da hood, with Sean Paul ripping a pulsing tabla raga".

James Anthony of the British newspaper ''The Guardian'' said the track "bridges the gap between the genres of R&B and dancehall". British record label EMI was honored by the American Society of Composers, Authors and Publishers (ASCAP) during the 2005 Pop Music Awards as Publisher of the Year for publishing "Baby Boy", among other songs. Scott Storch earned Songwriter of the Year at the same event.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2e78454539b396235caa89702a70e851" name="Beyonce_Baby_Boy" sectnum="3#1">../img/2e78454539b396235caa89702a70e851.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>