<document id="9debe920043a70eeb1daf47b569e78f8-2" name="Beyond_Fantasy_Fiction" cat="17">
<text>
According to science-fiction historian Donald H. Tuck, ''Beyond'' published "some very good material,"Donald H. Tuck writes "Although it printed some very good material, it was never commercially successful." "''Beyond Fantasy Fiction''", in Donald H. Tuck, ed., ''The Encyclopedia of Science Fiction and Fantasy'' (Chicago: Advent, 1982; ISBN 0-911682-26-0), Vol. 3, p.549. with appearances by many well-known authors, and the magazine is often cited as being the successor to the unusual fantasy tradition of ''Unknown''.Malcolm Edwards describes it as "conceived in the same spirit as ''Unknown''". Edwards, "Beyond Fantasy Fiction", in Peter Nicholls and John Clute, eds, ''The Encyclopedia of Science Fiction: An Illustrated A to Z'' (London: Granada, 1981; ISBN 0586053808), p.70. Mike Ashley comments that ''Beyond'' "is generally acknowledged as the natural successor to ''Unknown''". Ashley, "''Beyond Fantasy Fiction''", p.110.  Author James Gunn said of the new fantasy magazines that appeared in the 1950s that "the best of these was ''Beyond'', created by Horace Gold as a companion fantasy magazine to ''Galaxy'', which he had created three years before. ''Beyond Fantasy Fiction'' aimed at the same rationalized fantasy niche that ''Unknown'' had established and to which Gold had contributed stories."  Excerpted from 2003 edition at   Not everyone thought the magazine was completely successful in emulating ''Unknown'', however; P. Schuyler Miller, reviewing an anthology drawn from the pages of ''Beyond'', was generally approving but commented that "Except for Budrys, Pohl, Brown and Sturgeon, these stories from ''Beyond'' are rather self-conscious.  They are best when they are not trying to be like ''Unknown''."  Miller's assessment of the magazine overall was that it "made a pass at the same position  but didn't make it.""The Reference Library", ''Analog Science Fact&mdash;Science Fiction'' vol. 71, no 5 (July 1963), pp. 87&ndash;88.

''Beyond'''s selection of stories has been described by science fiction historian Michael Ashley as "seeking to achieve … high quality fantasy fiction acceptable to all readers"; he adds that ''Beyond'' was more successful than ''Fantastic Science Fiction'', a competitor in this niche, because Gold "had a clearer vision and was more determined … to achieve it. … despite sales problems, Gold persisted in publishing fiction that sought to stretch the boundaries of imagination."

Several significant or widely reprinted stories appeared during ''Beyond'''s short history:All but the Gunn and Dick stories are included by Tuck in his list of "Notable fiction" from ''Beyond''. The Gunn story is mentioned as a classic by Ashley, in "''Beyond Fantasy Fiction''", p.110. Dick's story is included because of his current prominence; see Tuck "''Beyond Fantasy Fiction''".

* "…And My Fear Is Great…", by Theodore Sturgeon (July 1953)
* "The Wall Around the World", by Theodore R. Cogswell (September 1953)
* "Kid Stuff", by Isaac Asimov (September 1953)
* "The Watchful Poker Chip", by Ray Bradbury (March 1954).  Generally reprinted under the title "The Watchful Poker Chip of H. Matisse"
* "Sine of the Magus", by James E. Gunn (May 1954)
* "The Green Magician", by L. Sprague de Camp and Fletcher Pratt (November 1954).  Part of the Incompleat Enchanter series
* "Upon the Dull Earth", by Philip K. Dick (November 1954)

Although no Hugo Awards were presented in 1954, the 2004 World Science Fiction Convention awarded "Retro Hugos" for that year.  Two ''Beyond'' stories appeared as runners-up: Sturgeon's "…And My Fear Is Great…" placed third in the novella category, and Cogswell's "The Wall Around the World" fifth in the novelette category.  In addition, Gold placed fifth in the editor category, though this recognized his work at ''Galaxy'' as well as at ''Beyond''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="aec1e505f0714e5e966918f157c91bce" name="BeyondFantasyFictionMar54" sectnum="2#1">../img/aec1e505f0714e5e966918f157c91bce.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>