<document id="9dffbfe79a6f8de8db78f3281eb180f8-1" name="Leek_Town_F.C." cat="26">
<text>
Football was played in Leek from at least 1876, with an earlier side called simply Leek F.C. having been part of The Combination in the 1890s, but the current Leek Town club traces its lineage to the formation of a team called '''Leek Lowe Hamil''' in 1946 (although the club's official history does not mention it, some sources state that the club was initially known as '''Abbey Green Rovers''' before adopting the Lowe Hamil name).  

The club began life playing in the local Leek and Moorlands League, playing on a field adjoining a pub, before joining the Staffordshire County League in 1947. In 1949&ndash;50 Lowe Hamil were champions of this league, becoming the first (and to date only) team to win the title without losing a single match (some sources state this title win occurred in 1950&ndash;51). In 1951 the team switched to the Manchester League, adopting the name Leek Town at the same time, and won the championship at the first attempt, after which the team relocated once more to the Mid-Cheshire League, where again they played for just one season. In 1954 the team joined the Birmingham & District League but resigned in the middle of the 1956&ndash;57 season due to financial difficulties, after which they had another brief spell in the Manchester League, which was also curtailed due to monetary problems, before eventually returning to the Staffordshire County League.

In 1968 a new committee was formed, under which the club emerged from the doldrums. Manager Paul Ogden took over in 1969 and led the club to two Staffordshire County League championships, followed in quick succession by two Manchester League titles. After the second Manchester League win, Leek joined the Cheshire County League, where they were league champions at the second attempt in the 1974&ndash;75 season, but after Ogden left in 1975 to take over as manager of Northwich Victoria a series of managers came and went in quick succession without being able to maintain this level of success.

In 1982 the Cheshire County League merged with the Lancashire Combination to form the new North West Counties League, where Leek spent five relatively unsuccessful seasons. During their spell in this league former England player Mike Pejic took over as manager, Leek's most high-profile appointment to date, but he had only a short reign before moving to Northwich Victoria. Following Kevin Lewis' brief reign Neil Baker took over in 1986 and was to lead the club to its greatest success to date.  

Leek were chosen to be among the founder members of the new Northern Premier League Division One in 1987 and in 1989&ndash;90 won the Division One title to gain promotion to the Premier Division, the highest level at which they had ever played.  In the same season they progressed through eight rounds of the FA Trophy, including a quarter-final win over Darlington, that season's Conference champions, to reach the final at Wembley Stadium but were defeated 3&ndash;0 by Barrow.

In 1993&ndash;94 Leek finished second in the Northern Premier League Premier Division, which should have been sufficient for promotion to the Football Conference, however they were refused promotion due to financial irregularities.  To compound their problems, they were shifted from the Northern Premier League to the Southern League; the resulting travel costs nearly crippled the club.  After one season the club was allowed to return to the Northern Premier League.


In 1996&ndash;97 Leek again claimed the Northern Premier League title and were this time granted promotion to the Conference.  In their first season at this level they narrowly managed to avoid relegation but could not repeat the feat the following year and were relegated back to the Northern Premier League Premier Division. In 2000&ndash;01 the Blues were relegated to Division One, but regained their place in the Premier Division when the league was restructured due to the formation of Conference North in 2004.  The club achieved several mid-table finishes in the league but struggled off the pitch. On 21 June 2006 it was announced that the club was in such severe financial peril that it was facing a winding-up order, but on 11 June the following year it was confirmed that a new consortium had taken over the club and secured its future.  In the 2007&ndash;08 season Leek finished in the bottom four, resulting in relegation to Division One South.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="abf795b8ca0afc798ce9bbd61e2c6938" name="LeekInAction" sectnum="1#1">../img/abf795b8ca0afc798ce9bbd61e2c6938.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>