<document id="9e321ce0b48fb892da5f51c04b1c80b9-3" name="James_Bowie" cat="14">
<text>
Bowie became internationally famous as a result of a feud with Norris Wright, the sheriff of Rapides Parish. Bowie had supported Wright's opponent in the race for sheriff, and Wright, a bank director, had been instrumental in turning down Bowie's loan application.Hopewell (1994), pp. 25&ndash;26.  After a confrontation in Alexandria one afternoon, Wright fired a shot at Bowie.  The uninjured Bowie was enraged and tried to kill Wright with his bare hands.  Wright's friends intervened and stopped the attack, after which Bowie resolved to carry his hunting knife at all times.Edmondson (2000), pp. 84&ndash;85. The knife he carried had a huge blade that was  long and  wide.



The following year, on September 19, 1827, Bowie and Wright attended a duel on a sandbar outside of Natchez, Mississippi. Bowie supported duelist Samuel Levi Wells III, while Wright supported Wells's opponent, Dr. Thomas Harris Maddox. The duelists each fired two shots, and, as neither man had been injured, resolved their duel with a handshake.Hopewell (1994), pp. 28, 30.Edmondson (2000), pp. 97&ndash;98.  Other members of the groups, who had various reasons for disliking each other, began fighting. Bowie was shot in the hip; after regaining his feet he drew a knife, described as a butcher knife, and charged his attacker. The attacker hit Bowie over the head with his empty pistol, breaking the pistol and knocking Bowie to the ground. Wright shot at and missed the prone Bowie, who returned fire and possibly, hit Wright. Wright then drew his sword cane and impaled Bowie. When Wright attempted to retrieve his blade by placing his foot on Bowie's chest and tugging, Bowie pulled him down and disemboweled Wright with his large knife.Hopewell (1994), p. 31.Edmondson (2000), pp. 99&ndash;101. Wright died instantly, and Bowie, with Wright's sword still protruding from his chest, was shot again and stabbed by another member of the group. The doctors who had been present for the duel retrieved the bullets and patched Bowie's other wounds.Hopewell (1994), p. 32.

Newspapers picked up the story, which became known as the Sandbar Fight, and described in detail Bowie's fighting prowess and his unusual knife. Witness accounts agreed that Bowie did not attack first, and the others had focused their attack on Bowie because "they considered him the most dangerous man among their opposition." Hopewell (1994), pp. 33&ndash;34.  The fight cemented Bowie's reputation across the South as a superb knife-fighter.

There is disagreement among scholars as to whether the knife used in this fight was the same kind of knife now known as a Bowie knife.  Multiple accounts exist of who designed and built the first Bowie knife. Some claim that Bowie designed it, while others attribute the design to noted knife makers of the time.Hopewell (1994), pp. 35&ndash;36. However, in a letter to ''The Planter's Advocate'', Rezin Bowie claimed to have invented the knife,Hopewell (1994), p. 41. and many Bowie family members as well as "most authorities on the Bowie knife tend to believe it was invented by" Rezin.Hopewell (1994), pp. 37, 39. Rezin Bowie's grandchildren, however, claimed that Rezin merely supervised his blacksmith, who was the creator of the knife.Edmondson (2000), p. 123

After the Sandbar Fight and subsequent battles in which Bowie successfully used his knife to defend himself, the Bowie knife became very popular. Many craftsmen and manufacturers made their own versions, and major cities of the Southwest had "Bowie knife schools", which taught "the art of cut, thrust, and parry."Hopewell (1994), p. 55.  His fame, and that of his knife, spread to England, and by the early 1830s many British manufacturers were producing Bowie knives for shipment to the United States.Hopewell (1994), p. 56.  Edmondson (2000), p. 122.  The design of the knife continued to evolve, but today a Bowie knife generally is considered to have a blade  long and  wide, with a curved point, a "sharp false edge cut from both sides", and a cross-guard to protect the user's hands.Hopewell (1994), pp. 40, 42.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="06c627cfbac6c66dbf188a8f13311fd2" name="Bowie_knife_1" sectnum="3#1">../img/06c627cfbac6c66dbf188a8f13311fd2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>