<document id="9ed3be384dfd4945dd94e3f14c0abe32-8" name="Shapinsay" cat="11">
<text>
In common with the other Orkney islands, Shapinsay is fertile agricultural land, with farms specialising in beef and lamb which export thousands of cattle and sheep annually. The Orcadian. Retrieved 12 October 2007.Wenham, Sheena "The South Isles" in Omand, Donald (ed.) (2003) ''op cit'' page 98. Orkney Ferries provides transport for pedestrians and vehicles, proximity to Kirkwall permitting closer contacts with the Orkney Mainland than is possible for most of the other North Isles. There are six crossings per day, the journey lasting about 25 minutes, which allows for a moderate amount of commuting. Undiscovered Scotland.  Retrieved 10 October 2007. (pdf) Orkney Ferries. Retrieved 10 October 2007.Hewitson, Jim "The North Isles", in Omand, Donald (ed.) (2003) ''op cit'' page 186. Between 1893 and 1964, the island was served by the steamer ''Iona''. Since 1964, the ''Klydon'' and then the ''Clytus'' have operated the service; the current ferry is the ''MV Shapinsay''.Muir, Tom "Transport and Communications" in Omand, Donald (ed.) (2003) ''op cit'' pages 216 and 219. The Orkney Islands Council has considered building a tunnel to the Orkney Mainland.. BBC News Website, 2005-03-09. Retrieved 18 October 2007. Balfour Castle is now run as a hotel by the family of Captain Tadeusz Zawadzki, a Polish cavalry officer. balfourcastle.co.uk. Retrieved 10 October 2007.


The Shapinsay development trust is working on the island's community plan, including plans to build a wind turbine. As of August 2007, a feasibility study has been carried out and, in December 2006, the trust held a "Renewable Energy Awareness Day" on the island. (pdf) (January 2007)  ''Community Energy News No.  4''. Dingwall. HICEC. Retrieved 10 October 2007. A study on the impact the turbine will have on the island's bird life is under way, and meteorological and visual impact studies are planned.The meteorological study will involve erecting a 50 metre (164 ft) mast with three anemometers at the proposed site of the turbine to record wind speed, direction and turbulence, while the Landscape Impact Assessment will involve the creation of computer generated photomontages.    According to the development trust, the turbine could earn more than £5 million during its 25-year lifetime.

Small businesses on Shapinsay include a jam and chutney manufacturer, which uses traditional methods, and a studio offering residential arts courses such as stained glass crafting.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="60d2579278748bb7884533ae7c1879c4" name="Shapinsay_Pier" sectnum="8#1">../img/60d2579278748bb7884533ae7c1879c4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>