<document id="9ed3be384dfd4945dd94e3f14c0abe32-2.2" name="Shapinsay" cat="11">
<text>
The 18th century saw the beginnings of change to agriculture on Shapinsay, courtesy of the Balfour family. The family owned the estate of Sound, which covered the western part of the island. Sound had passed from the Tulloch family to the Buchanan family in the 17th century. In 1674, Arthur Buchanan built the house of Sound, where Balfour Castle now stands. His granddaughter married James Fea, who is best known for his role in the capture of the Orkney Pirate John Gow. Fea was a supporter of the Jacobite Rebellion, and the house was burned by Hanoverian troops in revenge. The estate was acquired by Andrew Ross, Stewart Depute in Orkney of the Earl of Morton.The office of Stewart Depute was also known as ''Sheriff Depute''  Ross's heirs, the Lindsay brothers, sold the estate to Thomas Balfour in 1782.Tait, Charles (2006) ''op cit'' pages 498&ndash;507 Balfour had previously rented the Bu of Burray, a large manor farm on another Orkney island. They did not possess enough wealth to acquire the estate, even though his wife had inherited a legacy on the death of her aristocratic brother.  To raise the necessary funds, Balfour had to sell his military commission and borrow money from his brother, John, who was prospering in India with the East India Company. Once installed on the island, he built a new house, Cliffdale, and founded the village of Shoreside, now known as Balfour. He also reformed the local agriculture, enclosing fields and constructing farm buildings.

William Irving was born c. 1740 in the small hamlet of Quholm in the northeast part of the island. He became a sailor before emigrating to New York in 1763. One of his sons was Washington Irving, author of Rip van Winkle and the first American author to gain international recognition.

Marjory Meason, a native of Shapinsay, was the last person to be executed in Orkney, in 1728. She was a young servant, hanged in Kirkwall for the murder of a child. The execution is recorded as requiring 24 armed men, not including officers, and costing £15 8s.

During this period, burning kelp was a mainstay of the island economy.  Over  of burned seaweed were produced per annum to make soda ash, bringing in £20,000 for the inhabitants. Thomas Balfour's income from the kelp industry brought him four times the income that farming did.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8c9dc911b76afc28aec6f2bd083eccc9" name="Shapinsaykirkyard" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/8c9dc911b76afc28aec6f2bd083eccc9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>