<document id="9ed3be384dfd4945dd94e3f14c0abe32-2.4" name="Shapinsay" cat="11">
<text>
The Balfour estate sold its farms on Shapinsay between 1924 and 1928. This was a common occurrence in Orkney at the time as wealthy landowners moved to more lucrative forms of investment. Farms were generally sold to the sitting tenant or to their neighbours who wished to expand.

The 20th century saw many changes in farming on Shapinsay. Mechanised implements came to the island, particularly after the Second World War. In common with the rest of Orkney, the amount of land given over to growing grass increased. The growing of grain (with the exception of barley) and turnips steadily declined as these were replaced as winter fodder for livestock by silage, usually harvested by mechanical forage harvesters. of farmland (90% of the archipelago's cultivated land excluding rough grazing) is now under grass, of which  are cut for hay or silage. Thomson, William P.L (2001) ''op cit'' page 422.

Orkney was a strategic site during both World Wars, and Shapinsay was no exception. In 1917, during the First World War, the  ''Swiftsure'' was hit by a mine 4 kilometres (2.5 mi) east of Haco's Ness and sank in 19 metres (62 ft) of water with the loss of a single life. The site of the wreck was not discovered until 1997. Scapa Flow Charters. Retrieved 13 October 2007

During the Second World War, gun batteries were built on the island. A twin six pounder emplacement at Galtness Battery on the coast at Salt Ness protected the Wide Firth from German torpedo boats. A Castle Battery was operational from 1941&ndash;43, as was an anti-aircraft battery. Mains electricity arrived on Shapinsay in the 1970s, when an underwater cable was laid from Kirkwall.

The trend towards more intensive farming began to be partially reversed by the end of the century as more environmentally friendly practices were encouraged by government and European Union grants. For example, Richard Zawadzki, owner of Balfour Mains (the largest farm on the island), ceased to breed livestock (instead keeping animals bred elsewhere) and grows less grain (some barley is still grown on the farm). Instead, some of the land is now managed under a Habitat Creation Scheme, which aims to encourage natural vegetation, wild flowers and nesting birds by limiting grazing and reducing the use of chemical fertilisers.

Tourism started to become important in the latter half of the century; the first restaurant to incorporate bed and breakfast facilities opened in 1980.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="244cbde93541854d9c334daa410e2654" name="Elwickshapinsay" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/244cbde93541854d9c334daa410e2654.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>