<document id="9f61eb10a3b4a7be3a81a913f3f2b9da-3" name="Andrew_Cunningham,_1st_Viscount_Cunningham_of_Hyndhope" cat="29">
<text>
Cunningham was a highly decorated officer during the First World War, receiving the Distinguished Service Order (DSO) and two bars. In 1911 he was given command of the destroyer HMS ''Scorpion'', which he commanded throughout the war. In 1914, ''Scorpion'' was involved in the shadowing of the German battlecruiser and cruiser SMS ''Goeben'' and SMS ''Breslau''. This operation was intended to find and destroy the ''Goeben'' and the ''Breslau'' but the German warships evaded the British fleet,Moorehead, Alan p11–28 and passed through the Dardanelles to reach Constantinople. Their arrival contributed to the Ottoman Empire joining the Central Powers in November 1914. Though a bloodless "battle", the failure of the British pursuit had enormous political and military ramifications—in the words of Winston Churchill, they brought "more slaughter, more misery and more ruin than has ever before been borne within the compass of a ship."Tuchman, Barbara p.154

Cunningham stayed on in the Mediterranean and in 1915 ''Scorpion'' was involved in the attack on the Dardanelles. For his performance Cunningham was rewarded with promotion to Commander and the award of the Distinguished Service Order. Cunningham spent much of 1916 on routine patrols. In late 1916, he was engaged in convoy protection, a duty he regarded as mundane.Michael Simpson p.13 He had no contact with German U-boats during this time, on which he commented; "The immunity of my convoys, was probably due to sheer luck". Convinced that the Mediterranean held few offensive possibilities he requested to sail for home. ''Scorpion'' paid off on 21 January 1918. In his seven years as captain of the ''Scorpion'', Cunningham had developed a reputation for first class seamanship.Michael Simpson p.14 He was transferred by Vice-Admiral Roger Keyes to HMS ''Termagent'', part of Keyes' Dover Patrol, in April 1918. and for his actions with the Dover Patrol, he was awarded a bar to his DSO the following year.Michael Simpson p.14–15
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="409217364d815afce461a03d8d38c33c" name="Distinghuised_Service_Order_correct" sectnum="3#1">../img/409217364d815afce461a03d8d38c33c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>