<document id="9f61eb10a3b4a7be3a81a913f3f2b9da-2" name="Andrew_Cunningham,_1st_Viscount_Cunningham_of_Hyndhope" cat="29">
<text>
Along with 64 other men Cunningham joined the Royal Navy as a cadet aboard the training ship HMS ''Britannia'' in 1897.Michael Simpson Chap1 p.2 One of his classmates was future Admiral of the Fleet James Fownes Somerville. Cunningham was known for his lack of enthusiasm for field sports, although he did enjoy golf and spent most of his spare time "messing around in boats". He said in his memoirs that by the end of his course he was "anxious to seek adventure at sea". Although he committed numerous minor misdemeanors, he still obtained a ''very good'' for conduct. He passed out tenth in April, 1898, with first-class-marks for mathematics and seamanship.Dartmouth archives 1897–1899 cited by Michael Simpson in the "References" section, p.283

His first service was as a Midshipman on HMS ''Doris'' in 1899, serving at the Cape Station when the Second Boer War began.; quote from source cited.  By February, 1900, he had transferred into the Naval Brigade as he believed "this promised opportunities for bravery and distinction in action." Cunningham then saw action at Pretoria and Diamond Hill as part of the Naval Brigade. He then went back to sea, as Midshipman in HMS ''Hannibal'' in December, 1901. The following November he joined the protected cruiser HMS ''Diadem''. Beginning in 1902, Cunningham took Sub-Lieutenant courses at Portsmouth and Greenwich; he served as Sub-Lieutenant on the battleship HMS ''Implacable'', in the Mediterranean, for six months in 1903. In September 1903, he was transferred to HMS ''Locust'' to serve as second-in-command. He was promoted to Lieutenant in 1904, and served on several vessels during the next four years. In 1908, he was awarded his first command, HM Torpedo Boat No. 14.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e03a572011036f0fc14fe11629f0d42f" name="United_Kingdom_-_England_-_London_-_Greenwich_-_Old_Royal_Naval_College" sectnum="2#1">../img/e03a572011036f0fc14fe11629f0d42f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>