<document id="9f65236f3f0c18b8b7845acd72c0a6ec-2.2" name="Humpback_Whale" cat="3">
<text>
The humpback social structure is loose-knit. Usually, individuals live alone or in small transient groups that assemble and break up over the course of a few hours. Groups may stay together a little longer in summer in order to forage and feed cooperatively. Longer-term relationships between pairs or small groups, lasting months or even years, have rarely been observed. Recent studies extrapolate feeding bonds observed with many females in Alaskan waters over the last 10 years. It is possible some females may retain these bonds for a lifetime. The range of the humpback overlaps considerably with many other whale and dolphin species &mdash; (for instance, the Minke Whale). However, humpbacks rarely interact socially with them. Humpback calves have been observed in Hawaiian waters playing with bottlenose dolphin calves.

Courtship rituals take place during the winter months, when the whales migrate toward the equator from their summer feeding grounds closer to the poles. Competition is usually fierce, and unrelated males dubbed ''escorts'' by researcher Louis Herman frequently trail females as well as mother-calf dyads. Groups of two to twenty males typically gather around a single female and exhibit a variety of behaviors in order to establish dominance in what is known as a ''competitive group''. Displays may last several hours. Competitive group size may ebb and flow as unsuccessful males retreat and others arrive to try their luck. Techniques used include breaching, spy-hopping, lob-tailing, tail-slapping, flipper-slapping, peduncle throws, charging and parrying.  "Super pods" have been observed numbering more than 40 males, all vying for the same female. (M. Ferrari et al.)

Whale song is assumed to have an important role in mate selection; however, scientists remain unsure whether the song is used between males in order to establish identity and dominance, between a male and a female as a mating call, or a mixture of the two. All these vocal and physical techniques have also been observed while not in the presence of potential mates. This indicates that they are probably important as a more general communication tool. Recent studies show singing males attracting other males. Scientists hypothesize that the singing may be a way to keep migrating populations connected. (Ferrari, Nicklin, Darling, et al.) It has also been noted that the singing begins when the competition ends.www.whaletrust.com
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="aeaf6efb4757f732c4c26f8dec5dc4c9" name="Humpback_stellwagen_edit" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/aeaf6efb4757f732c4c26f8dec5dc4c9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>