<document id="9f65236f3f0c18b8b7845acd72c0a6ec-5" name="Humpback_Whale" cat="3">
<text>
Internationally this species is considered "least concern" from a conservation standpoint as of 2008. This is an improvement from vulnerable status in the prior assessment.  Most monitored stocks of humpback whales have rebounded well since the end of the commercial whaling era, such as the North Atlantic where stocks are now believed to be approaching pre-hunting levels. However, the species is considered endangered in some countries, including the United States.http://www.nmfs.noaa.gov/pr/species/mammals/cetaceans/humpbackwhale.htm US National Marine Fisheries Service humpback whale web page  The United States initiated a status review of the species on August 12, 2009 and is seeking public comment on potential changes to the species listing under the U.S. Endangered Species Act.http://edocket.access.gpo.gov/2009/E9-19336.htm Initiation of a Status Review 
for the Humpback Whale Comments must be received by October 13, 2009. Areas where population data is limited and the species may be at higher risk include the Arabian Sea, the western North Pacific Ocean, the west coast of Africa and parts of Oceania.

Today, individuals are vulnerable to collisions with ships, entanglement in fishing gear, and noise pollution. Like other cetaceans, humpbacks are sensitive to noise and can even be injured by it. In the 19th century, two humpback whales were found dead near sites of repeated oceanic sub-bottom blasting, with traumatic injuries and fractures in the ears.

Once hunted to the brink of extinction the humpback whale has made a dramatic comeback in the North Pacific Ocean.  A study released May 22, 2008 estimates that the humpback whale population that hit a low of 1,500 whales before hunting was banned worldwide, has made a comeback to a population of between 18,000 and 20,000.

The ingestion of saxitoxin, a Paralytic shellfish poisoning (PSP) from contaminated mackerel has been implicated in humpback whale deaths.

Some countries are creating action plans to protect the humpback; for example, in the United Kingdom, the humpback whale has been designated as a priority species under the national Biodiversity Action Plan, generating a set of actions to conserve the species. The sanctuary provided by National Parks such as Glacier Bay National Park and Preserve and Cape Hatteras National Seashore, among others, have also become a major factor in sustaining the populations of the species in those areas.

Although much was learned about the humpback from whaling, migratory patterns and social interactions of the species were not well understood until two studies by R. Chittleborough and W. H. Dawbin in the 1960s.Chittleborough RG. (1965) Dynamics of two populations of the humpback whale. ''Australian Journal of Marine and Freshwater Research'' '''16''': 33&ndash;128. Roger Payne and Scott McVay made further studies of the species in 1971.Payne RS, McVay S. (1971) Songs of humpback whales. ''Science'' '''173''':585–597. Their analysis of whale song led to worldwide media interest, and left an impression in the public mind that whales were highly intelligent species, contributing to the anti-whaling stance of many countries.

In August 2008, the IUCN changed the whale's status from Vulnerable to Least Concern, although two subpopulations remain endangered.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5071e0bea3e483ca7a144e897f27c51b" name="DeadHumpback" sectnum="5#1">../img/5071e0bea3e483ca7a144e897f27c51b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>