<document id="9f9776cf2869d6f5ff0db275b44cc599-3.10" name="Tyrannosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
There are two main issues concerning the locomotory abilities of ''Tyrannosaurus'': how well it could turn; and what its maximum straight-line speed was likely to have been. Both are relevant to the debate about whether it was a hunter or a scavenger (see below).

''Tyrannosaurus'' may have been slow to turn, possibly taking one to two seconds to turn only 45° — an amount that humans, being vertically oriented and tail-less, can spin in a fraction of a second. The cause of the difficulty is rotational inertia, since much of ''Tyrannosaurus''’ mass was some distance from its center of gravity, like a human carrying a heavy timber — although it might have reduced the average distance by arching its back and tail and pulling its head and forelimbs close to its body, rather like the way ice skaters pull their arms closer in order to spin faster.

Scientists have produced a wide range of maximum speed estimates, mostly around , but a few as low as , and a few as high as . Researchers have to rely on various estimating techniques because, while there are many tracks of very large theropods walking, so far none have been found of very large theropods running—and this absence ''may'' indicate that they did not run. Scientists who think that ''Tyrannosaurus'' was able to run point out that hollow bones and other features that would have lightened its body may have kept adult weight to a mere 5 tons or so, or that other animals like ostriches and horses with long, flexible legs are able to achieve high speeds through slower but longer strides. Additionally, some have argued that ''Tyrannosaurus'' had relatively larger leg muscles than any animal alive today, which could have enabled fast running .

Jack Horner and Don Lessem argued in 1993 that ''Tyrannosaurus'' was slow and probably could not run (no airborne phase in mid-stride), because its ratio of femur (thigh bone) to tibia (shin bone) length was greater than 1, as in most large theropods and like a modern elephant. However, Holtz (1998) noted that tyrannosaurids and some closely related groups had significantly longer distal hindlimb components (shin plus foot plus toes) relative to the femur length than most other theropods), and that tyrannosaurids and their close relatives had a tightly interlocked metatarsus that more effectively transmitted locomotory forces from the foot to the lower leg than in earlier theropods ("metatarsus" means the foot bones, which function as part of the leg in digitigrade animals). He therefore concluded that tyrannosaurids and their close relatives were the fastest large theropods.

Christiansen (1998) estimated that the leg bones of ''Tyrannosaurus'' were not significantly stronger than those of elephants, which are relatively limited in their top speed and never actually run (there is no airborne phase), and hence proposed that the dinosaur's maximum speed would have been about , which is about the speed of a human sprinter. But he also noted that such estimates depend on many dubious assumptions.

Farlow and colleagues (1995) have argued that a ''Tyrannosaurus'' weighing  to  would have been critically or even fatally injured if it had fallen while moving quickly, since its torso would have slammed into the ground at a deceleration of 6 ''g'' (six times the acceleration due to gravity, or about 60 meters/s²) and its tiny arms could not have reduced the impact. However, giraffes have been known to gallop at , despite the risk that they might break a leg or worse, which can be fatal even in a "safe" environment such as a zoo. Thus it is quite possible that ''Tyrannosaurus'' also moved fast when necessary and had to accept such risks. catalogs the injuries of the ''Allosaurus'' known as "Big Al" - at least one was attributed to a fall.

Most recent research on ''Tyrannosaurus'' locomotion does not support speeds faster than , i.e. moderate-speed running. For example, a 2002 paper in the journal ''Nature'' used a mathematical model (validated by applying it to three living animals, alligators, chickens, and humans; additionally later eight more species including emus and ostriches) to gauge the leg muscle mass needed for fast running (over ). They found that proposed top speeds in excess of  were unfeasible, because they would require very large leg muscles (more than approximately 40&ndash;86% of total body mass). Even moderately fast speeds would have required large leg muscles. This discussion is difficult to resolve, as it is unknown how large the leg muscles actually were in ''Tyrannosaurus''. If they were smaller, only  walking/jogging might have been possible.

A study in 2007 used computer models to estimate running speeds, based on data taken directly from fossils, and claimed that ''Tyrannosaurus rex'' had a top running speed of . An average professional football (soccer) player would be slightly slower, while a human sprinter can reach . Note that these computer models predict a top speed of  for a  ''Compsognathus'' (probably a juvenile individual).

Those who argue that ''Tyrannosaurus'' was incapable of running estimate the top speed of ''Tyrannosaurus'' at about . This is still faster than its most likely prey species, hadrosaurids and ceratopsians. In addition, some advocates of the idea that ''Tyrannosaurus'' was a predator claim that tyrannosaur running speed is not important, since it may have been slow but still faster than its probable prey. However, Paul and Christiansen (2000) argued that at least the later ceratopsians had upright forelimbs and the larger species may have been as fast as rhinos. Healed ''Tyrannosaurus'' bite wounds on ceratopsian fossils are interpreted as evidence of attacks on living ceratopsians (see below). If the ceratopsians that lived alongside ''Tyrannosaurus'' were fast, that casts doubt on the argument that ''Tyrannosaurus'' did not have to be fast to catch its prey.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="992dff2c01476a686109cdab0d2dbcd5" name="France_Lozère_Saint-Laurent-de-Trèves_Empreinte_3" sectnum="3.10#1">../img/992dff2c01476a686109cdab0d2dbcd5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>