<document id="9fcafe9f332d55c162a92732cd7e486f-1.4" name="Plunketts_Creek_Bridge_No._3" cat="11">
<text>
In January 1996, there was major flooding throughout Pennsylvania. The 1995&ndash;1996 early winter was unusually cold, and considerable ice buildup formed in local streams. A major blizzard on January 6&ndash;8 produced up to  of snow, which was followed on January 19&ndash;21 by more than  of rain with temperatures as high as  and winds up to . The rain and snowmelt caused flooding throughout Pennsylvania and ice jams made this worse on many streams. Elsewhere in Lycoming County, flooding on Lycoming Creek in and near Williamsport killed six people and caused millions of dollars in damage. 

On Plunketts Creek, ice jams led to record flooding, which caused irreparable major damage to the mid-19th century stone arch bridge.  Metadata including black and white photographs and descriptive captions is .  Downstream in Barbours, the waters were  deep in the village's "worst flood in history". Plunketts Creek Bridge No. 3 was one of two destroyed in Lycoming County, and on January 31 a photograph of the damaged bridge was featured on the front page of the ''Williamsport Sun-Gazette'' with the caption "This old stone arch bridge over Plunketts Creek must be replaced." In neighboring Sullivan County, the Sonestown Covered Bridge, also on the NRHP, was so damaged by the flood that it remained closed for repairs until late December 1996. Throughout Pennsylvania, these floods led to 20 deaths and 69 municipal- or state-owned bridges being either "destroyed or closed until inspections could verify their safety". 

When it became clear that the bridge could not be repaired, PennDOT awarded an emergency contract for a temporary bridge before the end of January, citing "emergency vehicles that can no longer travel directly from Barbours" to Proctor and beyond. The temporary bridge cost $87,000 and was  wide. The photographs for the bridge's inclusion in the Historic American Engineering Record (HAER) were taken in January, and the HAER "documentation package was prepared as mitigation for the emergency demolition" of the bridge, which was collapsed in March. The permanent replacement bridge was completed in 1996, and the bridge was removed from the NRHP on July 22, 2002.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="13f2d4316ff2f69f26d55aa2668eef2b" name="Plunketts_Creek_Bridge_No._3,_photo_6,_Crop" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/13f2d4316ff2f69f26d55aa2668eef2b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>