<document id="a028e1749e4473deebc6bc15478ff248-2.2" name="Maggie_Gyllenhaal" cat="19">
<text>
Gyllenhaal's break-out role was in the black comedy  ''Secretary'' (2002), a film about two people who embark on a mutually fulfilling BDSM lifestyle. ''New York Times'' critic Stephen Holden noted: "The role of Lee, which Maggie Gyllenhaal imbues with a restrained comic delicacy and sweetness, should make her a star." Mick LaSalle of the ''San Francisco Chronicle'' wrote: "Maggie Gyllenhaal, as the self-destructive secretary, is enigmatic and, at moments, sympathetic." The film received generally favorable reviews, and Gyllenhaal's performance earned her the Best Breakthrough Performance award from the Online Film Critics Society, her first Golden Globe nomination, and an Independent Spirit Award nomination. ''Secretary'' was Gyllenhaal's first film role which featured full frontal nudity. Although impressed with the script, she initially had some qualms about doing the film, which she believed could deliver an antifeminist message. Yet after carefully discussing the script with the film's director, Steven Shainberg, she agreed to join the project. Although insisting Shainberg did not exploit her, Gyllenhaal has said she felt "scared when filming began" and that "in the wrong hands ... even in just slightly less intelligent hands, this movie could say something really weird." Since then, she is guarded about discussing her role in the film, saying only that "despite myself, sometimes the dynamic that you are exploring in your work spills over into your life."

She next played a supporting role in the comedy-drama ''Adaptation.'' (2002), a film that tells the story of screenwriter Charlie Kaufman's struggle to adapt ''The Orchid Thief'' into a film. She later appeared in the unauthorized biography ''Confessions of a Dangerous Mind'' (2002), part of an ensemble cast that included Sam Rockwell, Drew Barrymore, George Clooney, and Julia Roberts. The movie grossed $33 million worldwide. That same year, she also had a smaller role in the comedy ''40 Days and 40 Nights''.

In 2003, she co-starred with Julia Roberts in ''Mona Lisa Smile'' in the role of Giselle. In an interview with ''The Daily Telegraph'', she revealed the reason for accepting the role was "to play somebody who feels confident in herself as a sexy, beautiful woman". The film generated mostly critical reviews, with Manohla Dargis of the ''Los Angeles Times'' describing it as "smug and reductive". Her next roles were in smaller independent films: ''Casa de los Babys'' (2003), a story about six American women impatiently waiting out their lengthy residency requirements in an unidentified South American country before picking up their adoptive babies, and ''Criminal'' (2004), a remake of the Argentinian film ''Nine Queens'', with John C. Reilly and Diego Luna. Gyllenhaal played an honest hotel manager forced to help her crooked brother (Reilly) by seducing one of his victims. Gyllenhaal was invited to join the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences in 2004. She starred in the HBO film ''Strip Search'' (2004), where she portrayed an American student in China suspected of terrorism.

In 2004, Gyllenhaal returned to theater in a Los Angeles production of Tony Kushner's ''Homebody/ Kabul'' as Priscilla, the Homebody's daughter, who spends most of the play searching for her elusive mother in Kabul, Afghanistan. Kushner gave her the role in ''Homebody/ Kabul'' on the strength of her performance in ''Closer''. Ben Brantley of ''The New York Times'' wrote: "Ms. Gyllenhaal provides the essential bridge between the parts of the play's title." John Heilpern of ''The New York Observer'' noted that Gyllenhaal's performance was "compelling". Viewed as a sex symbol, she was ranked in the "Hot 100 List" by ''Maxim'' magazine in 2004 and 2005.

Gyllenhaal's next film role was in the 2005 comedy-drama ''Happy Endings'', in which she played an adventuress singer who seduces a young gay musician (Jason Ritter) as well as his rich father (Tom Arnold). She recorded songs for the movie's soundtrack, calling the role the "roughest, scariest acting ever" and adding she is more natural singing on screen than acting. Lisa Schwarzbaum of ''Entertainment Weekly'' declared Gyllenhaal's performance "as wonderfully, naturally slouchy-sexy as her character is artificial".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2cf7e433eaf7a36d4eab628257ad14d9" name="Maggie_Gyllenhaal_-_003" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/2cf7e433eaf7a36d4eab628257ad14d9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>