<document id="a0379bab1b29d0217d15cff1354ad8be-7" name="Siward,_Earl_of_Northumbria" cat="25">
<text>
The 12th-century historian, Henry of Huntingdon, in his ''Historia Anglorum'', relates that when Siward was attacked by dysentery, fearing to die "like a cow" and wishing rather to die like a soldier, he clothed himself in armour and took to hand an axe and shield. Ennobled in such a manner, Siward died. This anecdote is of doubtful historicity, and is thought to be derived from the saga devoted to Earl Siward, now lost.Mason, ''House of Godwine'', pp. 88&ndash;89 The ''Vita Ædwardi Regis'' states that Siward died at York and was buried in "the monastery of St Olaf" at Galmanho, a claim confirmed by the ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'', John of Worcester,  and the ''Historia Regum''.Barlow (ed.), ''Life of King Edward'', p. 49 (= ''Vita Ædwardi'', i. 5), & note ''Ibid'', p. 48, n. 114; Darlington, McGurk and Bray (eds.), ''Chronicle of John of Worcester'', vol. ii, pp. 576, & n. 5; Stevenson, ''Simeon of Durham'', p. 124 

Material incorporated in two surviving sources is thought by some to attest to the existence of a lost saga or some other kind of literary tradition concerning Siward's life. The first source is the ''Vita et Passio Waldevi'', a hagiographic history of Siward's cult-inspiring son Waltheof. This text contains an account of Waltheof's paternal origin, and in the process recounts certain adventures of his father Siward (see boxes throughout article). The second major witness of the tradition is Henry of Huntingdon's ''Historia Anglorum'', which contains extracts of saga-like material relating to Siward's invasion of Scotland (1054) and his death (1055).Wright, ''Cultivation of Saga'', pp. 75, 76, 127&ndash;33, 136 The Anglo-Saxonist Frank Stenton declared that Siward was "not a statesman, but a Danish warrior of the primitive type".Stenton, ''Anglo-Saxon England'', p. 417 Writers in the half-century after his death remembered Siward as a strong ruler who brought peace and suppressed brigandage.Aird, ''St Cuthbert'', p. 54, and notes 163&ndash;63

Siward died more than a decade before the death of Edward the Confessor, but despite this the ''Domesday Book'' recorded 4 manors, 3 in Yorkshire and 1 in Derbyshire, owned directly by Earl Siward in 1066, all of them subsequently held by Hugh d'Avranches, Earl of Chester.See Williams & Martin (eds.), ''Domesday Book'', pp. 744, 802&ndash;03; Clarke, ''English Nobility'', pp. 28, 220 This land was stated to have been worth £212, while his son Waltheof was said to have held £136 worth of land across 9 counties.Clarke, ''English Nobility'', pp. 221&ndash;24 Domesday records give an incomplete picture of Siward's holdings. In total it recorded property worth £348 for Siward and his son, which on its own would compare poorly with the £2493 in value recorded to have been held by the family of the earls of Mercia.Clarke, ''English Nobility'', pp. 206&ndash;20 Of the latter, however, Morcar of Mercia, Earl of Northumbria on the day of King Edward's death, possessed land worth £968, while Tostig, exiled earl at the time, had land worth £491; both may have come into possession of some of Siward's land in the course of becoming Earls of Northumbria.Clarke, ''English Nobility'',  pp. 191&ndash;94, 205, 215&ndash;17, 220 Moreover, the counties that would become Durham, Northumberland, Cumberland and Westmorland were largely omitted from the survey, while, besides being only very poorly documented, the lands in Yorkshire had been severely devastated and devalued during the Harrying of the North.Green, ''Aristocracy'', pp. 100&ndash;10; Kapelle, ''Norman Conquest'', pp. 158&ndash;90  

Siward is said to have built a church dedicated to St Olaf at Galmanho, York. The record of his burial in this church is the only notice of a non-royal lay burial inside a church in pre-Norman England.Daniell, ''Death and Burial in Medieval England'', p. 186 Siward's Howe, ''i.e.'', Heslington Hill near York, was most likely named after Earl Siward, although probably because Siward held popular courts there rather than because it was his burial place.Baxter, ''Earls of Mercia'', p. 103 One of Siward's sons is known to have survived him, Waltheof, whose mother was Ælfflæd. Waltheof later rose to be an earl in the East Midlands before becoming Earl of Northumbria.Lewis, "Waltheof" When Waltheof rebelled against William the Conqueror, however, the act led to his execution and to his subsequent veneration as a saint at Crowland Abbey.Lewis, "Waltheof"; Scott, "Earl Waltheof", pp. 206&ndash;07; Watkins, "Cult of Earl Waltheof", pp. 95&ndash;101 Waltheof's daughter married David I, King of the Scots, and through this connection Siward became one of the many ancestors of the later Scottish and British monarchs. Besides Ælfflæd, Siward is known to have been married to a woman named Godgifu, who died before Siward. The marriage is known from a grant she made of territory around Stamford, Lincolnshire, to Peterborough Abbey. Although no surviving children are attested, and no source states the name of Osbjorn's mother, this marriage has nonetheless raised the possibility that Waltheof and Osbjorn were born to different mothers, and William Kapelle suggested that Siward may have originally intended Osbjorn to inherit his southern territories while Waltheof inherited those territories in the north associated with the family of his mother Ælfflæd.Aird, ''St Cuthbert'', p. 53, n. 160; Kapelle, ''Norman Conquest'', p. 31
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="eae394c42ae3eece9fc61a817d5359e9" name="Death_of_Earl_Siward_(Smetham)" sectnum="7#1">../img/eae394c42ae3eece9fc61a817d5359e9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>