<document id="a09df49ba116b24b71300c107b642814-1.4" name="Pearl_Jam" cat="20">
<text>
Following the round of touring for ''Vitalogy'', the band went into the studio to record its follow-up, ''No Code''. Vedder said, "Making ''No Code'' was all about gaining perspective."Marks, Craig. "The Road Less Traveled". ''Spin''. February 1997. Released on August 27, 1996, ''No Code'' was seen as a deliberate break from the band's sound since ''Ten'', favoring experimental ballads and noisy garage rockers. David Browne of ''Entertainment Weekly'' stated that "''No Code'' displays a wider range of moods and instrumentation than on any previous Pearl Jam album." The lyrical themes on the album deal with issues of self-examination,Hilburn, Robert. "Working Their Way Out of a Jam". ''Los Angeles Times''. December 22, 1996. with Ament stating, "In some ways, it's like the band's story. It's about growing up." Although the album debuted at number one on the ''Billboard'' charts, it quickly fell down the charts. ''No Code'' included the singles "Who You Are" (), "Hail, Hail", and "Off He Goes". As with ''Vitalogy'', very little touring was done to promote ''No Code'' because of the band's refusal to play in Ticketmaster's venue areas. A European tour took place in the fall of 1996. Gossard stated that there was "a lot of stress associated with trying to tour at that time" and that "it was growing more and more difficult to be excited about being part of the band."


Following the short tour for ''No Code'', the band went into the studio in 1997 to record its follow-up. The sessions for the band's fifth album represented more of a team effort between all members of the group, with Ament stating that "everybody really got a little bit of their say on the record...because of that, everybody feels like they're an integral part of the band.". MTV.com. February 4, 1998. On February 3, 1998, Pearl Jam released its fifth album, ''Yield''. The album was cited as a return to the band's early, straightforward rock sound. Tom Sinclair of ''Entertainment Weekly'' stated that the band has "turned in an intermittently affecting album that veers between fiery garage rock and rootsy, acoustic-based ruminations. Perhaps mindful of their position as the last alt-rock ambassadors with any degree of clout, they've come up with their most cohesive album since their 1991 debut, ''Ten''." Lyrically, ''Yield'' continued with the more contemplative type of writing found on ''No Code'',Mulvey, John. "Interview with Pearl Jam". ''NME''. May 13, 2000. with Vedder saying, "What was rage in the past has become reflection.""Tentaciones". ''El País''. February 13, 1998. ''Yield'' debuted at number two on the ''Billboard'' charts, but like ''No Code'' soon began dropping down the charts. It included the singles "Given to Fly" and "Wishlist". The band hired comic book artist Todd McFarlane to create an animated video for the song "Do the Evolution" from the album, its first music video since 1992. A documentary detailing the making of ''Yield'', ''Single Video Theory'', was released on VHS and DVD later that year.

In April 1998, Pearl Jam once again changed drummers. Jack Irons left the band due to dissatisfaction with touring and was replaced with former Soundgarden drummer Matt Cameron on an initially temporary basis, but he soon became a permanent replacement for Irons. Pearl Jam's 1998 Yield Tour in North America marked the band’s return to full-scale touring. The band's anti-trust lawsuit against Ticketmaster had proven to be unsuccessful and hindered live tours. Many fans had complained about the difficulty in obtaining tickets and the use of non-Ticketmaster venues, which were judged to be out-of-the-way and impersonal. For this tour and future tours, Pearl Jam once again began using Ticketmaster in order to "better accommodate concertgoers." The 1998 summer tour was a big success,Hinckley, David. "Vedder's Not Finished". ''New York Daily News''. August 10, 1999. and after it was completed the band released ''Live on Two Legs'', a live album which featured select performances from the tour.

In 1998, Pearl Jam recorded "Last Kiss", a cover of a 1960s ballad made famous by J. Frank Wilson and the Cavaliers. It was recorded during a soundcheck and released on the band's 1998 fan club Christmas single. The following year, the cover was put into heavy rotation across the country. By popular demand, the cover was released to the public as a single in 1999, with all of the proceeds going to the aid of refugees of the Kosovo War. The band also decided to include the song on the 1999 charity compilation album, ''No Boundaries: A Benefit for the Kosovar Refugees''. "Last Kiss" peaked at number two on the ''Billboard'' charts and became the band's highest-charting single.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="06e02791a4ef75cf14f2d8ce7ea34cf2" name="MikeMcCready1998" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/06e02791a4ef75cf14f2d8ce7ea34cf2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>