<document id="a09df49ba116b24b71300c107b642814-1.7" name="Pearl_Jam" cat="20">
<text>
The work for Pearl Jam's follow-up to ''Riot Act'' began after its appearance on the 2004 Vote for Change tour. The time period between the two albums was the longest gap between Pearl Jam's studio albums to date and the new album was its first release for a new label. Clive Davis announced in February 2006 that Pearl Jam had signed with his label, J Records, which like Epic, is part of the Sony BMG group. The band's eighth studio album, ''Pearl Jam'', was released on May 2, 2006. A number of critics cited ''Pearl Jam'' as a return to the band's early sound, and McCready compared the new material to ''Vs.'' in a 2005 interview. Ament said, "The band playing in a room—that came across. There’s a kind of immediacy to the record, and that’s what we were going for."Porosky, Pamela. . ''Bass Player''. July 2006. Chris Willman of ''Entertainment Weekly'' said that "in a world full of boys sent to do a man's job of rocking, Pearl Jam can still pull off gravitas." Current socio-political issues in the United States are addressed on the album. "World Wide Suicide", a song criticizing the Iraq War and U.S. foreign policy, was released as a single and topped the ''Billboard'' Modern Rock chart; it was Pearl Jam's first number one on that chart since "Who You Are" in 1996, and first number one on any chart in the United States since 1998 when "Given to Fly" reached number one on the Mainstream Rock chart. ''Pearl Jam'' also included the singles "Life Wasted" and "Gone".

To support ''Pearl Jam'', the band embarked on its 2006 world tour. It toured North America, Australia and notably Europe; Pearl Jam had not toured the continent for six years. The North American tour included three two-night stands opening for Tom Petty and the Heartbreakers. The band served as the headliners for the Leeds and Reading festivals, despite having vowed to never play at a festival again after Roskilde. Vedder started both concerts with an emotional plea to the crowd to look after each other. He commented during the Leeds set that the band's decision to play a festival for the first time after Roskilde had nothing to do with "guts" but with trust in the audience.

In 2007, Pearl Jam recorded a cover of The Who's "Love, Reign o'er Me" for the Mike Binder film, ''Reign Over Me''; it was later made available as a music download on the iTunes Music Store. The band embarked on a 13-date European tour, and headlined Lollapalooza in Grant Park, on August 5, 2007. The band released a CD box set in June 2007, entitled ''Live at the Gorge 05/06'', that documents its shows at The Gorge Amphitheatre, and in September 2007 a concert DVD, entitled ''Immagine in Cornice'', which documents the band's Italian shows from its 2006 tour was released.

In June 2008, Pearl Jam performed as the headline act at the Bonnaroo Music Festival. The Bonnaroo appearance took place amidst a twelve-date tour in the Eastern United States. In July 2008, the band performed at the VH1 tribute to The Who alongside Foo Fighters, Incubus and The Flaming Lips. In the days prior to Election Day 2008, Pearl Jam digitally released through its official website a free documentary film, entitled ''Vote for Change? 2004'', which follows the band's time spent on the 2004 Vote for Change tour.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c39b6e5f18462cf9807c033a05b70292" name="Eddie_Vedder_and_Pearl_Jam_in_concert_in_Italy_2006" sectnum="1.7#1">../img/c39b6e5f18462cf9807c033a05b70292.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>