<document id="a0bd4962d01f0c5a6338363a868b4eca-3.8" name="Fauna_of_Scotland" cat="3">
<text>
Red-listed Western Capercaillie and Ptarmigan breed in Scotland and are absent elsewhere in the British Isles. The former became extinct in Scotland in 1785 but was successfully reintroduced from Swedish stock in 1837. Trees for Life. Retrieved 8 September 2008. UK Biodiversity Action Plan. Retrieved 8 September 2008. There are significant populations of other Galliformes including Blackcock and the famous Red Grouse.Gooders (1994) pp. 98&ndash;101. Common Quail, Grey Partridge and Pheasant are well-distributed, although the Red-legged Partridge is less so.Gooders (1994) pp. 97, 102, 103, 106. A small colony of the introduced Golden Pheasant exists in the southwest.Gooders (1994) pp. 104&ndash;05.

Among the waders, Avocet, Stone-curlew, Little Ringed Plover and Kentish Plover are absent, but most of the 100 or so pairs of Dotterel in the UK spend their summers in Scotland as do all of the breeding Whimbrel, Greenshank and Red-necked Phalarope, (although the latter two species also breed in Ireland).Gooders (1994) pp. 113&ndash;44.Peterson ''et al.'' (1993) Maps 152 and 157. In summer the shallow lochs of the machair lands in the Uists and Benbecula provide for a remarkable variety of waders and ducks including Shoveler, Eider, Slavonian Grebe and the 'red-listed' Common Scoter.Perrot, D. et al. (1995) ''The Outer Hebrides Handbook and Guide''. Machynlleth. Kittiwake. pp. 86&ndash;90. Goldeneye have colonised an area centred around the Cairngorms National Park since the 1970s, and about 100 pairs breed there. The majority of the roughly 8,000 Whooper Swans in the British Isles winter in Scotland and 

Virtually all of the 40,000 Barnacle Geese, which breed in Greenland, arrive on Islay for the winter, most staying only for a few days before dispersing to the surrounding area. A similar number use the Montrose Basin as a temporary roost in October, and 20% of the world population of 225,000 birds over-winter on Scottish lochs. Benvie (2004) p. 74. The amber-listed Black and Red-throated Diver's freshwater breeding strongholds in the British Isles are in the north and west of Scotland.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="266ed513071b92765ed9c5f01207fe82" name="Capercaillie_Lomvi_2004" sectnum="3.8#1">../img/266ed513071b92765ed9c5f01207fe82.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>