<document id="a0bd4962d01f0c5a6338363a868b4eca-2.1" name="Fauna_of_Scotland" cat="3">
<text>
The representation of the weasel family (Mustelidae) in Scotland is typical of Britain as a whole save that the Polecat is absent and that Scotland is the UK's stronghold of the Pine Marten,Corbet and Ovenden (1984) pp. 180&ndash;86. although the purity of the latter breed is threatened by a release of American Martens in northern England.Benvie (2004) p. 48. Scotland hosts the only populations of European Wildcat in the British Isles with an assumed total of between 400 and 2,000 animals, and of the Red Fox sub-species ''Vulpes vulpes vulpes,'' a larger race than the more common ''V. v. crucigera'' and which has two distinct forms.Matthews (1968) pp. 231&ndash;32. The Wild Cat is at risk due to the inadequacy of protective legislation and is now considered at serious risk of extinction.Benvie (2004) p. 18. Hull (2007) pp. 184&ndash;89. Exterminations of the population of feral American Mink, which were brought to Britain for fur farms in the 1950s, have been undertaken under the auspices of the Hebridean Mink Project. These may be extended to other areas where mink are abundant such as Cairngorms National Park and perhaps throughout the UK.Haworth, Jenny (3 February 2009) "National cull may exterminate UK mink". Edinburgh. ''The Scotsman.''

Other than occasional vagrants, among the seals only the Phocidae, or earless seals, are represented.  Two species, the Grey Seal and Harbour or Common Seal are present around the coast of Scotland in internationally important numbers. In 2002 the Scottish Grey Seal population was estimated at 120,600 adult animals, which is around 36% of the world population and more than 90% of the UK's. The Scottish population of the Common Seal is 29,700, about 90% of the UK and 36% of the European total.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5ca7ec2d865c76c1fde8702a9521959a" name="Wildkatze_002" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/5ca7ec2d865c76c1fde8702a9521959a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>