<document id="a0bd4962d01f0c5a6338363a868b4eca-8.15" name="Fauna_of_Scotland" cat="3">
<text>
Various public sector organisations have an important role in the stewardship of the country's fauna. Scottish Natural Heritage is the statutory body responsible for natural heritage management in Scotland. One of its duties is to establish National Nature Reserves (NNR)s. Until 2004 there were 73, but a review carried out in that year resulted in a significant number of sites losing their NNR status, and as of 2006 there are 55.A new policy for NNRs was developed in 1996, which required them to have four attributes: primacy of nature, national importance, best practice management and continuity of management. The sites not meeting these characteristics were removed from the list. See  (pdf)  SNH. Retrieved on 23 August 2008. The Forestry Commission in Scotland serves as the forestry department of the Scottish Government and is one of the country's largest landowners. The Joint Nature Conservation Committee is the statutory adviser to Government on UK and international nature conservation.

The country has two national parks. Cairngorms National Park includes the largest area of arctic mountain landscape in the UK. Sites designated as of importance to natural heritage take up 39% of the land area, two thirds of which are of Europe-wide importance. Cairngorms National Park Authority. Retrieved on 16 January 2006. Loch Lomond and the Trossachs National Park includes Britain's largest body of fresh water, the mountains of Breadalbane and the sea lochs of Argyll. 

Charitable and voluntary organisations also have important roles to play. The National Trust for Scotland is the conservation charity that protects and promotes Scotland's natural and cultural heritage. With more than 270,000 members it is the largest conservation charity in Scotland. The Scottish Wildlife Trust is a leading voluntary conservation organisation, working to protect Scotland's natural environment. The Royal Zoological Society of Scotland is a learned society and registered charity that maintains Edinburgh Zoo and the Highland Wildlife Park (a safari park and zoo near Kingussie, which specialises in native fauna). The Society is also involved in various conservation programs around Scotland and the world. The Royal Society for the Protection of Birds promotes conservation of birds and other wildlife through the protection and re-creation of habitats. The John Muir Trust is a charity whose main role is as a guardian of wild land and wildlife, through the ownership of land and the promotion of education and conservation. The trust owns and manages estates in locations including Knoydart and Assynt, and on the isle of Skye. It has links with the Sierra Club in the United States which also celebrates the legacy of Dunbar-born John Muir. John Muir Trust. Retrieved on 3 January 2007. Trees for Life is a charity that aims to restore a "wild forest" in the Northwest Highlands and Grampian Mountains.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6d2c1c72c4fa12cf51222cc3ae5bc910" name="Cairn_toul" sectnum="8.15#1">../img/6d2c1c72c4fa12cf51222cc3ae5bc910.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>