<document id="a0d889e03873462f3d73f918cf85f0fa-5.1" name="Spiderland" cat="20">
<text>
Despite having plans for a tour of Europe to promote ''Spiderland'', Slint broke up in 1991 for reasons that were not revealed. Members of the band went on to join other musical projects, including Tortoise, The Breeders, Palace, and The For Carnation.Ankeny, Jason. "". Allmusic. Retrieved on November 12, 2007. Slint reunited briefly in 2005 for an eighteen-date tour. Pajo said, "We don't want to be a reunion band that keeps reuniting. .... I know that this is going to be it."Harrington, Richard. "". ''The Washington Post'', March 18, 2005. Retrieved on November 12, 2007. However, in 2007 Slint reunited again for a tour featuring performances of ''Spiderland'' in its entirety as part of All Tomorrow's Parties' "Don't Look Back" concert series celebrating classic albums."". ''NME'', March 23, 2007. Retrieved on November 4, 2007. The tour included appearances at the 2007 Pitchfork Music FestivalSolarski, Matthew. "". Pitchfork Media, April 20, 2007. Retrieved on November 12, 2007. and Primavera Sound Festival.Solarski, Matthew. "". Pitchfork Media, January 16, 2007. Retrieved on November 12, 2007. McMahan said in an interview at the Pitchfork Music Festival that performing the album live was "pretty cool. It moves a little slower than it does on the record, but it's all there. .... It took some getting used to, some revisiting the material and rehearsing."Thompson, Paul. "". Pitchfork Media, July 13, 2007. Retrieved on November 7, 2007.

Critical responses to Slint's reunion has been mixed, with detractors commenting on the music's unsuitability for a live setting. ''Chicago Sun-Times'' music critic Jim DeRogatis wrote that although "fans greeted  as manna from heaven. .... the musicians' fragile, intertwining guitar lines, mumbled attempts at poetry and uninspiring shoe-gazer personas were poor matches for the setting and the occasion, especially during the static, percussion-deprived 'Don, Aman' and the bloated anthem 'Good Morning Captain.'"DeRogatis, Jim. "". ''Chicago Sun-Times'', July 15, 2007. Retrieved on December 7, 2007. According to members of ''The A.V. Club'', Slint's performance of "Don, Aman" at the festival "captures the band's greatness ''and'' its greatest weakness: Slint completely lacks stage charisma, and playing a deathly quiet, moody song on a big outdoor stage just doesn't work."Gordon, Scott; Modell, Josh; O'Neal, Sean; Ryan, Kyle. "". ''The A.V. Club'', July 18, 2007. Retrieved on November 11, 2007. Both DeRogatis and the ''A.V. Club'' review also noted that the band's performance was plagued by sound problems.DeRogatis, Jim. "". ''Chicago Sun-Times'', July 16, 2007. Retrieved on December 7, 2007. A ''New York'' review of a performance at Webster Hall opined "the deeply brooding, fussily executed album finally sounded, sixteen years later, like the existential, cosmos-annihilating shrug it was envisioned as. Which is to say: It sounded fucking great."Catucci, Nick. "". ''New York'', July 18, 2007. Retrieved on November 12, 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8bdf0a7c1966e3354e455c914a3d0485" name="Spiderland_advert" sectnum="5.1#1">../img/8bdf0a7c1966e3354e455c914a3d0485.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>