<document id="a0d889e03873462f3d73f918cf85f0fa-5" name="Spiderland" cat="20">
<text>
Though largely ignored upon its initial release, ''Spiderland'' has attracted greater attention through time. This growth in popularity has been attributed in part to the appearance of the track "Good Morning Captain" on the soundtrack to the 1995 film ''Kids''. The album has sold over 50,000 copies,Frere-Jones, Sasha. "". sfj.abstractdynamics.org, July 25, 2005. Retrieved on November 11, 2007. though Kory Grow of the ''College Music Journal'' suggested that the album "has inspired countless bands (and therefore fans) far beyond its SoundScan numbers".Grow, Kory. "". ''College Music Journal'', July 19, 2007. Retrieved on November 11, 2007. ''Spiderland'' has become a landmark indie rock album and is considered, along with Talk Talk's ''Spirit Of Eden'' and ''Laughing Stock'', to have been the primary catalyst of the post-rock and math rock genres."". Allmusic. Retrieved on December 14, 2007.Keefe, Michael. "". About.com. Retrieved on December 20, 2007. David Peschek said that the album is "the ur-text for what became known as post-rock, a fractured, almost geometric reimagining of rock music stripped of its dionysiac impulse."Peschek, David. "". ''The Guardian'', February 28, 2007. Retrieved on November 7, 2007. Rachel Devine of ''The List'' called ''Spiderland'' "arguably the most disproportionately influential  in music history".Devine, Rachel. "". ''The List'', August 16, 2007. Retrieved on November 12, 2007.

McMahan reflected on the album's success: "We worked really hard on ''Spiderland''. I mean, I definitely felt much more personal about it. I thought it represented us as people, musically, a lot more than ''Tweez'' did. That's about it. It seemed like when we were around, and actively playing and stuff, that people's responses to us were fairly ambivalent. I thought it was funny when the press picked up on it. For an independent release, it had a strange sort of audience and kept selling three or four years after we recorded it; it still sells more copies than when it first came out."Modell, Josh. "". ''Milk'', April 1996. Retrieved on November 12, 2007. Touch and Go founder Corey Rusk said that ''Spiderland'' is "like an icon now. But when it came out, nobody cared! The band had broken up by the time the album came out, and it really didn't sell particularly well or get written about all that much in the year it was released. But it was a revolutionary, groundbreaking record, and it's one of the few instances where people catch up to it later on."Crock, Jason. "". Pitchfork Media, September 5, 2006. Retrieved on November 12, 2007

Post-rock bands Mogwai, Godspeed You Black Emperor!, Isis, and Explosions in the Sky have been influenced by ''Spiderland''.Goldberg, Michael Alan. "". ''SF Weekly'', July 18, 2007. Retrieved on November 11, 2007. Dinosaur Jr and Sebadoh member Lou Barlow said of ''Spiderland'', "It was quiet to loud without sounding like grunge or indie-rock. It sounded more like a new kind of music."Irvin, Jim (2001). ''The Mojo Collection: The Greatest Albums of All Time''. (Edinburgh) Mojo Books. ISBN 184195067X. p. 640 PJ Harvey has named ''Spiderland'' as one of her favorite albums,Blandford, James R. (2004). ''PJ Harvey: Siren Rising''. (London) Omnibus Press. ISBN 1844494330. p. 37 and supposedly contacted Slint regarding the band's request for a female vocalist.Chen, George. "". ''San Francisco Bay Guardian''. Retrieved on November 8, 2007. Bob Nastanovich of PavementJovanovic, Rob (2004). ''Perfect Sound Forever: The Story of Pavement''. (Boston) Justin, Charles & Co. ISBN 1932112073. p. 129 and Mark Clifford of Seefeel"". ''Perfect Sound Forever''. Retrieved on November 9, 2007. have also cited ''Spiderland'' as among their favorite albums. The album cover of ''Spiderland'' was recreated by The Shins in the music video for "New Slang".Mercer, Ben. "". ''Dallas Observer'', July 11, 2002. Retrieved on November 11, 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e977c24f7609151d25de916d79c6a8a8" name="Slint_at_Pitchfork_Music_Festival" sectnum="5#1">../img/e977c24f7609151d25de916d79c6a8a8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>