<document id="a0d889e03873462f3d73f918cf85f0fa-3" name="Spiderland" cat="20">
<text>
The name ''Spiderland'' originates from McMahan's younger brother, who thought that the record sounded "spidery". The album's black-and-white cover photograph, which depicts members of the band treading water in the lake of an abandoned quarry, was taken by Will Oldham.McCarthy, Shannon. "" Musicianguide.com. Retrieved on November 8, 2007. An article in ''The Stranger'' credited the cover for creating a mystique surrounding Slint, noting "ost people only had seen Slint as four heads floating in a Kentucky quarry on Spiderland's cover. Listeners pondered the band's sparsely adorned black-and-white covers as if they were runes bearing secrets."Segal, Dave. "". ''The Stranger'', March 10, 2005. Retrieved on November 12, 2007. Chris Gaerig of the ''Michigan Daily'' wrote "the cover of Slint's masterful ''Spiderland'' captures the joyous fear and violence of the album so precisely it shakes souls. The group—submerged in a lake to their chins with deranged smiles—seems to be stalking you, hovering out of the black-and-white façade."Gaerig, Chris. "". ''Michigan Daily'', September 20, 2007. Retrieved on November 8, 2007. Several other promotional images have been taken from the same photo session with Oldham.

A photo of a spider taken by Noel Saltzman is used on the back cover, reflecting the album's title.  The inside sleeve contains the message "interested female vocalists write 1864 douglas blvd. louisville, ky. 40205".(1991) Album notes for ''Spiderland'' by Slint, . Chicago: Tough & Go (TG64CD). McMahan confirmed that this message was serious, and said "We did get some responses and we did listen to CDs and tapes. We didn’t end up doing anything immediately, so that idea of adding someone sort of fell by the wayside."Simigis, Antonia. "". ''Time Out Chicago'', July 12, 2007. Retrieved on November 8, 2007. The message "this recording is meant to be listened to on vinyl" is printed on some compact disc issues of ''Spiderland'', demonstrating Slint's preference of analog audio devices.Agarwal, Manish. "". Don't Look Back, May 2007. Retrieved on November 9, 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="823ac1a1493794f2228e515eab538582" name="Slint_-_Spiderland_promo" sectnum="3#1">../img/823ac1a1493794f2228e515eab538582.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>