<document id="a0da912602423766b97cefce738bd408-1.4" name="Crusaders_(rugby)" cat="26">
<text>
In 2006, the Super 12 expanded to form the Super 14 when the Western Force from Perth, Australia, and the Central Cheetahs from the Free State and Northern Cape Provinces, South Africa joined the competition. An unbeaten run of sixteen matches was nearly halted when the Crusaders drew with the Western Force in Perth in round eleven. The following week, the unbeaten run was ended when the Crusaders lost to the Stormers in Cape Town. That loss was their only one of the year, as they finished top of the table with eleven wins. After beating the Bulls in their semi-final, the Crusaders faced the Hurricanes in the final at Jade Stadium that was played in a thick fog, causing poor visibility. Sections of the crowd could not see the field, and many spectators left during the match. The scorers were tied 9-9 going into the game’s last 20 minutes. The Crusaders' Casey Laulala then scored the game’s only try before the match finished 19-12.

In the 2007 Super 14 season, seven Crusaders players missed the first seven rounds of the competition to participate in an All Black "conditioning programme". The conditioning programme was part of the All Blacks' 2007 Rugby World Cup preparations; 22 players were selected for the programme. The Crusaders' seven players in the programme was more than any other New Zealand Super 14 franchise. The Crusaders players were Chris Jack, Richie McCaw, Greg Somerville, Reuben Thorne, Dan Carter, Leon MacDonald, and Aaron Mauger. All but one of the seven returned to play for the Crusaders in their eighth round match against the Stormers (Greg Somerville did not return due to injury). The Crusaders climbed to second on the table before defeating the Western Force 53-0 at Jade Stadium in the tenth round. The victory over the Force was the one hundredth Super rugby win for the Crusaders - the first franchise to reach the milestone.It was also the Crusaders' first victory over the Force - they drew in 2006.

The Crusaders were top of the table going into the last round of the Super 14 before the play-offs. In order to guarantee a home semi-final they needed to defeat the Chiefs at Jade Stadium. The Chiefs won 30-24 - and ended the Crusaders 26 game winning streak at home. As the Bulls defeated the Reds 92-3 in the same round, they overtook the Crusaders to finish second in the round robin. The Crusaders then traveled to Pretoria to face the Bulls in their semi-final where they lost 27-12.

The 2008 season was another highly successful one for the Crusaders.
Finishing top of the table at the end of week 14, they comfortably defeated the Hurricanes 33-22 (although the scoreline did not reflect their dominance in the game) in the semi-final and went on to beat the 
Waratahs in the final 20-12. It was a fitting way to send off long-serving coach Robbie Deans as he headed to Australia to coach the Wallabies (the national rugby union team). It was also the last game for Crusaders stalwarts Caleb Ralph (a former All-Black wing, and versatile utility back player) and former captain Reuben Thorne (former All Black captain and one of the few players present in each of the Crusaders' final appearances). In late July, 2008 it was announced that former All Black and Crusaders captain Todd Blackadder will take over as head coach for the 2009 season. Blackadder will be assisted by former All Black and Crusaders teammates Mark Hammett and Daryl Gibson.

The 2009 season got off to a poor start for the Crusaders winning just one of its first five games with some uninspiring low scoring encounters. The side found its feet later in the season, winning some key away games which ultimately saw them finish in fourth place on the table just ahead of the Waratahs. Both the Crusaders and Warratahs finished the Super 14 with 41 competition points but the Crusaders advanced through to the semi-finals with a greater 'points for and against' difference.

The Crusaders lost the semi-final to the Bulls 36&ndash;23 at Loftus Versfeld, Pretoria in front of a capacity 52,000 crowd. It was only the second time the Crusaders have lost a semi-final and the previous failure also came at Loftus Versfeld in 2007 when they fell 27-12 to the Bulls. The Bulls went on to win the 2009 Super 14 title beating the Chiefs 61-17.

Statistically, the Crusaders 2009 season saw them with the best defensive record of the competition conceding just 198 points however points for and total tries scored for the season was the second lowest in the competition with just 231 points and 27 tries, only the last placed Cheetahs had a worse record (213 points 26 tries).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="28d4ba08ae318ee88eed470dd40afcb5" name="Lineout" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/28d4ba08ae318ee88eed470dd40afcb5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>