<document id="a0da912602423766b97cefce738bd408-1.3" name="Crusaders_(rugby)" cat="26">
<text>
After winning three consecutive Super 12 titles, the Crusaders finished tenth in 2001 — their worst finish since 1996. The season was the last for captain Todd Blackadder before he left to play for Edinburgh in Scotland.Before leaving for Scotland, Blackadder led the Canterbury NPC team to victory in the 2002 National Provincial Championship.

The Crusaders bounced back dramatically in 2002 when they went through the Super 12 season unbeaten, achieving their fourth title. Although the Crusaders won all eleven of their round-robin matches, six of them were won by a margin of seven points or less.Seven points is significant because it is the value of a converted tryMcIlraith (2006), p.164 Their eleven round-robin games also included a record 96&ndash;19 win over the Waratahs in the final match of the round-robin stage, which was especially noteworthy given that both teams finished at the top of the table.

The Crusaders met the Highlanders in their 2002 semi-final, which they eventually won 34&ndash;23 after being ahead 18-6 at half time. The following week, they faced the Brumbies in the first final to be hosted at Jade Stadium. The Brumbies trailed 11&ndash;3 after the first half, having had only 30 per cent possession.Gifford (2004), p.189 Although the Brumbies closed the gap to 14&ndash;13 with eight minutes to go, the Crusaders held on and steadied to win 31&ndash;13 with a last-minute try to Caleb Ralph.McIlraith (2006), p.165 The season was their first under the captaincy of Reuben Thorne, who went on to captain the All Blacks until the end of the 2003 Rugby World Cup.

The Crusaders' winning run finally came to an end when they were beaten 39&ndash;5 by the Blues in the third round of the 2003 Super 12 season.McIlraith (2005), p.288. Although their 15-match unbeaten streak had ended, Richie McCaw said of the loss, "...in some ways it was almost a relief. We'd finally been beaten, the run was over, so people could stop talking about it and we could get on with playing it week by week."McIlraith (2005), pg. 170. The Crusaders recovered to finish second on the table with eight wins.McIlraith (2005), pg. 294. They hosted a semi-final against the Hurricanes, who were coached by Colin Cooper, a former assistant coach for the Crusaders. Despite this inside knowledge of the team by the Wellington coach, the Crusaders won the match 39&ndash;16. In the final, the Crusaders met the Blues, another team coached by a former Crusaders assistant coach, Peter Sloane. Hooker Mark Hammett scored two tries to give the Crusaders a 10&ndash;6 lead at half-time.McIlraith (2005), pg. 186. The Blues hit back to lead 21&ndash;10 with ten minutes to go. The Crusaders managed another converted try, but it was not enough, and the Blues won 21&ndash;17.

The Crusaders' 2004 season began with two losses: first to the Waratahs, then to the Blues.McIlraith (2005), p.191 They recovered to again finish second on the table with seven wins.McIlraith (2005), p.302. They played the Stormers at Jade Stadium in their semi-final, and won 27-16. They met the Brumbies at Canberra Stadium in a replay of the 2000 final. The Brumbies dominated in the final, scoring 33 unanswered points in the first 19 minutes.McIlraith (2005), p.188 The Crusaders managed to salvage some pride by narrowing the loss to a 47&ndash;38 finish.

The 2005 season started with a repeat of the previous year’s final: a Brumbies victory over the Crusaders in Canberra.McIlraith (2005), pg 303. There was a win the following week at home over the Chiefs, followed by a win over the Reds at Trafalgar Park.McIlraith (2005), pg 305. Although there was a 35&ndash;20 loss to the Bulls after Crusaders captain Richie McCaw was knocked unconscious, they eventually finished the regular season top of the table.McIlraith (2005), pg 203.McIlraith (2005), p.310 McCaw returned from his five weeks on the sideline to lead the Crusaders in their semifinal victory over the Hurricanes. They faced the Waratahs in the final at Jade Stadium. 
Leading 14&ndash;6 at halftime, the Crusaders then moved out to a 29-point lead.McIlraith (2005), p.205 Despite three late tries by the Waratahs, the Crusaders won their fifth title with a 35&ndash;20 win.McIlraith (2005), p.311

As a reward for their seventh finals appearance and fifth title, the Crusaders were allowed to keep the Super 12 trophy. After the 2005 season, the franchise saw the departure of stalwarts Andrew Mehrtens and Justin Marshall, both of whom had played for the team since its formation in 1996.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4db2c0d8fe4b4e96ecea3d51b4ffabfc" name="Scrum" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/4db2c0d8fe4b4e96ecea3d51b4ffabfc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>