<document id="a1b7d77895dbd92fd780389171358b26-4.6" name="Leonard_Harrison_State_Park" cat="11">
<text>
Leonard Harrison State Park is part of Important Bird Area #28, which encompasses  of both publicly and private held land. State managed acreage accounts for 68 percent of the total area and includes Leonard Harrison and Colton Point State Parks and the surrounding Tioga State Forest lands. The Pennsylvania Audubon Society has designated all  of Leonard Harrison State Park as part of the IBA, which is an area designated as a globally important habitat for the conservation of bird populations.

Ornithologists and bird watchers have recorded a total of 128 species of birds in the IBA. Several factors contribute to the high total of bird species observed: there is a large area of forest in the IBA, as well as great habitat diversity, with  of open water that is used by many of the birds, especially Bald Eagles. The location of the IBA along the Pine Creek Gorge also contributes to the diverse bird populations.

In addition to Bald Eagles, which live in the IBA year round and have successfully established a breeding population there, the IBA is home to Belted Kingfishers, Scarlet Tanagers, Black-throated Blue Warblers, Common Mergansers, Blue and Green Heron, Hermit Thrushes, and Wood Ducks. Large numbers of Ospreys use the gorge during spring and fall migration periods. The woodlands are inhabited by the Ruffed Grouse, Pennsylvania's state bird, and Wild Turkeys. Swainson's Thrush breeds in the IBA and the Northern Harrier breeds and overwinters in Pine Creek Gorge.

A variety of warblers is found in Leonard Harrison State Park. The Pennsylvania Audubon Society states that Pine Creek Gorge is "especially rich in warbler species, including Pine, Black-throated Blue, Black-throated Green, Blackburnian, and Black-and-white." ''Note'': This guide is available both as a book (page number given) and website (URL given).  Many of these smaller birds are more often heard than seen as they keep away from the trails and overlooks.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="56123f566b663ed51d6fa75c41abdb1f" name="LHSP_Turkey_Vulture" sectnum="4.6#1">../img/56123f566b663ed51d6fa75c41abdb1f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>