<document id="a1b7d77895dbd92fd780389171358b26-5.7" name="Leonard_Harrison_State_Park" cat="11">
<text>
Leonard Harrison State Park is a destination for avid hikers, with some challenging hikes in and around the Grand Canyon of Pennsylvania. The park has  of trails that feature very rugged terrain, pass close to steep cliffs, and can be slick in some areas. In 2003, the DCNR reported that 37,775 people used the trails in the park, and another 24,407 bicycled in it.

*'''Overlook Trail''' is a  path to Otter View, a vista looking to the south. This moderately difficult loop passes reminders of the CCC's work in the park, including a plantation of Red Pines and an old incinerator.
*'''Turkey Path''' is a difficult trail,  long (down and back), that follows Little Fourmile Run down the side of the canyon, descending over  to Pine Creek and the rail trail at the bottom of the gorge. It was originally a mule drag used to haul timber to the creek.
 There are several waterfalls on the trail, which passes through an environmentally sensitive area and is on a steep slope. Hikers are encouraged to remain on the path to reduce erosion and protect fragile plant life along the trail. In 2006 a hiker who had left the path slipped near a waterfall and fell to his death. 

A vista at the halfway point on Turkey Path was constructed in 1978 by the Youth Conservation Corps. Hand rails, steps and observation decks were added to the path in 1993 by the Pennsylvania Conservation Corps. The park website classifies it as a "down and back trail" since there is no bridge across Pine Creek. However, there is also a Turkey Path from Colton Point State Park on the west rim of the gorge down to a point on Pine Creek just upstream of the end of this trail. According to Owlett and the DCNR Pine Creek Rail Trail map, the creek can be forded with care when the water is low, and the Turkey Path connects the two parks.

*'''Pine Creek Rail Trail''' is a  rail trail from Wellsboro Junction, just north of Wellsboro, south through the Pine Creek Gorge to Jersey Shore:  of this trail is in Leonard Harrison and Colton Point State Parks. A 2001 article in ''USA Today'' said the scenic beauty of the Grand Canyon of Pennsylvania made the trail one of "10 great places to take a bike tour" in the world.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a25086a4f7f67b55f9a72ec42c8e4b1b" name="Leonard_Harrison_State_Park_Turkey_Path_1" sectnum="5.7#1">../img/a25086a4f7f67b55f9a72ec42c8e4b1b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>