<document id="a1bcc7ab3088dbdbffca5a29084604c2-4.1" name="Yes_Minister" cat="19">
<text>
'''The Rt Hon. Jim Hacker, Lord Hacker of Islington KG PC BSc''' (Paul Eddington) was the editor of a newspaper, ''Reform'', before entering government. He apparently spent a good deal of time in Parliament on the Opposition benches before his party won the general election. In ''Yes Minister'' he is the Minister for Administrative Affairs (a fictitious ministry of the British government) and a Cabinet Minister, and in ''Yes, Prime Minister'' he becomes the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom. Hacker received his degree from the London School of Economics (graduating with a Third), for which he is often derided by the Oxford-educated Sir Humphrey (who attended the fictitious Baillie College graduating with a First in Classics). His early character is that of a gung-ho, but naïve, politician, bringing sweeping changes to his department. Before long, Hacker begins to notice that Civil Service tactics are preventing his planned changes being put into practice. As he learns he becomes more sly and cynical, and uses some of the Civil Service ruses himself. While Sir Humphrey initially held all the aces, Hacker now and again plays a trump card of his own.

Throughout ''Yes Minister'' Hacker is regularly portrayed as a publicity-mad bungler who is incapable of making a firm decision, prone to make potentially embarrassing blunders, and a frequent target of criticism from the press and stern lectures from the Chief Whip. However, in ''Yes, Prime Minister'' Hacker becomes more statesmanlike. He practises more grandiose speeches, dreams up his "grand design" and hones his diplomatic skills. Nearly all of these efforts land him in trouble. In a ''Radio Times'' interview to promote ''Yes, Prime Minister'', Paul Eddington stated, "He's beginning to find his feet as a man of power, and he's begun to confound those who thought they'd be able to manipulate him out of hand."''Radio Times'': 4–10 January 1986
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="eb176e16aeff6cc43e19ed3e05cf7200" name="Administrative_Affairs" sectnum="4.1#1">../img/eb176e16aeff6cc43e19ed3e05cf7200.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>