<document id="a1bcc7ab3088dbdbffca5a29084604c2-7" name="Yes_Minister" cat="19">
<text>
The opening titles were drawn by artist Gerald Scarfe, who provided distinctive caricatures of Eddington, Hawthorne and Fowlds in their respective roles to represent distortion. He animated them as 'self-drawing' by positioning the camera above his paper, adding parts of lines, and then photographing two frames at a time. The sequence ended with the title of the episode superimposed on a facsimile of an edition of the House of Commons ''Weekly Information Bulletin.'' Curiously, the legend ''Compiled in the Public Information Office of the House of Commons Library'' was left in the sequence. Scarfe created a second set of graphics for ''Yes, Prime Minister'', including a different title card for each episode. Derek Fowlds wanted to buy an original drawing but was unable to afford it. The series' performance credits typically only featured those of the actors who appeared in the particular episode, not the names of characters.

The theme music was composed by Ronnie Hazlehurst and is largely based on the Westminster Quarters: the chimes of Big Ben. When asked in an interview about its Westminster influence, Hazlehurst replied, "That's all it is. It's the easiest thing I've ever done." Scarfe's and Hazlehurst's work was not used for the first episode, "Open Government". The final version of the titles and music had yet to be agreed, and both differ substantially from those used for subsequent instalments. The opening and closing title caption cards feature drawings of most of the cast, but are less exaggerated than those of Scarfe, while the unaccredited music is a more up-tempo piece for brass band. The Scarfe and Hazlehurst credits were used for some repeat broadcasts of the first episode, but the original pilot credits were retained for the DVD release.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1c534d55b6a5fcafc011cc99f083c282" name="Scarfejh" sectnum="7#1">../img/1c534d55b6a5fcafc011cc99f083c282.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>