<document id="a231a85052fe34e0fcfe764b7964c25b-3.5" name="Operation_Uranus" cat="29">
<text>
While the Stalingrad Front launched its offensive on 20 November, the 65th Soviet Army continued to apply pressure to the German 11th Corps along the northern shoulder of the Sixth Army's flank. The Red Army's 4th Tank Corps advanced beyond the German 11th Corps, while the 3rd Guards Cavalry Corps crashed into the German unit's rear.Beevor (1998), p. 251 The German 376th Infantry Division and the Austrian 44th Infantry Division began to redeploy to face the enemy on their flanks, but were hindered by shortage of fuel.McTaggart (2006), pp. 54–55 The 14th Panzer Division's remaining panzer regiment destroyed a flanking regiment of the Soviet 3rd Guards Cavalry Corps, but its anti-tank artillery suffered heavy casualties when it was overrun by Soviet forces. By the end of the day the Soviet 1st Tank Corps was chasing the retreating 48th Panzer Corps, while the Soviet 26th Tank Corps had captured the town of Perelazovsky, almost  to the northwest of Stalingrad.McTaggart (2006), p. 55


The Red Army's offensive continued on 21 November, with forces of the Stalingrad Front achieving penetrations of up to . By this time remaining Romanian units in the north were being destroyed in isolated battles, while the Red Army began to engage flanking portions of the German Fourth Panzer and Sixth Armies.Erickson (1975), p. 468 The German 22nd Panzer Division, despite attempting a short counterattack, was reduced to little more than a tank company and forced to withdraw to the southwest.Beevor (1998), p. 252 The Soviet 26th Tank Corps, having destroyed a large portion of the Romanian 1st Armored Division, continued its advanced to the southeast, avoiding engaging enemy left behind, although remnants of the Romanian 5th Corps were able to reorganize and put up a hastily constructed defense in the hope that it would be aided by the German 48th Panzer Corps.Beevor (1998), pp. 252–253 That day German General Friedrich Paulus, commander of the Sixth Army, received reports that the Soviets were less than  from his headquarters; furthermore, there were no remaining units which could contest the Soviet advance.Beevor (1998), p. 253 In the south, after a brief halt, the Soviet 4th Mechanized Corps continued its advance north, removing German defenders from several towns in the area, towards Stalingrad.Erickson (1975), pp. 468–469 As German forces in and around Stalingrad were at risk, Hitler ordered German forces in the area to establish an "all-around defensive position" and designated forces between the Don River and Volga River as "Fortress Stalingrad", shattering hopes of an attempted breakout by the Sixth Army.Beevor (1998), p. 254 The Sixth Army, other Axis units, and most of the Fourth Panzer Army's German units were caught inside the growing Soviet encirclement. Only the 16th Panzergrenadier Division began to fight its way out. Lack of coordination between Soviet tanks and infantry as the Red Army's tank corps attempted to exploit the breakthrough along the German's southern flank allowed much of the Fourth Romanian Army to escape destruction.

On 22 November Soviet forces began to cross the Don River and continued their advance towards the town of Kalach.Erickson (1975), p. 469 German forces defending Kalach, mostly composed of maintenance and supply personnel, were not aware of the Soviet offensive until 21 November, and even then did not know in what strength the Red Army was approaching.McTaggart (2006), p. 72 The task of taking the bridge at Kalach was given to the 26th Tank Corps, which used two captured German tanks and a reconnaissance vehicle to approach it and fire on the guards.Beevor (1998), p. 255 Soviet forces broke into the town by mid-morning and drove the defenders out, allowing themselves and the 4th Tank Corps to link up with the Red Army's 4th Mechanized Corps approaching from the south.Beevor (1998), pp. 255–256 The encirclement of German forces in Stalingrad was completed on 22 November 1942.McCarthy & Syron (2002), pp. 140–141 That day Soviet formations also continued to fight pockets of Romanian resistance, such as that put up by the Romanian 5th Corps.Beevor (1998), p. 256

Fighting continued on 23 November as the Germans attempted in vain to mount local counterattacks to break the encirclement. By this time Axis personnel inside the encirclement moved east towards Stalingrad to avoid Soviet tanks, while those that managed to escape the encirclement moved west toward German and other Axis forces.Erickson (1975), pp. 469–470
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2a311b928bb810832d1d84b2c3022b97" name="Bundesarchiv_Bild_101I-021-2081-31A,_General_Friedrich_Paulus" sectnum="3.5#1">../img/2a311b928bb810832d1d84b2c3022b97.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>