<document id="a231a85052fe34e0fcfe764b7964c25b-1" name="Operation_Uranus" cat="29">
<text>
In early May 1942, the Wehrmacht began its offensive against Soviet forces opposite of Army Group South, codenamed Case Blue.McCarthy & Syron (2002), p. 131 After breaking through Red Army forces by 13 July, German forces encircled and captured the city of Rostov.Glantz (1995), p. 119 Following the fall of Rostov, Hitler split German forces operating in the southern extremity of the southern Soviet Union in an effort to simultaneously capture the city of Stalingrad and the Caucasus oil fields.Glantz (1995), p. 120 The responsibility to take Stalingrad was given to the Sixth Army, which immediately turned towards the Volga River and began its advance with heavy air support from the ''Luftwaffe's'' ''Luftflotte 4''.McCarthy & Syron (2002), pp. 135–136 On 7 August, two German panzer corps were able to flank and encircle a Soviet force of 50,000 personnel and approximately 1,000 tanks, and on 22 August German forces began to cross the Don River to complete the advance towards the Volga.McCarthy & Syron (2002), p. 136 The following day, the Battle of Stalingrad began when vanguards of the Sixth Army penetrated the suburbs of the city.Cooper (1978), p. 422



By November, the Sixth Army was able to occupy most of Stalingrad, pushing the defending Red Army to the banks of the Volga River.Clark (1965), p. 239 By this stage, there were indications of an impending Soviet offensive which would target Wehrmacht forces around the city, including increased Soviet activity opposite the Sixth Army's flanks and information gained through the interrogation of Soviet prisoners.Clark (1965), p. 241 However, the German command was more interested in finalizing its capture of Stalinrad.Clark (1965), p. 242 In fact, the head of Army General Staff General Franz Halder had been sacked in September after his efforts to warn about the danger which was developing along the over-extended flanks of the Sixth Army and the Fourth Panzer Army.McCarthy & Syron (2002), pp. 137–138 As early as September, the Soviet ''Stavka'' (high command) began planning a series of counteroffensives which encompassed the destruction of German forces in the south, fighting in Stalingrad and in the Caucasus, and against Army Group Center.Glantz (1999), p. 17 Ultimately, command of Soviet efforts to relieve Stalingrad was put under the leadership of General Aleksandr Vasilevsky.Glantz (1999), p. 18

The ''Stavka'' developed two major operations to be conducted against enemy forces near Stalingrad, ''Uranus'' and ''Saturn'', and also planned for Operation ''Mars'' designed to engage German Army Group Center in an effort to distract reinforcements and to inflict as much damage as possible.Glantz (1995), pp. 129–130 Operation ''Uranus'' involved the use of large Soviet mechanized and infantry forces to encircle German and other Axis forces directly around Stalingrad.Glantz (1995), p. 130 As preparations for the offensive commenced, the attack's starting points were positioned on stretches of front to the rear of the German Sixth Army, disallowing the Germans the ability to reinforce those sectors quickly where Axis units were too overstretched to occupy effectively.Beevor (1998), pp. 225–226 The offensive was a double envelopment; Soviet mechanized forces would penetrate deep to the German rear, while another attack would occur closer to the German Sixth Army in an effort to attack German units there directly in the rear.Beevor (1998), p. 226 While the Red Army prepared, the German high commanders—influenced by their belief that the Red Army, in building up opposite of Germany Army Group Center to the north, was incapable of mounting a simultaneous offensive in the south—continued to deny the possibility of an impending Soviet offensive.McTaggart (2006), pp. 49–50
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ed530420828c5a9822b09f979d0cb2f6" name="Bundesarchiv_Bild_101I-216-0445-18,_Russland-Mitte-Nord,_Panzer_IV." sectnum="1#1">../img/ed530420828c5a9822b09f979d0cb2f6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>