<document id="a231a85052fe34e0fcfe764b7964c25b-2.1" name="Operation_Uranus" cat="29">
<text>
Case Blue involved German and other Axis forces sprawled out across a front over  wide and several hundred kilometers deep, while the decision to conquer Stalingrad had stretched Axis forces even more thinly by drawing away personnel eastwards.Cooper (1978), p. 420 For example, in early July the Sixth Army was defending a  line, while also committing to an offensive which involved a distance of around .Cooper (1978), p. 418 Army Group B, which was split from Army Group South (the forces operating around the Caucasus were named Army Group A), seemed strong on paper:Erickson (1975), p. 453 it included the 16th Motorized Division, the German Second, Fourth Panzer and Sixth, Fourth and Third Romanian, Italian Eighth and Hungarian Second armies.Erickson, pp. 453–454 Army Group B held the 48th Panzer Corps, which had the strength of a weakened panzer division, and a single infantry division as reserves.Erickson, p. 454 For the most part the German flanks were held by arriving non-German armies, while German forces were used to spearhead continued operations in Stalingrad and in the Caucasus.McTaggart (2006), p. 49


While Adolf Hitler expressed confidence in the ability of non-German Axis units to protect German flanks,McTaggart (2006), p. 48 in reality these units relied on largely obsolete equipment and horse-drawn artillery, while in many cases the unenlightened treatment of enlisted personnel by officers caused poor morale.McTaggart (2006), pp. 48–49 In regard to mechanization, the First Romanian Armored Division was equipped with around 100 Czech-built Panzer 38(t)s. Its  anti-tank gunPerrett (1998), p. 17 was ineffective against Soviet T-34s.Perrett (1998), p. 21 Similarly, the  PaK anti-tank guns were also antiquated and largely short of ammunition.Beevor (1998), p. 229 Only after repeated requests did the Germans send the Romanian units  PaK guns; six per division.Clark (1975), pp. 240–241 These units were extended over very large sections of front; for example, the Third Romanian Army occupied a line  long, while the Fourth Romanian Army protected a sector no less than  long. The Italians and Hungarians were positioned between the two Romanian formations, although the German commanders, realistically, did not hold in high regard the capability of those units to fight.Manstein (1982), p. 293
Generally, German forces were in no better shape; they were weakened by months of fighting the Red Army, and, while ''Stavka'' raised new armies, the German high command attempted to maintain its existing mechanized units.Glantz (1995), p. 124 Furthermore during the course of the German offensive between May and November 1942 two motorized divisions, the elite Leibstandarte and the Großdeutschland, were redeployed from Army Group A to the West, to provide a mechanized reserve in case of a British landing in France.Cooper (1978), p. 425 The Sixth Army had also suffered many casualties during the fighting in the city of Stalingrad proper.Cooper (1978), pp. 425–426 In some cases, such as that of the 22nd Panzer Division, their equipment was no better than that of the First Romanian Armored Division.McTaggart (2006), pp. 50–51 German formations were also overextended along large stretches of front; the XI Army Corps, for example, had to defend a front around  long.McTaggart (2006), p. 50
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9fd79da9bb90703bf2d61a8ff47182dc" name="Bundesarchiv_Bild_183-B24575,_Friedrich_Paulus" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/9fd79da9bb90703bf2d61a8ff47182dc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>