<document id="a25b2dff7d13c650e6c7e6bfb3bba5a3-6.5" name="Houston" cat="11">
<text>
The Theater District is a 17-block area in the center of downtown Houston that is home to the Bayou Place entertainment complex, restaurants, movies, plazas, and parks. Bayou Place is a large multilevel building containing full-service restaurants, bars, live music, billiards, and art house films. The Houston Verizon Wireless Theater stages live concerts, stage plays, and stand-up comedy; and the Angelika Film Center presents art, foreign and independent films.. ''Angelika Film Center.'' Retrieved on 2007-01-10.

Houston is home to 337 parks including Hermann Park, which houses the Houston Zoo and the Houston Museum of Natural Science, Terry Hershey Park, Lake Houston Park, Memorial Park, Tranquility Park, Sesquicentennial Park, Discovery Green and Sam Houston Park (which contains restored and reconstructed homes which were originally built between 1823 and 1905).. ''The Heritage Society.'' Retrieved on 2007-01-10. Of the 10 most populous U.S. cities, Houston has the most total area of parks and green space: . Continental Magazine, March 2008. p.67.  The city also has over 200 additional green spaces—totaling over  that are managed by the city—including the Houston Arboretum and Nature Center. The Williams Waterwall serves as a popular tourist attraction and sits in Uptown Houston. The Houston Civic Center was replaced by the George R. Brown Convention Center—one of the nation's largest—and the Jesse H. Jones Hall for the Performing Arts, home of the Houston Symphony Orchestra and Society for the Performing Arts. The Sam Houston Coliseum and Music Hall have been replaced by the Hobby Center for the Performing Arts.

Space Center Houston is the official visitors’ center of NASA's Lyndon B. Johnson Space Center. Here one will find many interactive exhibits including moon rocks, a shuttle simulator, and presentations about the history of NASA's manned space flight program.

Other tourist attractions include the Galleria (Texas's largest shopping mall located in the Uptown District), Old Market Square, the Downtown Aquarium, and Sam Houston Race Park.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ff9498fd86ea34ef94a6561a90e8fa81" name="Hermann_Park_Texas" sectnum="6.5#1">../img/ff9498fd86ea34ef94a6561a90e8fa81.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>