<document id="a25b2dff7d13c650e6c7e6bfb3bba5a3-3" name="Houston" cat="11">
<text>
The city of Houston has a strong mayoral form of municipal government. Houston is a home rule city and all municipal elections in the state of Texas are nonpartisan. The City's elected officials are the mayor, city controller and 14 members of the city council. As of 2009, the mayor of Houston is William "Bill" White, a Democrat elected on a nonpartisan ballot who is serving his third and final term (due to term limits). Houston's mayor serves as the city's chief administrator, executive officer, and official representative. He is responsible for the general management of the city and for seeing that all laws and ordinances are enforced. As the result of a 1991 referendum in Houston, a mayor is elected for a two-year term, and can be elected to as many as three consecutive terms.

The current city council line-up of nine district based and five at-large positions was based on a U.S. Justice Department mandate which took effect in 1979.  At-large council members represent the entire city. Under the current city charter, if the population in the city limits goes past 2.1 million residents, the current nine-member city council districts will be expanded with the addition of two city council districts.

The city controller is elected independently of the mayor and council.  The controller's duties are to certify available funds prior to committing such funds, processing disbursements, and performing financial and performance audits of city departments. Annise Parker is the current (as of 2009) city controller, serving her third term in office. The city's fiscal year begins on July 1 and ends on June 30.

The city of Houston has been criticized for running the most deficient recycling program among the United States' 30 largest cities. In October 2008, the city's Sustainable Growth Committee, Chaired by Council Member Peter Brown, initiated a program to recycle heavy organic yard waste which is expected to salvage  annually, enough to fill the Chase Tower, the city's tallest structure.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a8b5d674300e67a20d390f6742f3f39b" name="HoustonCityHall_DANIEL2986" sectnum="3#1">../img/a8b5d674300e67a20d390f6742f3f39b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>