<document id="a25b2dff7d13c650e6c7e6bfb3bba5a3-2" name="Houston" cat="11">
<text>
According to the United States Census Bureau, the city has a total area of 601.7 square miles (1,558.4 km²); this comprises 579.4 square miles (1,500.7 km²) of land and 22.3 square miles (57.7 km²) of water.
Most of Houston is located on the gulf coastal plain, and its vegetation is classified as temperate grassland and forest. Much of the city was built on forested land, marshes, swamp, or prairie, which are all still visible in surrounding areas. Flatness of the local terrain, when combined with urban sprawl, has made flooding a recurring problem for the city.. ''Center for Research in Water Resources, The University of Texas at Austin'' Retrieved on 2007-01-10. Downtown stands about 50 feet (15 m) above sea level,. ''TopoQuest.com'' Retrieved on 2008-07-05. and the highest point in far northwest Houston is about 125 feet (38 m) in elevation.. ''TopoQuest.com''. 2008. Retrieved on 2008-07-05. '''''Note:''''' ''The boundaries of the City of Houston are shown as "HOUSTON CORP BDY" along the dotted line.''. ''City of Houston''. Retrieved on 2007-01-11. The city once relied on groundwater for its needs, but land subsidence forced the city to turn to ground-level water sources such as Lake Houston and Lake Conroe.. ''United States Geological Survey''. Retrieved on 2007-01-11.

Houston has four major bayous passing through the city. Buffalo Bayou runs through downtown and the Houston Ship Channel, and has three tributaries: White Oak Bayou, which runs through the Heights neighborhood north of downtown and then towards downtown; Braes Bayou, which runs along the Texas Medical Center; and Sims Bayou, which runs through the south of Houston and downtown Houston. The ship channel continues past Galveston and then into the Gulf of Mexico.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a9422f95408038806d39623b555f2799" name="Large_Houston_Landsat" sectnum="2#1">../img/a9422f95408038806d39623b555f2799.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>