<document id="a2952754ac4942cf7ea5e22ac9fbe80c-2.7" name="Degrassi:_The_Next_Generation" cat="19">
<text>
The opening season of ''Degrassi: The Next Generation'' featured thirteen actors in starring roles. Providing ties to the previous series in the Degrassi universe, Stefan Brogren was hired to play his old character Archie "Snake" Simpson, now working at the school as the media immersion teacher. Dan Woods reprised his role as Mr. Raditch, now promoted to school principal. Amanda Stepto also returned to the franchise to play her character Christine "Spike" Nelson in a recurring role. Miriam McDonald was hired to replace Ashlee Henricks (who had, in turn, replaced Samantha Morrison) as Spike's daughter, Emma Nelson; she would remain the only character from ''Degrassi Junior High'' or ''Degrassi High'' to be recast with a different actor until the season three episode "Father Figure".

For the new generation of students, the producers chose eleven school-aged children from six hundred applicants in an attempt to provide characters to which the teenage target audience could relate. This was in contrast to other shows of the same period, such as Dawson's Creek, which cast actors in their twenties as teenagers. Sarah Barrable-Tishauer acted as high-achiever yet lonely Liberty Van Zandt. Daniel Clark played bad-boy Sean Cameron. Lauren Collins acted as cool cheerleader Paige Michalchuk. Ryan Cooley acted as class clown James Tiberius "J.T." Yorke. Jake Goldsbie portrayed Toby Isaacs, a computer geek. Aubrey Graham portrayed rich and athletic Jimmy Brooks. Shane Kippel played Gavin "Spinner" Mason, the school bully with a heart of gold. Miriam McDonald portrayed environmentalist Emma Nelson. Melissa McIntyre played Ashley Kerwin, the perfect girl who attracts the popular boys, and the other girls are jealous of. Cassie Steele played Emma's sidekick, the sweet and innocent Manuela "Manny" Santos. Christina Schmidt portrayed chubby and insecure Terri McGreggor. 

In season two, former ''Degrassi'' actor Pat Mastroianni returned to the franchise as Joey Jeremiah, followed by the return of Joey's former on-screen girlfriend, Caitlin Ryan (played by Stacie Mistysyn), in the third season.

There have been a number departures from the series, and season six depicted the first death of one of the show's main characters, when J.T. Yorke was stabbed and killed. Daniel Clark's character Sean Cameron has been written out of the show twice. He left the series during the fourth season in the wake of the shooting death of Rick Murray, and returned for the sixth season. He left the series once again, but made another reappearance for one episode in season seven. The family of Joey Jeremiah was written out of the series at the end of season five, when Joey and his daughter Angie, moved to Calgary, Alberta, and his stepson Craig Manning left Degrassi to pursue his music career. Craig has made guest appearances three times since then, reappearing in a two-part episode in season six and an episode in season seven. He also made an appearance in the eighth season. Caitlin Ryan left to continue her career in Los Angeles, California, though she returned in one episode of season seven.


At the end of season five several main characters graduated from Degrassi Community School, and either left the series or went on to university. As a result, six new characters were introduced in season seven in a storyline where nearby rival high school Lakehurst merged with Degrassi due to a fire. Season eight saw major changes when many of the existing cast members, including Lauren Collins (Paige Michalchuk), Marc Minardi (Lucas Valieri), Stacey Farber (Ellie Nash), Aubrey Graham (Jimmy Brooks), Amanda Stepto (Christine Nelson), Shenae Grimes (Darcy Edwards), Mike Lobel (Jay Hogart), Adamo Ruggiero (Marco Del Rossi), Melissa DiMarco (Ms. Hatzilakos), and Mazin Elsadig (Damian Hayes) either moved to recurring status or left the series entirely. The exodus of several major cast members was reportedly an executive decision that left the actors and producers on bad terms, with Graham stating " did us foul." Thirteen actors were added to the main cast to replace them; Samantha Munro, Jajube Mandiela, Aislinn Paul, Raymond Ablack, Natty Zavitz, and Scott Paterson all held recurring roles in previous seasons, while Evan Williams, Judy Jiao, AJ Saudin, Sam Earle, Melinda Shankar, Jordan Hudyma, and Argiris Karras are new to the series.

Season nine saw a couple of minor changes when major characters Sarah Barrable-Tishauer (Liberty Van Zandt), Nina Dobrev (Mia Jones), Evan Williams (Kelly Ashoona), and Marc Donato (Derek Haig) were either moved to recurring or left the series to pursue something else. With their departures brought four new additions Landon Liboiron, Annie Clark, Jahmil French, and Jessica Tyler.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9972db8ade003ed753e632e697d8086e" name="ETalk2008-Degrassi_Cast" sectnum="2.7#1">../img/9972db8ade003ed753e632e697d8086e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>