<document id="a2e17a649fb25baa2961ff47894f1984-2.1" name="Carnivàle" cat="19">
<text>
Daniel Knauf conceived the initial script for the show between 1990 and 1992 when he was unsatisfied with his job as a Californian health insurance broker and hoped to become a screenwriter. He had always been interested in carnivals and noted that this subject had rarely been dramatized on film. The resulting story and its treatment of freaks was strongly informed by Knauf's experiences of growing up with a disabled father who was not commonly accepted as a normal human being.

Knauf named the intended feature film script ''Carnivàle'', using an unusual spelling for a more outlandish look. Knauf had plotted the story's broad strokes as well as several plot details from early on and knew the story destination up until the final scene. However, the resulting 180-page long script was twice the length of a typical feature film script, and Knauf still felt that it was too short to do his story justice. He therefore shelved the screenplay as a learning experience. In the meantime, all but one of Knauf's other scripts were rejected by Hollywood studios, often for being "too weird."

In the mid-1990s, Knauf met a few Writers Guild TV writers who encouraged him to revise ''Carnivàle'' as a TV series. Knauf turned the script's first act into a pilot episode, but, having no contacts in the television business, he was forced to shelve the project again and return to his regular job. A few years later, after realizing that his insurance career was not working out, he decided to give his screenwriting efforts a last chance by offering the ''Carnivàle'' pilot on his website. The script was subsequently forwarded to Howard Klein via Scott Winant, a mutual friend of the two men. After several meetings and conversations, Klein felt confident that ''Carnivàle'' would make a good episodic television series that could last for many years. Klein brought it to the attention of Chris Albrecht and Carolyn Strauss of HBO, who were immediately receptive. But the network deemed Knauf too inexperienced in the television business to give him full control over the budget, and appointed Ronald D. Moore as showrunner. (Knauf would replace Moore after one season when Moore left for the re-imagined ''Battlestar Galactica''.)

The pilot episode, which was filmed over a period of twenty-one days, served as the basis for additional tweaking of intended story lines. Long creative discussions took place among the writers and the network, leading to the postponement of the filming of the second episode for fourteen months. One major change was the addition of extra material for Brother Justin's side of the story. Brother Justin was originally conceived as a well-established preacher, and as a recurring character rather than a regular one. However, after perusing the preliminary version of the pilot, Knauf and the producers realized that there was no room for Justin to grow in a television series. Hence, it was decided to make Brother Justin an ordinary Methodist minister in a small town, setting him back in his career by about one or two years. Expanding Brother Justin's role opened new possibilities, and his sister Iris was created as a supporting character. Little was changed on Ben Hawkins' side except for the addition of the cootch (striptease) family; a ''Carnivàle'' consultant had elated the producers by calling attention to his research about families managing cootch shows in the 1930s.Daniel Knauf in the DVD audio commentary for the episode "Milfay"
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="38067857d110d4fbcd68ceec5a13b8ca" name="Daniel_Knauf_1" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/38067857d110d4fbcd68ceec5a13b8ca.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>