<document id="a35ff6f42d1dc5bb259402f6c61c13ed-4.5" name="Rashtrakuta_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
With the ending of the Gupta Dynasty in northern India in the early sixth century, major changes began taking place in the Deccan south of the Vindyas and in the southern regions of India. These changes were not only political but also linguistic and cultural. The royal courts of  peninsular India (outside of Tamilakam) interfaced between the increasing use of the local Kannada language  and the expanding Sanskritic culture. Inscriptions, including those that were bilingual, demonstrate the use of Kannada as the primary administrative language in conjunction with Sanskrit. Government archives used Kannada for recording pragmatic information relating to grants of land.Thapar (2002), pp393–4 The local language formed the ''desi'' (popular) literature while literature in Sanskrit was more ''marga'' (formal). Educational institutions and places of higher learning (''ghatikas'') taught in Sanskrit, the language of the learned Brahmins, while Kannada increasingly became the speech of personal expression of devotional closeness of a worshipper to a private deity. The patronage Kannada received from rich and literate Jains eventually led to its use in the devotional movements of later centuries.Thapar (2002), p396

Contemporaneous literature and inscriptions show that Kannada was not only popular in the modern Karnataka region but the linguistic change had spread further north into present day southern Maharashtra and to the northern Deccan by the eighth century.Vaidya (1924), p170  Kavirajamarga, the work on poetics, refers to the entire region between the Kaveri River and the Godavari River as "Kannada country".Sastri (1955), p355Rice, E.P. (1921), p12Rice, B.L. (1897), p497 Higher education in Sanskrit included the subjects of Veda, ''Vyakarana'' (grammar), ''Jyotisha'' (astronomy and astrology), ''Sahitya'' (literature), ''Mimansa'' (Exegesis), ''Dharmashastra'' (law), ''Puranas'' (ritual), and ''Nyaya'' (logic). An examination of inscriptions from this period shows that the ''Kavya'' (classical) style of writing was popular. The awareness of the merits and defects in inscriptions by the archivists indicates that even they, though mediocre poets, had studied standard classical literature in Sanskrit.Altekar (1934), p404 An inscription in Kannada by King Krishna III, written in a poetic Kanda metre, has been found as far away as Jabalpur in modern Madhya Pradesh.Kamath (2001), p73 Kavirajamarga, a work on poetics in Kannada by Amoghavarsha I, shows that the study of poetry was popular in the Deccan during this time. Trivikrama's Sanskrit writing, ''Nalachampu'', is perhaps the earliest in the ''champu'' style from the Deccan.Altekar (1934), p408
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="945378829e7e5d13de3371a19542e56f" name="Kuknur_oldKannada_inscription" sectnum="4.5#1">../img/945378829e7e5d13de3371a19542e56f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>