<document id="a35ff6f42d1dc5bb259402f6c61c13ed-4.3" name="Rashtrakuta_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
Kannada became more prominent as a literary language during the Rashtrakuta rule with its script and literature showing remarkable growth, dignity and productivity. This period effectively marked the end of the classical Prakrit and Sanskrit era. Court poets and royalty created eminent works in Kannada and Sanskrit that spanned such literary forms as prose, poetry, rhetoric, Hindu epics and life history of Jain tirthankaras. Famous scholars wrote on secular subjects such as mathematics. 

''Kavirajamarga'' (850) by King Amoghavarsha I is the earliest available book on rhetoric and poetics in Kannada,Kamath (2001), p90Reu (1933), p38 though it is evident from this book that other styles of Kannada literature and poetry had already existed in previous centuries.The ''Bedande'' and ''Chattana'' type of composition (Narasimhacharya 1988, p12) ''Kavirajamarga'' is a guide to poets (''Kavishiksha'') that aims to standardize these various styles. The book refers to early Kannada prose and poetry writers such as Durvinita, perhaps the 6th century monarch of Western Ganga Dynasty.It is said ''Kavirajamarga'' may have been co-authored by Amoghavarsha I and court poet Sri Vijaya (Sastri 1955,  pp355–356)Other early writers mentioned in ''Kavirajamarga'' are Vimala, Udaya, Nagarjuna, Jayabhandu for Kannada prose and Kavisvara, Pandita, Chandra and Lokapala in Kannada poetry (Narasimhacharya 1988, p2) 

A jain writer named Pampa, widely regarded as one of the greatest Kannada writers, became famous for ''Adipurana'' (941). Written in champu (mixed prose-verse style) style, it is the life history of the first Jain tirthankara Rishabhadeva.He is called as Adikavi Pampa. Pampa's other notable work was ''Vikramarjuna Vijaya'' (941), the author's version of the Hindu epic, Mahabharata, with Arjuna as the hero.Sastri (1955), p356 Also called ''Pampa Bharata'', it  praises the writer's patron, King Chalukya Arikeseri of Vemulavada (a Rashtrakuta feudatory), comparing the king's virtues favorably to those of Arjuna. Pampa demonstrates such a command of classical Kannada that scholars over the centuries have written many interpretations of his work. 

Another great jain writer in Kannada was Sri Ponna, patronised by King Krishna III and famed for  his description of the life of the 16th Jain tirthankara Shantinatha entitled ''Santipurana''.  He earned the title ''Ubhaya Kavichakravathi'' (supreme poet in two languages) for his command over both Kannada and Sanskrit. His other writings in Kannada were ''Bhuvanaika-karamabhyudaya'', ''Jinaksaramale'' and ''Gatapratiagata''.Narasimhacharya (1988, p18 Adikavi Pampa, Sri Ponna are called "gems of Kannada literature". 

Prose works in Sanskrit was prolific during this era as well. Important mathematical theories and axioms were postulated by Mahaviracharya, a native of Gulbarga, who belonged to the Karnataka mathematical tradition and was patronised by King Amoghavarsha I.Kamath (2001), p89 His greatest contribution was ''Ganitasarasangraha'', a writing in 9 chapters. Somadevasuri of 950 wrote in the court of Arikesari II, a feudatory of Rashtrakuta Krishna III in Vemulavada. He was the author of ''Yasastilaka champu'', ''Nitivakyamrita'' and other writings. The main aim of the ''champu'' writing was to propagate Jain tenets and ethics. The second writing reviews the subject matter of ''Arthasastra'' from the standpoint of Jain morals in a clear and pithy manner.Sastri (1955), p314

Trivikrama was a noted scholar in the court of King Indra III. His classics were ''Nalachampu'' (915), the earliest in champu style in Sanskrit, ''Damayanti Katha'', ''Madalasachampu'' and Begumra plates. Legend has it that Goddess Saraswati helped him in his effort to compete with a rival in the kings court.Sastri (1955), p314 Jinasena was the spiritual preceptor and guru of Amoghavarsha I. A theologian, his contributions are ''Dhavala'' and ''Jayadhavala'' (written with another theologian Virasena). These writings are named after their patron king who was also called Athishayadhavala. Other contributions from Jinasena were ''Adipurana'' later completed by his disciple Gunabhadra, ''Harivamsha'' and ''Parshvabhyudaya''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="50beaf577890d6471042615c27ecc794" name="Jain_Narayana_temple_at_Pattadakal" sectnum="4.3#1">../img/50beaf577890d6471042615c27ecc794.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>