<document id="a42b88727b019cfe407e458b9f01c03c-2.4" name="Warwick_Castle" cat="11">
<text>
Warwick Castle is protected against unauthorised change as a Scheduled Ancient Monument, in recognition of its status as a "nationally important" archaeological site or historic building. Retrieved on 30 December 2007. The castle is a Grade I listed building; it is listed with the castle's boundary walls, stables, conservatory, mill and lodge. In 1978 Warwick Castle became a member of the Treasure Houses of England, a heritage consortium founded by ten of the foremost privately owned stately homes in England with the aim of marketing and promoting themselves as tourist venues. In 1978, Warwick Castle was sold to Tussauds, a large visitor attraction operator. Tussauds performed extensive restorations to the castle and grounds in addition to opening its gates to the public. In 2001, Warwick Castle was named one of Britain's "Top 10 historic houses and monuments" by the British Tourist Authority; the list included Tower of London, Stonehenge, and Edinburgh Castle. Retrieved on 19 June 2008. Warwick Castle was recognised as Britain's best castle by the ''Good Britain Guide 2003''. Retrieved on 19 June 2008.

In June 2005, Warwick Castle became home to one of the world's largest working siege engines. The trebuchet is  tall, made from over 300 pieces of oak and weighs . The machine, which was made in Wiltshire, takes eight men half an hour to load and release. Retrieved on 19 June 2008. It is designed to be capable of hurling projectiles distances of up to  and as high as  and can throw up to  of ammunition at a time. On 21 August 2006, the trebuchet claimed the record as the most powerful catapult in the world when it sent a projectile weighing  a distance of  at a speed of , beating the previous record of  held by the Dutch. Retrieved on 19 June 2008. The war machine is situated on the banks of the River Avon which runs below the castle.

During a break-in on 23 June 2006, a £20,000 stained glass window was damaged and a ceremonial sword was stolen by three teenagers. The  sword was later found in a hedge outside a house in the Castle Close area and was returned to the care of Warwick Castle. Retrieved on 19 June 2008. During the winter of 2006–07, Warwick Castle had the largest ice slide in the country at . Retrieved on 19 June 2008. However its ice rink did not freeze over because of the unusually warm weather. Fourteen metric tons (fifteen short tons) of ice were shipped in from Grimsby to help the rink freeze over. Retrieved on 19 June 2008. Seasonal attractions include "Warwick, Ghosts Alive," "Flight of the Eagles'" (a bird show, featuring bald eagles, vultures, and sea eagles), an archery display, and the "Kingmaker" Exhibit. Retrieved on 19 June 2008. In May 2007 Tussauds was purchased by Merlin Entertainments who continue to operate the castle on a lease, having sold the freehold to Nick Leslau's Prestbury Group on 17 July 2007. Retrieved on 19 June 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8ad5d2b9915be9b7f96c7761543ac20a" name="WarwickCastle_Trebuchet" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/8ad5d2b9915be9b7f96c7761543ac20a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>