<document id="a4bbc4793cbdd82c56c22e830394d176-4" name="W._S._Gilbert" cat="17">
<text>
Although many have written that Gilbert was often prickly, many have defended him.  Actress May Fortescue recalled, "His kindness was extraordinary.  On wet nights and when rehearsals were late and the last buses were gone, he would pay the cab-fares of the girls whether they were pretty or not, instead of letting them trudge home on foot.... He was just as large-hearted when he was poor as when he was rich and successful.  For money as money he cared less than nothing.  Gilbert was no plaster saint, but he was an ideal friend.  Journalist Frank M. Boyd wrote,
I fancy that seldom was a man more generally given credit for a personality quite other than his own, than was the case with Sir W. S. Gilbert.... Till one actually came to know the man, one shared the opinion held by so many, that he was a gruff, disagreeable person; but nothing could be less true of the really great humorist. He had rather a severe appearance... and like many other clever people, he had precious little use for fools of either sex, but he was at heart as kindly and lovable a man as you could wish to meet.Boyd, Frank M.  p. 195, London: Herbert Jenkins, Ltd (1919)



Jessie Bond wrote that Gilbert "was quick-tempered, often unreasonable, and he could not bear to be thwarted, but how anyone could call him unamiable I cannot understand."Bond, Jessie,  George Grossmith to ''The Daily Telegraph'', that although Gilbert had been described as an autocrat at rehearsals, "That was really only his manner when he was playing the part of stage director at rehearsals. As a matter of fact, he was a generous, kind true gentleman, and I use the word in the purest and original sense."George Grossmith's tribute to Gilbert in ''The Daily Telegraph'', 7 June 1911

Aside from his occasional creative disagreements with, and eventual rift from, Sullivan, Gilbert's temper led to the loss of friendships with a number of people. For instance, he quarrelled with his old associate C. H. Workman, over the firing of Nancy McIntosh from the production of ''Fallen Fairies'', and with actress Henrietta Hodson. He also saw his friendship with theatre critic Clement Scott turn bitter. However, Gilbert could be extraordinarily kind. During Scott's final illness in 1904, for instance, Gilbert donated to a fund for him, visited nearly every day, and assisted Scott's wife,Scott, Mrs. Clement, ''Old Days in Bohemian London'' (c.1910). New York: Frederick A. Stokes Company. pp. 71–72 despite having not been on friendly terms with him for the previous sixteen years.See Stedman (1996), pp. 254-56 and 323-24 Similarly, Gilbert had written several plays at the behest of comic actor Ned Sothern. However, Sothern died before he could perform the last of these, ''Foggerty’s Fairy''. Gilbert purchased the play back from his grateful widow.See, e.g., Ainger, pp. 193–94.  According to one London society lady:


As the writings about Gilbert by husband and wife Seymour Hicks and Ellaline Terriss (frequent guests at his home) vividly illustrate, Gilbert's relationships with women were generally more successful than his relationships with men. Hicks, Seymour and Terriss, Ellaline  Also, according to George Grossmith, Gilbert loved children:



Gilbert's niece Mary Carter confirmed, "...he loved children very much and lost no opportunity of making them happy.....  the kindest and most human of uncles."Carter, Mary. Letter to the editor of ''The Daily Telegraph'', 6 January 1956 Grossmith quoted Gilbert as saying, "Deer-stalking would be a very fine sport if only the deer had guns."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="017dc9783dbd15cb0559f60e88b3195a" name="WSGilbert_by_Spy" sectnum="4#1">../img/017dc9783dbd15cb0559f60e88b3195a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>