<document id="a4bbc4793cbdd82c56c22e830394d176-1.1" name="W._S._Gilbert" cat="17">
<text>
Gilbert was born at 17 Southampton Street, Strand, London. His father, also named William, was a naval surgeon who later became a writer of novels and short stories, some of which were illustrated by his son.  Gilbert's mother was the former Ann Mary Bye Morris (1812-88), the daughter of Dr. Thomas Morris. Gilbert's parents were distant and stern, and he did not have a particularly close relationship with either of them.  They quarrelled constantly, and following the break-up of their marriage in 1876, his relationships with them, especially his mother, became even more strained.Pearson, pp. 16–17 Gilbert had three younger sisters, two of whom were born outside England because of the family's travels during these years: Jane Morris (b. 1838 in Milan, Italy – 1906), who married Alfred Weigall, a miniature painter; and Anne Maude (1845–1932) and Mary Florence (b. 1843 in Boulogne, France – 1911), neither of whom married.Ainger, p. xxiEden, David. ''Gilbert: Appearance and Reality'', p. 44, Sir Arthur Sullivan Society (2003) Gilbert was nicknamed "Bab" as a baby, and then "Schwenck", after his father's godparents.

As a child, Gilbert travelled in Europe with his parents (they finally settled in London in 1849). He was educated at Boulogne, France from the age of seven (he later kept his diary in French so that the servants could not read it),Noted in Morrison, Robert, '''' then Western Grammar School, Brompton, London, and then at the Great Ealing School, where he became head boy and wrote plays for school performances and painted scenery. He then attended King's College London, graduating in 1856. After taking his degree, he intended to take the examinations for a commission in the Royal Artillery, but with the end of the Crimean War, fewer recruits were needed, and the only commission available to Gilbert would have been in a line regiment. He served instead in the Civil Service, as an assistant clerk in the Privy Council Office, for four years and hated it. In 1859 he joined the Militia, a part-time home service force, with which he remained until 1878 (in between writing and other work), reaching the rank of Captain.Pearson, p. 16. He first joined the 5th West Yorkshire Militia, and later the Royal Aberdeenshire Highlanders. Upon leaving the Militia, Gilbert was given an honorary promotion to major. Stedman (1996) p. 157 and Ainger, p. 154 In 1863 he received a bequest of £300 that he used to leave the civil service and take up a brief career as a barrister (he had already entered the Inner Temple as a student), but his legal practice was not successful, averaging just five clients a year.Gilbert, W.S. ed. Peter Haining - Introduction


To supplement his income from 1861 on, Gilbert wrote a variety of stories, comic rants, grotesque illustrations, theatre reviews (many in the form of a parody of the play being reviewed),Stedman, Jane W. ''W. S. Gilbert's Theatrical Criticism''. London: The Society for Theatre Research, 2000. ISBN 0-85430-068-6 and, under the pseudonym "Bab" (his childhood nickname), illustrated poems for several comic magazines, primarily ''Fun'', started in 1861 by H. J. Byron. He published stories, articles, and reviews in papers such as the ''Cornhill Magazine, London Society, Tinsley's Magazine'' and ''Temple Bar''. In addition, Gilbert was the London correspondent for ''L'Invalide Russe'' and a drama critic for the ''Illustrated London Times''. In the 1860s he also contributed to Tom Hood's Christmas annuals, to ''Saturday Night'', the ''Comic News'' and the ''Savage Club Papers''. ''The Observer'' newspaper in 1870 sent him to France as a war correspondent reporting on the Franco-Prussian War.


The poems, illustrated humorously by Gilbert, proved immensely popular and were reprinted in book form as the ''Bab Ballads''.Stedman (1996), pp. 26–29. See also the introduction to Gilbert, W.S. (1908), ''The Bab Ballads,'' etc, which details the history of the collections it was drawn from. He would later return to many of these as source material for his plays and comic operas. Gilbert and his colleagues from ''Fun'', including Tom Robertson, Tom Hood, Clement Scott and F. C. Burnand (who defected to ''Punch'' in 1862) frequented the Arundel Club, the Savage Club, and especially Evans's café, where they had a table in competition with the ''Punch'' 'Round table'.Stedman (1996), pp. 16–18. See also Tom Robertson's play ''Society'', which fictionalised the evenings in Evans's café in one scene.

Gilbert married Lucy Agnes Turner, whom he called "Kitty", in 1867; she was 11 years his junior. He wrote many affectionate letters to her over the years. Gilbert and Lucy were socially active both in London and later at Grim's Dyke, often holding dinner parties and being invited to others' homes for dinner, in contrast to the picture painted by fictionalisations such as the film ''Topsy-Turvy''. The Gilberts had no children, but they had many pets, including some exotic ones.Ainger, p. 148 and Stedman (1996), pp. 318-20. See also Bond, Jessie, and McIntosh.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ea4bf4f3618953d3b26a835028951141" name="Gentle_Alice_Brown" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/ea4bf4f3618953d3b26a835028951141.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>