<document id="a4bbc4793cbdd82c56c22e830394d176-2.5" name="W._S._Gilbert" cat="17">
<text>
In 1871, John Hollingshead commissioned Gilbert to work with Sullivan on a holiday piece for Christmas, ''Thespis, or The Gods Grown Old'', at the Gaiety Theatre. ''Thespis'' outran five of its nine competitors for the 1871 holiday season and was later revived for a benefit performance. However, nothing more came of it at that point, and Gilbert and Sullivan went their separate ways. Gilbert worked again with Clay on ''Happy Arcadia'' (1872), and with Alfred Cellier on ''Topsyturveydom'' (1874), as well as writing several farces, operetta libretti, extravaganzas, fairy comedies, adaptations from novels, translations from the French, and the dramas described above. Also in 1874, he published his last contribution for ''Fun'' magazine (''"Rosencrantz and Guildenstern"''), after a gap of three years, then resigned due to disapproval of the new owner's other publishing interests.Jones, John Bush, "W.S. Gilbert's Contributions to Fun, 1865–1874", published in the ''Bulletin of the New York Public Library'', vol 73 (April 1969), pp. 253–66


It would be nearly four years after ''Thespis'' was produced before the two men worked together again. In 1868, Gilbert had published a short comedic sketch libretto in ''Fun'' magazine entitled "Trial by Jury: An Operetta". In 1873, Gilbert arranged with the theatrical manager and composer, Carl Rosa, to expand the piece into a one-act libretto. Rosa's wife was to sing the role of the plaintiff. However, Rosa's wife died in childbirth in 1874. Later in 1874 Gilbert offered the libretto to Richard D'Oyly Carte, but Carte could not use the piece at that time. By early 1875, Carte was managing the Royalty Theatre, and he needed a short opera to be played as an afterpiece to Offenbach's ''La Périchole''. He contacted Gilbert, asked about the piece, and suggested Sullivan to set the work. Sullivan was enthusiastic, and ''Trial by Jury'' was composed in a matter of weeks. The little piece was a runaway hit, outlasting the run of ''La Périchole'' and being revived at another theatre.Walbrook, H. M. (1922), . See also Barker, John W. , which quotes Sullivan's recollection of Gilbert reading the libretto of ''Trial by Jury'' to him: "As soon as he had come to the last word he closed up the manuscript violently, apparently unconscious of the fact that he had achieved his purpose so far as I was concerned, in as much as I was screaming with laughter the whole time."


Gilbert continued his quest to gain respect in and respectability for his profession. One thing that may have been holding dramatists back from respectability was that plays were not published in a form suitable for a "gentleman's library", as, at the time, they were generally cheaply and unattractively published for the use of actors rather than the home reader. To help rectify this, at least for himself, Gilbert arranged in late 1875 for publishers Chatto and Windus to print a volume of his plays in a format designed to appeal to the general reader, with an attractive binding and clear type, containing Gilbert's most respectable plays, including his most serious works, but mischievously capped off with ''Trial by Jury''.

After the success of ''Trial by Jury'', there were discussions towards reviving ''Thespis'', but Gilbert and Sullivan were not able to agree on terms with Carte and his backers. The score to ''Thespis'' was never published, and most of the music is now lost. It took some time for Carte to gather funds for another Gilbert and Sullivan opera, and in this gap Gilbert produced several works including ''Tom Cobb'' (1875), ''Eyes and No Eyes'' (1875, his last German Reed Entertainment), and ''Princess Toto'' (1876), his last and most ambitious work with Clay, a three-act comic opera with full orchestra, as opposed to the shorter works for much reduced accompaniment that came before. Gilbert also wrote two serious works during this time, ''Broken Hearts'' (1875) and ''Dan'l Druce, Blacksmith'' (1876).

Also during this period, Gilbert wrote his most successful comic play, ''Engaged'' (1877), which inspired Oscar Wilde's ''The Importance of Being Earnest''. ''Engaged'' is a parody of romantic drama written in the "topsy-turvy" satiric style of many of Gilbert's Bab Ballads and the Savoy Operas, with one character pledging his love, in the most poetic and romantic language possible, to every single woman in the play; the "innocent" Scottish rustics being revealed to be making a living through throwing trains off the lines and then charging the passengers for services, and, in general, romance being gladly thrown over in favour of monetary gain. ''Engaged'' continues to be performed today by both professional and amateur companies.Gilbert, W. S., , see also Feingold, Michael,  (Note the last paragraph, where Feingold writes, "Wilde pillaged this piece for ideas."); Gardner, Lyn, , etc.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="897ca21af39bb15ea82078c6af06e3a7" name="W.S._Gilbert's_burlesque_comedy,_Engaged" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/897ca21af39bb15ea82078c6af06e3a7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>