<document id="a592286c072793b47ca673a015a2f520-1.5" name="Calgary_Flames" cat="26">
<text>
After seven consecutive seasons of not making the playoffs, the Flames finally returned to the post-season in 2004. The Flames became the first team in NHL history to defeat three division champions en route to becoming the first Canadian team to make it to the Stanley Cup Finals since the Vancouver Canucks in 1994. The
Flames' first victim was the Northwest Division champion Vancouver Canucks, whom they defeated in seven games. It was the Flames' first playoff series win since they won the 1989 final.


The Flames then upset the Presidents' Trophy winning Detroit Red Wings in six games. After eliminating the Pacific Division champion Sharks, also in six games, in the Western Conference Final, the Flames earned a trip to the 2004 Stanley Cup Finals to face the Tampa Bay Lightning. Martin Gelinas scored the winning goal in all three series. The Canadian Embassy in Washington DC, flew the Flames flag beside the Maple Leaf, while Prime Minister Paul Martin dubbed the Flames "Canada's team".

The final series went to seven games, with the Flames suffering a controversial non-goal in game six at home. Replays showed that Martin Gelinas may have scored what would have been the go-ahead goal late in the third period; however, the referees never signaled a goal, and later replays were ruled inconclusive. This goal could have made Gelinas the only player in NHL history to score the winning goal in every playoff series en route to winning the Stanley Cup. The Lightning would go on to win the game in double overtime, before winning game seven at home to capture the Stanley Cup. Despite the loss, 30,000 fans packed into Olympic Plaza to celebrate the Flames run. 

The Flames would not raise their Western Conference championship banner for nearly 15 months, as the 2004–05 season was wiped out by a labour dispute. During the lockout, team owner and Chairman of the Board, Harley Hotchkiss, attempted to save the season by engaging in discussions with National Hockey League Players Association president Trevor Linden. While their discussions failed to save the season, Hotchkiss was credited with easing tensions that allowed for a successful negotiation of a new collective bargaining agreement.


The Flames played their 25th season in Calgary in 2005–06, finishing with 103 points. It was their best total since the 1989 Cup winning season, and good enough to capture their first division title in 12 years. However, the Flames lost to the Mighty Ducks of Anaheim in seven games during the first round of the playoffs. Miikka Kiprusoff captured both the William M. Jennings Trophy and the Vezina Trophy as the NHL's top goaltender, while defenceman Dion Phaneuf set a franchise record for goals by a rookie blue-liner with 20.

The 2006 off-season began with a trade for Alex Tanguay, formerly of the Colorado Avalanche, and with Sutter relinquishing his head coaching position to assistant Jim Playfair so he could focus on his duties as general manager. Despite a marked improvement in team offence and a solid 96-point season, it was only good enough for eighth place in a Western Conference where seven teams cracked the 100-point barrier. In the playoffs, Calgary fell in six games to the top seeded Red Wings in the first round. During the series, the Flames were fined by the NHL for several stick-related penalties in the fifth game. Notably, backup goaltender Jamie McLennan was suspended five games for slashing Red Wings forward Johan Franzen. Franzen would score the series clinching goal in the Game 6 defeat in Double Overtime.

Prior to the start of the 2007–08 season, the Flames demoted Playfair to associate coach, bringing in Mike Keenan as the team's third head coach in three years. During the season, Jarome Iginla became the Flames' all-time leader in games played, passing Al MacInnis' mark of 803. Iginla also passed Theoren Fleury's mark of 364 goals to become the Flames all-time goal scoring leader on March 10, 2008. Despite another solid season, with 94 points, they only garnered the seventh seed in the Western Conference.  They fell in the Western Conference quarterfinals to the Pacific Division champion Sharks in seven games. Iginla continued to set franchise records in 2008–09, surpassing Fleury's franchise mark of 830 points, and scoring his 400th goal on the same night against the Lightning. On May 22, 2009, head coach Mike Keenan was fired by the Flames after two consecutive 1st round playoff exits and an overall record of 88-60-16. Brent Sutter was named his successor on June 23, 2009. Sutter joins the team after two seasons as the head coach of the New Jersey Devils with an overall record of 97-56-11, and won the Atlantic Division title in 2008–09 season.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2c77f218ffdc0a532633472dd3a8127b" name="MiikkaKiprusoff" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/2c77f218ffdc0a532633472dd3a8127b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>