<document id="a60f626443630e8c42a3fe352b98dc17-2.2" name="USS_Wisconsin_(BB-64)" cat="29">
<text>
''Wisconsin'' was assigned to the 5th Fleet when Admiral Raymond A. Spruance relieved Admiral Halsey as Commander of the Fleet. She moved northward with the redesignated TF 58 as the carriers headed for the Tokyo area. On 16 February, the task force approached the Japanese coast under cover of adverse weather conditions and achieved complete tactical surprise. As a result, ''Wisconsin'' and the other ships shot down 322 enemy planes and destroyed 177 more on the ground. Japanese shipping, both naval and merchant, also suffered drastically, as did hangars and aircraft installations.

''Wisconsin'' and the task force moved to Iwo Jima on 17 February to provide direct support for the landings slated to take place on 19 February. They revisited Tokyo on 25 February and hit the island of Hachino off the coast of Honshū the next day, resulting in heavy damage to ground facilities; additionally, American planes sank five small vessels and destroyed 158 planes.

''Wisconsin''s task force stood out of Ulithi on 14 March bound for Japan. The mission of that group was to eliminate airborne resistance from the Japanese homeland to American forces off Okinawa. Enemy fleet units at Kure and Kobe, on southern Honshū, reeled under the impact of the explosive blows delivered by TF 58's airmen. On 18-19 March, from a point  southwest of Kyūshū, TF 58 hit enemy airfields on that island; unfortunately, allied anti-aircraft fire on 19 March failed to stop an attack on the carrier . That afternoon, ''Wisconsin'' and the task force retired from Kyūshū, screening the blazing and battered flattop, and shooting down 48 attackers.

On 24 March, ''Wisconsin'' trained her  guns on targets ashore on Okinawa. Together with the other battle-wagons of the task force, she pounded Japanese positions and installations in preparation for the landings. Japanese resistance, while fierce, was doomed to failure by dwindling numbers of aircraft and trained pilots.



While TF 58's planes were dealing with  and her escorts, enemy aircraft attacked the American surface units. Combat air patrols (CAP) shot down 15 enemy planes, and ships' gunfire shot down another three, but not before one ''kamikaze'' attack penetrated the CAP and screen to crash on the flight deck of the fleet carrier . On 11 April, the Japanese renewed their ''kamikaze'' attacks; and only drastic maneuvers and heavy barrages of gunfire saved the task force. Combat air patrols shot down 17 planes, and ships' gunfire shot down 12. The next day, 151 enemy aircraft attacked TF 58, but ''Wisconsin'', together with other units of the screens for the vital carriers, kept the ''kamikaze'' pilots at bay and destroyed them before they could reach their targets. Over the days that ensued, Japanese ''kamikaze'' attacks managed to crash into three carriers — ,  and  — on successive days.

By 4 June, a typhoon was swirling through the Fleet. ''Wisconsin'' rode out the storm unscathed, but three cruisers, two carriers, and a destroyer suffered serious damage. Offensive operations were resumed on 8 June with a final aerial assault on Kyūshū. Japanese aerial response was virtually nonexistent; 29 planes were located and destroyed. On that day, one of ''Wisconsin''s floatplanes landed and rescued a downed pilot from the carrier .
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e790972267e69c572444a98af9c0b206" name="WWII_Wisconsin" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/e790972267e69c572444a98af9c0b206.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>