<document id="a6111ef1d184fb6f317803c64ccd35cd-2.4" name="Riverina" cat="11">
<text>
The first European explorer in the Riverina was John Oxley in 1817 following the Lachlan River to what is now the town of Booligal.  Oxley was followed by Charles Sturt, who followed the Murrumbidgee downstream to Lake Alexandrina in South Australia between 1828–1831 and Major Thomas Mitchell in 1836 on his way to the Wimmera and the Western District.

Pastoral settlement followed soon after, with grazing runs established along the Murray and Murrumbidgee as far west as Hay by 1839. At the time, the area was known as the Murrumbidgee District. Moulamein, in the western Riverina, appears to make legitimate claims as the oldest town in the Riverina, and indeed to being older than Melbourne. The settlers often came into conflict with the indigenous inhabitants. In the Narrandera district, a battle took place between settlers and the local Narrungderra clan at a location now known as Massacre Island, reportedly leaving only one survivor.

Cattle raising was the major industry in the 1840s with sheep becoming predominant in the 1860s.  At this time  many Victorians settled in the Riverina to breed sheep and cattle to feed the miners taking part in the Victorian Gold Rush. The herds were considered inferior at first, but these pastures were good for stock, and the land which seemed a desert was actually good fattening country.
In the 1860s and 1870s, German settlers from the Barossa Valley travelled upstream to settle in the eastern Riverina. Because of their religious distinctiveness as Lutherans, they preferred to form clustered German settlements.Spennemann, Dirk H.R. (2007) Mapping the German Footprint in the Riverina in 1884.  (ISSN 1834-7797) n° 2, pp. 1-9 In 1867 and 1868 several land parcels were taken up in the Jindera area.Spennemann, Dirk H.R. (2007) A Baunscheidt Homeopathic Medicine Kit in the Jindera Pioneer Museum.  (ISSN 1834-7797) n° 4, pp. 1-87  56 German farmers, in 1869, took six weeks to travel six hundred miles in covered wagons to establish the town of Walla Walla.
Nearby Holbrook was originally named Germantown after these settlers until changing its name in 1914 as a result of tensions caused by World War I.

The name "Riverine", coined from the Entre Ríos Province (between two rivers) in Argentina, South America, was in use as early as 1857: a long letter under the caption "Riverine Colony" appeared in the Albury ''Border Post''  of 24 January that year. The name was coined by Dunmore Lang who translated it from the Spanish.

Dunmore Lang was also involved with the short lived Riverina secession movement which was active in the 1860s. The movement was inspired by the success of the Victorian and Queensland secession movements and motivated by a desire to draw more public funds to the region and maintain the favourable land tenure the "squatter" pastoralists enjoyed. With the movement strongest in Deniliquin and Albury, Dunmore Lang, unrelated squatter and parliamentarian Gideon Lang and other influential pastoralists joined with local newspaper editors, George Mott and David Jones in the campaign.  This culminated in presenting petitions to the Governor of New South Wales, Sir John Young and the Colonial Secretary, Edward Cardwell. Soon after the movement fell apart due to the differences between the squatters on one side and the small farmers and townspeople on the other causing its objectives to become obscured by other associated issues such as inter-colonial tariffs and rail links.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="46204ef82ab19bdae8a9c5c4cb378558" name="CharlesSturt" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/46204ef82ab19bdae8a9c5c4cb378558.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>