<document id="a6155778e1470f746c176633d032476f-3.3.4" name="Tibet_during_the_Ming_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
The Ming Dynasty granted titles to sects such as the Black Hat Karmapa lamas, but the latter had previously declined Mongol invitations to receive titles.Wylie, "Lama Tribute in the Ming Dynasty", 469&ndash;470. When the Ming Yongle Emperor invited Je Tsongkhapa (1357&ndash;1419), founder of the Yellow Hat sect, to come to the Ming court and pay tribute, the latter declined. Wang and Nyima write that this was due to old age and physical weakness, and also because of efforts being made to build three major monasteries.Wang & Nyima, ''The Historical Status of China's Tibet'', 35. Chen Qingying states that Tsongkhapa wrote a letter to decline the Emperor's invitation, and in this reply, Tsongkhapa wrote:




It is not that I don't know it is the edict of the Great dominator of the world for the sake of Buddhist doctrine, or that I do not obey the edict of Your Majesty. I am seriously ill whenever I meet the public, so I cannot embark on a journey in compliance with the imperial edict. I wish that Your Majesty might be merciful, and not be displeased; it will really be a great mercy.Chen Qingying, ''Tibetan History'' (Beijing: China Intercontinental Press, 2003), 51; original text: 余非不知此是大地之大主宰為佛法著想之諭旨，亦非不遵不敬陛下之詔書，但我每與眾人相會，便發生重病，故不能遵照聖旨而行，惟祈陛下如虛空廣大之胸懷，不致不悅，實為幸甚。

 
Tom Grunfeld, Professor of History at Empire State College of the State University of New York, says that Tsongkhapa claimed ill health in his refusal to appear at the Ming court,A. Tom Grunfeld, ''The Making of Modern Tibet'' (New York: M.E. Sharpe, Inc., 1996), 40. while Rossabi adds that Tsongkhapa cited the "length and arduousness of the journey" to China as another reason not to make an appearance. This first request by the Ming was made in 1407, but the Ming court sent another embassy in 1413, this one led by the eunuch Hou Xian (候顯; fl. 1403&ndash;1427), which was again refused by Tsongkhapa. Rossabi writes that Tsongkhapa did not want to entirely alienate the Ming court, so he sent his disciple Chosrje Shākya Yeshes (Jamchen Choje, 釋迦也失) to Nanjing in 1414 on his behalf, and upon his arrival in 1415 the Yongle Emperor bestowed upon him the title of "State Teacher"—the same title earlier awarded the Phagmodru ruler of Tibet. The Xuande Emperor (r. 1425&ndash;1435) even granted this disciple Chosrje Shākya Yeshes the title of a "King" (王).  This title does not appear to have held any practical meaning, or to have given its holder any power, at Tsongkhapa's Ganden monastery.  Wylie notes that this—like the Black Hat sect—cannot be seen as a reappointment of Mongol Yuan offices, since the Yellow Hat sect was created after the fall of the Yuan Dynasty.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e3e2c54e9bd0943dbcadb6507e9b58d0" name="Xuande_Emperor" sectnum="3.3.4#1">../img/e3e2c54e9bd0943dbcadb6507e9b58d0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>