<document id="a6155778e1470f746c176633d032476f-3.3.3" name="Tibet_during_the_Ming_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
Wang and Nyima state that after the official title "Education Minister" was granted to Janchub Gyaltsän (Byang chub rgyal mtshan, 1302&ndash;1364) by the Yuan court, this title appeared frequently with his name in various Tibetan texts, while his Tibetan title "Degsi" is seldom mentioned.Wang & Nyima, ''The Historical Status of China's Tibet'', 42. Wang and Nyima take this to mean that "even in the later period of the Yuan Dynasty, the Yuan imperial court and the Pagmo Drupa regime maintained a Central-local government relation." Janchub Gyaltsän is even supposed to have written in his will: "In the past I received loving care from the emperor in the east. If the emperor continues to care for us, please follow his edicts and the imperial envoy should be well received."Wang & Nyima, ''Historical Status of China's Tibet'', 42.



However, Lok-Ham Chan, a professor of history at the University of Washington, writes that Janchub Gyaltsän's aims were to recreate the old Tibetan Kingdom that existed during the Chinese Tang Dynasty, to build "nationalist sentiment" amongst Tibetans, and to "remove all traces of Mongol suzerainty." Georges Dreyfus, a professor of religion at Williams College, writes that it was Janchub Gyaltsän who adopted the old administrative system of Songtsän Gampo (c. 605&ndash;649)—the first Yarlung king to establish Tibet as a strong power—by reinstating its legal code of punishments and administrative units.Georges Dreyfus, "Cherished memories, cherished communities: proto-nationalism in Tibet", in ''The History of Tibet: Volume 2, The Medieval Period: c. AD 850–1895, the Development of Buddhist Paramountcy'' (New York: Routledge, 2003), 504. For example, instead of the 13 governorships established by the Mongol Sakya viceroy, Janchub Gyaltsän divided Central Tibet into districts (dzong) with district heads (dzong dpon) who had to conform to old rituals and wear clothing styles of old Imperial Tibet. Van Praag asserts that Janchub Gyaltsän's ambitions were to "restore to Tibet the glories of its Imperial Age" by reinstating secular administration, promoting "national culture and traditions," and installing a law code that survived into the 20th century.Van Praag, ''The Status of Tibet'', 7.

According to Chen, the Ming officer of Hezhou (modern day Linxia) informed the Hongwu Emperor that the general situation in Dbus and Gtsang "was under control," and so he suggested to the emperor that he offer the second Phagmodru ruler Shakya Gyaltsen ()  an official title.Chen, ''Tibetan History'', 44. According to the Records of the Founding Emperor, Hongwu issued an edict granting the title "Initiation State Master" to Sagya Gyaincain, while the latter sent envoys to the Ming court to hand over his jade seal of authority along with tribute of colored silk and satin, statues of the Buddha, Buddhist scriptures, and sarira. 

Dreyfus writes that after the Phagmodru myriarchy lost its centralizing power over Tibet in 1434, several attempts by other families to establish hegemonies failed over the next two centuries until 1642 with Lozang Gyatso, the Fifth Dalai Lama's effective hegemony over Tibet.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f28a1dc6ce2873ea427637472cb3814e" name="Tsongkhapa" sectnum="3.3.3#1">../img/f28a1dc6ce2873ea427637472cb3814e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>