<document id="a6155778e1470f746c176633d032476f-3.7" name="Tibet_during_the_Ming_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
Elliot Sperling, a specialist of Indian studies and the director of the Tibetan Studies program at Indiana University’s Department of Central Eurasia Studies, writes that "the idea that Tibet became part of China in the 13th century is a very recent construction."Sperling, Elliot. (April 13, 2008). . ''The New York Times''. Retrieved on 2008-04-24. He writes that Chinese writers of the early 20th century were of the view that Tibet was not annexed by China until the Manchu Qing Dynasty invasion during the 18th century.  He also states that Chinese writers of the early 20th century described Tibet as a feudal dependent of China, not an integral part of it. Sperling states that this is because "Tibet was ruled as such, within the empires of the Mongols and the Manchus" and also that "China's intervening Ming Dynasty ... had no control over Tibet." He writes that the Ming relationship with Tibet is problematic for China’s insistence of its unbroken sovereignty over Tibet since the 13th century. As for the Tibetan view that Tibet was never subject to the rule of the Yuan or Qing emperors of China, Sperling also discounts this by stating that Tibet was "subject to rules, laws and decisions made by the Yuan and Qing rulers" and that even Tibetans described themselves as subjects of these emperors. 

Josef Kolmaš, a sinologist, Tibetologist, and Professor of Oriental Studies at the Academy of Sciences of the Czech Republic, writes that it was during the Qing Dynasty "that developments took place on the basis of which Tibet came to be considered an organic part of China, both practically and theoretically subject to the Chinese central government."Kolmas, ''Tibet and Imperial China'', 33. Yet he states that this was a radical change in regards to all previous eras of Sino-Tibetan relations. 

P. Christiaan Klieger, an anthropologist and scholar of the California Academy of Sciences in San Francisco, writes that the vice royalty of the Sakya regime installed by the Mongols established a patron-priest relationship between Tibetans and Mongol converts to Tibetan Buddhism.P. Christiaan Klieger, "Riding High on the Manchurian Dream: Three Paradigms in the Construction of the Tibetan Question", in ''Contemporary Tibet: Politics, Development, and Society in a Disputed Region'' (New York: M.E. Sharpe, Inc., 2006), 217. According to him, the Tibetan lamas and Mongol khans upheld a "mutual role of religious prelate and secular patron," respectively. He adds that "Although agreements were made between Tibetan leaders and Mongol khans, Ming and Qing emperors, it was the Republic of China and its Communist successors that assumed the former imperial tributaries and subject states as integral parts of the Chinese nation-state."

Marina Illich, a scholar of Indo-Tibetan Buddhism, while discussing the life of the Yellow Hat lama Chankya Rolpe Dorje (1717&ndash;1786), mentions the limitations of both Western and Chinese modern scholarship in their interpretation of Tibetan sources. As for the limitations imposed on scholars by the central government of the People's Republic of China on issues regarding the history of Tibet, Illich writes:

PRC scholars ... work under the strict supervision of censor bureaus and must adhere to historiographic guidelines issued by the state  have little choice but to frame their discussion of eighteenth-century Tibetan history in the anachronistic terms of contemporary People's Republic of China (P.R.C.) state discourse ... Bound by Party directives, these scholars have little choice but to portray Tibet as a trans-historically inalienable  part of China in a way that profoundly obscures questions of Tibetan agency.Marina Illich, "Imperial Stooge or Emissary to the Dge lugs Throne? Rethinking the Biographies of Chankya Rolpé Dorjé", in ''Power, Politics, and the Reinvention of Tradition: Tibet in the Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries'' (Leiden: Koninklijke Brill, 2006), 19.

''China Daily'', a CCP-controlled news organization since 1981, states that although there were dynastic changes after Tibet was incorporated into the territory of China's Yuan Dynasty in the 13th century, "Tibet has remained under the jurisdiction of the central government of China."''China Daily''. (April 9, 2008). . Chinadaily.com.cn. Retrieved on 2008-04-25. It also states that the Ming Dynasty "inherited the right to rule Tibet" from the Yuan Dynasty, and repeats the claims in the ''Mingshi'' about the Ming establishing two itinerant high commands over Tibet. ''China Daily'' states that the Ming handled Tibet's civil administration, appointed all leading officials of these administrative organs, and punished Tibetans who broke the law. The party-controlled ''People's Daily'', the state-controlled Xinhua News Agency, and the state-controlled national television network China Central Television post the same article that ''China Daily'' has, the only difference being their headlines and some additional text.''People's Daily''. (April 14, 2008). . English.peopledaily.com.cn. Retrieved on 2008-04-26.CCTV. (2005). . CCTV.com. Retrieved on 2008-04-26.Xinhua News Agency. (April 15, 2008). . Retrieved on 2008-05-06.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5f1e851d744b3cc0f0710bb3f494c445" name="Ming-Empire2" sectnum="3.7#1">../img/5f1e851d744b3cc0f0710bb3f494c445.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>