<document id="a62df44f3769dde1bbe94b7959674ddf-3" name="Styracosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
The first fossil remains of ''Styracosaurus'' were collected in Alberta, Canada by C.M. Sternberg (from an area now known as Dinosaur Provincial Park, in a formation now called the Dinosaur Park Formation) and named by Lawrence Lambe in 1913. This quarry was revisited in 1935 by a Royal Ontario Museum crew who found the missing lower jaws and most of the skeleton. These fossils indicate that ''S. albertensis'' was around 5.5 to 5.8 meters in length and stood about 1.65 meters high at the hips. An unusual feature of this first skull is that the smallest frill spike on the left side is partially overlapped at its base by the next spike. It appears that the frill suffered a break at this point in life and was shortened by about 6 centimeters (2 in). The normal shape of this area is unknown because the corresponding area of the right side of the frill was not recovered.

Barnum Brown and Erich Maren Schlaikjer, working for the American Museum of Natural History in New York, collected a nearly complete articulated skeleton with a partial skull in 1915. These fossils were also found in the Dinosaur Park Formation, near Steveville, Alberta. Brown and Schlaikjer compared the finds, and, though they allowed that both specimens were from the same general locality and geological formation, they considered the specimen sufficiently distinct from the holotype to warrant erecting a new species, and described the fossils as ''Styracosaurus parksi'', named in honor of William Parks. Among the differences between the specimens cited by Brown and Schlaikjer were a cheekbone quite different from that of ''S. albertensis'', and smaller tail vertebrae. ''S. parksi'' also had a more robust jaw, a shorter dentary, and the frill differed in shape from that of the type species. However, much of the skull consisted of plaster reconstruction, and the original 1937 paper did not illustrate the actual skull bones. It is now accepted as a specimen of ''S. albertensis''.

In the summer of 2006, Darren Tanke of the Royal Tyrrell Museum of Palaeontology in Drumheller, Alberta relocated the long lost ''S. parksi'' site. Pieces of the skull, evidently abandoned by the 1915 crew, were found in the quarry. These were collected and it is hoped more pieces will be found, perhaps enough to warrant a redescription of the skull and test whether ''S. albertensis'' and ''S. parksi'' are the same. The Tyrrell Museum has also collected several partial ''Styracosaurus'' skulls. At least one confirmed bonebed (bonebed 42) in Dinosaur Provincial Park has also been explored (other proposed ''Styracosaurus'' bonebeds instead have fossils from a mix of animals, and nondiagnostic ceratopsian remains). Bonebed 42 is known to contain numerous pieces of skulls such as horncores, jaws and frill pieces.

A third species, ''S. ovatus'', from the Two Medicine Formation of Montana, was described by Gilmore in 1930. The fossil material is limited, with the best being a portion of the parietal bone of the frill, but one unusual feature is that the pair of spikes closest to the midline converge towards the midline, rather than away from it as in ''S. albertensis''. There also may only have been two sets of spikes on each side of the frill, instead of three. The spikes are much shorter than in ''S. albertensis'', with the longest only 295 millimeters (11.6 in) long. A recent review of styracosaur skull remains by Ryan, Holmes, and Russell finds it to be a distinct species.

Several other species which were assigned to ''Styracosaurus'' have since been assigned to other genera. ''S. sphenocerus'', described by Edward Drinker Cope in 1890 as a species of ''Monoclonius'' and based on a nasal bone with a broken ''Styracosaurus''-like straight nose horn, was attributed to ''Styracosaurus'' in 1915. "S. makeli", mentioned informally by amateur paleontologists Stephen and Sylvia Czerkas in 1990 in a caption to an illustration, is an early name for ''Einiosaurus''. "S. borealis" is an early informal name for ''S. parksi''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c44e98c965907404977ce4b170eb1c86" name="Styracosaurus_skeleton" sectnum="3#1">../img/c44e98c965907404977ce4b170eb1c86.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>