<document id="a62df44f3769dde1bbe94b7959674ddf-4.3" name="Styracosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
The large nasal horns and frills of ''Styracosaurus'' are among the most distinctive facial adornments of all dinosaurs. Their function has been the subject of debate since the first horned dinosaurs were discovered.

Early in the 20th century, paleontologist R. S. Lull proposed that the frills of ceratopsian dinosaurs acted as anchor points for their jaw muscles. He later noted that for ''Styracosaurus'', the spikes would have given it a formidable appearance. In 1996, Dodson supported the idea of muscle attachments in part and created detailed diagrams of possible muscle attachments in the frills of ''Styracosaurus'' and ''Chasmosaurus'', but did not subscribe to the idea that they completely filled in the fenestrae.Dodson, P. (1996). ''The Horned Dinosaurs: A Natural History''. Princeton University Press: Princeton, New Jersey, p. 269. ISBN 0-691-02882-6. C.A. Forster, however, found no evidence of large muscle attachments on the frill bones.Forster, C. A. (1990). The cranial morphology and systematics of ''Triceratops'', with a preliminary analysis of ceratopsian phylogeny. Ph.D. Dissertation. University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia. 227 pp. OCLC 61500040 

It was long believed that ceratopsians like ''Styracosaurus'' used their frills and horns in defence against the large predatory dinosaurs of the time. Although pitting, holes, lesions, and other damage on ceratopsid skulls are often attributed to horn damage in combat, a 2006 study found no evidence for horn thrust injuries causing these forms of damage (for example, there is no evidence of infection or healing). Instead, non-pathological bone resorption, or unknown bone diseases, are suggested as causes.Tanke, D. H, and Farke, A. A. (2006). Bone resorption, bone lesions, and extracranial fenestrae in ceratopsid dinosaurs: a preliminary assessment. in: Carpenter, K. (ed.). ''Horns and Beaks: Ceratopsian and Ornithopod Dinosaurs'' Indiana University Press: Bloomington. pp. 319–347. ISBN 0-253-34817-X.

The large frill on ''Styracosaurus'' and related genera also may have helped to increase body area to regulate body temperature, like the ears of the modern elephant. A similar theory has been proposed regarding the plates of ''Stegosaurus'', although this use alone would not account for the bizarre and extravagant variation seen in different members of the Ceratopsidae. This observation is highly suggestive of what is now believed to be the primary function, display.

The theory of frill use in sexual display was first proposed in 1961 by Davitashvili. This theory has gained increasing acceptance. Evidence that visual display was important, either in courtship or in other social behavior, can be seen in the fact that horned dinosaurs differ markedly in their adornments, making each species highly distinctive. Also, modern living creatures with such displays of horns and adornments use them in similar behavior.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="33c7af9cd8deb4c4bccdb717f2d73595" name="Styracosaurussk" sectnum="4.3#1">../img/33c7af9cd8deb4c4bccdb717f2d73595.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>