<document id="a66156f1a171a341488eb0cb694cd06b-4" name="Queluz_National_Palace" cat="1">
<text>
Queluz is famed for the glory of its gardens, which include a large topiary parterre laid out in the manner of Le Nôtre at the rear of the palace (''see key 14''). The Flemish influences, including the canals, in the garden are the work of the Dutch gardener Gerald van der Kolk, who assisted Robillon from 1760.Dynes, p. 186. Formal terraces and walkways are given extra interest by statuary and fountains. The dominant feature of the principal parterre is the "Portico dos Cavalinhos", a garden temple flanked by two allegorical equestrian statues depicting Fames, and two sphinxes (''see final illustration'') surreally dressed in 18th-century costume, combining the formal and the fantastic.Fielding, p. 277. This surreal theme continues elsewhere in the gardens where such motifs as the rape of the Sabines and the death of Abel alternate with statuary of donkeys dressed in human clothing. Deeper in the gardens is a grotto complete with a cascade. Later to be a popular feature in Portuguese gardens, the Queluz cascade was the first artificial waterfall to be constructed near Lisbon.

An avenue of huge magnolias forms the approach to the classical Robillon wing of the palace (''see key 7''), while from the wing a double staircase leads to the canal. More than 100 metres (330 ft) long, the walls of the canal are decorated with tiled panels depicting seascapes and associated scenes. This is the largest of a series of canals in the gardens bordered with chinoiserie-style azulejo tiles. Fed by a stream, the sluice gates to the canals are only opened in May. During the 18th century, the canals were the setting for fête champêtres during which fully rigged ships would sail in processions with figures aboard in allegorical costumes.Fielding, p. 278.

The gardens also contain a fountain with tritons and dolphins which has been attributed to Bernini.Lowndes, p. 185. There are further fountains and statuary in the lower gardens, set within tall hedges of yew and cypress, and magnolia and mulberry trees planted by Marshal Junot during the French occupation in the Napoleonic wars.Lowndes, p. 184.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="826c71b6b9497dc61d02dccded2633dd" name="Palacio_Queluz_Corredor_Mangas3" sectnum="4#1">../img/826c71b6b9497dc61d02dccded2633dd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>