<document id="a6d6097fd19c757ced0bf10147e2eadf-3.1" name="Short-beaked_Echidna" cat="3">
<text>
The solitary Short-beaked Echidna looks for a mate between May and September; the precise timing of the mating season varies with geographic location. Both males and females give off a strong odour during the mating season. During courtship — observed for the first time in 1989 — males locate and pursue females. Trains of up to ten males may follow a single female in a courtship ritual that may last for up to four weeks; the duration of the courtship period varies with location.Rismiller, P.D., Seymour, R.S., 1991. The echidna. ''Scientific American'' 264, 96–103. In cooler parts of their range, such as Tasmania, females may mate within a few hours of arousal from hibernation.Nicol, S.C., Andersen, N.A., and Jones, S.M., 2005. Seasonal variations in reproductive hormones of free-ranging echidnas (''Tachyglossus aculeatus''): interaction between reproduction and hibernation. ''General and Comparative Endocrinology'' 144: 204–210 

Before mating, the male smells the female, paying particular attention to the cloaca. The male is often observed to roll the female onto her side and then assumes a similar position so that the two animals are abdomen to abdomen. Each side of the bilaterally symmetrical, rosettelike 4 headed penis  is used alternately, with the other half being shut down between ejaculations. Sperm bundles of ~100 each, appears to confer increased sperm motility, which may provide the potential for sperm competition between males.Johnston SD, Smith B, Pyne M, Stenzel D, Holt WV. One-Sided Ejaculation of Echidna Sperm Bundles (''Tachyglossus aculeatus''). ''Am. Nat.'' 2007. Vol. 170, p. E000.  Each mating results in the production of a single egg, and females are known to mate only once during the breeding season; each mating is successful.Rismiller, P.D. and McKelvey, M.W. 2000. Frequency of breeding recruitment in the Short-beaked Echidna, ''Tachyglossus aculeatus''. ''Journal of Mammalogy'' 81:1–17

Fertilisation occurs in the oviduct. Gestation takes between 21 and 28 days, during which time the female constructs a nursery burrow. Following the gestation period, a single rubbery-skinned egg between 13 and 17 millimetres in diameter is laid directly into a small, backward-facing pouch that has developed on her abdomen. Ten days after it is laid, the egg hatches within the pouch. The embryo develops an "egg tooth" during incubation, which it uses to tear open the egg; the tooth disappears soon after hatching. 

Hatchlings are about 1.5 cm long and weigh between 0.3 and 0.4 grams.Rismiller, P.D. and McKelvey, M.W. 2003. Body mass, age and sexual maturity in short-beaked echidnas, ''Tachyglossus aculeatus''. ''Comparative Biochemistry and Physiology. A, Molecular & Integrative Physiology'' 136:851–865 After hatching, young Echidnas are known as ''puggles''. Hatchlings attach themselves to their mothers' milk areolae, a specialised patch on the skin that secretes milk (monotremes lack nipples). The way in which puggles imbibe the milk is not yet known, but they have been observed ingesting large amounts during each feeding period, since mothers may leave them unattended in the burrow for between five and ten days. The principal components of the milk are fucosyllactose and saialyllactose; it is high in iron content, giving it a pink colour. Juveniles are eventually ejected from the pouch at around two to three months of age, because of the continuing growth in the length of their spines. Suckling gradually decreases until juveniles are weaned at about six months of age. The duration of lactation is about 200 days, and the young leave the burrow between 180 and 240 days.

The age of sexual maturity is uncertain, but may be four to five years. A twelve-year field study, published in 2003, found that the Short-beaked Echidna reached sexual maturity between five and 12 years of age, and that the frequency of reproduction varies from once every two years to once every six years. The Short-beaked Echidna can live as long as 45 years in the wild.

Similar to its fellow monotreme the Platypus, the Short-beaked Echidna has an unusual system of sex chromosomes, resulting in males having one fewer chromosomes than females. Male individuals appear to be XYXYXYXYX, with the final X unpaired, while females are XXXXXXXXXX. Weak identity between chromosomes results in meiotic pairing that yields only two possible genotypes of sperm, XXXXX or YYYY, thus preserving this complex system.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f99fecf5f831318fc474848ad3d3d8f8" name="Ameisenigel_Unterseite-drawing" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/f99fecf5f831318fc474848ad3d3d8f8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>