<document id="a6ed05911356fc578c660f121f2ad0de-8" name="Ahmedabad" cat="11">
<text>
the Ahmedabad-Vadodara expressway
Ahmedabad is one of the six operating divisions of the Western Railway. Railway lines connect the city to all towns in Gujarat and other major Indian cities. The Kalupur Railway Station is the city's main terminus; Ahmedabad's fifteen other stations are Maninagar, Vatva,  Gandhigram, Asarva, Chandlodia, Kali gam, Vastrapur, Sabarmati, Sarkhej, Naroda, Aamli. The Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel International Airport serves both domestic and international flights to and from Ahmedabad and the neighboring cities of Surendranagar, Mehsana and Nadiad. The airport connects the city with destinations across India and the world.

National Highway 8, linking Delhi to Mumbai, passes though Ahmedabad. It connects Gandhinagar, Delhi and Mumbai. From The National Highway 8c Ahmedabad is linked to Gandhinagar. Ahmedabad is connected to Vadodara through National Expressway 1, a 94 km (58 mi) long highway with only two exits. This expressway is part of the Golden Quadrilateral project.

The city's main traffic arteries are the Mahatma Gandhi Road, C. G. Road, the Jawaharlal Nehru Road, Ashram Road. The Sarkhej-Gandhinagar Highway is known as Ahmedabad's growth symbol. Transportation For Gandhinagar is available for 24 hours from SG highway. Auto rickshaws, share autos and buses are the most popular forms of public transport. The Ahmedabad Municipal Transport Service (AMTS) runs the local bus service in the city. In 2005, AMTS began a drive to convert all of its petrol and diesel engine buses to run on compressed natural gas engines to reduce the effects of air pollution. AMTS runs 750 buses. Bicycles and motorcycles are a popular medium of transport with the city's young people and students. The Ahmedabad BRTS project has been launched by the Government of Gujarat. The project's first phase is projected to be completed by May 2009.

In 2001, Ahmedabad was ranked as the 1st most polluted city in India, out of 85 cities, by the Central Pollution Control Board. The Gujarat Pollution Control Board gave auto rickshaw drivers an incentive of Rs. 10,000 to convert all 37,733 auto rickshaws in Ahmedabad to cleaner burning compressed natural gas to reduce pollution. As a result, in 2008, Ahmedabad was ranked 50th most polluted city in India.

The state government has registered Metro link Express for Gandhinagar and Ahmedabad Company Ltd as a special purpose vehicle (SPV) for the metro rail project for Ahmedabad and Gandhinagar. The state government plans to use this SPV as a nodal agency to implement the metro and regional rail project based on public-private partnership for Ahmedabad Region and Gandhinagar Cosmopolitan Region.

Ahmedabad Municipal Corpaoration has recently started a new transport system called BRTS (Bus Rapid Transit System). First phase of the project is over and it has already started. First phase include the placed between Ranip Cross Roads to Vasna. This buses are comfortable and technically advanced. They have separate lane and no other vehicles are allowed. Remaining phases are about to over and they will be operated by mid 2010.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="799cb0234e925344e6f400aae263ce9c" name="SG_Road2" sectnum="8#1">../img/799cb0234e925344e6f400aae263ce9c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>