<document id="a6fe2e9e3fe88359f95b5b8f867f5d4c-1.1" name="Anton_Chekhov" cat="17">
<text>
Chekhov now assumed responsibility for the whole family.Wood, 79. To support them and to pay his tuition fees, he daily wrote short, humorous sketches and vignettes of contemporary Russian life, many under pseudonyms such as "Antosha Chekhonte" (Антоша Чехонте) and "Man without a Spleen" (Человек без селезенки). His prodigious output gradually earned him a reputation as a satirical chronicler of Russian street life, and by 1882 he was writing for ''Oskolki'' (''Fragments''), owned by Nikolai Leikin, one of the leading publishers of the time.Rayfield, 91. Chekhov's tone at this stage was harsher than that familiar from his mature fiction."There is in these miniatures an arresting potion of cruelty… The wonderfully compassionate Chekhov was yet to mature." , George Steiner's review of ''The Undiscovered Chekhov'' in ''The Observer'', 13 May 2001. Retrieved 16 February 2007.

In 1884, Chekhov qualified as a physician, which he considered his principal profession though he made little money from it and treated the poor for free.Malcolm, 26. In 1884 and 1885, Chekhov found himself coughing blood, and in 1886 the attacks worsened; but he would not admit tuberculosis to his family and friends, confessing to Leikin, "I am afraid to submit myself to be sounded by my colleagues."Letter to N.A .Leikin, 6 April 1886.  He continued writing for weekly periodicals, earning enough money to move the family into progressively better accommodation. Early in 1886 he was invited to write for one of the most popular papers in St. Petersburg, ''Novoye Vremya'' (''New Times''), owned and edited by the millionaire magnate Alexey Suvorin, who paid per line a rate double Leikin's and allowed him three times the space.Rayfield, 128. Suvorin was to become a lifelong friend, perhaps Chekhov's closest.They only ever fell out once, when Chekhov objected to the anti-Semitic attacks in ''New Times'' against Dreyfus and Zola in 1898. Rayfield, 448–50.In many ways, the right-wing Suvorin, whom Lenin later called "The running dog of the Tzar" (Payne, XXXV), was Chekhov's opposite; "Chekhov had to function like Suvorin's kidney, extracting the businessman's poisons." Wood, 79.

Before long, Chekhov was attracting literary as well as popular attention. The sixty-four-year-old Dmitry Grigorovich, a celebrated Russian writer of the day, wrote to Chekhov after reading his short story ''The Huntsman'',. Retrieved 16 February 2007. "You have ''real'' talent—a talent which places you in the front rank among writers in the new generation." He went on to advise Chekhov to slow down, write less, and concentrate on literary quality.

Chekhov replied that the letter had struck him "like a thunderbolt" and confessed, "I have written my stories the way reporters write up their notes about fires—mechanically, half-consciously, caring nothing about either the reader or myself."Malcolm, 32–3. The admission may have done Chekhov a disservice, since early manuscripts reveal that he often wrote with extreme care, continually revising.Payne, XXIV. Grigorovich's advice nevertheless inspired a more serious, artistic ambition in the twenty-six-year-old. In 1887, with a little string-pulling by Grigorovich, the short story collection ''At Dusk'' (''V Sumerkakh'') won Chekhov the coveted Pushkin Prize "for the best literary production distinguished by high artistic worth."Simmons, 160.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1d9e4dab559047e07feb5066c8bfda86" name="Chekhov_with_brother_1882" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/1d9e4dab559047e07feb5066c8bfda86.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>