<document id="a79133abe3132caf9491427873dc9560-5" name="Jonathan_Wild" cat="14">
<text>
On 15 February Wild and Quilt Arnold were arrested for helping one of his men in a jailbreak.Moore, p. 239. Wild was placed in Newgate, where he continued to attempt to run his business. In the illustration from the ''True Effigy'' (top of page), Wild is pictured in Newgate, still with notebook in hand to account for goods coming in and going out of his office. Evidence was presented against Wild for the violent jailbreak and for having stolen jewels during the previous August's installation of Knights of the Garter.

The public's mood had shifted; they supported the average man and resented authority figures. Wild's trial occurred at the same time as that of the Lord Chancellor, Lord Thomas Parker, 1st Earl of Macclesfield, for taking £100,000 in bribes. With the changing tide, it appeared at last to Wild's gang that their leader would not escape, and they began to come forward. Slowly, gang members began to turn evidence on him, until all of his activities, including his grand scheme of running and then hanging thieves, became known. Additionally, evidence was offered as to Wild's frequent bribery of public officers.

Wild's final trial occurred at the Old Bailey on 15 May.Moore, p. 246.  He was tried on two indictments of privately stealing  of lace from Catherine Statham (a lace-seller who had visited him in prison on 10 March) at Holborn on 22 January.  He was acquitted of the first charge, but with Statham's evidence presented against him on the second charge, he was convicted and sentenced to death. on two charges of theft, 13 May 1725, where Wild's last name is spelled with an "e" at the end.  Retrieved on 30 September 2007.  Terrified, Wild asked for a reprieve but was refused.  He could not eat or go to church, and suffered from insanity and gout.Moore, p. 251.  On the morning of his execution, in fear of death, he attempted suicide by drinking a large dose of laudanum, but because he was weakened by fasting, he vomited violently and sank into a coma that he would not awaken from.Moore, p. 252.

When Wild was taken to the gallows at Tyburn on 24 May 1725, Daniel Defoe said that the crowd was far larger than any they had seen before and that, instead of any celebration or commiseration with the condemned,



Wild's hanging was a great event, and tickets were sold in advance for the best vantage points (see the reproduction of the gallows ticket). Even in a year with a great many macabre spectacles, Wild drew an especially large and boisterous crowd.  Eighteen-year-old Henry Fielding was in attendance. Wild was accompanied by William Sperry and the two Roberts Sanford and Harpham, three of the four prisoners who had been condemned to die with Wild a few days before. of the proceedings of the Old Bailey on 13 May 1725.  Retrieved on 30 September 2007. Because he was heavily drugged, he was the last to die after the three of them, without any difficulty that had happened at Sheppard's execution.Moore, p. 256.

In the dead of night, Wild's body was buried in secret at the churchyard of St Pancras Old Church next to Elizabeth Mann, his third wife and one of his many lovers (who had died in about 1718), as he had wished.Moore, p. 260.. Retrieved on 30 September 2007.Moore, p. 155.  His burial was only temporary. In the 18th century, autopsies and dissections were performed on the most notorious criminals, and consequently Wild's body was exhumed and sold to the Royal College of Surgeons for dissection.  His skeleton remains on public display in the Royal College's Hunterian Museum in Lincoln's Inn Fields.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9452b311c054c041f51f8a88f680255d" name="Wild-tick" sectnum="5#1">../img/9452b311c054c041f51f8a88f680255d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>