<document id="a79133abe3132caf9491427873dc9560-4" name="Jonathan_Wild" cat="14">
<text>
By 1724, London political life was experiencing a crisis of public confidence.  In 1720, the South Sea Bubble had burst, and the public was growing restive about corruption. Authority figures were beginning to be viewed with scepticism.



In late April 1724, the most famous housebreaker of the era, Jack Sheppard, was apprehended by one of Wild's men, James "Hell-and-Fury" Sykes, for a burglary Sheppard had committed in Clare Market on 5 February.Moore, p. 100. Sheppard had worked with Wild in the past, though he had struck out on his own. Consequently, as with other arrests, Wild's interests in saving the public from Sheppard were personal.

Sheppard was imprisoned in St Giles's Roundhouse, but escaped within three hours.Moore, p. 104. On 19 May, Wild again had Sheppard arrested for pickpocketing, and this time he was put in St. Ann's Roundhouse in Soho, where he was visited by Elizabeth "Edgworth Bess" Lyon the next day; she too was locked up with him, and, being recognized as man and wife, they were sent to the New Prison at Clerkenwell. They both escaped on 25 May.Moore, p. 105 In July, Field informed Wild about Sheppard, so Wild sought for Lyon on 22 July and plied her with drinks at Temple Bar until she betrayed Sheppard.Moore, p. 111. 

The following day, Wild sent another one of his men, Quilt Arnold, and had Sheppard arrested a third time and put into Newgate Prison to await trial.Moore, p. 112. On 13 August he was tried on three charges of burglary, but was acquitted of the first two due to lack of evidence.  However, Wild, along with Field and William Kneebone, Sheppard's former master, presented evidence against him on the final charge of the burglary of Kneebone's house on 12 July; and Sheppard was convicted, sentenced to death, and put in the condemned hold of Newgate Prison. on three charges of theft, 12 August 1724, where Sheppard's name is incorrectly recorded as Joseph Sheppard. Retrieved 30 September 2007. 

On the night that the death warrant arrived, 31 August, Sheppard escaped. By this point, Sheppard was a working class hero for apprentices (being a cockney apprentice in love, non-violent, and handsome). On 9 September, Sheppard avoided capture by Wild's men, but he was caught for a fourth time by a posse from Newgate as he hid out on Finchley Common,Moore, p. 209. and Sheppard was placed in the most secure room of Newgate. Further, Sheppard was put in shackles ''and'' chained to the floor. 

Meanwhile, on 9 October, Wild and his men arrested Joseph "Blueskin" Blake, a highwayman and Sheppard's partner-in-crime.Moore, p. 158. On 15 October Blueskin was tried for the same act of burglary committed on 12 July, with Wild, Field, and his men giving evidence.  Their accounts were not consistent with the evidence given at Sheppard's trial, but Blueskin was convicted and sentenced to death anyway. on Blueskin's charge of theft, 14 October 1724.  Retrieved on 30 September 2007.  After the trial, Blueskin pleaded with Wild in the courtroom to have his sentence commuted from hanging to transportation (since he had worked with Wild before), but Wild refused.  Enraged, Blueskin attempted to murder Wild, slashing his throat in the process and causing an uproar, and Wild collapsed and was taken to a surgeon for treatment.Moore, p. 159.

Taking advantage of the disturbance that spread to Newgate next door and continued into the night, Sheppard escaped yet again in early 16 October.Moore, p. 161. Sheppard had broken the chains, padlocks, and six iron-barred doors. This escape astonished everyone, and Daniel Defoe, working as a journalist, wrote an account. In the early morning on 1 November, Sheppard was found for a fifth and final time by a constable and arrested.''The London Journal'', 7 November 1724. Mullan, p. 186. This time, Sheppard was placed in the centre of Newgate, where he could be observed at all times, and loaded with three hundred pounds of iron weights. He was so celebrated that the gaolers charged high society visitors to see him, and James Thornhill painted his portrait.

On 11 November, Blueskin was hanged.''The Daily Journal'', 12 November 1724. Moore, p. 170.  Five days later Sheppard was similarly executed at Tyburn.  Wild missed out on the execution while he was confined to his bed for several weeks and his throat was recovering.Moore, p. 233.

During the pursuit of Sheppard, Wild appeared as much to disadvantage in the press as Sheppard did to advantage. Wild was now despised. When, after his recovery, Wild used violence to perform a jail break for one of his gang members, he was being sought out and went into hiding for several weeks, and returned to business when he thought the affair had blown over.  On 6 February 1725, he was summoned to Leicester house, where he failed to recover a gold watch for one of his attendants because of the jail break and the incident with Blueskin at the Old Bailey. Moore, p. 238.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f945e3aff1b2d137bc173ac68ee7da14" name="Jack_Sheppard_-_Thornhill" sectnum="4#1">../img/f945e3aff1b2d137bc173ac68ee7da14.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>