<document id="a7e16132aa63413b1fa0701b14661080-2.8" name="Josquin_des_Prez" cat="20">
<text>
Josquin wrote towards the end of the period in which the mass was the predominant form of sacred composition in Europe.  The mass, as it had developed through the 15th century, was a long, multi-section form, with opportunities for large-scale structure and organization not possible in the other forms such as the motet.  Josquin wrote some of the most famous examples of the genre, most using some kind of cyclic organization.

He wrote masses using the following general techniques, although there is considerable overlap between techniques in individual compositions:

* cantus firmus mass, in which a pre-existing tune appeared, mostly unchanged, in one voice of the texture, with the other voices being more or less freely composed; 
* paraphrase mass, in which a pre-existing tune was used freely in all voices, and in many variations; 
* parody mass, in which a pre-existing multi-voice song appeared in whole or in part, with material from all voices in use, not just the tune;
* soggetto cavato, or solmization mass, in which the tune is drawn from the syllables of a name or phrase (for example "la sol fa re mi" — A, G, F, D, E — based on the syllables of ''Lascia fare mi'' ("leave me alone", a phrase used by an unknown patron, in a context around which much legend has arisen).
* canon, in which an entire mass is based on canonic techniques, and no pre-existing material has been identified.Blackburn, Planchart, Bloxham, Sherr, in Sherr, 51–248.

Most of these techniques, particularly paraphrase and parody, become standardized during the first half of the 16th century; Josquin was very much a pioneer, and what was perceived as mixing of these techniques by later observers was actually the process by which they were created.  

Josquin was fond of canonic techniques, as were many other composers of his generation, and canon appears in all of his masses, sometimes to the exclusion of other structural devices.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8fc50e532ee78eb5b53e9d72d90e535e" name="Josquin_Missa_BV_Kyrie" sectnum="2.8#1">../img/8fc50e532ee78eb5b53e9d72d90e535e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>