<document id="a8b1b10367a55b3c9316a6fbaa63baaa-6" name="Fanno_Creek" cat="11">
<text>
Fanno Creek passes through or near 14 parks in several jurisdictions. The Portland Parks and Recreation Department manages three: Hillsdale Park,  with picnic tables and a dog park near the headwaters;  Albert Kelly Park,  with unpaved paths, picnic tables, play areas, and Wi-Fi north of the creek about  from the mouth, and the Fanno Creek Natural Area,  north of the creek about  from the mouth. 

THPRD manages seven Fanno Creek parks in Beaverton and unincorporated Washington County. The district, tax-supported and governed by an elected board, is the largest special park and recreation district in Oregon.  The seven include Bauman Park, about  at about  from the mouth. Slightly downstream from Bauman Park are Vista Brook Park, about  with trails including one that is accessible to people with physical handicaps, a playground, and courts for basketball and tennis, and Fanno Creek Trail, about , with picnic tables and trails. Other THPRD parks lie along Fanno Creek from roughly  to roughly  from the mouth. These are Fanno Creek Park, about , with trails including one accessible to people with handicaps; Fanno Farmhouse, about  with an accessible trail and picnic tables as well as the Fanno family home, restored by THPRD and listed on the National Register of Historic Places; Greenway Park, about  with trails including an accessible trail, picnic tables, a playground, and sports fields, and Koll Center Wetlands, about  with wildlife. 

The three Fanno Creek parks managed by the city of Tigard include Woodard Park,  of big trees, trails, and play structures;  Bonita Park, with a playground and picnic areas,  and Fanno Park, a natural area behind City Hall. About 20 percent of the small city of Durham is parkland. Surrounded by the larger cities of Tigard and Tualatin, the city covers  occupied by about 1,400 people. Durham City Park, at the confluence of Fanno Creek and the Tualatin River, consists of  of heavily wooded floodplain with paved trails, children's play areas, and a picnic shelter.

Sections of trail along the main stem of Fanno Creek form part of a planned   Fanno Creek Greenway Trail linking Willamette Park on the Willamette River in southwest Portland to the confluence of the creek with the Tualatin River in Durham. The trail, for pedestrians and bicyclists, is accessible to people with disabilities. Many unfinished segments remained as of 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3339cb9d47f991b85c126b1a2470274f" name="Greenway_Trail_section" sectnum="6#1">../img/3339cb9d47f991b85c126b1a2470274f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>