<document id="a8d02ad8c306be96bf8e882a813784ef-2" name="Swedish_allotment_system" cat="29">
<text>
In the 16th century, the system was changed with regard to both cavalry (1536) and infantry (1544), to provide an army that could be quickly mobilized. This was still done by forced conscription for the infantry, and tax exemptions for those who financed horsemen. The new system gave the conscripted soldiers a means of subsistence between campaigns, by making a whole group of farmers responsible for the keep of each soldier. While the soldiers would be hired and salaried full-time if at war, they lived at home and off duty in peacetime. This meant that it would always be possible to raise a trained army in case of war.



The forced conscription of the foot soldiers was called ''utskrivning'' (literally "writing out"), and was based on a grouping, called a ''rote'' (similar to an English "file" or "ward"; in the eastern parts of the Swedish realm, this became the Finnish ''ruotu''), of ten men from an estate or a few farms, fit for military service and between the ages of 15 and 40. One randomly chosen man from each rote was forced to serve in the province's or county's regiment in case of war.

The organization of the cavalry was based on a slightly different grouping. This grouping was known as a ''rusthåll'' (literally "arm household"), a bigger farm or estate (practically a peasant manor) that could support a horseman with his horse and equipment in exchange for tax exemption. The horseman who volunteered for service was often the estate master himself or a close relative. This option resembled the medieval origin of knighthood but no longer carried the Swedish noble status with it, as the cavalryman was not permanently stationed in war, but was allowed to remain home at peacetime. In particular cases, the estate owner received some taxes from neighbors to augment his own tax exemption: as the burden of a cavalryman with horse and equipment was deemed considerable, compensation needed to be commensurate.

The infantry was organized in units of 525 (later 300) men called a ''landsfänika'' and the cavalry in units of 300 horsemen called a ''landsfana''. Later on, this was changed to a company&mdash;battalion&mdash;regiment organization. The system, used and refined by Gustav Vasa and Gustavus Adolphus, was later to be known as the old allotment system. Many people disliked forced conscription, though, and the peasantry in some provinces soon wrote contracts with the state to provide a certain number of soldiers in exchange for being spared from conscription.

There were a number of reasons for the dislike of the system. First, any of the ten men in each rote could be picked to serve in case of war, which made it hard for the generals to estimate the knowledge and level of practice their soldiers would have. Secondly, the richest of the men in the rote could buy their way out, which in turn sometimes led to the "10th man" being the poorest or weakest in the rote, which of course was not good for the army. The system of forced conscription also often led to desertions.For example, out of 306 forcibly conscripted soldiers in Kronoberg County in 1627, only 60 showed up for the first muster. ''Nelsson, p. 13.''
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5ea5aab976819df21036ad34890b1ae1" name="Gustav_Vasa" sectnum="2#1">../img/5ea5aab976819df21036ad34890b1ae1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>