<document id="a9139b3215d7f5e0c64f9eede7b85bc0-1.1" name="The_Smashing_Pumpkins" cat="20">
<text>
At the age of nineteen, singer and guitarist Billy Corgan left his native city of Chicago and moved to St. Petersburg, Florida with his gothic rock band The Marked. The band had limited success and quickly broke up. Corgan returned to Chicago, taking a job in a record store. While working there, he met guitarist James Iha. Adorning themselves with paisley and other psychedelic trappings, the two began writing songs together (with the aid of a drum machine) that were heavily influenced by The Cure and New Order.Kot, Greg. "Pumpkin Seeds", ''Guitar World''. January 2002. Corgan met bassist D'arcy Wretzky in 1988 after a show by the Dan Reed Network where they argued the merits of the band. After finding out Wretzky played bass, Corgan stated his band's need for a bassist and gave Wretzky his telephone number. Wretzky soon joined the band, and she and Iha later had a short-lived romance."From Fighting to Smashing", ''Washington Post''. November 19, 1993.

The first performance of The Smashing Pumpkins was on July 9, 1988, at the Polish bar Chicago 21. This performance included only Corgan and Iha with a drum machine.Kelly, Christina. "Smashing Pumpkins: The Multi-Platinum Band Is Over the Infighting But Can the Harmony Last?", ''US Weekly''. December 1, 1995 On August 10, 1988, the band played for the first time as a trio at the Avalon Nightclub."Jimmy Chamberlin ", ''Modern Drummer''. January 1994. After this show, Cabaret Metro owner Joe Shanahan agreed to book the band on the condition that they replace the drum machine with a live drummer. Jazz drummer Jimmy Chamberlin was recruited for the band after a recommendation from a friend of Corgan's. Chamberlin was at first an unlikely match, as he knew nothing of alternative rock at the time. As Corgan recalled of the period, "We were completely into the sad-rock, Cure kind of thing. It took about two or three practices before I realized that the power in his playing was something that enabled us to rock harder than we could ever have imagined." On October 5, 1988, the complete band took the stage for the first time at the Cabaret Metro.



In 1989, The Smashing Pumpkins made their first appearance on record with the compilation album ''Light Into Dark'', which featured several Chicago alternative bands. The group released its first record, a limited edition single of "I Am One", in 1990 on local Chicago label Limited Potential. The single sold out and they released another single, "Tristessa", on Sub Pop, after which they signed to Caroline Records.Keedle, Jayne. "Patchin' It Back Together", ''Hartford Advocate''. October 1, 1996. The Smashing Pumpkins recorded their 1991 debut album ''Gish'' with producer Butch Vig at his Smart Studios in Madison, Wisconsin, for $20,000.Kot, Greg. "Out of the Patch for Smashing Pumpkins, New Album Is Another Sign of Liftoff", ''Chicago Tribune''. June 21, 1991. In order to gain the consistency he desired, Corgan often played all instruments save drums, which created tension in the band. The music fused heavy metal guitars, psychedelia and dream pop, garnering them comparisons to Jane's Addiction.Rotondi, James. "Orange Crunch", ''Guitar Player''. January 1996. ''Gish'' became a minor success, with the single "Rhinoceros" receiving some airplay on modern rock radio. After releasing the ''Lull'' EP in October 1991 on Caroline Records, the band formally signed with Virgin Records, which was affiliated with Caroline. The band supported the album with a tour that included opening for bands such as the Red Hot Chili Peppers, Jane's Addiction, and Guns N' Roses. During the tour, Iha and Wretzky went through a messy breakup, Chamberlin became addicted to narcotics and alcohol, and Corgan entered a deep depression,Hilburn, Robert. "Smashing Pumpkins Endures When (and What) Other '90s Bands Couldn't", ''Los Angeles Times''. August 3, 1998 (available ) Retrieved on 2007-03-11. writing some songs for the upcoming album in the parking garage where he lived at the time.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ffddfbf6b67f7d2e3094d503f905d1aa" name="Smashing_pumpkins_1990_promo_cropped" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/ffddfbf6b67f7d2e3094d503f905d1aa.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>