<document id="a9139b3215d7f5e0c64f9eede7b85bc0-3" name="The_Smashing_Pumpkins" cat="20">
<text>
The Smashing Pumpkins have been praised for being "responsible for some of the '90s' most striking and memorable video clips" and for having "approached videos from a completely artistic standpoint rather than mere commercials to sell albums". MTV's 2001 anniversary special ''Testimony: 20 Years of Rock on MTV'' credited the Pumpkins, along with Nine Inch Nails, with treating music videos as an art form during the 1990s. Corgan has said, "We generally resisted the idea of what I call the classic MTV rock video, which is like lots of people jumping around and stuff."Commentary for "Bullet with Butterfly Wings" music video. ''The Smashing Pumpkins 1991–2000: Greatest Hits Video Collection'' (Virgin Records, 2001). The band worked with video directors including Kevin Kerslake ("Cherub Rock"), Samuel Bayer ("Bullet with Butterfly Wings"), and, most frequently, the team of Jonathan Dayton and Valerie Faris ("Rocket", "1979", "Tonight, Tonight", "The End is the Beginning is the End", and "Perfect"). Corgan, who was frequently heavily involved in the conception of the videos, said of Dayton and Faris, "I know my  versions are always darker, and they're always talking me into something a little kinder and gentler."Commentary for "Rocket" music video. ''The Smashing Pumpkins 1991–2000: Greatest Hits Video Collection'' (Virgin Records, 2001). Videos like "Today", "Rocket", and "1979" dealt with images taken from middle American culture, albeit exaggerated. The group's videos so often avoid the literal interpretation of the song lyrics that the video for "Thirty-Three", with images closely related to the words of the song, was created as an intentional stylistic departure.Commentary for "Thirty-Three" music video. ''The Smashing Pumpkins 1991–2000: Greatest Hits Video Collection'' (Virgin Records, 2001).

The band was nominated for several MTV Video Music Awards during the 1990s. In 1996, the group won seven VMAs total for the "1979" and "Tonight, Tonight" videos, including the top award, Video of the Year, for "Tonight, Tonight". The video was also nominated for a Grammy at the 1997 ceremony. Fans reacted with equal fervor. Of the "Tonight, Tonight" video, Corgan remarked, "I don't think we've ever had people react ...  it just seemed to touch a nerve."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4339f281c5be4616541bfcb574e3bb89" name="Smashing_pumpkins_tonight_video_02" sectnum="3#1">../img/4339f281c5be4616541bfcb574e3bb89.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>