<document id="a9139b3215d7f5e0c64f9eede7b85bc0-1.3" name="The_Smashing_Pumpkins" cat="20">
<text>
Corgan worked nonstop over the next year and wrote, according to statements in interviews, about fifty-six songs for the next album.  Following this spell of concentrated creativity, the Pumpkins went back into the studio with producers Flood and Alan Moulder to work on what Corgan described as "''The Wall'' for Generation X",DeRogatis, pp. 46, 80. a comparison with the 1979 Pink Floyd two-LP concept album.

The result was ''Mellon Collie and the Infinite Sadness'', a double album featuring twenty-eight songs and lasting over two hours (the vinyl version of the album contained three records, two extra songs, and an alternate tracklisting). The songs were intended to hang together conceptually as a symbol of the cycle of life and death. Praised by ''Time'' as "the group's most ambitious and accomplished work yet",Farley, Christopher John. "A Journey, Not a Joyride". ''Time''. November 13, 1995. ''Mellon Collie'' debuted at number one on the ''Billboard'' charts in October 1995. Even more successful than ''Siamese Dream'', it was certified nine times platinum in the United States Sales for double albums are counted for each disc, thus 4.5 million copies of the double album package have been certified. and became the best-selling double album of the decade to date."Germ Warfare", ''Newsweek''. October 14, 1996. It also garnered seven 1997 Grammy Award nominations, including Album of the Year. The band won only the Best Hard Rock Performance award, for the album's lead single "Bullet with Butterfly Wings". The album spawned five singles—"Bullet with Butterfly Wings", "1979", "Zero", "Tonight, Tonight", and "Thirty-Three"—of which the first three were certified gold and all but "Zero" entered the Top 40. Many of the remaining songs that did not make it onto ''Mellon Collie'' were released as B-sides to the singles, and were eventually compiled in ''The Aeroplane Flies High'' box set. As a testament to the band's popularity, Virgin Records originally intended to limit the set to 200,000 copies, but produced more after the original run sold out due to overwhelming demand.

In 1996, the Pumpkins embarked on an extended world tour in support of ''Mellon Collie''. Corgan's look during this period—a shaved head, a longsleeve black shirt with the word "Zero" printed on it, and silver pants—became iconic. That year, the band also made a guest appearance in an episode of ''The Simpsons'', "Homerpalooza". With considerable video rotation on MTV, major industry awards, and "Zero" shirts selling in many malls, the Pumpkins were considered one of the most popular bands of the time.Marks, Craig. "Zero Worship", ''Spin''. June 1996.Violanti, Anthony. "Cool in Control Smashing Pumpkins Weathers the Storms of Celebrity", ''Buffalo News''. June 30, 1996. But the year was far from entirely positive for the band. In May, the Smashing Pumpkins played a gig at The Point Theatre in Dublin, Ireland. Despite the band's repeated requests for moshing to stop, a seventeen-year-old fan named Bernadette O'Brien was crushed to death. The concert ended early and the following night's performance in Belfast was cancelled out of respect for her. However, while Corgan maintained that moshing’s “time  come and gone,” the band would continue to request open-floor concerts throughout the rest of the tour.Durando, Stu. "Wary of Injuries and Litigation, Concert Venues Take Extra Precautions to Deal with Moshing", ''St. Louis Post-Dispatch''. July 17, 1996.

The band suffered a personal tragedy on the night of July 11, 1996, when touring keyboardist Jonathan Melvoin and Chamberlin overdosed on heroin in a hotel room in New York City. Melvoin died, and Chamberlin was arrested for drug possession. A few days later, the band announced that Chamberlin had been fired as a result of the incident. The Pumpkins chose to finish the tour, and hired drummer Matt Walker and keyboardist Dennis Flemion. Corgan later said the decision to continue touring was the worst the band had ever made, damaging both their music and their reputation. Meanwhile the band had given interviews since the release of ''Mellon Collie'' stating that it would be the last conventional Pumpkins record,Di Perna, Alan. "Zero Worship", ''Guitar World''. December 1995. and that rock was becoming stale. James Iha said at the end of 1996, "The future is in electronic music. It really seems boring just to play rock music."Graff, Gary. "Smashing Pumpkins—Rave of the Future", ''Guitar World''. December 1996.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="14623c7661a41b843ebd02cda353fc1b" name="Billy_Corgan_pic" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/14623c7661a41b843ebd02cda353fc1b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>