<document id="a9468b7ef6b5ac7c0f257da2e2e3db82-5.1" name="Quiriguá" cat="1">
<text>
There is evidence that Quiriguá was occupied as early as the Late Preclassic (400 BC &ndash; AD 200). Although no structures have been securely dated to this period, a number of Late Preclassic artifacts have been recovered, including 63 figurines and a chert blade. Early Classic ceramics from Quiriguá are similar to finds at both Copán and Chalchuapa in El Salvador, while jade hunchback figurines from the same period resemble those found in central Honduras and in the Guatemalan highlands. These early finds demonstrate the participation of Quiriguá in the wider southeastern Maya region from the Late Preclassic onwards.Looper 2003, p.38.

A combination of hieroglyphic texts from Tikal, Copán and Quiriguá, together with architectural styles and chemical tests of the bones of the founder of the Copán dynasty all suggest that Quiriguá and Copán were founded by elite colonists from the great city of Tikal as a part of its expansion into the southeastern border area of the Maya region.Sharer & Traxler 2006, p.333.Sharer ''et al.'' 2005, p.196.Looper 2003, pp.37–38. The recorded history of Quiriguá starts in 426, in the Early Classic (''c''.200 &ndash; ''c''. 600); according to hieroglyphic inscriptions at other sites, on 5 September of that year K'inich Yax K'uk' Mo' was enthroned as king of Copán.Martin & Grube 2000, p.192. Just three days later he installed "Tok Casper", the first known king of Quiriguá, upon the throne. From this it is evident that right from the beginning of its recorded history Quiriguá was subservient to its southern neighbour, and was founded to bring the lucrative trade route of the Motagua River under the control of Copán and, indirectly, of Tikal. During the next few centuries, about which little is known, the ceremonial architecture at Quiriguá was limited to the hilltop Group A and a broad earthen platform on the valley floor. It is recorded that a stela, as yet unfound, was erected in 455 by Tutuum Yohl K'inich, the second king of Quiriguá.Martin & Grube 2000, p.217. An early monument records the supervision of a ritual in 480 by the then overlord from Copán, demonstrating Quiriguá's continued status as a vassal of that city. A hieroglyphic text dating to 493 mentions two further kings of Quiriguá but interruptions in the text make the reading and decipherment of their names particularly difficult.

There are close parallels between the 5th-century architecture and monuments of Quiriguá and Uaxactun in the northern Petén, a site that fell under the domination of Tikal in the late 4th century. The similarities show that Quiriguá remained strongly aligned with the great Tikal alliance network.Looper 2003, p.50.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1d4af706d21ae366485b62524a936d42" name="QuiriguaStelaDNorth" sectnum="5.1#1">../img/1d4af706d21ae366485b62524a936d42.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>