<document id="a9d9fe90d37d82ea843321c9440b67aa-4.4" name="Amateur_radio_direction_finding" cat="26">
<text>
ARDF transmitters have a low power output and operate in either the two meter or eighty meter amateur radio band. The transmissions are in Morse code. Each transmitter sends a unique identification that can be easily interpreted even by those unfamiliar with the Morse code by counting the number of dits that follow a series of dashes. The transmitters on course all transmit on the same frequency and each transmit in sequence for one minute at a time in a repeating cycle. Within a few meters of each transmitter, an orienteering control flag and punch device will be present. The punch device is either a paper punch with which competitors will mark a special card they carry with them, or an electronic recording device that competitors will use to record their visit on a small magnetic storage device they carry with them. Competitors need to locate the control flag at the transmitter site and use the punch device to record their visit. Good course design will attempt to preclude, as much as possible, runners interfering with the transmitter equipment as they approach the control. At large international or national events, jurors might be present at transmitter controls to ensure fair play.

The IARU rules include detailed technical specifications for transmitter equipment.IARU Region I ARDF Working Group (2005) . Retrieved September 13, 2009. Transmitters for two meters are typically 0.25 to 1 watts power output, and use keyed amplitude modulation. The transmitter antennas used on two meters must be horizontally polarized and omnidirectional. Transmitters for eighty meters are typically one to five watts power output keyed CW modulation. The transmitter antennas used on eighty meters must be vertically polarized and omnidirectional. It is common for the transmitter, a battery, and any controlling hardware to be placed inside a weatherproof container such as an old ammunition case or large plastic food storage container for protection from the elements and wildlife.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7bc76d3974f6b085fcb0c6628d60fc95" name="Ardf_transmitter-2m" sectnum="4.4#1">../img/7bc76d3974f6b085fcb0c6628d60fc95.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>