<document id="aa4f333e8a7c4cc2a34e232c5be41c3f-1.2" name="Hippopotamus" cat="3">
<text>
The most recent theory of the origins of Hippopotamidae suggests that hippos and whales shared a common semi-aquatic ancestor that branched off from other artiodactyls around .  This hypothesized ancestral group likely split into two branches around .  One branch would evolve into cetaceans, possibly beginning about  with the proto-whale ''Pakicetus'' and other early whale ancestors collectively known as Archaeoceti, which eventually underwent aquatic adaptation into the completely aquatic cetaceans.


The other branch became the anthracotheres, a large family of four-legged beasts, the earliest of whom in the late Eocene would have resembled skinny hippopotamuses with comparatively small and narrow heads.  All branches of the anthracotheres, except that which evolved into Hippopotamidae, became extinct during the Pliocene without leaving any descendants.

A rough evolutionary lineage can be traced, however, from Eocene and Oligocene species: ''Anthracotherium'' and ''Elomeryx'' to the Miocene  ''Merycopotamus'' and ''Libycosaurus'' and the very latest anthracotheres in the Pliocene.  ''Merycopotamus'', ''Libycosaurus'' and all hippopotamids can be considered to form a clade, with ''Libycosaurus'' being more closely related to hippos.  Their common ancestor would have lived in the Miocene, about .

Hippopotamids are therefore deeply nested within the family Anthracotheriidae. The Hippopotamidae are believed to have evolved in Africa; the oldest known hippopotamid is the genus ''Kenyapotamus'' which lived in Africa from 16 to . While hippoptamid species spread across Asia and Europe, no hippopotamuses have ever been discovered in the Americas, although various anthracothere genera emigrated into North America during the early Oligocene.  From 7.5 to  an ancestor to the modern hippopotamus, ''Archaeopotamus'', lived in Africa and the Middle East.

While the fossil record of hippos is still poorly understood, the two modern genera, ''Hippopotamus'' and ''Choeropsis'' (sometimes ''Hexaprotodon''), may have diverged as far back as . Taxonomists disagree whether or not the modern Pygmy Hippopotamus is a member of ''Hexaprotodon''—an apparently paraphyletic genus also embracing many extinct Asian hippopotamuses that is more closely related to ''Hippopotamus'', or ''Choeropsis''—an older and basal genus.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d2b4fa4cf7d9f9f6b75d51a17a8698eb" name="Anthracotherium_magnus" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/d2b4fa4cf7d9f9f6b75d51a17a8698eb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>