<document id="aa4f333e8a7c4cc2a34e232c5be41c3f-5.10" name="Hippopotamus" cat="3">
<text>
The Hippopotamus was known to the Greeks and Romans as the Beast of the Nile. A red hippo also represented the Ancient Egyptian god Set; the thigh is the 'phallic leg of set' symbolic of virility. Set's consort Tawaret was also seen as part hippo. The Behemoth from the Book of Job, 40:15–24 is also thought to be based on a hippo.

Ever since Obaysch inspired the Hippopotamus Polka, hippos have been popular animals in western culture for their rotund appearance that many consider comical.  Stories of hippos like Huberta who became a celebrity in South Africa in the 1930s for trekking across the country; or the tale of Owen and Mzee, a hippo and tortoise who developed an intimate bond; have amused people who have bought hippo books, merchandise, and many a stuffed hippo toy. Hippos were mentioned in the novelty Christmas song "I Want a Hippopotamus for Christmas" that became a hit for child star Gayla Peevey in 1953. . They also feature in the songs "The Hippopotamus" and "Hippo Encore" by Flanders and Swann, with the famous refrain ''Mud, Mud, Glorious Mud''.  They even inspired a popular board game, Hungry Hungry Hippos.

Hippos have also been popular cartoon characters, where their rotund frame is used for humorous effect.  The Disney film ''Fantasia'' featured a ballerina hippopotamus dancing to the opera, ''La Gioconda''.  Other cartoon hippos have included Hanna-Barbera's Peter Potamus, the book and TV series ''George and Martha'', Flavio and Marita on the ''Animaniacs'', Pat of the French duo ''Pat et Stanley'', ''The Backyardigan's'' Tasha, and Gloria and Moto-Moto from the ''Madagascar'' franchise.

The hippopotamus characters "Happy Hippos" were created in 1988 by the French designer Andre Roche Andre Roche at . Retrieved on 14 August 2008. based in Munich, to be hidden in the "Kinder Surprise egg" of the Italian chocolate company Ferrero SpA. These characters were not placid like real hippos but rather cute and lively, and had such a success that they reappeared several times in different products of this company in the following years, increasing their popularity worldwide each time. The Nintendo Company published in the years 2001 and 2007 Game Boy adventures of them.

In the game of chess, the hippopotamus lends its name to the Hippopotamus Defense, a solid if unadventurous opening system.

Hippopotamus was one of the many exotic animals brought to fight gladiators in Rome  by  the emperor Philip I the Arab to commemorate Rome's 1000 years anniversary in 250 AD. Silver coins with hippo's image were minted that year.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9dee04499785b6e930a298852c2d3dbe" name="Hippopotamus-polka-early1850s" sectnum="5.10#1">../img/9dee04499785b6e930a298852c2d3dbe.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>