<document id="aa8e11ae071bdc128e827ead9b4c0e68-1.5" name="Wilco" cat="20">
<text>
While waiting for the commercial release of ''Yankee Hotel Foxtrot'', Wilco agreed to support R.E.M. collaborator Scott McCaughey for an album release by The Minus 5. They scheduled a recording session for September 11, 2001, but were distraught about the 9/11 terrorist attacks that day.Kot 2004. p. 220 Later that day, Wilco and McCaughey agreed to "create something good in the world right now" and record some material.Kot 2004. p. 221 Influenced by Bill Fay's ''Time of the Last Persecution'', The Minus 5's ''Down with Wilco'' was released in 2003.Kot 2004. p. 222

In November 2003, Wilco traveled to New York City to record their fifth album. The album was produced by Jim O'Rourke, who mixed ''Foxtrot'' and was a member of Wilco side project Loose Fur. Unlike ''Summerteeth'' and ''Yankee Hotel Foxtrot'', ''A Ghost Is Born'' featured songs that were created with Pro Tools before ever performing them live.Kot 2004. p. 240–1 The album featured the song "Less Than You Think", which included a fifteen-minute track of electronic noises and synthesizers, which Tweedy called "the track that everyone will hate". Tweedy justified the inclusion of the song:



Leroy Bach left the band immediately after the album's completion to join a music theatre operation in Chicago. Like ''Yankee Hotel Foxtrot'', Wilco streamed the album online before its commercial release. Instead of using their own web page, the band streamed it in MPEG-4 form on Apple's website. Last accessed July 23, 2007. Wilco sought to substantially change their lineup after Bach's departure, and added Mikael Jorgensen, who had engineered ''Down with Wilco'', Pat Sansone of The Autumn Defense, and avant-garde guitarist Nels Cline to the lineup.Kot 2004. p. 243 Just as the band was about to tour to promote the album, Tweedy checked himself in to a rehabilitation clinic in Chicago for an addiction to painkillers. As a result, tour plans for Europe were canceled, and the release date for the album was set back several weeks.Kot 2004. p. 244''A Ghost Is Born'' was released on June 22, 2004, and became Wilco's first top ten album in the U.S. Last accessed July 16, 2007. The album earned Wilco Grammy Awards for Best Alternative Music Album and Best Recording Package in 2005. Last accessed July 16, 2007. It also placed thirteenth on 2004's Pazz & Jop Critics Poll. Last accessed July 16, 2007.

In 2004, the band released ''The Wilco Book'', a picture book detailing the creation of ''A Ghost Is Born''. The book also contains writings and drawings from band members, as well as a CD with demos from the ''A Ghost Is Born'' recording sessions. Last accessed July 16, 2007. Also that year, ''Chicago Tribune'' music critic Greg Kot released a biography of the band entitled ''Wilco: Learning How to Die''. The new six-piece Wilco lineup debuted on ''Kicking Television: Live in Chicago'', a two disc live album recorded at The Vic Theater in Chicago. Released on November 15, 2005, the album received high accolades from ''Spin'', ''Billboard'', and ''Entertainment Weekly''. Last accessed July 16, 2007. As of 2007, it has sold over 114,000 copies.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0eb3b2720f930b0073c71c91ef2da9b4" name="Wired_Wilco" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/0eb3b2720f930b0073c71c91ef2da9b4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>