<document id="aa8e11ae071bdc128e827ead9b4c0e68-1.4" name="Wilco" cat="20">
<text>
Shortly after the recording sessions for ''Mermaid Avenue Vol. II'', Wilco purchased a studio in Irving Park, Chicago, which they named the Wilco Loft.Kot 2004. p. 168 The band recorded some tracks in the studio in early 2000 for a fourth studio album. In May 2000, Jeff Tweedy requested to perform with Jim O'Rourke at a festival in Chicago; Tweedy was a fan of O'Rourke's ''Bad Timing''. O'Rourke introduced Tweedy to drummer Glenn Kotche, and the trio enjoyed working together so much that they decided to record an album as a side project named Loose Fur.Kot 2004. p. 177–9 Wilco had recorded an entire album of music at this point, but Tweedy was unhappy with the drum parts. He enjoyed Kotche's contributions to Loose Fur so much that Tweedy brought him into the studio to re-record some demos. Some believe that Tweedy sought to make Wilco sound like Loose Fur after officially replacing Ken Coomer with Kotche in January 2001.Kot 2004. p. 186–8

Although Bennett sought to act as both mixer and engineer for ''Yankee Hotel Foxtrot'', Tweedy was unsure of Bennett's abilities against those of O'Rourke. Tweedy and Bennett frequently argued over whether the album should be accessible to a general listener, or attempt to cover new musical ground.Kot 2004. p. 195–6 Unbeknownst to Bennett, Tweedy invited O'Rourke to remix "I Am Trying to Break Your Heart", and the results impressed the other band members—even Bennett. Tensions grew between Bennett and O'Rourke because Bennett wanted to mix every song on the album. O'Rourke cut the contributions of other members on several of the songs; some songs, such as "Poor Places", only featured the Loose Fur trio.Kot 2004. p. 198–9 The album was completed in 2001, and Bennett was dismissed from the band immediately afterwards. The recording of the album was documented by Sam Jones and released in 2002 as the film ''I Am Trying to Break Your Heart: A Film About Wilco''.

Time Warner, which owned Warner Brothers, merged with America Online in 2001, leading to more pressure on Warner's record labels to cut costs. Over 600 employees of Warner Music Group were fired, including Howie Klein, the president of Reprise Records. In absence of Klein, David Kahne became the interim head of Reprise.Kot 2004. p. 201 Kahne assigned Mio Vukovic to monitor the progress of ''Yankee Hotel Foxtrot'' and to offer suggestions. Music journalist Greg Kot claims that Vukovic disdained the album and was unhappy that Wilco ignored his suggestions.Kot 2004. p. 202 He brought the album to Kahne, who felt that there was no single on the album. In June 2001, the album was rejected by Reprise and Wilco was asked to leave the label.Kot 2004. p. 203

Wilco managed to negotiate terms to a buy-out from Reprise. Music journalist Greg Kot claims that instead of financial compensation, the band agreed to leave the label with the master tapes of ''Yankee Hotel Foxtrot''.Kot 2004, p. 207 The label was already receiving bad publicity for its treatment of the band and were willing to accommodate Wilco's request. Last accessed via the Wayback Machine on July 15, 2007. However, Allmusic claims that Wilco "bought the finished studio tapes from Warner/Reprise for a reported $50,000 and left the label altogether" after Wilco was "nwilling to change the album to make it more 'commercially viable'" allmusic.com To curb the negative publicity, Reprise began to invest more in bands such as The Flaming Lips. Lead singer Wayne Coyne once remarked:Kot 2004. p. 209

We are benefiting from the label's regret over Wilco. We are living in the golden age of that being such a public mistake. The people on Warners said, "we'll never have a band like Wilco feel we don't believe in them again." They'd tell me that it would never happen to us. And what a great day for me!

As the band searched for a new label to release the album, they decided to stream it at their official website to discourage illegal trading of low-quality MP3s.Kot 2004. p. 225–6 The band signed with Nonesuch Records, another Time Warner subsidiary, and the album was released in the spring of 2002. When it was released, ''Yankee Hotel Foxtrot'' reached number thirteen on the ''Billboard'' 200, Wilco's highest chart position to that date. ''Yankee Hotel Foxtrot'' sold over 590,000 copies, and to date remains Wilco's best selling album. Last accessed July 15, 2007. ''Yankee Hotel Foxtrot'' was met with wide critical acclaim: it topped 2002's Pazz & Jop critics' poll, was named one of the 100 greatest albums of all time by ''Q Magazine''. Last accessed July 15, 2007.Levy 2005. p. 216
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f153829683f141ff3344167ec14300cd" name="WilcoYankeeHotelFoxtrot" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/f153829683f141ff3344167ec14300cd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>