<document id="aa8e11ae071bdc128e827ead9b4c0e68-1.3" name="Wilco" cat="20">
<text>
In November 1997, Wilco entered Willie Nelson's recording studio in Spicewood, Texas to record a third studio album.Kot 2004. p. 138 The album was lyrically inspired by the marital problems of Tweedy and his wife, as well as by twentieth-century literature.Kot 2004. p. 135 Tweedy relied heavily on Bennett to provide music for the singer's "bold, but depressing" lyrics.Kot 2004. p. 140–1 Wilco recorded several songs, including "Via Chicago" and "She's a Jar," but began working on another project before assembling the tracks into an album.

Nora Guthrie contacted singer-songwriter Billy Bragg in spring 1995 about recording some unreleased songs by her father, folk singer Woody Guthrie. Most of the songs were written late in Guthrie's life when he was unable to record due to the motor impairments of Huntington's disease. By the 1990s, Woody Guthrie had become a "relic" to the MTV generation, and Nora sought to establish a different legacy for the musician. To Nora, Bragg was "the only singer I knew taking on the same issues as Woody." Bragg was concerned, however, that his fans would not realize that the songs were written by Guthrie when he performed them on tour, so he decided to record the album with another band.Kot 2004. p. 143

Bragg contacted Tweedy and Bennett about co-recording the album while Wilco was on the European segment of their ''Being There'' tour. Bragg was particularly fond of ''Being There'' because their influences extended farther back than the 1950s. Although Tweedy was indifferent to the offer, Bennett was enthused about recording songs of one of his idols—Bennett's previous band Titanic Love Affair was named after a Billy Bragg lyric. A recording contract between Bragg and Wilco was signed after a show at Shepherd's Bush Empire. Bragg mostly recorded the politically-charged lyrics, while Tweedy preferred to record lyrics that showcased Guthrie as a "freak weirdo". The recording of ''Mermaid Avenue'' began on December 12, 1997, and was the topic of BBC's ''Man in the Sand'' documentary film.Kot 2004. p. 144–5

Tempers flared between Bragg and Wilco after the album was completed. Bennett believed that Bragg was overproducing his songs, a sharp contrast to Wilco's sparser contributions. Bennett called Bragg about the possibility of remixing Bragg's songs, to which Bragg responded "you make your record, and I'll make mine, fucker." Eventually Bragg sent copies of his recordings to Chicago for Bennett to remix, but Bragg refused to use the new mixes on the album. The two parties were unable to establish a promotional tour and quarreled over royalties and guest musician fees.

Despite these conflicts, the album was released on June 23, 1998, and sold over 277,000 copies.Kot 2004. p. 151–3 The album received rave reviews from Robert Christgau and ''Rolling Stone'', and was nominated for a Grammy Award for Best Contemporary Folk Album. Last accessed July 14, 2007. Last accessed July 14, 2007. It also placed fourth on the Pazz & Jop critics poll for 1998. Last accessed July 14, 2007. After the album was released, Bob Egan was replaced by multi-instrumentalist Leroy Bach.Kot 2004. p. 169

After the completion of the ''Mermaid Avenue'' sessions, Wilco returned to Spicewood to complete their third studio album, ''Summerteeth''. Unlike previous Wilco and Uncle Tupelo recordings, the album featured a lot of overdubbing with Pro Tools.Kot 2004. p. 154–5 Stirratt and Coomer were concerned with the production, since it reduced their involvement in the music. According to Stirratt:Kot 2004. p. 158

The story of ''Summerteeth'' is Jay bought a Mellotron and he was going to use it, no matter what. It was lovely, but it was overdone. Once they got going on the overdubs, they didn't stop. And nobody in the band stepped up to stop the madness ... It reminds me of ''Heart of Darkness'', where you knowingly extend the creative process for the purpose of exploration or redemption, or whatever it is you're looking for.

During 1999, Warner Brothers was looking to help repay a $16 billion debt acquired during the recent merger of parent company Warner Communications with Time Inc..Kot 2004. p. 161 As a result, Warner's imprints were under pressure to produce musical acts that would yield hit records. The head of Reprise, Howie Klein, who had previously authorized the release of ''Being There'' as a double album, was willing to let Wilco produce ''Summerteeth'' without label input. When Klein played the album for Reprise's A&R department, however, they demanded a radio single for the album. Wilco agreed to do this "once and once only" and recorded a radio-friendly version of "Can't Stand It" at the request of David Kahne, the head of the A&R department.Kot 2004. p. 162–5 The single version of "Can't Stand It" failed to cross over from Triple-A radio to alternative rock stations. Consequently, the album sold only 200,000 copies, significantly less than ''Being There''.Kot 2004. p. 167 This was despite critical acclaim; the album placed eighth on the Pazz & Jop critics' poll for 1999. Last accessed July 15, 2007.

After the release of ''Summerteeth'', the band resumed the ''Mermaid Avenue'' sessions. Although they had recorded enough material for a second release in 1998, Wilco recorded a few new songs for ''Mermaid Avenue Vol. II''. "Someday Some Morning Sometime," featuring a vibraphone filtered through a space echo, was identified by Tweedy as being the "piece to the puzzle" towards the creation of their fourth studio album. The album was released on May 30, 2000, and was the last release from the sessions.Kot 2004. p. 175
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="796699a24d98c4d0f7040c6385f33aa3" name="Woody_Guthrie_2" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/796699a24d98c4d0f7040c6385f33aa3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>