<document id="aa927d147a4db1c3524f0bbde5125a40-3.2" name="Sarah_Trimmer" cat="17">
<text>
Because, in Trimmer's opinion, there was a dearth of good educational material to use in charity schools, she decided to write her own. The series of books she produced between 1786 and 1798 were used in Britain and its colonies well into the nineteenth century. Trimmer was a savvy promoter of her materials; she knew that her books would not reach large numbers of poor children in charity schools unless they were funded and publicized by the SPCK. She wrote in her journal “my scheme without its aid, will fall to the ground".Trimmer, , 296. Thus, she joined the society in 1787. In 1793, she sent twelve copies of her treatise ''Reflections upon the Education in Charity Schools with the Outlines of a Plan Appropriate Instruction for the Children of the Poor'' to the subcommittee that chose the books funded by the organization. In the treatise, she argued that the current charity school curriculum was outdated (it was over 100 years old) and needed to be replaced. She suggested a list of seven books that she herself would write:
:*A Spelling Book in two Parts
:*Scripture Lessons from the Old Testament
:*Scripture Lessons from the New Testament
:*Moral Instructions from the Scriptures
:*Lessons on the Liturgy from the Book of Common Prayer
:*Exemplary Tales
:*The Teacher's Assistant
The committee largely accepted her proposal.Heath, 391–92. The ''Charity School Spelling Book'' was printed first and was the most widely-used. It was one of the first children's books for the poor that was small but still had large type and large margins (features often considered appropriate only for books for more privileged readers). The stories themselves were also innovative: they emphasized the ordinary lives of ordinary children—"these children climbed trees, played with fire, threw cricket bats at sheep and begged in the streets".Heath, 392–93. The book was adopted by Andrew Bell around 1800 for his Madras system of education and by various educational societies throughout Britain and its colonies; it was even used to educate adult slaves in Antigua and Jamaica.

The proposed "Scripture Lessons" became Trimmer's ''An Abridgement of Scripture History, consisting of Lessons selected from the Old Testament, for the Use of Schools and Families'' which was an anthology of selections from the Bible. Like the ''Charity School Spelling Book'', it was adopted throughout the British educational system and was part of school life well into the mid-nineteenth century. In 1798 SPCK published ''Scripture Catechisms, Part I and II''; these works were intended to aid the teacher while the ''Abridgements'' (a short-hand name for the ''Scripture Histories'' of both the Old and New Testament that Trimmer eventually published) were intended to aid the pupil. The "Exemplary Tales" seem not to have been written exactly as planned but Trimmer's ''Servant's Friend'' and ''Two Farmers'' fulfilled the purpose she outlined in her plan of publishing pleasurable moral tales. These two books served as Sunday school prizes as well. ''The Teacher's Assistant'' was an instruction aid and was also widely adopted throughout British schools. The only texts not published by the SPCK were Trimmer's adaptations and commentaries on the ''Book of Common Prayer'', which she had printed elsewhere.Heath, 394–97.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6746eea73023792d8c3b2083992bcf47" name="TrimmerFabulousHistories" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/6746eea73023792d8c3b2083992bcf47.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>