<document id="aab8ba8d49dcab281f97186deaa805a4-1.8" name="Elliott_Smith" cat="20">
<text>
Elliott Smith died on October 21, 2003, at age 34 from two stab wounds to the chest. According to girlfriend Jennifer Chiba—with whom he was living at the time—the two were arguing, and she locked herself in the bathroom to take a shower. Chiba heard him scream, and upon opening the door, saw Smith standing with a knife in his chest. She pulled the knife out, after which he collapsed and she called 9-1-1. Smith died in the hospital with the time of death listed as 1:36 p.m. While Smith's death was originally reported as a suicide, the official autopsy report released in December 2003 left open the question of possible homicide. A possible suicide note, written on a Post-it, read, "I'm so sorry—love, Elliott. God forgive me."

According to Pitchfork Media, record producer Larry Crane reported on his Tape Op message board that he had planned to help Smith mix his album in mid-November. Crane wrote, "I hadn't talked to Elliott in over a year. His girlfriend, Jennifer, called me  and asked if I'd like to come to L.A. and help mix and finish . I said yes, of course, and chatted with Elliott for the first time in ages. It seems surreal that he would call me to finish an album and then a week later kill himself. I talked to Jennifer this morning, who was obviously shattered and in tears, and she said, 'I don't understand, he was so healthy.'"
The coroner's report revealed that no traces of illegal substances or alcohol were found in his system at the time of his death. The coroner did find anti-depressant and attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder medications in his system, but at prescribed levels. With his death not being officially declared a suicide, a journalist noted that some have suspected  foul play, but also that the authorities do not seem to be investigating the case further.


Smith's body was cremated,Find a Grave: . but no information has been provided by his family as to whether his ashes have been scattered or remain intact. No public burial site or memorial was ever formally announced; however, soon after his death a fan memorial was initiated outside of Solutions Audio (4334 Sunset Boulevard, Los Angeles, California), the site at which the cover of the ''Figure 8'' album was shot. Farewell messages to Smith were written on the wall, and flowers, photos, candles, and empty bottles of alcohol mentioned in Smith's songs were left. At one point in 2007, the wall was largely vandalized with unrelated graffiti, to the point where almost all of its original paint had been obscured.LAist article: http://laist.com/2007/08/28/this_is_why_we.php This Is Why We Can't Have Nice Things. Fans of Smith led an effort to repaint the mural,MySpace page: . and by February 28, 2008, the Solutions wall was repaired to its original state, resembling the cover of ''Figure 8''.LAist article: . In turn, the owner of Solutions—re-energized by Smith's fans—announced his ambition to create a statue composed of crushed electronics that would play music by "Elliott's influences". The piece, which is Smith's height (5'7"), is to be placed where the singer stood during the wall's famous photo shoot.

Memorial concerts were held in several cities in the United States and the United Kingdom. A petition was soon put forth with intent to make part of the Silver Lake area a memorial park in Smith's honor. It received over 10,000 signatures, but no plans to establish the park have been announced. A memorial plaque located inside Smith's former high school, Lincoln High, was hung in July 2006.


Since Smith's death, many musical acts have paid him tribute. Songs in tribute to, or about Smith have been released by Rilo Kiley ("Ripchord" and "It Just Is" on ''More Adventurous''), Sparta ("Bombs and Us"), Third Eye Blind ("Elliott Smith" on ''Symphony of Decay''), Mary Lorson ("Lonely Boy" on ''Realistic'' ), Ben Folds ("Late" on ''Songs for Silverman''), Rhett Miller ("The Believer" on ''The Believer''), Earlimart ("Heaven Adores You" on ''Treble and Tremble''), Joan As Police Woman ("We Don't Own It" on ''Real Life''),Tiny Mix Tapes review: "." and Pete Yorn ("Bandstand in the Sky" on ''Nightcrawler'', a song jointly dedicated to Jeff Buckley). Several tribute albums have been released since his death.

On July 30, 2004, Jennifer Chiba filed a lawsuitCalifornia Court of Appeals . against the Smith family for 15% of his earnings (over $1 million), claiming that she and Smith lived as "husband and wife",''Rolling Stone'' article: "". that the singer pledged to take care of her financially for the rest of her life, and that she worked as his manager and agent from around 2000 until his death.Mtv.com article: "". A state labor commissioner ruled her claim as manager to be invalid, as she had worked as an "unlicensed talent agent" under California's Talent Agencies Act. The case made it to the California appellate court in October 2007, but was defeated 2–1; Chiba could potentially appeal the case to the Supreme Court of California.AOL.com article: "".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7f5d08a5abbd72490bcbfb481118f76e" name="Elliott_Smith_Memorial_Wall" sectnum="1.8#1">../img/7f5d08a5abbd72490bcbfb481118f76e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>