<document id="aab8ba8d49dcab281f97186deaa805a4-1.4" name="Elliott_Smith" cat="20">
<text>
In 1995, Smith's self-titled album was released on Kill Rock Stars; the record featured a similar style of recording to ''Roman Candle'', but with hints of growth and experimentation. Though the majority of the album was recorded by Smith alone, friend and The Spinanes vocalist Rebecca Gates sang harmony vocals on "St. Ides Heaven", and Heatmiser guitarist Neil Gust played guitar on "Single File". Several songs made reference to drugs, but Smith explained that he used the theme of drugs as a vehicle for conveying dependence rather than the songs being about drugs specifically.Shutt, 2002, p. 7 Looking back, Smith felt that the album's pervasive mood gave him "a reputation for being a really dark, depressed person," and said that he later made a conscious move toward more diverse moods in his music.

In 1996, filmmaker Jem Cohen recorded Smith playing acoustic songs for the short film ''Lucky Three: An Elliott Smith Portrait''. Two of these songs would appear on his next album—''Either/Or''—another Kill Rock Stars release that came out in 1997 to favorable reviews.  The album found Smith venturing further into full instrumentation, with several songs containing bass guitar, drums, keyboards, and electric guitars, all played by Smith. The album title was derived from the two-volume book of the same name by Danish philosopher Søren Kierkegaard, whose works generally deal with such themes as existential despair, angst, death, and God.

By this time, Smith's already-heavy drinking was now being compounded with use of anti-depressants. At the end of the ''Either/Or'' tour, some of his close friends staged an intervention in Chicago, but it proved ineffective. Shortly after, he relocated from Portland to Brooklyn.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="47e973dd4edf90a302935d047e27dad7" name="Elliott_Smith_live_1997" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/47e973dd4edf90a302935d047e27dad7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>