<document id="aafac65ae06628be791f7d5faa1c4aa3-7.9" name="Hispanic_Americans_in_World_War_II" cat="29">
<text>
Captain Marion Frederic Ramirez de Arellano, (1913–1980) USN, the first Hispanic submarine commanding officer,"The Submarine Forces Diversity Trailblazer - Capt. Marion Frederick Ramirez de Arellano"; Summer 2007 Undersea Warfare magazine; pg.31. participated in five war patrols. He led the effort to rescue five Navy pilots and one enlisted gunner off Wake Island, and contributed to the sinking of two Japanese freighters and damaging a third. For his actions, he was awarded a Silver Star Medal and a Legion of Merit Medal. Association of Naval Services Officers. Retrieved on July 27, 2007.

After a brief stint at the Mare Island Naval Shipyard, he was reassigned to the USS ''Skate'', a ''Balao''-class submarine. He participated in the ''Skate''s first three war patrols and was awarded a second Silver Star Medal for his contribution in sinking the Japanese light cruiser ''Agano'' on his third patrol. The Agano had survived a previous torpedo attack by submarine USS ''Scamp''.

In April 1944, Ramirez de Arellano was named Commanding Officer of the USS ''Balao''. He participated in his ship's war patrols 5, 6 and 7. On July 5, 1944, Ramirez de Arellano led the rescue of three downed Navy pilots in the Palau area. On December 4, 1944, the ''Balao'' departed from Pearl Harbor to patrol in the Yellow Sea. The ''Balao'' engaged and sunk the Japanese cargo ship ''Daigo Maru'' on January 8, 1945. Ramirez de Arellano was awarded a Bronze Star Medal with Combat V and a Letter of Commendation.

Among the Hispanic submarine commanders were Rear Admiral Rafael Celestino Benitez and Captain C. Kenneth Ruiz.

Rear Admiral Rafael Celestino Benitez, USN, was a Lieutenant Commander who saw action aboard submarines and on various occasions weathered depth charge attacks. For his actions, he was awarded the Silver and Bronze Star Medals. Benitez would go on to play an important role in the first American undersea spy mission of the Cold War as commander of the submarine USS ''Cochino'' in what became known as the "Cochino Incident". Retrieved on July 27, 2007.

Captain C. Kenneth Ruiz, USN, was a crew member of the cruiser USS ''Vincennes'' (CA-44), during the Battle of Savo Island. After being rescued at sea and sent to Pearl Harbor, he was invited by Admiral Chester Nimitz to join the Submarine Service. He served with distinction aboard the submarine USS ''Pollack'' and participated in eight war patrols in the hostile waters of the Pacific during WWII.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6cbb21b088f23d065b7d0d2859be3b3b" name="De_Arellano_with_awards_cropped" sectnum="7.9#1">../img/6cbb21b088f23d065b7d0d2859be3b3b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>