<document id="aafac65ae06628be791f7d5faa1c4aa3-3.1" name="Hispanic_Americans_in_World_War_II" cat="29">
<text>
A small detachment of insular troops from Puerto Rico was sent to Cuba in late March as a guard for Batista Field. In 1943, the 65th Infantry was sent to Panama to protect the Pacific and the Atlantic sides of the isthmus and the Panama Canal, critical to oceangoing ships.  An increase in the Puerto Rican induction program was immediately authorized.  Continental troops such as the 762nd Antiaircraft Artillery Gun Battalion, 766th AAA Gun Battalion and the 891st AAA Gun Battalions were replaced by Puerto Ricans in Panama.United States War Department, History of the 762nd Antiaircraft Artillery Gun Battalion; September 15, 1943, to May 31, 1945; Former designation 72d Coast Artillery Regiment; Fort Randolph, Canal Zone; Prepared at Inglewood, California and dated May 31, 1945; Available from the National Archives and Records Administration, Maryland.United States War Department; History of the 891st Antiaircraft Artillery Gun Battalion; September 15, 1943, to February 28, 1945; Former designation First Battalion, 615th CA (AA). Fort Clayton, Canal Zone; Prepared at Inglewood, California and dated May 31, 1945; Available from the National Archives and Records Administration, Maryland. They also replaced troops in the bases on British Islands, to the extent permitted by the availability of trained Puerto Rican units.  The 295th Infantry Regiment followed the 65th Infantry in 1944, departing from San Juan, Puerto Rico to the Panama Canal Zone. 

That same year, the 65th Infantry was sent to North Africa, arriving at Casablanca, where they underwent further training.  By April 29, 1944, the Regiment had landed in Italy and moved on to Corsica.  On September 22, 1944, the 65th Infantry landed in France and was committed to action in the Maritime Alps at Peira Cava.  On December 13, 1944, the 65th Infantry, under the command of Lieutenant Colonel Juan Cesar Cordero Davila, relieved the 2nd Battalion of the 442nd Infantry Regiment, a regiment which was made up of Japanese Americans under the command of Col. Virgil R. Miller, a native of Puerto Rico.

The 3rd Battalion fought against and defeated Germany's 34th Infantry Division's 107th Infantry Regiment. There were 47 battle casualties, including Pvt. Sergio Sanchez-Sanchez and Sergeant Angel Martinez from Sabana Grande, who were the first two Puerto Ricans from the 65th Infantry to be killed in combat action.  On March 18, 1945, the regiment was sent to the District of Mannheim and assigned to military occupation duties after the end of the war. The regiment suffered 23 soldiers killed in action.

In March 1943, Private First Class Joseph (Jose) R. Martinez, member of Patton's Seventh Army, destroyed a German Infantry unit and tank in Tunis by providing heavy artillery fire, saving his platoon from being attacked in the process. He received the Distinguished Service Cross, second to the Medal of Honor, from General George S. Patton, thus becoming the first Puerto Rican recipient of said military decoration. 
Sergeant First Class Agustin Ramos Calero
Sergeant First Class Agustin Ramos Calero, a member of the 65th Infantry who was reassigned to the 3rd U.S. Infantry Division because of his ability to speak and understand English, was one of the most decorated Hispanic soldiers in the European Theater.  Calero was born and raised in Isabela, in the northern region of Puerto Rico.  He joined the U.S. Army in 1941 and was assigned to Puerto Rico's 65th Infantry Regiment at Camp Las Casas in Santurce, where he received training as a rifleman. At the outbreak of World War II, Calero was reassigned to the 3rd U.S. Infantry Division and sent to Europe. 

In 1945, Calero's company engaged in combat against a squad of German soldiers in what is known as the Battle of Colmar Pocket in the vicinity of Colmar, France. Calero attacked the enemy squad, killing 10 and capturing 21 before being wounded. For these actions, he was awarded the Silver Star Medal and nicknamed "One-Man Army" by his comrades. Calero was wounded four times during combat in Europe.  He was awarded 22 decorations and medals for his actions, making him one of the most decorated Hispanic soldiers in the U.S. military during World War II. Among his many decorations were the Silver Star Medal, four Purple Hearts and the French Croix de Guerre.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7bf81343846511ff111f3d5e5e09ae5c" name="PRWWII_" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/7bf81343846511ff111f3d5e5e09ae5c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>