<document id="aafac65ae06628be791f7d5faa1c4aa3-8.12" name="Hispanic_Americans_in_World_War_II" cat="29">
<text>
In the mid-West town of Silvis, Illinois, the former Second Street is now known as Hero Street USA. The muddy block and a half long street was home to Mexican immigrants who worked the railroads. The 22 families who lived on the street were a close-knit group. From this small street, 84 men served in World War II, Korea, and Vietnam. The street contributed more men to military services in World War II and Korea than any other street of comparable size in the U.S. In total, eight men from Hero Street gave their lives during World War II—Joseph Gomez, Peter Macias, Johnny Muños, Tony Pompa, Frank Sandoval, Joseph “Joe” Sandoval, William “Bill” Sandoval and Claro Soliz. Second Street's name was changed to Hero Street in honor of these men and their families. The Hero Street Monument Committee. Retrieved on July 27, 2007.

Of the 22 families on Second Street, the two Sandoval families had a total of thirteen men who served in the armed forces. Three died in service during World War II. The Sandovals were two families of Mexican immigrants, with the same surname, who settled in the town of Silvis, Illinois and lived on Second Street.. U.S. Navy's Military Sealift Command. September 2004. Retrieved on July 27, 2007.


Edubigis and Angelina Sandoval immigrated to the U.S. from Mexico. When the news reached Silvis that the Japanese had attacked Pearl Harbor, two of the Sandoval sons, Joe and Frank, joined the U.S. Army. Joe was sent to combat in Africa, the Middle East and Europe with the 41st Armored Infantry Division. Frank was assigned to the 209 Combat Engineering Battalion and served in the Pacific. Frank was the first of the Sandovals to die and Joe followed a year later.

Joseph and Carmen Sandoval also immigrated to the United States from Mexico. When the war broke out, their son Bill asked for permission to enlist in the Army and both parents consented to their son's request. Bill Sandoval was trained as a paratrooper and was assigned to the 82nd Airborne Division. He was killed during a combat mission on October 6, 1944.

Other families like the Sandovals had multiple members join the Armed Forces. The Banuelo family, originally from Mexico and who resided in Los Angeles, California, the Garcia family from Los Angeles, California, and the Mora family from Laredo, Texas, each had six siblings who served in the military during the war. The Nevarez family, from Los Angeles, California, had a total of eight siblings serving in the Armed Forces.''Undaunted Courage Mexican American Patriots Of World War II'' (2005). Latino Advocates for Education, Inc.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b801476b4e887668b35d8daf01fa5d2a" name="PurpleHeart" sectnum="8.12#1">../img/b801476b4e887668b35d8daf01fa5d2a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>