<document id="ab9bb925d3e927e749fa1b54e2bf79e8-2.1" name="Clements_Markham" cat="14">
<text>
In May 1844 Markham was introduced by his aunt, the Countess of Mansfield, to Rear-Admiral Sir George Seymour, a Lord of the Admiralty. The boy made a favourable impression on the admiral, and the meeting led to the offer of a cadetship in the Royal Navy. Accordingly, on 28 June 1844 Markham travelled to Portsmouth and  joined Seymour's flagship HMS ''Collingwood'' a few days later.  ''Collingwood'' was being fitted out for an extended voyage to the Pacific Ocean where Seymour was to assume command of the Pacific station.A. Markham, pp. 17–26 This voyage lasted for almost four years. Markham's social connections evidently assured him of a relatively comfortable time; it is reported that he was frequently invited to dine with the admiral, whose wife and daughters were  aboard.A. Markham, pp. 28–35 The ship reached the Chilean port of Valparaíso, the headquarters of the Pacific station, on 15 December after a cruise that incorporated visits to Rio de Janeiro and the Falkland Islands, and a stormy  passage in the Southern Ocean.

After a few weeks' respite ''Collingwood'' sailed again, this time for Callao, the main port on the Peruvian coast, giving Markham his first experience of a country that would  figure prominently in his later career.A. Markham, pp. 38–47 During the next two years ''Collingwood'' cruised in the Pacific, visiting the Sandwich Islands (Hawaii),  Mexico, and Tahiti,  where Markham attempted to assist the nationalist rebels against their  French governor.A. Markham, pp. 64–69 He experienced his first taste of naval discipline when he was punished for impertinence to a naval instructor; he was made to stand on deck from eight in the morning until sunset.A. Markham, pp. 49–51 On 25 June 1846 Markham passed the examination for midshipman, being placed third in a group of ten. The long periods spent in Chilean and Peruvian ports had also enabled him to learn Spanish.

Towards the end of the voyage Markham's aspirations evidently changed from those of a conventional naval career. He now desired above all to be an explorer and a geographer, carrying these thoughts with him on the voyage home. On arrival in Portsmouth in July 1848 he informed his father of his wish to leave the navy, but was persuaded by him to stay.A. Markham, pp. 97–99 After a brief period of service in the Mediterranean Markham experienced months of inactivity while based at Spithead and the Cove of Cork, which further diminished his interest in the service.A. Markham, p. 106 However, early in 1850 he learned that a squadron of four ships was being assembled to undertake a new search for the lost Arctic expedition of Sir John Franklin.Coleman, p. 51 Markham used his family's influence to secure a place in this venture, and on 1 April 1850 was informed of his appointment to HMS ''Assistance'', one of the squadron's two principal vessels.A. Markham, pp. 108–09
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="42d4603f44059664ecd3ee01dd4461e2" name="CadetMarkham" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/42d4603f44059664ecd3ee01dd4461e2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>