<document id="ab9bb925d3e927e749fa1b54e2bf79e8-5.9" name="Clements_Markham" cat="14">
<text>
In May 1888 Markham resigned from his position as RGS Secretary, finding himself at odds with the Society's new policies which appeared to favour education over exploration.Jones, p. 38 He was awarded the Society's Founder's Medal, "in acknowledgement of the value of his numerous achievements to geographic literature ... on his retirement from the secretaryship after 25 years' service."

The next few years were filled with travel and writing. There were further cruises with the training squadron, and extended visits to the Baltic and the Mediterranean. In 1893, during the course of one of these journeys, Markham was elected ''in absentia'' President of the Royal Geographical Society. This unexpected elevation was the result of a dispute within the Society over the question of women members, about which Markham had kept silent. When in July 1893 the issue was put to a special general meeting, the proposal to admit women was narrowly defeated despite an overwhelming postal ballot in favour. In these circumstances the Society's President, Sir Mountstuart Elphinstone Grant Duff, resigned his office. The 22 existing women members were allowed to remain, but no more were admitted until January 1913 when the RGS changed its policy. Although Markham was not the first choice as a replacement—other notable figures were approached—he had kept out of the women members controversy and was broadly acceptable to the membership. Jones, pp. 51–56 Shortly after his accession to the presidency, in recognition of his services to geography Markham was raised in the Order of the Bath to the rank of Knight Commander (KCB), and became Sir Clements Markham.

In a letter written many years later, Markham said that on the assumption of the presidency he had felt the need, after the dispute over women, to "restore the Society's good name"  by the adoption of some great enterprise.  He chose Antarctic exploration as the basis for this mission;Jones, p. 57 there had been no significant Antarctic exploration since Sir James Clark Ross's expedition fifty years previously.Coleman, p. 239 A new impetus was provided through a lecture given to the RGS in 1893  by the oceanographer Professor John Murray, calling for "an expedition to resolve the outstanding questions still posed in the south."Crane, p. 75  In response to Murray the RGS and the Royal Society formed a joint committee, to campaign for a British Antarctic expedition. Markham devoted his entire presidency to the furtherance of this cause.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="68466220d9de684d4d49dab07291e92d" name="ClementsRMarkham_geographer" sectnum="5.9#1">../img/68466220d9de684d4d49dab07291e92d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>