<document id="ab9bb925d3e927e749fa1b54e2bf79e8-3.3" name="Clements_Markham" cat="14">
<text>
In the summer of 1852, freed from his naval obligations, Markham made plans for an extended visit to Peru. Supported by a gift from his father of £500 (more than £40,000 at 2008 values) to cover expenses, Markham sailed from Liverpool on 20 August.

Markham travelled by a roundabout route, proceeding first to Halifax, Nova Scotia, then overland to Boston and New York, before taking a steamer to Panama. After crossing the isthmus he sailed for Callao, finally arriving there on 16 October. He set out for the Peruvian interior on 7 December 1852, heading across the Andes towards his goal, the ancient Inca city of Cuzco.A. Markham, pp. 132–37  On the way, Markham paused for nearly a month in the town of Ayacucho, to study the local culture and increase his knowledge of the Quechua. He then travelled on towards Cuzco, and after crossing a swinging bridge suspended  above the raging Apurímac River, he and his party passed through fertile valleys which brought them finally to the city of Cuzco, on 20 March 1853.A. Markham, pp. 147–52

Markham remained in the city for several weeks, researching Inca history, describing in his journal the many buildings and ruins that he visited.  During the course of an excursion to nearby towns and ruins he reached the area of San Miguel, where he first learned of the properties of the cinchona plant, a source of quinine, cultivated in that vicinity.A. Markham, p. 158  He finally left Cuzco on 18 May, accompanied by a party of six who, like him, were returning to Lima. Their journey took them southwards, descending the mountains to the city of Arequipa which would later be described as "an outstanding example of a colonial settlement" with its mixture of native and European architecture. The city is overlooked by the conical volcano Mount Misti, which Markham likened to Mount Fuji in Japan. On 23 June the party reached Lima, where Markham learned of the death of his father. He departed immediately for England, where he arrived on 17 September.A. Markham, pp. 159–63
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="171a98f4722267176bd0fe81f8980074" name="Arequipa" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/171a98f4722267176bd0fe81f8980074.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>