<document id="ab9bb925d3e927e749fa1b54e2bf79e8-2.2" name="Clements_Markham" cat="14">
<text>
Sir John Franklin had left England in May 1845 with two ships, HMS ''Erebus'' and HMS ''Terror'', in  search of the Northwest Passage. The expedition was last seen on 29 July by whalers in the northern waters of Baffin Bay, moored to an ice floe and waiting for the chance to continue westward.Coleman, p. 19 

The hunt for the missing ships began two years later. The relief squadron which Markham joined was commanded by Captain Horatio Austin in HMS ''Resolute''. Markham's ship ''Assistance'' was captained by Erasmus Ommanney.Coleman, pp. 51–52 Markham, as the youngest member of the expedition and its only midshipman, had a limited role, but carefully noted every detail of expedition life in his journal. The ships sailed on 4 May 1850.A. Markham, p. 119

After rounding the southernmost point of Greenland on 28 May, the squadron proceeded northwards until stopped by ice in Melville Bay on 25 June.Coleman, pp. 54–58 They were held here until 18 August, when they were finally able to proceed west into Lancaster Sound, the known route taken by Franklin. Here the ships dispersed to search different areas for signs of the vanished expedition. On 23 August Ommanney sighted a cairn, and discovered packing materials nearby which bore the name of "Goldner", Franklin's canned meat supplier. Together with other odds and ends of abandoned equipment, these fragments were the first traces of Franklin that anyone had found. A few days later, on Beechey Island, the party came across three graves, which proved to be those of members of Franklin's crew who had died between January and April 1846. 

Searches continued until the ships were laid up for the long Arctic winter. The chief work during the ensuing months was detailed preparation for the spring sledging season. There were lectures and classes for the crew, and  various theatrical diversions in which Markham was able to display his "great histrionic talent". He  did much reading, mainly Arctic history and classical literature, and thought about a possible return visit to Peru, a country which had captivated him during the ''Collingwood'' voyage.A. Markham, pp. 119–23 When spring returned, a series of sledging expeditions was launched to search for further signs of the missing crews. Markham played a full part in these activities,Described by Clements Markham in ''The Lands of Silence'', pp. 255–60 which produced no further evidence of Franklin, but led to the mapping of hundreds of miles of previously uncharted coast.Coleman, pp. 63–68 The expedition returned to England in early October 1851.Coleman, p. 73

Immediately on his return to England Markham informed his father of his determination to leave the navy. One of the main reasons for his disaffection  appears to have been the severity of the corporal punishment that was constantly administered for what in his view were trivial offences. He had been in  trouble during his ''Collingwood'' service for attempting to prevent the flogging of a crewman. He had also become disenchanted by the idleness that had occupied long periods of his service. With some regret the elder Markham consented to his son's request, and after taking and passing the gunnery part of the examination for the rank of lieutenant, Markham resigned the service at the end of 1851.A. Markham, pp. 127–31
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="77f3507c5e8eb4c36a85398fbde340b5" name="BeecheyIsland_Graves" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/77f3507c5e8eb4c36a85398fbde340b5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>