<document id="ab9bb925d3e927e749fa1b54e2bf79e8-5.8" name="Clements_Markham" cat="14">
<text>
In November 1854 Markham had been elected a Fellow of the Royal Geographical Society.  The Society soon became the centre of his geographical interests, and in 1863 he was appointed its honorary secretary, a position he was to hold for 25 years.

In addition to his work in promoting the Nares Arctic expedition,  Markham followed the work of other Arctic explorers, organising a reception in 1880 for the Swedish explorer Adolf Erik Nordenskiöld after the latter's successful navigation of the North-East Passage, and monitoring the progress of the American expeditions of  Adolphus Greely and George Washington De Long. Release from the India Office provided Markham with more time for travel. He made regular trips to Europe and in 1885 went to America, where he met with President Grover Cleveland in the White House. Throughout his secretaryship Markham was a prolific writer of travel books and biographies, and of many papers presented to the RGS and elsewhere. He was the author of the ''Encyclopædia Britannica'' (ninth edition) article entitled "Progress of Geographical Discovery". He also wrote popular histories.  Within the RGS Markham was responsible for the revision of the Society's standard ''Hints to Travellers'', and for relaunching the journal ''Proceedings of the Royal Geographical Society'' in a much livelier format.Jones, pp. 33–36

In parallel with his RGS duties Markham served as secretary of the Hakluyt Society until 1886, subsequently becoming that society's president. As part of his work for this body, Markham was responsible for many translations from Spanish into English of rare accounts of travel, in particular those relating to Peru. In time scholars would express doubts about the quality of some of these translations, finding them prepared in haste and lacking in rigor. Nevertheless this work ran to 22 volumes in the society's publications. In 1873 Markham had been elected a Fellow of the Royal Society, and in subsequent years received several overseas honours, including the Portuguese Order of Christ and the Order of the Rose of Brazil. He  briefly considered, but did not pursue, the idea of a parliamentary career.A. Markham, pp. 267–68

Markham maintained his interest in the navy, particularly in the training of its officers. He often visited the merchant officer training vessels, HMS ''Conway'' and HMS ''Worcester'', and became a member of the latter's governing body. In early 1887 he accepted an invitation from his cousin Albert Markham, who now commanded the Royal Navy's training squadron, to join the squadron at its station in the West Indies. Markham spent three months aboard the flagship HMS '' Active'', during which, on 1 March 1887, he had his first encounter with Robert Falcon Scott, who was serving as a midshipman aboard HMS ''Rover''. Scott was victorious in a race between cutters, an event that was noted and remembered by Markham.Crane, p. 82
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a38eee091657b0e3291b565365de3c69" name="CRMarkham25" sectnum="5.8#1">../img/a38eee091657b0e3291b565365de3c69.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>