<document id="abf3429b71ec0b04b9957b091f9d90b2-3.6.7" name="SMS_Seydlitz" cat="29">
<text>
Almost immediately after the Lowestoft raid, Admiral Reinhard Scheer began planning another foray into the North Sea. He had initially intended to launch the operation in mid-May, but the mine damage to ''Seydlitz'' had proved difficult to repair&mdash;Scheer was unwilling to embark on a major raid without his battlecruiser forces at full strength. On May 22, the Wilhelmshaven dockyard reported the ship to be fit for duty, but tests carried out that night showed that the broadside torpedo flat that had been damaged by the mine was still not watertight, and there were still leaks in the fore and aft transverse bulkheads. Further repairs were necessary, and so the operation was postponed another week, by which time the Wilhelmshaven dockyard assured Scheer that the ship would be ready.Tarrant, p. 58 At noon on 28 May, the repairs to ''Seydlitz'' were finally completed, and the ship returned to the I Scouting Group.Tarrant, p. 62

On the night of 30 May 1916, ''Seydlitz'' and the other four battlecruisers of the I Scouting Group lay in anchor in the Jade roadstead. The following morning, at 02:00 CET,It should be noted that the times mentioned in this section are in CET, which is congruent with the German perspective. This is one hour ahead of GMT, the time zone commonly used in British works. the ships slowly steamed out towards the Skagerrak at a speed of . By this time, Hipper had transferred his flag from ''Seydlitz'' to the newer battlecruiser ''Lützow''. ''Seydlitz'' took her place in the center of the line, to the rear of ''Derfflinger'' and ahead of ''Moltke''. The II Scouting Group, consisting of the light cruisers , Rear Admiral Bödicker's flagship, , , and , and 30 torpedo boats of the II, VI, and IX Flotillas, accompanied Hipper's battlecruisers. 

An hour and a half later, the High Seas Fleet under the command of Admiral Scheer left the Jade; the force was composed of 16 dreadnoughts. was in dock at the time. The High Seas Fleet was accompanied by the IV Scouting Group, composed of the light cruisers , , , , and , and 31 torpedo boats of the I, III, V, and VII Flotillas, led by the light cruiser ''Rostock''. The six pre-dreadnoughts of the II Battle Squadron had departed from the Elbe roads at 02:45, and rendezvoused with the battle fleet at 5:00.

Shortly before 16:00, Hipper's force encountered Vice Admiral Beatty's battlecruiser squadron. The German ships were the first to open fire, at a range of approximately .Bennett, p. 183 The British rangefinders had misread the range to their German targets, and so the first salvos fired by the British ships fell a mile past the German battlecruisers. As the two lines of battlecruisers deployed to engage each other, ''Seydlitz'' began to duel with her opposite in the British line, .Tarrant, p. 90 By 16:54, the range between the ships decreased to , which enabled ''Seydlitz''s secondary battery to enter the fray. She was close enough to the ships of the British 9th and 10th Destroyer Flotillas that her secondary guns could effectively engage them. The other four German battlecruisers employed their secondary battery against the British battlecruisers.Tarrant, p. 92

Between 16:55 and 16:57, ''Seydlitz'' was struck by two heavy caliber shells from ''Queen Mary''. The first shell penetrated the side of the ship five feet above the main battery deck, and caused a number of small fires. The second shell penetrated the barbette of the aft superfiring turret. Four propellant charges were ignited in the working chamber; the resulting fire flashed up into the turret and down to the magazine. The anti-flash precautions that had been put in place after the explosion at Dogger Bank prevented any further propellant explosions. Regardless, the turret was destroyed and most of the gun crew had been killed in the blaze.Tarrant, pp. 92&ndash;93

alt=A large warship is almost completely obscured by a huge column of smoke.
By 17:25, the British battlecruisers were taking a severe battering from their German opponents.  had been destroyed by a salvo from ''Von der Tann'' approximately 20 minutes before, and Beatty sought to turn his ships away by 2 degrees in order to regroup, while the s of the 5th Battle Squadron arrived on the scene and provided covering fire. As the British battlecruisers began to turn away, ''Seydlitz'' and ''Derfflinger'' were able to concentrate their fire on ''Queen Mary''. Witnesses reported at least 5 shells from two salvos hit the ship, which caused an intense explosion that ripped the ''Queen Mary'' in half.Tarrant, pp. 100&ndash;101 Shortly after the destruction of ''Queen Mary'', both British and German destroyers attempted to make torpedo attacks on the opposing lines. One British torpedo struck ''Seydlitz'' at 17:57. The torpedo hit the ship directly below the fore turret, slightly aft of where she had been mined the month before. The explosion tore a hole 40 feet long by 13 feet wide (12 m × 4.0 m), and caused a slight list. Despite the damage, the ship was still able to maintain her top speed, and kept position in the line.Tarrant, p. 113

The leading ships of the German battle fleet had by 18:00 come within effective range of the British ships, and had begun trading shots with the British battlecruisers and ''Queen Elizabeth''-class battleships. Between 18:09 and 18:19, ''Seydlitz'' was hit by a  shell from either  or .Tarrant, p. 118 This shell struck the face of the port wing turret and disabled the guns. A second 380 mm shell penetrated the already disabled aft superfiring turret and detonated the cordite charges that had not already burned. The ship also had two of her 150 mm guns disabled from British gunfire, and the rear turret lost its right-hand gun.Tarrant, p. 119

As the evening wore on, visibility steadily decreased for the German ships. ''Seydlitz''s commander, ''Kapitän zur See'' von Egidy, later remarked: 

"Visibility had generally become unfavorable. There was a dense mist, so that as a rule only the flashes of the enemy's guns, but not the ships themselves, could be seen. Our distance had been reduced from 18,000  to 13,000 yards. From north-west to north-east we had before us a hostile line firing its guns, though in the mist we could only glimpse the flashes from time to time. It was a mighty and terrible spectacle."Tarrant, p. 122

At around 19:00, Beatty's forces were nearing the main body of the Grand Fleet, and to delay the discovery of the Grand Fleet's location by the German fleet, he turned his ships towards the German line, in order to force them to turn as well. This reduced the distance between the British and German battlecruisers from . Visibility continued to favor the British, and the German battlecruisers paid the price. Over the next several minutes, ''Seydlitz'' was hit six times, primarily on the forward section of the ship. A fire started under the ship's forecastle. The smothering fire from Beatty's ships forced Hipper to temporarily withdraw his battlecruisers to the southwest.Tarrant, p. 126 As the ships withdrew, ''Seydlitz'' began taking on more water, and the list to starboard worsened. The ship was thoroughly flooded above the middle deck in the fore compartments, and had nearly lost all buoyancy.Tarrant, p. 137

By 19:30, the High Seas Fleet, which was by that point pursuing the British battlecruisers, had not yet encountered the Grand Fleet. Scheer had been considering retiring his forces before darkness exposed his ships to torpedo boat attack.Tarrant, p. 150 He had not yet made a decision when his leading battleships encountered the main body of the Grand Fleet. This development made it impossible for Scheer to retreat, for doing so would have sacrificed the slower pre-dreadnought battleships of the II Battle Squadron, while using his dreadnoughts and battlecruisers to cover their retreat would have subjected his strongest ships to overwhelming British fire.Tarrant, p. 152 Instead, Scheer ordered his ships to turn 16 points to starboard, which would bring the pre-dreadnoughts to the relative safety of the disengaged side of the German battle line.Tarrant, pp. 152&ndash;153

''Seydlitz'' and the other battlecruisers followed the move,With the exception of ''Lützow'', which had lost speed and was unable to keep up. which put them astern of ''König''.Tarrant, pp. 155&ndash;156 Hipper's badly battered ships gained a temporary moment of respite, and uncertainty over the exact location and course of Scheer's ships led Admiral Jellicoe to turn his ships eastward, towards what he thought was the likely path of the German retreat.Tarrant, p. 163 The German fleet was instead sailing west, but Scheer ordered a second 16-point turn, which reversed course and pointed his ships at the center of the British fleet.Tarrant, p. 165 The German fleet came under intense fire from the British line, and Scheer sent ''Seydlitz'', ''Von der Tann'', ''Moltke'', and ''Derfflinger'' at high speed towards the British fleet, in an attempt to disrupt their formation and gain time for his main force to retreat.Tarrant, p. 173 By 20:17, the German battlecruisers had closed to within  of , at which point Scheer directed the ships to engage the lead ship of the British line.Tarrant, p. 179 ''Seydlitz'' managed to hit ''Colossus'' once, but caused only minor damage to the ship's superstructure.Tarrant, p. 170 Three minutes later, the German battlecruisers turned in retreat, covered by a torpedo boat attack.Tarrant, p. 181

alt=A large gray warship, heavily flooded, it's deck is nearly submerged. Thick black smoke pours from the funnels. An in-photo caption reads: "Seydlitz nach Skaggerak-schlacht", or "Seydlitz after the Skaggerack battle."
A pause in the battle at dusk allowed ''Seydlitz'' and the other German battlecruisers to cut away wreckage that interfered with the main guns, extinguish fires, repair the fire control and signal equipment, and ready the searchlights for nighttime action.Tarrant, p. 188 During this period, the German fleet reorganized into a well-ordered formation in reverse order, when the German light forces encountered the British screen shortly after 21:00. The renewed gunfire gained Beatty's attention, so he turned his battlecruisers westward. At 21:09, he sighted the German battlecruisers, and drew to within  before opening fire at 20:20.Tarrant, p. 193 In the ensuing melee, ''Seydlitz'' was hit several times; one shell struck the rear gun turret and other hit the ship's bridge. The entire bridge crew was killed and several men in the conning tower were wounded.Tarrant, p. 194 The German ships returned fire with every gun available, and at 21:32 hit both ''Lion'' and ''Princess Royal'' in the darkness.Tarrant, p. 195 The maneuvering of the German battlecruisers forced the leading I Battle Squadron to turn westward to avoid collision. This brought the pre-dreadnoughts of the II Battle Squadron directly behind the battlecruisers, and prevented the British ships from pursuing the German battlecruisers when they turned southward. The British battlecruisers opened fire on the old battleships; the German ships turned southwest to bring all of their guns to bear against the British ships.

By 22:15, Hipper was finally able to transfer to ''Moltke'', and then ordered his ships to steam at  towards the head of the German line.Tarrant, p. 213 Only ''Seydlitz'' and ''Moltke'' were in condition to comply; ''Derfflinger'' and ''Von der Tann'' could make at most , and so these ships lagged behind. ''Seydlitz'' and ''Moltke'' were in the process of steaming to the front of the line when the ships passed close to ''Stettin'', which forced the ship to drastically slow down to avoid collision. This forced ''Frauenlob'', ''Stuttgart'', and ''München'' to turn to port, which led them into contact with the 2nd Light Cruiser Squadron; at a range of , the cruisers on both sides pummeled each other. Rear Admiral Ludwig von Reuter decided to attempt to lure the British cruisers towards ''Moltke'' and ''Seydlitz''. Nearly simultaneously, the heavily damaged British cruisers broke off the attack.Tarrant, pp. 213&ndash;214 As the light cruisers were disengaging, a torpedo fired by  struck ''Frauenlob'', and the ship exploded.Tarrant, p. 214 The German formation fell into disarray, and in the confusion, ''Seydlitz'' lost sight of ''Moltke''. The ship was no longer able to keep up with ''Moltke''s 22 knots, and so detached herself to proceed to the Horns Reef lighthouse independently.

At 00:45, ''Seydlitz'' was attempting to thread her way through the British fleet, but was sighted by the dreadnought  and noted as a "ship or Destroyer". ''Agincourt''s captain did not want to risk giving away his ship's position, and so allowed her to pass.Battle of Jutland: Official Despatches, p. 93 By 01:12, ''Seydlitz'' had managed to slip through the British fleet, and she was able to head for the safety of Horns Reef.Tarrant, p. 217 At approximately 03:40, she scraped over Horns Reef. Both of the ship's gyro-compasses had failed, so the light cruiser  was sent to guide the ship home. By 15:30 on 1 June, ''Seydlitz'' was in critical condition; the bow was nearly completely submerged, and the only buoyancy that remained in the forward section of the ship was the broadside torpedo room. Preparations were being made to evacuate the wounded crew when a pair of pump steamers arrived on the scene. The ships were able to stabilize ''Seydlitz''s flooding, and the ship managed to limp back to port. She reached the outer Jade river on the morning of 2 June, and on 3 June the ship entered Entrance III of the Wilhelmshaven Lock. At most, ''Seydlitz'' had been flooded by  of water.Staff, p. 33


Close to the end of the battle, at 03:55, Hipper transmitted a report to Admiral Scheer informing him of the tremendous damage his ships had suffered. By that time, ''Derfflinger'' and ''Von der Tann'' each had only two guns in operation, ''Moltke'' was flooded with 1,000 tons of water, and ''Seydlitz'' was severely damaged.Tarrant, p. 255 Hipper reported: "I Scouting Group was therefore no longer of any value for a serious engagement, and was consequently directed to return to harbor by the Commander-in-Chief, while he himself determined to await developments off Horns Reef with the battlefleet."

During the course of the battle, ''Seydlitz'' was hit 21 times by heavy-caliber shells, twice by secondary battery shells, and once by a torpedo.Tarrant, p. 296 The ship suffered a total of 98 of her crew killed and 55 wounded.Tarrant, p. 298 ''Seydlitz'' herself fired 376 main battery shells, but only scored approximately 10 hits.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="edbd812c8d2c4c516e19b1b6dfd814b7" name="SMS_Seydlitz_battle_damage" sectnum="3.6.7#1">../img/edbd812c8d2c4c516e19b1b6dfd814b7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>