<document id="accb3a5d7efdf213bf2884e814d15ecf-8" name="St_Kilda,_Scotland" cat="11">
<text>
In 1937, after reading of the St Kilda evacuation, Michael Powell made the film ''The Edge of the World'' about the dangers of island depopulation. It was shot, however, not on St Kilda but on Foula, one of the Shetland Islands. IMDb. Retrieved 25 May 2007. The writer Dorothy Dunnett wrote a short story, "The Proving Climb", set on St Kilda; it was published in 1973 in the anthology ''Scottish Short Stories''. 

In 1982, the noted Scottish filmmaker and theatre director Bill Bryden made the Channel 4-funded film ''Ill Fares The Land'' about the last years of St Kilda. It is not currently on commercial release. BFI. 1 March 2008.

The fictional island of Laerg, which features in the 1962 novel ''Atlantic Fury'' by Hammond Innes, is closely based on Hirta.

The Scottish folk rock band Runrig recorded a song called ''Edge Of The World'' on the album "The Big Wheel", which dwells on the islanders' isolated existence and how "the man from St Kilda went over the cliff on a winter's day". Radiance.org. Retrieved 25 May 2007. In a 2005 poll of ''Radio Times'' readers, St Kilda was named as the ninth greatest natural wonder in the British Isles. (2 August 2005) BBC News. Retrieved 25 May 2007. In 2007 an opera in Scots Gaelic called ''St Kilda: A European Opera'' about the story of the islands received funding from the Scottish Government. It was performed simultaneously at six venues in Austria, Belgium, France, Germany and Scotland over the summer solstice of 2007. As part of the lasting legacy, this production left a long-term time lapse camera on Hirta. Events Scotland. Retrieved 3 March 2007.McKenzie, Steven (23 June 2007). BBC Scotland. Retrieved 11 August 2007. designiscentral.com. Retrieved 7 May 2007. ''Britain's Lost World'', a three-part BBC documentary series about St Kilda began broadcasting on 19 June 2008. BBC. Retrieved 20 June 2008.

Stamps were issued by the Post Office depicting St. Kilda in 1986 and 2004. St Kilda is also to be commemorated on a new series of banknotes issued by the Clydesdale Bank in 2009; an image based on a historical photograph of residents will appear on an issue of £5 notes.

Also in 2009 Pròiseact nan Ealan, the Gaelic Arts Agency announced plans to commemorate the evacuation on 29th August, (the 79th anniversary) including an exhibition in Kelvingrove Art Gallery.  Comhairle nan Eilean Siar are also planning a feasibility study for a new visitor centre to tell the story of St Kilda, although they have specifically ruled out using Hirta as a location.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f24b2f6b6c124f4d284c379e2c810bea" name="Stac_an_Armin_and_Boreray" sectnum="8#1">../img/f24b2f6b6c124f4d284c379e2c810bea.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>