<document id="accb3a5d7efdf213bf2884e814d15ecf-5.5" name="St_Kilda,_Scotland" cat="11">
<text>
Numerous factors led to the evacuation. The islands had existed for centuries in relative isolation until tourism and the presence of the military in World War I induced the islanders to seek alternatives to privations they routinely suffered. The changes made to the island by visitors in the nineteenth century disconnected the islanders from the way of life that had allowed their forebears to survive in this unique environment. kilda.org.uk Accessed 02/12/08 Despite construction of a small jetty in 1902, the islands remained at the weather's mercy.Even in the 21st century this is a problem. The National Trust reported in 2006 that it was cancelling 2007 work parties as "adverse weather conditions resulted in our supplies failing to reach St Kilda and our next opportunity to get supplies out is May 2007."  National Trust for Scotland. Retrieved 18 March 2007.

After World War I most of the young men left the island, and the population fell from 73 in 1920 to 37 in 1928. After the death of four men from influenza in 1926 there was a succession of crop failures in the 1920s. Investigations by Aberdeen University into the soil where crops had been grown have shown that there had been contamination by lead and other pollutants, caused by the use of seabird carcasses and peat ash in the manure used on the village fields. This occurred over a lengthy period of time as manuring practices became more intensive and may have been a factor in the evacuation. National Trust for Scotland. Retrieved 20 June 2008.Meharga, Andrew. A ''et al.'' (September 2006)  Chemosphere '''64''', Issue 11. Pages 1818–1828. Retrieved 20 June 2008. The last straw came with the death from appendicitis of a young woman, Mary Gillies, in January 1930. On 29 August 1930, the remaining 36 inhabitants were removed to Morvern on the Scottish mainland at their own request.


The morning of the evacuation promised a perfect day. The sun rose out of a calm and sparkling sea and warmed the impressive cliffs of Oiseval.... Observing tradition the islanders left an open Bible and a small pile of oats in each house, locked all the doors and at 7 a.m. boarded the ''Harebell''... They were reported to have stayed cheerful throughout the operation. But as the long antler of Dun fell back onto the horizon and the familiar outline of the island grew faint, the severing of an ancient tie became a reality and the St Kildans gave way to tears.Maclean (1977) page 142.


The islands were purchased in 1931 by Lord Dumfries (later 5th Marquess of Bute), from Sir Reginald MacLeod. For the next 26 years the island experienced quietude, save for the occasional summer visit from tourists or a returning St Kildan family. Thompson, Francis (1970) ''St Kilda and other Hebridean Outliers''. David & Charles. ISBN 071534885XSteel (1988) pages 229–32.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5c52232bbb04c351cbfde08fae27837e" name="Boreray_and_the_Stacs" sectnum="5.5#1">../img/5c52232bbb04c351cbfde08fae27837e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>