<document id="ad06177176192a2b7d78733595b97770-2.3" name="The_Four_Stages_of_Cruelty" cat="1">
<text>
By the time of the third plate, Tom Nero has progressed from the mistreatment of animals to theft and murder. Having encouraged his pregnant lover, Ann Gill, to rob and leave her mistress, he murders the girl when she meets him. The murder is shown to be particularly brutal: her neck, wrist, and index finger are almost severed. Her trinket box and the goods she had stolen lie on the ground beside her, and the index finger of her partially severed hand points to the words "God's Revenge against Murder" written on a book that, along with the ''Book of Common Prayer'', has fallen from the box.Uglow, p.504. A woman searching Nero's pockets uncovers pistols, a number of pocket watches—evidence of his having turned to highway robbery (as Tom Idle did in ''Industry and Idleness'' ),It has been suggested that he has done so out of desperation following his dismissal as a coach driver because of the report against him from the Second Stage, as well as other atrocities assuredly committed by him.   and a letter from Ann Gill which reads:



The spelling is perfect and while this is perhaps unrealistic, Hogarth deliberately avoids any chance of the scene becoming comical. A discarded envelope is addressed "To Thos Nero at Pinne...". Ronald Paulson sees a parallel between the lamb beaten to death in the ''Second Stage'' and the defenceless girl murdered here. Below the print, the text claims that Nero, if not repentant, is at least stunned by his actions:



Various features in the print are meant to intensify the feelings of dread: the murder takes place in a graveyard, said to be St Pancras but suggested by John Ireland to resemble Marylebone; an owl and a bat fly around the scene; the moon shines down on the crime; the clock strikes one for the end of the witching hour. The composition of the image may allude to Anthony van Dyck's ''The Arrest of Christ''. A lone Good Samaritan appears again: among the snarling faces of Tom's accusers, a single face looks to the heavens in pity.

In the alternative image for this stage, produced as a woodcut by Bell, Tom is shown with his hands free. There are also differences in the wording of the letter and some items, like the lantern and books, are larger and simpler while others, such as the man to the left of Tom and the topiary bush, have been removed. The owl has become a winged hourglass on the clock tower.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="33107ddc1eb81b0098b368dd41734fd2" name="cruelty3" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/33107ddc1eb81b0098b368dd41734fd2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>