<document id="ad1900cb874496bdf4d5f34c4f75a2ef-2" name="The_Hitchhiker's_Guide_to_the_Galaxy_(radio_series)" cat="19">
<text>
The first radio series (first six episodes) was broadcast in March and April, 1978. A seventh episode was broadcast on 24 December 1978. This seventh episode was commonly known as the Christmas Episode. This had nothing to do with Christmas except in an early draft (which would have had Marvin the Paranoid Android as the "star" that was followed by the Three Wise Men); Adams. Perkins (ed.) Additional material by M.J. Simpson. Page 147. it was called the Christmas Episode because it was first broadcast on Christmas Eve. The final five episodes, completing the second radio series, were broadcast in January 1980.

Production on the second series was delayed several times. While Adams was meant to be working on scripts for a stage adaptation of ''Hitchhiker's'' in April 1979, he was also employed as the Script Editor for ''Doctor Who'' and turned down an offer from John Lloyd to submit material for ''Not the Nine O'Clock News''. The recording on the first day scheduled for the second radio series, 19 May 1979, was left incomplete because Adams had not finished the script. Further scheduled recordings on 11 July and 1 August of that year were also cancelled, this time due in part to Adams trying to work on the LP re-recordings of the first series, as well as its novelization. Further recording attempts were made on 23 October and 3 December. The recording of the final episode in the second series was completed on 13 January 1980: the audio mixing of the episode was not finished until 25 January, the day it was transmitted. The tape "arrived just a few minutes before transmission."Adams. Perkins (ed.) Additional material by M.J. Simpson. Page 246

All of the episodes, including those completed after Adams's death, are referred to as 'Fits,' after Lewis Carroll's "The Hunting of the Snark: an Agony, in Eight Fits". In 1981, upon a rebroadcast of the twelve episodes of the first two series, it was decided that the Christmas episode, which previously had no episode number, would be called "Fit the Seventh" and the episodes in the second series, which had first been billed as Fit the First through Fit the Fifth (representing five parts of the second series) would become Fit the Eighth through Fit the Twelfth.Adams. Perkins (ed.) Additional material by M.J. Simpson. Page 253

The two series were first released on audio cassette and CD in 1988, marking the tenth anniversary of the first broadcast of the first episode. The two radio series were known simply as "the first series" and "the second series" until 1992 when the BBC made its first re-release in separate boxes as "The Primary Phase" and "The Secondary Phase." The episodes were released with those titles in 1993, and again in 1998, for the series' twentieth anniversary.

There were many other staff members of the BBC who worked on the first two radio series. Sound and effects for the BBC Radiophonic Workshop were by Paddy Kingsland, Dick Mills and Harry Parker. The Chief Sound Engineer was Alick Hale-Munro, and Anne Ling was the production secretary. The "Technical Team" is given as: Paul Hawdon, Lisa Braun (studio manager), Colin Duff (studio manager), Eric Young, Martha Knight, Max Alcock and John Whitehall.Webb, pages 329–330. Several of the sound effects recorded by Dick Mills for the first series were released on the album ''BBC Sound Effects No. 26 - Sci-Fi Sound Effects''.

The twelve original radio episodes have been translated and transmitted in Finland, France, The Netherlands and Sweden. A German radio version of the first six radio episodes was transmitted in 1981. For full details, see The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy as international phenomenon.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="26b682326bfb67195f97d497ce231575" name="BBC_Hitchhiker's_Guide" sectnum="2#1">../img/26b682326bfb67195f97d497ce231575.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>