<document id="ad1900cb874496bdf4d5f34c4f75a2ef-1" name="The_Hitchhiker's_Guide_to_the_Galaxy_(radio_series)" cat="19">
<text>
Douglas Adams had contributed comedy sketches for BBC radio programmes produced by Simon Brett (including ''The Burkiss Way'' and ''Week Ending''). The two of them came up with an idea for a radio science fiction comedy series in early 1977. Originally to be called ''The Ends of the Earth,'' each episode would have ended with the planet Earth meeting its demise in a different way.

While writing the first episode, Adams said that he needed a character who knew what was going to happen. He decided to make this character an alien, and, remembering an idea he supposedly had had while lying drunk in a field in Innsbruck, Austria in 1971, decided that this character would be a "roving reporter" for ''The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy''.  Later recollections by his friends at the time indicate that Adams first spoke openly of the idea of "hitch-hiking around the galaxy" while on holiday in Greece, in 1973.


Adams wrote his first outlines in February 1977. Copies of these have been republished. A pilot episode was commissioned on 1 March 1977, and the recording was completed on 28 June 1977. Brett and Adams both later recounted different parts of the pilot episode's genesis, including convincing the BBC that such a programme could not be recorded with a studio audience, and insisting that the programme be recorded in stereo sound. To win this latter argument, Hitchhiker's was briefly classified as a Drama instead of a Comedy, as Drama programmes were allowed to be recorded in stereo, and Comedy programmes were not, in 1977.

A full series of six episodes (five new episodes, plus the pilot) was commissioned on 31 August 1977. However, Adams had in the meantime sent a copy of the Hitchhiker's pilot episode to the BBC's Doctor Who production office, and was thus commissioned to write a four part Doctor Who serial (The Pirate Planet) a few weeks later. In addition, Simon Brett had left the BBC, and the final five episodes in the first series were produced by Geoffrey Perkins.

With conflicting writing commitments, Adams engaged his friend John Lloyd to assist in writing what became known as "Fit the Fifth" and "Fit the Sixth." Aside from the later Infocom computer game (and, arguably, the movie screenplay), this is the only co-writer credit in any form of the Hitchhiker's Guide.  The second episode was produced in November, 1977.  The script of the last episode of the first series (which was later retitled "The Primary Phase") was completed in February 1978, and production (including sound mixing and effects) was completed on 3 March 1978.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="47511f39821ff852f75a2f428aa24dff" name="DNA_Guide_to_H2G2_front" sectnum="1#1">../img/47511f39821ff852f75a2f428aa24dff.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>