<document id="ad37f5c5cef207a7528ce960ac174255-3" name="Slavery_in_ancient_Greece" cat="14">
<text>
All activities were open to slaves with the exception of politics.Finley (1997), p.180. For the Greeks, politics was the only activity worthy of a citizen, the rest being relegated wherever possible to non-citizens.Finley (1997), p.148. It was status that was of importance, not activity.
 
The principal use of slaves was in agriculture, the foundation of the Greek economy. Some small landowners might own one slave, or even two.Finley (1997), p.149. An abundant literature of manuals for landowners (such as the ''Economy'' of Xenophon or that of Pseudo-Aristotle) confirms the presence of dozens of slaves on the larger estates; they could be common labourers or foremen. The extent to which slaves were used as a labour force in farming is disputed.Jameson argues in favour of a very large use of slaves; Wood (1983 and 1988) disputes it. It is certain that rural slavery was very common in Athens, and that ancient Greece did not know of the immense slave populations found on the Roman ''latifundia''.Finley (1997), p.150. 
 
In mines and quarries slave labour was prevalent, with found large slave populations often leased out by rich private citizens. The strategos Nicias leased a thousand slaves to the silver mines of Laurium in Attica; Hipponicos, 600; and Philomidès, 300. Xenophon''Poroi'' (''On Revenues''), 4. indicates that they received one obolus per slave per day, amounting to 60 drachmas per year. This was one of the most prized investments for Athenians. The number of slaves working in the Laurium mines or in the mills processing ore has been estimated at 30,000.Lauffer, p.916. Xenophon suggested that the city buy a large number of slaves, up to three state slaves per citizen, so that their leasing would assure the upkeep of all the citizens.
 
Slaves were also used as craftsmen and tradespersons. As in agriculture, they were used for labour that was beyond the capability of the family. The slave population was greatest in workshops: the shield factory of Lysias employed 120 slaves,Demosthenes, 12:8–19. and the father of Demosthenes owned 32 cutlers and 20 bedmakers.Demosthenes, ''Against Aphobos'', 1:9. 
 
Slaves were also employed in the home. The domestic's main role was to stand in for his master at his trade and to accompany him on trips. In time of war he was batman to the hoplite; it has been argued that their actual role was far greater.See Hunt for further reading. The female slave carried out domestic tasks, in particular bread baking and textile making. Only the poorest citizens did not possess a domestic slave.Finley (1997), pp.151–152.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="51ab3d45866b9e52fda1f0fc7fa9a3b0" name="Amphora_olive-gathering_BM_B226" sectnum="3#1">../img/51ab3d45866b9e52fda1f0fc7fa9a3b0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>