<document id="ad37f5c5cef207a7528ce960ac174255-7.10" name="Slavery_in_ancient_Greece" cat="14">
<text>
Slavery in Greek antiquity has long been an object of apologetic discourse among Christians, who awarded themselves the merit of its collapse. From the 16th century the discourse became moralizing in nature. The existence of colonial slavery had significant impact on the debate, with some authors lending it civilizing merits and others denouncing its misdeeds.Garlan, p.8. Thus Henri-Alexandre Wallon in 1847 published a ''History of Slavery in Antiquity'' amongst his works for the abolition of slavery in the French colonies.

In the 19th century a politico-economic discourse emerged. It concerned itself with distinguishing the phases in the organisation of human societies and correctly identifying the place of Greek slavery. The influence of Marx is decisive; for him the ancient society was characterized by development of private ownership and the dominant (and not secondary as in other pre-capitalist societies) character of slavery as a mode of production.Garlan, p.10–13. The Positivists represented by the historian Eduard Meyer (''Slavery in Antiquity'', 1898) were soon to oppose the Marxist theory. According to him slavery was the foundation of Greek democracy. It was thus a legal and social phenomenon, and not economic.Garlan, p.13–14. 

Current historiography developed in the 20th century; led by authors such as Joseph Vogt, it saw in slavery the conditions for the development of elites. Conversely, the theory also demonstrates an opportunity for slaves to join the elite. Finally, Vogt estimates that modern society, founded on humanist values, has surpassed this level of development.Garlan, p.19–20. 
 
In 2007, Greek slavery remains the subject of historiographical debate, on two questions in particular: can it be said that ancient Greece was a "slave society", and did Greek slaves comprise a social class?Garlan, p.201.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c642a0ba2b703db47737c1b650466bde" name="NAMA_Masque_esclave" sectnum="7.10#1">../img/c642a0ba2b703db47737c1b650466bde.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>