<document id="ad37f5c5cef207a7528ce960ac174255-6" name="Slavery_in_ancient_Greece" cat="14">
<text>
It is difficult to appreciate the condition of Greek slaves. According to pseudo-Aristotle, the daily routine of slaves could be summed up in three words: "work, discipline, and feeding".''Economics'', 1344a35. Xenophon's advice is to treat slaves as domestic animals, that is to say punish disobedience and reward good behaviour.Xenophon, ''Economics'', 13:6. For his part, Aristotle prefers to see slaves treated as children and to use not only orders but also recommendations, as the slave is capable of understanding reasons when they are explained.''Politics'', I, 3, 14. 
 
Greek literature abounds with scenes of slaves being flogged; it was a means of forcing them to work, as were control of rations, clothing, and rest. This violence could be meted out by the master or the supervisor, who was possibly also a slave. Thus, at the beginning of Aristophanes' ''The Knights'' (4–5), two slaves complain of being "bruised and thrashed without respite" by their new supervisor. However, Aristophanes himself cites what is a typical old saw in ancient Greek comedy:
 
"He also dismissed those slaves who kept on running off, or deceiving someone, or getting whipped. They were always led out crying, so one of their fellow slaves could mock the bruises and ask then: 'Oh you poor miserable fellow, what's happened to your skin? Surely a huge army of lashes from a whip has fallen down on you and laid waste your back?'"''Peace'', v.743–749. Trans. , 2006, accessed 17 May 06.
 
 
The condition of slaves varied very much according to their status; the mine slaves of Laureion and the ''pornai'' (brothel prostitutes) lived a particularly brutal existence, while public slaves, craftsmen, tradesmen and bankers enjoyed relative independence.Garlan, p.147. In return for a fee ( / ''apophora'') paid to their master, they could live and work alone.Garlan, p.148. They could thus earn some money on the side, sometimes enough to purchase their freedom. Potential emancipation was indeed a powerful motivator, though the real scale of this is difficult to estimate.Finley (1997), p. 165.

Ancient writers considered that Attic slaves enjoyed a “peculiarly happy lot”:Morrow, p.210. See Plato, ''The Republic'', 8:563b; Demosthenes, ''Third Philippic'', 3; Aeschines, ''Against Timarchos'', 54; Aristophanes, ''Assemblywomen'', 721–22 and Plautus, ''Stichus'', 447–50. Pseudo-Xenophon deplores the liberties taken by Athenian slaves: "as for the slaves and Metics of Athens, they take the greatest licence; you cannot just strike them, and they do not step aside to give you free passage".''Constitution of the Athenians'', I, 10. This alleged good treatment did not prevent 20,000 Athenian slaves from running away at the end of the Peloponnesian War at the incitement of the Spartan garrison at Attica in Decelea.Thucydides (7:27). These were principally skilled artisans (''kheirotekhnai''), probably amongst the better-treated slaves. The title of a 4th-century comedy by Antiphanes, ''The Runaway-catcher'' (),Apud Athenaeus, 161e. suggests that slave flight was not uncommon.Cartledge, p.139. Conversely, the absence of a large-scale Greek slave revolt comparable to that of Spartacus in Rome, for instance, can undoubtedly be explained by the relative dispersion of Greek slaves, which would have prevented any large-scale planning. Slave revolts were rare, even in Rome or the American South. Individual acts of rebellion of slaves against their master, even if scarce, are not unheard of; a judicial speech mentions the attempted murder of his master by a boy slave, not 12 years old.Antiphon, ''On the Murder of Herodes'', 69.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4dca0d66be59ff520b89cf80c045c5c3" name="Black_slave_Louvre_Br361" sectnum="6#1">../img/4dca0d66be59ff520b89cf80c045c5c3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>