<document id="ad37f5c5cef207a7528ce960ac174255-4.1" name="Slavery_in_ancient_Greece" cat="14">
<text>
It is difficult to estimate the number of slaves in ancient Greece, given the lack of a precise census and variations in definitions during that era. It is certain that Athens had the largest slave population, with as many as 80,000 in the 5th and 6th centuries BC, on average three or four slaves per household. In the 5th century BC, Thucydides remarked on the desertion of 20,000 slaves during the war of Decelea, mostly tradesmen. The lowest estimate, of 20,000 slaves, during the time of Demosthenes,Jones, pp.76–79. corresponds to one slave per family. Between 317 BC and 307 BC, the tyrant Demetrius Phalereus orderedCtesicles, apud Athenaeus 6:272c. a general census of Attica, which arrived at the following figures: 21,000 citizens, 10,000 metics and 400,000 slaves. The orator Hypereides, in his ''Against Areistogiton'', recalls that the effort to enlist 150,000 male slaves of military age led to the defeat of the Greeks at the Battle of Chaeronea (338 BC), which corresponds to the figures of Ctesicles.Ctesicles was the author of a history preserved as two fragments in the Athenaeus.

According to the literature, it appears that the majority of free Athenians owned at least one slave. Aristophanes, in ''Plutus'', portrays poor peasants who have several slaves; Aristotle defines a house as containing freemen and slaves.''Politics'', 252a26–b15. Conversely, not owning even one slave was a clear sign of poverty. In the celebrated discourse of Lysias ''For the Invalid'', a cripple pleading for a pension explains "my income is very small and now I'm required to do these things myself and do not even have the means to purchase a slave who can do these things for me."Lysias, ''For the invalid'', 3. However, the huge slave populations of the Romans were unknown in ancient Greece. When AthenaeusAthenaeus, 6:264d. cites the case of Mnason, friend of Aristotle and owner of a thousand slaves, this appears to be exceptional. Plato, owner of five slaves at the time of his death, describes the very rich as owning 50 slaves.''Republic'', 9:578d–e.
 
Thucydides estimates that the isle of Chios had proportionally the largest number of slaves.Thucydide, 8:40, 2.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="408200e28130b1bc3b7f0bb27000a45c" name="NAMA_Cheval_%26_esclave_éthiopien" sectnum="4.1#1">../img/408200e28130b1bc3b7f0bb27000a45c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>