<document id="ad37f5c5cef207a7528ce960ac174255-1" name="Slavery_in_ancient_Greece" cat="14">
<text>
The ancient Greeks had many words to describe slaves, which need to be placed in context to avoid ambiguity. In Homer, Hesiod and Theognis of Megara, the slave was called  / ''dmôs''.Chantraine, s.v. . The term has a general meaning but refers particularly to war prisoners taken as booty,For instance ''Odyssey'' 1:398, where Telemachus mentions “the slaves that goodly Odysseus won for ”. in other words, property. During the classical period, the Greeks frequently used  / ''andrápodon'',Used once by Homer in ''Iliad'' 7:475 to refer to prisoners taken in war; the line was athetized by Aristarchus of Samothrace following Zenodotus and Aristophanes of Byzantium, see Kirk, p.291. literally, "one with the feet of a man", as opposed to  / ''tetrapodon'', "quadruped", or livestock.Chantraine, s.v. . The most common word is  / ''doûlos'', from LSJ. an earlier form of which appears in Mycenaean inscriptions as ''do-e-ro'',Mycenean transliterations can be confusing and do not directly reflect pronunciation; for clarification see Linear B. used in opposition to "free man" ( / ''eleútheros''). The verb  can be used metaphorically for other forms of dominion, as of one city over another or parents over their children.Chantraine, s.v. . See also Mactoux (1981). Finally, the term  / ''oikétês'' was used, meaning "one who lives in the house", referring to household servants.Chantraine, s.v. .
 
Other terms used were less precise and required context: 
:*  / ''therápôn'' – At the time of Homer, the word meant "squire" (Patroclus was referred to as the ''therapôn'' of Achilles''Iliad'', 16:244 and 18:152. and Meriones that of Idomeneus''Iliad'', 23:113.); during the classical age, it meant "servant".Chantraine, s.v. .
:*  / ''akólouthos'' – literally, "the follower" or "the one who accompanies". Also, the diminutive , used for page boys.Chantraine, s.v. .
:*  / ''pais'' – literally "child", used in the same way as "houseboy",Chantraine, s.v. . also used in a derogatory way to call adult slaves.Cartledge, p.137.
:*  / ''sôma'' – literally "body", used in the context of emancipation.Chantraine, s.v. .
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="46dc921eb10f4242744f0fef8f5f625c" name="Phlyax_scene_Louvre_CA7249" sectnum="1#1">../img/46dc921eb10f4242744f0fef8f5f625c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>