<document id="ad37f5c5cef207a7528ce960ac174255-2" name="Slavery_in_ancient_Greece" cat="14">
<text>
Slaves were present in the Mycenaean civilization. In the tablets from Pylos 140 ''do-e-ro'' can be identified with certainty. Two legal categories can be distinguished: "common" slaves and "slaves of the god" (''te-o-jo do-e-ro'' / θεοιο), the God in this case probably being Poseidon. Slaves of the god are always mentioned by name and own their own land; their legal status is close to that of freemen. The nature and origin of their bond to the divinity is unclear.Burkert, p.45. The names of common slaves show that some of them came from Kythera, Chios, Lemnos or Halicarnassus, and were probably enslaved as a result of piracy. The tablets indicate that unions between slaves and non-slaves were not uncommon and that slaves could be independent artisans and retain plots of land. It appears that the major division in Mycenaean civilization was not between slave and free, but between those attached to the palace and those not.Mele, pp.115–155.
 
There is no continuity between the Mycenaean era and the time of Homer, where social structures reflected those of the Greek dark ages. The terminology differs: the slave is no longer ''do-e-ro'' (doulos) but ''dmôs''.Garlan, p.36. In the Iliad, slaves are mainly women taken as booty of war,For instance Chryseis (1:12–3, 29–30, 111–5), Briseis (2:688–9), Diomede (6:654–5), Iphis (6:666–8) and Hecamede (11:624–7). while men were either ransomedSee in the ''Iliad'' the pleas of Adrastus the Trojan (1:46–50), the sons of Antimachus (11:131–5) and Lycaon (21:74–96), all begging for mercy in exchange of a ransom. or killed on the battlefield. In the ''Odyssey'', the slaves also seem to be mostly women.There are 50 of them in Ulysses' house (22:421) and in Alcinous' house (7:103). These slaves were servantsBefore his fight with Achilles, Hector predicts for his wife Andromache a life of bondage and mentions weaving and water-fetching (6:454–8). In the ''Odyssey'', servants tend the fire (20:123), prepare the suitors' feast (1:147), grind wheat (7:104, 20:108–9), make the bed (7:340–2) and take care of the guests. and sometimes concubines.In the ''Iliad'', Chryseis sleeps with Agamemnon, Briseis and Diomede with Achilles, Iphis with Patroclus. In the ''Odyssey'', twelve female servants sleep with the suitors (20:6–8) against Euryclea's direct orders (22:423–425). There were some male slaves, especially in the ''Odyssey'', a prime example being the swineherd Eumaeus. The slave was distinctive in being a member of the core part of the ''oikos'' ("family unit", "household"): Laertes eats and drinks with his servants;''Odyssey'', 16:140–1. in the winter, he sleeps in their company.''Odyssey'', 11:188–91. The term ''dmôs'' is not considered pejorative, and Eumaeus, the "divine" swineherd,''Odyssey'', 14:3. benefits from the same Homeric epithet as the Greek heroes. In spite of this, slavery remained a disgrace. Eumaeus himself declares that “Zeus, of the far-borne voice, takes away the half of a man's virtue, when the day of slavery comes upon him.”''Odyssey'' 17:322–323. Online version of . 
 
It is difficult to determine when slave trading began in the archaic period. In ''Works and Days'' (8th century BC), Hesiod owns numerous ''dmôes'',For instance ''Works and Days'', 405. although their status is unclear. The presence of ''douloi'' is confirmed by lyric poets such as Archilochus or Theognis of Megara.Garlan, p.43. According to epigraphic evidence, the homicide law of Draco (c. 620 BC) mentioned slaves."." Dareste, Haussoulier and Reinach, 4, 5, 8. According to Plutarch,''Life of Solon'', 1:6. Solon (c. 594-593 BC) forbade slaves from practising gymnastics and pederasty. By the end of the period, references become more common. Slavery becomes prevalent at the very moment when Solon establishes the basis for Athenian democracy. Classical scholar Moses Finley likewise remarks that Chios, which, according to Theopompus,Apud Athenaeus, 6:265bc = FGrH 115, fgt.122. was the first city to organize a slave trade, also enjoyed an early democratic process (in the 6th century BC). He concludes that “one aspect of Greek history, in short, is the advance hand in hand, of freedom ''and'' slavery.”Finley (1997), pp.170–171.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="11213ee02b3c3d9a67ff60a7a92b6782" name="Aias_Kassandra_Louvre_G458" sectnum="2#1">../img/11213ee02b3c3d9a67ff60a7a92b6782.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>