<document id="ad4ab82ca451cbf0f92dfcf53cdd06a2-3" name="The_Last_Temptation_of_Krust" cat="19">
<text>
In addition to Jay Leno, other real-life comedians that portrayed themselves in the episode include Steven Wright, Janeane Garofalo, Bobcat Goldthwait and Bruce Baum, whose appearance helped increase his popularity.  Krusty's "Krustylu Studios" is a spoof on the company Desilu studios set up by Lucille Ball and her husband Desi Arnaz, where the series ''Star Trek'' was once filmed. During Krusty's "bender to end all benders" montage he is seen drinking out of, and vomiting into, the Stanley Cup. The National Hockey League sent a letter regarding this scene. Mike Scully described it as a "kind of a cease and desist", but the production staff decided not to cut the scene from the episode.

The "Canyonero" song and visual sequence was modeled after Ford commercials. The sequence is a parody of a commercial for a sport utility vehicle, and Hank Williams Jr. sings a song about the Canyonero accompanied by country guitar music and whip cracks. The song "Canyonero" closely resembles the theme to the 1960s television series ''Rawhide''. The first verse of the song is: "Can you name the car with a four-wheel drive / Smells like a steak and seats thirty-five? / Canyonero! / Canyonero!" This episode was the first appearance of the Canyonero, which again appeared in ''The Simpsons'' season 10 episode Marge Simpson in: "Screaming Yellow Honkers". The "Canyonero" song is included on the 1999 soundtrack album ''Go Simpsonic with The Simpsons''.

Chris Turner wrote positively of the Canyonero spoof piece in ''Planet Simpson: How a Cartoon Masterpiece Defined a Generation'', calling it "a brilliant parody of an SUV ad". In an article in the journal ''Environmental Politics'' Steve Vanderheiden commented that the Canyonero reflected an "anti-SUV" stance by ''The Simpsons''. Vanderheiden wrote: "Even the popular animated television series ‘The Simpsons’ joined the anti-SUV fray in 1998, featuring a mammoth vehicle called the ‘Canyonero’ (marketed with the jingle: ‘Twelve yards long, two lanes wide/Sixty-five tons of American pride!’), which promised to help the family transcend its mundane station-wagon existence but instead brought only misery." The term "Canyonero" has since been used in the news media to refer critically to large trucks and SUVs. In an article in the ''San Francisco Chronicle'' about SUV owners, Vicki Haddock wrote "SUV owners have become something of a punch line, succinctly captured in a "Simpsons" parody touting the apocryphal Canyonero " In a 2006 article, Seth Jayson of ''The Motley Fool'' compared the wording in a Ford advertisement ''myFord Owner Magazine'' to this episode, writing: " the unholiest of unholies is the writing, which is so thick with absurd adspeak, you'd think it was written by the crew at ''The Onion'' or ''The Simpsons'' – especially that episode where Krusty starts shilling for the Canyonero." In a 2004 article in the ''Chicago Tribune'', Jim Mateja noted that people have pointed out a similarity between the GMC Canyon and the Canyonero. When contacted, GMC responded that the GMC is a pickup truck, while the Canyonero is a parody of an SUV. Joshua Dowling of ''The Sun Herald'' described the philosophy of the Ford F-250 as "The Canyonero comes to life".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7338437560df606f4b103eb7f03dbc30" name="Canyonero" sectnum="3#1">../img/7338437560df606f4b103eb7f03dbc30.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>