<document id="ad4ab82ca451cbf0f92dfcf53cdd06a2-4" name="The_Last_Temptation_of_Krust" cat="19">
<text>
In 2006, ''USA Today'' highlighted the episode in a review of the ''The Simpsons'' ninth season.  In his review of the season nine DVD, Joseph Szadkowski of ''The Washington Times'' noted: "Among the 22-minute gems found in the set, I most enjoyed ...  work with Jay Leno."  Mark Evans of the ''Evening Herald'' wrote, "'The Last Temptation of Krust' is a winner for its title alone as Krusty the clown becomes a satiric 'alternative' comedian but then sells out by advertising the Canyonero SUV road hazard." Alan Sepinwall wrote positively of the episode in ''The Star-Ledger'', citing the Canyonero sequence as "the real reason to watch" the episode, and that "It's an oversize vehicle that will create oversized laughs." Some sources mistakenly refer to this episode as "The Last Temptation of Krusty".

In the book ''I Can't Believe It's a Bigger and Better Updated Unofficial Simpsons Guide'', Warren Martyn and Adrian Wood characterized the episode as "a good twist on the never-ending Krusty story", and suggested that while "Jay Leno turns in a nice cameo  the show is stolen by the advert for the Canyonero".  The authors also praised Krusty's "ponytail and black sweater" look.  In the Season 9 DVD commentary, Leno said that he believed the essence of comedy clubs was depicted very well in the episode, and referred to Krusty's remodeled appearance as " Carlin post-Vegas act".  He also appreciated Krusty's poke at Leno's use of news headlines on ''The Tonight Show with Jay Leno'' and said that he couldn't figure out whether parts of the episode were making fun of him or complimenting him. William Irwin's ''The Simpsons and Philosophy: The D'oh! of Homer'' references a scene from the episode as an example of Marge's passive resistance, her moral influence on Lisa, and her value as a role model for her children.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d35548e720e175a771d87f5e0397d6fd" name="Jaylenocropped" sectnum="4#1">../img/d35548e720e175a771d87f5e0397d6fd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>