<document id="ad6895104e3e31ee3f06cf5ad7df4239-1" name="T-26" cat="29">
<text>
It is well known that the T-26 was a Soviet development of the British Vickers Mk.E 6-ton light tank which was designed by Vickers-Armstrongs company in 1928-1929. The simple to maintain Vickers 6-ton tank was intended especially for export to countries with a low level of machine-building industry: Soviet Union, Poland, Finland, Bulgaria, Greece, Japan, Thailand, China, Brazil, Argentina, Bolivia. There was an active advertising of the tank in military publications that time, and Soviet Union and Poland were the first countries indeed which became interested in that Vickers design.

In spring 1930, the Soviet buying committee under the direction of S. Ginzburg arrived to Great Britain to select tanks, tractors and cars available to be used in the Red Army. Soviet representatives selected four tank models during the visit to Vickers-Armstrongs company: Vickers-Carden-Loyd Mk.VI tankette, Vickers-Carden-Loyd amphibious tank, Vickers Mk.E 6-ton light tank and Vickers Armstrong Mk.II 12-ton medium tank. According to the contract signed on 28 May 1930 Vickers-Armstrongs delivered to the USSR 15 twin-turreted Mk.E (Model A armed with two 7.71 mm water-cooled Vickers machine guns) 6-ton tanks together with the full set of technical documentation to organize the series production of this tank in the USSR. Model A was intended for kill enemy troops during breakthrough of field entrenchments - turn of two turrets made possible to shoot a trench right and left.Kolomiets (2007), pp. 6-9 Several Soviet engineers participated in assembly of those tanks at Vickers Factory in 1930.Baryatinskiy (2003), p. 2  

The first four Vickers 6-ton tanks arrived to USSR in the end of 1930 and the last ones - in 1932 only (when series production of the native T-26 was in progress). Those arrived British tanks were issued to Soviet factories for study the organization of their series production, military educational institutions and training units; later some of Vickers light tanks were given to military supply depots and proving grounds. Production of a new tank was planned at the Chelyabinsk Tractor Factory and at the Stalingrad Tractor Factory (both were under construction that time), finally it was decided to use ''Bolshevik'' Factory in Leningrad for that purpose.

The arrived Vickers 6-ton tanks had the designator V-26 in the USSR, and three of them (No. 215/1, 214/2 and 216/3) were successfully tested on the small proving ground near Moscow on Poklonnaya Hill in January 1931. The "special commission for the RKKA new tanks" under the direction of S. Ginzburg was created according to the order of K. Voroshilov to define the tank type suitable for the Red Army. The T-19 8-ton light infantry tank, developed that time by S. Ginzburg in the Design Office of the ''Bolshevik'' Factory, was a theoretical competitor to British Vickers (the prototype of the quite complicated and expensive T-19 was finished in August 1931 only). As both tank models had their own advantages and disadvantages, S. Ginzburg suggested to develop a more powerful hybrid tank (so called "improved" T-19) - with a hull, a  six-cylinder engine developed by A. Mikulin and an armament (37 mm PS-2 mod. 1930 semi-automatic tank gun and two DT tank machine guns) from the T-19, and a transmission and a chassis from the Vickers 6-ton.Kolomiets (2007), pp. 6-9Svirin (2007), pp. 162-172 

But on 26 January 1931 the chief of Department of Mechanization and Motorization of the RKKA (UMM RKKA) I. Khalepsky wrote a letter to S. Ginzburg with the information obtained through intelligence service that Polish government decided to purchase Vickers 6-ton infantry tanks as well as Christie 10-ton cavalry tanks and to mass produce them with the British-French assistance in 1931 already. So the Soviet Revolutionary Military Council took this erroneous information into consideration and decided to pass the aforementioned foreign tank models into Red Army's service immediately without any further experimental work in order to meet a possible aggression. It should be clarified that Poland was considered by the Soviet military doctrine as the main enemy till around 1935. The RKKA had only several tens of outdated captured Mk.V, Mk.A and Renault FT-17 tanks of WWI period together with different armoured cars and obsolescent home-produced MS-1 (T-18) light infantry tanks that time. On 13 February 1931 the Vickers 6-ton light infantry tank under the designator T-26 officially entered service in the Red Army as the "main tank for close support of combined arms units and tank units of High Command reserve".Kolomiets (2007), pp. 6-9


At the same time the engineer group from the Faculty of Mechanization and Motorization of the Military Technical Academy named after F.E. Dzerzhinsky developed two tank models (TMM-1 and TMM-2) based on the purchased Vickers 6-ton tank design but with an American Hercules  six-cylinder water-cooled engine, increased to 15-20 mm front armour and driver's place on the left side. TMM stands for ''tank maloy moshchnosti'' - ''tank of low power''. The TMM-1 was equipped with transmission details from the home-produced Ya-5 truck and a ball mount for the DT tank machine gun in front of the hull (a crew consisted of 4 men) whereas the TMM-2 was equipped with an improved gear box, a steering device without clutches and a 37 mm Hotchkiss gun in the right turret. But representatives from the main Soviet tank manufacturers (''Bolshevik'' Factory and Kharkov Locomotive Factory) together with officials from the RKKA Mobilization Department were against the overheated and complicated in production Hercules engine, also tests of TMM-1 and TMM-2 prototypes performed in the beginning of 1932 demonstrated no any advantage over the Vickers 6-ton and the already produced T-26 (a maneuverability of the TMM-2 was worse even).Baryatinskiy (2003), pp. 3-4Solyankin et al. (2002), pp. 89-91

One of the Vickers 6-ton tanks was tested for gunfire resistance at the Factory named after S. Ordzhonikidze in August 1931 - the hull was shelled from rifle and Maxim machine gun with the use of usual and armour-piercing bullets from . It was found that tank armour plates withstood gunfire (only some rivets were damaged), the chemical analysis demonstrated that  turret and front armour plates were made from a high-quality cemented armour (S.t.a Plat according to Vickers-Armstrongs classification) whereas homogenous  roof and bottom armour plates were made from mediocre steel. Nevertheless, the British armour was better than armour produced by Izhora Factory for the first T-26 light tanks (because of shortage of modern metallurgical equipment in the USSR that time).Svirin (2007), pp. 173-174
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4bc32397be0a55db74ba7c607d18abf7" name="TMM-1_during_tests" sectnum="1#1">../img/4bc32397be0a55db74ba7c607d18abf7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>