<document id="ad6895104e3e31ee3f06cf5ad7df4239-4" name="T-26" cat="29">
<text>
The first tank unit equipped with the T-26 tanks was 1st mechanized brigade named after K.B. Kalinovsky (Moscow Military District), 11th mechanized brigade (Leningrad Military District) and 6th mechanized brigade (Special Red Banner Far Eastern Army) received the T-26 tanks in 1931 also. Tanks delivered to the Red Army till the end of 1931 were unarmed and intended for training, the active service of the T-26 began in 1932. An organization of new mechanized brigades (178 T-26 tanks in each) started that time also. First T-26 tanks often suffered from technical failures because of insufficiently proven technology of engine and transmission production, the training of attending personel was insufficient also. Military exercises demonstrated that the T-26 mod. 1931 had a little bit worse cross-country ability in comparison with old tanks used in the RKKA that time, but its speed capability was superior. Twin-turreted T-26 tanks were used also for anti-tank training of infantry battalions during military exercises of Leningrad Military District in 1934-1935.Svirin, Kolomiets (2000), p. 48

The RKKA Staff decided to form larger tank units basing on the experience acquired during military exercises of 1931-1932: so mechanized corps were created in Moscow, Ukrainian and Leningrad Military Districts since autumn 1932. Each mechanized corps consisted of two mechanized brigades (one equipped with the T-26 and another - with the BT), since 1935 all mechanized corps were equipped with the BT tanks only. When a series production of the T-26 mod. 1933 started, each tank platoon consisted of three vehicles at first (one single-turreted mod. 1933 and two twin-turreted mod. 1931 tanks). Later twin-turreted T-26 tanks were given to combat training depots and to tank battalions of rifle divisions (in the beginning of 1935 tank battalion of rifle division consisted of 3 companies, 15 T-26 tanks in each). In august 1938 mechanized corps, brigades and regiments were reorganized into corresponding tank units. In the end of 1938 the Red Army had 17 light tank brigades (267 T-26 tanks in each) and 3 chemical tank brigades (equipped with flame-throwing tanks based on the T-26 chassis).Baryatinsky (2003), p. 44
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2710017d5df007337b6c950022a1ca95" name="T26_19-1-" sectnum="4#1">../img/2710017d5df007337b6c950022a1ca95.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>