<document id="adbef27a1851164435f7d51aa06ecc0f-2.4" name="Mozart_in_Italy" cat="20">
<text>
The journey from Bologna to Milan was delayed by storms and floods, but Leopold and his son arrived on 18 October, ten weeks before the first performance of ''Mitridate''. Wolfgang's fingers ached from writing recitatives,Sadie (2006), p. 212 and in any case he could not begin work on the arias until the singers were present, collaboration with the principal performers being the custom for composers of the time.Halliwell, pp. 153&ndash;54: "The first hurdle to be overcome was that of pleasing the singers." As the singers assembled, problems arose. Quirino Gasparini, composer of an earlier version of ''Mitridate'', tried to persuade the prima donna Antonia Bernasconi to use ''his'' settings for her arias, but met with failure. "Thank God", Leopold wrote, "that we have routed the enemy". However, the principal tenor, Guglielmo d'Ettore, made repeated requests for his arias to be rewritten, and sang one of Gasparini's settings in Act 3, an insertion that survives in the published score of the opera.Sadie (2006), pp. 219&ndash;20

Rehearsals began on 6 December. Wolfgang's mastery of Italian diction was revealed as the recitatives were practised, and a run-through of the instrumental score displayed his professionalism.Gutman, p. 285 Leopold wrote home: "An awful lot of this undertaking, blessed be God, is safely over, and, God be praised, once more with honour!" On 26 December, at the Teatro Regio Ducal (Milan's great opera house at the time), Wolfgang directed the first public performance of his ''Mitridate'' from the keyboard, dressed for the occasion in a scarlet coat lined with blue satin and edged with gold.Halliwell, p. 154 The occasion was a triumph: at the conclusion the audience cried "Evviva il maestro!" (Long live the master!) and demanded encores. The opera ran for 22 performances,Sadie (2006), pp. 222&ndash;23 and the ''Gazetta di Milano'' praised the work handsomely: "The young ''maestro di capella'', who is not yet fifteen years of age, studies the beauties of nature, and represents them adorned with the rarest musical graces." The arias sung by Bernasconi "vividly expressed the passions and touched the heart". Subsequent reactions to the opera proved less effusive; there are no records of further performances of ''Mitridate'' before its revival in Salzburg in 1971.Osborne, p. 55

Having fulfilled his major obligation for this trip, Wolfgang gave a concert at Firmian's palace on 4 January 1771. A few days later, news arrived that Wolfgang had been granted membership in the Accademia Filarmonica of Verona. On 14 January they departed for a two-week sojourn in Turin, where they met many of the leading Italian musicians: the distinguished violinist Gaetano Pugnani, his 15-year-old prodigy pupil Giovanni Battista Viotti, and the composer Giovanni Paisiello whose opera ''Annibale in Torino'' Leopold declared to be magnificent. They returned to Milan for a farewell lunch with Firmian before their departure for Salzburg on 4 February.Sadie (2006), pp. 228&ndash;29
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d383def77904f2dcf77949c4bdd98aad" name="Dal_Re,_Marc'Antonio_(1697-1766)_-_Vedute_di_Milano_-_71_-_S._Maria_alla_Scala_-_ca._1745.jpg" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/d383def77904f2dcf77949c4bdd98aad.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>