<document id="adbef27a1851164435f7d51aa06ecc0f-4" name="Mozart_in_Italy" cat="20">
<text>
The day after Leopold and Wolfgang arrived back in Salzburg the court was thrown into turmoil by the death of  Archbishop  Schrattenbach.Sadie (2006), p. 257 This created a predicament for Leopold, who had unresolved issues with the court. Part of his salary during the second Italian visit had been stopped, and Leopold wished to petition for its payment, and to pursue the matter of Wolfgang's salary as a Konzertmeister, which Schrattenbach had indicated might be paid on Wolfgang's return from the first Italian journey.Halliwell, p. 166

The Salzburg Kapellmeister post, which Leopold might earlier have expected to secure, was opening up. The incumbent, Giuseppe Lolli, was over 70 years old and ready for retirement; Leopold had followed Lolli as Vice-Kapellmeister, and in ordinary circumstances might have felt confident of succeeding him again. However, the appointment would now be made by the new archbishop, whose policies and attitudes were unknown. On 14 March 1772, amid various political machinations, Count Hieronymus von Colloredo was elected to the archbishopric as a compromise candidate acceptable to the Imperial court in Vienna. 

Although unpopular among Salzburgers, this appointment appeared at first to be to the Mozarts' advantage: Leopold's withheld salary was paid,Halliwell, p. 174 and on 31 August Colloredo authorised the payment of Wolfgang's Konzertmeister salary.Halliwell, pp. 177&ndash;79 However, the new archbishop began to look for someone outside the Salzburg court to be his new Kapellmeister. Eventually, he chose the Italian Domenico Fischietti, who was several years younger than Leopold. Realising that his chances of promotion had probably been irrevocably lost, Leopold turned his hopes for a comfortable old age towards Wolfgang, giving new urgency to the third Italian journey which began in October 1772.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b347475d5d82b35ced288aec392f15f8" name="Hieronymus_Count_Colloredo" sectnum="4#1">../img/b347475d5d82b35ced288aec392f15f8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>