<document id="adbef27a1851164435f7d51aa06ecc0f-2.1" name="Mozart_in_Italy" cat="20">
<text>
On 13 December 1769, Leopold and Wolfgang set out from Salzburg, armed with testimonials and letters that Leopold hoped would smooth their passage. Among the most important was an introduction to Count Karl Joseph Firmian of Milan, described as the "King of Milan", an influential and cultivated patron of the arts. His support would be vital to the success of the entire Italian undertaking.Halliwell, p. 145 

The pair travelled through Innsbruck, then due south to the Brenner Pass into Italy. They continued through Bolzano and Rovereto to Verona and Mantua, before turning west towards Milan. Leopold's financial plans for the journey were broadly the same as for the family's grand tour&mdash;travel and accommodation costs were to be met by concert proceeds. This 350-mile winter journey to Milan occupied a difficult and unpleasant six weeks, with the weather forcing extended stops. Leopold complained in his letters home about unheated inn rooms: "... freezing like a dog, everything I touch is ice".  Early concert receipts were modest; according to Leopold, costs were running at around 50 florins a week.Halliwell, p.146 After some unwise boasting about profits during the grand tour, Leopold was now more cautious about revealing financial details. He tended to emphasise his expenses and minimise his takings,Solomon, p. 58 writing, for example: "... On the whole we shall not make much in Italy ... one must generally accept admiration and bravos as payment."Solomon, pp. 86&ndash;87

The longest pause was two weeks spent in Verona, where the press reported glowingly on Wolfgang's concert of 5 January 1770.Sadie (2006), pp. 181&ndash;84 Father and son attended a performance of Guglielmi's ''Ruggiero'', which Wolfgang described dismissively in a letter to Nannerl. The boy also had his portrait painted by a local artist, Saverio dalla Rosa. This interlude was followed by a shorter stop in Mantua, where Wolfgang gave a concert at the Accademia Filarmonica, with a programme designed to test his abilities in performance, sight reading, and improvisation. According to a press review the audience was "dumbfounded" at this "miracle in music, one of those freaks that Nature causes to be born".Sadie (2006), pp. 185&ndash;86 In Mantua, they suffered a snub from Prince Michael of Thurn and Taxis, who informed them through a servant that he had no desire to meet them. Historian Robert Gutman surmises that the Prince, aware of the Affligio affair in Vienna, wanted no dealings with musicians who did not know their place.Gutman, pp. 260&ndash;61 By contrast, Count Arco, whose family were members of the Salzburg court, received them warmly.Ironically, it would be another Count Arco, of the family in Salzburg, who ten years later would administer the famous "kick in the ass" that ended Wolfgang's appointment in the Salzburg court; Gutman, pp. 548&ndash;49.

The pair arrived in Milan on 23 January and found comfortable lodgings in the monastery of San Marco, not far from Count Firmian's palace.Halliwell, pp. 146&ndash;48 While they waited to see the Count, they attended Nicola Piccini's opera ''Cesare in Egitto''.Zaslaw, p. 163 Firmian eventually welcomed them with generous hospitality and friendship, presenting Wolfgang with a complete edition of the works of Pietro Metastasio, Italy's leading dramatic writer and librettist. Firmian also hosted a series of concerts attended by many of the city's notables, including the Habsburg Archduke Ferdinand, a possible future patron for the young composer. For the last of these occasions, Wolfgang wrote a set of arias using Metastasio's texts. These were so well received that Firmian commissioned Wolfgang to write the opening opera for the following winter's carnival season in Milan, just as Leopold had hoped he might.Sadie (2006), p. 190Gutman, p. 263 Wolfgang would receive a fee of around 500 florins, and free lodgings during the writing and rehearsal. The Mozarts left Milan on 15 March, heading south towards Florence and Rome, committed to return in the autumn and taking with them fresh letters of recommendation from Firmian.

Up to this point in the tour Wolfgang appears to have done little composition. The Accademia Filarmonica concert in Mantua had included much improvisation but little of Wolfgang's own music; the only certain compositions from this phase of the tour are the arias composed for the final Firmian concert, which sealed his contract for the carnival opera. These are ''Se tutti i mali miei'', K. 83/73p,"K" refers to the catalogue of Mozart's works, completed in 1862 by Ludwig von Köchel and revised several times. Where two K numbers are given, the first is the number in the original catalogue, and the second the number in the most recent revision (1964). See Sadie (2006), pp. 613&ndash;21, also Zaslaw, pp. 558&ndash;61. ''Misero me'', K. 77/73e, and ''Ah più tremar ...'', K. 71. The Symphony in G, K. 74, evidently completed in Rome in April, may have been started in Milan.Zaslaw, p. 178
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d08e1134c9c380a20ef0a5d97a6cd1c7" name="IMG_7459_-_Milano_-_San_Marco_-_Foto_Giovanni_Dall'Orto_-_25-mar-2007" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/d08e1134c9c380a20ef0a5d97a6cd1c7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>