<document id="adbef27a1851164435f7d51aa06ecc0f-5" name="Mozart_in_Italy" cat="20">
<text>
The Mozarts returned to Milan for Wolfgang to complete the second carnival opera, commissioned at the end of the first journey after the success of ''Mitridate''. The text was ''Lucio Silla'', revised by Metastasio from an original by Giovanni de Gamerra.Osborne, p. 81 Wolfgang found himself in the familiar routine of composing rapidly while coping with problems such as the late arrival of singers and the withdrawal of the principal tenor due to illness.Sadie (2006), pp. 278&ndash;80 Leopold reported on 18 December that the tenor had arrived, that Wolfgang was composing his arias at breakneck speed, and that rehearsals were in full swing.Halliwell, pp. 180&ndash;86 The first performance, on 26 December, was chaotic: its start was delayed two hours by the late arrival of Archduke Ferdinand, there were quarrels among the principal performers, and the running time was extended by the insertion of ballets (a common practice of the time), so the performance was not over until two o'clock the following morning.Osborne (p. 82) notes that the work was timed to last four hours without the ballets, and that the tempi must therefore have been very leisurely, though no doubt many of the arias were encored. Despite this, subsequent performances were well received. Leopold wrote on 9 January 1773 that the theatre was still full, and that the premiere of the season's second opera, Giovanni Paisiello's ''Sismano nel Mogul'', had been postponed to allow Wolfgang's piece a longer run&mdash;26 performances in all.Osborne, p. 82 Such success for the new work seems to have been fleeting; but during the next few years the libretto was reset by several different composers, including Wolfgang's London mentor Johann Christian Bach.Sadie (2006), p. 284Rushton, p. 31


Leopold, unaware of the Empress's views, continued to pursue an appointment for Wolfgang by applying to Grand Duke Leopold of Tuscany, the Empress's third son. The application was strongly supported by Count Firmian, and Leopold, in a coded letter home, said he was quite hopeful. While the Mozarts waited for a reply, Wolfgang composed a series of "Milanese" string quartets (K. 155/134a to K. 160/159a), and the famous motet ''Exsultate, jubilate'', K. 165.Sadie, (2006) pp. 292&ndash;95 Leopold resorted to deception to explain his extended stay in Milan, claiming to be suffering from severe rheumatism that prevented his travelling. His ciphered lettersLeopold's letters home were in part for public consumption, and would have circulated around Salzburg. They were also subject to censorship (Gutman, p. 11). Private messages to Anna Maria were encrypted. to his wife Anna Maria assure her that he is in fact well, but urge her to spread the story of his indisposition.Gutman, p. 308 He waited through most of January and all of February for the Grand Duke's reply. The negative response arrived on 27 February. It is not known whether the Grand Duke was influenced by his mother's opinion of the Mozart family, but his rejection effectively ended Leopold's hope of an Italian appointment for Wolfgang. The Mozarts had no choice now but to return to Salzburg, leaving Milan on 4 March and reaching home nine days later. Neither father nor son visited Italy again.Gutman, p. 309Blom, p. 62
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="19d87fe358b4c7383b75bd8665e72fb3" name="Johann_Zoffany_005" sectnum="5#1">../img/19d87fe358b4c7383b75bd8665e72fb3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>