<document id="adcc21cd76c53e93b399336bcf4a4145-1.1" name="The_Supremes" cat="20">
<text>
The Supremes began by performing hit songs by artists such as Ray Charles and The Drifters at sock hops, social clubs and talent shows around the Detroit area. Receiving additional guidance from group friend and established performer Jesse Greer, the quartet quickly earned a local fan following.Wilson et al., 49. The girls crafted an age-appropriate style that was inspired by the collegiate dress of popular doo-wop group Frankie Lymon & the TeenagersWilson et al., 38.; and, for the most part, Ballard, Ross and Wilson performed equal leads on songs. Within a few months, guitarist Marvin Tarplin was added to The Primettes' lineup - a move that helped distinguish the group from Detroit's many other aspiring acts by allowing the girls to sing live as opposed to lip-synch.Wilson et al., 37.

After winning a prestigious local talent contest,Wilson et al., 51. The Primettes' sights were set on making a record. In hopes of getting the group signed to the local upstart Motown label, in 1960 Ross asked an old neighbor, Miracles lead singer Smokey Robinson, to help the group land an audition for Motown executive Berry Gordy, Jr.Wilson et al., 53–56., who had already proven himself a capable songwriter.Wilson et al., 75. Robinson liked the girls and agreed to help, but he liked their guitarist even more; with The Primettes' permission he hired Tarplin, who became the guitarist for The Miracles. Robinson arranged for The Primettes to audition ''a cappella'' for Gordy - but Gordy, feeling the girls too young and inexperienced to be recording artists, encouraged them to return upon graduating from high school. Undaunted, later that year The Primettes recorded a single for Lupine Records (a label created just for them) entitled "Tears of Sorrow", which was backed with "Pretty Baby".Wilson et al., 69. The single, however, failed to find an audience.Wilson et al., 69–71. Shortly thereafter, McGlown became engaged and left the group.Wilson et al., 62. Local youth Barbara Martin was McGlown's quick replacement.

Determined to leave an impression on Gordy and join the stable of rising Motown stars, The Primettes frequented his Hitsville, U.S.A. recording studio every day after school.Wilson et al., 57. Eventually, they convinced Gordy to allow them to contribute hand claps and background vocals for the songs of other Motown artists including Marvin Gaye and Mary Wells.Wilson et al., 58. In January 1961, Gordy finally relented and agreed to sign the girls to his label - but under the condition that they change the name of their group.Wilson et al., 84–85. The Primes had by this time combined with Otis Williams & the Distants and would soon sign to Motown as The Temptations.Wilson et al., 81. Gordy gave Ballard a list of names to choose from that included suggestions such as "The Darleens", "The Sweet Ps", "The Melodees", "The Royaltones" and "The Jewelettes".Benjaminson, 27. Ballard chose "The Supremes", a name that Ross initially disliked as she felt it too masculine. Nevertheless, on January 15 the group signed with Motown as The Supremes."". The Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum, 1988. Retrieved on July 21, 2008. In the spring of 1962, Martin left the group to start a family. Thus, the newly named Supremes continued as a trio.Slonimsky, Nicolas & Kuhn, Laura Diane. ''Baker's Biographical Dictionary of Musicians''. Schirmer Books, 2001. 3539. ISBN 0-0286-5527-3

Between 1961 and 1963, The Supremes released eight singles, none of which charted in the Top 40 positions of the ''Billboard'' Hot 100. Jokingly referred to as the "no-hit Supremes" around Motown's Hitsville U.S.A. offices,Wilson et al., 136. the group attempted to compensate for their lack of hits by taking on any work available at the studio, including providing hand claps and singing backup for Motown artists such as Marvin Gaye and The Temptations. During these years, all three members took turns singing lead: Wilson favored soft ballads; Ballard favored soulful, hard-driving songs; and Ross favored mainstream pop songs. Most of their early material was written and produced by Berry Gordy or Smokey Robinson.Bronson, Fred. ''Billboard's Hottest Hot 100 Hits: Top Songs and Song Makers, 1955 to 2000''. ''Billboard'' Books, 2000. 25. ISBN 0-8230-7738-1 In December 1963, the single "When the Lovelight Starts Shining Through His Eyes" peaked at number 23 on the ''Billboard'' Hot 100.Adrahtas, 361. 

"Lovelight" was the first of many Supremes songs written by the Motown songwriting and production team known as Holland-Dozier-Holland.Wilson et al., 141. In late 1963, Berry Gordy chose Diana Ross as the official lead singer of the group. Ballard and Wilson were periodically given solos on Supremes albums, and Ballard continued to sing her solo number, "People", in concert for the next two years.Wilson et al., 173. 

In the spring of 1964, The Supremes recorded the single "Where Did Our Love Go." Wilson et al., 141–143. The song was originally intended by Holland-Dozier-Holland for The Marvelettes, who rejected it. Although The Supremes disliked the song, the producers coerced them into recording it. In August 1964, while The Supremes toured as part of Dick Clark's ''Caravan of Stars'', "Where Did Our Love Go" reached number one on the US pop charts, much to the surprise and delight of the group.Wilson et al., 147. It was also their first song to appear on the UK pop charts, where it reached number three.

"Where Did Our Love Go" was followed by four consecutive US number-one hits: "Baby Love" (which was also a number-one hit in the UK), "Come See About Me", "Stop! In the Name of Love" and "Back in My Arms Again"."". Allmusic. Retrieved on July 25, 2008. "Baby Love" was nominated for the 1965 Grammy Award for Best Rhythm & Blues Recording, and "You Keep Me Hangin' On" was awarded the 1966 Grammy for Best Pop single."". grammy.com. Retrieved on July 24, 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d209c084b54826635e308e51d2f49f88" name="Frederick_Douglass_HomestowerDetroit" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/d209c084b54826635e308e51d2f49f88.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>