<document id="ae10157e7e4d8155ae3f67a22e870333-1.2" name="Yukon_Quest" cat="26">
<text>
The 1995 race featured 22 mushers, of whom 13 finished.Saari, Matias. , ''Fairbanks Daily News-Miner''. February 6, 2008. Accessed February 27, 2009. Budget problems caused the first prize to drop by 25% to $15,000, contributing to the low participation.Firth, p. 265 This problem was fixed for the 1996 race, with a first-place prize of $25,000. The 1997 race was won by Rick Mackey, brother of later Quest winner Lance Mackey; the two are the only brother-brother winning tandem in Quest history.Saari, Matias. , ''Fairbanks Daily News-Miner''. February 6, 2008. Accessed February 27, 2009. Following the 1997 race, financial troubles again arose, this time on the Alaska side. Canadian organizers secured international sponsorship for the 1998 race, and when they refused to let this sponsorship money be used to pay debts accumulated in Alaska, members of the Alaska board threatened to host a separate competition. In the end, the Alaska board members were forced to resign, and a deal was worked out between the two sides.Firth, p. 236


The 1998 race was run on schedule and had 38 entrants.Saari, Matias. , ''Fairbanks Daily News-Miner''. February 6, 2008. Accessed February 27, 2009. The 1999 race was won by Alaska Native veterinarian Ramy Brooks, who defeated Mark May by 10 minutes.Saari, Matias. , ''Fairbanks Daily News-Miner''. February 6, 2008. Accessed February 27, 2009. In 2000, Aliy Zirkle became the first woman to win the Yukon Quest after taking 10 days, 22 hours, and 57 minutes to trek the .Saari, Matias. , ''Fairbanks Daily News-Miner''. February 6, 2008. Accessed February 27, 2009. Also in 2000, Yukon Quest International added two races: the Quest 250 (today the Quest 300) and the Junior Quest (both described below). Competitors in each have gone on to participate in the Yukon Quest. The first of these graduated mushers competed in the 2001 race, won by Tim Osmar.Saari, Matias. , ''Fairbanks Daily News-Miner''. February 6, 2008. Accessed February 27, 2009. 

In 2002, the Yukon Quest was won by Hans Gatt, an Austrian-born resident of British Columbia and the first European to win. This was the first of three consecutive wins, making him the first three-time winner.Saari, Matias. , ''Fairbanks Daily News-Miner''. February 6, 2008. Accessed February 27, 2009. In 2003, Gatt's second win was truncated by a lack of snow near Whitehorse. Unseasonable warmth forced organizers to truck mushers and their dog teams to Braeburn before continuing what became a  competition. The 2004 race saw 31 mushers start the race and 20 finish, a drop-out rate of 35%.Saari, Matias. , ''Fairbanks Daily News-Miner''. February 6, 2008. Accessed February 27, 2009. During the first 24 years of the competition, there were 776 starters and 513 finishers. Though 90 more mushers attempted the race in the first 12 years than in the next dozen runnings, there is little difference in the percentage that did not finish (35% in 1984&ndash;1995; 33% in 1996&ndash;2007).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="cb40bacb3f6da84c1ce287cdc510001b" name="Quest_dogs" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/cb40bacb3f6da84c1ce287cdc510001b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>