<document id="ae112cebbfdc6463f065b96633ad87ed-1.4" name="The_Greencards" cat="20">
<text>
On their previous albums, The Greencards had individually recorded their musical tracks separately in isolation booths of recording studios.  For ''Viridian'', however, the bandmembers recorded their album together in real time in an open room, which was said to be a factor in creating a spontaneous feel for some of the album. Most of the songs on ''Viridian'' are sung by Young, and all of the tracks on ''Viridian'' were written by The Greencards, with the exception of "Travel On", which was penned by Kim Richey of Nashville. Their sound, through ''Viridian'', was likened to the Canadian alternative country band The Duhks. After its release, ''Viridian'' claimed the #1 position on ''Billboard'' magazine's Bluegrass Music Chart. Doug Lancio, a producer who had previously worked with Patty Griffin, was said to have been a positive factor in the success of ''Viridian''. Prior to the 2007 album, Lancio had not previously worked with The Greencards.  The Greencards are the first international musical act to ever reach #1 on the Bluegrass Music Chart.

In a review of ''Viridian'', Embo Blake of ''Hybrid Magazine'' noted Carol Young's vocal skill, as she "effortlessly diphthongs cadence" on the track "Waiting On The Night". According to ABC News in Dallas/Fort Worth, the album has a traditional bluegrass core, with a worldly flavor. Bruce Elder of the ''Sydney Morning Herald'' called ''Viridian'' a "tour de force".

In the wake of ''Viridian'', The Greencards have been internationally referred to as one of the most popular Americana musical acts in the United States. Bruce Elder went on to say that the band may, after ''Viridian'', be the best country music performers to ever come out of Australia. In 2007, they were nominated for Best Country Album at the 21st Australian Recording Industry Association awards, ultimately losing out to Keith Urban. In December 2007, it was announced that their song "Mucky the Duck" from ''Viridian'' was nominated for the Grammy Award for Best Country Instrumental Performance at the 50th Grammy Awards, but ultimately lost to Brad Paisley's "Throttleneck". Written by Warner, "Mucky the Duck" was inspired by one of the band's favorite Houston musical venues, The Mucky Duck. Eamon McLoughlin is a regular blogger for Country Music Television. After the Grammy Awards, he wrote about the band's experience at the event, noting that despite not winning, the bar had been raised for their next album.

The Greencards announced on their website in August 2008 that they had returned to the studio to record their fourth album with producer Jay Joyce. In September 2008, again via their website, they announced that they signed with Sugar Hill Records for their fourth album, to be released in spring 2009.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0100bb7b3f6e7b201aef5cc98de4b3cd" name="The_Greencards_5" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/0100bb7b3f6e7b201aef5cc98de4b3cd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>