<document id="ae18e1b5d3d98c3d561bcdd43dce6537-3" name="Hamlet" cat="17">
<text>
"Any dating of ''Hamlet'' must be tentative", cautions the ''New Cambridge'' editor, Phillip Edwards.MacCary suggests 1599 or 1600 (1998, 13); James Shapiro offers late 1600 or early 1601 (2005, 341); Wells and Taylor suggest that the play was written in 1600 and revised later (1988, 653); the New Cambridge editor settles on mid-1601 (Edwards 1985, 8); the New Swan Shakespeare Advanced Series editor agrees with 1601 (Lott 1970, xlvi); Thompson and Taylor, tentatively ("according to whether one is the more persuaded by Jenkins or by Honigmann") suggest a ''terminus ad quem'' of either Spring 1601 or sometime in 1600 (2001a, 58–59). The earliest date estimate relies on ''Hamlet'''s frequent allusions to Shakespeare's ''Julius Caesar'', itself dated to mid-1599.MacCary (1998, 12–13) and Edwards (1985, 5–6). The latest date estimate is based on an entry, of 26 July 1602, in the Register of the Stationers' Company, indicating that ''Hamlet'' was "latelie Acted by the Lo: Chamberleyne his servantes".

In 1598, Francis Meres published in his ''Palladis Tamia'' a survey of English literature from Chaucer to its present day, within which twelve of Shakespeare's plays are named. ''Hamlet'' is not among them, suggesting that it had not yet been written. As ''Hamlet'' was very popular, the ''New Swan'' series editor Bernard Lott believes it "unlikely that he  would have overlooked ... so significant a piece".Lott (1970, xlvi).

The phrase "little eyases"''Hamlet F1'' 2.2.337. The whole conversation between Rozencrantz, Guildenstern and Hamlet concerning the touring players' departure from the city is at ''Hamlet "F1"'' 2.2.324–360. in the First Folio (F1) may allude to the Children of the Chapel, whose popularity in London forced the Globe company into provincial touring. This became known as the War of the Theatres, and supports a 1601 dating.

A contemporary of Shakespere's, Gabriel Harvey, wrote a marginal note in his copy of the 1598 edition of Chaucer's works, which some scholars use as dating evidence. Harvey's note says that "the wiser sort" enjoy ''Hamlet'', and implies that the Earl of Essex—executed in February 1601 for rebellion—was still alive. Other scholars consider this inconclusive. Edwards, for example, concludes that the "sense of time is so confused in Harvey's note that it is really of little use in trying to date ''Hamlet''". This is because the same note also refers to Spenser and Watson as if they were still alive ("our flourishing metricians"), but also mentions "Owen's new epigrams", published in 1607.Edwards (1985, 5).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1c26eafa7bbf85d806b6a0028a37539b" name="Hamlet_quarto_3rd" sectnum="3#1">../img/1c26eafa7bbf85d806b6a0028a37539b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>