<document id="ae18e1b5d3d98c3d561bcdd43dce6537-6.4" name="Hamlet" cat="17">
<text>
Written at a time of religious upheaval, and in the wake of the English Reformation, the play is alternately Catholic (or piously medieval) and Protestant (or consciously modern). The Ghost describes himself as being in purgatory, and as dying without last rites. This and Ophelia's burial ceremony, which is characteristically Catholic, make up most of the play's Catholic connections. Some scholars have observed that revenge tragedies come from traditionally Catholic countries, such as Spain and Italy; and they present a contradiction, since according to Catholic doctrine the strongest duty is to God and family. Hamlet's conundrum, then, is whether to avenge his father and kill Claudius, or to leave the vengeance to God, as his religion requires.MacCary (1998, 37–38); in the New Testament, see Romans 12:19: " 'vengeance is mine, I will repay' sayeth the Lord".

Much of the play's Protestantism derives from its location in Denmark—then and now a predominantly Protestant country, though it is unclear whether the fictional Denmark of the play is intended to mirror this fact. The play does mention Wittenberg, where Hamlet, Horatio, and Rosencrantz and Guildenstern attend university, and where Martin Luther first nailed up his 95 theses.MacCary (1998, 38). When Hamlet speaks of the "special providence in the fall of a sparrow",''Hamlet'' 5.2.197–202. he reflects the Protestant belief that the will of God—Divine Providence—controls even the smallest event. In Q1, the first sentence of the same section reads: "There's a predestinate providence in the fall of a sparrow,"''Hamlet Q1'' 17.45–46. which suggests an even stronger Protestant connection through John Calvin's doctrine of predestination. Scholars speculate that ''Hamlet'' may have been censored, as "predestined" appears only in this quarto.Blits (2001, 3–21).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="df2f518330c23e690437de442ff16589" name="Millais_-_Ophelia" sectnum="6.4#1">../img/df2f518330c23e690437de442ff16589.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>