<document id="ae18e1b5d3d98c3d561bcdd43dce6537-6.8" name="Hamlet" cat="17">
<text>
In the 20th century feminist critics opened up new approaches to Gertrude and Ophelia. New Historicist and cultural materialist critics examined the play in its historical context, attempting to piece together its original cultural environment.Wofford (1994, 199–202). They focused on the gender system of early modern England, pointing to the common trinity of ''maid, wife, or widow'', with ''whores'' alone outside of the stereotype. In this analysis, the essence of ''Hamlet'' is the central character's changed perception of his mother as a whore because of her failure to remain faithful to Old Hamlet. In consequence, Hamlet loses his faith in all women, treating Ophelia as if she too were a whore and dishonest with Hamlet. Ophelia, by some critics, can be honest and fair; however, it is virtually impossible to link these two traits, since 'fairness' is an outward trait, while 'honesty' is an inward trait.Howard (2003, 411–415).

Carolyn Heilbrun's 1957 essay "Hamlet's Mother" defends Gertrude, arguing that the text never hints that Gertrude knew of Claudius poisoning King Hamlet. This analysis has been championed by many feminist critics. Heilbrun argued that men have for centuries completely misinterpreted Gertrude, accepting at face value Hamlet's view of her instead of following the actual text of the play. By this account, no clear evidence suggests that Gertrude is an adulteress: she is merely adapting to the circumstances of her husband's death for the good of the kingdom.Bloom (2003, 58–59); Thompson (2001, 4).

Ophelia has also been defended by feminist critics, most notably Elaine Showalter.Showalter (1985). Ophelia is surrounded by powerful men: her father, brother, and Hamlet. All three disappear: Laertes leaves, Hamlet abandons her, and Polonius dies. Conventional theories had argued that without these three powerful men making decisions for her, Ophelia is driven into madness.Bloom (2003, 57). Feminist theorists argue that she goes mad with guilt because, when Hamlet kills her father, he has fulfilled her sexual desire to have Hamlet kill her father so they can be together. Showalter points out that Ophelia has become the symbol of the distraught and hysterical woman in modern culture.MacCary (1998, 111–113).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="585d7d40952282d052579d06dd8b0df8" name="Ophelia_-_Henrietta_Rae" sectnum="6.8#1">../img/585d7d40952282d052579d06dd8b0df8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>