<document id="ae18e1b5d3d98c3d561bcdd43dce6537-6.7" name="Hamlet" cat="17">
<text>
In the first half of the 20th century, when psychoanalysis was at the height of its influence, its concepts were applied to ''Hamlet'', notably by Sigmund Freud, Ernest Jones, and Jacques Lacan, and these studies influenced theatrical productions.

In his ''The Interpretation of Dreams'' (1900), Freud's analysis starts from the premise that "the play is built up on Hamlet's hesitations over fulfilling the task of revenge that is assigned to him; but its text offers no reasons or motives for these hesitations".Freud (1900, 367). After reviewing various literary theories, Freud concludes that Hamlet has an "Oedipal desire for his mother and the subsequent guilt  preventing him from murdering the man  who has done what he unconsciously wanted to do".Britton (1995, 207–211). Confronted with his repressed desires, Hamlet realises that "he himself is literally no better than the sinner whom he is to punish". Freud suggests that Hamlet's apparent "distaste for sexuality"—articulated in his "nunnery" conversation with Ophelia—accords with this interpretation.Freud (1900, 368).The nunnery conversation referred to in this sentence is ''Hamlet'' 3.1.87–160. John Barrymore introduced Freudian overtones into his landmark 1922 production in New York, which ran for a record-breaking 101 nights.

In the 1940s, Ernest Jones—a psychoanalyst and Freud's biographer—developed Freud's ideas into a series of essays that culminated in his book ''Hamlet and Oedipus'' (1949). Influenced by Jones's psychoanalytic approach, several productions have portrayed the "closet scene",''The Closet Scene'': ''Hamlet'' 3.4. where Hamlet confronts his mother in her private quarters, in a sexual light. In this reading, Hamlet is disgusted by his mother's "incestuous" relationship with Claudius while simultaneously fearful of killing him, as this would clear Hamlet's path to his mother's bed. Ophelia's madness after her father's death may also be read through the Freudian lens: as a reaction to the death of her hoped-for lover, her father. She is overwhelmed by having her unfulfilled love for him so abruptly terminated and drifts into the oblivion of insanity.MacCary (1998, 104–107, 113–116) and de Grazia (2007, 168–170). In 1937, Tyrone Guthrie directed Laurence Olivier in a Jones-inspired ''Hamlet'' at the Old Vic.Smallwood (2002, 102). Olivier later used some of these same ideas in his 1948 film version of the play.

In the 1950s, Lacan's structuralist theories about ''Hamlet'' were first presented in a series of seminars given in Paris and later published in "Desire and the Interpretation of Desire in ''Hamlet''". Lacan postulated that the human psyche is determined by structures of language and that the linguistic structures of ''Hamlet'' shed light on human desire. His point  of departure is Freud's Oedipal theories, and the central theme of mourning that runs through ''Hamlet''. In Lacan's analysis, Hamlet unconsciously assumes the role of ''phallus''—the cause of his inaction—and is increasingly distanced from reality "by mourning, fantasy, narcissism and psychosis", which create holes (or lack (manque)) in the real, imaginary, and symbolic aspects of his psyche. Lacan's theories influenced literary criticism of ''Hamlet'' because of his alternative vision of the play and his use of semantics to explore the play's psychological landscape.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5c39eb62c22441fa5e3ca88e893088a5" name="Claudius_at_Prayer_Hamlet_3-3_Delacroix_1844" sectnum="6.7#1">../img/5c39eb62c22441fa5e3ca88e893088a5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>