<document id="ae18e1b5d3d98c3d561bcdd43dce6537-8.10" name="Hamlet" cat="17">
<text>
The play was revived early in the Restoration. When the existing stock of pre-civil war plays was divided between the two newly created patent theatre companies, ''Hamlet'' was the only Shakespearean favourite that Sir William Davenant's Duke's Company secured.Marsden (2002, 21–22). It became the first of Shakespeare's plays to be presented with movable flats painted with generic scenery behind the proscenium arch of Lincoln's Inn Fields Theatre.Samuel Pepys records his delight at the novelty of ''Hamlet'' "done with scenes"; see Thompson and Taylor (1996, 57). This new stage convention highlighted the frequency with which Shakespeare shifts dramatic location, encouraging the recurrent criticisms of his violation of the neoclassical principle of maintaining a unity of place.Taylor (1989, 16). Davenant cast Thomas Betterton in the eponymous role, and he continued to play the Dane until he was 74.Thompson and Taylor (2006a, 98–99). David Garrick at Drury Lane produced a version that adapted Shakespeare heavily; he declared: "I had sworn I would not leave the stage till I had rescued that noble play from all the rubbish of the fifth act. I have brought it forth without the grave-digger's trick, Osrick, & the fencing match".Letter to Sir William Young, 10 January 1773, quoted by Uglow (1977, 473). The first actor known to have played Hamlet in North America is Lewis Hallam. Jr., in the American Company's production in Philadelphia in 1759.Morrison (2002, 231).

John Philip Kemble made his Drury Lane debut as Hamlet in 1783.Moody (2002, 41). His performance was said to be 20 minutes longer than anyone else's, and his lengthy pauses provoked the suggestion that "music should be played between the words".Moody (2002, 44), quoting Sheridan. Sarah Siddons was the first actress known to play Hamlet; many women have since played him as a breeches role, to great acclaim.Gay (2002, 159). In 1748, Alexander Sumarokov wrote a Russian adaptation that focused on Prince Hamlet as the embodiment of an opposition to Claudius's tyranny—a treatment that would recur in Eastern European versions into the 20th century.Dawson (2002, 185–187). In the years following America's independence, Thomas Abthorpe Cooper, the young nation's leading tragedian, performed ''Hamlet'' among other plays at the Chestnut Street Theatre in Philadelphia, and at the Park Theatre in New York. Although chided for "acknowledging acquaintances in the audience" and "inadequate memorisation of his lines", he became a national celebrity.Morrison (2002, 232–233).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ba62ffd6c081e54240df3d74a2244a79" name="Garrick_as_Hamlet" sectnum="8.10#1">../img/ba62ffd6c081e54240df3d74a2244a79.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>