<document id="ae407441fc460b133232a81b98fc1df4-4.9" name="Black_Moshannon_State_Park" cat="11">
<text>
There are  of trails at Black Moshannon State Park that are open to hiking, mountain biking, cross-country skiing, and snowmobiling. All trails are open to hiking, most are open to skiing during the winter months, and select trails are open to snowmobiles and mountain bikes. The park is especially popular among cross-country skiing enthusiasts due to its high elevation. Skiers will find trails that are largely free of rocks, with a layer of grass beneath the snow. Sleepy Hollow, Seneca, Indian, and Hay Road Trails are most frequently used. Seven of the park's thirteen trails are described above, the remaining six follow.


*'''Allegheny Front Trail''' is a  hiking trail that passes through Black Moshannon State Park and Moshannon State Forest. It was built in the late 1990s and offers several vistas looking out from atop the Allegheny Front. 

*'''Bog Trail''' is a  boardwalk hiking trail that was built by the Pennsylvania Conservation Corps and has received awards for its  handicapped accessibility. Bog Trail loops through the bog at the park passing by lilies, sedges, rushes, Leatherleaf, and various carnivorous plants. Visitors may observe waterfowl and wildlife in the bogs. Access for the handicapped is provided at the boating area.

*'''Dry Hollow Trail''' is a  trail open to hiking, cross-country skiing, mountain biking, and snowmobiling. It is in a narrow valley at the base of the former ski slope. The hollow consists of open woods with mountain laurel and meadows.

*'''Hay Road Trail''' is a  trail that is open to hiking and cross-country skiing. An old road overgrown with grass, it passes through a mixed-oak and Black Cherry forest. It was formerly used by farmers to gather grasses from the marshes of what is now Black Moshannon State Park.

*'''Moss-Hanne Trail''' is an  loop trail through the Black Moshannon Bog Natural Area. It is open to hiking and cross-country skiing. The trail passes through pine plantations, hardwood forests, spruce groves, hemlock-filled bottomlands, patches of wild blueberries, and by beaver ponds. The area is marshy; waterproof footwear is recommended and parts of the trail are boardwalks.

*'''Snowmobile Trail''' is a  trail that runs parallel to Dry Hollow Trail. It provides access to the many miles of trails in Moshannon State Forest that are open to recreational snowmobiling. It is open during summer months for hiking and mountain biking.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="655154e7ccf5fb0fc50931db1d23c9ee" name="Black_Moshannon_SP_Bog_Boardwalk_2" sectnum="4.9#1">../img/655154e7ccf5fb0fc50931db1d23c9ee.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>