<document id="ae407441fc460b133232a81b98fc1df4-3.6" name="Black_Moshannon_State_Park" cat="11">
<text>
White-tailed Deer, Wild Turkey, Ruffed Grouse, opossum, Raccoon, hawks, chipmunks, porcupine, woodpeckers, and flying, Red, and Eastern Gray Squirrels are all fairly common in the park. Black Bears also inhabit Black Moshannon State Park. Many of these animals were decimated due to the effects of deforestation, pollution and unregulated hunting and trapping that took place during the late 19th century. Hunting controls established by the Pennsylvania Game Commission and the work of the  Civilian Conservation Corps and Pennsylvania Department of Conservation and Natural Resources in re-establishing the second growth forest have led to the strong comeback of game species at Black Moshannon State Park and throughout the forests of Pennsylvania. 

The lake is home to American Beavers, as well as Great Blue Heron, swans, Snow Geese, Common Loons, and many other types of waterfowl, with Canada Goose, Ring-necked Duck, Mallard, and Wood Duck the most commonly seen. The bogs, marshes, and swamps contain frogs and salamanders, and provide a habitat for carnivorous plants like the pitcher plant and sundew. Black Moshannon State Park is home to many common species of songbirds, including Ovenbirds.

The conifer and mixed-forests of the park and its surroundings provide habitats for Northern Saw-whet Owl, Blue-headed Vireo, Hermit Thrush, Dark-eyed Junco, and Magnolia, Pine, Yellow-rumped, Blackburnian, and Black-throated Green Warblers. The deciduous forests provide habitats for songbirds, such as Scarlet Tanager and Red-eyed Vireo. 

An outbreak of the non-native gypsy moth in the mid-1980s nearly devastated the woods in a small valley. Selective timber cuts harvested the trees that were affected by species of moth. Today the  Sleepy Hollow Trail for hiking and cross-country skiing loops through the new growth in the area, which provides an ideal habitat for populations of White-tailed Deer and Wild Turkey.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ef4c6cd5fd24dd5cc9d27b59c5918ded" name="Black_Moshannon_SP_Museum" sectnum="3.6#1">../img/ef4c6cd5fd24dd5cc9d27b59c5918ded.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>