<document id="ae407441fc460b133232a81b98fc1df4-3.6.2" name="Black_Moshannon_State_Park" cat="11">
<text>
Pennsylvania Important Bird Area #33 encompasses . The land includes parts of the state park and surrounding Moshannon State Forest, as well as Pennsylvania State Game Lands No. 33, Mid-State Regional Airport (which borders both the park and forest), and some other nearby parcels of private land. The Pennsylvania Audubon Society has designated  of Black Moshannon State Park as an IBA, which is an area designated as a globally important habitat for the conservation of bird populations.


Ornithologists and bird watchers have recorded a total of 175 species at the IBA. Several factors contribute to the high total of bird species observed: there is a large area of forest in the IBA, as well as great habitat diversity. The location of the IBA along the Allegheny Front also contributes to the diverse bird populations.

Black Moshannon Lake and the bogs of the Natural Area are especially important to the IBA. They serve as a stopover for migratory waterfowl and shorebirds. Waterfowl observed at the park include Pied-billed and Slavonian Grebes, Common Loon, American Black Duck, Ruddy Duck, Blue-winged and Green-winged Teal, Tundra Swan, Long-tailed Duck, Hooded and Red-breasted Merganser, Greater and Lesser Scaup, Northern Pintail, Bufflehead, American Wigeon, and Northern Shoveler.

Pennsylvania IBA #33 is on the Allegheny Front, which is along a prime migratory path for a variety of birds of prey. The Golden Eagle, Bald Eagle, Osprey, and Northern Harrier pass through the area during their annual migration periods. It is possible that the Bald Eagle may nest within the IBA, but this has not been confirmed. Raptors which do nest in the forests of the IBA include the Northern Goshawk, Red-shouldered, Broad-winged, Red-tailed, Sharp-shinned, and Cooper's Hawks.

The cool, damp habitat provided by the bogs at Black Moshannon State Park provides a home for some birds that are at the southern limit of their habitat in central Pennsylvania. The Canada Warbler and Northern Waterthrush nest in the bogs, as do the Alder Flycatcher, Common Yellowthroat, Swamp Sparrow, Red-winged Blackbird, and Gray Catbird. The Olive-sided Flycatcher, which is designated as locally extinct in Pennsylvania, has been seen during the breeding season at Black Moshannon State Natural Area. Bird watchers have observed nesting Barred Owls in the IBA, as well as Virginia Rail and Sora.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f41f51a6a6966af038121013ef81aa71" name="Black_Moshannon_SP_Geese" sectnum="3.6.2#1">../img/f41f51a6a6966af038121013ef81aa71.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>