<document id="aebab2f72b1c7fe0660acc7e056941cd-2.3" name="Red_River_Trails" cat="14">
<text>
The '''Middle''' or '''East Plains Trail''' also came into common use in the 1840s. Shorter than the competing West Plain Trail, it became the route of the large cart trains originating from Pembina when well-known trader Henry Sibley retired from the fur trade in 1854. His successor and former partner Norman Kittson moved their company's cart trains from the West Plains Trail in the Minnesota River valley to the East Plains route.Gilman, ''Red River Trails'' (1979), p. 16. 

The East Plains Trail followed the older routes of the West Plains Trail from Pembina to Breckenridge, Minnesota, then struck east by a variety of routes out of the Red River Valley across the upper valleys of the Pomme de Terre and Chippewa Rivers (tributaries of the Minnesota River), to Saint Cloud and Sauk Rapids on the Upper Mississippi.Gilman, ''Red River Trails'' (1979), pp. 71–75. Soon however, a branch was added to connect the East Plains Trail with the Woods Trail. This link skirted the west slope of the Leaf Mountains and joined the East Plains routes at Elbow Lake or near the Otter Tail River. At times, this eastern connection may have been the better-travelled of the two variants.Gilman, ''Red River Trails'' (1979), pp. 71&ndash;72. Vera Kelsey in fact shows the East Plains Trail along this route. Kelsey, ''Red River Runs North!'' (1951), at 120 (map).  

At Saint Cloud, the furs of some of the cart brigades were transshipped to river craft on the Mississippi, which operated to Saint Anthony Falls at Minneapolis. Other cart trains crossed the Mississippi and travelled on to Saint Paul on a route shared with the Woods Trail. 

Over most of its route, the East Plains Trail went through a post-glacial landscape of lakes, moraines, and drumlins, with beautiful scenery and difficult swamps. As the area became settled during Minnesota’s territorial and early statehood days, the routes were improved, stagecoach service was instituted, towns were established, and permanent settlement began.Hess, '''' (1989), pp. E–5, 6; Holmquist, ''They Chose Minnesota'' (1981), pp. 39–41.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8e4c8be455424582c97b8d6fd1c7ba54" name="Red_River_cart_in_Saint_Cloud,_Minnesota" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/8e4c8be455424582c97b8d6fd1c7ba54.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>