<document id="aebab2f72b1c7fe0660acc7e056941cd-2.2" name="Red_River_Trails" cat="14">
<text>
The West Plains Trail, although relatively level, went by a lengthy route through the lands of the Dakota people, and the shorter East Plains Trail also skirted Dakota land. The Dakota were the enemy of the Ojibwa, to whom the  carters were related by blood and marriage.Gilman, ''Red River Trails'' (1979), p. 9.  These tensions led to conflicts. One such bloody confrontation in the summer of 1844 (caused by an attack by  carters on Dakota hunters) occurred when that year's expedition of free traders were in Saint Paul. This meant that they could not safely return by the normal route.Gilman, ''Red River Trails'' (1979), p. 9; Hess, ''Minnesota Red River Trails'' (1989), p. E–3.  The traders therefore struck northwest up the Mississippi to Crow Wing at the mouth of the Crow Wing River, west up that river and across the height of land to the fur post at Otter Tail Lake, then northwest across the prairie to a crossing of the Red River near its confluence with the Forest River.Gilman, ''Red River Trails'' (1979), pp. 9&ndash;10, 55&ndash;56.  The next year, a southbound party followed its tracks, and by the year after (1846), the final route had been well-established inland from the Red River bottomlands. This trail was known as the '''Woods''' or '''Crow Wing Trail'''; it was also known locally as the '''Saint Paul Trail''' and '''Pembina Trail'''.The trails were not named officially, and local names and usages differ.   


As the first of these names indicates, the path was partially wooded, as its southern reaches crossed the transition zone between the western prairies and eastern woodland. From Fort Garry, southbound cart trains followed the east bank of the Red River, crossing the Roseau River and the international border. In Minnesota, the trail was joined by a route coming from Pembina to the northwest, and continued south on a level prairie in the former lakebed of prehistoric Lake Agassiz. It ascended to and followed a firm gravelly ridge which was once among the higher beaches or strandlines of that ancient lake, forded the Red Lake River at the Old Crossing near modern Huot, and angled south by southeast to the fur post at White Earth. At Otter Tail Lake, the route left the plains and turned east into a forest in the Leaf Mountains on the continental divide. Taking a difficult but scenic path east through the woods, the trail crossed the Mississippi River at Old Crow Wing. It then went south down the east bank of that river on a smooth and open glacial outwash sandplain to Sauk Rapids and East Saint Cloud.Gilman, ''Red River Trails'' (1979), pp. 16, 55&ndash;68.  

The final lap of the trail to Saint Paul, which had replaced Mendota as the principal ''entrepôt'' for the cart trade, continued along the sandplain on the east bank of the Mississippi. This route ran within a few miles of the river to Saint Anthony Falls and the community of that name which was growing on the east bank of the Mississippi. The trail then left the river and crossed open country to Saint Paul. The carters camped on the uplands west of the steamboat landing during the interval between their arrival with the furs and their return to the north with supplies and trade goods.Gilman, ''Red River Trails'' (1979), pp. 79&ndash;87; Hess, '''' (1989), p. E–5.  

Inferior in terrain to other routes, the Woods Trail was superior in safety, as it was well within the lands of the Ojibwa. It was less well used during times of relative calm.Hess, '''' (1989), p. E–3.  In the late 1850s, its utility was increased by improvements made by the U.S. Army,  Gilman, ''Red River Trails'' (1979), p. 56. which straightened and improved the winding ox path through the woods along the Leaf and Crow Wing Rivers, and also replaced the old trail along the Mississippi River between Fort Ripley (near Crow Wing) and Sauk Rapids with a military road.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4b944f2c1a64fb2075102e806b9f6b54" name="Red_river_ox_cart_and_driver_in_St._Paul" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/4b944f2c1a64fb2075102e806b9f6b54.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>