<document id="af1df4d04666ed6239f885f313f37302-2.1" name="History_of_the_board_game_Monopoly" cat="26">
<text>
In December 1935, Parker Brothers sent a copy of the game to Victor Watson Sr. of Waddington Games. Watson and his son Norman tried the game over a weekend, and liked it so much that Waddington took the (then extraordinary) step of making a transatlantic "trunk call" to Parker Brothers; this impressed Parker Brothers sufficiently that Waddington was granted licensing rights for Europe and the then-British Commonwealth, excluding Canada.Orbanes, ''The Game Makers''. Pages 98&ndash;99 Waddington's version, their first board game, with locations from London substituted for the original Atlantic City ones, was first produced in 1936. The game was very successful in the United Kingdom and France, but was denounced in Nazi Germany.Orbanes, ''The Game Makers''. Page 103 A new German edition would not appear until the 1960s.Orbanes, ''Monopoly: The World's Most Famous Game'', Appendix V, page 211. Waddington licensed other editions from 1936–38, and the game was exported from the UK and resold or reprinted in Switzerland, Belgium, Australia, Chile, Italy, The Netherlands, and Sweden. In Italy, under the fascists, the game was changed dramatically so that it would have an Italian name, locations in Milan, and changes in the rules. Italian publishers Editrice Giochi still produce the game in Italy, holding a special and mostly independent relationship from Hasbro. page for Italy, by Albert C. Veldhuis.

In Austria, versions of the game first appeared as ''Business'' and ''Spekulation'' (''Speculation''), and eventually evolved to become ''Das Kaufmännische Talent'' (DKT) (''The Businessman's Talent''). Versions of DKT have been sold in Austria since 1940. The game first appeared as ''Monopoly'' in Austria in about 1981. page for Austrian Standard Editions. The Waddingtons edition was imported into The Netherlands starting in 1937, and a fully translated edition first appeared in 1941. page for early Monopoly editions in The Netherlands, in Dutch. Waddingtons later produced special games during World War II, distributed by the International Committee of the Red Cross, which secretly contained files, a compass, a map printed on silk, and real currency hidden amongst the Monopoly money, to enable prisoners of war to escape from German camps.Walsh. Page 56.Orbanes. ''The Game Makers''. Color photographic insert, page 10. Collector Albert C. Veldhuis features a map on his "Monopoly Lexicon" website showing which versions of the game were remade and distributed in other countries, with the Atlantic City, London, and Paris versions being the most influential. to the Monopoly Lexicon website.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f5084daea5ffaf4f4a86d30610c5b67c" name="Monopoly_UK_postcard" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/f5084daea5ffaf4f4a86d30610c5b67c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>