<document id="af1df4d04666ed6239f885f313f37302-5" name="History_of_the_board_game_Monopoly" cat="26">
<text>
The original Monopoly game had been localized for the cities or areas in which it was played, and Parker Brothers has continued this practice. Their version of Monopoly has been produced for international markets, with the place names being localized for cities including London and Paris and for countries including the Netherlands and Germany, among others. By 1982, Parker Brothers stated that the game "has been translated into over 15 languages...."Quotation from the inside cover of the game booklet included with the special Canadian Edition of Monopoly, published in 1982. As of 2007, Hasbro reports that Monopoly has been translated into 37 languages, and has been licensed in 103 countries. Monopoly FAQ page


The game has also inspired official spin-offs, such as the board game Advance to Boardwalk from 1985. There have been five card games: Water Works from 1972. Free Parking from 1988, Express Monopoly from 1993, Monopoly: The Card Game from 1999, and Monopoly Deal from 2008. Finally, there have been two dice games: Don't Go to Jail from 1991 and an update, Monopoly Express, (2006-2007). A second product line of games and licenses exists in Monopoly Junior, first published in 1990. In the late 1980s, official editions of Monopoly appeared for the Sega Master System and the Commodore 64 and Commodore 128. A television game show, produced by King World Productions, was attempted in the summer of 1990, but lasted for only 12 episodes. In 1991&ndash;1992, official versions appeared for the Apple Macintosh and Nintendo's NES, SNES, and Game Boy. on monopolycollector.com. In 1995, as Hasbro (which had taken over Tonka Kenner Parker in the early 1990s) was preparing to launch Hasbro Interactive as a new brand, they chose Monopoly to be their first CD-ROM game, with an option for playing over the Internet. CD-ROM versions of the officially licensed Star Wars and FIFA World Cup '98 editions also were released.Orbanes, ''Monopoly Companion'' Second Edition. Page 185. Later CD-ROM exclusive spin-offs, Monopoly Casino and Monopoly Tycoon, were also produced under license.

Since 1994, various manufacturers of the game have created dozens of versions in which the names of the properties and other elements of the game are replaced by others according to the game's theme. There are officially-licensed versions with themes that include national parks, Star Trek, Star Wars, Nintendo, Disney, Peanuts, various particular cities (such as Las Vegas or Cambridge), states, colleges and universities, the World Cup, NASCAR, and many others. Hasbro has officially licensed two companies to produce further Monopoly editions: USAopoly and Winning Moves Games. USAopoly also sells special corporate editions of Monopoly. information Official corporate editions have been produced for Best Buy, the Boy Scouts of America, FedEx, and UPS, among others.Orbanes, Monopoly: The World's Most Famous Game, pages 203–204.

Unofficial versions of the game, which share some of the same playing features, but also incorporate changes so as not to infringe on copyrights, have been created by firms such as Late for the Sky Production Company and Help on Board. These are done for smaller cities, sometimes as charity fundraisers, and some have been created for college and university campuses. Others have non-geographical themes such as Wine-opoly and Chocolate-opoly.

In late 1998, Hasbro announced a campaign to add an all-new token to U.S. standard edition sets of Monopoly. Voters were allowed to select from a biplane, a piggy bank, and a sack of money &mdash; with votes being tallied through a special website, via a toll-free phone number, and at FAO Schwarz stores. In March 1999, Hasbro announced that the winner was the sack of money (with 51 percent of the vote, compared to 29 percent for the biplane and 20 percent for the piggy bank). Thus, the sack of money became the first new token added to the game since the early 1950s. for the new game token in its 1998&ndash;1999 campaign. In 1999, in a major marketing effort, Hasbro renamed the mascot Rich Uncle Pennybags to "Mr. Monopoly," felt by some to be a less-interesting name.

Before the creation of Hasbro Interactive, and after its later sale to Infogrames, official computer and video game versions have been made available on many platforms. In addition to the versions listed above, they have been produced for PC, Amiga, BBC Micro, Game Boy Color, Game Boy Advance, Sega Genesis, Nintendo 64, PlayStation, PlayStation 2, GameCube, Xbox, and mobile phones, as well as a handheld electronic game in 1997 and a Nintendo DS release (along with Boggle, Yahtzee, and Battleship). In 2001, Stern Pinball, Inc. released a pinball machine version of Monopoly, designed by Pat Lawlor. at sternpinball.com.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e694801872ad7b3d6785c2ec573d89f1" name="Licensed_and_collectible_US_Monopoly_sets" sectnum="5#1">../img/e694801872ad7b3d6785c2ec573d89f1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>