<document id="af91710fd9c8a2bb4ebef4f3837f7031-3.2" name="Casino_Royale_(2006_film)" cat="19">
<text>
Principal photography for ''Casino Royale'' commenced on 30 January 2006 and concluded on 21 July 2006. The film was primarily shot at Barrandov Studios in Prague, with additional location shooting in the Czech Republic, the Bahamas, Italy, and the United Kingdom. The shoot concluded at Pinewood Studios.

Initially, Michael G. Wilson confirmed that ''Casino Royale'' would either be filmed or take place in Prague and South Africa. However, EON Productions encountered problems in securing film locations in South Africa. After no other locations became available, the producers had to reconsider their options. In September 2005, Martin Campbell and director of photography Phil Meheux were scouting Paradise Island in the Bahamas as a possible location for the film. On 6 October 2005, Martin Campbell confirmed that ''Casino Royale'' would film in the Bahamas and "maybe Italy". In addition to the extensive location filming, studio work including choreography and stunt coordination practice was performed at the Barrandov Studios in Prague and at Pinewood Studios where the film used several stages as well as the paddock tank and the historic 007 Stage. Further shooting in the UK was scheduled for Dunsfold Aerodrome in Surrey, the cricket pavilion at Eton College (although that particular scene was cut from the completed movie) and the Millbrook Vehicle Proving Ground in Bedfordshire.

After Prague, the production moved to the Bahamas. Several locations around New Providence were used for filming during February and March, particularly on Paradise Island. Footage set in Mbale, Uganda was filmed at Black Park, Country Park in Buckinghamshire on 4 July 2006. Additional scenes took place at Albany House, an estate owned by golfers Ernie Els and Tiger Woods. The crew returned to the Czech Republic in April, and continued there, filming in Prague, Planá and Loket, before completing in the town of Karlovy Vary in May. A famous Czech spa Karlovy Vary, in German known as the Karlsbad, was used as the exterior of the Casino Royale, with the Grandhotel Pupp serving as "Hotel Splendide". The main Italian location was Venice, where the majority of the film's ending is set. Other scenes in the later half of the film were shot in late May and early June at the Villa del Balbianello on the shores of Lake Como. Further exterior shooting for the movie took place at properties such as the Villa la Gaeta, near the lakeside town of Menaggio.

A recreation of the Body Worlds exhibit provided a setting for one scene in the film. Among the Body Worlds plastinates featured in that scene were the '''' (which plays a key role in one scene) and ''''. The exhibition's developer and promoter, German anatomist Gunther von Hagens, also has a cameo appearance in the filmCasino Royale's Cold War Symbols, Featuring Body Worlds | http://commanderbond.net/article/3742.

On 30 July 2006, a fire broke out at the 007 Stage. The damage was significant, but had no effect on the release of ''Casino Royale'' as the incident occurred one week after filming had been completed, and the sets were in the process of being dismantled. On 11 August 2006, Pinewood Studios confirmed that no attempt would be made to salvage the remains of the stage, instead it would be rebuilt from scratch.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="14abd46a62dcb0139e8e61339767cdfb" name="Daniel_Craig_on_Venice_yacht_crop_w_Wilson" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/14abd46a62dcb0139e8e61339767cdfb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>