<document id="af97da7a883fc3efdc07490b2a552461-1.2" name="Calgary_Hitmen" cat="26">
<text>
Dean Clark took over the club early the previous season as head coach, and led the 1997–98 Hitmen to a remarkable turnaround. The team improved to a 40–28–4 record and first place finish in the Central Division, qualifying for the playoffs for the first time in franchise history. During the playoffs, the Hitmen defeated the Saskatoon Blades and Swift Current Broncos to reach the Eastern Conference final before falling to the Brandon Wheat Kings. Clark was awarded the Dunc McCallum Memorial Trophy as WHL Coach of the Year as well as the Canadian Hockey League's Brian Kilrea Coach of the Year Award. Calgary improved to 51–13–8 in 1998–99, finishing one point ahead of the Kamloops Blazers for the regular season title. Led by Brad Moran, Pavel Brendl and goaltender Alexandre Fomitchev, the Hitmen lost just five games in the playoffs en route to their first President's Cup, at home, before a WHL playoff record crowd of 17,139. The Hitmen became the first Calgary-based team to qualify for the Memorial Cup since the Calgary Canadians in 1926.

In the 1999 Memorial Cup, the Hitmen opened their tournament with a 5–3 victory over the Ontario Hockey League's Belleville Bulls, followed by a 4–3 loss to the host Ottawa 67's. The Hitmen followed with a 3–1 win over the Acadie-Bathurst Titan of the Quebec Major Junior Hockey League. Finishing atop the round robin standings, the Hitmen earned a bye into the championship game, and a rematch against the 67's. The championship game was a back-and-forth affair. Ottawa held 4–1 and 6–5 leads, while Calgary led 5–4 at one point and tied the game late to send it to overtime. The Hitmen fell short of winning the title however, as Ottawa's Matt Zultek won the game 1:58 into overtime. Brendl and Matt Kinch were named to the Memorial Cup All-Star team.

The Hitmen entered the 1999–2000 season with a strong squad, along with expectations at making another run to a Memorial Cup. The club finished the regular season with a record of 58–12–2–2, once again winning the regular season title. The team set franchise records for victories (58) and points (120), which stood until the 2008–09 year. After sweeping the Moose Jaw Warriors and Saskatoon Blades, the Hitmen were upset by the Kootenay Ice in the Eastern Conference final, falling four games to one.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="430649db5b9dac91bd871f671e6e7816" name="Hitmen_v_Oil_Kings" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/430649db5b9dac91bd871f671e6e7816.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>