<document id="b019e6865c0b6339de03c39c10e02009-1.1" name="Amanita_muscaria" cat="3">
<text>
''Amanita muscaria'' var. ''formosa'' sensu Thiers, southern Oregon Coast''Amanita muscaria'' is the type species of the genus ''Amanita''. By extension, it is also the type species of ''Amanita'' subgenus ''Amanita'', as well as section ''Amanita'' within this subgenus. ''Amanita'' subgenus ''Amanita'' includes all ''Amanita'' with inamyloid spores. ''Amanita'' section ''Amanita'' includes those species with patchy universal veil remnants, including a volva that is reduced to a series of concentric rings and the veil remnants on the cap being a series of patches or warts. Most species in this group also have a bulbous base. ''Amanita'' section ''Amanita'' consists of ''A. muscaria'' and its close relatives, including ''A. pantherina'' (the panther cap), ''A. gemmata'', ''A. farinosa'', and ''A. xanthocephala''. Modern fungal taxonomists have classified ''Amanita muscaria'' and its allies this way based on gross morphology and spore inamyloidy. Two recent molecular phylogenetic studies have confirmed this classification as natural.

''Amanita muscaria'' varies considerably in its morphology and many authorities recognize a number of subspecies or varieties within the species. In ''The Agaricales in Modern Taxonomy'', German mycologist Rolf Singer listed three subspecies, though without description: ''A. muscaria'' ssp. ''muscaria'', ''A. muscaria'' ssp. ''americana'', and ''A. muscaria'' ssp. ''flavivolvata''.

Contemporary authorities recognize up to seven varieties:
* var. '''''muscaria''''', the typical red-and-white spotted variety. Some authorities, such as Rodham Tulloss, only use this name for Eurasian and western Alaskan populations.
* var. '''''flavivolvata''''' is red, with yellow to yellowish-white warts, and occurs in the western regions of the North American continent, from southern Alaska down through the Rocky Mountains, through Central America, to at least Andean Colombia. Rodham Tulloss uses this name to describe all "typical" ''A. muscaria'' from indigenous New World populations from Alaska southward.
* var. '''''alba''''', an uncommon fungus, has a white to silvery white cap with white warts but otherwise similar to the usual form.
* var. '''''formosa''''', has a yellow to orange-yellow cap with yellowish or tan warts and stem. Some authorities use this name for all ''A. muscaria'' fitting this description worldwide (cf. Jenkins), others (cf. Tulloss) restrict its use to Eurasian populations. 

* var. '''''guessowii''''' is yellow to orange, with center of cap more orange or reddish orange than the outer part. It is found throughout North America, but is most common in northeastern North America, from Newfoundland and Quebec down to Tennessee. Some authorities (cf, Jenkins) treat these populations as part of ''A. muscaria'' var. ''formosa'', while others (cf, Tulloss) recognize it as a distinct variety.
* var. '''''persicina''''' is pinkish to orangish "melon" colored with poorly formed or absent remnants of universal veil on the stem and vasal bulb, known from the Southeastern Coastal areas of the U.S.A, described in 1977.
* var. '''''regalis''''' from Scandinavia and Alaska, is liver-brown and has yellow warts. It appears to be uniformly distinctive and some authorities (cf, Tulloss) treat it as a separate species, while others (cf, Jenkins) treat it as a variety of ''A. muscaria''.

A 2006 molecular phylogenetic study of different regional populations of ''A. muscaria'' by mycologist József Geml and colleagues found three distinct clades within this species representing, roughly, Eurasian, Eurasian "subalpine", and North American populations. Specimens belonging to all three clades have been found in Alaska; this has led to the hypothesis that this was the center of diversification of this species. The study also looked at four named varieties of this species: var. ''alba'', var. ''flavivolvata'', var. ''formosa'' (including var. ''guessowii''), and var. ''regalis'' from both areas. All four varieties were found within both the Eurasian and North American clades, evidence that these morphological forms are simply polymorphisms found throughout the species rather than distinct subspecies or varieties. Further molecular study by Geml and colleagues published in 2008 show these three genetic groups, plus a fourth associated with oak–hickory–pine forest in the southeastern United States, and two more on Santa Cruz Island in California, are delineated from each other enough genetically to be considered separate species; thus ''A. muscaria'' as it stands currently is a species complex. The complex also includes at least three other closely related taxa currently regarded as species: ''A. breckonii'' is a buff-capped mushroom associated with conifers from the Pacific Northwest, and the brown-capped ''A. gioiosa'' and ''A. heterochroma'' from the mediterranean and Sardinia alone respectively. Both these last two are found with ''Eucalyptus'' and ''Cistus'' trees and it is unclear whether they are native or have been introduced from Australia.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2247efe72999b432f85b0d1482c628a6" name="Amanita_muscaria_americana" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/2247efe72999b432f85b0d1482c628a6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>