<document id="b02710d7581ae2770e07ec4949f1d256-2" name="TAM_(tank)" cat="29">
<text>
A number of variants were built on the same chassis as the TAM tank.  The original program called for the design of an infantry fighting vehicle, and in 1977 the program finished manufacturing the prototype of the ''Vehículo de Combate Transporte de Personal'' (Personnel Transport Combat Vehicle), or VCTP.  The VCTP is able to transport a squad of 12 men, including the squad leader and nine riflemen.  The squad leader is situated in the turret of the vehicle; one rifleman sits behind him and another six are seated in the chassis, the eighth manning the hull machine gun and the ninth situated in the turret with the gunner.  All personnel can fire their weapons from inside the vehicle, and the VCTP's turret is armed with Rheinmetall's Rh-202 20 millimeter (.79 in) autocannon.  The VCTP holds 880 rounds for the autocannon, including subcaliber armor-piercing DM63 rounds.  It is also armed with a 7.62 millimeter FN MAG 60-20 mounted on the turret roof.  Infantry can dismount through a door on the rear of the hull.Mazarrasa, pp. 40–43  The commander has a day sight and seven observation periscopes, while the gunner has a day sight and three observation periscopes.Foss, ''Jane's Armour & Artillery 2004-2005'', p. 277



Variants also include the ''Vehículo de Combate de Artillería de 155 mm'' (155 millimeter Artillery Combat Vehicle), or VCA 155, and the ''Vehículo de Combate Transporte de Mortero'' (Mortar Transport Combat Vehicle), or VCTM.  The VCA-155 is an elongated TAM chassis fitted with Oto Melara's Palmaria 155 millimeter (6.1 in) self-propelled howitzer turret.Foss, ''Tank Recognition Guide'', p. 11  It carries 28 projectiles, 23 of which are stored in the turret bustle.Mazarrasa, p. 48  The VCTM carries an AM-50 120 millimeter (4.72 in) internal mortar, which has  a range of 9,500 meters (31167.98 ft) and a rate of fire of 8 to 12 shots per minute.  Based on the TAM chassis, the ''Vehículo de Combate Puesto de Mando'' (command combat vehicle), or VCPC, is another variant designed in 1982.Mazarrasa, pp. 43–44  The ''Vehículo de Combate Lanzacohetes'' (Rocket launcher combat vehicle), or VCLC, designed in 1986, is also based on the TAM chassis and can be fitted with both 160 mm (6.3 in.) and 350 millimeter (13.8 in.) rockets.  A combat ambulance, ''Vehículo de Combate Ambulancia'' (VCA), and an armored recovery vehicle, ''Vehículo de Combate de Recuperación'' (VCRT) are other combat variants of the tank.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b7fe4c11e31be75e6decd84efe26dbd3" name="Tam_paz" sectnum="2#1">../img/b7fe4c11e31be75e6decd84efe26dbd3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>