<document id="b02710d7581ae2770e07ec4949f1d256-3" name="TAM_(tank)" cat="29">
<text>
Production began in 1979, with the intent to build a total of 512 armored vehicles (200 tanks and 312 VCTP infantry fighting vehicles). Economic problems, however, ended production in 1983 with only 150 TAMs and 100 VCTPs built. These vehicles were produced by an Argentine company, ''Tanque Argentino Mediano Sociedad del Estado'' (or TAMSE) founded by the government in March 1980.  70% of the TAM's components were manufactured in Argentina, while the 30% manufactured in Germany corresponded to the transmission, optics and fire control system.  In 1983, 20 TAMs and 26 VCTPs were delivered to the Argentine Army after an original order of 80 TAMs by Peru was canceled due to budgetary issues.  In 1991, TAMSE and the TAM production line were shut down, although in 1994 TAMSE was reactivated to complete an order for 120 of both TAMs and VCTPs to replace the M4 Shermans in the 2nd Armored Cavalry Brigade of the Argentine Army. By 1995 the Argentine Army was equipped with 200 TAM tanks and 216 VCTP and VCPC armored vehicles.Mazarrasa, pp. 16–18  Although 25 VCA-155s were originally planned for production starting 1990,Mazarrasa, p. 45 only 19 were completed and delivered by 1995, along with 50 VCTMs.Mazarrasa, p. 18  No other variants of the TAM, including the VCLC, VAC and VCRT  were put into production due to budget restrictions.Foss, ''The Encyclopedia of Tanks and Armored Fighting Vehicles'', p. 250

The TAMSE plant is a 9,600 square meter (103,300 ft²) facility.  The factory is completely covered, with two warehouses for storing components, quality control laboratories, a project office, an engine test room and a firing range.  Also participating in the production of TAM and variant components were Argentine companies Military Factories General San Martín (manufacturing the chassis), Río Tercero (turret and armament) and Bator Cocchis, S.A.Mazarrasa, p. 17
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="57ecdf570eb2375423a58123b8a232a9" name="VCA_155" sectnum="3#1">../img/57ecdf570eb2375423a58123b8a232a9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>