<document id="b07f538d55c0927bd86da1d489c93f95-4" name="Sumatran_Rhinoceros" cat="3">
<text>
Sumatran Rhinoceroses are solitary creatures except for coupling before mating and during child rearing. Individuals have home ranges: bulls have territories as large as 50 km2 (19 sq mi) whereas females' ranges are 10–15 km2 (3.9–5.8 sq mi).  The ranges of females appear to be spaced apart; male ranges often overlap.  There is no evidence that Sumatran Rhinos defend their territory through fighting.  Marking their territory is done by scraping soil with their feet, bending saplings into distinctive patterns, and leaving excrement. The Sumatran Rhino is usually most active when eating, at dawn, and just after dusk. During the day the rhino wallows in mud baths to cool down and rest.  In the rainy season they move to higher elevation areas; in the cooler months they return to lower areas in their range.


The rhino spends a large part of its day in wallows.  When mud holes are unavailable, the rhino will deepen puddles with its feet and horns.  The wallowing behavior helps the rhino maintain its body temperature and protect its skin from ectoparasites and other insects.  Captive specimens of Sumatran Rhinoceros, deprived of adequate wallowing, have quickly developed broken and inflamed skins, suppurations, eye problems, inflamed nails, hair loss and eventually died.  One 20-month study of wallowing behavior found that the Sumatran Rhinoceros will visit no more than three wallows at any given time.  After 2–12 weeks using a particular wallow, the rhino will abandon it.  Typically, the rhino will wallow around midday for 2–3 hours at a time before venturing out for food.  Although in zoos the Sumatran Rhino has been observed wallowing less than 45 minutes a day, the study on wild animals found 80–300 minutes (an average of 166 minutes) per day spent in wallows.

There has been little opportunity to study epidemiology in the Sumatran Rhinoceros.  Ticks and gyrostigma were reported to cause deaths in captive animals in the 19th century.  The rhino is also known to be vulnerable to the blood disease surra which can be spread by horse-flies carrying parasitic trypanosomes; in 2004, all five rhinos at the Sumatran Rhinoceros Conservation Centre died over an 18-day period after becoming infected by the disease.  The Sumatran Rhino has no known predators other than humans.  Tigers and wild dogs may be capable of killing a calf, but calves stay close to their mother and the frequency of such killings is unknown.  Although the rhino's range overlaps with elephants and tapirs, the species do not appear to compete for food or habitat.  Elephants (''Elephas maximus'') and Sumatran Rhinos are even known to share trails and many smaller species such as deer, boar and wild dogs will use the trails that the rhinos and elephants create.

The Sumatran Rhino maintains trails across its range.  The trails fall into two types.  Main trails will be used by generations of rhinos to travel between important areas in the rhino's range, such as between salt licks, or between areas that are separated by inhospitable terrain.  In feeding areas the rhinos will make smaller trails, still covered by vegetation, to areas containing food the rhino eats.  Sumatran Rhino trails have been found that cross rivers deeper than 1.5 meters (5 ft) and about 50 meters (165 ft) across.  The currents of these rivers are known to be strong, but the rhino is a strong swimmer.  A relative absence of wallows near rivers in the range of the Sumatran Rhinoceros indicates that they may occasionally bathe in rivers in lieu of wallowing.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="913348eaf8442ebf5f194683692d08e3" name="Sumatran_Rhino_001" sectnum="4#1">../img/913348eaf8442ebf5f194683692d08e3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>