<document id="b07f538d55c0927bd86da1d489c93f95-2" name="Sumatran_Rhinoceros" cat="3">
<text>
A mature Sumatran Rhino stands about 120–145 centimetres (3.9–4.8 ft) high at the shoulder, has a body length of around  and weighs 500–800 kilograms (1100–1760 lb), though the largest individuals in zoos have been known to weigh as much as .  Like the African species, it has two horns.  The larger is the nasal horn, typically only 15–25 cm (6–10 in), though the longest recorded specimen was much longer at .  The posterior horn is much smaller, usually less than  long, and often little more than a knob.  The larger nasal horn is also known as the anterior horn; the smaller posterior horn as the frontal horn.  The horns are dark gray or black in color.  The males have larger horns than the females, though the species is not otherwise sexually dimorphic.  The Sumatran Rhino lives an estimated 30–45 years in the wild, while the record time in captivity is a female ''D. lasiotis'' who lived for 32 years and 8 months before dying in the London Zoo in 1900.

Two thick folds of skin encircle the body behind the front legs and before the hind legs.  The rhino has a smaller fold of skin around its neck.  The skin itself is thin, 10–16 mm (0.4–0.6 in), and in the wild the rhino appears to have no subcutaneous fat.  Hair can range from dense (the most dense hair in young calves) to scarce and is usually a reddish brown.  In the wild this hair is hard to observe because the rhinos are often covered in mud.  In captivity, however, the hair grows out and becomes much shaggier, likely because of less abrasion from walking through vegetation.  The rhino has a patch of long hair around the ears and a thick clump of hair at the end of the tail.  Like all rhinos, they have very poor vision.  The Sumatran Rhinoceros is fast and agile; it climbs mountains easily and comfortably traverses steep slopes and riverbanks.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a59b96bb4619e69a77d51ccc7f94abc3" name="Sumatran_Rhino_skeleton" sectnum="2#1">../img/a59b96bb4619e69a77d51ccc7f94abc3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>