<document id="b07f538d55c0927bd86da1d489c93f95-6" name="Sumatran_Rhinoceros" cat="3">
<text>
Aside from those few individuals kept in zoos and pictured in books, the Sumatran Rhinoceros has remained little known, overshadowed by the more common Indian, Black and White rhinos.  Recently, however, video footage of the Sumatran Rhinoceros in its native habitat and in breeding centers has been featured in several nature documentaries.  Extensive footage can be found in an Asia Geographic documentary ''The Littlest Rhino''. Natural History New Zealand showed footage of a Sumatran rhino, shot by freelance Indonesian-based cameraman Alain Compost, in the 2001 documentary ''The Forgotten Rhino'', which featured mainly Javan and Indian rhinos.

Though documented by droppings and tracks, pictures of the Bornean Rhinoceros were first taken and widely distributed by modern conservationists in April 2006 when camera traps photographed a healthy adult in the jungles of Sabah in Malaysian Borneo.  On April 24, 2007 it was announced that cameras had captured the first ever video footage of a wild Bornean Rhino.  The night-time footage showed the rhino eating, peering through jungle foliage, and sniffing the film equipment.  The World Wildlife Fund which took the video has used it in efforts to convince local governments to turn the area into a rhino conservation zone.Video of the Sumatran Rhinoceros is available on the .

A number of folk tales about the Sumatran Rhino were collected by colonial naturalists and hunters from the mid 1800s to early 1900s.  In Burma, the belief was once widespread that the Sumatran Rhino ate fire.  Tales described the fire-eating rhino following smoke to its source, especially camp-fires, and then attacking the camp.  There was also a Burmese belief that the best time to hunt was every July when the Sumatran Rhinos would congregate beneath the full moon.  In Malaya it was said that the rhino's horn was hollow and could be used as a sort of hose for breathing air and squirting water.  In Malaya and Sumatra it was once believed that the rhino shed its horn every year and buried it under the ground.  In Borneo, the rhino was said to have a strange carnivorous practice: after defecating in a stream it would turn around and eat fish that had been stupefied by the excrement.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="67c7945de050d21b630a2e01303a721b" name="Rauhohr-Nashorn-drawing" sectnum="6#1">../img/67c7945de050d21b630a2e01303a721b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>