<document id="b0c92e375a8c0700d2e4fab038f7a153-2.1" name="Mario_Vargas_Llosa" cat="17">
<text>
Vargas Llosa's first novel, ''The Time of the Hero'' (''La ciudad y los perros''), was published in 1963.  The book is set among a community of cadets in a Lima military school, and the plot is based on the author's own experiences at Lima's Leoncio Prado Military Academy. This early piece gained wide public attention and immediate success. Its vitality and adept use of sophisticated literary techniques immediately impressed critics, and it won the ''Premio de la Crítica Española'' award. Nevertheless, its sharp criticism of the Peruvian military establishment led to controversy in Peru. Several Peruvian generals attacked the novel, claiming that it was the work of a "degenerate mind" and stating that Vargas Llosa was "paid by Ecuador" to undermine the prestige of the Peruvian Army.

In 1965, Vargas Llosa followed ''The Time of the Hero'' with ''The Green House'' (''La casa verde''), about a brothel called "The Green House" and how its quasi-mythical presence affects the lives of the characters. The main plot follows Bonifacia, a girl who is about to receive the vows of the church, and her transformation into ''la Selvatica'', the best-known prostitute of "The Green House".  The novel immediately received an enthusiastic critical reception, confirming Vargas Llosa as an important voice of Latin American narrative. ''The Green House'' won the first edition of the Rómulo Gallegos International Novel Prize in 1967, contending with works by veteran Uruguayan writer Juan Carlos Onetti and by Gabriel García Márquez..  See also . This novel alone accumulated enough awards to place the author among the leading figures of the Latin American Boom. Some critics still consider ''The Green House'' to be Vargas Llosa's finest and most important achievement. Indeed, Latin American literary critic Gerald Martin suggests that ''The Green House'' is "one of the greatest novels to have emerged from Latin America".

Vargas Llosa's third novel, ''Conversation in the Cathedral'' (''Conversación en la catedral''), was published in 1969, when he was 33. This ambitious narrative is the story of Santiago Zavala, the son of a minister, and Ambrosio, his chauffeur. A random meeting at a dog pound leads the pair to a riveting conversation at a nearby bar known as "The Cathedral". During the encounter, Zavala searches for the truth about his father's role in the murder of a notorious Peruvian underworld figure, shedding light on the workings of a dictatorship along the way. Unfortunately for Zavala, his quest results in a dead end with no answers and no sign of a better future. The novel attacks the dictatorial government of Odría by showing how a dictatorship controls and destroys lives. The persistent theme of hopelessness makes ''Conversation in the Cathedral'' Vargas Llosa's most bitter novel.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bc66b5ae82cdf8517cb17b05422ce91d" name="Gallegos_-_Vargas_Llosa" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/bc66b5ae82cdf8517cb17b05422ce91d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>