<document id="b133b4dcf8c57bb419a377851078f1ac-3.7" name="Paulins_Kill" cat="11">
<text>
The Paulins Kill valley contains many protected areas. Swartswood State Park, established in 1914 as the first and oldest state park in New Jersey, is on 2,272 acres (919 ha) just north of the Paulins Kill Lake in Sussex County., official website, no further authorship information given, accessed December 20, 2006 Along Kittatinny Ridge in the northern part of the watershed are parts of Worthington State Forest (west), Delaware Water Gap National Recreation Area (central), and Stokes State Forests (east)., official website, no further authorship information given, accessed December 20, 2006, official website, no further authorship information given, accessed December 20, 2006, official website, no further authorship information given,  accessed December 20, 2006 In addition to these state forests, the Paulins Kill valley is host to a variety of common coniferous and deciduous trees, which have been harvested for lumber in the past, including: White and Black Oak, Buttonwood, Eastern Red Cedar, Eastern Hemlock, American Chestnut, Black Walnut, Tamarack Larch, Spruce, and Pine. Trees that add to the beauty of the fall foliage include Maple, Birch, Hickory, Elm, and Crab Apple.Schaeffer and Johnson, op. cit., 45 ff.

New Jersey's Green Acres program has targeted the Paulins Kill and its surrounding valley as an excellent natural resources for open space and farmland preservation and recreational opportunities.  The state, working together with agricultural development boards in Sussex and Warren Counties, and with the ''Ridge and Valley Conservancy'', a local nonprofit land trust, share land acquisition costs to enter tracts of real estate into the program. no further authorship information given, accessed August 24, 2006.  Since 1983, several farms across New Jersey have sold development rights to the county programs.  Sussex County has permanently preserved 12,242.39 acres (4,954.32 ha) of woodland and farmland., spreadsheet from the County of Sussex (New Jersey) no further authorship information given, accessed October 30, 2006.  Likewise, Warren County has preserved 100 farm properties, comprising over 12,200 acres (4,937 ha). (2004 Press Release) Warren County (NJ), no further authorship information given, accessed October 30, 2006. 

In addition, four Wildlife Management Areas (WMAs) are in the Paulins Kill valley: Bear Swamp WMA, Trout Brook WMA, White Lake WMA, and Columbia Lake WMA. Together they comprise 6,564 acres (2656 ha) of protected lands, mostly acquired through "Green Acres" funds., no further authorship information given, accessed December 20, 2006. Hunting and trapping are permitted in season in many of these protected areas. Common game animals include White-tailed Deer, Eastern Coyote, Red Fox, Gray Fox, Opossum, Eastern Cottontail Rabbit, Raccoon, Gray and Red Squirrel, Beaver, Muskrat, andWoodchuck or Groundhog. Common game birds include Ring-necked Pheasant, Eastern Wild Turkey, American Crow, and Canada Goose., no further authorship information given, accessed December 20, 2006. 

The Paulins Kill watershed is home to a variety of other animals. Other mammals include Eastern Chipmunk,  Porcupine, Black Bear, Striped Skunk, River Otter, and Bobcat., no further authorship information given, accessed December 20, 2006. Common northeastern American reptiles found there include snakes such as the American Copperhead,  Eastern Diamondback Rattlesnake, Northern Water Snake, Common Garter Snake and Milk Snake, and turtles, including the Eastern Box Turtle, and Common Snapping Turtle., no further authorship information given, accessed December 20, 2006.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c7e1d67678b2aaedb2f837f9a0cbac61" name="Goldfinch_tgo" sectnum="3.7#1">../img/c7e1d67678b2aaedb2f837f9a0cbac61.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>