<document id="b133b4dcf8c57bb419a377851078f1ac-2.4" name="Paulins_Kill" cat="11">
<text>
The first human settlement along the Paulins Kill was by early Native Americans circa 8,000–10,000 BC at the close of the last ice age (known as the Wisconsin glaciation). At the time of the first settlement by emigrating Europeans in this region, it was populated by the Munsee tribe of the Lenni Lenape (or Delaware) Indians.  Artifacts (often of stone, clay or bone) of the Native American culture are often found in nearby farm fields and at the site of their ancient villages.Schrabisch, Max. ''Indian habitations in Sussex County, New Jersey'' Geological Survey of New Jersey, Bulletin No. 13. (Union Hill, New Jersey: Dispatch Printing Company, 1915); and ''Archaeology of Warren and Hunterdon counties'' Geological Survey of New Jersey, Bulletin No. 18. (Trenton, N.J., MacCrellish and Quigley co., state printers, 1917).

Typically, early European settlement along the Paulins Kill was by Palatine Germans who had emigrated to the New World via the port of Philadelphia from 1720 to 1800. Many had trekked north through the valley of the Delaware and settled along the Musconetcong, Pequest and Paulins Kill valleys in New Jersey and along the Lehigh River valley in Pennsylvania.  Areas along the Paulins Kill generally were not settled until the 1740s and 1750s.Chambers, Theodore Frelinghuysen. ''The early Germans of New Jersey: Their History, Churches, and Genealogies''. (Dover, New Jersey, Dover Printing Company, 1895), passim. Often villages established and settled by German emigrants remained culturally German well into the Nineteenth Century, with German Lutheran and Reformed churches (often as "Union" churches) established shortly after the first settlements (as was the case in Knowlton and in Stillwater).  However, by the early Nineteenth Century, many descendants of these German settlers removed to newly opened lands in the West (i.e. Ohio, the Northwest Territory, the Southern Tier of New York) and those that remained had assimilated into English-speaking culture, and the German Reformed or Lutheran Churches often became Presbyterian.Schaeffer, Casper, M.D. and Johnson, William M. ''Memoirs and Reminiscences: Together with Sketches of the Early History of Sussex County, New Jersey.'' (Hackensack, New Jersey: Privately Printed, 1907). 42–43, 46–47; Chambers, op. cit., passim. The German cultural impact of this community can still be seen in local architecture&mdash;most notably in barns and in stone houses&mdash;and in cemeteries containing intricately carved gravestones often bearing archaic German text and funerary symbols.Viet, Richard F. "John Solomon Teetzel and the Anglo-German Gravestone Carving Tradition of 18th century Northwestern New Jersey" in ''Markers XVII'' (Richard E. Meyer, ed.), Journal of the Association for Gravestone Studies, XVII: 124–161 (2000). English, Scottish, Welsh settlers located in the Paulins Kill valley throughout the latter half of the eighteenth century, often traveling north from Philadelphia, or west from Long Island, Newark, and Elizabethtown (now Elizabeth).Schaeffer, Casper, M.D. and Johnson, William M. ''Memoirs and Reminiscences: Together with Sketches of the Early History of Sussex County, New Jersey.'' (Hackensack, New Jersey: Privately Printed, 1907). passim.; Snell, op. cit., passim.; Armstrong, William C. ''Pioneer Families of Northwestern New Jersey'' (Lambertville, New Jersey: Hunterdon House, 1979), passim; Stickney, Charles E. ''Old Sussex County families of the Minisink Region'' from articles in the ''Wantage Recorder'' (compiled by Virginia Alleman Brown) (Washington, N.J. : Genealogical Researchers, 1988), passim. 

The area around present-day Stillwater was first settled by the family of Casper Shafer (1712&ndash;1784), a Palatine German who had emigrated to Philadelphia a few years earlier.  Shafer, with his father-in-law, Johan Peter Bernhardt (?&ndash;1748), and his brother-in-law Johann Georg Windemuth (or John George Wintermute) (1711&ndash;1782), settled at Stillwater in 1742.  Both Shafer and Windemuth were married to Bernhardt's daughters.Wintermute, Jacob Perry. ''Wintermute Family History''. (Columbus, Ohio: Champlin Press, 1900); Wintermute, Leonard. ''Windemuth Family Heritage''.  (Baltimore, Maryland: Gateway Press, 1996).  Shafer, who operated a grist mill at Stillwater starting in 1746, transported flour, fruit, and other products by flatboat down the Paulins Kill and the Delaware River to the market in Philadelphia.  Most of the New Jersey shoreline and cities such as Elizabethtown and Newark were practically unknown to the German settlers along the Paulins Kill who learned of the existence of these cities only through trade with the local Lenni Lenape.Schaeffer and Johnson. op. cit., 33.; Snell, op. cit., passim. Part of this was because of the incredible hardship of an overland journey east to these cities resulting from a lack of roads.

The first road connecting Elizabethtown, and Morristown with settlements along the Delaware River, was the Military Road built by Jonathan Hampton (1711–1777) in 1755–1756. at Delaware Water Gap National Recreation Area website, no further authorship information given, accessed October 29, 2006. This road, which crosses the Paulins Kill at present-day Baleville, in Hampton Township, was built to supply fortifications built in the Delaware valley at this time to protect New Jersey during the French and Indian War. Very few passable, large roads were built in this section of New Jersey, then largely a sparsely populated wilderness, before the creation of turnpike companies in the early decades of the Nineteenth Century.  During much of the mid-eighteenth century, trade in the northwestern reaches of New Jersey was conducted through Philadelphia by way of the Delaware River.Schaeffer and Johnson, loc. cit.

About the year 1760, Mark Thomson (1739–1803) settled in Hardwick Township (now Frelinghuysen Township) and erected a gristmill and sawmill on the Paulins Kill.  The settlement that arose was later named Marksboro in his honour.  Thomson, who removed to Changewater in Hunterdon County, became an officer in the Continental Army during the American Revolution, and served two terms in the House of Representatives.Snell, op. cit., passim.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="db679085fc2de4918e8fa43e3fa73646" name="Caspershaferhouse1741" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/db679085fc2de4918e8fa43e3fa73646.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>