<document id="b133b4dcf8c57bb419a377851078f1ac-2.5" name="Paulins_Kill" cat="11">
<text>
From the standpoint of conservation, the Paulins Kill has benefited from having remained chiefly a pastoral river in a largely undeveloped area of New Jersey. No significant industry had developed since the 1740s to cause irreversible damage to the flow of the river or to heavily pollute its waters.  During this time, the river was dammed to provide power to the only industries established in these small rural towns:  grist, saw, oil, and fulling mills.Snell, op. cit., passim. Many of the dams that once powered the mills, and the electrical power plant at Branchville established in 1903, have been breached, or no longer impede the flow of the river., no further authorship information given, accessed October 29, 2006.

Columbia, a hamlet near the mouth of the Paulins Kill in Knowlton Township, was known for a large glass manufacturing factory. Near Columbia, the Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad also constructed the Paulinskill Viaduct (known also as the ''Hainesburg Viaduct''), a bridge crossing the Paulins Kill along the Lackawanna Cut-Off rail corridor.  Begun in 1908, this bridge was deemed an engineering marvel for its use of reinforced concrete.  Spanning 1,100 feet (335 m) across the Paulins Kill Valley, the Viaduct rises 115 feet (35 m) above the valley floor, and opened for rail traffic in 1911.Cunningham, John T. ''Railroad Wonder: The Lackawanna Cut-Off'' (Newark, New Jersey: Newark Sunday News, 1961). NO ISBNRichman, Steven M. ''The Bridges Of New Jersey: Portraits Of Garden State Crossings'' (New Brunswick, New Jersey: Rutgers University Press, 2005). ISBN 0-8135-3510-7 by Don Barnicle and Paula Williams in ''Skylands Magazine'', accessed October 29, 2006. It was the largest such viaduct in the world until 1915, when the Lackawanna Railroad opened the Tunkhannock Viaduct in Nicholson, Pennsylvania spanning over twice the Paulinskill Viaduct's length.
 at the American Society of Civil Engineers website (ASCE.org), accessed October 29, 2006. Currently abandoned, several plans are underway by New Jersey Transit to open the route as a passenger line to Scranton, Pennsylvania., New Jersey Transit, (www.NJTransit.com), no further authorship information given, (April 2005), accessed October 29, 2006.  This site is commonly visited by adventure-seeking individuals., by 
"Myke L.", no further authorship information given, accessed October 29, 2006. Today Interstate 80 crosses the Paulins Kill near Columbia.

However, despite its rural character, the Paulins Kill is still impacted by pollution, chiefly through nearby residential developments and farm run-off (agricultural pesticides and fertilizers), known as "non-point pollution."  Several farms are located along the banks of the Paulins Kill, raising crops including such grain-producing grasses as alfalfa, wheat, corn, hay (and historically barley, buckwheat and rye). Fruit trees in orchards produce cherries, apple, plum, peach and pear, while native wild grape vines, and Blackberry bushes are also found in the valley.

The New Jersey Public Interest Research Group (NJPIRG) has ranked the Paulins Kill as the seventh in a collection of rivers and creeks in a Top 30 listing of ''New Jersey waterways to Save'' (Press Release), November 21, 2001 at the NJPIRG website, no further authorship information given, accessed October 29, 2006. Also, New Jersey's Department of Environmental Protection often brings civil actions against local firms that deliberately pollute in the Paulins Kill watershed, most recently levying a $121,500 fine against a Sussex County shopping mall owner who discharged pollutants from a sewage treatment facility into the main branch near Newton, New Jersey between 1996 and 1998. (Press Release) at NJDEP website, no further authorship information given, accessed October 29, 2006.  

Recent development, prompted by an enlarging New York City Metropolitan area, has led to development issues which could threaten the Paulins Kill's future.  A public sewer and water project in Branchville, New Jersey was halted in the 2000 out of concern for a population of Dwarf wedgemussels (''Alasmidonta heterodon''), an endangered species.  This project was reauthorized in 2002."Branchville Sewer Plant May Still Be Built" by Jamie Goldenbaum in ''New Jersey Herald'' (April 16, 2002), transcribed at , accessed October 29, 2006. The Paulins Kill is also home to a wide variety of amphibians, including the Spotted Salamander, Red Spotted Newt, American Toad, Fowler's Toad, American Bull Frog and others., no further authorship information given, accessed December 20, 2006.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1bfc62d4575a72f270707efc02bc8d9a" name="October_2006_021" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/1bfc62d4575a72f270707efc02bc8d9a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>