<document id="b17103126d7f2be5f09567c19aec17d1-4" name="Magic_Johnson" cat="26">
<text>
In 905 NBA games, Johnson scored 17,707 points, 6,559 rebounds, and 10,141 assists, translating to career averages of 19.5 points, 7.2 rebounds, and 11.2 assists per game. Johnson shares the single-game playoff record for assists (24), holds the Finals record for assists in a game (21), and has the most playoff assists (2,346). He holds the All-Star Game single-game record for assists (22), and the All-Star Game record for career assists (127).
Johnson introduced a fast-paced style of basketball called "Showtime", described as a mix of "no-look passes off the fastbreak, pin-point alley-oops from halfcourt, spinning feeds and overhand bullets under the basket through triple teams." Fellow Lakers guard Michael Cooper said, "There have been times when  has thrown passes and I wasn't sure where he was going. Then one of our guys catches the ball and scores, and I run back up the floor convinced that he must've thrown it through somebody." Johnson was exceptional because he played point guard despite being 6 ft 9 in (2.06 m), a size reserved normally for frontcourt players. He combined the size of a power forward, the one-on-one skills of a swingman, and the ball handling talent of a guard, making him one of the most dangerous triple-double threats of all time; his 138 triple-double games are second only to Oscar Robertson's 181.

For his feats, Johnson was voted as one of the 50 Greatest Players of All Time by the NBA in 1996, and was inducted into the Basketball Hall of Fame in 2002. ESPN's ''SportsCentury'' ranked Johnson #17 in their "50 Greatest Athletes of the 20th Century""#17: Magic Johnson". ''ESPN's SportsCentury 50 Greatest Athletes of the 20th Century''. 1 October 1999.  In 2006, ESPN.com rated Johnson the greatest point guard of all time, stating, "It could be argued that he's the one player in NBA history who was better than Michael Jordan." Several of his achievements in individual games have also been named among the top moments in the NBA.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3a642923965b47c74759a6218343cea2" name="LakersRetiredJerseys" sectnum="4#1">../img/3a642923965b47c74759a6218343cea2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>