<document id="b22ba8256eab5a211a56f3a6e8553469-6.7" name="Sir_Gawain_and_the_Green_Knight" cat="17">
<text>
Scholars have puzzled over the Green Knight's symbolism since the discovery of the poem. He could be a version of the Green Man, a mythological being connected with nature in medieval art, a Christian symbol, or the Devil himself. British medieval scholar C. S. Lewis said the character was "as vivid and concrete as any image in literature" and J. R. R. Tolkien said he was the "most difficult character" to interpret in ''Sir Gawain''. His major role in Arthurian literature is that of a judge and tester of knights, thus he is at once terrifying, friendly, and mysterious.Besserman, Lawrence. "The Idea of the Green Knight." ''ELH''. (Summer, 1986) 53.2 pp. 219–239. The Johns Hopkins University Press. He appears in only two other poems: ''The Greene Knight'' and ''King Arthur and King Cornwall''.Hahn, Thomas. "The Greene Knight". In ''Sir Gawain: Eleven Romances and Tales''. Western Michigan University Medieval Institute Publications, 2000 p. 314. ISBN 1-879288-59-1Hahn, Thomas. "King Arthur and King Cornwall". In ''Sir Gawain: Eleven Romances and Tales''. Western Michigan University Medieval Institute Publications, 2000. p. 427. ISBN 1-879288-59-1 Scholars have attempted to connect him to other mythical characters, such as Jack in the Green of British tradition but no definitive connection has yet been established.Lasater, Alice E. ''Spain to England: A Comparative Study of Arabic, European, and English Literature of the Middle Ages''. University Press of Mississippi, 1974. ISBN 0-878-05056-6Rix, Michael M. "A Re-Examination of the Castleton Garlanding". ''Folklore''. (June 1953) 64.2 pp. 342–344

However, there is a possibility, as Alice Buchanan has argued, that the color green is erroneously attributed to the Green Knight due to a mistranslation or misunderstanding of the Irish word 'glas', which could either mean gray or green. In the Death of Curoi (one of the Irish stories from Bricriu's Feast), Curoi stands in for Bertilak, and is often called "the man of the gray mantle". Though the words usually used for gray in the Death of Curoi are 'lachtna' or 'odar', roughly meaning milk-colored and shadowy respectively, in later works featuring a green knight, the word 'glas' is used and may have been the basis of misunderstanding.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f48717576b6a9983d185f13690c7eb36" name="JWW_TheLadyOfShallot_1888" sectnum="6.7#1">../img/f48717576b6a9983d185f13690c7eb36.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>