<document id="b22ba8256eab5a211a56f3a6e8553469-7.12" name="Sir_Gawain_and_the_Green_Knight" cat="17">
<text>
Many critics argue that ''Sir Gawain and the Green Knight'' should be viewed, above all, as a romance. Medieval romances typically recount the marvellous adventures of a chivalrous, heroic knight, often of super-human ability, who abides by chivalry's strict codes of honour and demeanour, embarks upon a quest and defeats monsters, thereby winning the favour of a lady. Thus, medieval romances focus not on love and sentiment (as the term "romance" implies today), but on adventure.Frye, Northrop. ''Anatomy of Criticism'', p. 186. ISBN 0-691-01298-9

Gawain's function, as medieval scholar Alan Markman says, "is the function of the romance hero … to stand as the champion of the human race, and by submitting to strange and severe tests, to demonstrate human capabilities for good or bad action." Through Gawain's adventure, it becomes clear that he is merely human. The reader becomes attached to this human view in the midst of the poem’s romanticism, relating to Gawain’s humanity while respecting his knightly qualities. Gawain "shows us what moral conduct is. We shall probably not equal his behaviour, but we admire him for pointing out the way."Markman, Alan M. "The Meaning of Sir Gawain and the Green Knight". ''PMLA''. (September 1957) 72.4 pp. 574–586

In viewing the poem as a chivalric romance, many scholars see it as intertwining chivalric and courtly love laws under the English Order of the Garter. The group's motto, 'honi soit qui mal y pense', or "Shamed be he who finds evil here," is written at the end of the poem. Some critics describe Gawain's peers wearing girdles of their own as evidence of the origin of the Order of the Garter. However, in the parallel poem, ''The Greene Knight'', the lace is white, not green, and is considered the origin of the collar worn by the knights of the Bath, not the Order of the Garter.''Sir Gawain and the Green Knight'', second edition. Ed. J.R.R. Tolkien and E.V. Gordon, 1925, note to lines 2514ff. ASIN B000IPU84U The motto on the poem was probably written by a copyist and not by the original author. Still, the connection made by the copyist to the Order is not extraordinary.''The Norton Anthology of English Literature'', eighth edition, Vol. B. Ed. Stephen Greenblatt. New York, London: W. W. Norton and Co., 2006, p. 213 (footnote). ISBN 0393928330
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ec04b1f2f89c9d46091259f00f0be8ef" name="Pettie,_The_Vigil" sectnum="7.12#1">../img/ec04b1f2f89c9d46091259f00f0be8ef.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>