<document id="b22ba8256eab5a211a56f3a6e8553469-7.14" name="Sir_Gawain_and_the_Green_Knight" cat="17">
<text>
Feminist literary critics see the poem as portraying women's ultimate power over men. Morgan le Fay and Bertilak's wife, for example, are the most powerful characters in the poem—Morgan especially, as she begins the game by enchanting the Green Knight. The girdle and Gawain's scar can be seen as symbols of feminine power, each of them diminishing Gawain's masculinity. Gawain's misogynist passage,Mills, David. "The Rhetorical Function of Gawain's Antifeminism?" ''Neuphilologische Mitteilungen''. (1970) 71 pp. 635–4. in which he blames all of his troubles on women and lists the many men who have fallen prey to women's wiles, further supports the feminist view of ultimate female power in the poem.

In contrast, others argue that the poem focuses mostly on the opinions, actions, and abilities of men. For example, on the surface, it appears that Bertilak’s wife is a strong leading character.Burns, E. Jane. "Courtly Love: Who Needs It? Recent Feminist Work in the Medieval Tradition". ''Signs''. (Autumn 2001) 27.1 pp. 23–57. Retrieved on 7 September 2007 from
  By adopting the masculine role, she appears to be an empowered individual, particularly in the bedroom scene. This is not entirely the case, however. While the Lady is being forward and outgoing, Gawain’s feelings and emotions are the focus of the story, and Gawain stands to gain or lose the most.Burns, p. 24 The Lady "makes the first move", so to speak, but Gawain ultimately decides what is to become of those actions. He, therefore, is in charge of the situation and even the relationship.

In the bedroom scene, both the negative and positive actions of the Lady are motivated by her desire.Rowley, Sharon M. "Textual Studies, Feminism, and Performance in Sir Gawain and the Green Knight". ''The Chaucer Review''. (2003) Vol. 38 pp. 158–177. Her feelings cause her to step out of the typical female role and into that of the male, thus becoming more empowered.Rowley, p. 161 At the same time, those same actions make the Lady appear adulterous; some scholars compare her with Eve in the Bible.Cox, p. 378 By forcing Gawain to take her girdle, i.e. the apple, the pact made with Bertilak—and therefore the Green Knight—is broken.Cox, p. 379 In this sense, it is clear that at the hands of the Lady, Gawain is a "good man seduced".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9be04754aa1ec0698496a879b7b68ae6" name="Lady_tempt_Gawain" sectnum="7.14#1">../img/9be04754aa1ec0698496a879b7b68ae6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>