<document id="b2dc02e795f8d5054cf6ea61c8f3af4d-1.5" name="B_movie" cat="19">
<text>
Despite all the transformations in the industry, by 1961 the average production cost of an American feature film was still only $2 million—after adjusting for inflation, less than 10 percent more than it had been in 1950. The traditional twin bill of B film preceding and balancing a subsequent-run A film had largely disappeared from American theaters. The AIP-style dual genre package was the new model. In July 1960, the latest Joseph E. Levine sword-and-sandals import, ''Hercules Unchained'', opened at neighborhood theaters in New York. A suspense film, ''Terror Is a Man'', ran as a "co-feature" with a now familiar sort of exploitation gimmick: "The dénouement helpfully includes a 'warning bell' so the sensitive can 'close their eyes.'"Thompson (1960). That year, Roger Corman took AIP down a new road: "When they asked me to make two ten-day black-and-white horror films to play as a double feature, I convinced them instead to finance one horror film in color."Quoted in Di Franco (1979), p. 97. ''House of Usher'' typifies the continuing ambiguities of B picture classification. It was clearly an A film by the standards of both director and studio, with the longest shooting schedule and biggest budget Corman had ever enjoyed. But it is generally seen as a B movie: the schedule was still a mere fifteen days, the budget just $200,000 (one-tenth the industry average),Per Corman, quoted in Di Franco (1979), p. 97. and its 85-minute running time close to an old thumbnail definition of the B: "Any movie that runs less than 80 minutes."Quoted in Reid (2005a), p. 5.

With the loosening of industry censorship constraints, the 1960s saw a major expansion in the commercial viability of a variety of B movie subgenres that came to be known collectively as ''exploitation films''. The combination of intensive and gimmick-laden publicity with movies featuring vulgar subject matter and often outrageous imagery dated back decades—the term had originally defined truly fringe productions, made at the lowest depths of Poverty Row or entirely outside the Hollywood system. Many graphically depicted the wages of sin in the context of promoting prudent lifestyle choices, particularly "sexual hygiene." Audiences might see explicit footage of anything from a live birth to a ritual circumcision.Schaefer (1999), pp. 187, 376. Such films were not generally booked as part of movie theaters' regular schedules but rather presented as special events by traveling roadshow promoters (they might also appear as fodder for "grindhouses", which typically had no regular schedule at all). The most famous of those promoters, Kroger Babb, was in the vanguard of marketing low-budget, sensationalistic films with a "100% saturation campaign," inundating the target audience with ads in almost any imaginable medium.Schaefer (1999), p. 118. In the era of the traditional double feature, no one would have characterized these graphic exploitation films as "B movies." With the majors having exited traditional B production and exploitation-style promotion becoming standard practice at the lower end of the industry, "exploitation" became a way to refer to the entire field of low-budget genre films. The 1960s would see exploitation-style themes and imagery become increasingly central to the realm of the B.

Exploitation movies in the original sense continued to appear: 1961's ''Damaged Goods'', a cautionary tale about a young lady whose boyfriend’s promiscuity leads to venereal disease, comes complete with enormous, grotesque closeups of VD's physical effects. review of DVD release with historical analysis by Bill Gibron, July 24, 2003; part of the ''DVD Verdict'' website. Retrieved 11/17/06. At the same time, the concept of fringe exploitation was merging with a related, similarly venerable tradition: “nudie" films featuring nudist-camp footage or striptease artists like Bettie Page had simply been the softcore pornography of previous decades. As far back as 1933, ''This Nude World'' was "Guaranteed the Most Educational Film Ever Produced!"Halperin (2006), p. 201. In the late 1950s, as more of the old grindhouse theaters devoted themselves specifically to "adult" product, a few filmmakers began making nudies with greater attention to plot. Best known was Russ Meyer, who released his first successful narrative nudie, ''The Immoral Mr. Teas'', in 1959. Five years later, on a sub-$100,000 budget, Meyer came out with ''Lorna'', "a harder-edged film that combined sex with gritty realism and violence." A talented director, Meyer would gain renown for so-called sexploitation pictures such as ''Faster, Pussycat! Kill! Kill!'' (1965) and ''Vixen!'' (1968). These films were largely relegated to the fringe circuit of "adult" theaters, while AIP teen movies with wink-wink titles like ''Beach Blanket Bingo'' (1965) and ''How to Stuff a Wild Bikini'' (1966), starring Annette Funicello and Frankie Avalon, played drive-ins and other reputable venues. Roger Corman's ''The Trip'' (1967) for American International, written by veteran AIP/Corman actor Jack Nicholson, never shows a fully bared, unpainted breast, but flirts with nudity throughout. The Meyer and Corman lines were drawing closer.

One of the most influential films of the era, on Bs and beyond, was Paramount's ''Psycho''. Its $8.5 million in earnings against a production cost of $800,000 made it the most profitable movie of 1960.Cook (2000), p. 222. Its mainstream distribution without the Production Code seal of approval helped weaken U.S. film censorship. And, as William Paul notes, this move into the horror genre by respected director Alfred Hitchcock was made, "significantly, with the lowest-budgeted film of his American career and the least glamorous stars.  greatest initial impact...was on schlock horror movies (notably those from second-tier director William Castle), each of which tried to bill itself as scarier than ''Psycho''."Paul (1994), p. 33. Castle's first film in the ''Psycho'' vein was ''Homicidal'' (1961), an early step in the development of the slasher subgenre that would take off in the late 1970s. ''Blood Feast'' (1963), a movie about human dismemberment and culinary preparation made for approximately $24,000 by experienced nudie-maker Herschell Gordon Lewis, established a new, more immediately successful subgenre, the gore or splatter film. Lewis's business partner David F. Friedman drummed up publicity by distributing vomit bags to theatergoers—the sort of gimmick Castle had mastered—and arranging for an injunction against the film in Sarasota, Florida—the sort of problem exploitation films had long run up against, except Friedman had planned it.Rockoff (2002), pp. 32–33. This new breed of gross-out movie typifies the emerging sense of "exploitation"—the progressive adoption of traditional exploitation and nudie elements into horror, into other classic B genres, and into the low-budget film industry as a whole. Imports of Hammer Film's increasingly explicit horror movies and Italian gialli, highly stylized pictures mixing sexploitation and ultraviolence, would fuel this trend.

The Production Code was officially scrapped in 1968, to be replaced by the first version of the modern rating system. That year, two horror films came out that heralded directions American cinema would take in the next decade, with major consequences for the B movie. One was a high-budget Paramount production, directed by the celebrated Roman Polanski. Produced by B horror veteran William Castle, ''Rosemary's Baby'' "took the genre up-market for the first time since the 1930s."Cook (2000), pp. 222–223. It was a critical success and the year's seventh-biggest hit. The other was George Romero's now classic ''Night of the Living Dead'', produced on weekends in and around Pittsburgh for $114,000. Building on the achievement of B genre predecessors like ''Invasion of the Body Snatchers'' in its subtextual exploration of social and political issues, it doubled as a highly effective thriller and an incisive allegory for both the Vietnam War and domestic racial conflicts. Its greatest influence, though, derived from its clever subversion of genre clichés and the connection made between its exploitation-style imagery, low-cost, truly independent means of production, and high profitability.Cook (2000), p. 223. With the Code gone and the X rating established, major studio A films like ''Midnight Cowboy'' could now show "adult" imagery, while the market for increasingly hardcore pornography exploded. In this transformed commercial context, work like Russ Meyer's gained a new legitimacy. In 1969, for the first time a Meyer film, ''Finders Keepers, Lovers Weepers!'', was reviewed in the ''The New York Times''.Canby (1969). Soon, Corman would be putting out nudity-filled sexploitation pictures such as ''Private Duty Nurses'' (1971) and ''Women in Cages'' (1971).

In May 1969, the most important of all exploitation movies premiered at the Cannes Film Festival. Much of its significance owes to the fact that it was produced for a respectable, if still modest, budget and released by a major studio. The project was first taken by one of its cocreators, Peter Fonda, to American International. Fonda had become AIP's top star in the Corman-directed ''The Wild Angels'' (1966), a biker movie, and ''The Trip'', as in LSD. The idea Fonda pitched would combine those two proven themes. AIP was intrigued but balked at giving his collaborator, Dennis Hopper, also a studio alumnus, free directorial rein. Eventually they arranged a financing and distribution deal with Columbia, as two more graduates of the Corman/AIP exploitation mill joined the project: Jack Nicholson and cinematographer László Kovács. The film (which incorporated another favorite exploitation theme, the redneck menace, as well as a fair amount of nudity) was brought in at a cost of $501,000. ''Easy Rider'' earned $19.1 million in rentals and became "the seminal film that provided the bridge between all the repressed tendencies represented by schlock/kitsch/hack since the dawn of Hollywood and the mainstream cinema of the seventies."Quote: Cagin and Dray (1984), p. 53. General history: Cagin and Dray (1984), pp. 61–66. Financial figures: per associate producer William L. Hayward, cited in Biskind (1998), p. 74.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3a1b784488e6a602ed69f20725b32ec4" name="MotorpsychoPoster" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/3a1b784488e6a602ed69f20725b32ec4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>