<document id="b2e9f9a1f627ec881f82495153e6f852-1.1" name="Sharon_Tate" cat="19">
<text>
Sharon Tate was born in Dallas, Texas, the first of three daughters, to Paul Tate, a United States Army officer, and his wife, Doris. At six months of age, Sharon Tate won the "Miss Tiny Tot of Dallas Pageant", but the Tates held no show business ambitions for their daughter. Paul Tate was promoted and transferred several times. By age 16, Sharon Tate had lived in six different American cities, and she found it difficult to maintain friendships. Her family described her as shy and lacking in self-confidence, and as an adult Sharon Tate commented that people often misinterpreted her shyness for aloofness until they knew her better.

As she matured, people commented on her beauty; she began entering beauty pageants, winning the title of "Miss Richland" in 1959. She spoke of her ambition to study psychiatry, and also stated her intention to compete in the "Miss Washington" pageant in 1960, but before she could follow either course of action, Paul Tate was transferred to Italy, taking his family with him.

On arriving in Verona, Sharon Tate learned that she had become a local celebrity owing to the publication of a photograph of her in a bathing suit on the cover of the military newspaper ''Stars and Stripes''. She discovered a kinship with other students at the American school she attended in nearby Vicenza, recognizing that their backgrounds and feelings of separation were similar to her own, and for the first time in her life began to form lasting friendships. Tate and her friends became interested in the filming of ''Adventures of a Young Man'', which was being made nearby with Paul Newman, Susan Strasberg and Richard Beymer, and obtained parts as film extras. Beymer noticed Tate in the crowd and introduced himself, and the two dated during the production of the film, with Beymer encouraging Tate to pursue a film career. In 1961, Tate was employed by the singer Pat Boone, and appeared with him in a television special he made in Venice.


Later that  year, when ''Barabbas'' was being filmed near Verona, Tate was once again hired as an extra. Actor Jack Palance was impressed by her appearance and her attitude, although her role was too small to judge her talent. He arranged a screen test for her in Rome, but this did not lead to further work. Tate returned to the United States alone, saying she wanted to further her studies, but tried to find film work. After a few months, Doris Tate, who feared for her daughter's safety, suffered a nervous breakdown and, after much coercion from her family, Tate returned to Italy.

The Tate family returned to the United States in 1962, and Sharon Tate moved to Los Angeles, where she contacted Richard Beymer's agent, Harold Gefsky. After their first meeting Gefsky agreed to represent her, and secured work for her in television and magazine advertisements. In 1963 he introduced her to Martin Ransohoff, director of Filmways, Inc., who signed her to a seven-year contract. Tate was considered for a lead role on ''Petticoat Junction'', but Ransohoff realized that she was too inexperienced to handle an important role. He gave her small parts in ''Mr. Ed'' and ''The Beverly Hillbillies'' to help her gain experience. Ransohoff signed Tate to an exclusive seven year contract but kept her under wraps until he felt she was ready to appear in substantial film roles. "Mr. Ransohoff didn't want the audience to see me till I was ready," Tate was quoted in a 1967 article in ''Playboy'' magazine.

During this time Tate met the French actor Philippe Forquet, and began a relationship with him. They became engaged, but the relationship was volatile and they frequently quarreled. After a violent confrontation with Forquet, Tate required hospital treatment for her injuries, and subsequently ended the relationship.

In 1964, she met Jay Sebring, a former sailor who had established himself as a leading hair stylist in Hollywood. Tate later said that Sebring's nature was especially gentle, but when he proposed marriage she would not accept. She said that she would retire from acting as soon as she married, and at that time she intended to focus on her career.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d0b4cc32f210e44dd8ccbb25ec731be7" name="Max_Baer_Jr,_Nancy_Kulp_and_Sharon_Tate_in_The_Beverly_Hillbillies,_The_Giant_Jackrabbit_episode" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/d0b4cc32f210e44dd8ccbb25ec731be7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>