<document id="b2e9f9a1f627ec881f82495153e6f852-2.6" name="Sharon_Tate" cat="19">
<text>
In the early 1980s, Stephen Kay, who had worked for the prosecution in the trial, became alarmed that Leslie Van Houten had gathered 900 signatures on a petition for her parole. He contacted Sharon Tate's mother, who said she was sure she could do better, and the two mounted a publicity campaign, collecting over 350,000 signatures supporting the denial of parole. Van Houten had been seen as the most likely of the killers to be paroled; following Kay's and Tate's efforts, her petition was denied.  Doris Tate became a vocal advocate for victims' rights and, in discussing her daughter's murder and meeting other crime victims, assumed the role of counselor, using her profile to encourage public discussion and criticism of the corrections system.

For the rest of her life she strongly campaigned against the parole of each of the Manson killers, and worked closely with other victims of violent crime.  Several times she confronted Charles Watson at parole hearings, explaining, "I feel that Sharon has to be represented in that hearing room. If they're  pleading for their lives, then I have to be there representing her." She addressed Watson directly during her victim impact statement in 1984: "What mercy, sir, did you show my daughter when she was begging for her life? What mercy did you show my daughter when she said, 'Give me two weeks to have my baby and then you can kill me'?.... When will Sharon come up for parole?  Will these seven victims and possibly more walk out of their graves if you get paroled? You cannot be trusted."

In 1992, President George H. W. Bush recognized Doris Tate as one of his "thousand points of light" for her volunteer work on behalf of victims' rights.  By this time Tate had been diagnosed with a malignant brain tumor and her health and strength were failing; her meeting with Bush marked her final public appearance. When she died later that year, her youngest daughter Patti continued her work. She contributed to the 1993 foundation of the '''Doris Tate Crime Victims Bureau''', a non-profit organization which aims to influence crime legislation throughout the United States and to give greater rights and protection to victims of violent crime. Retrieved July 13, 2005. In 1995, the "Doris Tate Crime Victims Foundation" was founded as a non-profit organization to promote public awareness of the judicial system and to provide support to the victims of violent crime.. Retrieved July 13, 2005.

Patti Tate confronted David Geffen and board members of Geffen Records in 1993 over plans to include a song written by Charles Manson on the Guns N' Roses album ''"The Spaghetti Incident?"''. She commented to a journalist that the record company was "putting Manson up on a pedestal for young people who don't know who he is to worship like an idol."

After Patti's death from breast cancer in 2000, her older sister Debra continued to represent the Tate family at parole hearings. Debra Tate said of the killers: "They don't show any personal responsibility. They haven't made atonement to any one of my family members." She has also unsuccessfully lobbied for Sharon Tate to be awarded a star on the Hollywood Walk of Fame.

Colonel Paul Tate preferred not to make public comments; however, he was a constant presence during the murder trial, and in the following years attended parole hearings with his wife, and wrote letters to authorities in which he strongly opposed any suggestion of parole. He died in May 2005.. May 25, 2005. Retrieved July 13, 2005. Tate Family Legacy website. Retrieved September 27, 2009.

Roman Polanski gave away all of his possessions after the murders, unable to bear any reminders of the period that he called "the happiest I ever was in my life". He remained in Los Angeles until the killers were arrested and then traveled to Europe. His 1979 film ''Tess'' was dedicated "For Sharon", as Tate had read Thomas Hardy's ''Tess of the d'Urbervilles'' during her final stay with Polanski in London, and had left it for him to read with the comment that it would be a good story for them to film together. He tried to explain his anguish after the murder of his wife and unborn son in his 1984 autobiography ''Roman by Polanski'', saying "Since Sharon's death, and despite appearances to the contrary, my enjoyment of life has been incomplete. In moments of unbearable personal tragedy some people find solace in religion. In my case the opposite happened. Any religious faith I had was shattered by Sharon's murder. It reinforced my faith in the absurd."

In July 2005 Polanski successfully sued ''Vanity Fair'' magazine for libel after it stated that he had tried to seduce a woman on his way to Tate's funeral. Among the witnesses who testified on his behalf were Debra Tate and Mia Farrow. Describing Polanski immediately after Tate's death, Farrow testified, "Of this I can be sure — of his frame of mind when we were there, of what we talked about, of his utter sense of loss, of despair and bewilderment and shock and love — a love that he had lost." At the conclusion of the case, Polanski read a statement, saying in part, "The memory of my late wife Sharon Tate was at the forefront of my mind in bringing this action."

The murders committed by the Manson "Family" have been described by social commentators as one of the defining moments of the 1960s. Joan Didion wrote, "Many people I know in Los Angeles believe that the Sixties ended abruptly on August 9, 1969, ended at the exact moment when word of the murders on Cielo Drive traveled like brushfire through the community, and in a sense this is true. The tension broke that day. The paranoia was fulfilled."

Sharon Tate's work as an actress has been reassessed after her death, with contemporary film writers and critics such as Leonard Maltin describing her potential as a comedienne. A restored version of ''The Fearless Vampire Killers'' more closely resembles Polanski's intention. Maltin lauded the film as "near-brilliant" and Tate's work in ''Don't Make Waves'' and ''The Wrecking Crew'' as her two best performances, as well as the best indicators of the career she might have established. ''Eye of the Devil'' with its supernatural themes, and ''Valley of the Dolls'', with its overstated melodrama, have each achieved a degree of cult status.

Tate's biographer, Greg King, holds a view often expressed by members of the Tate family, writing in ''Sharon Tate and the Manson Murders'' (2000): "Sharon's real legacy lies not in her movies or in her television work. The very fact that, today, victims or their families in California are able to sit before those convicted of a crime and have a voice in the sentencing at trials or at parole hearings, is largely due to the work of Doris  Tate. Their years of devotion to Sharon's memory and dedication to victims' rights... have helped transform Sharon from mere victim,  restore a human face to one of the twentieth century's most infamous crimes."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a24f1ebd09e5ec5e640571ed995b3ffb" name="GeorgeBushwithTateFamily" sectnum="2.6#1">../img/a24f1ebd09e5ec5e640571ed995b3ffb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>