<document id="b2f45b3643284cccc13534a099ec0866-1.2" name="Trial_by_Jury" cat="17">
<text>
The result of Gilbert and Sullivan's collaboration was a witty, tuneful and very "English" piece, in contrast to the bawdy burlesques and adaptations of French operettas that dominated the London musical stage at that time.Stedman, 129&ndash;30 


Initially, ''Trial by Jury'', which runs only 30 minutes or so, was played last on a triple bill, on which the main attraction, ''La Périchole'' (starring Dolaro as the title character and Fred Sullivan as Don Andres), was preceded by the one-act farce ''Cryptoconchoidsyphonostomata''.  The latter was immediately replaced by a series of other curtain raisers.Ainger, p. 110The fashion in the late Victorian era was to present long evenings in the theatre, and so Carte preceded his savoy operas with curtain raisers.  See Lee Bernard,   ''Sheffield Telegraph'', 1 August 2008  Arthur Sullivan conducted the first night's performance, and the theatre's music director, B. Simmons, conducted thereafter.  The composer's brother, Fred Sullivan, starred as the Learned Judge, with Nellie Bromley as the Plaintiff.  One of the choristers in ''Trial by Jury'', W. S. Penley, was promoted in November 1875Ainger, p. 114 to the small part of the Foreman of the Jury and made a strong impact on audiences with his amusing facial expressions and gestures.Walbrook, pp. 38&ndash;40  In March 1876, he temporarily replaced Fred Sullivan as the Judge, when Fred's health declined from tuberculosis.Ainger, pp. 113, 120  With this start, Penley went on to a successful career as comic actor, culminating with the lead role in the record-breaking original production of ''Charley's Aunt''. Fred Sullivan died in January 1877.Ainger, p. 128

Offenbach's works were then at the height of their popularity in Britain, but ''Trial by Jury'' proved even more popular than ''La Périchole'',''The Times'', 29 March 1875, quoted and discussed in Ainger, p. 109 becoming an unexpected hit.Stedman, pp. 129&ndash;30  ''Trial by Jury'' drew crowds and continued to run after ''La Périchole'' closed.Ainger, p. 117  While the Royalty Theatre closed for the summer in 1875, Dolaro immediately took ''Trial'' on tour in England and Ireland.Ainger, p. 111  The piece was revived for additional London seasons in 1876 at the Opera Comique and in 1877 at the Strand Theatre.Ainger, pp. 118 and 130  

''Trial by Jury'' soon became the most desirable supporting piece for any London production, and, outside London, the major British theatrical touring companies had added it to their repertoire by about 1877.  The original production was even given a world tour by Opera Comique assistant manager Emily Soldene, which travelled as far as Australia.Gänzl, pp. 89&ndash;90  Unauthorised "pirate" productions quickly sprang up in America, taking advantage of the fact that American courts did not enforce foreign copyrights.Gänzl, p. 95  It also became popular as part of the Victorian tradition of "benefit concerts", where the theatrical community came together to raise money for actors and actresses down on their luck or retiring. The D'Oyly Carte Opera Company continued to play the work for a century, licensing the piece to amateur and foreign professional companies, such as the J. C. Williamson Gilbert and Sullivan Opera Company. (1906 programme), ''National Library of Australia'', Retrieved on 23 June 2008  Since the copyrights to Gilbert and Sullivan works ran out in 1961,, reprinted from theatre programme of 29 January 1968, ''The Gilbert and Sullivan Archive'', Retrieved on 17 June 2008 the piece has been available to theatre companies around the world free of royalties.  The work's enduring popularity since 1875 makes it, according to theatrical scholar Kurt Gänzl, "probably the most successful British one-act operetta of all time".

The success of ''Trial by Jury'' spurred several attempts to reunite Gilbert and Sullivan, but difficulties arose.  Plans for a collaboration for Carl Rosa in 1875 fell through because Gilbert was too busy with other projects,Stedman, p. 132Ainger, p. 112 and an attempted Christmas 1875 revival of ''Thespis'' by Richard D'Oyly Carte failed when the financiers backed out.Ainger, pp. 113&ndash;14  Gilbert and Sullivan continued their separate careers, though both continued writing light opera, among other projects: Sullivan's next light opera, ''The Zoo'', opened while ''Trial by Jury'' was still playing, in June 1875; and Gilbert's ''Eyes and No Eyes'' premièred a month later,Gänzl (1986), p. 90 followed by ''Princess Toto'' in 1876.Crowther, p. 211  However, Gilbert and Sullivan would not be reunited until ''The Sorcerer'' in 1877.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9ee4c4dc3aa13778133a4b65707979c3" name="Trial_by_Jury_cover" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/9ee4c4dc3aa13778133a4b65707979c3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>