<document id="b2f45b3643284cccc13534a099ec0866-1.1" name="Trial_by_Jury" cat="17">
<text>
The story of ''Trial by Jury'' started in 1868, when Gilbert wrote a single-page illustrated comic piece for the magazine ''Fun'' entitled ''Trial by Jury: An Operetta''.  Drawing on Gilbert's training and brief practice as a barrister, it detailed a "breach of promise" trial going awry, in the process spoofing the law, lawyers and the legal system.  (In the Victorian era, a man could be required to pay compensation should he fail to marry a woman to whom he was engaged.)  The outline of this story was followed in the later opera, and two of its numbers appeared in nearly their final form in ''Fun''.  The skit, however, ended abruptly: the moment the attractive plaintiff stepped into the witness box, the judge leapt into her arms and vowed to marry her, whereas in the opera, the case is allowed to proceed further before this conclusion is reached., from ''Fun'', 11 April 1868; Also  (Gilbert and Sullivan Archive editions, accessed 11 October 2007)Bradley, pp. 6, 24, 36

In 1873, Gilbert arranged with the opera manager and composer, Carl Rosa, to expand the piece into a one-act libretto.  Rosa was to write the music, and Euphrosyne Parepa-Rosa, his wife and an old friend of Gilbert's, was to sing the role of the Plaintiff, as part of a season of English opera that Rosa planned to present at the Drury Lane Theatre.Ainger, pp. 101–02 and 105 Euphrosyne died in childbirth in 1874, and the despondent Rosa dropped the project.Stedman, pp. 120&ndash;21  Later in the same year, Gilbert offered the libretto to the impresario Richard D'Oyly Carte, but Carte knew of no composer available to set it to music.Stedman, p. 125  

Meanwhile, Sullivan may have been considering a return to light opera: ''Cox and Box'', his first comic opera, had received a London revival (co-starring his brother, Fred Sullivan) in September 1874.  In November, Sullivan travelled to Paris and contacted Albert Millaud, one of the librettists for Jacques Offenbach's operettas.  However, he returned to London empty-handed and worked on incidental music for the Gaiety Theatre's production of ''The Merry Wives of Windsor''.Ainger, pp. 107&ndash;08  By early 1875, Carte was managing Selina Dolaro's Royalty Theatre, and he needed a short opera to be played as an afterpiece to Offenbach's ''La Périchole'', which was to open on 30 January, and in which Dolaro starred.  Carte had asked Sullivan to compose something for the theatre and advertised in ''The Times'' in late January: "In Preparation, a New Comic Opera composed expressly for this theatre by Mr. Arthur Sullivan in which Madame Dolaro and Nellie Bromley will appear."Ainger, p. 108Apparently, this refers to another opera that Sullivan was working on for the Royalty, since an advertisement in ''The Era'' on 14 March 1875 stated that "In consequence of the continued success of ''La Périchole'', the production of Mr. Sullivan's two-act opera is postponed" (McElroy, p. 40).  A gossip column in the ''Athenæum'', dated 13 March 1875, stated that Sullivan was working on new music for a piece at the St. James's Theatre.  From this, McElroy speculates that Sullivan had already begun writing musical numbers for ''The Zoo'' before he shifted his energies to ''Trial by Jury'' and decided "to salvage them by telling  to boil the libretto down to one act and  the project to another theatre." (McElroy, pp. 51&ndash;52)  But around the same time, Carte also remembered Gilbert's ''Trial by Jury'' and knew that Gilbert had worked with Sullivan to create ''Thespis''.  He suggested to Gilbert that Sullivan was the man to write the music for ''Trial''.  

Gilbert finally called on Sullivan and read the libretto to him on 20 February 1875.  Sullivan was enthusiastic, later recalling, " read it through... in the manner of a man considerably disappointed with what he had written.  As soon as he had come to the last word, he closed up the manuscript violently, apparently unconscious of the fact that he had achieved his purpose so far as I was concerned, inasmuch as I was screaming with laughter the whole time."Ainger, p. 109  ''Trial by Jury'', described as "A Novel and Original Dramatic Cantata" in the original promotional material,See  on exhibition at the University of Rochester Libraries.  In 1871, Sullivan had composed his only other "dramatic cantata", ''On Shore and Sea''. was composed and rehearsed in a matter of weeks.Stedman, pp. 128&ndash;29
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f25e5c3c21fe42a430c307c5d6a1b010" name="Trial_by_Jury_-_curve_bend" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/f25e5c3c21fe42a430c307c5d6a1b010.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>