<document id="b2f45b3643284cccc13534a099ec0866-6.4" name="Trial_by_Jury" cat="17">
<text>
''Trial by Jury'' is the only Gilbert and Sullivan opera played in one act and the only theatrical work by W. S. Gilbert without spoken dialogue. However, later Gilbert and Sullivan operas retained a number of patterns seen in ''Trial''.  For example, all except for ''The Yeomen of the Guard'' begin with a chorus number.Bradley, p. 758   Also, like ''Trial by Jury'', the later operas generally end with a relatively short finale consisting of a chorus number interspersed with short solos by the principal characters.  "Comes the broken flower" (part of No. 3) was the first in a string of meditative "Horatian" lyrics, "mingling happiness and sadness, an acceptance and a smiling resignation".Stedman, p. 244  These would, from this point forward, allow the characters, in each of the Savoy operas, an introspective scene where they stop and consider life, in contrast to the foolishness of the surrounding scenes.Stedman, pp. 129&ndash;30, 244; Crowther, pp. 133&ndash;35  Like both of the tenor's arias in ''Trial by Jury'', tenor arias in later Savoy operas were set in 6/8 time so frequently that comedienne Anna Russell, in her 1953 parody, "How to Write Your Own Gilbert and Sullivan Opera",Recording and re-issue history available at: Shepherd, Marc (2002), , ''A Gilbert and Sullivan Discography'', Retrieved on 12 June 2008. exclaimed, "the tenor ... according to tradition, ''must'' sing an aria in 6/8 time, usually accompanying himself on a stringed instrument".''Anna Russell Sings! Again?'' 1953 Columbia Masterworks Mono LP ML4594/ML4733  In ''Trial by Jury'' hypocrisy is revealed as the characters' motivations are held up to satire, and Gilbert mocks the underlying absurdity of the judicial procedures.  As Gilbert scholar Andrew Crowther explains, Gilbert combines his criticisms with comic entertainment, which renders them more palatable, while at the same time underlining their truth: "By laughing at a joke you show that you accept its premise."Crowther, p. 78 This too would become characteristic of Gilbert's work.Crowther, pp. 78&ndash;79


The judge's song, "When I, good friends, was called to the Bar" was followed by a string of similar patter songs that would come to epitomise Gilbert and Sullivan's collaboration.Bradley, p. 14  In these, often, a "dignified personage  supply a humorous biography of himself.Fitzgerald, pp. 25–26   Just as in Gilbert's earlier play, ''The Palace of Truth'', in these songs, the characters "naïvely reveal their innermost thoughts, unconscious of their egotism, vanity, baseness, or cruelty".Crowther, p. 77, quoting Archer, p. 161  Crowther points out that such revelations work particularly well in ''Trial by Jury'', because people commonly expect "characters singing in opera/operetta will communicate at a deeper level of truth than they would in mere speech."  In "When I, good friends", the judge outlines the path of corruption that led to his becoming a judge, and this, too, would set the pattern for many of the patter songs in Gilbert and Sullivan operas to follow.

One of Gilbert's most notable innovations, first found in ''Thespis'' and repeated in ''Trial by Jury'' and all of the later Savoy operas, is the use of the chorus as an essential part of the action.  In most earlier operas, burlesques, and comedies, the chorus had very little impact on the plot and served mainly as "noise or ornament".  In the Gilbert and Sullivan operas, however, the chorus is essential, taking part in the action and often acting as an important character in its own right.Dark & Grey, pp. 67&ndash;68  Sullivan recalled, "Until Gilbert took the matter in hand choruses were dummy concerns, and were practically nothing more than a part of the stage setting.  It was in 'Thespis' that Gilbert began to carry out his expressed determination to get the chorus to play its proper part in the performance.  At this moment it seems difficult to realise that the idea of the chorus being anything more than a sort of stage audience was, at that time, a tremendous novelty."Lawrence, pp. 85–86  Another Gilbert innovation, following the example of his mentor, T. W. Robertson, was that the costumes and sets were made as realistic as possible:Stedman, p. 129  Gilbert based the scenery for the production on the Clerkenwell Sessions House, where he had practised law in the 1860s.Dark & Grey, p. 65  The costumes were contemporary, and Angelina and her bridesmaids were dressed in real wedding attire.  This attention to detail and careful creation of realistic sets and scenes were typical of Gilbert's stage management and would be repeated in all of Gilbert's work.Crowther, p. 90  For instance, when preparing the sets for ''H.M.S. Pinafore'' (1878), Gilbert and Sullivan visited Portsmouth to inspect ships.  Gilbert made sketches of the ''H.M.S. Victory'' and the ''H.M.S. St Vincent'' and created a model set for the carpenters to work from.Stedman, pp. 157–58; Crowther, p. 90 This was far from standard procedure in Victorian drama, where naturalism was still a relatively new concept, and where most authors had very little influence on how their plays and libretti were staged.Crowther, pp. 87–89
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="08382ea41628a19156fe89b600fff27a" name="FredSullivan" sectnum="6.4#1">../img/08382ea41628a19156fe89b600fff27a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>