<document id="b2f45b3643284cccc13534a099ec0866-6.5" name="Trial_by_Jury" cat="17">
<text>
Andrew Crowther places ''Trial by Jury'' at the centre of Gilbert's development as a librettist.  He notes that in some of Gilbert's early libretti, such as ''Topsyturveydom'' (1874), the songs simply emphasise the dialogue.  In others, such as ''Thespis'' (1871), some songs are relatively disconnected from both the story and characterisation, such as "I once knew a chap" or "Little maid of Arcadee", which simply convey a moral lesson.Crowther, pp. 76&ndash;77  In ''Trial by Jury'', however, each song carries the plot forward and adds depth to the characters.  In addition, unlike some of Gilbert's more fantastical early plots, "Aside from the ending, nothing essentially improbable happens."Crowther, p. 77  Theatre historian Kurt Gänzl agrees, writing that "Gilbert's libretto was superior to any of his previous efforts.  It was concise, modern and satirical without being impossibly whimsical.  Having no spoken dialogue it was perforce tightly constructed and allowed of no interpolation or alteration."Gänzl, p. 88  Sullivan's development as a comic opera writer, too, would mature with ''Trial by Jury''.  Except for incidental music for productions of Shakespeare, he had not written any music for the stage since ''Thespis''.  Gänzl wrote that ''Trial by Jury'' "brought Sullivan firmly and finally into the world of the musical" stage and confirmed, after his previous success with ''Cox and Box'' and ''Thespis'', that "Sullivan was a composer of light lyric and comic music who could rival Offenbach, Lecocq and any English musician alive."Gänzl, p. 89 


Sullivan used the opportunities suggested by Gilbert's satire of the pomp and ceremony of the law to provide a variety of musical jokes.  "From the first chords ... Sullivan's music sets the scene of mock-seriousness....  His ... humorous use of the orchestra runs throughout".Ainger, pp. 109–10  For example, counterpointing the plaintiff's calculated swooning in "That she is reeling is plain to see!" (No. 9) with a reeling, minor-key theme in the string accompaniment, heading up and down the octaves.  The instruments are also used to comically set the scene; for instance, he underlines the Counsel's misstatement in the line "To marry two at once is burglaree" with a comic bassoon "sting" in octaves and has the Defendant tune his guitar on stage (simulated by a violin in the orchestra) in the opening to his song.Bradley, p. 10  

The score also contains two parodies or pastiches of other composers: No. 3, "All hail great Judge" is an elaborate parody of Handel's fugues,Bradley, pp. 4 and 12; Burgess, pp. 38&ndash;39 and No. 12, "A nice dilemma", parodies "dilemma" ensembles of Italian opera in the Bel canto era; in particular "D'un pensiero" from Act I of Bellini's ''La sonnambula''.Bradley, p. 4; Burgess, p. 47  "A nice dilemma" uses the dominant rhythm and key of "D'un pensiero" and divides up some of the choral lines between the basses and higher voices to create an ''oom-pa-pa'' effect common in Italian opera choruses.Jacobs, p. 91
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4e31a12a30cbfc89372819158ca1ec03" name="Trial_by_Jury_-_A_Nice_Dilemma" sectnum="6.5#1">../img/4e31a12a30cbfc89372819158ca1ec03.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>