<document id="b3150b0c281960b6a6d33407824fd40a-1.2" name="Aaron_Sorkin" cat="19">
<text>
Sorkin got the inspiration to write his next play, a courtroom drama called ''A Few Good Men'', from a phone conversation with his sister Deborah, who had graduated from Boston University Law School and signed up for a 3-year stint with the U.S. Navy Judge Advocate General's Corps. She was going to Guantanamo Bay to defend a group of Marines who came close to killing a fellow Marine in a hazing ordered by a superior officer. Sorkin took that information and wrote much of his story on cocktail napkins while bartending at the Palace Theatre on Broadway. He and his roommates had purchased a Macintosh 512K so when he returned home he would empty his pockets of the cocktail napkins and type them into the computer, forming a basis from which he wrote many drafts for ''A Few Good Men''.

In 1988 Sorkin sold the film rights for his play ''A Few Good Men'' to producer David Brown before it even premiered, for a deal possibly worth a sum well into six-figures. Brown had read an article in ''The New York Times'' about Sorkin's one-act play ''Hidden in this Picture'' and found out Sorkin also had a play called ''A Few Good Men'' that was having off-Broadway readings. Brown produced ''A Few Good Men'' on Broadway at the Music Box Theatre. It starred Tom Hulce and was directed by Don Scardino. After opening in late 1989, it ran for 497 performances.

Sorkin continued writing ''Making Movies'' and in 1990 it debuted off-Broadway at the Promenade Theatre, produced by John A. McQuiggan and directed by Don Scardino. Meanwhile, David Brown was producing a few projects at TriStar Pictures and tried to interest them in making ''A Few Good Men'' into a film but his proposal was declined due to the lack of star actor involvement. Brown later got a call from Alan Horn at Castle Rock Entertainment who was anxious to make the film. Rob Reiner, a producing partner at Castle Rock, opted to direct it.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f2fb578a657fed96dcab2d906604aef6" name="A_Few_Good_Men_at_Haymarket_Theatre_London" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/f2fb578a657fed96dcab2d906604aef6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>