<document id="b37a101c0006eaca4d4a18520623e47e-4" name="Alanya" cat="11">
<text>
On the peninsula stands Alanya Castle, a Seljuk era citadel dating from 1226.  Most major landmarks in the city are found inside and around the castle.  The current castle was built over existing fortifications and served the double purpose of a palace of local government and as a defensive structure in case of attack. In 2007, the city began renovating various sections of the castle area, including adapting a Byzantine church for use as a Christian community center.  Inside the castle is the Süleymaniye mosque and caravanserai, built by Suleiman the Magnificent. The old city walls surround much of the eastern peninsula, and can be walked.  Inside the walls are numerous historic villas, well preserved examples of the classical period of Ottoman architecture, most built in the early 19th century.

The Kızıl Kule (Red Tower) is another well-known building in Alanya.  The 108-foot  high brick building stands at the harbor below the castle, and contains the municipal ethnographic museum.  Sultan Alaeddin Keykubad I brought the accomplished architect Ebu Ali from Aleppo, Syria to Alanya to design the building. The last of Alanya Castle's , the octagonal structure specifically protected the Tersane (arsenal), it remains one of the finest examples of medieval military architecture. The Tersane, a medieval drydock built by the Seljuk Turks in 1221,     is divided into five vaulted bays with equilateral pointed arches. The Alarahan caravanserai near Manavgat, also built under Keykubad's authority, has been converted into a museum and heritage center.

Atatürk's House and Museum, from his short stay in the city on February 18, 1935 is preserved in its historic state and is a good example of the interior of a traditional Ottoman villa, with artifacts from the 1930s.  The house was built between 1880 and 1885 in the "karniyarik" (stuffed eggplant) style.  Bright colors and red roofs are often mandated by neighborhood councils, and give the modern town a pastel glow. Housed in a 1967 Republican era building, The Alanya Museum is inland from Damlataşh Beach. With its rich architectural heritage, Alanya is a member of the Norwich-based European Association of Historic Towns and Regions. In 2009, city officials filed to include Alanya Castle and Tersane as UNESCO World Heritage Sites, and were named to the 2009 Tentative List.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a33564d14bdb6ce0382031a545b371ba" name="Byzantine_era_church_inside_the_Alanya_Castle" sectnum="4#1">../img/a33564d14bdb6ce0382031a545b371ba.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>