<document id="b3bbe6e0c76675357c84c22e04afe6ed-1.5" name="Simeon_I_of_Bulgaria" cat="25">
<text>
By 917, Simeon was preparing for yet another war against Byzantium. He attempted to conclude an anti-Byzantine union with the Pechenegs, but his envoys could not match the financial resources of the Byzantines, who succeeded in outbidding them.Runciman, ''A history of the First Bulgarian Empire'', p. 159. The Byzantines hatched a large-scale campaign against Bulgaria and also tried to persuade the Serbian Prince Petar Gojniković to attack the Bulgarians with Magyar support.Zlatarski, ''Istorija na Pǎrvoto bǎlgarsko carstvo'', pp. 375–376.

In 917, a particularly strong Byzantine army led by Leo Phokas the Elder, son of Nikephoros Phokas, invaded Bulgaria accompanied by the Byzantine navy under the command of Romanos Lekapenos, which sailed to the Bulgarian Black Sea ports. En route to Mesembria (Nesebǎr), where they were supposed to be reinforced by troops transported by the navy, Phokas' forces stopped to rest near the river of Acheloos, not far from the port of Anchialos (Pomorie).Runciman, ''A history of the First Bulgarian Empire'', pp. 160–161.Zlatarski, ''Istorija na Pǎrvoto bǎlgarsko carstvo'', pp. 376–377. Once informed of the invasion, Simeon rushed to intercept the Byzantines, and attacked them from the nearby hills while they were resting disorganized. In the Battle of Acheloos of 20 August 917, one of the largest in medieval history,Dimitrov, ''Bulgaria: illustrated history''. the Bulgarians completely routed the Byzantines and killed many of their commanders, although Phokas managed to escape to Mesembria. Decades later, Leo the Deacon would write that "piles of bones can still be seen today at the river Acheloos, where the fleeing army of the Byzantines was then infamously slain".Leo the Deacon, '''', p. 12410–12. Cited in Canev, ''Bǎlgarski hroniki'', p. 216.



The planned Pecheneg attack from the north also failed, as the Pechenegs quarrelled with admiral Lekapenos, who refused to transport them across the Danube to aid the main Byzantine army. The Byzantines were not aided by Serbs and Magyars either: the Magyars were engaged in Western Europe as Frankish allies, and the Serbs under Petar Gojniković were reluctant to attack Bulgaria because the Bulgarian ally Mihailo Višević of Zahumlje had notified Simeon of their plans.Zlatarski, ''Istorija na Pǎrvoto bǎlgarsko carstvo'', p. 370.

Simeon's army quickly followed up the victory of Acheloos with another success. The Bulgarians sent to pursuit the remnants of the Byzantine army approached Constantinople and encountered Byzantine forces under Leo Phokas, who had returned to the capital, at the village of Katasyrtai in the immediate proximity of Constantinople. The Bulgarian regiments attacked and again defeated the Byzantines, destroying some of their last units before returning to Bulgaria.Zlatarski, ''Istorija na Pǎrvoto bǎlgarsko carstvo'', p. 382.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0d3bb65b6dcefb7a4f080f263bcd6421" name="Skylitzes_Simeon_at_Anchialos_917" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/0d3bb65b6dcefb7a4f080f263bcd6421.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>