<document id="b43ebf97d12c3cc04168eb6ec85c09c7-3" name="Eric_Bana" cat="19">
<text>
Bana posing with fans at the 2009 Tribeca Film Festival.
In 1995, while working on the television series ''Full Frontal'', Bana began dating Rebecca Gleeson, a publicist with the Seven Network and daughter of then Chief Justice of New South Wales, and later Chief Justice of Australia, Murray Gleeson. They married in 1997, after Bana proposed to her on a trip to the United States, which he won from ''Cleo Magazine'' after being named their "Bachelor of the Year" in 1996."Eric's Secret Love: Going Bananas". ''The New Post''. 1 March 1997 Bana and Gleeson have two children, a son Klaus (born August 1999), and a daughter Sophia (born April 2002). They live in Melbourne.

Bana is a motor racing enthusiast, and participates in various motor racing competitions in Australia. At the age of fourteen, Bana wanted to leave school to focus full-time on becoming a motor mechanic, but his father convinced him to complete school, advising him to avoid making his hobby a job.. 17 June 2003. Retrieved 1 June 2006. Bana purchased his first car, a 1974 XB Ford Falcon coupé, at the age of fifteen for AU$1100Hawley, Janet. "Lucky Eric". ''The Age Good Weekend''. 5 May 2007. and driving it, made his motor sport racing debut in 1996's Targa Tasmania, a week-long race around the island state of Tasmania.. ''Street Machine''. June 1996. Retrieved 1 June 2006. In 2004, Bana purchased a Porsche 944 to compete in Australia's Porsche Challenge. Competing throughout 2004, he often finished in the top ten and in November, finished fourth at the Sandown 500, a personal best.Naulty, Matt.. ''Australian Porsche Drivers Challenge's''. November 2004. Retrieved 12 July 2006. On 21 April 2007 Bana crashed his 1974 XB Falcon Coupe in the Targa Tasmania rally. Neither he nor his co-driver were injured.. ''The LA Daily News''. 23 April 2007. Retrieved 23 April 2007.

Bana is a prominent fan of Australian rules football. His love of the sport began at a young age when his godfather took him to games to see the St Kilda Football Club, his favourite team in the Australian Football League. Bana can often be seen at AFL games when he is back in Australia on vacation or promoting his films.Kramp, Leif. . ''RP Online''. 24 January 2006. Retrieved 12 July 2006.Freydkin, Donna. . ''USA Today''. 9 January 2003. Retrieved 1 July 2006.
Bana's love for St Kilda FC has seen the club featured in the film ''Funny People'' and in Bana's promotion the film in 2009, particularly on NBC Show Late Night with Jimmy Fallon. ''US Footy News''. 12 August 2009. Retrieved 11 September 2009.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0541908b530f06c5e47fa1396ff7c0b0" name="EricBanaatCamp_Arifjan" sectnum="3#1">../img/0541908b530f06c5e47fa1396ff7c0b0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>