<document id="b47ea6603f6c3f8c6c8287c0f318e8d8-8" name="Radcliffe,_Greater_Manchester" cat="11">
<text>
One of the earliest schools in the parish was the Close Wesleyan Day School, a Dame school opened around 1840.  St Thomas's day school was opened on 4 March 1861, and housed over 500 children.  Due to overcrowding and the risk of subsidence caused by local mining activity, the school was rebuilt on a new site along School Street, provided by the Earl of Wilton.  It was opened in October 1877 by Lady Wilton.  On the opposite side of the town St John's school started life in 1860 as an institute along Irwell Street, and by 1864 contained 120 children.  The buildings were enlarged in 1869.  In 1897 eight teachers and a monitor taught 358 children.  In 1899 the school leaving age was twelve, and many of the senior class were "half-timers" who would spend half the day at school, and the other half at work.  This system was abolished in 1919.  Regular epidemics of scarlet fever, chicken pox, mumps, and especially measles, meant that in 1897 and 1903 the school was temporarily closed.  St John's school and the nearby Church were demolished in the 1970s.  Radcliffe also had a Technical school on Whittaker Street.  Formally opened by Lord Stanley on 7 November 1896, it adjoined the public baths on Whittaker Street. The building is now used as council offices.

Radcliffe County Secondary School was founded in 1933 on the former Peel Park Ground near School Street, but Radcliffe's first secondary school (apart from an endowed grammar school in nearby Stand) was held at the New Jerusalem schoolroom from the early 1860s.  Radcliffe East, latterly known as Coney Green County Comprehensive School, was built in 1975 on the site of the former railway goods yard alongside Radcliffe East Fork.  Part of the school, known as "Phase One", opened in September 1975, with 150 first-year pupils, and 70 second-year pupils (from Radcliffe County Secondary School).  The remainder, known as "Phase Two", opened two years later.

Radcliffe has ten primary schools, and one secondary school which is spread across two sites.  Presently, these two secondary school sites have been renamed Radcliffe Riverside East Campus (Coney Green) and Radcliffe Riverside West Campus (Radcliffe High).  The lower school students in years 7–9 study at the Coney Green building, while the upper school students between years 10–11 study in the Radcliffe High building.  A new school is proposed to replace Coney Green High School and Radcliffe High School, however recent developments have delayed construction of the new school.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e0aacce7fc0edd9514b0cef510868e81" name="Radcliffe_technical_school_1896_greater_manchester" sectnum="8#1">../img/e0aacce7fc0edd9514b0cef510868e81.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>