<document id="b47ea6603f6c3f8c6c8287c0f318e8d8-7" name="Radcliffe,_Greater_Manchester" cat="11">
<text>
The Manchester to Blackburn packhorse route passed through the town (hence the name Blackburn Street).  The bridge across the Irwell was likely first erected during the late Medieval period at the site of a ford.  An Act of Parliament in 1754 authorised the first turnpike through the hamlet of Radcliffe Bridge, and included Manchester to Bury via Crumpsall, and from Prestwich to Radcliffe.  An Act of 1821 created a turnpike from Bury to Radcliffe, Stoneclough and Bolton.  An Act of 1836 created a turnpike from Starling Lane to Ainsworth, and Radcliffe to Bury and Manchester Road (near Fletcher Fold).  A turnpike from Whitefield to Radcliffe Bridge via Stand Lane was created in 1857 with toll houses at Besses o' th' Barn, Stand Lane, the junction of Dumers Lane and Manchester Road, on Bolton Road near Countess Lane, and on Radcliffe Moor Road at Bradley Fold.  Radcliffe New Road was created in an Act of 1860 which enabled the construction of a toll road between Radcliffe and Whitefield.  To prevent damage to the road surfaces, weighing machines were used at various strategic positions including at the bridge end of Dumers Lane, at Sandiford turning, and on Ainsworth Road.


During the Industrial Revolution, as local cottage industries were gradually supplanted by the factory system the roads became inadequate for use.  A convoy of horse-drawn lorries carrying salt between Bealey's Bleach Works and Northwich would take up to two weeks to make a return journey.  These problems gave rise to the construction of the Manchester, Bolton & Bury Canal, which reached the town in 1796 and which was navigable throughout in 1808.  For 38 years the canal was the town's main route for trade and transport, with a wharf near Hampson Street.  The proprietors later converted into a railway company and built a line between Salford and Bolton, which opened in 1838.  A branch from this line was to have been built to Bury, along the line of the canal, but due to technical constraints this did not happen.  Radcliffe's closest railway connection therefore remained several miles distant at Stoneclough.

The opening of the Manchester, Bury and Rossendale Railway (later known as the East Lancashire Railway (ELR)) in 1846 brought the town a direct connection to Manchester and Bury.  Two stations served the town, Radcliffe Bridge station, and Withins Lane station (although this closed in 1851 after only a few years of operation).  Ringley Road station was located to the south of the parish, close to the civil parish of Pilkington.  The line crossed the Irwell over Outwood Viaduct, an impressive structure which remains to this day.

The Liverpool and Bury Railway (L&BR) opened on 28 November 1848, with a station to the north of the town, called Black Lane station. On 18 July 1872 the Lancashire and Yorkshire Railway (L&YR), which had amalgamated with the ELR some years previously, gained an Act of Parliament to construct a railway between Manchester and Bury, via Whitefield and Prestwich.  This opened in 1879 with a new station, known as Radcliffe New Station,From 1933 this station was renamed "Radcliffe Central" with a link to the L&BR line at Bradley Fold (near the present day Chatsworth Road), and a new station along Ainsworth Road, Ainsworth Road Halt. The new L&YR route joined the existing ELR route near Withins Lane (North Junction), whereon they shared the connection to Bury.  The L&YR gained a further Act of 1877 to construct a link between North Junction and Coney Green Farm (West Junction). The LY&R line was electrified in 1916 for which a substation was constructed, between the canal and the West Fork.

The town also had an extensive tram network.  The first tram ran from Black Lane (latterly Ainsworth Road) in 1905, with a terminus next to St Andrew's Church on Black Lane Bridge.  In 1907 a branch was built to connect to the Bury to Bolton part of the network.  A large bus station is located between Dale Street and the river.  Officially abandoned in 1961, the canal is currently undergoing restoration on the Salford arm, although a rebuilt bridge along Water Street presents a barrier to its full restoration.


Public transport in Radcliffe is now coordinated by the Greater Manchester Passenger Transport Executive (GMPTE), a county-wide public body with direct operational responsibilities such as supporting (and in some cases running) local bus services, and managing integrated ticketing in Greater Manchester.

The town is now served only by a single light rail system and regular bus services.  The Metrolink opened on 6 April 1992 along the L&YR line between Manchester and Bury.  Trams leave from the town's station every six minutes between 7:15 am and 6:30 pm, and every 12 minutes at other times of the day.  Radcliffe Bridge station closed on 5 July 1958, and has since been replaced by the path of the A665 Pilkington Way (the new road has been built below the level of the old station).  The path of the ELR line is still quite visible from aerial photography, with Outwood Viaduct fully restored, and the route of the line southwest of the town converted for use as a nature trail forming part of the Irwell Sculpture Trail.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="96341ae30d24a2e493d19a350944a342" name="Metrolink_at_Dolly_Molly" sectnum="7#1">../img/96341ae30d24a2e493d19a350944a342.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>