<document id="b4e54d900ed36f16a1457ca01981208f-2.4" name="Battle_for_Henderson_Field" cat="29">
<text>
Sumiyoshi was informed by Hyakutake's staff of the postponement of the offensive to October 24, but was unable to contact Nakaguma to inform him of the delay.  Thus, at dusk on October 23, two battalions of Nakaguma's 4th Infantry Regiment and the nine tanks of the 1st Independent Tank Company launched attacks on the U.S. Marine defenses at the mouth of the Matanikau.Hough, ''Pearl Harbor to Guadalcanal'', pp. 332–33, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', pp. 349–50, Rottman, ''Japanese Army'', pp. 62–3, Griffith, ''Battle for Guadalcanal'', pp. 195–96.  Twelve tanks were originally landed by the Japanese.  Two were damaged during the landing and one was later destroyed during a feint at the mouth of the Matanikau (Gilbert, ''Marine Tank Battles'', p. 48–49.

Nakaguma's tanks attacked in pairs across the sandbar at the mouth of the Matanikau behind a barrage of artillery.  Marine 37 mm anti-tank guns and artillery quickly destroyed all nine tanks.  At the same time, four battalions of Marine artillery, totalling 40 howitzers, fired over 6,000 rounds into the area between Point Cruz and the Matanikau, causing heavy casualties in Nakaguma's infantry battalions as they tried to approach the Marine lines.  Nakaguma's attacks ended by 01:15 on October 24, inflicting only light casualties on the Marines and gaining no ground.Gilbert, ''Marine Tank Battles'', p. 49, Miller, ''Guadalcanal:  The First Offensive'', pp. 157–58, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', pp. 349–50, Hough, ''Pearl Harbor to Guadalcanal'', p. 332, Griffith, ''Battle for Guadalcanal'', pp. 195–96.  The Marines lost 2 killed in the action.  Nakaguma's infantry losses aren't recorded but were, according to Frank, "unquestionably severe."  Griffith says that 600 of Nakaguma's men were killed.  Only 17 of the 44 members of the 1st Independent Tank Company survived the battle.

Partly in response to Nakaguma's attacks, on October 24 the 2nd Battalion, 7th Marines under Lieutenant Colonel Herman H. Hanneken deployed to the Matanikau.  After Oka's forces were sighted approaching the Marine Matanikau positions from the south, Hanneken's battalion was placed on a ridge facing south which formed a continuous extension of the inland flank of the Marine's horseshoe-shaped Matanikau defenses.  A gap, however, still remained between Hanneken's left (east) flank and the main perimeter.Griffith, ''Battle for Guadalcanal'', p. 196, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', pp. 351–52, Hough, ''Pearl Harbor to Guadalcanal'', p. 333.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3c3a59b4de20b27da4bcf1a58f4c550e" name="MatanikauTank" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/3c3a59b4de20b27da4bcf1a58f4c550e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>