<document id="b4e54d900ed36f16a1457ca01981208f-3.10" name="Battle_for_Henderson_Field" cat="29">
<text>
At the same time that Hyakutake's troops were attacking the Lunga perimeter, Japanese aircraft carriers and other large warships under the overall direction of Isoroku Yamamoto moved into a position near the southern Solomon Islands.  From this location, the Japanese naval forces hoped to engage and decisively defeat any Allied (primarily U.S.) naval forces, especially carrier forces, that responded to Hyakutake's ground offensive.  Allied naval carrier forces in the area, now under the command of William Halsey, Jr. who had replaced Ghormley, also hoped to meet the Japanese naval forces in battle.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', pp. 199–207, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', pp. 368–78, Dull, ''Imperial Japanese Navy'', pp. 235–37.  Admiral Chester Nimitz, Allied Commander in Chief of Pacific Forces, replaced Ghormley with Halsey on October 18.

The two opposing carrier forces confronted each other on the morning of October 26, in what became known as the Battle of the Santa Cruz Islands. After an exchange of carrier air attacks, Allied surface ships were forced to retreat from the battle area with the loss of one carrier sunk and another heavily damaged. The participating Japanese carrier forces, however, also retreated because of high aircraft and aircrew losses and significant damage to two carriers. Although an apparent tactical victory for the Japanese in terms of ships sunk and damaged, the loss of many irreplaceable, veteran aircrews by the Japanese provided a long-term strategic advantage for the Allies, whose aircrew losses in the battle were relatively low.Dull, ''Imperial Japanese Navy'', pp. 237–44, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', pp. 379–03, Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', pp. 207–24.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5c66490150b63519d46f72509d59ee32" name="Henderson1944" sectnum="3.10#1">../img/5c66490150b63519d46f72509d59ee32.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>