<document id="b4ea4bb7f9b436f5cba6a9b6732dc9e2-5.3" name="West_Indian_cricket_team_in_England_in_1988" cat="26">
<text>
The third Test changed the pattern of the summer. England were "unable to cope for any length of time with the West Indian fast bowlers" and never gave even a sign of competing in a one-sided affair. 

The England team had a different look, with four changes to the team. Essex 36 year-old off-spinner John Childs made his debut, the oldest England debutant for 40 years.Dick Howorth was 37 when he was capped in 1947.  confirms that no other England player made a debut aged 36 or older in this period. Childs joined the recalled Gatting and DeFreitas, and newcomer David Capel.  Small and Paul Jarvis were both left out due to injury, and Derek Pringle was dropped, but the most media attention focused on Chris Broad, who was also dropped, "ostensibly for his consistent failure to make runs in home Tests, but there was always a suspicion that he was being disciplined for the incident at Lord's when he was spotted by a television camera mouthing his disappointment at an lbw decision".

For West Indies, Desmond Haynes was unfit, ending a run of 72 consecutive caps. He was replaced by the spinner Roger Harper, and Patrick Patterson was replaced by Winston Benjamin.

No batsman scored more than 33 in England's first innings, as the four quick bowlers shared cheap wickets.  In reply, West Indies piled up 384-7, again without a century, in a team effort down to and including man-of-the-match Marshall, who scored 43* batting at number eight.

Needing 249 to make West Indies bat again, England were dismissed for just 93, Marshall finishing with magnificent figures of 15.4-5-22-7, the best of his Test career.  Extras were the third highest scorer, with 12.

With such a huge margin of victory and such a poor performance, England (and Emburey) were strongly criticised. After being bowled out for just 93 runs, and a personally very unsuccessful match (no wickets as a bowler, and scoring just 1 and 8 runs as a batsman), Emburey was sacked as England captain and dropped from the team.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e463a00fcdbefa0666ea1718400c2e27" name="Courtney_walsh" sectnum="5.3#1">../img/e463a00fcdbefa0666ea1718400c2e27.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>