<document id="b50559ebd1e407ddd42671bef4012e9a-2.2" name="No_Way_Out_(2004)" cat="26">
<text>
The fifth match featured the WWE Cruiserweight Champion Rey Mysterio (managed by Jorge Paez), defending against Chavo Guerrero (managed by his father Chavo Guerrero, Sr.) During the fight, Mysterio performed a 619 on Guerrero (at the time positioned on the second ring rope) and hit him in the face with both legs while using the ropes for leverage, leading to an attack by Paez on Guerrero, Sr. As determined by the storyline, the referee ordered Paez backstage. Both fighters wrestled inconclusively until Mysterio hit a second 619. During the second sequence of the move, Guerrero grabbed Mysterio's legs and achieved a position with his shoulders spread so as to win both a pinfall and the WWE Cruiserweight title.

The following match was the Triple Threat between The Big Show, John Cena, and Kurt Angle fighting for the opportunity to face the WWE Champion at WrestleMania XX. For the duration of the match, The Big Show, who stood at  and weighed , used his body size to his advantage as he squashed, or easily and quickly performed moves on, Cena and Angle. Thereafter, Cena lifted The Big Show over his shoulders and threw him down to execute the ''FU'', while Angle lifted The Big Show by the side to throw him out of the ring. Angle then applied an ankle lock on Cena, forcing him to submit. As a result, Angle won a WWE Championship match at WrestleMania XX.

The main event was a singles match in which WWE Champion Brock Lesnar defended his title against Eddie Guerrero. Lesnar did not show any effect from the Jackhammer Goldberg performed on him earlier in the event; similar to the prior match, Lesnar used his size advantage over Guerrero throughout the match. As Lesnar lifted Guerrero over his shoulders to slam his face down to perform an "F-5", he was scripted to knock the referee down. Lesnar then attempted to take advantage of the referee's state, as he went to retrieve the WWE title belt to hit Guerrero. Meanwhile, Goldberg came down into the ring to execute a spear on Lesnar; because the referee was incapacitated, Guerrero could not be disqualified for Goldberg's interference. As Goldberg retreated, the referee regained consciousness while Guerrero drove Lesnar's head onto the WWE title belt Lesnar had left in the ring. Guerrero kicked the belt out of the ring to prevent the referee from seeing it and performed a body splash, known in wrestling as a frog splash, from the top turnbuckle to pin Lesnar and win the WWE Championship from him.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f91c643c1ee39a421291ba05015a0c37" name="Chavo_Guerrero,_Jr._in_Kitchener,_Ontario,_Canada" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/f91c643c1ee39a421291ba05015a0c37.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>