<document id="b50559ebd1e407ddd42671bef4012e9a-2.1" name="No_Way_Out_(2004)" cat="26">
<text>
After ''Sunday Night Heat'', the pay-per-view began with a handicap match - a tag team match in which a team of two wrestlers face a team of three. WWE Tag Team Champions Rikishi and Scotty 2 Hotty defended their titles against the Basham Brothers (Doug and Danny Basham) and Shaniqua. During the match Hotty attempted to hit Shaniqua, who was lying on her back, with a slap over her chest, but Shaniqua countered by hitting him with her forearm. The challengers had the advantage until Hotty hit both Basham brothers with his forearm, causing them to flip over the top ring rope and into ringside. Afterwards, Rikishi lifted Shaniqua over his shoulders before falling backwards in a Samoan drop. Rikishi then covered Shaniqua to pin her, a move that allowed Rikishi and Hotty to retain their championships. Next was a singles blindfold match, in which Jamie Noble was blindfolded as he faced his storyline girlfriend Nidia. Nidia would take advantage of Noble's inability to see by performing antics that caused him to fall. Eventually, Noble was able to apply the guillotine choke on Nidia. Noble won the match after he forced her to submit with this move.

The third contest was a tag team match, in which The World's Greatest Tag Team (Shelton Benjamin and Charlie Haas) faced the APA (Bradshaw and Faarooq). At one point, Bradshaw performed a high-impact forearm "Clothesline from Hell" attack on Haas. Benjamin then hit Bradshaw with a superkick and pinned him to gain the win for his team. After the match, Goldberg was seen arriving at the arena and being escorted to his seat by arena security. In the ring, General Manager Paul Heyman gave a promotional in-ring segment on how ''SmackDown!'' was the better program over ''Raw''. Lesnar would come down to the ring to promote his match and to insult Goldberg. As part of the storyline, Goldberg immediately jumped over the barricade into the ring, where Lesnar performed a spear, a running shoulder block to Goldberg's stomach; however he recuperated and lifted Lesnar vertically in the air before slamming him down to perform the Jackhammer. Goldberg was then escorted out of the arena by security. This altercation was followed by a singles match between Hardcore Holly and Rhyno. Before the match began, Holly and Rhyno were scripted to brawl on the entrance ramp, before they entered the ring. Once there, Holly slammed Rhyno off the top rope with a superplex, though, as they recuperated, Rhyno hit Holly with a spear that caused Holly to roll out of the ring. Afterwards, Holly lifted Rhyno by his legs over his shoulders before throwing him down with an Alabama slam; Holly covered Rhyno for a pinfall.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f1400d327018515f36e928a17087b283" name="Solofa_Fatu" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/f1400d327018515f36e928a17087b283.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>