<document id="b531f3e99952920dd922869482b096cd-1.4" name="Making_Waves_(TV_series)" cat="19">
<text>
The series producers scouted Portsmouth in 2002 for ship locations. Potential main settings HMS ''Marlborough'' and HMS ''Dryad'' were put aside in favour of HMS ''Grafton'' and filming commenced on 24 March 2003 with 30 actors and 60 crew moving onto the ship for the shoot. Alex Ferns arrived two days earlier than the rest of the cast to settle in, and made a trip to Yeovilton to meet Harrier pilots, while Emily Hamilton prepared for her role by shadowing Vanessa Spiller, XO of HMS ''Kent''. The series was directed by Matthew Evans and Nigel Douglas and was shot on digital DV cameras. The production staff filmed approximately three hours of footage on every 12-hour day, editing it using Avid systems in the production offices at the naval base.

Other vessels made cameos in the series; filming took place around and aboard HMS ''Victory'' for scenes in episode two, and aerial footage of HMS ''Invincible'' and HMS ''Gloucester'' was done for the war games scenes in episode four. HMS ''Lindisfarne'' appeared for the funeral scenes in episode five. Health and safety regulations required that ''Grafton'' was shadowed at all times by a support vessel during filming at sea, in the event of a member of the production team falling overboard.

Location filming lasted until 26 June 2003 before post-production was completed in London, and the series was delivered to ITV in August 2003 for broadcast in the autumn schedules, though it would be held back for several months. A special preview screening of episode one was held aboard HMS ''Richmond'' on 13 February 2004, while the ship was in Aberdeen on a recruitment and promotional tour of the UK.  It was also premièred aboard HMS ''Northumberland'' during the same month whilst at the Excel London Boatshow and was attended by much of the cast and crew.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ff0b4c5d379eaee6a366d4eeb8f9c66a" name="HMS_Sutherland_F81" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/ff0b4c5d379eaee6a366d4eeb8f9c66a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>