<document id="b561db7df9e3e9719d45d41154a01a53-1" name="Templon" cat="1">
<text>
The templon most likely has an independent origin from that of Latin chancel barriers. Classical stage architecture is one possible source. At certain times during Byzantine history, theater heavily influenced painting and sculpture. Architects then, influenced by stage backdrops dating back to Sophocles, consciously imitated the classical proscenium (the backdrop of a classical Greek stage), copying the multiple columns punctuated by a large door in the middle and two smaller doors to each side. The statues on top of the backdrop would thus be analogous to the icons of the saints looking down.Strzygowski, Josef. "A Sarcophagus of the Sidamara Type … and the Influence of Stage Architecture upon the Art of Antioch." ''The Journal of Hellenic Studies'', '''Vol. 27''' (1907). 99–122. The similarities, however, are probably only visual. Although classical drama was performed in Constantinople, the capital of the Byzantine Empire, during the 5th and 6th century when the first templa appear, when Christian liturgy was first being developed, the plays and their architecture had lost their importance and could not have influenced Christian ritual.

A more plausible theory is that the templon models in both form and content the decorative wall of the Torah screen in Jewish synagogues of the second and third centuries. These, too, had three main divisions: a central door leading to the altar, smaller flanking passages, and a distribution of parts similar to a templon. The Torah screen was probably not the direct prototype of the templon; it probably derives from the imitation of the Torah screen in the altar of a typical Syrian pagan temple.Swift, Emerson Howland. ''Hagia Sophia''. Columbia University Press, New York, 1940.

Barriers called templons in Greek were also used on occasions when the Roman Emperors appeared in public, to segregate the Imperial retinue from the crowd.Maria Cheremeteff in Leong, Albert ed.;''The Millennium: Christianity and Russia, A.D. 988-1988''; p.108-110; 1990; St Vladimir's Seminary Press;ISBN 0881410802
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9c407d0515146e8b91f3cdc5358df491" name="Proskenionastemplon" sectnum="1#1">../img/9c407d0515146e8b91f3cdc5358df491.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>