<document id="b603ac31e34db4178f661d642503ed15-2" name="Confirmed_Dead" cat="19">
<text>
While casting the "freighter folk"&mdash;the nickname that ''Lost'''s executive producers/writers/show runners Damon Lindelof and Carlton Cuse use to refer to Daniel, Charlotte, Miles and FrankJensen, Jeff "Doc", (February 20, 2008) ", ''Entertainment Weekly''.  Retrieved on March 17, 2008.&mdash;fake names, occupations and scenes were temporarily assigned, to limit the leak of spoilers.Littleton, Cynthia, (October 12, 2007) "", ''Variety''.  Retrieved on October 13, 2007.  After seeing Ken Leung guest star on HBO's ''The Sopranos'' in April 2007, Lindelof and Cuse wrote the role of Miles specifically for him,Jensen, Jeff, (August 29, 2007) "", ''Entertainment Weekly''.  Retrieved on August 30, 2007. although Leung believed that he was trying out for the part of "brilliant mathematician" "Russell".Ausiello, Michael, (August 19, 2007) "", ''TV Guide''.  Retrieved on April 3, 2008.  The name Miles Straume was simply chosen because the writer-producers thought that "it would be cool if his name sounded like 'maelstrom'".  Had he not taken the part, Lindelof and Cuse claim that Miles would have been scrapped and a new and much different character would have been written into the story instead.  Leung, who was originally contracted as a recurring guest star, was quoted as saying that "Miles doesn't know how to be social, which is great, because I don't know how to be social."Malcolm, Shawna, (February 7, 2008) "", ''TV Guide''.  Retrieved on March 16, 2008.  Costume designer Roland Sanchez wanted to base one of the freighter folk's clothing after that of Keith Richards, specifically a picture in which he wore a sleeveless vest, which he admired.  Sanchez believed that Miles fit the haggard look and bought an Armani Exchange jacket, cut off the sleeves and added a hood and this outfit helped Leung develop Miles.Sanchez, Roland, (February 8, 2008) "", ABC.  Retrieved on March 17, 2008.  Co-executive producer/writer Edward Kitsis had been pitching the name "Lapidus" for years, finally naming an unseen character in the fourteenth episode of the third season Rick Lapidus.Lindelof, Damon & Cuse, Carlton, (March 21, 2008) "", ABC.  Retrieved on March 31, 2008.   Unsatisfied, Kitsis developed the character "Frank Lapidus, Helicopter Pilot".  According to the show runners, recurring guest star Jeff Fahey "was the first and only choice for the role".  They also commended his "intense eyes" and stated that "he has exactly the right sensibilities" for the part.Jensen, Jeff, (August 27, 2007) "", ''Entertainment Weekly''.  Retrieved on August 27, 2007.  Frank was not envisioned with a beard, however, the writer-producers allowed Fahey to keep it for the role.  The writer-producers have said that Frank "never takes anything at face value  a true conspiracy nut  has probably seen every episode of ''The X-Files'',  pay off for him".Keck, Will, (February 13, 2008) "", ''USA Today''.  Retrieved on March 16, 2008.

Rebecca Mader's audition scene was a fake flashback and she was disappointed that it was not used for the show.SBK & Cabin Boy, (February 29, 2008) "", WTKS-FM.  Retrieved on March 9, 2008.  The character's name was spoiled months in advance of broadcast.  Charlotte was originally envisioned as an American;Ausiello, Michael, (February 15, 2008) "", ''TV Guide''.  Retrieved on March 16, 2008. however, the writers preferred Mader's natural English accent to her fake American accent and they changed Charlotte accordingly.  ''Lost'''s writer-producers compared Mader to "a young Nicole Kidman".Jensen, Jeff, (August 29, 2007) "", ''Entertainment Weekly''.  Retrieved on August 30, 2007.  During the casting process, Charlotte was described as a "successful academic".Ausiello, Michael, (August 1, 2007) "", ''TV Guide''.  Retrieved on January 19, 2008.  It was falsely rumored that Kristen Bell was offered the role of Charlotte;Ausiello, Michael, (August 8, 2008) "", ''TV Guide''.  Retrieved on January 19, 2008. Bell had actually spoken to the producers about having a part, however, no role was offered to her.Kubicek, John, (October 16, 2007) "", BuddyTV.  Retrieved on October 24, 2007.  Despite never having seen ''Lost'', Mader decided that she "was not going to leave  room until  made  fall in love with ".Kexk, Will, (February 24, 2008) "", ''USA Today''.  Retrieved on March 16, 2008.  Mader subsequently began to watch the first three seasons of ''Lost'' and was watching the fourth episode when she received the news that she had been chosen for the role.Lachonis, Jon "DocArzt", (February 13, 2008) "", UGO Networks.  Retrieved on March 16, 2008.  In the next two to three weeks, Mader—who was then signed on as a recurring guest star—watched the rest of the first three seasons, watching the third season finale a matter of hours before she began shooting her first "Confirmed Dead" scene, in which Charlotte meets Locke and his group.  Mader was told little about her character by the writer-producers, except that "she was sort of like a female Indiana Jones type".  Mader has found it challenging but fun to play a character with an unknown backstory and motives.  Charlotte's full name is Charlotte Staples Lewis, which is an homage to the author C.S. Lewis, best known for ''The Chronicles of Narnia'' and various books about Christianity.  Lewis was one of Mader's favorite authors as a child and found it "wicked" and "cool" for her character to be named after him.Porter, Rick, (February 13, 2008) "", Zap2it.  Retrieved on March 16, 2008.  Mader also enjoyed that she only requires a small amount of hair and makeup done, saying that "I just wanted to rough it.  I wanted to roll around in the mud with a gun."Nichols, Katherine, (February 19, 2008) "", ''Honolulu Star-Bulletin''.  Retrieved on March 16, 2008.  Mader claims that she has "never had so much fun in  life" as when she is shooting ''Lost''.Dos Santos, Kristin, (February 8, 2008) "", E!.  Retrieved on March 16, 2008. In the episode, Charlotte's birthday is said to be July 2, 1979, Mader's actual birthday. This led to a minor continuity error in the fifth season episode "LaFleur", when Charlotte is depicted as being a little girl in 1974. Executive producers Cuse and Lindelof claimed in a podcast that the original script for "Confirmed Dead" listed Charlotte's birthday as being in 1970 and that Mader had it changed because she did not want people to think she was significantly older than she actually is. This caused a controversy when Mader later stated on her blog that Gregg Nations, the script coordinator, was the one who suggested the change. Cuse and Lindelof later conceded that she was right.

Most or all of the episode was shot from September 11Perez, Mario, (September 11, 2008) "", ABC Medianet.  Retrieved on March 16, 2008. to 23, 2007Harada, Wayne, (September 27, 2008) "", ''Honolulu Advertiser''.  Retrieved on March 17, 2008. and filming overlapped with the following episode.Perez, Mario, (September 19, 2008) "", ABC Medianet.  Retrieved on March 16, 2008.  The Tunisian desert scene was filmed on location in Oahu, Hawaii, like the rest of the episode, at a stone quarry with industrial fans blowing fake sand.  A typical ''Lost'' episode contains fifty visual effects shots.  Among scenes created entirely or partially with effects are the opening scene of "Confirmed Dead", which shows what appears to be the wreckage of 815 underwater and the scene from Daniel's perspective as he parachutes from the helicopter to the ground.  In Frank's flashback, he drops a toy plane, which spirals into a small aquarium.  This shot was not intended to use effects; however, "it's impossible to get a toy plane to spiral the way you want it to", according to supervisor Mitch Suskin.  A tank with still water and rocks on the bottom was filmed and the plane was added in editing.  Suskin said that creating effects for "Confirmed Dead" "was slightly too leisurely" because the episode aired over four months after post-production began.Raugust, Karen, (March 4, 2008) "", VFXWorld.  Retrieved on March 19, 2008.

In fall 2007, ''Lost'''s writers presented ABC executives with the story that a salvage vessel called the ''Christiane I'' looking for the ''Black Rock'', among other things, in the Sunda Trench would come across what would appear to be the wreckage of 815.  ABC hired the Australian company Hoodlum to design a $3 million viral marketing alternate reality game (ARG) titled ''Find 815''.Sinclair, Lara, (february 14, 2008) "", ''The Australian''.  Retrieved on March 17, 2008.  ''Find 815'' ran from December 28, 2007 to January 31, 2008, beginning with a press release issued from ABC Medianet announcing the fictitious return of the fictional Oceanic Airlines' return to business.Connelly, Michael Alan, (January 31, 2008) "", ''Ames Tribune''.  Retrieved on March 17, 2008.  The ARG—apparently the largest ever—followed Sam Thomas, an Oceanic technician who had lost his girlfriend in the crash, as he received cryptic e-mails from ''The Maxwell Group'' (a division of Widmore Industries, but nonexistent in ''Lost''), joined the crew of the ''Christiane I'' and ultimately uncovered 815.La Gesse, Bobby, (January 9, 2008) "", ''New York''.  Retrieved on March 17, 2008.  Because ''Find 815'' was produced separately from the show and without the show's writers, it contradicts events in the TV series.Lindelof, Damon & Cuse, Carlton, (March 10, 2008) "", ABC.  Retrieved on March 1, 2008.  In "Confirmed Dead", 815 is found by a man not present in the game named Ron; Thomas is not mentioned.  Lindelof and Cuse dismissed the game as not being canon (not containing genuine information within the fictional universe) and was largely just a bonus for fans during the between-seasons hiatus.Jensen, Jeff "Doc", (February 20, 2008) "", ''Entertainment Weekly''.  Retrieved on March 17, 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="680e8b3bbdead0c56b8f64b40a0ca9b1" name="Jeff_Fahey" sectnum="2#1">../img/680e8b3bbdead0c56b8f64b40a0ca9b1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>