<document id="b611d063437ed2de37351e8ec76ee3e7-2" name="William_IV_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
The newly created Duke ceased his active service in the Royal Navy in 1790. When the United Kingdom declared war on France in 1793, he was anxious to serve his country and expected a command, but was not given a ship, perhaps at first because he had broken his arm by falling down some stairs drunk, but later because he gave a speech in the House of Lords opposing the war.Ziegler, pp.91–94 The following year he spoke in favour of the war, expecting a command after his change of heart. None came. The Admiralty did not even reply to his request.Ziegler, p.94 He did not lose hope of being appointed to an active post, but when he was made an admiral in 1798, the rank was purely titular.Ziegler, p.95 Despite repeated petitions, he was never given a command throughout the Napoleonic Wars.Ziegler, pp.95–97 In 1811, he was appointed to the honorary position of Admiral of the Fleet. In 1813, he came nearest to any actual fighting, when he visited the British troops fighting in the Low Countries. Watching the bombardment of Antwerp from a church steeple, he came under fire. A bullet pierced his coat.Ziegler, p.115

Instead of serving at sea, he spent time in the House of Lords, where he spoke in opposition to the abolition of slavery, which although not legal in the United Kingdom still existed in the British colonies. Freedom would do the slaves little good, he argued. He had travelled widely and, in his eyes, the living standard among freemen in the Highlands and Islands of Scotland was worse than that among slaves in the West Indies.Ziegler, p.54 His experience in the West Indies lent gravitas to his position, which was perceived as well-argued and just by some of his contemporaries.Ziegler, pp.97–99 Others thought it "shocking that so young a man, under no bias of interest, should be earnest in continuance of the slave trade".Zachary Macaulay writing to Miss Mills, 1 June 1799, quoted in Ziegler, p.98 In his speech to the House of Lords, the Duke insulted the leading abolitionist, saying "the proponents of the abolition are either fanatics or hypocrites, and in one of those classes I rank Mr. Wilberforce".Fulford, p. 121 On other issues he was more liberal, such as supporting moves to abolish penal laws against dissenting Christians.Ziegler, p.99 He also opposed efforts to bar those found guilty of adultery from remarriage.Fulford, pp. 121–122
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9f17e7fda2d9f3421580e53e741c04cc" name="William_IV_by_Sir_Martin_Archer_Shee" sectnum="2#1">../img/9f17e7fda2d9f3421580e53e741c04cc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>