<document id="b65814ec08957f800aac72f7832e9d21-4.2" name="George_Jones_(RAAF_officer)" cat="29">
<text>
Passed over as CAS, Bostock became Air Officer Commanding RAAF Command, in charge of RAAF operations in the Pacific. Jones' role, in contrast, was primarily administrative, that of "raising, training and maintaining" the service.Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp.120–123 Though the CAS was ''de jure'' head of the RAAF, Jones’ new rank of Air Vice Marshal was no higher than Bostock's. In the words of Air Force historian Alan Stephens, "Jones was the head of his service, but he was neither unambiguously its senior officer, nor presiding over a unified command.  The system of divided command... was not an ideal arrangement, but with men of goodwill it could have worked. Regrettably Bostock and Jones were not of that mind..." 

Friction between the two senior officers over the command structure rapidly deteriorated into a state of "complete obduracy", and remained so until the end of the war.Gillison,  As a direct report to George C. Kenney, USAAF, commander of Allied Air Forces in the South West Pacific Area (SWPA), Bostock was able to ignore many directives from Jones, his nominal superior in the RAAF.Helson, ''10 Years at the Top'', pp.132,159 The CAS, however, continued to assert his authority over Bostock’s supplies of manpower and equipment. 

In March 1943 Jones proposed that he take over responsibility for air operations in defence of the Australian mainland but General Douglas MacArthur, Supreme Commander SWPA, refused to countenance it.Odgers,  The next month, with the support of the Air Board, Jones tried to remove Bostock from RAAF Command and replace him with Air Commodore Joe Hewitt, Air Officer Commanding No. 9 Operational Group (9OG). Bostock appealed to Kenney, who advised Jones that he was opposed to any such change of command and threatened to escalate the matter to the Australian Government. MacArthur subsequently told Prime Minister Curtin that Hewitt "was not an adequate replacement" for Bostock, and the matter was dropped.Helson, ''10 Years at the Top'', pp.123–126 Six months later Jones would sack Hewitt over morale issues in 9OG raised during the offensive on Rabaul; Kenney called Hewitt’s removal "bad news". 

Jones (right) in 1942 with members of HQ Allied Air Forces SWPA, including Group Captain Val Hancock (centre) and Air Commodore Joe Hewitt, later AOC 9OG (second right)
Jones himself came under threat of transfer or subordination in April 1943 when the Federal Government began moves to unite the Air Force's command by creating an overarching ''Air Officer Commanding RAAF'' position that would have effectively replaced Jones as CAS and also been senior to Bostock. Air Marshal Drummond was again approached but once more the British Air Ministry refused to release him, having selected him for an Air Council post. Macarthur rejected two other RAF candidates, and the plan was held over.Helson, ''10 Years at the Top'', pp.165–172Odgers,  In the King's Birthday Honours that June, Jones was appointed a Companion of the Order of the Bath.

By June 1944 the Jones-Bostock conflict and the anomalous division of administrative and operational responsibilities again led the Australian government to consider the appointment of a new commander senior to both officers. Air Marshal Sir Keith Park, the New Zealand-born AOC of No. 11 Group RAF during the Battle of Britain, was sought for the position but negotiations were broken off when MacArthur advised that it was too late to make such a change and that the problem had now gone "quiet". That it was far from over, however, was apparent in a series of cables exchanged between the two Air Vice Marshals in January 1945. Jones sent a signal to Bostock complaining of the latter’s "insubordinate tone" and "repeated attempts to usurp authority of this Headquarters". Bostock replied that as AOC RAAF Command he was "responsible to Commander, Allied Air Forces, and not, repeat not, subordinate to you”, and that he would "continue to take the strongest exception to your unwarranted and uninformed interference".Odgers,  Despite such acrimony, the command structure remained unchanged for the rest of the war. 

Responsible as CAS for building up Australia's air combat assets, in 1943 Jones had given an assurance to the Australian government that he could maintain a force of 73 squadrons, despite Kenney's prediction that even the RAAF's then-currently approved strength of 45 squadrons was beyond its capacity.Odgers,  In the event, by the end of the war Jones had expanded the RAAF to 70 squadrons in the Pacific and Europe, including several heavy bomber units. One of his most controversial decisions of the war was during the invasion of Tarakan in May 1945 when he grounded Australian B-24 Liberator squadrons scheduled to take part in the attack, due to their crews having exceeded their monthly quota of flying hours. Bostock was not consulted, and said that he would have thankfully "fallen through a crack in the boards on the deck" as he watched the attacking formations from a U.S. warship, minus the expected RAAF aircraft. Kenney sympathised with him; he once commented in his diary that "Jones and Bostock ... fight each other harder than the Japs".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="78e086ccc86550684c10dac9a7fd01e1" name="AVM_George_Jones" sectnum="4.2#1">../img/78e086ccc86550684c10dac9a7fd01e1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>