<document id="b65814ec08957f800aac72f7832e9d21-7" name="George_Jones_(RAAF_officer)" cat="29">
<text>
Jones' ten years as CAS was the longest continuous tour of any RAAF chief. at . Retrieved on 1 December 2008. Air Marshal Sir Richard Williams' thirteen years as head of the RAAF comprised three separate terms, the longest of which was eight years. Despite his longevity in the position, he is still primarily known for two events early in his term, the surprise circumstance of his appointment, and his feud with Bill Bostock that lasted until the end of World War II.Helson, ''10 Years at the Top'', pp.ii-xv,299 The conflict between its two senior officers has been labelled "disastrous" for the RAAF, one that "diminished its standing" in the eyes of its Allies.Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp.123–125Horner, "The Evolution of Australian Higher Command Arrangements", p.13 Jones would claim in his autobiography that he had never intrigued for the role of CAS and would have worked loyally for Bostock if the latter had been appointed.


Beyond these controversies, however, Jones significantly influenced the Air Force's development during and after the war. He was honoured for his work running the Empire Air Training Scheme in 1940–42 and has received credit as CAS for building up the RAAF's strength to 70 squadrons by 1945. After the war he played a personal part in improving education within the service, including the establishment of RAAF College, along similar lines to Royal Military College, Duntroon and the Royal Australian Naval College, as well as the RAAF Staff College. One of his last directions as Chief was the formation of RAAF Museum at Point Cook, where it is still based. Official Site. Retrieved on 23 June 2007.

Jones encouraged local industry to design and build trainers for the RAAF and produce more sophisticated combat aircraft under licence from overseas manufacturers. This led to the Winjeel basic trainer and Australian industry co-partnership in production of the CAC Sabre and Canberra jets; such local participation has continued to figure in major RAAF aircraft acquisitions.Stephens, ''Going Solo'', p.188

He refused to update the Air Force's command structure from one based on region to one of function, something his successor, Air Marshal Sir Donald Hardman, would accomplish, and has been criticised for a systemic resistance to change.Helson, ''10 Years at the Top'', pp.253–254 Jones was described in David Horner's ''The Commanders'' as "a steady, sincere but colourless leader",Horner, ''The Commanders'', p.305 while the official Air Force historian, Dr Alan Stephens, found him "a good and decent man, who had overcome considerable personal hardship in his youth to achieve exceptional professional success" but "neither an inspiring leader, nor a notable thinker". Nevertheless his 'Plan D' for the RAAF's post-war organisation remained the service’s blueprint until the early 1970s.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5eb49dce51280661f8953ef519f02a1f" name="AWM019070Jones" sectnum="7#1">../img/5eb49dce51280661f8953ef519f02a1f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>