<document id="b698ff8744eba17a13e6e2b022fe38e2-6.10.2" name="Edmontosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
Both of the "mummy" specimens collected by the Sternbergs were reported to have had possible gut contents.  Charles H. Sternberg reported the presence of carbonized gut contents in the American Museum of Natural History specimen, but this material has not been described. The plant remains in the Senckenberg Museum specimen have been described, but have proven difficult to interpret.  The plants found in the carcass included needles of the conifer ''Cunninghamites elegans'', twigs from conifer and broadleaf trees, and numerous small seeds or fruits. Upon their description in 1922, they were the subject of a debate in the German-language journal ''Paläontologische Zeitschrift''. Kräusel, who described the material, interpreted it as the gut contents of the animal, while Abel could not rule out that the plants had been washed into the carcass after death. At the time, hadrosaurids were thought to have been aquatic animals, and Kräusel made a point of stating that the specimen did not rule out hadrosaurids eating water plants. The discovery of possible gut contents made little impact in English-speaking circles, except for another brief mention of the aquatic-terrestrial dichotomy, until it was brought up by John Ostrom in the course of an article reassessing the old interpretation of hadrosaurids as water-bound.  Instead of trying to adapt the discovery to the aquatic model, he used it as a line of evidence that hadrosaurids were terrestrial herbivores. While his interpretation of hadrosaurids as terrestrial animals has been generally accepted, the Senckenberg plant fossils remain equivocal. Kenneth Carpenter has suggested that they may actually represent the gut contents of a starving animal, instead of a typical diet. Other authors have noted that because the plant fossils were removed from their original context in the specimen and were heavily prepared, it is no longer possible to follow up on the original work, leaving open the possibility that the plants were washed-in debris.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="459414c75b9dc76c3ca2fe6fc55f124a" name="Pasta_-_mummified_trachodon_-_AmMusNatHist" sectnum="6.10.2#1">../img/459414c75b9dc76c3ca2fe6fc55f124a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>