<document id="b698ff8744eba17a13e6e2b022fe38e2-1.1" name="Edmontosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
The skull of a fully grown ''Edmontosaurus'' was around a meter (or yard) long, with ''E. regalis'' falling on the longer end of the spectrum and ''E. annectens'' falling on the shorter end. The skull was roughly triangular in profile, with no bony cranial crest. Viewed from above, the front and rear of the skull were expanded, with the broad front forming a duck-bill or spoon-bill shape.  The beak was toothless, and both the upper and lower beaks were extended by keratinous material. Substantial remains of the keratinous upper beak are known from the "mummy" kept at the Senckenberg Museum. In this specimen, the preserved nonbony part of the beak extended for at least  beyond the bone, projecting down vertically.Lull, Richard Swann; and Wright, Nelda E. (1942). ''Hadrosaurian Dinosaurs of North America''. pp. 110–117. The nasal openings of ''Edmontosaurus'' were elongate and housed in deep depressions surrounded by distinct bony rims above, behind, and below. In at least one case (the Senckenberg specimen), rarely preserved sclerotic rings were preserved in the eye sockets.Lull, Richard Swann; and Wright, Nelda E. (1942). ''Hadrosaurian Dinosaurs of North America''. pp. 128–130. Another rarely seen bone, the stapes (the reptilian ear bone), has also been seen in a specimen of ''Edmontosaurus''.

Teeth were present only in the maxillae (upper cheeks) and dentaries (main bone of the lower jaw).  The teeth were continually replaced, taking about half a year to form. They grew in columns, with an observed maximum of six in each, and the number of columns varied based on the animal's size. Known column counts for the various species are: 51 to 53 columns per maxilla and 48 to 49 per dentary (teeth of the upper jaw being slightly narrower than those in the lower jaw) for ''E. regalis''; 43 columns per maxilla and 36 per dentary for ''E. annectens''; and 52 and 44 for ''E. saskatchewanensis''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ed533c3d8778c8c02b94ea9a2d882555" name="Edmontosaurus_annectens" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/ed533c3d8778c8c02b94ea9a2d882555.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>