<document id="b698ff8744eba17a13e6e2b022fe38e2-1.2" name="Edmontosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
Hip bones of ''Edmontosaurus'', an ornithischian dinosaur.
The number of vertebrae differs between specimens.  ''E. regalis'' had thirteen neck vertebrae, eighteen back vertebrae, nine hip vertebrae, and an unknown number of tail vertebrae.  A specimen once identified as belonging to ''Anatosaurus edmontoni'' (now considered to be the same as ''E. annectens'') is reported as having an additional back vertebra and 85 tail vertebrae, with an undisclosed amount of restoration. Other hadrosaurids are only reported as having 50 to 70 tail vertebrae, so this appears to have been an overestimate. The anterior back was curved toward the ground, with the neck flexed upward and the rest of the back and tail held horizontally. Most of the back and tail were lined by ossified tendons arranged in a latticework along the neural spines of the vertebrae.  This condition has been described as making the back and at least part of the tail "ramrod" straight. The ossified tendons are interpreted as having strengthened the vertebral column against gravitational stress, incurred through being a large animal with a horizontal vertebral column otherwise supported mostly by the hind legs and hips. 

The shoulder blades were long flat blade-like bones, held roughly parallel to the vertebral column. The hips were composed of three elements each: an elongate ilium above the articulation with the leg, an ischium below and behind with a long thin rod, and a pubis in front that flared into a plate-like structure.  The structure of the hip hindered the animal from standing with its back erect, because in such a position the thigh bone would have pushed against the joint of the ilium and pubis, instead of pushing only against the solid ilium.  The nine fused hip vertebrae provided support for the hip. 

The fore legs were shorter and less heavily built than the hind legs.  The upper arm had a large deltopectoral crest for muscle attachment, while the ulna and radius were slim.  The upper arm and forearm were similar in length.  The wrist was simple, with only two small bones.  Each hand had four fingers, with no thumb (first finger).  The index second, third, and fourth fingers were approximately the same length and were united in life within a fleshy covering.  Although the second and third finger had hoof-like unguals, these bones were also within the skin and not apparent from the outside.  The little finger diverged from the other three and was much shorter. The thigh bone was robust and straight, with a prominent flange about halfway down the posterior side. This ridge was for the attachment of powerful muscles attached to the hips and tail that pulled the thighs (and thus the hind legs) backward and helped maintain the use of the tail as a balancing organ.Lull, Richard Swann; and Wright, Nelda E. (1942). ''Hadrosaurian Dinosaurs of North America''. pp. 98–110.  Each foot had three toes, with no big toe or little toe.  The toes had hoof-like tips.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9f3286d8f3174065de3354a2f4fc9ffa" name="Edmontosaurusskel" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/9f3286d8f3174065de3354a2f4fc9ffa.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>