<document id="b6d348d347abf6bf79ee669f12acea70-2.1" name="AMX-30E" cat="29">
<text>
Ultimately, a mixed solution named ''Tecnología Santa Bárbara-Bazán'' (Santa Bárbara-Bazán Technology) (or TSB) was chosen.Mazarrasa, ''Carro de Combate AMX-30E'', p. 80  The improvement of the tank's mobility entailed replacing the HS-110 diesel engine with an MTU 833 Ka-501 diesel engine, producing 850 metric horsepower (625.17 kW), and the transmission with a German ZF LSG-3000, compatible with engines of up to 1,500 metric horsepower (1103.25 kW).  The first 30 engines were to have 50% of the engine manufactured in Spain; the rest, 73% were to be produced indigenously.Pérez-Guerra, ''Spanish AMX-30 MBT upgrade program'', p. 500  This new engine gave the modernized tank a power ratio of 23 metric horsepower to tonne (21.13 hp/S/T).  The new engine was coupled with the AMX-30B2's improved torsion-bar suspension, which used larger diameter torsion-bars and new shocks.Mazarrasa, ''Carro de Combate AMX-30E'', p. 82

 

To improve the tank's firepower, the gun mount around the loader's turret hatch was modified to allow the installation of a 12.7-millimeter (0.5 in.) machine gun, while the main gun's firepower was augmented through the introduction of the new CETME437A armor piercing fin stabilized discarding sabot (APFSDS).  The gun's accuracy was improved through the installation of the new Mark 9 modification A/D fire control system, designed by Hughes Aircraft Company.  The new system allowed firing during the day and during night operations, and increased the likelihood of a first round impact (meaning, the chances of the first projectile fired by the gun hitting its target).  The fire control system was also modernized through the exchange of the old M282 gunner's periscope with a new periscope and a new Nd:YAG laser rangefinder.  A new ballistic computer, the NSC-800, was issued, as well as a new digital panel for the gunner, designed and manufactured by the Spanish company INISEL.  The tank commander also received a control unit that allowed the choice of ammunition for the gun and provided information on the ballistics of the round and the target to be engaged.  As a result, the loader received a presentation unit to display information on which round to load into the gun's breech and to communicate ballistic data received, including angular velocity, wind velocity, gun elevation and vehicle inclination.  The fire control system also allowed for the future upgrade to a more sophisticated stabilization system for the tank's main gun.  Survivability improvements included the addition of new steel side-skirts, a new smoke generating system linked to the engine and a new fire suppression system.Mazarrasa, ''Carro de Combate AMX-30'', pp. 81–83

One hundred fifty AMX-30Es received this modernization package and were designated AMX-30EM2s.  The program began in 1989 and ended in 1993.Mazarrasa, ''Carro de Combate AMX-30E'', p. 85  Ultimately, Spain's AMX-30EM2s were replaced by brand-new Centauro anti-tank vehicles, which were partially manufactured in Spain, in the early 21st century.''Defensa firma un contrato de 200 millones de euros con Finmeccanica'', El País
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f60047c1da07ad392e844f7bee80210c" name="AMX30_side" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/f60047c1da07ad392e844f7bee80210c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>