<document id="b71ff51adfd06cdef61b317cadd67cd1-1" name="Banksia_ericifolia" cat="3">
<text>
''Banksia ericifolia'' grows as a large shrub up to 6 metres (20 ft) in height, though often smaller, around 1&ndash;2 metres (3&ndash;6 ft), in exposed places such as coastal or mountain heathlands. The grey-coloured bark is smooth and fairly thin with lenticels; however it can thicken significantly with age. The linear dark green leaves are small and narrow, 9&ndash;20 mm (⅓&ndash;¾ in) long and up to 1 mm wide, generally with two small teeth at the tips. The leaves are crowded and alternately arranged on the branches. New growth generally occurs in summer and is an attractive lime green colour. 

Flowering is in autumn, or in winter in cooler areas; the inflorescences are flower spikes 7&ndash;22 cm (3&ndash;10 in) high and 5 cm (2 in) broad or so. Each individual flower consists of a tubular perianth made up of four fused tepals, and one long wiry style. Characteristic of the taxonomic section in which it is placed, the styles are hooked rather than straight. The styles' ends are initially trapped inside the upper perianth parts, but break free at anthesis, when the flowers open. The spikes are red or gold in overall colour, with styles golden, orange, orange-red or burgundy. Some unusual forms have striking red styles on a whitish perianth. Very occasionally, forms with all yellow inflorescences are seen. Though not terminal, the flower spikes are fairly prominently displayed emerging from the foliage; they arise from two- to three-year-old nodes.

Old flower spikes fade to brown and then grey with age; old flower parts soon fall, revealing numerous small dark grey to dull black finely furred follicles. Oblong in shape and 15&ndash;20 mm (½&ndash;⅔ in) in diameter, the follicles are ridged on each valve and remain closed until burnt by fire. ''Banksia ericifolia'' responds to fire by seeding, the parent plant being killed. As plants take several years to flower in the wild, it is very sensitive to too-frequent burns and has been eliminated in some areas where this occurs. With time and the production of more cones with seed-containing follicles, however, plants can store up to 16,500 seeds at eight years of age. Some plants produce multiple flower spikes, possibly of varying sizes, from a single point of origin.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a2e5d9f401c31da82f2d9a51c5ef3e93" name="Banksia_ericifolia_WC_multibuds_email" sectnum="1#1">../img/a2e5d9f401c31da82f2d9a51c5ef3e93.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>