<document id="b74492d9fb770ce268d7d8b3ff5f7d2a-3.2" name="Princess_Louise,_Duchess_of_Argyll" cat="25">
<text>
Louise became engaged to the Marquess of Lorne on 3 October 1870. Lorne was invited to Balmoral Castle in Scotland, and accompanied Louise, the Lord Chancellor, Lord Hatherley and Queen Victoria's lady-in-waiting, Jane, Marchioness of Ely on a drive. Later that day, Louise returned and announced to the Queen that Lorne had “spoken of his devotion” to Louise, and she accepted his proposal in the knowledge of the Queen's approval.Victoria, Queen (More leaves), p. 74 The Queen found it difficult to let go of her daughter, confiding in her journal that she “felt painfully the thought of losing her”. The new breach in royal tradition caused surprise, especially in Germany, and Queen Victoria wrote to the Queen of Prussia that princes of small impoverished German houses were “very unpopular” in Britain and that Lord Lorne, a “person of distinction at home” with “an independent fortune” was “really no lower in rank than minor German Royalty”.Quoted in Benson, p. 166

Victoria settled an annuity on Louise shortly before her marriage. The ceremony was conducted at St George's Chapel at Windsor Castle on 21 March 1871,Wake, p. 138 and the crowd outside was so large that, for the first time, policemen had to form chain barriers to keep control.Wake, p. 139 Louise wore a wedding veil of Honiton lace that she designed herself, and was escorted into the Chapel by her mother, and her two eldest brothers, the Prince of Wales and the Duke of Edinburgh. On this occasion, the usually severe black of the Queen's mourning dress was relieved by the crimson rubies and blues of the Garter star. Following the ceremony, the Queen kissed Louise, and Lorne – now a member of the royal family, but still a subject – kissed the Queen's hand. The couple then journeyed to Claremont in Surrey for the honeymoon, but the presence of attendants on the journey, and at meal times, made it impossible for them to talk privately.Wake, p. 145 The short four-day visit did not pass without an interruption from the Queen, who was curious about her daughter's thoughts on married life.Wake, p. 146
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b389f42f7f468e1086a9a09080d22718" name="Lorne" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/b389f42f7f468e1086a9a09080d22718.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>