<document id="b74492d9fb770ce268d7d8b3ff5f7d2a-6.9" name="Princess_Louise,_Duchess_of_Argyll" cat="25">
<text>
Upon Queen Victoria's death, Louise entered the social circle of her brother, the new King Edward VII, with whom she had much in common, including smoking.Longford (''Letters''), p. 74 She had an obsession with physical fitness, and if she was sneered at for this, she would retort by saying: “Never mind, I'll outlive you all.”Quoted in Longford (''Letters''), p. 74 Meanwhile, Louise's husband, 9th Duke of Argyll since 1900, took his seat in the House of Lords. The Colonial Secretary, Joseph Chamberlain, offered him the office of Governor General of Australia that year, but the offer was declined. Louise continued her sculpture, and in 1902, designed a memorial to the colonial soldiers who died in the Boer War.Longford (''Letters''), p. 73 In the same year, she began a nude study on a married woman suggested by the English painter Sir William Blake Richmond.

Louise spent much of her time at Kent House, and she frequently visited Scotland with her husband. Financial pressures did not disappear when Lorne became Duke, and Louise avoided inviting the King to Inveraray, Argyll's ancestral home, because the couple were economising. When Queen Victoria had visited the house before Lorne became Duke of Argyll, there were seventy servants and seventy-four dogs.  By the time of Edward VII's accession, there were four servants and two dogs.

The Duke of Argyll's health continued to deteriorate. He became increasingly senile, and Louise nursed him devotedly from 1911. In these years Louise and her husband were closer than they had been before.   In spring 1914 Louise stayed at Kensington Palace while her husband remained on the Isle of Wight. He developed bronchial problems followed by double pneumonia. Louise was sent for on 28 April 1914, and he died on 2 May.Longford (''Letters''), p. 77 Following his death, Louise had a nervous breakdown and suffered from intense loneliness, writing to a friend shortly afterwards: “My loneliness without the Duke is quite terrible. I wonder what he does now!”Quoted in Longford (''Letters''), p. 77
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9008f9cb60f7921c2f214d2d3ccdd225" name="Princess_Louise_Laszlo" sectnum="6.9#1">../img/9008f9cb60f7921c2f214d2d3ccdd225.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>