<document id="b74492d9fb770ce268d7d8b3ff5f7d2a-3.1" name="Princess_Louise,_Duchess_of_Argyll" cat="25">
<text>
As a daughter of the Queen, Louise was a desirable bride; more so as she is regarded as the Queen's most beautiful daughter by both contemporary and modern biographers.The biographers Jehanne Wake, Elizabeth Longford and Mark Stocker claim this However, she was accused by the press, without substantiation, of romantic affairs. This, coupled with her liberalism and feminism, prompted the Queen to find her a husband. The choice had to suit Victoria as well as Louise, and the Queen insisted that her daughter's husband should live near her, a promise also made by Helena's husband. Various suitors were proposed by the leading royal houses of Europe: Princess Alexandra proposed her brother, the Crown Prince of Denmark, but the Queen was strongly opposed to another Danish marriage that could antagonise Prussia.Prussia and Denmark were in conflict over the Schleswig-Holstein question Victoria, Louise's eldest sister, proposed the tall and rich Prince Albrecht of Prussia, but Queen Victoria disapproved of another Prussian marriage that would have been unpopular in England.Buckle (Vol I), p. 632 Prince Albrecht was also reluctant to settle in England as required. William, Prince of Orange was also considered a suitor, but because of his extravagant lifestyle in Paris, where he lived openly with a mistress, the Queen quickly vetoed the idea.Wake, p. 100



Louise viewed marriage to any prince as undesirable, and announced that she wished to marry John Campbell, the Marquess of Lorne, heir to the Duke of Argyll. No such marriage, between a daughter of a Sovereign and a British subject, had been given official recognition since 1515, when Charles Brandon, the first Duke of Suffolk, married Mary Tudor. Louise's brother, the Prince of Wales, was strongly opposed to a marriage with a non-mediatized noble.Benson, p. 162 Furthermore, Lorne's father, George Campbell, the eighth Duke of Argyll, was an ardent supporter of William Gladstone, and the Prince of Wales was worried that he would drag the royal family into political disputes.Buckle (Vol I), p. 632 Nevertheless, the opposition was crushed by the Queen, who wrote to the Prince of Wales in 1869:



The Queen also stated that Louise's marriage to a subject would bring “''new'' blood” into the family, while all European princes were related to each other. She was convinced that this would strengthen the royal family morally and physically.Paraphrased from Buckle (second series) pp. 632–633
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="cad8a00faf8522956dee3432db885c4a" name="Princess_Louise_and_Lorne_engagement" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/cad8a00faf8522956dee3432db885c4a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>