<document id="b7a2bf685b4f6d1418c759ab53e83cda-4.2" name="2005_Texas_Longhorns_football_team" cat="26">
<text>
According to ''USA Today'', the match-up between the Longhorns and the Ohio State Buckeyes (OSU) was one of the most-anticipated games of the 2005 season. Teams have become increasingly conservative in scheduling highly-ranked non-conference opponents, so a meeting of the number 2 and number 4 teams in the country was unusual this early in the season.  Because of the significance of the game in the national championship race, ESPN College GameDay chose the game as the site of its weekly broadcast. The American Football Coaches Association brought the national championship trophy to the game and displayed it on the field near Bevo, the UT mascot (photo below).

Texas and Ohio State are two of the oldest and "most storied" programs in college football, but this game was the first meeting between the two teams. For Texas, it meant playing a second Big Ten Conference "powerhouse" less than one year after winning the first meeting between Texas and the University of Michigan at the end of the 2004 season.

The game was played in Ohio Stadium, also known as "The Horseshoe" or "the Shoe". This stadium is notoriously tough for visiting teams, as its large capacity and structural design focus a tremendous amount of crowd noise that can make it difficult for the visiting team to call audibles at the line of scrimmage. The game's 105,565 attendance set a record for Ohio Stadium.

Texas scored first with a 42 yard field goal, which was a career-long for Longhorn kicker David Pino.  A five yard touchdown pass from Vince Young to Billy Pittman gave the Longhorns a 10&ndash;0 lead at the end of the first quarter.  The Buckeyes controlled most of the second quarter.  Their first score was a 45 yd field goal by Josh Huston followed by a 36 yard touchdown pass from Troy Smith to Santonio Holmes to tie the score at 10&ndash;10.  They took the lead with two more field goals from Josh Huston.  Texas made a field goal to trim Ohio State's lead to 16&ndash;13 at the half.  In the third quarter, Texas made one field goal and OSU made two, extending Ohio State's lead to 22&ndash;16.  In the fourth quarter, Texas regained the lead with a touchdown pass from Young to Limas Sweed.  UT's Aaron Harris sacked OSU's Troy Smith for a safety and Texas took a three point lead, which they held when time expired.  

Texas' win, by a score of 25&ndash;22, was the lowest scoring game Texas would experience all season, both in terms of points scored by Texas and total points.  Fourth-ranked OSU became the highest-ranked non-conference opponent the Longhorns had ever beaten at an opponent's home stadium. The previous high came in 1983 when third-ranked Texas pulled off a 20&ndash;7 upset versus fifth-ranked Auburn. Texas became the first non-conference opponent to beat the Buckeyes in Ohio Stadium since 1990, putting an end to a 36-game home victory string over non-conference opponents. The Longhorns also were the first team to beat the Buckeyes in a night game at The Horseshoe and it was UT's 10th straight victory in a night-game road contest. ESPN and ''College Football Rivals'' each named the game one of the best football games of the season.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="af17c19614e73eea541a174ac3594570" name="Guadalupe_Street_After_the_Texas_Beat_Ohio_State_2005" sectnum="4.2#1">../img/af17c19614e73eea541a174ac3594570.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>