<document id="b7a2bf685b4f6d1418c759ab53e83cda-4.5" name="2005_Texas_Longhorns_football_team" cat="26">
<text>
Football fans consider the annual game between Texas and the Oklahoma Sooners (OU) one of the greatest rivalries games in all of college sports. Though officially called the Red River Rivalry, it remains better known by its traditional name, the Red River Shootout; the 2005 match-up was the 100th in the series. 

Since 1912 the teams have played the game at the Cotton Bowl stadium in Dallas, Texas, amid the atmosphere of the adjacent Texas State Fair. This is unusual because most college football games alternate between the opponents home stadiums.   Dallas was chosen as the neutral site because it is approximately halfway between the two schools.  The stadium is divided down the 50-yard line, with half of the stadium predominantly clad in the crimson and cream colors of Oklahoma, and the other half mostly wearing the burnt orange and white of Texas.

The game frequently has implications for the conference and national championship races. Since 1945, at least one of the teams was ranked among the top 25 teams in the nation coming into 60 out of 65 games. Prior to the 2005 game, Texas held an advantage in the all-time series 55&ndash;39&ndash;5, which included a 43&ndash;35&ndash;4 edge in Dallas, but Oklahoma had won the 5 previous games, including the two worst losses ever for a Texas team in the series. Those losses had helped build a reputation that Mack Brown was not capable of winning in "Big Games". Four times during those five years, Texas' loss to Oklahoma prevented them from playing in the Big 12 Conference Championship Game.  One of these two teams appeared in four of the nine BCS national championship games from 1999–2007.

The Longhorns scored first with a touchdown pass from Vince Young to Ramonce Taylor; this was the first time for Texas to lead Oklahoma since 2002 and Texas' first passing touchdown against Oklahoma since 2000.  The Sooners' Garret Hartley answered with a 52-yard field goal, the longest of his college career, and a 9-yard field goal.  Longhorn Jamaal Charles scored next on a 80-yard touchdown run.  UT then scored with a 38-yard field goal by Richmond McGee and a 64-yard long bomb from Young to Billy Pittman just before halftime, giving Texas a 24&ndash;6 lead at the half.  UT made the only score of the third quarter: a 27-yard touchdown pass from Young to Pittman.  In the fourth quarter UT scored two touchdowns while OU scored one.

UT was favored by 14 points and won the game by 33 points, tying the biggest margin of victory for the Longhorns in the history of the rivalry, a 40&ndash;7 victory in 1941. The game also marked the sixth time the Longhorns entered the contest ranked second nationally; they have won all six. With the win, Texas started their season 5&ndash;0 for the first time since 1983.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d5c8387a3029d641bc143f01e1a83937" name="2005_Red_River_Shootout_cropped" sectnum="4.5#1">../img/d5c8387a3029d641bc143f01e1a83937.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>