<document id="b7a2bf685b4f6d1418c759ab53e83cda-6" name="2005_Texas_Longhorns_football_team" cat="26">
<text>
Analysts labeled the team, their season, and their championship victory as the greatest or among the greatest in the history of the sport.  College Football News judged the 2005 Longhorns to have played the greatest college football season ever. Sports-writers at College Football News also consider the 2006 Rose Bowl to be the best college football game ever played. Furman Bisher of the Atlanta Journal-Constitution said "if there ever has been a greater game, I never saw it, and I’ve been watching college football games since 1934." ''Scout.com'' called it "one of the best national title games ever", while Kevin Hench of Fox Sports called it "perhaps the greatest college football game ever played."  ESPN declared the 2006 Rose Bowl Game an instant classic and re-aired it within a week of the original broadcast. ESPN later awarded the 2006 ESPY Award to the Longhorns and Trojans for the 2006 "Best Game" in any sport. Vince Young and Matt Leinart accepted the award on behalf of their teams. ESPN columnist Mark Schlabach ranked the 2005 Texas Longhorns as fourth-best among the first ten BCS-era champions. 

The championship game drew attention from political figures.  Head Coach Mack Brown took a congratulatory call from United States President George W. Bush, who told Brown, "Congratulations on a wonderful moment...Tell the team congratulations, we're proud of them." White House Press Secretary Scott McClellan said Bush wished Brown and the Longhorns all the best, and said that he looked forward to having them visit the White House soon. Bush was formerly a Governor of Texas and his daughter Jenna is a UT graduate. On February 14, 2006, Bush did host the team and coaches at the White House.  California Governor Arnold Schwarzenegger lost a bet with Texas Governor Rick Perry on the outcome and had to send Perry a basket of “California wines, fruit and other goodies”. The food was donated to National Guard troops in Texas.  Both governors also offered autographed, handmade cowboy boots that were auctioned to benefit survivors of Hurricane Rita and Hurricane Katrina.  Los Angeles Mayor Antonio Villaraigosa, lost a bet with Austin Mayor Will Wynn and had to send a basket of produce, such as avocados, from a local farmers' market; Wynn had bet Texas finest barbecue.

Seconds after Texas beat Southern California 41-38, the university lit the UT tower orange, the traditional signal of victory on the campus. Since this was a national championship, office lights were also left selectively lit in order to form a number "1" on all four sides of the tower (pictured).  Texas students and fans spilled onto the streets of Austin and made their way to campus for an impromptu celebration. Though police were out in force, there were no reports of problems.  The school commissioned a painting titled ''The University of Texas National Championship 2005'' by Opie Otterstad to commemorate the win in the Rose Bowl and the National Championship.

Special editions of magazines and products featured the team.  ''Dave Campbell's Texas Football'' put out a 45,000-copy special issue titled ''One for the Ages - Vince Young Leads Longhorns to the Fourth National Title''. This issue included a column from Longhorn fan Matthew McConaughey as well as 15 pages of photos from the Rose Bowl. The cover featured Young kissing the "crystal football" national championship trophy.  Sports Illustrated held up their regular weekly edition to await the results of the Rose Bowl. They finally went to press with a cover showing Young diving into the end zone with the label "Superman". Analysis inside the issue gave Young a large part of the credit for the win. They also printed a special commemorative issue in the state of Texas with Young on the cover, shouting in triumph amidst a storm of multi-colored confetti after winning the game. Features in the special edition included a story on ''Vince Young's Glory Days'' by Tim Layden, as well as a story dissecting ''How the'' Rose Bowl ''was won'' by Austin Murphy. The issue was on sale alongside the regular edition of the magazine.  General Mills produced a commemorative issue Wheaties box featuring Mack Brown and a Texas Longhorns football helmet on the front. The commemorative packaging was sold nationwide. Texas is the first national college football champion to be featured since Nebraska was on the box in 1997.

Individual players and coaches also received honors.  "Vince Young Day" was proclaimed by Mayor Bill White in Houston, Texas on January 10, 2006, to honor the Houston native. White said that Young is "an inspiration to all Houstonians, both young and old." On January 15, 2006, 51,244 Texas fans gathered in Darrell K. Royal-Texas Memorial Stadium to celebrate the team and their victorious season.  Mack Brown was named the Paul "Bear" Bryant College Football Coach of the Year, as voted on by the National Sportscasters and Sportswriters Association. Brown became the first winner of the award from UT since Darrell Royal in 1963.  The championship season lifted the reputation of Mack Brown and the offensive coordinator, Greg Davis.  Davis was consistently criticized for over-conservative play-calling.  After the championship win the criticism quieted down, but did not go away completely.  As of 2007 sportswriters continue to debate whether Vince Young and the other talented UT players succeeded despite Davis or because of him.

Despite previous statements that he would return for his senior season, redshirt junior quarterback Vince Young announced that he would forgo his final year of NCAA eligibility and made himself eligible for the 2006 National Football League draft. The Tennessee Titans chose him as the third overall draft pick. Besides Young, five other Longhorns from this championship team joined professional teams through the 2006 NFL Draft - Michael Huff (number 7 overall), Cedric Griffin (number 48 overall), David Thomas (number 86 overall), Jonathan Scott (number 141 overall) and Rodrique Wright (number 222 overall). As a result, fullback Ahmard Hall was re-united with his former team-mate Vince Young in the NFL, playing for Tennessee.  One year later, seven more members of this team were selected in the 2007 NFL Draft - Michael Griffin (number 19 overall), Aaron Ross (number 20 overall), Justin Blalock (number 39 overall), Tim Crowder (number 56 overall), Brian Robison (number 102 overall), Tarell Brown (number 147 overall), Kasey Studdard (number 183 overall).  Lyle Sendlein and Selvin Young were not drafted but signed with NFL teams as free agents.  In the 2008 NFL Draft, five more Longhorns from this team were selected: Limas Sweed (number 53rd overall), Jamaal Charles (number 73 overall), Jermichael Finley (number 91 overall), Tony Hills (number 130 overall), and Frank Okam (number 151 overall). In addition, Brandon Foster, Marcus Griffin, Nate Jones and Derek Lokey agreed to sign free-agent contracts with NFL teams. 

For the fiscal year which ended in August 2005, just as the 2005 football season was starting, Texas was the nation's richest and most profitable football program, with revenue of $53.2 million, and a profit of $38.7 million.  Following the national championship, for the 2005&ndash;2006 fiscal year, UT also led the nation in royalties from merchandise sales, setting a new national record at $8.2 million.  These royalties went to the University as a whole, not specifically to the athletics programs.  The team topped the merchandise rankings again for he 2006&ndash;2007 fiscal year.

The official website of UT football posted a special logo (pictured) proclaiming the Longhorns as the national champions.  The logo featured the script "National Champions" centered prominently in the center, with "MACKBROWN-TEXASFOOTBALL.COM" in the lower left and "THE OFFICIAL SITE OF THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS LONGHORNS" in the lower right. In the background was an image of a rose, with a small Longhorn symbol appearing in front of the rose and between the two sections of the smaller print. In the upper right-hand side, the years "1963, 1969, 1970, 2005" appear, with the "2005" given special emphasis. These years correspond to the four consensus national championships won by the UT football team. The special logo was removed from the website's home page after a few months, but as of 2007 it is still found on certain portions of the site related to the 2005 season.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7262615ecfde874baa7a7f260f5ba442" name="George_W._Bush_and_Mack_Brown_with_the_2005_Texas_Longhorn_football_team" sectnum="6#1">../img/7262615ecfde874baa7a7f260f5ba442.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>