<document id="b7c7ddd154707249989ce1bf220b0617-4.2" name="Battle_of_Grand_Port" cat="29">
<text>
At 01:50 on 24 August, ''Bellone'' ceased firing on the shattered ''Nereide''. During the remaining hours of darkness, Pym continued his efforts to dislodge ''Sirius'' from the reef and sent orders to Lambert, whose ''Iphigenia'' had been blocked from firing on the French by ''Nereide'' and also prevented from pursuing the ''Minerve'' by a large reef blocking access to the beach.Taylor, p. 293 With ''Iphigenia'' now becalmed in the coastal waters, Pym instructed Lambert to begin warping his ship out of the harbour, using anchors attached to the capstan to drag the ship slowly through the shallow water.James, p. 288 ''Magicienne'', like ''Iphigenia'', had been stranded out of range of the beached French ships and so had instead directed her fire against a battery erected on shore, which she had destroyed by 02:00. When daylight rose, it showed a scene of great confusion, with ''Sirius'' and ''Magicienne'' grounded in the approaches to the harbour, the French ships "on shore in a heap" in the words of Captain Pym, ''Iphigenia'' slowly pulling herself away from the French squadron and ''Nereide'' lying broken and battered under the guns of ''Bellone'', a Union Flag nailed to her masthead. This flag prompted a fresh burst of cannon fire from Bouvet, and it was not until Willoughby ordered the mizenmast to be chopped down that the French acknowledged the surrender and ceased firing.James, p. 287


At 07:00, Lambert notified Pym that he had cleared the reef separating ''Iphigenia'' from the French ships and suggested that if Pym sent reinforcements from ''Sirius'' he might be able to board and capture the entire French squadron. Pym refused permission, insisting that Lambert assist him in pulling ''Sirius'' off the reef instead.Taylor, p. 296 Although Lambert intended to subsequently attack the French alone, Pym forbade him and sent a direct order for Lambert to move out of range of the enemy. At 10:00, ''Iphigenia'' reached ''Sirius'' and together the ships began firing at French troops ashore, who were endeavouring to raise a gun battery within range of the frigates. ''Magicienne'', irretrievably stuck on the reef, rapidly flooding and with her capstan smashed by French shot, now bore the brunt of long-range French fire from both ''Bellone'' and the shore until Pym ordered Curtis to abandon his ship, transferring his men aboard ''Iphigenia''.Taylor, p. 297 At 19:30  ''Magicienne'' was set on fire, her magazines exploding at 23:00.Macmillan, p. 36 On the shoreline, Duperré had been unable to spare any men to take possession of ''Nereide'' until 15:00. A party under Lieutenant Roussin, second in command on ''Victor'' and temporarily in command of ''Minerve'', , Revue des 2 Mondes, 1887, tome 84, p.102 was sent but had orders to return once the ship had been disarmed: freeing the remaining French prisoners, Roussin spiked the guns to prevent their further use, administered basic medical care and returned to shore, recounting that over 100 men lay dead or dying aboard the British frigate.

At 04:00 on 25 August, the newly erected French gun battery opened fire on ''Sirius'' and ''Iphigenia'', which returned fire as best they could. Accepting that ''Sirius'' was beyond repair, Pym removed all her personnel and military supplies, setting fire to the frigate at 09:00, shortly after ''Iphigenia'' had pulled beyond the range of the battery, using a cannon as an anchor after losing hers the previous day.Clowes, p. 465 French boats attempted to reach ''Sirius'' and capture her before she exploded, although they turned back when Pym launched his own boats to contest possession of the wreck.James, p. 290 The frigate's remaining munitions exploded at 11:00.Woodman, p. 289 During the morning, Duperré sent an official boarding party aboard ''Nereide'', who wet the decks to prevent any risk of fire from the ships burning in the harbour and removed 75 corpses from the frigate.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bc0e6d8891959b108ad52f3aa8cccccd" name="NavalBattleOfGrandPort" sectnum="4.2#1">../img/bc0e6d8891959b108ad52f3aa8cccccd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>