<document id="b7c7ddd154707249989ce1bf220b0617-3" name="Battle_of_Grand_Port" cat="29">
<text>
Willoughby's raiding was interrupted at 10:00 on 20 August when five ships were sighted, rapidly approaching from the southeast.James, p. 278 These ships were Guy-Victor Duperré's squadron of ''Bellone'', ''Minerve'', corvette ''Victor'' and prizes ''Windham'' and ''Ceylon'' returning from the Comoros Islands. Following a month of repairs on Anjouan, Duperré had sailed for Île de France without encountering any opposition on his return passage, and was intending to enter Grand Port via the channel protected by Île de la Passe.Macmillan, p. 30 Duperré was unaware of the British occupation of the island, and Willoughby intended to lure the French squadron into the channel by concealing the British presence off the harbour. Once there, Willoughby hoped to defeat them or damage them so severely that they would be unable to break out unaided, thus isolating Duperré's squadron from Hamelin's force in Port Napoleon and containing the French in separate harbours to prevent them from concentrating against the British blockade squadrons.Clowes, p. 461 Willoughby brought ''Nereide'' close to Île de la Passe to combine their fire and protect his boats, which were carrying 160 men back to ''Nereide'' from a raid near Grand Port that morning.

Raising a French tricolour over Île de la Passe and on ''Nereide'', Willoughby transmitted the French code captured on the island: "''L'ennemi croise au Coin de Mire''" and received an acknowledgement from Duperré.Taylor, p. 286 The use of these signals convinced Duperré, over the objections of Captain Pierre Bouvet on ''Minerve'', that ''Nereide'' was a French ship. The French squadron closed with the harbour during the morning, ''Victor''  entering the channel under Île de la Passe at 13:40. As ''Victor'' passed ''Nereide'' and the fort Willoughby opened fire, Captain Morice surrendering the outnumbered corvette after the first volley. Willoughby sent boats to attempt to take possession of ''Victor'', but they were unable to reach the vessel.James, p. 279 Behind the corvette, ''Minerve'' and ''Ceylon'' pushed into the channel and signalled Morice to follow them, exchanging fire with the fort. As Morice raised his colours again and followed ''Minerve'', a large explosion boiled out of Île de la Passe, where the false French flag had ignited on a brazier as it was lowered and set fire to a nearby stack of cartridges, which exploded in the close confines of the fort. Three men were killed and 12 badly burned, six cannons were dismounted and one discharged unexpectedly, killing a British sailor in a boat attempting to board ''Victor''. With the fort out of action and a significant number of her crew scattered in small boats in the channel, ''Nereide'' alone was unable to block French entry to Grand Port.

With Willoughby's ambush plan ruined, the scattered boats sought to rejoin ''Nereide'', passing directly through the French squadron. Although several boats were in danger of being run down by the French ships and one even bumped alongside ''Minerve'', all eventually rejoined ''Nereide'' safely. However, the opportunity to cause significant damage to the French in the narrow channel had been lost, ''Bellone'' joining the squadron in passing through the channel with minimal resistance. In addition to British losses in the explosion at the fort, two men had been killed and one wounded on ''Nereide''. French losses were more severe, ''Minerve'' suffering 23 casualties and ''Ceylon'' eight. With both sides recognising that further action was inevitable, Willoughby sent a boat to ''Sirius'' requesting additional assistance and Duperré sent a message overland with Lieutenant Morice, requesting support from Hamelin's squadron (Morice fell from his horse during the mission and was very severely injured).Macmillan, p. 32 In the afternoon, Willoughby used mortars on Île de la Passe to shell the French squadron, forcing Duperré to retreat into the shallow harbour at Grand Port and Willoughby subsequently sent officers into Grand Port on 21 August under a flag of truce, demanding the release of ''Victor'', which he insisted had surrendered and should thus be handed over to the blockade squadron as a prize. Duperré refused to consider the request.James, p. 281 One French ship had failed to enter the channel off Grand Port: the captured East Indiaman ''Windham''. Early on 21 August, her French commander attempted to shelter in Rivière Noire. ''Sirius'' spotted the merchant ship under the batteries there and sent two boats into the anchorage, stormed the ship and brought her out without a single casualty. This success  was remarkable as the boarding party had forgotten to take any weapons with them and were only armed with wooden foot-stretchers wielded as clubs.Woodman, p. 287
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4e18f614e063b61b4ea2f6f5e07d30d6" name="Grand_Port_mg6973" sectnum="3#1">../img/4e18f614e063b61b4ea2f6f5e07d30d6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>