<document id="b81cf562e4ffbd106db5b591ac29dfcb-4" name="2nd_Canadian_Infantry_Division" cat="29">
<text>
In early 1942, under Major General J. H. Roberts, the 2nd Canadian Infantry Division participated in several additional full-scale combat exercises, again gauging the ability of Commonwealth divisions to repel a possible German invasion. As April and May progressed, the exercises intensified, becoming significantly more demanding on the participants.Copp, p.29 As a result, the 2nd Division was judged to be one of the four best divisions in the United Kingdom,Copp, p. 30 and was selected as the primary force for the upcoming Allied attack on the German-occupied port of Dieppe&mdash;codenamed Operation Jubilee.  Mounted as a test of whether or not such a landing was feasible,Bercuson, p. 62 the Dieppe raid was to be undertaken by the 4th and 6th Brigades, with additional naval, air, and infantry support.

On 19 August 1942, while British commando units attacked bunker positions on the outskirts of Dieppe, forces of the 2nd Division landed on four beaches. The easternmost, Blue Beach, which was situated at the foot of a sheer cliff, presented the most difficulties; the Royal Regiment of Canada, with a company of the Black Watch, was held at bay by two platoons of German defenders. Only six percent of the men that landed on Blue Beach returned to Britain.Bercuson, p.69

The main beaches, codenamed White and Red, lay in front of Dieppe itself. Making only minor gains, the majority of the 4th and 6th brigades became pinned down on the beach, and despite the arrival of an armoured squadron from the Calgary Tank Regiment, casualties were heavy.Zuehlke, p.151 Reinforcements from the Mont Royals had little effect, and surviving forces were withdrawn by 11:00. Of the nearly 5,000 Canadian troops that participated, more than half were killed, wounded or captured.Bercuson, p.73

At Green Beach to the west, the South Saskatchewan Regiment was landed on the wrong side of the Scie River, necessitating an assault on the bridge there, as well as on the German positions in and around the town of Pourville.Bercuson, p. 71 The Queen's Own Cameron Highlanders were deployed as reinforcements, but neither unit was able to reach its objectives. As with the other three beaches, casualties among the Canadians were high.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="db47044e7645eca3e2e6921ed8039a10" name="Bodies_of_Canadian_soldiers_-_Dieppe_Raid" sectnum="4#1">../img/db47044e7645eca3e2e6921ed8039a10.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>