<document id="b846373e48cf002363110ff72973f24b-7" name="Battleship" cat="29">
<text>
Operation Crossroads Event Baker explosion

After World War II, several navies retained their existing battleships, but they were no longer strategically dominant military assets. Indeed, it soon become apparent they were no longer worth the considerable cost of construction and maintenance and only one new battleship was commissioned after the war, HMS Vanguard. During the war it had been demonstrated that battleship-on-battleship engagements like Leyte Gulf or the sinking of  were the exception and not the rule, and with the growing role of aircraft engagement ranges were becoming longer and longer, making heavy gun armament irrelevant. The armor of a battleship was equally irrelevant in the face of a nuclear attack as tactical missiles with a range of  or more could be mounted on the Soviet  and  by the end of the 1950s, minor vessel classes which formerly offered no noteworthy opposition now were capable of eliminating battleships at will.   

The remaining battleships met a variety of ends.  and  were sunk during the testing of nuclear weapons in Operation Crossroads in 1946. Both battleships proved resistant to nuclear air burst but vulnerable to underwater nuclear explosions. The Italian ''Giulio Cesare'' was taken by the Soviets as reparations and renamed ''Novorossiysk''; she was sunk by a German mine in the Black Sea on 29 October 1955. The two ''Andrea Doria'' class ships were scrapped in 1956.Fitzsimons, Bernard, ed. (technical assistance from Bill Gunston, Antony Preston, & Ian Hogg) ''Illustrated Encyclopedia of 20th Century Weapons and Warfare'' (London: Phoebus, 1978), Volume 2, p.114. The French ''Lorraine'' was scrapped in 1954, ''Richelieu'' in 1968,Fitzsimons, Volume 20, p.2213, "''Richelieu''". No mention of her sister, ''Jean Bart''. and ''Jean Bart'' in 1970.Gardiner, Robert (Ed.); (1980); ''Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships 1922–1946''; ISBN 0-85177-146-7; p. 260
The United Kingdom's four surviving ''King George V'' class ships were scrapped in 1957,Fitzsimons, Volume 15, p.1636, "''King George V''" and ''Vanguard'' followed in 1960.Fitzsimons, Volume 23, p.2554, "''Vanguard''" All other surviving British battleships had been sold or broken up by 1949.Gardiner, pp. 7 and 14 The Soviet Union's ''''Petropavlovsk'''' was scrapped in 1953, ''Sevastopol'' in 1957 and ''Oktyabrskaya Revolutsiya'' (back under her original name, ''Gangut'', since 1942)Fitzsimons, Volume 10, p.1086, "''Gangut''" in 1956-7. Brazil's ''Minas Gerais'' was scrapped in Genoa in 1953,Fitzsimons, Volume 17, p.1896, "''Minas Gerais''" and her sister ship ''São Paulo'' sank during a storm in the Atlantic ''en route'' to the breakers in Italy in 1951. Argentina kept its two ''Rivadavia'' class ships until 1956 and Chile kept ''Almirante Latorre'' (formerly HMS ''Canada'') until 1959.Fitzsimons, Volume 1, p.84, "''Almirante Latorre''" The Turkish battlecruiser ''Yavuz'' (formerly ''Goeben'', launched in 1911) was scrapped in 1976 after an offer to sell her back to Germany was refused. Sweden had several small coastal-defense battleships, one of which, ''Gustav V'', survived until 1970.Gardiner, p. 368 The Soviets scrapped four large incomplete cruisers in the late 1950s, whilst plans to build a number of new ''Stalingrad''-class battlecruisers were abandoned following the death of Joseph Stalin in 1953. The three old German battleships , , and ''Hessen'' all met similar ends. ''Hessen'' was taken over by the Soviet Union and renamed ''Tsel''. She was scrapped in 1960. ''Schleswig-Holstein'' was renamed ''Borodino'', and was used as a target ship until 1960. ''Schlesien'', too, was used as a target ship. She was broken up between 1952 and 1957.Gardiner, p. 222



The ''Iowa'' class battleships gained a new lease of life in the U.S. Navy as fire support ships. Radar and computer-controlled gunfire could be aimed with pinpoint accuracy to target. The U.S. recommissioned all four ''Iowa'' class battleships for the Korean War and the  for the Vietnam War. These were primarily used for shore bombardment, ''New Jersey'' firing nearly 6,000 rounds of 16 inch shells and over 14,000 rounds of 5 inch projectiles during her tour on the gunline,Polmar, p. 129 seven times more rounds against shore targets in Vietnam than she had in the Second World War.History of World Seapower, Bernard Brett, ISBN 0-603-03723-2, p. 236

As part of Navy Secretary John F. Lehman's effort to build a 600-ship Navy in the 1980s, and in response to the commissioning of ''Kirov'' by the Soviet Union, the United States recommissioned all four ''Iowa'' class battleships. On several occasions, battleships were support ships in carrier battle groups, or led their own battleship battle group. These were modernized to carry Tomahawk missiles, with ''New Jersey'' seeing action bombarding Lebanon in 1983 and 1984, while  and  fired their 16 inch (406 mm) guns at land targets and launched missiles during Operation Desert Storm in 1991. ''Wisconsin'' served as the TLAM strike commander for the Persian Gulf, directing the sequence of launches that marked the opening of ''Desert Storm'',  firing a total of 24 TLAMs during the first two days of the campaign.  The primary threat to the battleships were Iraqi shore based surface-to-surface missiles; ''Missouri'' was targeted by two Iraqi Silkworm missiles, with one missing and another being intercepted by the British destroyer . Defence power: developments of the decade

All four ''Iowas'' were decommissioned in the early 1990s, making them the last battleships to see active service. USS ''Iowa'' and USS ''Wisconsin'' were, until fiscal year 2006, maintained to a standard where they could be rapidly returned to service as fire support vessels, pending the development of a superior fire support vessel. The U.S. Marine Corps believes that the current naval surface fire support gun and missile programs will not be able to provide adequate fire support for an amphibious assault or onshore operations.The USMC has revised its Naval Surface Gunfire Support requirements, leaving some questions as to whether or not the Zumwalt class destroyer can meet the Marine qualifications.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="621e60a8cdb9451936404413156e2224" name="Missouri_missile_BGM-109_Tomahawk" sectnum="7#1">../img/621e60a8cdb9451936404413156e2224.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>