<document id="b846373e48cf002363110ff72973f24b-1" name="Battleship" cat="29">
<text>
A ship of the line was a large, unarmored wooden sailing ship on which was mounted a battery of up to 120 smoothbore guns and carronades. The ship of the line was a gradual evolution of a basic design that dates back to the 1400s, and, apart from growing in size, it changed little between the adoption of line of battle tactics in the early 17th century and the end of the sailing battleship's heyday in the 1830s. From 1794, the alternative term 'line of battle ship' was contracted (informally at first) to 'battle ship' or 'battleship'.


The sheer number of guns fired broadside meant that a sailing battleship could wreck any wooden vessel, smashing its hull and masts and killing its crew. However, the effective range of the guns was as little as a few hundred yards, so the battle tactics of sailing ships depended in part on the wind.

The first major change to the ship of the line concept was the introduction of steam power as an auxiliary propulsion system. Steam power was gradually introduced to the navy in the first half of the 19th century, initially for small craft and later for frigates. The French Navy introduced steam to the line of battle with the 90-gun ''Le Napoléon'' in 1850"Napoleon (90 guns), the first purpose-designed screw line of battleships", ''Steam, Steel and Shellfire'', Conway's History of the Ship (p. 39)—the first true steam battleship.''"Hastened to completion Le Napoleon was launched on 16 May 1850, to become the world's first true steam battleship"'', ''Steam, Steel and Shellfire'', Conway's History of the Ship (p39) ''Napoleon'' was armed as a conventional ship-of-the-line, but her steam engines could give her a speed of , regardless of the wind conditions: a potentially decisive advantage in a naval engagement. The introduction of steam accelerated the growth in size of battleships. France and the United Kingdom were the only countries to develop fleets of wooden steam screw battleships, although several other navies operated small numbers of screw battleships These included Russia (9), Turkey (3), Sweden (2), Naples (1), Denmark (1) and Austria (1).Lambert, Andrew, ''Battleships in Transition'', pub Conway1984, ISBN0-85177315-X pages 144-147. In addition the Navy of the North Germany Confederacy (which included Prussia) bought HMS ''Renown'' from Britain in 1870 for use as a gunnery training ship.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="89dd5444126c45e230d74e6b653b07bb" name="TheNapoleonAtToulonIn1852ByLauvergne" sectnum="1#1">../img/89dd5444126c45e230d74e6b653b07bb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>