<document id="b846373e48cf002363110ff72973f24b-5.7" name="Battleship" cat="29">
<text>
The Royal Navy, United States Navy, and Imperial Japanese Navy extensively upgraded and modernized their World War I–era battleships during the 1930s. Among new features were tower height and stability such that optical rangefinder equipment for gunnery control could be used, deck plating was increased especially around turrets against plunging fire and aerial bombing, anti-aircraft weapons added. Some British ships received a large block superstructure nicknamed the "Queen Anne's castle", such as in the ''Queen Elizabeth'' and ''Warspite'', which would be used in the new conning towers of the ''King George V'' fast battleships. External bulges were added to improve both buoyancy to counteract weight increase and provide underwater protection against mines and torpedoes. The Japanese rebuilt all of their battleships, plus their battlecruisers, with distinctive "pagoda" structures, though the  received a more modern bridge tower that would influence the new ''Yamato'' battleships. Bulges were fitted, including steel tube array to improve both underwater and vertical protection along waterline. The U.S. experimented with cage masts and later tripod masts, though after Pearl Harbor some of the most severely damaged ships such as ''West Virginia'' and ''California'' were rebuilt to a similar appearance to their Iowa class contemporaries (called tower masts). Radar, which was effective beyond visual contact and was effective in complete darkness or adverse weather conditions, was introduced to supplement optical fire control.

Even when war threatened again in the late 1930s, battleship construction did not regain the level of importance which it had held in the years before World War I. The "building holiday" imposed by the naval treaties meant that the building capacity of dockyards worldwide was relatively reduced, and the strategic position had changed. The development of the strategic bomber meant that the navy was no longer the only method of projecting power overseas, and the development of the aircraft carrier meant that battleships had a rival for the resources available for capital ship construction.


In Germany, the ambitious Plan Z for naval rearmament was abandoned in favour of a strategy of submarine warfare supplemented by the use of battlecruisers and ''Bismarck''-class battleships as commerce raiders. In Britain, the most pressing need was for air defenses and convoy escorts to safeguard the civilian population from bombing or starvation, and re-armament construction plans consisted of five ships of the ''King George V'' class. It was in the Mediterranean that navies remained most committed to battleship warfare. France intended to build six battleships of the ''Dunkerque'' and ''Richelieu'' classes, and the Italians two ''Littorio''-class ships. Neither navy built significant aircraft carriers. The U.S. preferred to spend limited funds on aircraft carriers until the ''South Dakota'' class. Japan, also prioritising aircraft carriers, nevertheless began work on three mammoth ''Yamato'' class ships (although the third, ''Shinano'', was later completed as a carrier) and a planned fourth was cancelled.

At the outbreak of the Spanish Civil War, the Spanish navy consisted of only two small dreadnought battleships, España and Jaime I. ''España'' (originally named ''Alfonso XIII''), by then in reserve at the northwestern naval base of El Ferrol, fell into Nationalist hands in July 1936. The crew aboard ''Jaime I'' murdered their officers, mutinied, and joined the Republican Navy. Thus each side had one battleship; however, the Republican Navy generally lacked experienced officers. The Spanish battleships mainly restricted themselves to mutual blockades, convoy escort duties, and shore bombardment, rarely in direct fighting against other surface units.Gibbons, p.195 In April 1937, ''España'' ran onto a mine laid by friendly forces, and sank with little loss of life. In May 1937, ''Jaime I'' was damaged by Nationalist air attacks and a grounding incident. The ship was forced to go back to port to be repaired. There she was again hit by several aerial bombs. It was then decided to tow the battleship to a more secure port, but during the transport she suffered an internal explosion that caused 300 deaths and her total loss. Several Italian and German capital ships participated in the non-intervention blockade. On 29 May 1937, two Republican aircraft managed to bomb the German pocket battleship  outside Ibiza, causing severe damage and loss of life.  retaliated two days later by bombarding Almería, causing much destruction, and the resulting ''Deutschland'' incident meant the end of German and Italian support for non-intervention.Greger, René: ''Schlachtschiffe der Welt'', p. 251
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7602a4c098a5447f85e56fcb094e1df9" name="RNVittorio_Veneto" sectnum="5.7#1">../img/7602a4c098a5447f85e56fcb094e1df9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>