<document id="b89426092b223f5cb53c0fb2ed1200bb-2.1" name="Brian_Horrocks" cat="29">
<text>
In 1919 Horrocks was posted to Russia as part of the Allied intervention in the Russian Civil War. After landing at Vladivostok on 19 April, he was taken to British headquarters and briefed. The White Army under Admiral Kolchak, with the help of released Czechoslovak Legion prisoners, had driven the Red Army out of Siberia. However, Kolchak's Czech troops were returning home, and the British military contingent was urgently trying to replace them with Russians. To accomplish this, the British had just two infantry battalions and two small administrative missions, one charged with training and arming the Russians with British war-surplus equipment, and the other with improving the White Army's communications.Warner. ''Horrocks'', pp. 28–29; Horrocks. ''A Full Life'', p. 38.


Horrocks' first task, along with a party of 13 British officers and 30 other ranks, was to guard a train delivering 27 carriages of shells to the White Army in Omsk,  away on the Trans-Siberian Railway.Warner. ''Horrocks'', p. 30. The journey took more than a month, and as the only party member fluent in Russian, Horrocks had to deal with many of the difficulties they encountered. At every station, he had to ward off station masters intent on acquiring the cars. While stopped in Manchuli, the British officers' presence provoked a duel between two Cossack officers. Horrocks accepted an invitation to act as a second, but the pair were arrested before the duel could take place. However, he managed to defuse the situation before it came to trial, by claiming his faulty Russian had been the cause of the misunderstanding.Horrocks. ''A Full Life'', pp. 41–22. The train eventually arrived in Omsk on 20 May, with a full cargo.

His next assignment was in Yekaterinburg in the Urals, where he was appointed second in command of a training school for non-commissioned officers attached to the Anglo-Russian Brigade.Horrocks. ''A Full Life'', p. 44; Warner. ''Horrocks'', p. 29. He found this post frustrating, having to dismiss nearly a third of his initial cadre on medical grounds, and struggling to get supplies and support from the White Army authorities.Horrocks. ''A Full Life'', p. 45. Despite this, he developed a rapport with his men and an admiration for the Russian soldier.Warner. ''Horrocks'', p. 32.

Although British forces were ordered home shortly afterwards, Horrocks and another officer, George Hayes, remained to advise the First Siberian Army.Horrocks. ''A Full Life'', p. 47. The White Army was in retreat, and Horrocks joined them as they fell back to Vladivostok,  away. He was captured by the Red Army on 7 January 1919, in the town of Krasnoyarsk,Horrocks. ''A Full Life'', p. 53. and spent 10 months as a prisoner, narrowly surviving severe typhus.Warner. ''Horrocks'', p. 36. The British government negotiated a prisoner release, and Horrocks left Russia on 29 October, returning home on the Royal Navy cruiser HMS ''Delhi''.Horrocks. ''A Full Life'', p. 61.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="37467d9813fe3cc89c40fd7b2e887cac" name="Bolshveki_killed_at_Vladavostak" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/37467d9813fe3cc89c40fd7b2e887cac.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>