<document id="b8b909a7d6d91b8e1db6aa48220dc191-3" name="History_of_Burnside" cat="14">
<text>
After shedding the burden of less profitable and unwieldy land with its angry residents, Burnside was on its own. The new Burnside District Council held its first meeting at the Greengate Inn, Tusmore on 19 August 1856. Due to the time it took to elect new councillors, it was not until 29 December that the council met again. Dr Christopher Penfold, chairman, met the rest of the representatives there: Daniel Ferguson of Glenunga, Alexander Ferguson of Monreith, John Townsend of Magill and James Grylls of Belle Vue.E Warburton, p. xxvi, ''The Paddocks Beneath'' It was during this time that Kent Town decided against becoming a part of Burnside and instead applied to enter Norwood-Kensington. The council was to meet at the Inn or at Ferguson's home right up until December 1869, when the first council chambers were built. However, it was still able to operate and fulfill its obligations under the ''Local Government Act 1852''. These included the management of minor roads, the administration of abattoir licences and public houses, and the prevention of the spread of the noxious Scotch thistle. The council was also obliged, under a different act of 1851, to encourage education. Much road and bridgework activity happened after the council had been formed—early residents were amazed at the influx of development and construction that occurred. At the same time, the council was almost overwhelmed by the sheer number of resident requests, and was forced to ask individual ratepayers for monetary assistance when building bridges in their area.E Warburton, p. xxix, ''The Paddocks Beneath''

Much of Burnside's history has been observed and documented by institutions that have remained an important part of the lives of its residents: the school and the church.A.C. Hill, p. 123–126, ''The First Hundred Years'' The first school to open in the area was in Magill during 1846, preceding a proper statewide education system. Magill Primary School was  enlarged in November 1855, when 38 boys and 29 girls enrolled; they were taught reading, writing, arithmetic, grammar, geography, history, drawing and singing by a sole teacher. By 1865 there were two teachers.Magill School: History (http://www.magillps.sa.edu.au/) Accessed 27 April 2006 Glen Osmond Primary School was established in October 1858, preceding the Glen Osmond Institute, a centre for community debate and learning.E Warburton, p. 308–309, ''The Paddocks Beneath'' Burnside Primary School was built in 1872, taking over from a small private institution.W.J. Adey, p. 135–136, ''The First Hundred Years'' These primary schools, in the absence of proper libraries and similar institutions, received large collections of books and writings from the town's residents. Residents also took advantage of schools for frequent and heated debates on the future of the state and region, and these discussions often drew large crowds. However, even with this intellectual spirit, the adult population was still relatively disadvantaged in the sphere of education. The drive for learning continued until the Boer War placed more emphasis on physical activity and merit within society. Somewhat strangely, this development of learned activity was not replicated in Burnside's traditional centre near Tusmore, where the present Council Chambers, Community Centre and Library are located.E Warburton, p. 310, ''The Paddocks Beneath''


By 1871 Burnside had grown significantly; it was now a mix of villages supporting a modest population of 1,557. By comparison, Kensington-Norwood, though smaller in area, had grown to 5,132 persons. Glen Osmond, still affected by its immense growth following the expansion of mining, was the largest single population centre with 343 residents.E Warburton, p. 355, ''The Paddocks Beneath'' The District Council had also constructed its first council chambers in December 1869, finally concluding the haphazard meeting agreement. Two villages, Beulah Park (North Kensington) and Eastwood experienced booms in population growth and development between 1870 and 1880, providing both housing to new immigrants and investments for the wealthy Adelaide Establishment.E Warburton, p. 265–266, ''The Paddocks Beneath'' Parkside Hospital (now Glenside), a mental health asylum was constructed in 1866 to replace a crowded building in the Parklands. Built on beautifully tended grounds and with an elaborate façade, it was an early Burnside architectural monument.E Warburton, p. 272–273, ''The Paddocks Beneath'' In 1881 Thomas Cooper started brewing South Australia's first branded beer, 'Coopers', at Leabrook.Coopers Brewery: Students Guide (http://www.coopers.com.au/pdfs/studentInfo.pdf) Accessed 27 April 2006 During this era, Stonyfell saw economic expansion as well; its large quarry changed hands in 1867 and the Stonyfell Olive Co was founded in 1873.E Warburton, p. 41–42, ''The Paddocks Beneath'' The late 19th century was a significant time of development in Burnside. This development, however, was brought to an abrupt end in the last decade, the 1890s, when depression stuck the economies of Australasia after decades of reckless expansion, hitting Burnside hard.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="26d594c7b5a9028f546e621765b592ee" name="Glen_osmond_primary" sectnum="3#1">../img/26d594c7b5a9028f546e621765b592ee.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>