<document id="b8d3edc2ebea4195860b31d604e90820-2.2" name="Murray_Maxwell" cat="29">
<text>
Maxwell's most notable service came during the Adriatic campaign of 1807–1814. ''Alceste'' was despatched to the Adriatic Sea to support James Brisbane in the absence of William Hoste, who had been wounded at the Battle of Lissa in March 1811. On 4 May, Maxwell and Brisbane led an attack on Parenza, where a brig carrying supplies to Ragusa had taken shelter.Clowes, Vol. 5, p. 484 Seizing an island at the mouth of the harbour, the British established a mortar position overlooking the anchorage, and sank the brig with a heavy bombardment.James, Vol. 5, p. 364 In November 1811, with the temporary absence of Brisbane, Maxwell became the senior officer in the Adriatic. Seven months later, a convoy of French frigates carrying cannon from Corfu to Trieste was spotted attempting to slip past his base of operations on the island of Lissa. Ashore in Port St. George, Maxwell was informed by telegraph, and led ''Alceste'' and the rest of his squadron&mdash; and &mdash;in pursuit.James, Vol. 5, p. 375

On 29 November, after a night's chase, the British caught their opponents near Pelagosa. The French force consisted of the large frigates ''Pauline'' and ''Pomone'', and the armed storeship ''Persanne''.James, Vol. 5, p. 378 In the battle that followed, ''Unite'' pursued and, after a lengthy chase, seized the smaller ''Persanne'', while Maxwell and James Alexander Gordon in ''Active'' engaged the frigates.Clowes, Vol. 5, p. 496 The action was bitterly contested, the British suffering 61 casualties, including Gordon who lost a leg. However, ''Alceste'' and ''Active'' successfully isolated ''Pomone'', and when another British ship, , appeared in the distance, ''Pauline'' fled.Gardiner, p. 178 Alone and having suffered very heavy losses, ''Pomone'' surrendered. The prizes were later sold along with their cargo of 200 cannon. Maxwell, despite attributing most of the credit for the victory to the wounded Gordon, was rewarded in 1812 with command of , a former Italian frigate captured at the Battle of Lissa.Henderson, p. 152
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f345f4682d4088a1bdac9e41d3f15982" name="La_Pomone_contre_les_fregates_Alceste_et_Active" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/f345f4682d4088a1bdac9e41d3f15982.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>