<document id="b912782edad0833864f573d22b749fca-4.3" name="Sir_William_Bruce,_1st_Baronet,_of_Balcaskie" cat="1">
<text>
Bruce's appointment as Surveyor General of the King's Works in Scotland was made chiefly for the purpose of rebuilding the palace of Holyroodhouse. Aside from this project, he only carried out minor repairs to Edinburgh and Stirling Castles, and to the fortifications on the Bass Rock.Colvin, p.173 Charles I had intended to extend and rebuild Holyroodhouse, and plans had been drawn up in the 1630s. Nothing was done however, and in 1650 the palace was burnt out, destroying all but the west range. Bruce was contracted to design and oversee the works, with Robert Mylne acting as contractor. Bruce's plans were drawn up by Mylne, as Bruce himself apparently lacked the technical skills of architectural drawing.Gifford (1989), p.62. Both Robert Mylne and Alexander Edward acted as Bruce's draughtsmen, which helped to disseminate and promote his work.

Charles II criticised Bruce's initial plans for the internal layout, and an improved scheme was eventually approved. Construction began in July 1671, and by 1674 much of the work was complete. Bruce built a second gothic tower to mirror the existing one built by James IV between 1498 and 1501, and created the courtyard block in a restrained classical style. A second phase of work started in 1676, when the Duke of Lauderdale ordered Bruce to demolish and rebuild the main west façade, resulting by 1679 in the screen wall, topped by a carved imperial crown, which forms the main entrance.Gifford ''et al.'' (1984), p.126–127

Also in 1676, Bruce drew up plans for the completion of Heriot's Hospital in Edinburgh, which had been started in the 1620s. His design, for the central tower of the south façade, was eventually executed in 1693.Gifford ''et al.'' (1984), p.180
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="26a7ebfafd331ec69ab9a618a9110a77" name="Wfm_holyrood_palace" sectnum="4.3#1">../img/26a7ebfafd331ec69ab9a618a9110a77.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>