<document id="b92a892bcdf82e097b0090789e3859b9-2.2" name="Battle_of_Rennell_Island" cat="29">
<text>
At sunset, as  TF 18 headed northwest 80 kilometers (50 mi) north of Rennell Island and 160 kilometers (100 mi) south of Guadalcanal, several of Giffen's ships detected unidentified aircraft on radar 100 kilometers (60 mi) west of their formation.  Having previously insisted on absolute radio silence, Giffen gave no orders about what to do about the unidentified contacts, or any orders at all, for that matter.  With the setting of the sun, TF 18's combat air patrol (CAP) from the two escort carriers returned to their ships for the night, leaving Giffen's ships without air cover.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 355.

The radar contacts were, in fact, the approaching 31 Japanese torpedo bombers, who circled around to the south of TF 18 so that they could attack from the east, with the black backdrop of the eastern sky behind them.  From this direction, the Japanese bombers were hidden by the night sky, but Giffen's ships were silhouetted against the twilight of the western horizon.  The 705AG aircraft attacked first, beginning at 19:19.  Nakamura's aircraft missed with all of their torpedoes and one was shot down by anti-aircraft fire from Giffen's ships.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 579; Tagaya, p. 66.

Believing the attack was over, Giffen ordered his ships to cease zigzagging and to continue heading towards Guadalcanal on the same course and at the same speed.  Meanwhile, a Japanese reconnaissance aircraft began dropping flares and floatlights to mark the course and speed of TF 18 in order to assist with the impending attack by Higai's bombers.Crenshaw, ''South Pacific Destroyer'', p. 63; Tagaya, p. 66.

At 19:38, 701AG attacked, planting two torpedoes in ''Chicago'', causing heavy damage and bringing the cruiser to a dead stop.  One other torpedo hit ''Wichita'' but did not explode, and two of the bombers were shot down by anti-aircraft fire, including the one piloted by Higai, who was killed.  At 20:08, Giffen ordered his ships to reverse direction, to slow to , and to cease firing their anti-aircraft guns, which succeeded in concealing his ships from the Japanese aircraft, who all departed the area by 23:35.Tagaya, p. 66.  In pitch darkness, ''Louisville'' managed to take the crippled ''Chicago'' under tow and slowly headed south, away from the battle area, escorted by the rest of TF 18.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 358–359.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1c92288013435729adadf9863a8c691d" name="RennellBattleMap" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/1c92288013435729adadf9863a8c691d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>