<document id="b92a892bcdf82e097b0090789e3859b9-1" name="Battle_of_Rennell_Island" cat="29">
<text>
On August 7, 1942, Allied forces (primarily U.S.) landed on Guadalcanal, Tulagi, and Florida Islands in the Solomon Islands.  The landings on the islands were meant to deny their use by the Japanese as bases for threatening the supply routes between the U.S. and Australia, and to secure the islands as starting points for a campaign with the eventual goal of isolating the major Japanese base at Rabaul while also supporting the Allied New Guinea campaign.  The landings initiated the six-month-long Guadalcanal campaign.Hogue, ''Pearl Harbor to Guadalcanal'', p. 235–236.

The last major attempt by the Japanese to drive Allied forces from Guadalcanal and Tulagi was defeated during the decisive Naval Battle of Guadalcanal in early November 1942.  Thereafter, the Japanese Navy was only able to deliver subsistence supplies and a few replacement troops to Japanese Army forces on Guadalcanal.  Because of the threat from Allied aircraft based at Henderson Field on Guadalcanal, plus nearby U.S. aircraft carriers, the Japanese delivered these supplies at night, usually by destroyer or submarine, in operations the Allies called the "Tokyo Express."Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 526.  However, these supplies and replacements were not enough to sustain Japanese troops on the island, who by December 7, 1942, were losing about 50 men each day from malnutrition, disease, and Allied ground or air attacks.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 527.  On December 12, the Japanese Navy proposed that Guadalcanal be abandoned. Despite initial opposition from Japanese Army leaders, who still hoped that Guadalcanal could eventually be retaken from the Allies, Japan's Imperial General Headquarters, with approval from the Emperor, on December 31, 1942, agreed to the evacuation of all Japanese forces from the island and establishment of a new line of defense for the Solomons on New Georgia.Dull, ''Imperial Japanese Navy'', p. 261.

The Japanese titled the evacuation effort of their forces from Guadalcanal ''Operation Ke'' (ケ号作戦) and planned to execute the operation beginning January 14, 1943.Dull, ''Imperial Japanese Navy'', p. 268.  An important element in the operation's plan was an air superiority campaign set to begin on January 28, with the objective of inhibiting Allied aircraft or warships from disrupting the final stage of the ''Ke'' operation, which was the actual evacuation of all Japanese troops from Guadalcanal.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 541.

Allied forces misinterpreted the ''Ke'' preparations as the beginning of another Japanese offensive to try to retake Guadalcanal.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 351.  At this same time, Admiral William Halsey, Jr., overall commander of Allied forces involved in the battle for Guadalcanal, was under pressure from his superiors to complete the replacement of the U.S. 2nd Marine Regiment on Guadalcanal, which had been involved in the fighting since the initial landings in August, with fresh U.S. Army troops.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 577.  Halsey hoped to take advantage of what he believed was an impending Japanese offensive to draw Japanese naval forces into a battle, while at the same time delivering the replacement army troops to Guadalcanal.McGee, ''The Solomons Campaigns'', p. 216.  On January 29, Halsey prepared and sent towards the southern Solomons area five warship task forces to cover the relief convoy and to engage any Japanese naval forces that came into range. These five task forces included two fleet carriers, two escort carriers, three battleships, 12 cruisers, and 25 destroyers.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 352.

In front of this array of task forces was the troop convoy (Task Group (TG) 62.8), consisting of four transports and four destroyers.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 577–578.  Ahead of the troop convoy, between Rennell Island and Guadalcanal, was a close support group called Task Force 18 (TF 18), under Rear Admiral Robert C. Giffen, which consisted of heavy cruisers USS ''Wichita'', ''Chicago'', and ''Louisville''; light cruisers ''Montpelier'', ''Cleveland'', and ''Columbia''; escort carriers ''Chenango'' and ''Suwannee''; and eight destroyers.  Admiral Giffen commanded TF 18 from ''Wichita''.Crenshaw, ''South Pacific Destroyer'', p. 62.  A fleet carrier task force, centered on carrier USS ''Enterprise'', steamed about 400 kilometers (250 mi) behind TG 62.8 and TF 18. The other fleet carrier and battleship task forces were about 240 kilometers (150 mi) further back. Admiral Giffen, along with cruiser ''Wichita'' and the two escort carriers, had just arrived in the Pacific after participating in Operation Torch in the North African Campaign.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 352–353.  Also, ''Chicago'' had just arrived back in the South Pacific, after completing repairs from damage suffered during the Battle of Savo Island almost six-months before.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fdf9169470fce2a3a28e4281845711bc" name="SoPac_fixtypo" sectnum="1#1">../img/fdf9169470fce2a3a28e4281845711bc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>