<document id="b93fde664b394200f65cb6cd25e823de-3.6" name="Jim_Thorpe" cat="26">
<text>
Thorpe signed with the New York Giants baseball club in 1913 and played sporadically with them as an outfielder for three seasons. After playing in the minors with the Milwaukee Brewers in 1916, ''The Janesville Daily Gazette '', July 10, 1916, accessed February 19, 2008., he returned to the Giants in 1917 but was sold to the Cincinnati Reds early in the season. In the "double no-hitter" between Fred Toney of the Reds and Hippo Vaughn of the Chicago Cubs, Thorpe drove in the winning run in the 10th inning.Daley, Arthur. , ''The New York Times'', April 17, 1949, accessed April 23, 2007. Late in the season, he was sold back to the Giants. Again, he played sporadically for the Giants in 1918 and was traded to the Boston Braves on May 21, 1919, for Pat Ragan. In his career, he amassed 91 runs scored, 82 runs batted in and a .252 batting average over 289 games., baseball-reference.com, accessed April 23, 2007. He continued to play baseball with teams in the minor leagues until 1922.

But Thorpe had not abandoned football either. He first played professional football in 1913, as a member of the Indiana-based "Pine Valley Pros." By 1915, Thorpe had signed with the Canton Bulldogs. They paid him $250 ($ in current dollar terms) a game, a tremendous wage at the time.Neft, Cohen, and Korch. pg. 18  Before Thorpe's signing, Canton was averaging 1,200 fans a game; 8,000 showed up for his debut against Massillon. The team won titles in 1916, 1917, and 1919. Thorpe reportedly ended the 1919 championship game by kicking a wind-assisted 95–yard punt from his team's own 5-yard line, effectively putting the game out of reach. In 1920, the Bulldogs were one of 14 teams to form the American Professional Football Association (APFA), which would become the National Football League (NFL) two years later. Thorpe was nominally the APFA's first president; however, he spent most of the year playing for Canton and a year later was replaced by Joseph Carr.Neft, Cohen, and Korch. pg. 20  He continued to play for Canton, coaching the team as well. Between 1921 and 1923, Thorpe played for the LaRue, Ohio, (Marion County, Ohio) Oorang Indians, an all-Native American team. Although the team went 3–6 in 1922,Neft, Cohen, and Korch. pg. 34  and 1–10 in 1923,Neft, Cohen, and Korch. pg. 40  Thorpe played well and was selected to the ''Green Bay Press-Gazette's'' first All-NFL team in 1923 (the Press-Gazette's team would later be formalized by the NFL as the league's official All-NFL team in 1931).Neft, Cohen, and Korch. pg. 41 

Thorpe never played on an NFL championship team. He retired from pro football at the age of 41, having played 52 NFL games for six teams from 1920 to 1928.

Thorpe continued to be active in sports. By 1926 he was the primary draw for the "World Famous Indians" in LaRue, which sponsored traveling football, baseball, and basketball teams.  A ticket discovered in an old book in 2005 only recently brought to light his career in basketball. "Jim Thorpe and His World-Famous Indians" barnstormed for at least two years (1927–28) in parts of New York, Pennsylvania, and Marion, Ohio. Although pictures of Thorpe in his WFI basketball uniform were printed on postcards and published in newspapers, this period of his life was not well documented.  Until 2005 most of Thorpe's biographers were unaware of his basketball career. (PDF), pbs.org, accessed April 23, 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="512e8433c2554ed28f9f3bd377ad1a12" name="WFI" sectnum="3.6#1">../img/512e8433c2554ed28f9f3bd377ad1a12.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>