<document id="b93fde664b394200f65cb6cd25e823de-2.1" name="Jim_Thorpe" cat="26">
<text>
Thorpe reportedly began his athletic career at Carlisle in 1907 when he walked past the track and beat the school's high jumpers with an impromptu 5-ft 9-in jump while still wearing street clothes.''Encyclopedia of World Biography''.  , Thomson-Gale, Bookrags, June 2005, accessed April 23, 2007  His earliest recorded track and field results are from 1907.  Track and field were not the only events in which Thorpe engaged at Carlisle.  He also competed in football, baseball, lacrosse and even ballroom dancing, winning the 1912 inter-collegiate ballroom dancing championship.  Reportedly, Pop Warner was hesitant to allow Thorpe, his star track and field athlete, to compete in a physical game such as football.Jeansonne.  p. 60.  Thorpe, however, convinced Warner to let him run some plays against the school's defense; Warner assumed he would be tackled easily and give up the idea of playing football.  Thorpe "ran around past and through them not once, but twice."  He then walked over to Warner and said, "Nobody is going to tackle Jim," while flipping him the ball.

Thorpe gained nationwide attention for the first time in 1911., ''The New York Times'', April 28, 1912, accessed April 2, 2007.  As a running back, defensive back, placekicker, and punter for his school's football team, Thorpe scored all of his team's points—four field goals and a touchdown—in an 18–15 upset of Harvard.  His team finished the season 11–1.

The following year, he led Carlisle to the national collegiate championship, scoring 25 touchdowns and 198 points.  Carlisle's 1912 record included a 27–6 victory over Army.  In that game, Thorpe scored a 92-yard touchdown that was nullified by a penalty incurred by a teammate; Thorpe then scored a 97-yard touchdown on the next play., usoc.org, accessed April 26, 2007.

During that game, future President Dwight Eisenhower injured his knee while trying to tackle Thorpe. Eisenhower recalled of Thorpe in a 1961 speech, "Here and there, there are some people who are supremely endowed. My memory goes back to Jim Thorpe. He never practiced in his life, and he could do anything better than any other football player I ever saw."Botelho, Greg. , CNN.com, July 14, 2004, accessed April 23, 2007. Thorpe was awarded All-American honors in both 1911 and 1912.

Football was—-and would remain—-Thorpe's favorite sport.O'Hanlon-Lincoln. p. 144 * , profootballhalloffame.com, accessed April 23, 2007.  He competed only sporadically in track and field.  Nevertheless, track and field would become the sport in which Thorpe would gain the most fame. "In the spring of 1912 he started training for the Olympics. He had confined his efforts to the jumps, the hurdles and the shot-put but now he undertook the pole vault, the javelin, discus, the hammer and the fifty-six-pound weight. In the Olympic trials held at Celtic Park in New York, his all-round ability stood out in all these events and so he riveted a claim to a place on the team that went to Sweden."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b93fde664b394200f65cb6cd25e823de" name="Jim_Thorpe" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/b93fde664b394200f65cb6cd25e823de.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>