<document id="b93fde664b394200f65cb6cd25e823de-4" name="Jim_Thorpe" cat="26">
<text>
In 1913, Thorpe married Iva Miller, whom he had met at Carlisle. They had four children: Jim Jr. (who died at age 2), Gale, Charlotte and Grace. Grace, a tribal judge and an anti-nuclear activist who participated in the occupation of Alcatraz, died in 2008., Alcatraz is not an island, PBS,, retrieved October 27, 2009. Thorpe was a chronic alcoholic in his later years. Jeansonne. pg 61  Miller filed for divorce from Thorpe in 1925, claiming desertion., ''TIME'', April 6, 1925, available online via time.com, accessed May 21, 2007.  	
 		
In 1926, Thorpe married Freeda V. Kirkpatrick (b.September 19, 1905, d. March 2, 2007). She was working for the manager of the baseball team on which he was playing at the time. They had four sons: Carl, William, Richard and John.  William, Richard and John "Jack" survived their mother, who had divorced their father in 1941 after 15 years of marriage.

After the end of his athletic career, Thorpe struggled to support his family. He found it difficult to work outside sports and never kept a job for an extended period of time. During the Great Depression in particular, Thorpe held various jobs, among others as an extra in several movies, usually playing an Indian chief in Westerns.  But he also worked as a construction worker, a bouncer, a security guard, and a ditch digger, and he briefly joined the United States Merchant Marine in 1945.O'Hanlon-Lincoln. pgs. 144–5 , ''TIME'', February 22, 1943, available online via time.com, accessed May 21, 2007. 
	
By the 1950s, Thorpe had no money left.  When he was hospitalized for lip cancer in 1950, he was admitted as a charity case.Associated Press. , ''The New York Times'', November 10, 1951, accessed April 23, 2007.  At a press conference announcing the procedure, Thorpe's wife wept and pleaded for help, saying: "e're broke.... Jim has nothing but his name and his memories. He has spent money on his own people and has given it away. He has often been exploited." In early 1953, Thorpe suffered his third heart attack while eating dinner with his third wife, Patricia Askew, in his trailer home in Lomita, California. Artificial respiration briefly revived him, and he was able to speak to those around him but lost consciousness shortly afterward and died on March 28.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="26f4255014309b8f0852b2e24af6a9a4" name="Jim_Thorpe_at_desk" sectnum="4#1">../img/26f4255014309b8f0852b2e24af6a9a4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>