<document id="b98d8e4be963ca017ec9ccb1513abff3-2.4" name="Worlds_End_State_Park" cat="11">
<text>
Since the CCC finished their work at the park in 1941, Worlds End State Park has continued to develop and change. In 1951 the Loyalsock Trail, which passes through the park, was laid out by Explorer Scouts. This trail has been maintained and extended by the Alpine Club of Williamsport since 1953. While the park was always popular in Pennsylvania, by the 1960s it began to attract attention from outside the state. The park was home to the first annual whitewater slalom race on Loyalsock Creek in 1964, which attracted over 100 competitors in 1965.  A 1964 ''The New York Times'' article featured Worlds End park and its "excellent trout stream",  and one in 1967 mentioned the park's "peerless wilderness views", "half-acre swimming pool carved into cool Loyalsock Creek" and "public campsites". 

In 1980 a  trailer was added as a temporary park office. The accomplishments of the CCC at Worlds End State Park were recognized in 1987 by the inclusion of the Family Cabin District on the NRHP. On November 12, 2002, a new  visitor center and park office was dedicated, which included  of public space for environmental education and public programs. The building, constructed with an "energy-efficient design and recycled materials", was part of a $1.1 million project that included the park's first flush toilets and wastewater treatment plant. In 2003 a $2.7 million project added flush toilets and running water to all the park's wash-houses, renovated the cabins, and made major improvements in the day use area. As of 2008, post-war facilities include the park office, five wash-houses and other modern restroom facilities, beach house with concession stand, chapel, amphitheater, and modern camping areas.

Worlds End State Park is one of twenty-one chosen by the Pennsylvania Bureau of Parks for its "Twenty Must-See Pennsylvania State Parks" list. The DCNR describes it as "irtually in a class by itself, this wild, rugged and rustic area seems almost untamed". It goes on to praise the opportunities for camping and hiking at the park, and its scenery and vistas. ''Note'': Despite the title, there are twenty-one parks in the list, with Colton Point and Leonard Harrison State Parks treated as one.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0314b3f30fbfa07aa2f52fd7d7e7d210" name="Worlds_End_State_Park_HQ" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/0314b3f30fbfa07aa2f52fd7d7e7d210.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>