<document id="b9b841cff6c543df5bed24222b316230-3.1" name="Scotland_in_the_High_Middle_Ages" cat="14">
<text>
King Domnall II was the first man to have been called ''rí Alban'' (i.e. ''King of Alba'') when he died at Dunnottar in 900 - this meant king of Britain or Scotland. All his predecessors bore the style of either ''King of the Picts'' or ''King of Fortriu''. Such an apparent innovation in the Gaelic chronicles is occasionally taken to spell the birth of Scotland, but there is nothing special about his reign that might confirm this. Domnall had the nickname ''dásachtach''. This simply meant a madman, or, in early Irish law, a man not in control of his functions and hence without legal culpability.Kelly, ''Early Irish Law'', (1998), p.92. In fact, the long reign (900&ndash;942/3) of Domnall's successor Causantín is more often regarded as the key to formation of the High Medieval Kingdom of Alba.e.g. BBC documentary ''In Search of Scotland'', ep. 2. Despite some setbacks, it was during his half-century reign that the Scots saw off any danger that the Vikings would expand their territory beyond the Western and Northern Isles and the Caithness area.

The period between the accession of Máel Coluim I and Máel Coluim II was marked by good relations with the Wessex rulers of England, intense internal dynastic disunity and, despite this, relatively successful expansionary policies. In 945, king Máel Coluim I received Strathclyde as part of a deal with King Edmund of England, an event offset somewhat by Máel Coluim's loss of control in Moray.A.O. Anderson, ''Early Sources'', vol. i, p. 452 Sometime in the reign of king Idulb (954&ndash;962), the Scots captured the fortress called ''oppidum Eden'', i.e. Edinburgh.Hudson, ''Celtic Kings'', (1994), p. 89 Scottish control of Lothian was strengthened with Máel Coluim II's victory over the Northumbrians at the Battle of Carham (1018). The Scots had probably had some authority in Strathclyde since the later part of the ninth century, but the kingdom kept its own rulers, and it is not clear that the Scots were always strong enough to enforce their authority.Hudson, ''Celtic Kings'', pp. 95&ndash;96

The reign of King Donnchad I from 1034 was marred by failed military adventures, and he was defeated and killed by the Mormaer of Moray, Mac Bethad mac Findláich, who became king in 1040.Hudson, ''Celtic Kings'', p. 124 Mac Bethad ruled for seventeen years, so peacefully that he was able to leave to go on pilgrimage to Rome. However, he was overthrown by Máel Coluim, the son of Donnchad who eighteen months later defeated Mac Bethad's successor Lulach to become king Máel Coluim III. In subsequent medieval propaganda Donnchad's reign was portrayed positively, while Mac Bethad was vilified. William Shakespeare followed this distorted history in describing both men in his play Macbeth.


It was Máel Coluim III, not his father Donnchad, who did more to create the dynasty that ruled Scotland for the following two centuries, successfully compared to some. Part of the resource was the large number of children he had, perhaps as many as a dozen, through marriage to the widow or daughter of Thorfinn Sigurdsson, Earl of Orkney and afterwards to the Anglo-Hungarian princess Margaret, granddaughter of Edmund Ironside. However, despite having a royal Anglo-Saxon wife, Máel Coluim spent much of his reign conducting slave raids against the English, adding to the woes of that people in the aftermath of the Norman Conquest of England and the Harrying of the North. Marianus Scotus tells us that "the Gaels and French devastated the English; and  were dispersed and died of hunger; and were compelled to eat human flesh".A.O. Anderson, ''Early Sources'', vol. ii, p. 23, & n. 1.

Máel Coluim's raids and attempts to further the claims for his successors to the English kingdom prompted interference by the Norman rulers of England in the Scottish kingdom. He had married the sister of the native English claimant to the English throne, Edgar Ætheling, and had given most of his children by this marriage Anglo-Saxon royal names. In 1080, King William the Conqueror sent his son on an invasion of Scotland, and Máel Coluim submitted to the authority of the king, giving his oldest son Donnchad as a hostage. King Máel Coluim himself died in one of the raids, in 1093.

Tradition would have made his brother Domnall Bán Máel Coluim's successor, but it seems that Edward, his eldest son by Margaret, was his chosen heir. With Máel Coluim and Edward dead in the same battle, and his other sons in Scotland still young,  Domnall was made king. However, Donnchad II, Máel Coluim's eldest son by his first wife, obtained some support from William Rufus and took the throne, but according to the Anglo-Saxon Chronicle his English and French followers were massacred,Anglo-Saxon Chronicle, MS. E, s.a. 1093; A.O. Anderson, ''Scottish Annals'', (1908), p. 118 and Donnchad II himself was killed later in the same year (1094) by Domnall's ally Máel Petair of Mearns. However, in 1097, William Rufus sent another of Máel Coluim's sons, Edgar, to take the kingship. The ensuing death of Domnall Bán secured the kingship for Edgar, and there followed a period of relative peace. The reigns of both Edgar and his successor Alexander are obscure in comparison with their successors. The former's most notable act was to send a camel (or perhaps an elephant) to his fellow Gael Muircheartach Ua Briain, High King of Ireland.Annals of Inisfallen, s.a. 1105&ndash;1107/7, available ; When Edgar died, Alexander took the kingship, while his youngest brother David became Prince of "Cumbria" and ruler of Lothian.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="895b924fd175818f34d0d347cdd17e25" name="MalcolmIII" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/895b924fd175818f34d0d347cdd17e25.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>