<document id="b9b841cff6c543df5bed24222b316230-11.5" name="Scotland_in_the_High_Middle_Ages" cat="14">
<text>
The ''Ecclesia Scoticana'' (lit. ''Scottish church'') as a system has no known starting point, although Causantín II's alleged Scoticisation of the "Pictish" Church might be taken as one. Before the Norman period, Scotland had little dioscesan structure, being primarily monastic after the fashion of Ireland. After the Norman Conquest of England, the Archbishops of both Canterbury and York each claimed superiority over the Scottish church. The church in Scotland attained independent status after the Papal Bull of Celestine III (''Cum universi'', 1192) by which all Scottish bishoprics except Galloway were formally independent of York and Canterbury. However, unlike Ireland which had been granted four Archbishoprics in the same century, Scotland received no Archbishop and the whole ''Ecclesia Scoticana'', with individual Scottish bishoprics (except Whithorn/Galloway), became the "special daughter of Rome". The following is a table of Bishoprics present in "Scotland-proper" in the thirteenth century:



*Bishop of Dunkeld
*Bishop of St Andrews, then called Kilrymont.
*Bishop of Brechin
*Bishop of Dunblane (often called ''Bishop of Strathearn'')
*Bishop of Mortlach-Aberdeen
*Bishop of Ross (often called ''Bishop of Rosemarkie'' then ''Fortrose '')
*Bishop of Moray (often called ''Bishop of Elgin '')
*Bishop of Caithness (often called ''Bishop of Dornoch'')
*Bishop of Argyll (often called ''Bishop of Lismore'')


Outside of Scotland-proper, the bishopric of Glasgow managed to secure its existence in the twelfth century with a vibrant church community who gained the favour of the Scottish kings. The Bishopric of Whithorn (Galloway) was resurrected by Fergus, King of Galloway, and Thurstan, Archbishop of York. The bishopric of the isles, under the nominal jurisdiction of Trondheim (and sometimes York), had its Episcopal seat at Peel, Isle of Man, later moving to Iona. Lothian had no bishop, but was controlled by St Andrews, Dunkeld and Glasgow. Its natural overlord was the Bishopric of Durham, and that bishopric continued to be important in Lothian, especially through the cult of St Cuthbert. There was also a bishopric of Orkney, based at Kirkwall.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="cea6c339c4392284671da0d4c5408c85" name="St_Andrews_Cathedral_Ruins_Front" sectnum="11.5#1">../img/cea6c339c4392284671da0d4c5408c85.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>