<document id="b9b841cff6c543df5bed24222b316230-6" name="Scotland_in_the_High_Middle_Ages" cat="14">
<text>
The Scottish economy of this period was dominated by agriculture and by short-distance, local trade. There was an increasing amount of foreign trade in the period, as well as exchange gained by means of military plunder. By the end of this period, coins were replacing barter goods, but for most of this period most exchange was done without the use of metal currency.Stringer, "Emergence of a Nation State", pp. 66&ndash;69


Most of Scotland's agricultural wealth in this period came from pastoralism, rather than arable farming. Arable farming grew significantly in the "Norman period", but with geographical differences, low-lying areas being subject to more arable farming than high-lying areas such as the Highlands, Galloway and the Southern Uplands. Galloway, in the words of G.W.S. Barrow, "already famous for its cattle, was so overwhelmingly pastoral, that there is little evidence in that region of land under any permanent cultivation, save along the Solway coast."Barrow, ''Kingship and Unity'', (1981), p. 12 The average amount of land used by a husbandman in Scotland might have been around 26 acres.Barrow, ''Kingship and Unity'', (1981), p. 18 There is a lot of evidence that the native Scots favoured pastoralism, in that Gaelic lords were happier to give away more land to French and Middle English-speaking settlers, whilst holding on tenaciously to more high-lying regions, perhaps contributing to the Highland/Galloway-Lowland division that emerged in Scotland in the later Middle Ages.e.g. for Galloway, Oram, ''Lordship'', pp. 212&ndash;213; for Strathearn and Lennox, see Neville, ''Native Lordship'', pp. 79&ndash;130 The main unit of land measurement in Scotland was the ''davoch'' (i.e. "vat"), called the ''arachor'' in Lennox. This unit is also known as the "Scottish ploughgate." In English-speaking Lothian, it was simply ploughgate.Barrow, ''Kingship and Unity'', p. 12&ndash;15 It may have measured about 104 acres,Barrow, ''Kingship and Unity'', (1981), p. 15 divided into 4 ''rath''s.Neville, ''Native Lordship'', p. 96 Cattle, pigs and cheeses were among the most produced foodstuffs,Driscoll, ''Alba'', (2002), p. 53 but of course a vast range of foodstuffs were produced, from sheep and fish, rye and barley, to bee wax and honey.

Pre-Davidian Scotland had no known chartered burghs, though most, if not all, of the burghs granted charters by the crown already existed long before the reign of David I but he gave them legal status - a new form of recognition. Scotland, outside Lothian, Lanarkshire, Roxburghshire, Berwickshire, Angus, Aberdeenshire and Fife at least, largely was populated by scattered hamlets, and outside that area, lacked the continental style nucleated village. David I established the first chartered burghs in Scotland. David I copied the burgher charters and ''Leges Burgorum'' (rules governing virtually every aspect of life and work in a burgh) almost verbatim from the English customs of Newcastle-Upon-Tyne.Barrow, ''Kingship and unity'', p. 98 Early burgesses were usually Flemish, English, French and German, rather than Gaelic Scots. The burgh’s vocabulary was composed totally of either Germanic and French terms.Murison, "Linguistic Relations", (1974), p. 74 The councils which ran individual burghs were individually known as ''lie doussane'', meaning the dozen.Murison, "Linguistic Relations", (1974), p. 102
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6fb3455f0582f7c1b2ce98fb442b4fa1" name="Burghs_of_Dabíd_mac_Maíl_Choluim" sectnum="6#1">../img/6fb3455f0582f7c1b2ce98fb442b4fa1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>