<document id="b9b841cff6c543df5bed24222b316230-2" name="Scotland_in_the_High_Middle_Ages" cat="14">
<text>
During the period of occupation by the Roman Empire, the province of Britannia formally ended at Hadrian's Wall. Between this wall and the Antonine Wall, the Romans fostered a series of buffer states separating the Roman-occupied territory from the territory of the Picts. The development of "Pictland" itself, according to the historical model developed by Peter Heather, was a natural response to Roman imperialism.Heather, "State Formation", (1994), 47&ndash;63 Around 400 the buffer states became the Brythonic kingdoms of "The Old North", and by 900 the Kingdom of the Picts had developed into the Gaelic Kingdom of Alba.

In the tenth century, the Scottish elite began to develop a conquest myth to explain their Gaelicization, a myth often known as MacAlpin's Treason, in which Cináed mac Ailpín is supposed to have annihilated the Picts in one fell takeover. The earliest versions include the ''Life of St Cathróe of Metz''Dumville, "St Cathróe of Metz", pp. 172&ndash;176; text translated on A.O. Anderson, ''Early Sources'', vol. i, pp. 431&ndash;443 and royal genealogies tracing their origin to Fergus Mór mac Eirc.for text and commentary, see Bannerman, ''Studies'' (1974) & Dumville "Ireland and North Britain", (2002). In the reign of Máel Coluim III, the ''Duan Albanach'' formalised the myth in Gaelic poetic tradition.M. Anderson, ''Kings and Kingship'' (1973), p. 79, n. 11; for text, . In the thirteenth and fourteenth centuries, these mythical traditions were incorporated into the documents now in the Poppleton Manuscript, and in the ''Declaration of Arbroath''. They were believed in the early modern period, and beyond; even King James VI/I traced his origin to Fergus, saying, in his own words, that he was a "Monarch sprunge of Ferguse race".Pittock, ''Celtic Identity'', (1999), p. 18.

However, modern historians are now beginning to reject this conceptualization of Scottish origins.e.g. Dauvit Broun, "Dunkeld and the Origins of Scottish Identity" (1999); Dauvit Broun, "Kenneth mac Alpin", (2001), p. 359; Alex Woolf, "Ungus (Onuist), son of Uurgust", (2001), p. 604; Katherine Forsyth, "Scotland to 1100" (2005) pp. 28&ndash;31. Compare older accounts, such as in Alfred Smyth, ''Warlords and Holy Men'', (Edinburgh, 1984), pp. 175&ndash;189 No contemporary sources mention this conquest. Moreover, the Gaelicization of Pictland was a long process predating Cináed, and is evidenced by Gaelic-speaking Pictish rulers,See Clancy, "Philosopher-King: Nechtan mac Der-Ilei". Pictish royal patronage of Gaelic poets,Clancy (ed.), ''The Triumph Tree'', p. 115; ibid. pp. 15&ndash;16 for suggestion as contemporary praise poetry. Gaelic inscriptions,Foster, Sally, ''Picts, Gaels and Scots'' (1996). and Gaelic placenames.Nicolaisen ''Scottish Place-names'' (1976/2001), pp. 165&ndash;191 ; Simon Taylor, "Place-names", (1996), pp. 93&ndash;103. The term ''king of Alba'', although only registered at the start of the tenth century,AU, s.a. 900; A.O. Anderson, ''Early Sources'', vol. i, p. 395 is possibly just a Gaelic translation of ''Pictland''. The change of identity can perhaps be explained by the death of the Pictish language, but also important may be Causantín II's alleged Scoticisation of the "Pictish" ChurchChronicle of the Kings of Alba; A.O. Anderson, ''Early Sources'', vol. i, p.445. and the trauma caused by Viking invasions, most strenuously felt in the Pictish Kingdom's heartland of Fortriu.Woolf, "Geography of the Picts", (forthcoming).

Outside of Alba, the Kingdom of Strathclyde on the valley of the river Clyde remained semi-independent, as did the Gaels of Argyll and the islands to the west (formerly Dál Riata). The south-east had been absorbed by the English Kingdom of Bernicia/Northumbria in the seventh century, and other Germanic invaders, the Norse, were beginning to incorporate much of the Western and Northern Isles, as well as the Caithness area. Galloway too was under strong Norse-Gaelic influence, but there was no one kingdom in that area.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="704270aea6fb5786e9e8f96678264835" name="Forres_sueno" sectnum="2#1">../img/704270aea6fb5786e9e8f96678264835.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>