<document id="b9fe7403b7c8ed2ee5f2c7bc8e6e9fb7-2.3.2" name="Panzer_I" cat="29">
<text>
Italian setbacks in Egypt and their colony of Libya caused Hitler to dispatch aircraft to Sicily, and a blocking force to North Africa. This blocking force was put under the command of Lieutenant General Erwin Rommel and included the motorized 5th Light Division and the 15th Panzer Division. This force landed at Tunis on 12 February 1941.Latimer, ''Alamein'', pp. 27–28 Upon arrival, Rommel had around 150 tanks, about half Panzer III and IV.Bierman, ''The Battle of Alamein'', p.67 The rest were Panzer I and II, although the Panzer I were soon replaced.Perrett, ''German Light Panzers'', pp. 43–44 On 6 April 1941, Germany attacked both Yugoslavia and Greece, with fourteen divisions invading Greece from neighboring Bulgaria, which by then had joined the Tripartite Pact.Porch, ''The Path to Victory'', p. 149 The invasion of Yugoslavia included no less than six panzer divisions,McCarthy, ''Panzerkrieg'', p. 94 which still fielded the Panzer I.Perrett, ''German Light Panzers'', p. 44, Yugoslavia surrendered 17 April 1941, and Greece fell on 30 April 1941.Porch, ''The Path to Victory'', p. 159

The final major campaign in which the Panzer I formed a large portion of the armored strength was Operation Barbarossa, 22 June, 1941. The 3,300 German tanks included about 410 Panzer I.McCarthy, ''Panzerkrieg'', p. 99; 750 were Panzer IIs, 150 Panzer 35(t)s, 625 Panzer 38(t)s, 965 Panzer IIIs and 440 Panzer IVs. By the end of the month, a large portion of the Red Army found itself trapped in the Minsk pocket,McCarthy, ''Panzerkrieg'', p. 103 and by 21 September Kiev had fallen, thereby allowing the Germans to concentrate on their ultimate objective, Moscow.Beevor, ''Stalingrad'', p. 29 Despite the success of Germany's armor in the Soviet Union, between June and September most German officers were shocked to find their tanks were inferior to newer Soviet models, the T-34 and KV series. Army Group North very quickly realized that none of the tank guns currently in use by German armor could penetrate the thick armor of the KV-1.Raus, p. 34, The performance of the Red Army during the Battle of Moscow and the growing numbers of new Soviet tanks made it obvious that the Panzer I was no longer suitable for combat. The Panzer Is were instead tasked with towing trains  through thick mud to alleviate logistics problems at the front.Perrett, ''German Light Panzers'', p. 45
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1838ce2d7e42c3b1e8ef93d1d0cbd7b8" name="Bundesarchiv_Bild_101I-265-0006-31,_Russland,_Befehlspanzer_1" sectnum="2.3.2#1">../img/1838ce2d7e42c3b1e8ef93d1d0cbd7b8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>