<document id="b9fe7403b7c8ed2ee5f2c7bc8e6e9fb7-2.3.1" name="Panzer_I" cat="29">
<text>
On 1 September 1939, Germany invaded Poland using seventy-two divisions (including 16 reserve infantry divisions in OKH reserves), including seven panzer divisions (1., 2., 3., 4., 5., 10., "Kempf") and four light divisions (1., 2., 3., 4.). Three days later, France and Britain declared war on Germany. The seven panzer and four light divisions were arrayed in five armies, forming two army groups. The battalion strength of the 1 Panzer Division included no less than fourteen Panzer I's, while the other six divisions included thirty-four Panzer I's.Perrett, ''German Light Panzers'', pp. 37 A total of about 2,700 tanks were available for the invasion of Poland, but only 310 of the heavier Panzer IIIs and IVs were available. Furthermore, 350 were of Czech design—the rest were either Panzer I's or Panzer II's.McCarthy, ''Panzerkrieg'', p. 50–51 The invasion was swift and the last Polish pockets of resistance surrendered on 6 October.McCarthy, ''Panzerkrieg'', p. 59 The entire campaign had lasted five weeks (with help of the Soviet forces which attacked on 17th of September), and the success of Germany's tanks in the campaign was summed up in response to Hitler on 5 September: when asked if it had been the dive bombers who destroyed a Polish artillery regiment, Guderian replied, "No, our panzers!"Guderian, ''Panzer Leader'', p. 73 



The Poles suffered almost 190,000 casualties (including around 66,300 killed) in the campaign, the Germans around 55,000 (including around 35,000 wounded) ''Wojna Obronna Polski 1939'', page 851. However, some 832 tanks (including 320 PzI, 259 PzII, 40 Pz III, 76 PzIV, 77 Pz35(t), 13 PzBef III, 7 PzBef 38(t), 34 other PzBef and some Pz38(t))Fritz Hahn, ''Waffen und Geheimwaffen des deutschen Heeres 1933-1945'', ''Polen 1939'' were lost during the campaign, approximately 341 of which were never to return to service. This represented about a third of Germany's armor deployed for in the Polish campaign. During the campaign no less than a half of Germany's tanks were unavailable due to maintenance issues or enemy action, and of all tanks, the Panzer I proved the most vulnerable to Polish anti-tank weapons.McCarthy, ''Panzerkrieg'', p. 60 Furthermore, it was found handling of armored forces during the campaign left much to be desired. During the beginning of Guderian's attack in northern Poland, his corps was held back to coordinate with infantry for quite a while, preventing a faster advance. It was only after Army Group South had its attention taken from Warsaw at the Battle of Bzura that Guderian's armor was fully unleashed. There were still lingering tendencies to reserve Germany's armor, even if in independent divisions, to cover an infantry advance or the flanks of advancing infantry armies.Cooper, ''The German Army'', p. 176  Although tank production was increased to 125 tanks per month after the Polish Campaign, losses forced the Germans to draw further strength from Czech tank designs, and light tanks continued to form the majority of Germany's armored strength.McCarthy, ''Panzerkrieg'', p. 61

Months later, Panzer Is participated in Operation Weserübung&mdash;the invasion of Denmark and Norway.Perrett, ''German Light Panzers'', p. 18 


Despite its obsolescence, the Panzer I was also used in the invasion of France in May 1940. Of 2,574 tanks available for the campaign, no fewer than 523 were Panzer Is. Furthermore, there were only 627 Panzer III's and IV's. At least a fifth of Germany's armor was composed of Panzer I's, while almost four-fifths was light tanks of one type or another, including 955 Panzer II, 106 Czech Panzer 35(t), and 228 Panzer 38(t).Guderian, ''Panzer Leader'', p. 472 For their defense, the French boasted up to 4,000 tanks, including 300 Char B1, armed with a 47-millimeter (1.7 in) gun in the turret and a larger 75-millimeter (2.95 in) low-velocity gun in the hull. The French also had around 250 Somua S-35, widely regarded as one of the best tanks of the period, armed with the same 47millimeter main gun and protected by almost 55 millimeter (2.17 in) of armor at its thickest point. Nevertheless, the French also deployed over 3,000 light tanks, including about 500 World War One-vintage FT-17s.McCarthy, ''Panzerkrieg'', p. 72 The two main advantages German armor enjoyed were radios allowing them to coordinate faster than their British or French counterpartsMcCarthy, ''Panzerkrieg'', p. 73 and superior tactical doctrine.McCarthy, ''Panzerkrieg'', p. 90
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0a2f20220c6693325874bda68b2ca6fd" name="Bundesarchiv_Bild_183-B14898,_Calais,_britische_Kriegsgefangene" sectnum="2.3.1#1">../img/0a2f20220c6693325874bda68b2ca6fd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>