<document id="b9fe7403b7c8ed2ee5f2c7bc8e6e9fb7-1.1" name="Panzer_I" cat="29">
<text>
Two more combat versions of the Panzer I were designed and produced between 1939 and 1942.  By this stage the design concept had been superseded by medium and heavy tanks and neither variant was produced in sufficient numbers to have a real impact on the progress of the war. These new tanks had nothing in common with either the Ausf. A or B except name.Gander, ''Tanks & Armour: Panzerkampfwagen I & II'', p. 14 One of these, the Panzer I Ausf. C, was designed jointly between Krauss-Maffei and Daimler-Benz in 1939 to provide an amply armored and armed reconnaissance light tank. The Ausf. C boasted a completely new chassis and turret, a modern torsion-bar suspension and five interleaved roadwheels.Franco, ''Panzer I'', pp. 37–38 It also had a maximum armor thickness of 30 millimeters (1.18 in), over twice that of either the Ausf. A or B, and was armed with a 20-millimeter (0.78 in) EW 141 autocannon.Franco, ''Panzer I'', p. 6 Both Franco and Perrett mention that the EW 141 cannon 20 millimeters, although Gander mentions a caliber of 7.92 millimeters. However, there is a picture of an Ausf. C with a 20-millimeter cannon on page 15 of Gander. Forty of these tanks were produced,Franco, ''Panzer I'', p. 37 along with six prototypes. Two tanks were deployed to 1 Panzer Division in 1943, and the other thirty-eight were deployed to the LVIII Panzer Reserve Corps during the Normandy landings.Franco, ''Panzer I'', p. 38

 

The second vehicle, the Ausf. F, was as different from the Ausf. C as it was from the Ausf. A and B.Gander, ''Tanks & Armour: Panzerkampfwagen I & II'', pp. 14–15 Intended as an infantry support tank, the Panzer I Ausf. F had a maximum armour thickness of 80 millimeters (3.15 in) and weighed between 18 and 21 tonnes.Perrett, ''German Light Panzers'', pp. 6–7. Perrett claims a weight of 18 tonnes, although Franco claims 21.  The Ausf. F was armed with two 7.92-millimeter MG-34s.Gander, ''Tanks & Armour: Panzerkampfwagen I & II'', p. 14; although this is similar to the armament of earlier Ausf. A and B, these two were armed with the older MG-13s, not the modern MG-34. Thirty were produced in 1940, and a second order of 100 was later canceled. In order to compensate for the increased weight, a new  Maybach HL45 Otto engine was used, allowing a maximum road speed of 25 kilometers per hour (15.5 mph). Eight of the thirty tanks produced were sent to the 1 Panzer Division in 1943 and saw combat at the Battle of Kursk. The rest were given to several army schools for training and evaluation purposes.Franco, ''Panzer I'', pp. 38–39
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8b20e5a32210c308ae01b06c3eedb0e7" name="Pz_II_Neu" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/8b20e5a32210c308ae01b06c3eedb0e7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>