<document id="bae0e6b899bcecb46fc76e673c1ca877-2.1" name="USS_Missouri_(BB-63)" cat="29">
<text>
After trials off New York and shakedown and battle practice in the Chesapeake Bay, ''Missouri'' departed Norfolk, Virginia on 11 November 1944, transited the Panama Canal on 18 November and steamed to San Francisco for final fitting out as fleet flagship. She stood out of San Francisco Bay on 14 December and arrived at Pearl Harbor, Hawaii on 24 December 1944. She departed Hawaii on 2 January 1945 and arrived in Ulithi, West Caroline Islands on 13 January. There she was temporary headquarters ship for Vice Admiral Marc A. Mitscher. The battleship put to sea on 27 January to serve in the screen of the  carrier task group of Mitscher's TF 58, and on 16 February her aircraft carriers launched the first air strikes against Japan since the famed Doolittle raid, which had been launched from the carrier  in April 1942.

''Missouri'' then steamed with the carriers to Iwo Jima where her main guns provided direct and continuous support to the invasion landings begun on 19 February. After TF 58 returned to Ulithi on 5 March, ''Missouri'' was assigned to the  carrier task group. On 14 March, ''Missouri'' departed Ulithi in the screen of the fast carriers and steamed to the Japanese mainland. During strikes against targets along the coast of the Inland Sea of Japan beginning on 18 March, ''Missouri'' shot down four Japanese aircraft.

Raids against airfields and naval bases near the Inland Sea and southwestern Honshū continued. During a Japanese attack, two bombs penetrated the hangar deck and decks aft of the carrier , leaving her dead in the water within  of the Japanese mainland. The heavy cruiser  took ''Franklin'' in tow until she gained speed to . ''Missouri''s carrier task group provided cover for ''Franklin''s retirement toward Ulithi until 22 March, then set course for pre-invasion strikes and bombardment of Okinawa.

''Missouri'' joined the fast battleships of TF 58 in bombarding the southeast coast of Okinawa on 24 March, an action intended to draw enemy strength from the west coast beaches that would be the actual site of invasion landings. ''Missouri'' rejoined the screen of the carriers as Marine and Army units stormed the shores of Okinawa on the morning of 1 April. Planes from the carriers shattered a special Japanese attacking force led by the battleship  on 7 April. ''Yamato'', the world's largest battleship, was sunk, as were a cruiser and a destroyer. Three other enemy destroyers were heavily damaged and scuttled. Four remaining destroyers, sole survivors of the attacking fleet, were damaged and retired to Sasebo.



On 11 April, a low-flying ''kamikaze'', although fired on, crashed on  ''Missouri''s starboard side just below her main deck level. The starboard wing of the plane was thrown far forward, starting a gasoline fire at  Gun Mount No. 3. The battleship suffered only superficial damage, and the fire was brought quickly under control. The remains of the pilot's body were recovered onboard the ship just aft of one of the 40 mm gun tubs, and was thought to be the body of the petty officer, Ishino Setsuo. Captain William Callaghan decided that the young Japanese pilot had done his job to the best of his ability and with honour, and that he should be given a military funeral. The following day he was buried at sea with military honors. The dent in the side of the ship remains to this day.

About 2305 on 17 April, ''Missouri'' detected an enemy submarine  from her formation. Her report set off a hunter-killer operation by the light carrier  and four destroyers, which sank the Japanese submarine ''I-56''.

''Missouri'' was detached from the carrier task force off Okinawa on 5 May and sailed for Ulithi. During the Okinawa campaign she had shot down five enemy planes, assisted in the destruction of six others, and scored one probable kill. She helped repel 12 daylight attacks of enemy raiders and fought off four night attacks on her carrier task group. Her shore bombardment destroyed several gun emplacements and many other military, governmental, and industrial structures.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a759731a6aa24a0e7c0d97ad8dcba8c7" name="Kamikaze_zero" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/a759731a6aa24a0e7c0d97ad8dcba8c7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>