<document id="bae0e6b899bcecb46fc76e673c1ca877-2.3" name="USS_Missouri_(BB-63)" cat="29">
<text>
Strikes on Hokkaidō and northern Honshū resumed on 9 August, the day the second atomic bomb was dropped. At 2054 on 10 August, ''Missouri''s men were electrified by the unofficial news that Japan was ready to surrender, provided that the Emperor's prerogatives as a sovereign ruler were not compromised. Not until 0745 on 15 August was word received that President Harry S. Truman had announced Japan's acceptance of unconditional surrender.

Admiral Sir Bruce Fraser of the Royal Navy, the Commander of the British Pacific Fleet, boarded ''Missouri'' on 16 August and conferred the honor of Knight of the British Empire upon Admiral Halsey. ''Missouri'' transferred a landing party of 200 officers and men to the battleship  for temporary duty with the initial occupation force for Tokyo on 21 August. ''Missouri'' herself entered Tokyo Bay early on 29 August to prepare for the signing by Japan of the official instrument of surrender.

High-ranking military officials of all the Allied Powers were received on board on 2 September, including Chinese General Hsu Yung-Ch'ang, British Admiral-of-the-Fleet Sir Bruce Fraser, Soviet Lieutenant-General Kuzma Nikolaevich Derevyanko, Australian General Sir Thomas Blamey, Canadian Colonel Lawrence Moore Cosgrave, French Général d'Armée Philippe Leclerc de Hautecloque, Dutch Vice Admiral Conrad Emil Lambert Helfrich, and New Zealand Air Vice Marshal Leonard M. Isitt. 
 
Fleet Admiral Chester Nimitz boarded shortly after 0800, and General of the Army Douglas MacArthur, the Supreme Commander for the Allies, came on board at 0843. The Japanese representatives, headed by Foreign Minister Mamoru Shigemitsu, arrived at 0856. At 0902, General MacArthur stepped before a battery of microphones and opened the 23-minute surrender ceremony to the waiting world by stating, "It is my earnest hope-indeed the hope of all mankind-that from the blood and carnage of the past, a world founded upon faith and understanding, a world dedicated to the dignity of man and the fulfillment of his most cherished wish for freedom, tolerance, and justice." 

During the surrender ceremony, the deck of ''Missouri'' was decorated with a 31-star American flag that had been taken ashore by Commodore Matthew Perry Commodore Perry's in 1853 after his squadron of "Black Ships" sailed into Tokyo Bay to urge the opening of Japan's ports to foreign trade. This flag was actually displayed with the reverse side showing, i.e., stars in the upper right corner: the historic flag was so fragile that the conservator at the Naval Academy Museum had sewn a protective linen backing to one side to help secure the fabric from deteriorating, leaving its "wrong side" visible. The flag was displayed in a wood-framed case secured to the bulkhead overlooking the surrender ceremony. Tsustsumi, Cheryl Lee.  ''Star-Bulletin'' (Honolulu). 26 August 2007. Another U.S. flag was raised and flown during the occasion, a flag that some sources have indicated was in fact that flag which had flown over the U.S. Capitol on December 7, 1941. This is not true; it was a flag taken from the ship's stock, according to Missouri's Commanding Officer, Captain Stuary "Sunshine" Murray, and it was "...just a plain ordinary GI-issue flag".

By 09:30 the Japanese emissaries had departed. In the afternoon of 5 September, Admiral Halsey transferred his flag to the battleship , and early the next day ''Missouri'' departed Tokyo Bay. As part of the ongoing Operation Magic Carpet she received homeward bound passengers at Guam, then sailed unescorted for Hawaii. She arrived at Pearl Harbor on 20 September and flew Admiral Nimitz's flag on the afternoon of 28 September for a reception.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="aeca48d62209b656d490a392423406a8" name="Douglas_MacArthur_signs_formal_surrender" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/aeca48d62209b656d490a392423406a8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>