<document id="bb936063e3841f4ed025b5f0c0a4f5c6-3" name="Ipswich_Town_F.C." cat="26">
<text>
Between 1878 and 1884, Ipswich Town played at two grounds in the town, Broom Hill and Brook's Hall, but in 1884, the club moved to Portman Road and have played there ever since.  At their new home, Ipswich became one of the first clubs to implement the use of goal nets, in 1890, but the more substantial elements of ground development did not begin until, in 1901, a tobacco processing plant was built along the south edge of the ground.
The first stand, a wooden structure, was built on the Portman Road side of the pitch in 1905. In 1911 the roof was blown off, and the ground was later commandeered by the British Army for the duration of the First World War. The club turned professional in 1936, and work began on the first bank of terracing at the north end of the pitch. The following year, on the back of winning the Southern League, a similar terrace was built at the southern "Churchmans" end.  All sides were terraced by 1954, and floodlights were erected in 1959 for use in lower light conditions.  The two-tier Portman Stand was built along the east side of the ground in place of the existing terraces in 1971, and the west stand, then known as the "Pioneer Stand" as a result of the club's sponsorship by the electronics company Pioneer Corporation, was converted to all-seating in 1990.
In 1990, following the recommendations of the Taylor Report in the wake of the Hillsborough disaster the previous year, the terraces in both the north and south stands were also converted to all-seating, creating the first complete all-seater stadium in the top flight of English football with a spectator capacity of 22,600.

Success on the pitch lead to further investment in the infrastructure, with the club spending over £22 million on redeveloping both North and South stands, resulting in a current capacity of 30,311. In the past ten years, statues of both Sir Alf Ramsey and Sir Bobby Robson have been unveiled outside the stadium.  The North Stand was renamed in honour of former manager Bobby Robson in September 2009.  The playing surface at Portman Road is highly regarded and has been voted best pitch in the league on a number of occasions.  The current groundsman, Alan Ferguson, has received a number of accolades, including both Premiership and Championship Groundsman of the Year.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a8fd0ef0b27146297f57bbdfe84e5309" name="2002-07-16_Portman_Road" sectnum="3#1">../img/a8fd0ef0b27146297f57bbdfe84e5309.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>