<document id="bc0aa2440dae6a180a0817b083e64850-2" name="Sinestro_Corps_War" cat="17">
<text>
"Sinestro Corps War" was based on concepts introduced by Alan Moore and Kevin O'Neill in the short story ''Tygers'', published in ''Tales of the Green Lantern Corps Annual'' #2 (1986). Writers Geoff Johns and Dave Gibbons incorporated several ideas from Moore's stories into "Sinestro Corps War", including the prophecy of the Blackest Night, Sodam Yat, Ranx the Sentient City and the Children of the White Lobe. Leezle Pon, a minor character only mentioned once in Moore's "Mogo Doesn't Socialize" story from 25 years previous, also makes an appearance in ''Green Lantern'' #25.

Work began on "Sinestro Corps War" in September 2006. The structure was fluid, at one point becoming a few issues with two bookends to just one gigantic issue. The title was originally just "Sinestro Corps", but during development the creators added the word "War". Eventually the structure finalized into a one-shot special for release in June, after which the story would alternate between ''Green Lantern'' and ''Green Lantern Corps'' until November. After the crossover's initial publishing successes, DC added four ''Tales of the Sinestro Corps'' one-shots to the publishing schedule.

Johns and Ethan Van Sciver first announced the crossover during the DC "Big Guns" panel at the 2006 Fan Expo Canada, with Johns calling it "the next level of ''Rebirth''". By January 2007, Johns, Gibbons and editor Peter Tomasi had planned out most of the storyline. Sterling Gates, whom Johns had met at a convention, was brought in to write a backup story for the Superman-Prime one-shot and co-write ''Green Lantern/Sinestro Corps Secret Files'' #1.

The creators called "Sinestro Corps War" "World War II with the entire universe". In a September 2007 interview, Johns compared "Sinestro Corps War" to the Star Wars trilogy, with ''Green Lantern: Rebirth'' as ''A New Hope'' and "Sinestro Corps War" as ''The Empire Strikes Back''. References to other science fiction stories were made by artist Ivan Reis, who inserted characters such as E.T., ALF and a Predator into large two-page illustrations. The writers also included the sound "EPA" in ''Green Lantern'' #25 as a direct reference to a scene in ''The Simpsons Movie'' where Comic Book Guy uses the sound while talking about a fight between Green Lantern and Sinestro.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="93fd071e7f76d040fd7966917d812742" name="Green_Lantern_Corps_prophecy" sectnum="2#1">../img/93fd071e7f76d040fd7966917d812742.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>