<document id="bcb4181747d354c65e150e6c6d2a8cdc-2" name="Sydney_Newman" cat="19">
<text>
Soon after Newman arrived in the UK, ABC's Head of Drama Dennis Vance was moved into a more senior position with the company, and Thomas offered Newman his position, which the Canadian quickly accepted. He was, however, somewhat disparaging of the state in which he found British television drama. "At that time, I found this country to be somewhat class-ridden," he told interviewers in 1988. "The only legitimate theatre was of the 'anyone for tennis' variety, which on the whole gave a condescending view of working-class people. Television dramas were usually adaptations of stage plays and invariably about the upper classes. I said 'Damn the upper classes: they don't even ''own'' televisions!'",  Interviewed by Auger, David & Walker, Stephen James. "Doctor Who Magazine", issue 141. October 1988.

Newman's principal tool for shaking up this established order was a Sunday night anthology series which had been initiated before he had arrived at ABC, but which he was to leave a firm mark upon. ''Armchair Theatre'' was networked nationally across the ITV regions on Sunday evenings, drawing huge audiences, and Newman used the strand to present plays by writers such as Alun Owen, Harold Pinter and Clive Exton, also bringing over associates from Canada such as William Kotcheff.

In 1960 Newman devised a thriller series for ABC called ''Police Surgeon'', starring Ian Hendry. Although ''Police Surgeon'' was not a success and was cancelled after only a short run, Newman took Hendry as the star and some of the ethos of the programme to create a new series (not a direct sequel as is sometimes claimed) called ''The Avengers''. Debuting in January 1961, ''The Avengers'' became a huge international success, although in later years its premise differed somewhat from Newman's initial set-up, veering into more surreal fantasy territory rather than remaining a gritty thriller.

Newman's great success at ABC had been noted by the British Broadcasting Corporation, whose executives were keen to revive their own drama department's fortunes in the face of fierce competition from ITV. In 1961 the BBC's Director of Television, Kenneth Adam, met with Newman &mdash; in a pub &mdash; and offered him the position of Head of Drama at the BBC. He accepted the position, eager for a new challenge, although he was forced by ABC to remain with them until the expiration of his contract in December 1962, after which he immediately began work with the BBC.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="923a32b988e0b146fdfe5424b11f3e51" name="ABC_Weekend_TV_studios_in_Didsbury_Manchester" sectnum="2#1">../img/923a32b988e0b146fdfe5424b11f3e51.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>