<document id="bccded0a80fdf599444673d421515c66-1.2" name="AHS_Centaur" cat="29">
<text>
At the beginning of 1943, ''Centaur'' was placed at the disposal of the Australian Department of Defence for conversion to a hospital ship. The conversion was performed by United Ship Services in Melbourne, Australia, and was initially estimated to cost AU£20,000.Smith, ''Three Minutes of Time'', p. 21

The cost increased to almost AU£55,000, for a variety of reasons. It was originally intended for the ship to travel between ports in New Guinea and Townsville, Queensland, Australia. Increasing casualty numbers in the New Guinea campaign meant that the hospitals in Queensland would quickly become unable to deal with the quantity of the casualties and the nature of their injuries, so a longer voyage to Sydney was required. The Army demanded that additional facilities and conversions be added to the original plans such as expanded bathing and washing facilities, hot water made available to all parts of the ship through installation of a calorifier, the rerouting of all steam pipes away from patient areas, and ventilation arrangements suitable for tropical conditions. The unions representing the ship's crew requested improved living and dining conditions, including new sinks in the food preparation areas and the replacement of flooring in the quarters and mess rooms.


When AHS ''Centaur'' was relaunched on 12 March 1943, she was equipped with an operating theatre, dispensary, two wards (located on the former cattle decks), and a dental surgery, along with quarters for seventy five crew and sixty five permanent Army medical staff.Milligan and Foley, ''Australian Hospital Ship Centaur'', p. 51Smith, ''Three Minutes of Time'', pp. 21–2 To maintain the ship's mean draught of ,  of ironstone were distributed through the cargo holds as ballast. AHS ''Centaur'' was capable of voyages of 18 days before resupply and could carry just over 250 bedridden patients.Milligan and Foley, ''Australian Hospital Ship Centaur'', p. 40
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="33c8116e1dbde0e135a89cfbd499d4db" name="Centaur_ward_(AWM_029717)" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/33c8116e1dbde0e135a89cfbd499d4db.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>