<document id="bccded0a80fdf599444673d421515c66-3.8" name="AHS_Centaur" cat="29">
<text>
On the morning of 15 May 1943, American destroyer  departed Brisbane to escort the 11,063 ton New Zealand freighter ''Sussex'' on the first stage of the latter's trans-Tasman voyage.Milligan and Foley, ''Australian Hospital Ship Centaur'', pp. 144–5 At 2:00 p.m., a lookout aboard ''Mugford'' reported an object on the horizon, and at the same time a Royal Australian Air Force Avro Anson of No. 71 Squadron flying ahead on anti-submarine watch dived towards the object. The aircraft returned to the two ships and signalled that there were shipwreck survivors in the water requiring rescue. ''Mugford''’s commanding officer ordered ''Sussex'' to continue alone while ''Mugford'' collected the survivors.Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945'', p. 257Smith, ''Three Minutes of Time'', p. 33 Marksmen were positioned around the ship to shoot sharks, while seamen stood ready to dive in and assist the wounded.Milligan and Foley, ''Australian Hospital Ship Centaur'', p. 149 ''Mugford''’s medical staff was present to inspect each person as they came aboard and provide necessary medical care. The American crew learned from the first group of survivors that they were from the hospital ship ''Centaur''. 

At 2:14 p.m., ''Mugford'' made contact with the Naval Officer-in-Charge in Brisbane; the first that anyone in Australia had knowledge of the attack on ''Centaur''.Smith, ''Three Minutes of Time'', p. 34 The rescue of the 64 survivors took an hour and twenty minutes, although ''Mugford'' remained in the area until dark, searching an area of approximately  for additional survivors.Milligan and Foley, ''Australian Hospital Ship Centaur'', p. 153 After darkness fell, ''Mugford'' returned to Brisbane, arriving shortly before midnight. Further searches of the waters off North Stradbroke Island were made by  during the night of 15 May until 6:00 p.m. on 16 May, and by  and four motor torpedo boats from 16 to 21 May, with neither search finding more survivors.Smith, ''Three Minutes of Time'', p. 35
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e434c7683c7b08a7dad73c6632fec7bb" name="Ellen_Savage_(AWM_061952)" sectnum="3.8#1">../img/e434c7683c7b08a7dad73c6632fec7bb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>