<document id="bccded0a80fdf599444673d421515c66-4.11" name="AHS_Centaur" cat="29">
<text>
The attack was universally condemned by Australian servicemen, who commonly believed that the attack on ''Centaur'' had been carried out deliberately and in full knowledge of her status.Jenkins, ''Battle Surface'', p. 282 Similar reactions were expressed by other Allied personnel; United States Army Air Force General George Kenney recalled having to talk a sergeant bombardier out of organising a retaliatory bombing run on a Japanese hospital ship known to be in their area.Kenney, ''General Kenney Reports'', pp. 245–6

Six days after the attack on ''Centaur'', a request was made by the Australian Department of Defence that the identification markings and lights be removed from Australian hospital ship ''Manunda'', weapons be installed, and that she begin to sail blacked out and under escort.Milligan and Foley, ''Australian Hospital Ship Centaur'', pp. 189–92 The conversion was performed, although efforts by the Department of the Navy, the Admiralty, and authorities in New Zealand and the United States of America caused the completed conversion to be undone. The cost of the roundabout work came to £12,500, and kept ''Manunda'' out of service for three months.Milligan and Foley, ''Australian Hospital Ship Centaur'', p. 192 On 9 June 1943, communications between the Combined Chiefs of Staff on the subject of hospital ships contained a section referring to the ''Manundra'' incident as a response to the attack on ''Centaur'', with the conclusion that the attack was the work of an irresponsible Japanese commander, and that it would be better to wait until further attacks had been made before considering the removal of hospital ship markings.Milligan and Foley, ''Australian Hospital Ship Centaur'', p. 191

When the consideration was made that the ambulance drivers' weapons incident just prior to Centaur's voyage may have been partially responsible for the attack, it led to the tightening of rules regarding who was allowed to travel on a hospital ship. Some quasi-medical staff, including repatriation teams, were no longer permitted aboard, while ambulance drivers had to transfer from the regular Army to the Australian Army Medical Corps before they were allowed aboard, although they were still permitted to carry their unloaded weapons and ammunition.Goodman, ''Our War Nurses'', p. 197
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="06b642ee18f7c65b3cb757dbe2b8f74f" name="Centaur_poster_Lae_(AWM_017536)" sectnum="4.11#1">../img/06b642ee18f7c65b3cb757dbe2b8f74f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>