<document id="bd390705dd1fc7fc3dd09e31b366d2e5-4" name="Flocke" cat="3">
<text>
In April 2008, the zoo decreased human interaction with the cub, hoping that one day she could coexist with members of her species and not be dependent on humans.  Becoming more independent from her keepers, Flocke was reported often playing happily on her own.  She was given a plastic "dummy", similar to a child's teething ring, tied to the bars on the inside of her stable door to suckle on while resting.  This suckling caused the cub's nose to appear bent; her muzzle remained in this shape for some time before returning to normal.  

 

At the age of six months, it was reported that Flocke, whose diet at the time consisted mostly of a kilogram of beef, assorted vegetables and a liter of puppy milk a day, was at the correct weight for her development at .  The zoo's vet, Bernhard Neurohr, also remarked upon the bear's sweet tooth, stating that "Flocke is very enthusiastic about grapes, melon, kiwi fruit and pears", with a particular fondness for bananas.  

United Nations Environment Program chief Achim Steiner became Flocke's official patron in May 2008.  By assuming this role, Steiner acknowledged Nuremberg Zoo's efforts towards local climate protection, stating "I am happy to have been asked to become 'godfather' to Nuremberg's polar bear cub Flocke. I sincerely hope that during her lifetime we will be able to implement a global green economy."

In June 2008, a new poster campaign featuring Flocke was announced; its goal was strengthening public awareness of individuals' ability to protect Earth's climate. Sponsored by the Nuremberg Zoo in conjunction with the Nuremberg Metropolitan Region, the poster showed Flocke and the phrase "Klimaschutz beginnt vor Ort ("Climate Protection Begins At Home").  The zoo also published a pocket-sized brochure featuring Flocke.  Entitled "Little Guide to Climate Protection", it taught visitors how to decrease their carbon dioxide emissions.  The Nuremberg Zoo announced in September that it had reached its one millionth visitor for 2008&mdash;two months earlier than last year.  Although ticket sales for the year increased due to Flocke's popularity, the numbers did not match high expectations.  The same month it was announced that the cub, now weighing , would no longer have lunchtime breaks in her stable, and would remain in the enclosure throughout the day.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="01bd57de3e95694d8400626ac181ccf9" name="Eisbärin_flocke" sectnum="4#1">../img/01bd57de3e95694d8400626ac181ccf9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>