<document id="bde65360c546ebf6f662041f1584b3ab-3" name="Ann_Bannon" cat="17">
<text>
After ''Beebo Brinker'', Bannon said the energy to write about the characters left her, but she got so good at her "obsessive fantasies" that even after the books were written she continued to live internally, and suspected it affected her subsequent relationships. "I realize now that I was in a sort of 'holding pattern,' a way of keeping my sanity intact while waiting for my children to grow up and the freedom door to open", she recalled.Parks, Joy (Summer, 2003) . "Sleaze Trash and Miracles: How Ann Bannon changed lesbian fiction by writing about the butch of her dreams." ''Velvet Park''; 42-43.''Forbidden Love: Unashamed Stories of Lesbian Lives''. Dir. Fernie, L., Weissman. Videocassette. Women Make Movies Home Video, 1994. Returning to school, Bannon completed her master’s degree at Sacramento State University and her doctorate in linguistics at Stanford University. She was an English professor at Sacramento State and later became the university’s associate dean of the School of Arts and Sciences—later the College of Arts and Letters..

Ann Bannon's books began to fade away from publishing memory after initial publication, especially after Gold Medal Books went out of business. In 1975 however, Bannon was asked to include four of her books in Arno Press' library edition of ''Homosexuality: Lesbians and Gay Men in Society, History and Literature''. Then in 1983, Barbara Grier, of lesbian publishing company Naiad Press actively tracked Bannon down and reissued the books in new covers. Grier discussed the novels, answering the question of who among lesbian paperback authors should be highlighted: "Ann Bannon. Without even a discussion ... In terms of actual influence, sales, everything, Bannon."

Reacting to the renewed interest in the books, Bannon was shocked to find out that her characters were not only remembered but that they were archetypes among the lesbian community. With the books released again, Bannon did not advertise it outwardly in her department at Sacramento State. Not being tenured, she was unsure how the information would be received. However word got out: "I was jet-propelled out of the closet. People stared at me around campus, and the PE majors all waved. My chairman told me to put the books into my promotion file, and one of my colleagues told me my file was the only one that was any fun."Irvine, Janice, et al. (January 14, 1984), "Community Voices." ''Gay Community News''. '''11''' (25) 4. She often received small recognitions from students and faculty who were pleased and surprised, once getting a bouquet of flowers from a student. She said of the rediscovery, "I was so ready for something fresh and exciting in my life. It had seemed to me, up to that point, that not only had the books and the characters died, so had Ann Bannon."

However, following a bitter divorce, and just as the Naiad Press editions of her books were released, Bannon endured a bout with chronic fatigue syndrome, which she connects to repressing herself for so long. "You've got to think that it's connected, somehow. At the time I denied it fiercely, but I really think I beat myself up horribly, in ways I'll never know."

In 1984 Bannon's books were featured in the documentary ''Before Stonewall'' about how gay men and lesbians lived prior to the 1969 Stonewall riots, wherein one woman remembered picking up one of Bannon's books for the first time: "I picked up this paperback and I opened it up...and it sent a shiver of excitement in my whole body that I had never felt before."
''Before Stonewall''. Dir. John Scagliotti. Videocassette. Before Stonewall, Inc. 1984. She was featured in the Canadian documentary ''Forbidden Love: The Unashamed Stories of Lesbian Lives'' in 1992 recounting women's personal stories living as lesbians from the 1940s to 1960s. The books were selected for the Quality Paperback Book Club in 1995. Bannon also provided the foreword text for ''Strange Sisters: The Art of Lesbian Pulp Fiction 1949–1969'' in 1999, discussing her reaction to the art on her own books and the other lesbian pulp fiction books she bought and read. Five of ''The Beebo Brinker Chronicles'' were reissued by Cleis Press again between 2001 and 2003—excluding ''The Marriage''—with autobiographical forewords that described Bannon's experiences of writing the books and her reaction to their popularity, causing another wave of interest.

Bannon's books are frequently on required reading lists for women's and LGBT studies college courses. The person most surprised by this was Bannon herself, who explained she had no such aspirations when she was writing ''Odd Girl Out'': "If I ''had'' known, it might well have resulted in a much more polished product, but one that would have been so cautious and self-conscious as to be entirely forgettable. It would never—my best guess—have had the vibrant life it has now."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ea7b6754df092b91d9b0ad0c6a97d8e1" name="oddgirl2001" sectnum="3#1">../img/ea7b6754df092b91d9b0ad0c6a97d8e1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>