<document id="bde65360c546ebf6f662041f1584b3ab-2.2.2" name="Ann_Bannon" cat="17">
<text>
Bannon followed ''Odd Girl Out'' with ''I Am A Woman (In Love With A Woman Must Society Reject Me?)'' in 1959. ''I Am A Woman'' (the working and common title) featured Laura after her affair with Beth, as she finds herself in New York City's Greenwich Village, and meets a wisecracking gay man named Jack, and becomes his best friend. Laura has to choose between a straight woman with a wild and curious streak, and a fascinating new character that proved to be her most popular of the series, Beebo Brinker, who came to embody the description of a thoroughly butch lesbian. Beebo was smart, handsome, chivalrous, and virile. Once again based on what she knew, Beebo was nearly  tall with a husky voice and a formidable physique. The personality however, Bannon says, was drawn out of her sheer need for Beebo to exist. After spending time in Greenwich Village and not finding anyone like her, Bannon instead created her. She remembered, "I put Beebo together just as I wanted her, in my heart and mind... She was just, quite literally, the butch of my dreams." The resolution to ''I Am A Woman'' completely flouted the trends of miserable lesbian fiction endings, which made Ann Bannon a hero to many lesbians.Strang, Lennox (1959). "I Am a Woman" (book review); ''The Ladder'', '''3''' (5) p. 16–17.

Letters began to pour in for her from all over the country. There were mostly propositions from men, but the letters from women thanked her profusely and begged her for reassurance that they would be all right. Bannon described the impact her books had from the letters she received from people who were isolated in small towns: "The most important things they learned (from the books) were that 1) they weren't unique and doomed to lifelong isolation, 2) ...they weren't "abnormal," and 3) there was hope for a happy life. They wrote to me in thousands, asking me to confirm these wonderful things, which I gladly did—even though I felt only marginally better informed than they were."Dean, William (January 8, 2003). " cleansheets.com. Retrieved on December 2, 2007. The books were even translated into other languages, which was also quite rare for the brief lives of pulp novels.Summers, Claude (2002). "Ann Bannon." ''The gay & lesbian literary heritage: A reader's companion to the writers and their works from antiquity to present''. Routledge. ISBN 0415929261 Bannon received international and domestic mail from women, saying, "This is the only book (and they would say this about all of them) that I've read where the women really love each other, where its OK for them to love each other, and they don't have to kill themselves afterwards."Tilchen, Maida (January 8, 1983). "Ann Bannon: The mystery solved!" ''Gay Community News''. '''10''' (25) 8.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c3fa8897c1091f1b2e8a057bee96ea62" name="I_Am_A_Woman_1959" sectnum="2.2.2#1">../img/c3fa8897c1091f1b2e8a057bee96ea62.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>