<document id="bde65360c546ebf6f662041f1584b3ab-2.2.1" name="Ann_Bannon" cat="17">
<text>
''The Beebo Brinker Chronicle''s were six books in all first published between 1957 and 1962. They featured four characters who appeared in at least three of the books in a chronological saga of coming to terms with their homosexuality and navigating their ways through gay and lesbian relationships. The first in the series, ''Odd Girl Out'', was published by Gold Medal Books in 1957, and became their second best-selling title of the year."Top Sellers of 1957 Reported for Mass-Market and Trade Paperbacks", ''Publishers' Weekly'' (January 20, 1958), '''173''' (3), p. 47–51. Based on Bannon's own experiences, the plot involved a lesbian relationship between two sorority sisters in a fictional sorority at a fictional midwestern university. As was custom with pulp fiction novels, neither the cover art nor the title were under the control of the author. Both were approved by the publisher in order to be as suggestive and lurid as possible. The main character is Laura Landon, who realizes that she's in love with Beth, her older, more experienced roommate, a leader in the sorority.

Lesbians depicted in literature were relatively rare in the 1950s. It was the publisher's policy in any novel involving lesbianism that the characters would never receive any satisfaction from the relationship. One or both usually ended up committing suicide, going insane, or leaving the relationship.Packer, Vin. "Introduction" ''Spring Fire''. Cleis Press, 2004. ISBN 9781573441872 Marijane Meaker discusses this in the 2004 foreword of ''Spring Fire'': she was told by editor Dick Carroll that postal inspectors would send the books back to the publisher if homosexuality was depicted positively. The Postal Service relaxed their censorship after the obscenity trial of Allen Ginsberg's ''Howl'' in 1956, which gave Bannon a modicum of freedom in her plots.Garland, David. Interview with Ann Bannon. ''Spinning on Air.'' WNYC. November 26, 2006. Although the ending to ''Odd Girl Out'' did not veer too far from the unsatisfactory resolution formula of ''Spring Fire'', ''Women's Barracks'', and ''The Well of Loneliness'', it examined Laura's internal struggle in the realization that despite her femininity, she was deeply in love with another woman, and at the end she embraced it, which was rare in lesbian fiction.

The characters and their stories served as an extension of the fantasy life Bannon developed as a child. They became her "fantasy friends" whose loves and lives she witnessed and through which she lived her own life vicariously, helping her through a difficult marriage, and a longing for a life she did not feel she was free to live.Brandt, Kate (2003). "Ann Bannon: A 1950s icon rediscovered." ''Paperback Parade'' '''59''' 39–45. "I realized very early that I should not marry, but I was going to make the best of a bad thing, and I was going to make it a good thing," she remembered.Lootens, Tricia (December 31, 1983). "Ann Bannon: A writer of lost lesbian fiction finds herself and her public." ''Off Our Backs.'' '''13''' (11) p. 12. Having no practical experience in a lesbian relationship while writing ''Odd Girl Out'', she set out to gain what she termed "fieldwork experience" in her trips Greenwich Village, and was successful enough to introduce those experiences into the next book in the series before relocating once more to Southern California. But she explained her fears about staying in Greenwich Village, saying I would sit there (in a gay bar) in the evenings thinking, 'What if (a police raid) happens tonight and I get hauled off to the slam with all these other women?' I had been extremely low profile, very proper, very Victorian wife. I know that sounds crazy in the 60s, but I was raised by my mother and grandmother, who really came out of that era, and talk about a rigid role-playing crowd! I couldn't imagine living through it. I just couldn't. I thought, 'Well, that would do it. I'd have to go jump off the Brooklyn Bridge.' As easy as it might be if you were a young woman in today's generation to think that was exaggerating, it wasn't. It was terrifying.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b247ad8a997bfe325192f1234f3b4e8c" name="Odd_Girl_Out_Cover_1957" sectnum="2.2.1#1">../img/b247ad8a997bfe325192f1234f3b4e8c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>