<document id="bde65360c546ebf6f662041f1584b3ab-1" name="Ann_Bannon" cat="17">
<text>
Ann Bannon was born Ann Weldy in Joliet, Illinois in 1932. She grew up in nearby Hinsdale with her mother and stepfather, and had the responsibility of taking care of four siblings due to the family's financial problems. A rich fantasy life came to be a comfort for her during this time and she found solace in writing. She grew up in a house filled with music, particularly jazz. Her family would host musicians giving small recitals for friends and neighbors, one of which became a character in her books: a perennial bachelor named Jack who slung jokes and witticisms at the audiences. 

She attended the University of Illinois at Champaign-Urbana and belonged to Kappa Kappa Gamma sorority where she befriended a beautiful older sorority sister, "the prettiest I had ever seen", quite popular with men and with women. Bannon witnessed a younger sorority sister's unabashed infatuation with the older sister. She recalls it was an awkward situation, even though the older sorority sister was "unfailingly gracious" to the younger one. In recognizing the younger woman's attractions, she began to suspect her own sexuality. She said, "I saw a lot of it happening and I didn't know what to make of it. I don't even know how to put it—I was absolutely consumed with it, it was an extraordinary thing." Another sorority sister was physically remarkable, very tall—almost , with a husky voice and boyish nickname, that Bannon imagined was a blend of Johnny Weissmuller and Ingrid Bergman. She recalled entering the communal restroom and seeing the sister, "both of us in underwear, and experienc(ing) a sort of electric shock", and trying not to stare at her. In 1954, she graduated with a degree in French and soon  married an engineer whose job made them relocate frequently.Elliott, Mary (2005). "Ann Bannon." ''Encyclopedia of Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender History in America''.

Bannon was 22 years old when she began writing her first pulp novel. She was influenced by the only lesbian novels she had read, ''The Well of Loneliness'' by Radclyffe Hall from 1928 and Vin Packer's ''Spring Fire'' from 1952, albeit in two different ways: she was unable to relate to the dismal tones in Hall's novel,Lovisi, Gary (2003). "On writing Lesbian Pulp Fiction: An interview with Ann Bannon." ''Paperback Parade''. '''59''' 20–39. but as a sorority girl was more familiar with the plot and circumstances of ''Spring Fire''. Bannon said, "Both books completely obsessed me for the better part of two years."Dean, William (2002).  The Erotica Readers and Writers Association. Retrieved on December 2, 2007. Although recently married and on her way to having two children, she found the books struck a chord in her life and recognized emotions in herself that compelled her to write about them. In the beginning of her marriage she was left alone quite a lot and said, "I was kind of desperate to get some of the things that had been consuming me for a long time down on paper".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2cc2873150ada3aa9fb73fad26b464c7" name="Ann_Bannon_in_1955" sectnum="1#1">../img/2cc2873150ada3aa9fb73fad26b464c7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>