<document id="bde76df7923dc199562b87d5972e0643-2.13" name="Chinua_Achebe" cat="17">
<text>
The style of Achebe's fiction draws heavily on the oral tradition of the Igbo people.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 66. He weaves folk tales into the fabric of his stories, illuminating community values in both the content and the form of the storytelling. The tale about the Earth and Sky in ''Things Fall Apart'', for example, emphasises the interdependency of the masculine and the feminine. Although Nwoye enjoys hearing his mother tell the tale, Okonkwo's dislike for it is evidence of his imbalance.Gera, pp 24–25. Later, Nwoye avoids beatings from his father by pretending to dislike such "women's stories".Achebe (1994), p. 54.



Another hallmark of Achebe's style is the use of proverbs, which often illustrate the values of the rural Igbo tradition. He sprinkles them throughout the narratives, repeating points made in conversation.  Critic Anjali Gera notes that the use of proverbs in ''Arrow of God'' "serves to create through an echo effect the judgement of a community upon an individual violation."Gera, p. 32. The use of such repetition in Achebe's urban novels, ''No Longer at Ease'' and ''A Man of the People'', is less pronounced.

For Achebe, however, proverbs and folk stories are not the sum total of the oral Igbo tradition. In combining philosophical thought and public performance into the use of oratory ("Okwu Oka" – "speech artistry" – in the Igbo phrase), his characters exhibit what he called "a matter of individual excellence ... part of Igbo culture."Quoted in Egejuru, p. 394. In ''Things Fall Apart'', Okonkwo's friend Obierika voices the most impassioned oratory, crystallising the events and their significance for the village. Nwaka in ''Arrow of God'' also exhibits a mastery of oratory, albeit for malicious ends.Egejuru, pp 395–396.

Achebe frequently includes folk songs and descriptions of dancing in his work. Obi, the protagonist of ''No Longer At Ease'', is at one point met by women singing a "Song of the Heart", which Achebe gives in both Igbo and English: "Is everyone here? / (Hele ee he ee he)"Quoted in Gera, p. 25. In ''Things Fall Apart'', ceremonial dancing and the singing of folk songs reflect the realities of Igbo tradition. The elderly Uchendu, attempting to shake Okonkwo out of his self-pity, refers to a song sung after the death of a woman: "For whom is it well, for whom is it well? There is no one for whom it is well."Achebe (1994), p. 135. This song contrasts with the "gay and rollicking tunes of evangelism" sung later by the white missionaries.Achebe (1994), p. 146.

Achebe's short stories are not as widely studied as his novels, and Achebe himself does not consider them a major part of his work. In the preface for ''Girls at War and Other Stories'', he writes: "A dozen pieces in twenty years must be accounted a pretty lean harvest by any reckoning."Quoted in Feuser, Willfried F (2001).  ''No Condition Is Permanent: Nigerian Writing and the Struggle for Democracy'' (Holger G. Ehling and Claus-Peter Holste-von Mutius, eds). Amsterdam and New York: Editions Rodopi. p. 65. Like his novels, the short stories are heavily influenced by the oral tradition. And like the folktales they follow, the stories often have morals emphasising the importance of cultural traditions.Ogede, Ode (1 January 2001). "Oral Tradition and Modern Storytelling: Revisiting Chinua Achebe's Short Stories". ''International Fiction Review''. Vol. 28, Issue 1/2. pp 67–77. ISSN 0315-4149.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0d5b55216debc9c27a98aeacb0edcafd" name="Udu" sectnum="2.13#1">../img/0d5b55216debc9c27a98aeacb0edcafd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>