<document id="bde76df7923dc199562b87d5972e0643-1.1.1" name="Chinua_Achebe" cat="17">
<text>
In 1936, Achebe entered St Philips' Central School. Despite his protests, he spent a week in the religious class for young children, but was quickly moved to a higher class when the school's chaplain took note of his intelligence.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 11. One teacher described him as the student with the best handwriting in class, and the best reading skills.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 14. He also attended Sunday school every week and the special evangelical services held monthly, often carrying his father's bag. A controversy erupted at one such session, when apostates from the new church challenged the catechist about the tenets of Christianity. Achebe later included a scene from this incident in ''Things Fall Apart''.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 12.Achebe 1994, pp 146–147.

At the age of twelve, Achebe moved away from his family to the village of Nekede, four kilometres from Owerri. He enrolled as a student at the Central School, where his older brother John taught.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 18. In Nekede, Achebe gained an appreciation for Mbari, a traditional art form which seeks to invoke the gods' protection through symbolic sacrifices in the form of sculpture and collage.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 19. When the time came to  change to secondary school, in 1944, Achebe sat entrance examinations for and was accepted at both the prestigious Dennis Memorial Grammar School in Onitsha and the even more prestigious Government College in Umuahia.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, pp 22–23.

Modelled on the British public school, and funded by the colonial administration, Government College had been established in 1929 to educate Nigeria's future elite. It had rigorous academic standards and was vigorously egalitarian, accepting boys purely on the basis of ability. The language of the school was English, not only to develop proficiency but also to provide a common tongue for pupils from different Nigerian language groups.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 30. Achebe described this later as being ordered to "put away their different mother tongues and communicate in the language of their colonisers".Quoted in Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 30. The rule was strictly enforced and Achebe recalls that his first punishment was for asking another boy to pass the soap in Igbo.

Once there, Achebe was double-promoted in his first year, completing the first two years' studies in one, and spending only four years in secondary school, instead of the standard five.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 25. Achebe was unsuited to the school's sports regimen and belonged instead to a group of six exceedingly studious pupils. So intense were their study habits that the headmaster banned the reading of textbooks from five to six o'clock in the afternoon (though other activities and other books were allowed).Ezenwa-Ohaeto, pp 26–27. 

Achebe started to explore the school's "wonderful library".Quoted in Ezenwa-Ohaeto, pp 26–27. There he discovered Booker T. Washington's ''Up From Slavery'' (1901), the autobiography of an American former slave; Achebe "found it sad, but it showed him another dimension of reality". He also read classic novels, such as  ''Gulliver's Travels'' (1726), ''David Copperfield'' (1850), and ''Treasure Island'' (1883) together with tales of colonial derring-do such as H. Rider Haggard's ''Allan Quatermain'' (1887) and  John Buchan's ''Prester John'' (1910). Achebe later recalled that, as a reader, he "took sides with the white characters against the savages" and even developed a dislike for Africans. "The white man was good and reasonable and intelligent and courageous. The savages arrayed against him were sinister and stupid or, at the most, cunning. I hated their guts."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3db7035e1aa86a761b8f6bfd77b350d4" name="Ibadan_street_scene" sectnum="1.1.1#1">../img/3db7035e1aa86a761b8f6bfd77b350d4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>