<document id="bde76df7923dc199562b87d5972e0643-1.3" name="Chinua_Achebe" cat="17">
<text>
Back in Nigeria, Achebe set to work revising and editing his novel (now titled ''Things Fall Apart'', after a line in the poem "The Second Coming" by William Butler Yeats). He cut away the second and third sections of the book, leaving only the story of a yam farmer named Okonkwo. He added sections, improved various chapters, and restructured the prose. By 1957, he had sculpted it to his liking, and took advantage of an advertisement offering a typing service. He sent his only copy of his handwritten manuscript (along with the ₤22 fee) to the London company. After he waited several months without receiving any communication from the typing service, Achebe began to worry. His boss at the NBS, Angela Beattie, was going to London for her annual leave; he asked her to visit the company. She did, and angrily demanded to know why it was lying ignored in the corner of the office. The company quickly sent a typed copy to Achebe. Beattie's intervention was crucial for his ability to continue as a writer. Had the novel been lost, he later said, "I would have been so discouraged that I would probably have given up altogether."Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 63.



In 1958, Achebe sent his novel to the agent recommended by Gilbert Phelps in London. It was sent to several publishing houses; some rejected it immediately, claiming that fiction from African writers had no market potential.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 65. Finally it reached the office of Heinemann, where executives hesitated until an educational adviser, Donald MacRae – just back in England after a trip through west Africa – read the book and forced the company's hand with his succinct report: "This is the best novel I have read since the war".Hill, Alan (1991). Quoted in Petersen, reprinted in Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 65.

Heinemann published 2,000 hardcover copies of ''Things Fall Apart'' on 17 June 1958. According to Alan Hill, employed by the publisher at the time, the company did not "touch a word of it" in preparation for release.Quoted in Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 65. The book was received well by the British press, and received positive reviews from critic Walter Allen and novelist Angus Wilson. Three days after publication, the ''Times Literary Supplement'' wrote that the book "genuinely succeeds in presenting tribal life from the inside". ''The Observer'' called it "an excellent novel", and the literary magazine ''Time and Tide'' said that "Mr. Achebe's style is a model for aspirants".Quoted in Ezenwa-Ohaeto, pp 65–66.

Initial reception in Nigeria was mixed. When Hill tried to promote the book in West Africa, he was met with scepticism and ridicule. The faculty at the University of Ibadan was amused at the thought of a worthwhile novel being written by an alumnus.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 68. Others were more supportive; one review in the magazine ''Black Orpheus'' said: "The book as a whole creates for the reader such a vivid picture of Ibo life that the plot and characters are little more than symbols representing a way of life lost irrevocably within living memory."Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 69.

In the book Okonkwo struggles with the legacy of his father – a shiftless debtor fond of playing the flute – as well as the complications and contradictions that arise when white missionaries arrive in his village of Umuofia.Achebe 1994, p. 4. Exploring the terrain of cultural conflict, particularly the encounter between Igbo tradition and Christian doctrine, Achebe returns to the themes of his earlier stories, which grew from his own background.

''Things Fall Apart'' has become one of the most important books in African literature.Booker, p. xvii. Selling over 8 million copies around the world, it has been translated into 50 languages, making Achebe the most translated African writer of all time.Yousaf, p. 34.Ogbaa, p. 5.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d915c5766eda43d4b99c06ee0c312232" name="Things_Fall_Apart_books_02" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/d915c5766eda43d4b99c06ee0c312232.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>