<document id="bde76df7923dc199562b87d5972e0643-1.2" name="Chinua_Achebe" cat="17">
<text>
While he meditated on his possible career paths, Achebe was visited by a friend from the university, who convinced him to apply for an English teaching position at the Merchants of Light school at Oba. It was a ramshackle institution with a crumbling infrastructure and a meagre library; the school was built on what the residents called "bad bush" – a section of land thought to be tainted by unfriendly spirits.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 53. Later, in ''Things Fall Apart'', Achebe describes a similar area called the "evil forest", where the Christian missionaries are given a place to build their church.Achebe (1994). The "evil forest" is a place where twins (considered an abomination by the community) are thrown away to die. When the Christian missionaries persevere despite their location, they are able to convince some in the community that the superstition is unwarranted.

As a teacher he urged his students to read extensively and be original in their work.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 55. The students did not have access to the newspapers he had read as a student, so Achebe made his own available in the classroom.  He taught in Oba for four months, but when an opportunity arose in 1954 to work for the Nigerian Broadcasting Service (NBS), he left the school and moved to Lagos.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 56.



The NBS, a radio network started in 1933 by the colonial government,Federal Radio Corporation of Nigeria. . Online at . Retrieved on 15 October 2007. assigned Achebe to the Talks Department, preparing scripts for oral delivery. This helped him master the subtle nuances between written and spoken language, a skill that helped him later to write realistic dialogue.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 57. 

The city of Lagos also made a significant impression on him. A huge conurbation, the city teemed with recent migrants from the rural villages. Achebe revelled in the social and political activity around him and later drew upon his experiences when describing the city in his 1960 novel ''No Longer At Ease''.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 58.

While in Lagos, Achebe started work on a novel.  This was challenging, since very little African fiction had been written in English, although Amos Tutuola's ''Palm-Wine Drinkard'' (1952) and Cyprian Ekwensi's ''People of the City'' (1954) were notable exceptions.  While appreciating Ekwensi's work, Achebe worked hard to develop his own style, even as he pioneered the creation of the Nigerian novel itself.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 62. A visit to Nigeria by Queen Elizabeth II in 1956 brought issues of colonialism and politics to the surface, and was a significant moment for Achebe.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 60.

Also in 1956, Achebe was selected for training in London at the Staff School run by the British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC). His first trip outside Nigeria was an opportunity to advance his technical production skills, and to solicit feedback on his novel (which was later split into two books). In London, he met a novelist named Gilbert Phelps, to whom he offered the manuscript. Phelps responded with great enthusiasm, asking Achebe if he could show it to his editor and publishers. Achebe declined, insisting that it needed more work.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a8a20d1b20e56d08cdeecd2ed7b3c6a7" name="Lagos_Island" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/a8a20d1b20e56d08cdeecd2ed7b3c6a7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>