<document id="bde76df7923dc199562b87d5972e0643-1.12" name="Chinua_Achebe" cat="17">
<text>
In 1987 Achebe released his fifth novel, ''Anthills of the Savannah'', about a military coup in the fictional West African nation of Kangan. A finalist for the Man Booker Prize, the novel was hailed in the ''Financial Times'': "in a powerful fusion of myth, legend and modern styles, Achebe has written a book which is wise, exciting and essential, a powerful antidote to the cynical commentators from 'overseas' who see nothing ever new out of Africa."Quoted in Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 253. An opinion piece in the magazine ''West Africa'' said the book deserved to win the Booker Prize, and that Achebe was "a writer who has long deserved the recognition that has already been accorded him by his sales figures." The prize went instead to Penelope Lively's novel ''Moon Tiger''.



On 22 March 1990, Achebe was riding in a car to Lagos when an axle collapsed and the car flipped. His son Ikechukwu and the driver suffered minor injuries, but the weight of the vehicle fell on Achebe and his spine was severely damaged. He was flown to the Paddocks Hospital in Buckinghamshire, England, and treated for his injuries. In July doctors announced that although he was recuperating well, he was paralysed from the waist down and would require the use of a wheelchair for the rest of his life.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, pp 278–279.

Soon afterwards, Achebe became the Charles P. Stevenson Professor of Languages and Literature at Bard College in Annandale-on-Hudson, New York; he has held the position for over fifteen years.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 280. In the Fall of 2009 he joined the Brown University faculty as the David and Marianna Fisher University Professor of Africana Studies.

In October 2005, the London ''Financial Times'' reported that Achebe was planning to write a novella for the Canongate Myth Series, a series of short novels in which ancient myths from myriad cultures are reimagined and rewritten by contemporary authors.Gurria-Quintana, Angel.  , Financial Times, 2005-10-28.  Retrieved on 2007-11-07.  Achebe's novella has not yet been scheduled for publication.

In June 2007, Achebe was awarded the Man Booker International Prize. (13 June 2007). BBC News Online. Retrieved on 23 September 2007. The judging panel included US critic Elaine Showalter, who said he "illuminated the path for writers around the world seeking new words and forms for new realities and societies";The Booker Prize Foundation (13 June 2007). . Online at . Retrieved on 11 October 2007. and South African writer Nadine Gordimer, who said Achebe has achieved "what one of his characters brilliantly defines as the writer’s purpose: 'a new-found utterance' for the capture of life’s complexity".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8677c1852a2312cae66aad8d433be0c2" name="Bard_stonerow_2007" sectnum="1.12#1">../img/8677c1852a2312cae66aad8d433be0c2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>