<document id="bde76df7923dc199562b87d5972e0643-1.6" name="Chinua_Achebe" cat="17">
<text>
Once he returned to Nigeria, Achebe was promoted at the NBS to the position of Director of External Broadcasting. One of his first duties was to help create the Voice of Nigeria network. The station broadcast its first transmission on New Year's Day 1962, and worked to maintain an objective perspective during the turbulent era immediately following independence.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, pp 87–88. This objectivity was put to the test when Nigerian Prime Minister Abubakar Tafawa Balewa declared a state of emergency in the Western Region, responding to a series of conflicts between officials of varying parties. Achebe became saddened by the evidence of corruption and silencing of political opposition.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 89.

In 1962 he attended a conference of African writers in English at the Makerere University College in Kampala, Uganda. He met with important literary figures from around the continent and the world, including Ghanaian poet Kofi Awoonor, Nigerian playwright and poet Wole Soyinka, and US poet-author Langston Hughes. Among the topics of discussion was an attempt to determine whether the term African literature ought to include work from the diaspora, or solely that writing composed by people living within the continent itself.  Achebe indicated that it was not "a very significant question",Quoted in Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 89. and that scholars would do well to wait until a body of work were large enough to judge.  Writing about the conference in several journals, Achebe hailed it as a milestone for the literature of Africa, and highlighted the importance of community among isolated voices on the continent and beyond.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, pp 89–90.



While at Makerere, Achebe was asked to read a novel written by a student (James Ngugi, later known as Ngugi wa Thiong'o) called ''Weep Not, Child''. Impressed, he sent it to Alan Hill at Heinemann, which published it two years later to coincide with its paperback line of books from African writers.  Hill indicated this was to remedy a situation where British publishers "regarded West Africa only as a place where you sold books."  Achebe was chosen to be General Editor of the African Writers Series, which became a significant force in bringing postcolonial literature from Africa to the rest of the world.Ezenwa-Ohaeto, pp 90–92.

As these works became more widely available, reviews and essays about African literature – especially from Europe – began to flourish. Bristling against the commentary flooding his home country, Achebe published an essay titled "Where Angels Fear to Tread" in the December 1962 issue of ''Nigeria Magazine''. In it, he distinguished between the hostile critic (entirely negative), the amazed critic (entirely positive), and the conscious critic (who seeks a balance). He lashed out at those who critiqued African writers from the outside, saying: "no man can understand another whose language he does not speak (and 'language' here does not mean simply words, but a man's entire world view)."Ezenwa-Ohaeto, p. 94.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="59d1b54b7b91dab3dbfa1e0cf417812a" name="Ngugi" sectnum="1.6#1">../img/59d1b54b7b91dab3dbfa1e0cf417812a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>