<document id="bdfc630666ac36a1b1ce38309983332d-3" name="Amanita_phalloides" cat="3">
<text>
The death cap is native to Europe, where it is widespread. It is found from the southern coastal regions of Scandinavia in the north, to Ireland in the west, east to Poland and western Russia, and south throughout the Balkans, in Italy, Spain and Portugal, and in Morocco and Algeria in north Africa. There are records from further east into Asia but these have yet to be confirmed as ''A. phalloides''.

It is ectomycorrhizally associated with a number of tree species, and are symbiotic to them. In Europe, these include a large number of hardwood and, less frequently, conifer species. It appears most commonly under oaks but also under beeches, chestnuts, horse-chestnuts, birches, filberts, hornbeams, pines, and spruces. In other areas, ''A. phalloides'' may also be associated with these trees or only with some species but not others. In coastal California, for example, ''A. phalloides'' is associated with coast live oak but not with the various coastal pine species, such as Monterey pine. In countries where it has been introduced it has been restricted to those exotic trees it would associate with in its natural range. There is, however, evidence of ''A. phalloides'' associating with hemlock and with genera of the Myrtaceae: ''Eucalyptus'' in Tanzania and Algeria, and ''Leptospermum'' and ''Kunzea'' in New Zealand. This suggests the species may have invasive potential.

By the end of the 19th century, Charles Horton Peck had reported ''A. phalloides'' in North America. However, in 1918, samples from the Eastern United States were identified as being a distinct though similar species, ''A. brunnescens'', by G. F. Atkinson of Cornell University. By the 1970s it had become clear that ''A. phalloides'' actually does occur in the United States, apparently having been introduced from Europe alongside chestnuts, with populations on the West and East Coasts.Benjamin.p204 A more recent historical review concluded that the East Coast populations were introduced but that the origins of the West Coast population remain unclear, owing to the scantness of historical records.

''Amanita phalloides'' has been conveyed to new countries across the southern hemisphere with the importation of hardwoods and conifers. Introduced oaks appear to have been the vector to Australia and South America; populations under oaks have been recorded from Melbourne and Canberra, as well as Uruguay. It has been recorded under other introduced trees in Argentina and Chile.
Pine plantations are associated with the fungus in Tanzania and South Africa, where it is also found under oaks and poplars.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="873dd0632b82eaf662d90363be5fe3e8" name="Amanita_phalloïdes" sectnum="3#1">../img/873dd0632b82eaf662d90363be5fe3e8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>