<document id="be53e183767d5ab750b0eb37f72280a3-3" name="Frank_Hubert_McNamara" cat="29">
<text>
Following the disbandment of the AFC, McNamara transferred to the Australian Air Corps in April 1920. He was invested with his Victoria Cross by the Prince of Wales at Government House, Melbourne, on 26 May. McNamara enlisted in the newly established Royal Australian Air Force in 1921. Ranked Flying Officer (honorary Flight Lieutenant), he was one of the original twenty-one officers on the Air Force's strength at its formation that March.Gillison,  Initially posted to RAAF Headquarters in Melbourne as Staff Officer Operations and Intelligence, McNamara was given command of No. 1 Flying Training School (1FTS) at Point Cook in July 1922. He was promoted Squadron Leader in March 1924 and the following month married Hélène Bluntschli, a Belgian national he had met in Cairo during the war, at St Patrick's Cathedral; his best man was fellow officer Frank Lukis.Coulthard-Clark, ''A Hero's Dilemma'', p.68 

McNamara travelled to England in 1925 for two years exchange with the Royal Air Force, serving at No. 5 Flying Training School, RAF Sealand, and the Directorate of Training at the Air Ministry, London.Gillison,  Returning to Australia in November 1927, he was appointed Second-in-Command 1FTS. In 1928, McNamara resumed his studies at the University of Melbourne, having earlier failed to pass the necessary exams to enter the RAF Staff College, Andover. A part-time student, he graduated with a Bachelor of Arts in International Relations (second-class honours) in 1933. McNamara was made Commanding Officer of 1FTS in October 1930, and promoted to Wing Commander one year later. at Australian War Memorial. Retrieved on 14 January 2009. He was put in charge of RAAF Station Laverton, Victoria, including No. 1 Aircraft Depot, in February 1933. McNamara was raised to Group Captain in 1936, and attended the Imperial Defence College, London, the following year. He was appointed a Commander of the Order of the British Empire (CBE) in the 1938 New Year Honours.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ebd8a366b874a8572c6cbcb7bee0c1ff" name="DAAV00225AMcNamara" sectnum="3#1">../img/ebd8a366b874a8572c6cbcb7bee0c1ff.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>