<document id="be53e183767d5ab750b0eb37f72280a3-2.2" name="Frank_Hubert_McNamara" cat="29">
<text>
On 20 March 1917, McNamara, flying a Martinsyde, was one of four No. 1 Squadron pilots taking part in a raid against a Turkish railway junction near Gaza. Owing to a shortage of bombs, the aircraft were each armed with six specially-modified 4.5-inch howitzer shells.Wilson, ''The Brotherhood of Airmen'', pp.11&ndash;13 McNamara had successfully dropped three of his shells when the fourth exploded prematurely, badly wounded him in the leg with shrapnel, an effect he likened to being "hit with a sledgehammer". Having turned to head back to base, he spotted a fellow squadron member from the same mission, Captain David Rutherford, on the ground beside his crashlanded B.E.2.Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp.14&ndash;15 Allied airmen had been hacked to death by enemy troops in similar situations, and McNamara saw that a company of Turkish cavalry was fast approaching Rutherford's position. Despite the rough terrain and the gash in his leg, McNamara landed near Rutherford in an attempt to rescue him. As there was no spare cockpit in the single-seat Martinsyde, the downed pilot jumped on to McNamara's wing and held the struts. McNamara crashed while attempting to take off, however, due to the effects of his leg wound and Rutherford's weight overbalancing the aircraft. The two men, who had escaped further injury in the accident, set fire to the Martinsyde and dashed back to Rutherford's two-seat B.E.2. Rutherford repaired the engine while McNamara used his revolver against the attacking cavalry, who had opened fire on them. Two other No. 1 Squadron pilots overhead, Lieutenant (later Air Marshal Sir) Roy "Peter" Drummond and Lieutenant Alfred Ellis, also began strafing the enemy troops. McNamara managed to start the B.E.2's engine and take off, with Rutherford in the observer's cockpit. In severe pain and close to blacking out from loss of blood, McNamara flew the damaged aircraft  back to base at El Arish.Cutlack, 

alt=Three men in hospital pyjamas sitting with female nurse
Having effected what was described in the Australian official history of the war as "a brilliant escape in the very nick of time and under hot fire", McNamara "could only emit exhausted expletives" before he lost consciousness shortly after landing. Evacuated to hospital, he almost died following an allergic reaction to a routine tetanus injection. McNamara had to be given artificial respiration and stimulants to keep him alive, but recovered quickly. A contemporary news report declared that he was "soon sitting up, eating chicken and drinking champagne". On 26 March, McNamara was recommended for the Victoria Cross by Brigadier General Geoffrey Salmond, General Officer Commanding the Middle East Brigade, RFC. at Australian War Memorial. Retrieved on 31 January 2009. Drummond, at Australian War Memorial. Retrieved on 31 January 2009. Ellis, at Australian War Memorial. Retrieved on 31 January 2009. and Rutherford all wrote statements on 3&ndash;4 April attesting to their comrade's actions, Rutherford declaring that "the risk of Lieut. MacNamara being killed or captured was so great that even had he not been wounded he would have been justified in not attempting my rescue &ndash; the fact of his already being wounded makes his action one of outstanding gallantry &ndash; his determination and resource and utter disregard of danger throughout the operation was worthy of the highest praise". at Australian War Memorial. Retrieved on 31 January 2009. The first and only VC won by an Australian airman in World War I, McNamara's award was gazetted on 8 June 1917: 



Promoted to Captain on 10 April 1917, McNamara became a flight commander in No. 4 Squadron AFC (also known until 1918 as No. 71 Squadron RFC), but was unable to continue flying due to the leg wound he suffered on 20 March.  He was invalided back to Australia in August aboard HT ''Boorara'', and given a hero's welcome on arrival in Melbourne.Macklin, ''Bravest'', pp.94&ndash;99 Found to be medically unfit for active service, McNamara was discharged from the Australian Flying Corps on 31 January 1918. However, panic caused by the intrusion into Australian waters of the German raider ''Wolf'' resulted in him being recalled to the AFC and put in charge of an aerial reconnaissance unit based in South Gippsland, Victoria, flying an F.E.2B and later a Maurice Farman Shorthorn.Coulthard-Clark, ''A Hero's Dilemma'', pp.54&ndash;55  In September 1918, he was posted as a flying instructor to Point Cook, where he saw out the remainder of the war.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="dde7c30f14370e080efaaf5b8bb3c8ba" name="A05340WilliamsMcNamara" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/dde7c30f14370e080efaaf5b8bb3c8ba.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>