<document id="be681b3fd0491dedf33c64e9a71c7517-4.4" name="Tomb_of_Antipope_John_XXIII" cat="1">
<text>
Above the Virtues, four classical consoles decorated with acanthus leaves support the sarcophagus. In the tripartite space between the consoles—from left to right—are Cossa’s family arms with the papal tiara, the papal coat of arms, and Cossa’s family arms with the cardinal’s hat.Lightbown, 1980, p. 27. The ''rilievo schiacciato'' (a type of very shallow bas-relief pioneered by Donatello) on the architrave sarcophagus ( wide and  high) depicts two putti or spiratelli ("little spirits") holding open  a large inscribed parchment, perhaps in the style of a papal brief.Lightbown, 1980, p. 28. The putti (or spiratelli) share many characteristics with their ancient counterparts, except for their crossed legs.Caplow, 1977, p. 135.


The inscription reads:




Which translates to:

John the former pope
XXIII. Died in Florence
A.D. 1419, on 11th
day before the Calends of January



Pope Martin V objected to a portion of the inscription—""—because he thought it implied Cossa had died as pope (the Latin "" could mean either "the former" or the "the late"). The use of "olim Papa", as was common in many contemporary documents, instead of "quondam Papa" would probably have removed Martin V’s objections. Martin himself suggested instead that Cossa be identified as a Neapolitan cardinal, thus emphasizing instead his submission.Caplow, 1977, p. 105; McHam, 1989, p. 149. Contemporary sources report that the Signoria mimicked the reply of Pontius Pilate regarding the inscription on the cross of Christ: "What is written, is written."McHam, 1989, p. 159. Martin V himself was buried underneath an undecorated bronze floor slab,McHam, 1989, p. 161. the only known example of a two-dimensional papal monument,Panofsky, 1964, p. 72. although also the first to be set in the central nave of a major basilica, the Basilica of St. John Lateran in Rome,Gardner, 1992, p. 62; Lightbown, 1980, p. 25. and cast in bronze—probably also by Donatello.Meyer, 1904, p. 76; Lightbown, 1980, p. 46.

According to Avery, Donatello’s ''Ascension of Christ and the Giving of the Keys to St. Peter'' may have been intended to share the front of the sarcophagus,Avery, 1994, pp. 36–39. further strengthening the papal associations, which were created by dating Cossa’s death using the ancient Roman Calends of January, which was uncommon on Florentine tombs, but was used in papal ones.McHam, 1989, pp. 163–4.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b413ded78b02cdb4d441f20d80220097" name="Marzocco_di_donatello" sectnum="4.4#1">../img/b413ded78b02cdb4d441f20d80220097.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>