<document id="be681b3fd0491dedf33c64e9a71c7517-5" name="Tomb_of_Antipope_John_XXIII" cat="1">
<text>
The tomb monument was the first collaboration between Donatello (1386–1466) and Michelozzo (1391–1472), who went on to collaborate on the tomb of Cardinal Rainaldo Brancacci in the Church of Sant’ Angelo a Nido in Naples, the tomb of Papal Secretary Bartolommeo Aragazzi in what is now the Duomo of Montepulciano, and the external pulpit of the Duomo of Prato.Lightbown, 1980, pp. 2–3. At the time of their partnership, Donatello was already well-known for his statues of prophets and saints for the Duomo and Orsanmichele, while Michelozzo was more obscure.Lightbown, 1980, p. 1.  Both had worked for a time for Ghiberti, whose  workshop then lead Florentine sculpture.

Nearly every element of the tomb monument has been attributed to both Donatello and Michelozzo by different art historians.Caplow, 1977, pp. 122–140; Janson, 1963, pp. 63–64; Lightbown, 1980, p. 18. These characterizations are mostly of historiographical interest: attribution to Donatello is more of an indication of what is valued by each commentator than any objective criteria; often, aspects are attributed to Michelozzo explicitly because they are "less well executed".

Descriptions from 1475 to 1568 attribute all of the tomb except for the figure of Faith to Donatello.Caplow, 1977, p. 119. Some modern sources reverse this dichotomy, attributing all of the tomb to Michelozzo with the exception of the gilded bronze effigy. Some sources credit Donatello only with the bronze effigy.Grassi, 1964, p. 69. According to Janson, of the marble work, only the ''putti'' can be attributed to "Donatello’s own hand". Donatello’s alleged deficiencies in casting or in architecture have been proposed as the reason for his partnership with Michelozzo,Janson, 1963, pp. 50–56, 63. in addition to his busy schedule.Lightbown, 1980, p. 33.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="96878905b95acec060b1fc0a18db8eae" name="Prato,_duomo_pulpito_di_donatello_e_michelozzo" sectnum="5#1">../img/96878905b95acec060b1fc0a18db8eae.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>