<document id="bee267762b4476dca6f3a077f7d140c6-2.3" name="Nagorno-Karabakh_War" cat="29">
<text>
Ethnic infighting soon broke out between Armenians and Azerbaijanis living in Karabakh. On February 22, 1988, a direct confrontation between Azerbaijanis and Armenians, near the town of Askeran (located on the road between Stepanakert and Agdam) in Nagorno-Karabakh, degenerated into a skirmish. During the clashes two Azerbaijani youths were killed. One of them was probably shot by a local policeman, purportedly an Azerbaijani, either by accident or as a result of a quarrel{ru icon}} . Memorial. On February 27, 1988, while speaking on Baku's central television, the Soviet Deputy Procurator Alexander Katusev mentioned the nationality of those killed.    
    
The Askeran clash was the prelude to pogroms in Sumgait, where emotions, already heightened by news about the Karabakh crisis, turned even uglier in a series of protests starting February 27, 1988. Speaking at the rallies, Azerbaijani refugees from the Armenian town of Ghapan accused Armenians of "murder and atrocities including raping women and cutting their breasts off"; these allegations were later disproved and many of the speakers were revealed to be agents provocateurs. Kulish, O. and Melikov, D. ''Социалистическая индустрия'' (Socialist Industry). March 27, 1988. Retrieved March 30, 2008 Within hours, a pogrom against Armenian residents began in Sumgait, a city some 25 kilometers north of Baku, where some 2,000 Azerbaijani refugees from Armenia were settled. The pogroms resulted in the deaths of 32 people, according to official Soviet statistics, although many Armenians feel that the figure was understated by the Soviet media, as nearly all of Sumgait's Armenian population left the city after the pogrom. Armenians were beaten, raped and killed both on the streets of Sumgait and inside their apartments in three days of violence that only subsided when Soviet armed forces entered the city and quelled much of the rioting on March 1.   
    
The manner in which many Armenians were killed reverberated amongst Armenians elsewhere who felt the pogrom was backed by government officials to intimidate those involved in the Karabakh movement. Violence slowly began to escalate after Sumgait as Gorbachev finally decided to send Soviet Interior troops to Armenia in September 1988. By October 1989, over 100 people were estimated to have been killed since the revived idea of unification with Karabakh in February 1988. The issue had been temporarily resolved when on December 7,   
1988, a devastating earthquake hit Armenia, leveling the towns of Leninakan (now Gyumri) and Spitak and killing an estimated 25,000 people.   
    
Gorbachev's attempts to stabilize the region were to no avail, as both sides were equally intransigent. Armenians refused to allow the issue to subside despite concessions made by Gorbachev, including a promise of a 400 million-ruble package to introduce Armenian language textbooks and television programming in Karabakh. At the same time, Azerbaijan was unwilling to cede any territory to Armenia. Furthermore, the newly formed Karabakh Committee, which comprised eleven members including the future president of Armenia Levon Ter-Petrossian, were jailed by Moscow officials in the ensuing chaos after the earthquake. Such actions polarized relations between Armenia and the Kremlin; Armenians lost faith in Gorbachev, despising him even more because of his mishandling of the earthquake aftermath and his uncompromising stance on Nagorno-Karabakh.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e60bd7f17830e38fbd2c16f96d97d628" name="Sumgaitrioting" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/e60bd7f17830e38fbd2c16f96d97d628.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>