<document id="bee267762b4476dca6f3a077f7d140c6-10" name="Nagorno-Karabakh_War" cat="29">
<text>
In early 2008, tensions between Armenia, the NKR Karabakh and Azerbaijan took a turn for the worse. On the diplomatic front, President Ilham Aliyev once again repeated increasingly bellicose statements that Azerbaijan would resort to force, if necessary, to take the territories back;Yevgrashina, Lada. "", Reuters. March 4, 2008. Retrieved March 10, 2008. concurrently, shooting incidents along the line of contact increased. The most significant breach of the ceasefire occurred on March 5, 2008, when up to sixteen soldiers were killed. Both sides accused the other of starting the battle.Yevgrashina, Lada and Hasmik Mkrtchyan. "", Reuters. March 5, 2008. Retrieved March 10, 2008. Moreover, the usage of artillery in the recent skirmishes marks a significant departure from previous clashes, which usually involved only sniper or machine gun fire.The Associated Press. "", International Herald Tribune. March 10, 2008. Retrieved March 10, 2008.

In 2008, Moscow Defense Brief opined that because of the rapid growth of Azeri defense expenditures  which is driving the strong rearmament of the Azeri armed forces  the military balance appeared to be now shifting in Azerbaijan's favour: "... The overall trend is clearly in Azerbaijan’s favor, and it seems that Armenia will not be able to sustain an arms race with Azerbaijan’s oil-fueled economy. And this could lead to the destabilization of the frozen conflict between these two states," the journal wrote. Other analysts have made more cautious observations, noting that administrative and military deficiencies are still found in the Azerbaijani military and  have stressed that the Nagorno-Karabakh Defense Army is in a "constant state of readiness, undergoing more serious combat training and operational exercises than any other former Soviet army."Giragosian, Richard. "Armenia and Karabakh: One Nation, Two States." ''AGBU Magazine''. Vol. 19, № 1, May 2009, pp. 12-13.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ca269d065e54962b1f00ef529dad3e39" name="Vaikmemorialfountain" sectnum="10#1">../img/ca269d065e54962b1f00ef529dad3e39.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>