<document id="bfabf896c8b5778f10bad2cf75c93527-2.1" name="SummerSlam_(2003)" cat="26">
<text>
After ''Sunday Night Heat'', the pay-per-view event began with a tag team match for the World Tag Team Championship, where the champions, La Résistance (René Duprée and Sylvain Grenier), defended their titles against The Dudley Boyz (Bubba Ray and D-Von). Throughout the match, both teams performed many offensive maneuvers, though The Dudley Boyz were able to gain the upper hand when they executed a flapjack and cutter combination on Duprée. As D-Von covered Duprée, Rob Conway was disguised as a cameraman and hit D-Von with a camera while the referee was distracted. Duprée then covered D-Von for a successful pinfall, in the process retaining the World Tag Team Championship for his team.



The following bout was The Undertaker versus A-Train in a standard match. In the early stages both competitors wrestled inconclusively before The Undertaker gained the advantage. He attempted to lift A-Train upside down and kneel to drop his head to the mat. A-Train countered the maneuver, in the process knocking the referee down. He attempted to take advantage of the situation by trying to hit The Undertaker with a folding chair. The Undertaker, however, countered the offensive attack by hitting the chair with his boot, resulting in the chair hitting A-Train in the face. The Undertaker then lifted A-Train by the throat and slammed him to the mat. This was followed by the referee recuperating and officiating a cover by Undertaker on A-Train for the pinfall.

The third contest had Shane McMahon against Eric Bischoff in a standard match. McMahon and Bischoff began by brawling on the arena ramp, as Jonathan Coachman appeared from the backstage area and hit McMahon with a folding chair. Bischoff grabbed a microphone and announced that the match would be contested under no disqualification, falls count anywhere regulations, where match outcomes could occur anywhere in the arena; as a result, Bischoff could not be disqualified for Coachman's interference. Coachman and Bischoff followed up on the announcement by performing double-team offensive attacks on McMahon. Steve Austin then interfered by performing a stunner on Coachman and then on Bischoff, executed by Austin grabbing their heads and forcefully pulling them down over his shoulders. After Austin's interference, McMahon positioned Bischoff on the television commentators' table and dove with his elbow cocked onto Bischoff's chest, in the process breaking the table. McMahon followed up by covering Bischoff for the pinfall.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1c0b20bd6657330e8a29f2f5cf67f2cd" name="Team3dlockdown" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/1c0b20bd6657330e8a29f2f5cf67f2cd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>