<document id="bfabf896c8b5778f10bad2cf75c93527-3" name="SummerSlam_(2003)" cat="26">
<text>
During an episode of ''Raw'' after SummerSlam, Goldberg challenged Triple H for the World Heavyweight Championship. This bout took place at the Unforgiven pay-per-view on September 21, 2003 with a stipulation that, should he lose, Goldberg would retire from WWE. However, Goldberg defeated Triple H to become the new champion. The rivalry between Kurt Angle and Brock Lesnar halted, as Angle began a staged rivalry with The Undertaker over the WWE Championship. A bout between Angle and The Undertaker took place during an episode of ''SmackDown!'' on September 4, 2003. Neither wrestler won, as Lesnar attacked both wrestlers with a folding chair.  As a result of the attack, Angle and Lesnar fought in a Iron man match (a match in which the wrestler with the most falls in a set period of time would win). Lesnar won five falls during the match, while Angle won four, and as a result Lesnar won the title.

The staged rivalry between Kane and Rob Van Dam also stopped, as Kane engaged in a feud against Shane McMahon. In a scenario on the August 25, 2003 episode of ''Raw'', Kane attempted to throw McMahon into a dumpster that was set on fire, but McMahon avoided it and threw Kane into the dumpster. On September 8, 2003 during an episode of ''Raw'', Eric Bischoff announced a match between Kane and McMahon at Unforgiven, in which the wrestler who was unable to respond to a ten count by the referee would lose. Kane defeated McMahon at Unforgiven after McMahon was unable to respond to a ten count. After SummerSlam, Eddie Guerrero began a staged rivalry with John Cena over the WWE United States Championship. Guerrero retained the title in two championship defenses that took place on ''SmackDown!''. Guerrero then engaged in a feud with The Big Show. At No Mercy, Big Show defeated Guerrero via pinfall to win the WWE United States Championship.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c27e0eabdbff6c53fe5c1d02e6a8f258" name="Bill_goldberg" sectnum="3#1">../img/c27e0eabdbff6c53fe5c1d02e6a8f258.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>