<document id="c0008d92a65249fa11a7bf1e8e758b85-2.4.12" name="Greece_runestones" cat="1">
<text>
Runestone U 518 () is in the RAK style and is raised on the southern side of a piny slope some  north-east of the main building of the homestead Västra Ledinge. The stone was made known by Richard Dybeck in several publications in the 1860s, and at the time it had recently been destroyed and was in several pieces of which the bottom part was still in the ground. In 1942, the stone was mended and raised anew at the original spot. The stone consists of grey and coarse granite.Wessén & Jansson 1943–1946:376 

The runestone was made in memory of three men, of whom two died in Greece, while a third one, Freygeirr, died at a debated location written as '''i silu × nur'''. Richard Dybeck suggested that it might either refer to the nearby estate of Skällnora or lake Siljan, and Sophus Bugge identified the location as "Saaremaa north" (''Øysilu nor''), whereas Erik Brate considered the location to have been Salo in present-day Finland.Wessén & Jansson 1943–1946:378 The contemporary view, as presented in Rundata, derives from a more recent analysis by Otterbjörk (1961) who consider it to refer to a sound at the island Selaön in Mälaren.

Latin transliteration:

: '''þurkir × uk × suin × þu litu × risa × stin × þina × iftiR × urmiR × uk × urmulf × uk × frikiR × on × etaþis × i silu × nur × ian þiR antriR × ut i × krikum × kuþ ihlbi --R(a) ot × uk salu'''

Old Norse transcription:

: ''Þorgærðr ok Svæinn þau letu ræisa stæin þenna æftiR OrmæiR ok Ormulf ok FrøygæiR. Hann ændaðis i Silu nor en þæiR andriR ut i Grikkium. Guð hialpi Ra and ok salu.''

English translation:

: "Þorgerðr and Sveinn, they had this stone raised in memory of Ormgeirr and Ormulfr and Freygeirr. He met his end in the sound of Sila (Selaön), and the others abroad in Greece. May God help their spirits and souls."Entry U 518 in Rundata 2.5 for Windows.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="63a603f57d6087bbf8bc8405bb2a929e" name="U_518,_Västra_Ledinge" sectnum="2.4.12#1">../img/63a603f57d6087bbf8bc8405bb2a929e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>