<document id="c0008d92a65249fa11a7bf1e8e758b85-2.4.14" name="Greece_runestones" cat="1">
<text>
Runestone U 792 () is in the Fp style and it is attributed to the runemaster Balli. The stone is in grey granite and it measures  in height and  in width. It was originally raised together with a second runestone, with one on each side of the Eriksgata where the road passed a ford,Jansson 1980:22 c.  west of where the farm Ulunda is today.Wessén & Jansson 1949–1951:379 The Eriksgata was the path that newly elected Swedish kings passed when they toured the country in order to be accepted by the local assemblies. The stone was first documented by Johannes Bureus in the 17th century, and later in the same century by Johan Peringskiöld, who considered it to be a remarkable stone raised in memory of a petty king, or war chief, in pagan times. When Richard Dybeck visited the stone, in 1863, it was reclining considerably, and in 1925, the stone was reported to have completely fallen down at the bank of the stream. It was not until 1946 that the Swedish National Heritage Board arranged to have it re-erected.Wessén & Jansson 1949–1951:380 It was raised in memory of a man (probably Haursi) by his son, Kárr, and his brother-in-law. Haursi had returned from Greece a wealthy man, which left his son heir to a fortune.Jesch 2001:100

Latin transliteration:

: '''kar lit * risa * stin * þtina * at * mursa * faþur * sin * auk * kabi * at * mah sin * fu- hfila * far * aflaþi ut i * krium * arfa * sinum'''

Old Norse transcription:

: ''Karr let ræisa stæin þenna at Horsa(?), faður sinn, ok Kabbi(?)/Kampi(?)/Kappi(?)/Gapi(?) at mag sinn. Fo hæfila, feaR aflaði ut i Grikkium arfa sinum.''

English translation:

: "Kárr had this stone raised in memory of Haursi(?), his father; and Kabbi(?)/Kampi(?)/Kappi(?)/Gapi(?) in memory of his kinsman-by-marriage. (He) travelled competently; earned wealth abroad in Greece for his heir."Entry U 792 in Rundata 2.5 for Windows.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0b357ab251ab2ee706a23b6d8fcdd726" name="U_792,_Ulunda" sectnum="2.4.14#1">../img/0b357ab251ab2ee706a23b6d8fcdd726.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>