<document id="c0008d92a65249fa11a7bf1e8e758b85-2.4.13" name="Greece_runestones" cat="1">
<text>
Runestone U 540 () is in the Urnes (Pr4) style and it is attributed to the runemaster Åsmund Kåresson. It is mounted with iron to the northern wall of the church of Husby-Sjuhundra, but when the stone was first documented by Johannes Bureus in 1638 he noted that it was used as a threshold in the atrium of the church. It was still used as a threshold when Richard Dybeck visited it in 1871, and he arranged so that the entire inscription was made visible in order to make a cast copy.Wessén & Jansson 1943–1946:422 In 1887, the parishioners decided to extract both U 540 and U 541 from the church and with financial help from the Royal Swedish Academy of Letters, History and Antiquities the stones were removed and attached outside the northern wall. The stone is of red sandstone and it is  high and  wide. Several parts of the stone and its inscription have been lost, and it is worn down due to its former use as a threshold.Wessén & Jansson 1943–1946:423

A theory, proposed by Germanist F. A. Braun (1910), which is based on the runestones runestone U 513, U 540, Sö 179 and Sö 279, holds the grieving Ingvar to be the same person as Ingvar the Far-Travelled, the son of the Swedish king Emund the Old. Braun notes that the stones were raised at a Husby, a royal residence, and the names ''Eiríkr'' (Eric) and ''Hákon'' were rather rare in Sweden, but known from the royal dynasty. Önundr would be Anund Gårdske, who was raised in Russia, while Eiríkr would be one of the two pretenders named Eric, and Hákon would be Håkan the Red.E.g. Braun 1910:99–118, Wessén & Jansson 1943–1946:426ff, and Pritsak 1981:376, 425, 430ff These identifications of the three men Eiríkr, Hákon and Ingvarr also appear in the reference work ''Nordiskt runnamnslexikon'' (2002), where it adds that Eiríkr is also considered to appear on the Hillersjö stone and runestone U 20. It also identifies Hákon with the one who commissioned the runestones Ög 162 and Ög Fv1970;310.''Nordisk runnamnslexikon''

Latin transliteration:

: '''airikr ' auk hokun ' auk inkuar aukk rahnr ' þou h--... ... ...-''''''R''' '''' -na hon uarþ þ(r)  kriklati ' kuþ hialbi hons| |salu| |uk| |kuþs muþi(''''''R'''''')'''

Old Norse transcription:

: ''ÆirikR ok Hakon ok Ingvarr ok Ragnhildr þau ... ... ... ... Hann varð dauðr a Grikklandi. Guð hialpi hans salu ok Guðs moðiR.''

English translation:

: "Eiríkr and Hákon and Ingvarr and Ragnhildr, they ... ... ... ... He died in Greece. May God and God's mother help his soul."Entry U 540 in Rundata 2.5 for Windows.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c9e4c39f818ec09d4d6aef0d18a61ec0" name="U540_Husby-Sjuhundra_kyrka_runestone" sectnum="2.4.13#1">../img/c9e4c39f818ec09d4d6aef0d18a61ec0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>