<document id="c0008d92a65249fa11a7bf1e8e758b85-2.4.17" name="Greece_runestones" cat="1">
<text>
Runestone U 1016 () is in light grey and coarse granite, and it is  high and  wide. The stone stands in a wooded field  west of the road to the village Fjuckby,  of the crossroads, and c.  south-south-east of the farm Fjuckby. The first scholar to comment on the stone was Johannes Bureus, who visited the  stone on June 19 1638. Several other scholars would visit the stone during the following centuries, such as Rhezelius in 1667, Peringskiöld in 1694, and Olof Celsius in 1726 and in 1738. In 1864, Richard Dybeck noted that the runestone was one of several in the vicinity that had been raised anew during the summer.Wessén & Jansson 1953–1958:223 

Parts of the ornamentation have been lost due to flaking, which probably happened during the 17th century, but the inscription is intact. The art on the runestone has tentatively been classified under style Pr2, but Wessén & Jansson (1953–1958) comment that the ornamention is considered unusual and it is different from that on most other runestones in the district. Other stones in the same style are the Vang stone and the Alstad stone in Norway, and Sö 280 and U 1146 in Sweden. The style was better suited for wood and metal and it is likely that only few runemasters ever tried to apply it on stone.Wessén & Jansson 1953–1958:231

There have been several different interpretations of parts of the inscription,For an extensive seven page discussion on various interpretions, see Wessén & Jansson 1953–1958:224–233 but the following two interpretations appear in ''Rundata'' (2008):

Latin transliteration:

: §P '''* liutr : sturimaþr * riti : stain : þinsa : aftir : sunu * sina : sa hit : aki : sims uti furs : sturþ(i) * -(n)ari * kuam *: hn krik*:hafnir : haima tu : ...-mu-... ...(k)(a)(r)... (i)uk (r)(u)-(a) * ...'''

: §Q '''* liutr : sturimaþr * riti : stain : þinsa : aftir : sunu * sina : sa hit : aki : sims uti furs : sturþ(i) * -(n)ari * kuam *: hn krik * : hafnir : haima tu : ...-mu-... ...(k)(a)(r)... (i)uk (r)(u)-(a) * ...'''

Old Norse transcription:

: §P ''Liutr styrimaðr retti stæin þennsa æftiR sunu sina. Sa het Aki, sem's uti fors. Styrði nærri, kvam hann GrikkhafniR, hæima do ... ... hiogg(?) ruaR(?) ...''

: §Q ''Liutr styrimaðr retti stæin þennsa æftiR sunu sina. Sa het Aki, sem's uti fors. Styrði nærri, kvam hann Grikkia. HæfniR, hæima do ... ... hiogg(?) ruaR(?) ...''

English translation:

: §P "Ljótr the captain erected this stone in memory of his sons. He who perished abroad was called Áki. (He) steered a cargo-ship; he came to Greek harbours; died at home ... ... cut the runes ..."

: §Q "Ljótr the captain erected this stone in memory of his sons. He who perished abroad was called Áki. (He) steered a cargo-ship; he came to Greece. Hefnir died at home ... ... cut the runes ..."Entry U 1016 in Rundata 2.5 for Windows.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9ef88b782cc940cfbe4775dbe7bd6b82" name="U_1016,_Fjuckby" sectnum="2.4.17#1">../img/9ef88b782cc940cfbe4775dbe7bd6b82.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>