<document id="c0008d92a65249fa11a7bf1e8e758b85-2.4.16" name="Greece_runestones" cat="1">
<text>
Runestone U 956 () was made by the runemaster Åsmund Kåresson in Urnes (Pr3) style. It is raised at Vedyxa near Uppsala, c.  east of the crossroads of the road to Lövsta and the country road between Uppsala and Funbo. The stone is in grey granite and it has an unusual shape with two flat surfaces and an obtuse angle between them. The inscription is  high, of which the upper part is  and the lower part , and the width is .Wessén & Jansson 1953–1958:79

It was first documented by Johannes Haquini Rhezelius (d. 1666), and later by Johan Peringskiöld (1710), who commented that the inscription was legible in spite of the stone having been split in two parts. Unlike modern scholars, Peringskiöld connected this stone, like the other Greece runestones, to the Gothic wars in south-eastern Europe from the 3rd century and onwards.Wessén & Jansson 1953–1958:80ff Olof Celsius visited the stone three times, and the last time was in 1726 together with his nephew Anders Celsius. Olof Celsius noted that Peringskiöld had been wrong and that the stone was intact, although it gives an impression of being split in two,Wessén & Jansson 1953–1958:78 and the same observation was made by Richard Dybeck in 1866.Wessén & Jansson 1953–1958:78ff 

Latin transliteration:

: '''' stniltr ' lit * rita stain þino ' abtiR ' uiþbiurn ' krikfara ' buanta sin kuþ hialbi hos| |salu| |uk| |kuþs u muþiR osmuntr kara sun markaþi'''

Old Norse transcription:

: ''Stæinhildr let retta stæin þenna æptiR Viðbiorn Grikkfara, boanda sinn. Guð hialpi hans salu ok Guðs  moðiR. Asmundr Kara sunn markaði.''

English translation:

: "Steinhildr had this stone erected in memory of Viðbjôrn, her husband, a traveller to Greece. May God and God's mother help his soul. Ásmundr Kári' son marked."Entry U 956 in Rundata 2.5 for Windows.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6b4e751cd9817e6c41e80ac80900ad55" name="U_956,_Vedyxa" sectnum="2.4.16#1">../img/6b4e751cd9817e6c41e80ac80900ad55.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>