<document id="c0008d92a65249fa11a7bf1e8e758b85-2.4.1" name="Greece_runestones" cat="1">
<text>
Runestone U 73 () was probably erected to explain the order of inheritance from two men who died as Varangians.Harrison & Svensson 2007:34 It is in the style Pr3 which is part of the more general urnes style. The stone, which is of greyish granite measuring  in height and  in width, is raised on a slope some  north of Hägerstalund farm, formerly Hansta(lund). The stone was discovered by Johan Peringskiöld during the national search for historic monuments in the late 17th century. The stone shares the same message as U 72, together with which it once formed a monument,Wessén & Jansson 1940–1943:96ff but U 72 was moved to Skansen in 1896.Wessén & Jansson 1940–1943:95 The latter stone relates that "these stones" were raised by Gerðarr and Jörundr in memory of Ernmundr and Ingimundr. Consequently, U 73's phrase "Inga's sons" and "they died in Greece" refer to Ernmundr and Ingimundr. Ernmundr and Ingimundr had inherited from their father, but they departed for the Byzantine Empire and died there as Varangians. As they had not fathered any children, their mother Inga inherited their property, and when she died, her brothers Gerðarr and Jörundr inherited from her. These two brothers then raised the two memorials in honour of their nephews, which was probably due to the nephews having distinguished themselves in the South. However, it may have also been in gratitude for wealth gathered by the nephews overseas. At the same time, the monument served to document how the property had passed from one clan to another.Cf. Jesch (2001:99–100) Sawyer (2000), on the other hand, suggests that because the two inscriptions do not mention who commissioned them, the only eventual claimant to the fortune, and the one that had the stones made, may have been the church.Sawyer 2000:115 The runemaster has been identified as Visäte.

Latin transliteration:

: '''' þisun ' merki ' iru ' gar ' eftR ' suni ' ikur ' hon kam ' þeira × at arfi ' in þeir × brþr * kamu hnaa : at ' arfi × kiaþar b'reþr ' þir to i kirikium'''

Old Norse transcription:

: ''Þessun mærki æRu gar æftiR syni InguR. Hon kvam þæiRa at arfi, en þæiR brøðr kvamu hænnaR at arfi, Gærðarr brøðr. ÞæiR dou i Grikkium.''

English translation:

: "These landmarks are made in memory of Inga's sons. She came to inherit from them, but these brothers—Gerðarr and his brothers—came to inherit from her. They died in Greece."Entry U 73 in Rundata 2.5 for Windows.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="79b1a30ccb7fef76fb3c9d143a8b5410" name="U_73,_Hägerstalund" sectnum="2.4.1#1">../img/79b1a30ccb7fef76fb3c9d143a8b5410.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>