<document id="c08daa3efbc3e2fe2d8de390a9792427-5" name="Mário_de_Andrade" cat="17">
<text>
Andrade was not directly affected by the Revolution of 1930, in which Getúlio Vargas seized power and became dictator, but he belonged to the landed class the Revolution was designed to displace, and his employment prospects declined under the Vargas regime.  He was able to remain at the Conservatory, where he was now Chair of History of Music and Aesthetics.  With this title he became a de facto national authority on the history of music, and his research turned from the personal bent of his 1920s work to textbooks and chronologies.  He continued to document rural folk music, and during the 1930s made an enormous collection of recordings of the songs and other forms of music of the interior.  The recordings were exhaustive, with a selection based on comprehensiveness rather than an aesthetic judgment, and including context, related folktalkes, and other non-musical sound.Luper 47.  Andrade's techniques were influential in the development of ethnomusicology in Brazil and predate similar work done elsewhere, including the well-known recordings of Alan Lomax.  He is credited with coining the word "popularesque," which he defined as imitations of Brazilian folk music by erudite urban musicians ("erudite" is generally a deprecation in Andrade's vocabulary).Filho and Herschmann 347–48.  The word, and Andrade's use of it, helped define Brazilian music, which was simultaneously a scholarly and nationalist category.

In 1935, during an unstable period in Vargas's government, Andrade and writer and archaeologist Paulo Duarte, who had for many years desired to promote cultural research and activity in the city through a municipal agency, were able to create a unified São Paulo Department of Culture (''Departamento de Cultura e Recreação da Prefeitura Municipal de São Paulo'').  Andrade was named founding director.www.prodam.sp.gov.br (see External links).  The Department of Culture had a broad purview, overseeing cultural and demographic research, the construction of parks and playgrounds, and a considerable publishing wing.  Andrade approached the position with characteristic ambition, using it to expand his work in folklore and folk music while organizing myriad performances, lectures, and expositions.  He moved his collection of recordings to the Department, and expanding and enhancing it became one of the Department's chief functions, overseen by Andrade's former student, Oneyda Alvarenga.  The collection, called the ''Discoteca Municipal,'' was "probably the largest and best-organized in the entire hemisphere."

At the same time, Andrade was refining his theory of music.  He attempted to pull together his research into a general theory.  Concerned as always with ''Modernismo's'' need to break from the past, he formulated a distinction between the classical music of 18th- and 19th-century Europe, and what he called the music of the future, which would be based simultaneously on modernist breakdowns of musical form and on an understanding of folk and popular music.  The music of the past, he said, was conceived in terms of space: whether counterpoint, with its multiple voices arranged in vertical alignment, or the symphonic forms, in which the dominant voice is typically projected on top of a complex accompaniment.  Future music would be arranged in time rather than space: "moment by moment" (in Luper's translation).  This temporal music would be inspired not by "contemplative remembrance", but by the deep longing or desire expressed by the Portuguese word ''saudade''.

Andrade's position at the Department of Culture was abruptly revoked in 1937, when Vargas returned to power and Duarte was exiled.  In 1938 Andrade moved to Rio de Janeiro to take up a post at the Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro.  While there he directed the Congresso da Língua Nacional Cantada (Congress of National Musical Language), a major folklore and folk music conference.  He returned to São Paulo in 1941, taking up his old post at the Department of Culture, although with less active oversight of its activities.

Andrade's final project was a long poem called "Meditação Sôbre o Tietê."  The work is dense and difficult, and was dismissed by its early critics as "without meaning", although recent work on it has been more enthusiastic.  One critic, David T Haberly, has compared it favorably to William Carlos Williams's ''Paterson,'' a dense but influential unfinished epic using composite construction.Haberly 277–79.  Like ''Paterson'', it is a poem about a city; the "Meditação" is centered around the Tietê River, which flows through São Paulo.  The poem is simultaneously a summation of Andrade's career, commenting on poems written long before, and a love poem addressed to the river and to the city itself.  In both cases, the poem hints at a larger context: it compares the river to the Tagus in Lisbon and the Seine in Paris, as if claiming an international position for Andrade as well.  At the same time, the poem associates both Andrade's voice and the river with "banzeiro," a word from the Afro-Brazilian musical tradition: music that can unite man and river.  The poem is the definitive and final statement of Andrade's ambition and his nationalism. 

Andrade died at his home in São Paulo of a heart attack on February 25, 1945, at the age of 52.  Because of his tenuous relationship with the Vargas regime, the initial official reaction to his career was muted.  However, the publication of his ''Complete Poems'' in 1955 (the year after Vargas's death) signalled the start of Andrade's canonization as one of the cultural heroes of Brazil.  On February 15, 1960, the municipal library of São Paulo was renamed ''Biblioteca Mário de Andrade.''
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="72df8cddd44239a87b0ae2f3b53508df" name="Biblioteca_Mário_de_Andrade" sectnum="5#1">../img/72df8cddd44239a87b0ae2f3b53508df.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>