<document id="c0c3ae7e7f370d1d4ee8c23eaca0f662-2.3.2" name="2003_Insight_Bowl" cat="26">
<text>
Running back Adimchinobe Echemandu was named California's regular-season most valuable player by ESPN.com writer Ted Miller, who pointed to Echemandu's 1,161 yards and 12 touchdowns on the ground despite missing one game and most of another due to injury. "California," Ted Miller, ESPN.com. December 11, 2003. Accessed July 3, 2008. He was picked ahead of Bears quarterback Aaron Rodgers, who finished the season with 2,509 passing yards and 17 touchdowns despite starting the season as the team's backup player in that position. He outplayed original starting quarterback Reggie Robertson and replaced him during most of the second half of the season. (PDF) "Rodgers Sets School’s Single Season Record for Lowest Interception Rate; His 141.7 Pass Efficiency Mark Ranks 3rd Best in Cal History," California Sports Information Department. Pgs. 16-17. Accessed July 7, 2008.


Rodgers' favorite passing target was wide receiver Geoff McArthur, who was the Bears' leading receiver during the regular season, catching 85 passes for a school-record 1,504 receiving yards and 10 touchdowns. In one of the Bears' final practices before the Insight Bowl, however, McArthur fractured his right forearm and was unable to play. McArthur recorded the third-highest receiving total for a Pac-10 player and had the second-highest average receiving yards per game in the country during the regular season. He set California single-game records for receiving yards and receptions. Junior receiver Chase Lyman was picked to start the Insight Bowl in McArthur's place. Lyman caught just seven passes for 107 yards during the season. Bob Baum, The Associated Press, ''The San Diego Union-Tribune''. December 24, 2003. Accessed July 7, 2008. Bruce Adams, ''San Francisco Chronicle''. December 25, 2003. Accessed July 7, 2008.

During practice before the game, California kicker Tyler Fredrickson practiced kicking the ball high to avoid what was expected to be a difficult Virginia Tech kick-blocking attack. During the regular season, Fredrickson had five kicks blocked and successfully converted just 14 of 29 field goal attempts. Virginia Tech, meanwhile, blocked 102 kicks in the 200 games previous to the Insight Bowl. Bruce Adams, ''San Francisco Chronicle''. December 19, 2003. Accessed July 3, 2008. Jake Curtis, ''San Francisco Chronicle''. December 2, 2003. Accessed July 7, 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="73cfd575dfc0e4d11547414ce6956e3e" name="AaronRodgers" sectnum="2.3.2#1">../img/73cfd575dfc0e4d11547414ce6956e3e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>