<document id="c167a71871f08137fcea8bee4013c6c8-5" name="By_the_Way" cat="20">
<text>
The launch of the record took place on New York City's Ellis Island. Sponsored by the rock radio station K-Rock, the event was titled the "Pep Rally". The band performed eight songs from ''By the Way'', as well as tracks from ''Californication'' and ''Blood Sugar Sex Magik'' in front of 900 contest winners. The ''New York Post'' declared the show "one of the top concerts of the year." The location was chosen in order to reinvigorate lower Manhattan after the September 11, 2001 attacks and all proceeds were donated to pertinent charity organizations. Immediately following this, the Chili Peppers embarked on a world tour to support the album. Beginning in Europe, they also played at events such as the Fuji Rock Festival and Coachella Valley Music and Arts Festival in between. The band eventually culminated their Europe leg of the tour in February 2003, and commenced the United States leg on May 1. The Chili Peppers played at Madison Square Garden in New York City on June 3, 2003 to a sold-out crowd and an enthusiastic response from critics. Kelefa Sanneh of ''The New York Times'' reported that "on Tuesday night, the  came to Madison Square Garden for an extraordinary two-hour performance...On 'Don't Forget Me',  strummed chords, while Mr. Frusciante contributed a gorgeous guitar line that bubbled and hissed like some sort of chemical reaction." The US leg ended on June 21; the band took a small hiatus before performing at Slane Castle on August 23, to a crowd of over 80,000. ''Live at Slane Castle'', the result of the concert, would become the Chili Peppers' second live DVD, after ''Off the Map''.

Following several Japanese and Australian performances, the Red Hot Chili Peppers planned three nights at London's Hyde Park. Over 240,000 tickets were sold within hours, with roughly 80,000 people attending each show on June 19, 20, and 25, respectively. It became the highest grossing concert at a single venue in history, accumulating an estimated $17 million gross revenue. Due to the success of the three shows, the band released their first live album ''Live in Hyde Park'' in Europe, Australia, Japan and New Zealand, excluding the United States. Later that year, the Chili Peppers played for the 2004 Democratic National Convention in support of their political beliefs, with Kiedis saying "Do what you gotta do" at the end of the band's set. Finally, they played at the Rock am Ring festival as one of the final performances of the ''By the Way'' tour.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9a92ec6e2f81d9635748318cce964ff9" name="Slane_Concert" sectnum="5#1">../img/9a92ec6e2f81d9635748318cce964ff9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>