<document id="c16fc36728dff580d2af90b4fe0983f7-5.8" name="Bath,_Somerset" cat="11">
<text>
During the 18th century Thomas Gainsborough and Sir Thomas Lawrence lived and worked in Bath. John Maggs, a painter best known for his coaching scenes, was born and lived in Bath with his artistic family.
William Friese-Greene began experimenting with celluloid and motion pictures in his studio in Bath in the 1870s, developing some of the earliest movie camera technology there. He is credited as the inventor of cinematography.

Jane Austen lived in the city from 1801 with her father, mother and sister Cassandra, and the family resided in the city at four successive addresses until 1806. However, Jane Austen never liked the city, and wrote to her sister Cassandra, "It will be two years tomorrow since we left Bath for Clifton, with what happy feelings of escape." Despite these feelings, Bath has honoured her name with the Jane Austen Centre and a city walk. Austen's later ''Northanger Abbey'' and ''Persuasion'' are largely set in the city and feature descriptions of taking the waters, social life, and music recitals. Taking the waters is also described in Charles Dickens' novel ''The Pickwick Papers'' in which Pickwick's servant, Sam Weller, comments that the water has "a very strong flavour o' warm flat irons", while the Royal Crescent is the venue for a chase between two of the characters, Dowler and Winkle.  Moyra Caldecott's novel The Waters of Sul is set in Roman Bath in 72 AD. Richard Brinsley Sheridan's play ''The Rivals'' takes place in the city, as does Roald Dahl's chilling short-story, ''The Landlady''.

Many films and television programmes have been filmed using the architecture of Bath as the backdrop including: the 2004 film of Thackeray's ''Vanity Fair'', ''The Duchess'' (2008), ''The Elusive Pimpernel'' (1950) and ''The Titfield Thunderbolt'' (1953).

In August 2003 the Three Tenors sang at a special concert to mark the opening of the Thermae Bath Spa, a new hot water spa in Bath City Centre; delays to the project meant the spa actually opened three years later on 7 August 2006.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="139fdd9c67c31efc47b80b3572f8c607" name="bath_pigs_art_project_2008_arp" sectnum="5.8#1">../img/139fdd9c67c31efc47b80b3572f8c607.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>