<document id="c17abe4a0cf53ad21edffef6ff66d017-1.1" name="Connie_Talbot" cat="20">
<text>
Talbot initially auditioned for the first series of television reality show ''Britain's Got Talent'' for fun, but her confidence increased when Simon Cowell, whom she is said to have idolised, described her as "pure magic" and said that he would make her earn "£1 million-plus this year". The judges expected a "joke" performance and she had never taken singing lessons, but Talbot's initial performance received international press coverage. She reached the final round after winning her semi-final with a live performance of "Ben" by Michael Jackson. On the night of the final, she sang ''The Wizard of Oz'''s "Over the Rainbow", but lost to Paul Potts as a result of the call-in vote. Talbot and Potts had been joint favourites to win the series.

According to journalist and ''Britain's Got Talent'' judge Piers Morgan, Talbot's performances resulted in many children, including Faryl Smith, auditioning for the second series of the show. After his victory, Series 2 winner George Sampson spoke of his participation in the first series, where he was knocked out before the live shows, saying "I don't think I had any shot of winning last year ... When you look at the standard of Paul Potts and Connie Talbot. Paul Potts is out of this league, and Connie is out of this league - I wasn't good enough." Talbot voted for Sampson, saying "I liked his dancing - he was good on the lamppost".

Cowell had preliminarily agreed to sign Talbot with his own record label, Sony BMG. After recording two songs in London with Talbot ("Over the Rainbow" and "Smile"), the label pulled out of the deal. Talbot's mother, Sharon, said she was told that her daughter "...was too young to be their sort of artist", adding "We have been told to look for a company which looks after children." In a statement, the label said "there was some deliberation over the possibility of recording with Connie ... However, the decision not to proceed was made with the best intentions for Connie, taking into consideration her age and that it would not be right to do so at this time." Cowell himself said that "when the time is right,  be delighted to see if  make it work". The Talbot family decided to search for another label, saying "while  loves what she's doing it would be cruel to stop her. Fame and money will never matter."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ef660251992cda2dfa581fd2e9396b1f" name="ConnieTalbot3" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/ef660251992cda2dfa581fd2e9396b1f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>