<document id="c1d255d33f1005688e0e084374c98ced-6" name="William_Shakespeare" cat="17">
<text>
Shakespeare was never revered in his lifetime, but he received his share of praise.; . In 1598, the cleric and author Francis Meres singled him out from a group of English writers as "the most excellent" in both comedy and tragedy.; . And the authors of the ''Parnassus'' plays at St John's College, Cambridge, numbered him with Chaucer, Gower and Spenser.. In the First Folio, Ben Jonson called Shakespeare the "Soul of the age, the applause, delight, the wonder of our stage", though he had remarked elsewhere that "Shakespeare wanted art"..


Between the Restoration of the monarchy in 1660 and the end of the seventeenth century, classical ideas were in vogue. As a result, critics of the time mostly rated Shakespeare below John Fletcher and Ben Jonson.. Thomas Rymer, for example, condemned Shakespeare for mixing the comic with the tragic. Nevertheless, poet and critic John Dryden rated Shakespeare highly, saying of Jonson, "I admire him, but I love Shakespeare".. For several decades, Rymer's view held sway; but during the eighteenth century, critics began to respond to Shakespeare on his own terms and acclaim what they termed his natural genius. A series of scholarly editions of his work, notably those of Samuel Johnson in 1765 and Edmond Malone in 1790, added to his growing reputation.; . By 1800, he was firmly enshrined as the national poet. Cited by . In the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, his reputation also spread abroad. Among those who championed him were the writers Voltaire, Goethe, Stendhal and Victor Hugo.Grady cites Voltaire's ''Philosophical Letters'' (1733); Goethe's ''Wilhelm Meister's Apprenticeship'' (1795); Stendhal's two-part pamphlet ''Racine et Shakespeare'' (1823–5); and Victor Hugo's prefaces to ''Cromwell'' (1827) and ''William Shakespeare'' (1864). .

During the Romantic era, Shakespeare was praised by the poet and literary philosopher Samuel Taylor Coleridge; and the critic August Wilhelm Schlegel translated his plays in the spirit of German Romanticism.. In the nineteenth century, critical admiration for Shakespeare's genius often bordered on adulation.. "That King Shakespeare," the essayist Thomas Carlyle wrote in 1840, "does not he shine, in crowned sovereignty, over us all, as the noblest, gentlest, yet strongest of rallying signs; indestructible".. The Victorians produced his plays as lavish spectacles on a grand scale.. The playwright and critic George Bernard Shaw mocked the cult of Shakespeare worship as "bardolatry". He claimed that the new naturalism of Ibsen's plays had made Shakespeare obsolete..

The modernist revolution in the arts during the early twentieth century, far from discarding Shakespeare, eagerly enlisted his work in the service of the avant garde. The Expressionists in Germany and the Futurists in Moscow mounted productions of his plays. Marxist playwright and director Bertolt Brecht devised an epic theatre under the influence of Shakespeare. The poet and critic T. S. Eliot argued against Shaw that Shakespeare's "primitiveness" in fact made him truly modern.. Eliot, along with G. Wilson Knight and the school of New Criticism, led a movement towards a closer reading of Shakespeare's imagery. In the 1950s, a wave of new critical approaches replaced modernism and paved the way for "post-modern" studies of Shakespeare.. By the eighties, Shakespeare studies were open to movements such as structuralism, feminism, New Historicism, African American studies, and queer studies..
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="97e1ac0bee9a182d7a0afffba50d285e" name="Millais_-_Ophelia_(detail)" sectnum="6#1">../img/97e1ac0bee9a182d7a0afffba50d285e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>