<document id="c1d96f851b917db3a34598927f632aac-3.13" name="Donald_Bradman" cat="26">
<text>
Cricket writer David Frith summed up the paradox of the continuing fascination with Bradman:Frith (2002), p 427.


On 10 December 1985, Bradman was the first of 120 inaugural inductees into the Sport Australia Hall of Fame. at ''sahof.org.au'' He spoke of his philosophy for considering the stature of athletes: 

Although modest about his own abilities and generous in his praise of other cricketers, Bradman was fully aware of the talents he possessed as a player;Williams (1996), p 274. there is some evidence that he sought to influence his legacy.Eason (2004), p 16. During the 1980s and 1990s, Bradman carefully selected the people to whom he gave interviews, assisting Michael Page, Roland Perry and Charles Williams, who all produced biographical works about him. Bradman also agreed to an extensive interview for ABC radio, broadcast as ''Bradman: The Don Declares'' in eight 55-minute episodes during 1988.Eason (2004), p 65.


The most significant of these legacy projects was a museum, opened in 1987 at the Bradman Oval in Bowral.Eason (2004), p 73. This organisation was reformed in 1993 as a non-profit charitable Trust, called the Bradman Foundation.Eason (2004), p 67. When the Australian Cricket Hall of Fame was created in 1996, Bradman was made one of its 10 inaugural members. In 2000, Bradman was selected by cricket experts as one of five ''Wisden Cricketers of the Century''. Each of the 100 members of the panel were able to select five cricketers: all 100 voted for Bradman.

After his wife's death in 1997, Bradman suffered "a discernible and not unexpected wilting of spirit".Frith (2002), p 429. The next year, on his 90th birthday, he hosted a meeting with his two favourite modern players, Shane Warne and Sachin Tendulkar, but he was not seen in his familiar place at the Adelaide Oval again.

Hospitalised with pneumonia in December 2000, he returned home in the New Year and died there on 25 February 2001, aged 92. BBC News. Retrieved on 14 May 2008

A memorial service to mark Bradman's life was held on 25 March 2001 at St Peter's Anglican Cathedral, Adelaide. The service was attended by a host of former and current Test cricketers, as well as Australia's then Prime Minister, John Howard, Leader of the Opposition Kim Beazley and former Prime Minister Bob Hawke. Eulogies were given by Richie Benaud and Governor-General Sir William Deane. The service was broadcast live on ABC Television to a viewing audience of 1.45 million.Hutchins (2002), p 4.

Bradman's life and achievements were recognised in Australia with two notable issues. Three years before he died, he became the first living Australian to be featured on an Australian postage stamp. After his death, the Australian Government produced a 20 cent coin to commemorate his life.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="006935571c4f0f8f1babc25d54fe4e21" name="BradmanStand" sectnum="3.13#1">../img/006935571c4f0f8f1babc25d54fe4e21.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>