<document id="c1d96f851b917db3a34598927f632aac-2.10" name="Donald_Bradman" cat="26">
<text>
In 1945–46, Bradman suffered regular bouts of fibrositis while coming to terms with increased administrative duties and the establishment of his business.Page (1983), pp 271–272. He played for SA in two matches to help with the re-establishment of first-class cricket and later described his batting as "painstaking". Bradman (1950), p 125. Batting against the Australian Services cricket team, Bradman scored 112 in less than two hours, yet Dick Whitington (playing for the Services) wrote, "I have seen today the ghost of a once great cricketer".Eason (2004), p 337. Bradman declined a tour of New Zealand and spent the winter of 1946 wondering whether he had played his last match. With the English team due to arrive for the Ashes series, the media and the public were anxious to know if Bradman would lead Australia.Williams (1996) pp 205–206. "It was all the more obvious that, on any analysis, the only figure of stature who could lead Australia back into the post-War cricket era was 'the little feller', the 'sick man of Adelaide', the wartime invalid now nearing forty. It is little wonder that all Australia wanted to know precisely what he was proposing to do." His doctor recommended against a return to the game.
Encouraged by his wife, Bradman agreed to play in lead-up fixtures to the Test series. Bradman (1950), p 126. After hitting two centuries, Bradman made himself available for the First Test at The Gabba.

Controversy emerged as early as the first day of the series. After compiling an uneasy 28 runs, Bradman hit a ball to the gully fieldsman, Jack Ikin. An appeal for a catch was denied in the umpire's contentious ruling that it was a bump ball. At the end of the over, England captain Wally Hammond spoke with Bradman and criticised him for not "walking"; "from then on the series was a cricketing war just when most people desired peace", Whitington wrote.Whitington (1974), p 190. Bradman regained his finest pre-war form in making 187, followed by 234 during the Second Test at Sydney. Australia won both matches by an innings. Jack Fingleton speculated that had the decision at Brisbane gone against him, Bradman would have retired, such were his fitness problems.Fingleton (1949), p 22. In the remainder of the series, Bradman made three half-centuries in six innings, but was unable to make another century; nevertheless, his team won handsomely, 3–0. He was the leading batsman on either side, with an average of 97.14. Nearly 850,000 spectators watched the Tests, which helped lift public spirits after the war.Bradman (1950), p 139.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4e3655ff389678f7724082ea11687497" name="Bradman_Barnes_234" sectnum="2.10#1">../img/4e3655ff389678f7724082ea11687497.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>