<document id="c221382cdc6d1af975eb442f2e7b8ca9-1.2" name="Damageplan" cat="20">
<text>
On December 8, 2004, Damageplan was on tour at the Alrosa Villa, a Columbus, Ohio nightclub. Moments into the concert, Nathan Gale, a former U.S. Marine, climbed onto the stage and shot Darrell in the head multiple times. Head of Security for the band Jeffery "Mayhem" Thompson engaged in hand-to-hand combat with Gale, which allowed Vinnie Paul Abbott and other members to escape. Thompson, however, was killed. A fan named Nathan Bray attempted to give CPR to Thompson and Darrell, but was shot by the gunman and killed. Roadie Erin Halk, also a former U.S. Marine, was killed when he charged at Gale while he was reloading. Once police arrived, officer James Niggemeyer approached the stage from the side and could see Gale holding a gun to a hostage. With a clear shot, Niggemeyer killed Gale with a single shotgun blast to the head. 15 Shots were fired by Gale, and an additional 36 rounds were found on his person.

A police investigation did not find a motive behind the shooting, although some fans claimed Gale blamed Darrell and Vinnie for the demise of Pantera, and that Gale said the brothers stole his lyrics  while trying to steal his identity. Gale used a Beretta 92F that was given to him by his mother, who was proud of his military service following his discharge. Although Major Jason Johnston, a Marine Corps spokesman at The Pentagon, was unable to comment on his discharge, his mother said he suffered from paranoid schizophrenia. He was given medication for the condition although she does not know if he took it.

A foundation called The Dimebag Darrell Memorial Fund was created after the incident, which donated  its profits to cover medical expenses of drum technician John Brooks and tour manager Chris Paluska, who were injured on December 8. A public memorial service for Darrell took place on December 14, 2004 at Arlington Convention Center in Arlington, Texas. Many musicians paid tribute to Darrell on message boards and at live performances.

In May 2005, Niggemeyer was called before a grand jury, which was assembled by the Franklin County prosecutor's office to examine the actions taken that night, a standard practice when lethal force is used. The jury found there was no wrongdoing on Niggemeyer's part. Franklin County prosecutor Ron O'Brien commented, "There was little doubt  was lawful, given the 200 eyewitnesses and the circumstances that surrounded the shooting. Nevertheless, we still have an independent body review the facts". Niggemeyer was nominated for a bravery award on the TV show ''America's Most Wanted''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8e005d952cede4406ad960da12f02eb6" name="Dimebag_001" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/8e005d952cede4406ad960da12f02eb6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>