<document id="c3577be372e2760055bf4af7e19df3bc-2.1" name="Battle_of_the_Santa_Cruz_Islands" cat="29">
<text>
From October 20 to October 25, Japanese land forces on Guadalcanal attempted to capture Henderson Field with a large-scale attack against U.S. troops defending the airfield.  However, the attack was decisively defeated with heavy casualties for the Japanese during the Battle for Henderson Field.Hammel, ''Carrier Strike'', p. 95–97.

Incorrectly believing that the Japanese army troops had succeeded in capturing Henderson Field, a force of Japanese warships approached Guadalcanal on the morning of October 25 to provide further support for the army offensive.  Aircraft from Henderson Field attacked the convoy throughout the day, sinking the light cruiser ''Yura'' and damaging the destroyer ''Akizuki''.Hammel, ''Carrier Strike'', p. 103–106.  The force consisted of Japanese cruiser ''Yura'', and destroyers ''Akizuki'', ''Harusame'', ''Murasame'', and ''Yudachi'' (Parshall, ''Imperial Japanese Navy Page''. Combinedfleet.com).  Although Hammel says that it was a supply convoy, Parshall says that it was a bombardment force.  ''Akizuki'' went to Japan for repairs, which were completed on December 16, 1942.  This incident is usually considered a separate action from the Battle of the Santa Cruz Islands.


Despite the failure of the Japanese ground offensive and the loss of ''Yura'', the rest of the Combined Fleet continued to maneuver near the southern Solomon Islands on October 25 with the hope of encountering Allied naval forces in battle.  The Japanese naval forces included four carriers, because ''Hiyō'' had suffered an accidental, damaging fire on October 22 that forced her to return to Truk for repairs.Hara, ''Japanese Destroyer Captain'', p. 124.  The Japanese naval forces were divided into three groups:  The "Advanced" force contained ''Junyō'', plus two battleships, four heavy cruisers, one light cruiser, and 10 destroyers, and was commanded by Vice Admiral Nobutake Kondo in heavy cruiser ''Atago''; the "Main Body" consisted of ''Shōkaku'', ''Zuikaku'', and ''Zuihō'' plus one heavy cruiser and eight destroyers, and was commanded by Vice Admiral Chuichi Nagumo in ''Shōkaku''; the "Vanguard" force contained two battleships, three heavy cruisers, one light cruiser, and seven destroyers, and was commanded by Rear Admiral Hiroaki Abe in battleship ''Hiei''.  In addition to commanding the Advanced force, Kondo acted as the overall commander of the three forces.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 374–375.

On the U.S. side, the ''Hornet'' and ''Enterprise'' task groups, under the overall command of Rear Admiral Thomas Kinkaid swept around to the north of the Santa Cruz Islands on October 25 searching for the Japanese naval forces.  The U.S. warships were deployed as two separate carrier groups, each centered on either ''Hornet'' or ''Enterprise'', and separated from each other by about 10 nmi (19 km).  A U.S. PBY Catalina based in the Santa Cruz Islands located the Japanese Main body carriers at 11:03.  However, the Japanese carriers were about 355 nmi (655 km) from the U.S. force, just beyond carrier aircraft range.  Kinkaid, hoping to close the range to be able to execute an attack that day, steamed towards the Japanese carriers at top speed and, at 14:25, launched a strike force of 23 aircraft.  But the Japanese, knowing that they had been spotted by U.S. aircraft and not knowing where the U.S. carriers were, turned to the north to stay out of range of the U.S. carriers' aircraft.Hara, ''Japanese Destroyer Captain'', p. 127.  Thus, the U.S. strike force returned to their carriers without finding or attacking the Japanese warships.Hammel, ''Carrier Strike'', p. 163–174.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="84b3a24817643949ba9d1e9e99d9b646" name="SantaCruzChart2" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/84b3a24817643949ba9d1e9e99d9b646.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>