<document id="c362a1f0f4b04c4d3f158119f2df342e-8" name="Fauna_of_Australia" cat="3">
<text>
For at least 40,000 years, Australia's fauna played an integral role in the traditional lifestyles of Indigenous Australians, who exploited many species as a source of food and skins. Vertebrates commonly harvested included macropods, opossums, seals, fish and the Short-tailed Shearwater, most commonly known as the Muttonbird. Invertebrates used as food included insects like the Bogong moth and larvae collectively called witchetty grubs and molluscs. The use of fire-stick farming, in which large swathes of bushland were burnt to facilitate hunting, modified both flora and fauna &mdash; and are thought to have contributed to the extinction of large herbivores with a specialised diet, such as the flightless birds from the genus ''Genyornis''.Miller, G. H. 2005. Ecosystem Collapse in Pleistocene Australia and a Human Role in Megafaunal Extinction. ''Science'', 309:287–290 PMID 16002615 The role of hunting and landscape modification by aboriginal people in the extinction of the Australian megafauna is debated.Thomson, J.M. et al. 1987. Human Exploitation of and Introductions to the Australian Fauna. In D.W. Walton Ed. ''Fauna of Australia'', Volume 1A. Australian Government Publishing Service, Canberra. 

 
The impact of Aborigines on native species populations is widely considered to be less significant than that of the European settlers,Thomson, J.M. et al. 1987. Human Exploitation of and Introductions to the Australian Fauna. In D.W. Walton Ed. ''Fauna of Australia'', Volume 1A. Australian Government Publishing Service, Canberra.  whose impact on the landscape has been on a relatively large scale. Since European settlement, direct exploitation of native fauna, habitat destruction and the introduction of exotic predators and competitive herbivores has led to the extinction of some 27 mammal, 23 bird and 4 frog species. Much of Australia's fauna is protected by legislation; a notable exception is kangaroos, which are prolific and are regularly culled. The federal ''Environment Protection and Biodiversity Conservation Act 1999'' was created to meet Australia's obligations as a signatory to the 1992 Convention on Biological Diversity. This act protects all native fauna and provides for the identification and protection of threatened species. In each state and territory, there is statutory listing of threatened species. At present, 380 animal species are classified as either endangered or threatened under the EPBC Act, and other species are protected under state and territory legislation.Department of the Environment and Heritage.  More broadly, a complete cataloguing of all the species within Australia has been undertaken, a key step in the conservation of Australian fauna and biodiversity. In 1973, the federal government established the Australian Biological Resources Study (ABRS), which coordinates research in the taxonomy, identification, classification and distribution of flora and fauna. The ABRS maintains free online databases cataloguing much of the described Australian flora and fauna. Impacts such as the illegal setting of traps in rivers affect animals such as the Australian platypus, along with lack of awareness each year an average of 2-5 australians lose their lives to what is presumed a safe creature. The key is understanding of Australia's diverse wildlife and fauna, what seems safe is often deadly.

Australia is a member of the International Whaling Commission and is strongly opposed to commercial whaling&mdash;all Cetacean species are protected in Australian waters. Australia is also a signatory to the CITES agreement and prohibits the export of endangered species. Protected areas have been created in every state and territory to protect and preserve the country's unique ecosystems. These protected areas include national parks and other reserves, as well as 64 wetlands registered under the Ramsar Convention and 16 World Heritage Sites. As of 2002, 10.8% (774,619.51 km²) of the total land area of Australia is within protected areas.Department of the Environment and Heritage. 2002.  Protected marine zones have been created in many areas to preserve marine biodiversity; as of 2002, these areas cover about 7% (646,000 km²) of Australia's marine jurisdiction.Department of the Environment and Heritage. 2002.  The Great Barrier Reef is managed by the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Authority under specific federal and state legislation. Some of Australia's fisheries are already overexploited,Newton, G and Boshier, J, eds. 2001. ''Coasts and Oceans Theme Report, Australia State of the Environment Report 2001'' (Theme Report), CSIRO Publishing on behalf of the Department of the Environment and Heritage, Canberra. ISBN 0-643-06749-3  and quotas have been set for the sustainable harvest of many marine species.

The ''State of the Environment Report, 2001'', prepared by independent researchers for the federal government, concluded that the condition of the environment and environmental management in Australia had worsened since the previous report in 1996. Of particular relevance to wildlife conservation, the report indicated that many processes—such as salinity, changing hydrological conditions, land clearing, fragmentation of ecosystems, poor management of the coastal environment, and invasive species—pose major problems for protecting Australia's biodiversity.Australian State of the Environment Committee. 2001. ''Australia State of the Environment 2001'', Independent Report to the Commonwealth Minister for the Environment and Heritage. CSIRO Publishing on behalf of the Department of the Environment and Heritage ISBN 0-643-06745-0
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="af71743e00fcf9f9fecbc8da39543ecb" name="Grey_Nurse_Shark_at_Fish_Rock_Cave,_NSW" sectnum="8#1">../img/af71743e00fcf9f9fecbc8da39543ecb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>