<document id="c39584729495496984371f0ec2f38974-11" name="Minneapolis" cat="11">
<text>
WCCO-TV on the Nicollet Mall
Five major newspapers are published in Minneapolis: ''Star Tribune'', ''Finance and Commerce'', ''Minnesota Spokesman-Recorder'', the university's ''The Minnesota Daily'' and ''MinnPost.com''. Other publications are the ''City Pages'' weekly, the ''Mpls.St.Paul'' and ''Minnesota Monthly'' monthlies, and ''Utne'' magazine. In 2008 readers of online news also used ''Minnesota Independent'', ''Twin Cities Daily Planet'', ''Downtown Journal'', ''Cursor'', ''MNSpeak'' and about fifteen other sites. ''The New York Times'' said in 1996, "Now there are T-shirts that read, 'Murderapolis,'" a name for the city that members of the local media have mistakenly attributed to the paper. and  and 

Minneapolis has a mix of radio stations and healthy listener support for public radio but in the commercial market, a single organization Clear Channel Communications operates seven stations. Listeners support three Minnesota Public Radio non-profit stations, the Minneapolis Public Schools and the University of Minnesota each operate a station, the networks broadcast on affiliate stations, and religious organizations run two stations. and 



The city's first television was broadcast by the St. Paul station and ABC affiliate KSTP-TV. The first to broadcast in color was WCCO-TV, the CBS affiliate which is located in downtown Minneapolis. The city also receives FOX, NBC, PBS, MyNetworkTV, and The CW through their affiliates and one independent station. Twins Brandon and Brenda Walsh were from Minneapolis on the TV series ''Beverly Hills, 90210''. ''American Idol'' held auditions for its sixth season in Minneapolis in 2006 and ''Last Comic Standing'' held auditions for its fifth season in Minneapolis in 2007. 

A statue of Mary Tyler Moore downtown on the Nicollet Mall commemorates the legendary 1970s CBS television situation comedy fictionally based in Minneapolis, ''The Mary Tyler Moore Show''. It marks the site where part of the series' iconic opening sequence was shot.

The show was awarded three Golden Globes and thirty-one Emmy Awards.and
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e32a4c1c0239d5b7da7543eb1e8213a3" name="KFAI-entrance-Minneapolis" sectnum="11#1">../img/e32a4c1c0239d5b7da7543eb1e8213a3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>