<document id="c39584729495496984371f0ec2f38974-2" name="Minneapolis" cat="11">
<text>
The history and economic growth of Minneapolis history are tied to water, the city's defining physical characteristic, which was sent to the region during the last ice age. Fed by receding glaciers and Lake Agassiz ten thousand years ago, torrents of water from a glacial river undercut the Mississippi and Minnehaha riverbeds, creating waterfalls important to modern Minneapolis. and  Lying on an artesian aquifer and otherwise flat terrain, Minneapolis has a total area of  and of this 6% is water. and  Water is managed by watershed districts that correspond to the Mississippi and the city's three creeks. Twelve lakes, three large ponds, and five unnamed wetlands are within Minneapolis.

The city center is located just south of 45° N latitude. The city's lowest elevation of  is near where Minnehaha Creek meets the Mississippi River. The site of the Prospect Park Water Tower is often cited as the city's highest point and  and  and a placard in Deming Heights Park denotes the highest elevation, but a spot at  in or near Waite Park in Northeast Minneapolis is corroborated by Google Earth as the highest ground.

alt=Downtown skyline in view over Lake Calhoun and its dock 

Minneapolis has a continental climate typical of the Upper Midwest. Winters can be cold and dry, while summer is comfortably warm although at times it can be hot and humid. On the Köppen climate classification, Minneapolis falls in the warm summer humid continental climate zone (''Dfa''); and has a USDA plant hardiness of zone 5. The city experiences a full range of precipitation and related weather events, including snow, sleet, ice, rain, thunderstorms, tornadoes, and fog. The warmest temperature ever recorded in Minneapolis was  in July 1936, and the coldest temperature ever recorded was , in January 1888. The snowiest winter of record was 1983&ndash;84, when  of snow fell.

Because of its northerly location in the United States and lack of large enough bodies of water in close proximity to moderate the air, Minneapolis is sometimes subjected to cold Arctic air masses, especially during the months of January and February. The average annual temperature of  gives the Minneapolis&ndash;St. Paul metropolitan area the coldest annual mean temperature of any major metropolitan area in the continental United States.45.4 °F for 1971 through 2000 per  who cites  or  per
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fb6242a4af5f65f96eccdfcb4cd859f9" name="Kites-Lake_Harriet-Minneapolis-20070120" sectnum="2#1">../img/fb6242a4af5f65f96eccdfcb4cd859f9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>