<document id="c3a05be9f79052d99d9121e54fd97c64-3" name="Western_Front_(World_War_I)" cat="29">
<text>
The German Chief of Staff, Erich von Falkenhayn, believed that a breakthrough might no longer be possible, and instead focused on forcing a French capitulation by inflicting massive casualties.Lyons, 141. His new goal was to "bleed France white".

As such, he adopted two new strategies. The first was the use of unrestricted submarine warfare to cut off Allied supplies arriving from overseas. The second would be targeted, high-casualty attacks against the French ground troops. To inflict the maximum possible casualties, he planned to attack a position from which the French could not retreat for reason of both strategic positions and national pride and thus trap the French. The town of Verdun was chosen for this because it was an important stronghold, surrounded by a ring of forts, that lay near the German lines and because it guarded the direct route to Paris. The operation was codenamed ''Gericht'', German for "court", but meant "place of execution".

Falkenhayn limited the size of the front to 3–4 miles (4.8–6.4 km) to concentrate their firepower and to prevent a breakthrough from a counteroffensive. He also kept tight control of the main reserve, feeding in just enough troops to keep the battle going.Marshall, 236–7. In preparation for their attack, the Germans had amassed a concentration of aircraft near the fortress. In the opening phase, they swept the air space of enemy spotters which allowed the accurate German artillery spotters and bombers to operate without interference. However, by May, the French countered by deploying ''escadrilles de chasse'' with superior Nieuport fighters. The tight air space over Verdun turned into an aerial battlefield, and illustrated the value of tactical air superiority, as each side sought to dominate air reconnaissance.Campbell, 40.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="44d73e5f44a85431fbfd1e49d312c38b" name="Bundesarchiv_Bild_183-R05148,_Westfront,_deutscher_Soldat" sectnum="3#1">../img/44d73e5f44a85431fbfd1e49d312c38b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>