<document id="c3b93f98a70472f1721e97638be04bed-2.8" name="History_of_the_Yosemite_area" cat="14">
<text>
The Ahwahnee Hotel, built in 1927 in Yosemite Valley, is a luxury hotel decorated in Native American motifs. It was designed by the architect Gilbert Stanley Underwood who designed lodges at many of the national parks.  For many years Ansel Adams produced an annual pageant there, and in World War II it was used as a rehabilitation hospital for soldiers. It is now a National Historic Landmark.


Yosemite National Park has had 11 winter floods since 1916 that have caused substantial damage to property. All of these floods took place between November 1 and January 30. The largest floods occurred in 1937, 1950, 1955, and 1997, and were in the range of 22,000 to 25,000 cubic feet (620 to 700 m³) per second, as measured at the Pohono Bridge gauging station in Yosemite Valley., National Park Service. Retrieved 4 January 2007. After the 1950 flood, all structures in Old Yosemite Village, except for the chapel, were either moved to the Pioneer Yosemite History center in Wawona or demolished in the 1950s and 1960s. Other structures from throughout the park were also moved to the history center. Some structures in the Old Village, such as the historic 1858 Cedar Cottage, then the oldest building in Yosemite Valley, were demolished even though they weren't flooded.  Back then little regard was given to historic preservation, the thought being that the "highest use" was preserving and restoring natural scenery.

Three different protected zones were added adjacent to Yosemite National Park in 1964:
*Ansel Adams Wilderness
*Hoover Wilderness
*Emigrant Wilderness
These additional protected areas include areas removed from Yosemite National Park just prior to the 1906 Act as well as other public land.

A 1964 act of Congress set aside about 94% of the park in a highly protected wilderness area. No roads, motorized vehicles (except rescue helicopters and other emergency vehicles), or any development of any kind beyond trail maintenance are allowed in this area.

In 1968 the famous ''Yosemite Firefall'', in which the embers from a bonfire were pushed off of a cliff near Glacier Point to create a spectacular effect, was ended because it drew excessively large crowds. The Firefall was occasionally performed in the 1870s and became a nightly tradition with the founding of Camp Curry.

The broader tensions in American society were felt in Yosemite in 1970, when a large number of youths gathered in the park over the summer. Rioting broke out on July 4 in Stoneman Meadow. The visitors attacked rangers with rocks and pulled mounted rangers from their horses. The National Guard was brought in to maintain order.

The late 1990s saw the high-profile murder case of Cary Stayner and some serious rock slides; one rockslide originating from the east side of Glacier Point ended near the Happy Isles of the Merced River, creating a debris field larger than several football fields. Tourism dropped a little after those incidents, but soon after returned to previous levels.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="196df32d7c1cba080cb6b2af38154caf" name="Yosemite_-_Ahwahnee_Hotel" sectnum="2.8#1">../img/196df32d7c1cba080cb6b2af38154caf.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>