<document id="c407db96a89986aa5f4a52a3e2f00686-5" name="Lost_(TV_series)" cat="19">
<text>
There are several recurring elements and motifs on ''Lost'', which generally have no direct effect on the story itself, but expand the show's literary and philosophical subtext. These elements include frequent appearances of the colors black and white, which reflect the dualism within characters and situations; as well as rebellion in almost all characters, especially Kate; dysfunctional family situations (especially ones which revolve around the fathers of many characters), as portrayed in the lives of nearly all the main characters; apocalyptic references, including Desmond's pushing the button to forestall the end of the world and the DHARMA Initiative's goal to alter the parameters of the Valenzetti Equation and prevent the end of humanity;Lindelof, Damon and Carlton Cuse.  Buddytv.com, March 7, 2007. coincidence versus fate, revealed most apparently through the juxtaposition of the characters Locke and Mr. Eko; conflict between science and faith, embodied by the leadership tug-of-war between Jack and Locke;Lindelof, Damon,  Carlton Cuse, Jack Bender and Bryan Burk. "Man of Science, Man of Faith."  ''Lost: The Complete Second Season'', Buena Vista Home Entertainment.  September 5, 2006.  Audio commentary, disc 1. and references to numerous works of literature, including mentions and discussions of particular novels. There are also many allusions in characters' names to famous historical thinkers and writers, such as John Locke (after the philosopher) and his alias Jeremy Bentham (after the philosopher), Danielle Rousseau (after philosopher Jean-Jacques Rousseau), Desmond Hume (after philosopher David Hume), Juliet Burke (after philosopher Edmund Burke), Mikhail Bakunin (after the anarchist philosopher), Daniel Faraday (after physicist Michael Faraday), Eloise Hawking (after physicist Stephen Hawking), George Minkowski (after mathematician Hermann Minkowski), Richard Alpert (the birth name of spiritual teacher Ram Dass) and Charlotte Staples Lewis (after author C. S. Lewis).
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="701c5089e083a598667159f1133e152d" name="Pilot2backgammon" sectnum="5#1">../img/701c5089e083a598667159f1133e152d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>