<document id="c407db96a89986aa5f4a52a3e2f00686-1.4" name="Lost_(TV_series)" cat="19">
<text>
''Lost'' is filmed on Panavision 35 mm cameras almost entirely on the Hawaiian island of Oahu. The original island scenes for the pilot were filmed at Mokulē'ia Beach, near the northwest tip of the island. Later beach scenes take place in secluded spots of the famous North Shore. Cave scenes in the first season were filmed on a sound stage built at a Xerox parts warehouse, which had been empty since an employee mass shooting took place there in 1999. Retrieved from Internet Archive on December 8, 2004. The sound-stage and production offices have since moved to the Hawaii Film Office-operated Hawaii Film Studio, where the sets depicting Season 2's "Swan Station" and Season 3's "Hydra Station" interiors were built.
Various urban areas in and around Honolulu are used as stand-ins for locations around the world, including California, New York, Iowa, Miami, South Korea, Iraq, Nigeria, United Kingdom, Paris, Thailand, Berlin and Australia. For example, scenes set in a Sydney Airport were filmed at the Hawaii Convention Center, while a World War II-era bunker was used as an Iraqi Republican Guard installation.  Also, scenes set in Germany during the winter were also filmed in a relatively regular Hawaiian neighborhood, with just crushed ice scattered everywhere to create snow and German automobile signs on the street were used. Several scenes in the Season 3 finale, "Through the Looking Glass," were shot in Los Angeles, including a hospital set borrowed from Grey's Anatomy. Two scenes during season four were filmed in London because Alan Dale who portrays Widmore was at the time performing in the musical Spamalot and was unable to travel to Hawaii. Extensive archives of filming locations are tracked at a repository at the .
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="20e07aa04367ccce165da34062cc1e4b" name="LOSTDock" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/20e07aa04367ccce165da34062cc1e4b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>