<document id="c407db96a89986aa5f4a52a3e2f00686-2" name="Lost_(TV_series)" cat="19">
<text>
Out of the 324 people on board Oceanic Flight 815,Goddard, Drew (writer) & Vaughan, Brian K. (writer) & Williams, Stephen (director), "Confirmed Dead".  ''Lost'', ABC.  Episode 2, season 4.  Aired on February 7, 2008. there are 71 initial survivors (as well as one dog) spread across the three sections of the plane crash. The opening season featured 14 regular speaking roles, making it the second largest cast in a currently airing American prime time television show behind ''Desperate Housewives''. While a large cast makes ''Lost'' more expensive to produce, the writers benefit from more flexibility in story decisions. According to series executive producer Bryan Burk, "You can have more interactions between characters and create more diverse characters, more back stories, more love triangles."

The initial season had 14 major roles getting star billing.  Naveen Andrews portrayed former Iraqi Republican Guard Sayid Jarrah.  Emilie de Ravin played the pregnant Australian Claire Littleton.  Matthew Fox acted as the troubled surgeon and protagonist Jack Shephard.  Jorge Garcia portrayed Hugo "Hurley" Reyes, an unlucky lottery winner.  Maggie Grace played Shannon Rutherford, a former dance teacher.  Josh Holloway acted as con man James "Sawyer" Ford.  Yunjin Kim played Sun-Hwa Kwon, the daughter of a powerful Korean businessman and mobster, with Daniel Dae Kim as her husband Jin-Soo Kwon.  Evangeline Lilly portrayed fugitive Kate Austen.  Dominic Monaghan acted as ex-rock star drug addict Charlie Pace.  Terry O'Quinn played the mysterious John Locke.  Harold Perrineau portrayed construction worker Michael Dawson, while child actor Malcolm David Kelley acted as his young son, Walt Lloyd.  Ian Somerhalder played Boone Carlyle, chief operating officer of his mother's wedding business and step brother of Shannon.

During the first two seasons, some characters were written out to make room for new characters with new stories. Boone Carlyle was the first major character to be written out, dying near the end of season one. Walt became a guest star after the events of the first season's finale, making rare appearances throughout season two. Shannon's departure eight episodes into season two made way for newcomers Mr. Eko, a Nigerian Catholic priest and former criminal played by Adewale Akinnuoye-Agbaje; Ana Lucia Cortez, an airport security guard and former police officer played by Michelle Rodriguez; and Libby, a purported clinical psychologist portrayed by Cynthia Watros. Ana Lucia and Libby were written out of the series toward the end of season two.

In season three, Henry Ian Cusick received star billing as former Scottish soldier Desmond Hume, as did Michael Emerson in the role of Ben Linus (formerly known as Henry Gale), a high ranking member of the "Others." In addition, three new actors joined the regular cast: Elizabeth Mitchell, as fertility doctor and "Other" Juliet Burke, and Kiele Sanchez and Rodrigo Santoro as background survivor couple Nikki Fernandez and Paulo. Eko was written out early in the season, and Nikki and Paulo were written out mid-season in their first flashback episode. Charlie was written out in the third season finale.

In season four, Harold Perrineau rejoined the main cast to reprise the role of Michael Dawson, now suicidal and on a desperate redemptive journey to atone for his previous crimes., ABC7Chicago.com, July 25, 2007. Along with Perrineau, additional new actors — Jeremy Davies as Daniel Faraday, a nervous physicist who takes a scientific interest in the island; Ken Leung as Miles Straume, a sarcastic supposed ghost whisperer, and Rebecca Mader as Charlotte Staples Lewis, a hard-headed and determined anthropologist and successful academic — joined the cast. Claire, who mysteriously disappears with her dead biological father near the end of the season, did not return as a series regular for the fifth season, but will return for the sixth and final season. Michael was written out in the fourth season finale. 

In Season 5, there were no new actors introduced to receive star billing. Saïd Taghmaoui and Zuleikha Robinson as Caesar and Ilana were originally set to appear as main cast members; however, they were downgraded to recurring before the start of the season. ABC did not list Rebecca Mader and Daniel Dae Kim as main cast members in season five. However, Mader was in the promotional material for season five and executive producer Damon Lindelof stated that " is still a series regular on the show". Kim reappeared in the fourth episode of the fifth season, "The Little Prince", and Mader was written out of the series in the fifth episode, as was Jeremy Davies towards the end of the season.

Currently, only two new main cast members have been announced for season 6; Nestor Carbonell as Richard Alpert will be promoted to regular cast status after three seasons as a recurring character, as will Jeff Fahey as Frank Lapidus. Several former cast members, including Ian Somerhalder, Dominic Monaghan, Jeremy Davies, and Elizabeth Mitchell, have been confirmed to make return appearances.

Numerous supporting characters have been given expansive and recurring appearances in the progressive storyline. Danielle Rousseau (Mira Furlan), a French member of an earlier scientific expedition to the island first encountered as a voice recording in the pilot episode, appears throughout the series; she is searching for her daughter, who later turns up in the form of Alex Rousseau (Tania Raymonde).  In the second season, married couple Rose Henderson (L. Scott Caldwell) and Bernard Nadler (Sam Anderson), separated on opposite sides of the island (she with the main characters, he with the tail section survivors) were featured in a flashback episode after being reunited.  Corporate magnate Charles Widmore (Alan Dale) has connections to both Ben and Desmond. Desmond is in love with his daughter Penelope "Penny" Widmore (Sonya Walger). The introduction of the "Others," inhabitants of the island, has featured such characters as Tom aka Mr. Friendly (M. C. Gainey), Ethan Rom (William Mapother), and Richard Alpert (Nestor Carbonell), all of whom have been shown in both flashbacks and the ongoing story.  Jack's father Christian Shephard (John Terry) has appeared in multiple flashbacks of various characters.  In the fourth season, Kevin Durand plays Martin Keamy and The team leader was Naomi Dorrit (Marsha Thomason), the first person to arrive to the island after the crash of Oceanic 815.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="cbf500a4f04fec5be2ff70c3e26fb648" name="LostS5Cast" sectnum="2#1">../img/cbf500a4f04fec5be2ff70c3e26fb648.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>