<document id="c412e1ec8d2bc397f4fa0db5579a0368-9" name="Altrincham" cat="11">
<text>
In 1754, a stretch of road south of Altrincham, along the Manchester to Chester route, was turnpiked. Turnnpikes were toll roads which taxed passengers for the maintenance of the road. Further sections were turnpiked in 1765 from Timperley to Sale, and 1821 from Altrincham to Stockport. The maintenance of roads local authorities in 1888, although by then most turnpike trusts had already declined.Nevell (1997), pp. 95&ndash;97.

Construction on the Bridgewater began in 1759, and on its completion in 1776, it provided a link by water between Manchester and the Irish Sea, via Altrincham. Canals were a quicker and more economical means of travel than roads. The Bridgewater Canal is still in use, although now by leisure craft rather than commercial. 


After a bill was passed in Parliament in 1845, construction of the Manchester South Junction and Altrincham Railway began. It was opened in 20 October 1849 and ran services from Manchester London RoadAwdry (1990), pp. 222–223. via Sale to Altrincham.Nevell (1997), p. 97. In 1931, the MSJAR line was electrified (1500 V DC OLE), one of the first electrified railway lines, supplied by overhead current, in Great Britain. At the same time a further Altrincham station was opened on that line, at Navigation Road, to serve the housing developments in the area. By 1937, there were 130 train services daily between Manchester and Altrincham.  The line was renovated in the early 1990s and is now part of the Metrolink.Nevell (1997), p. 100. Broadheath railway station served the northern part of Altrincham between 1853 and 1962, on the line from Manchester, via Lymm to Warrington.

Altrincham railway station is the southern terminus of one of the lines of the Manchester Metrolink light rail system, which connects it with the centre of Manchester and locations in Greater Manchester such as Sale and Bury. The Metrolink service also serves the Navigation Road railway station. Metrolink services leave around every six minutes between 7:15 and 18:30, and every 12 minutes at other times of the day. Retrieved on 6 May 2007. National Rail services link Altrincham and Navigation Road stations with Chester via Northwich, and with Manchester via Stockport. Altrincham Interchange, next to the railway station, is a hub for local bus routes. Manchester Airport, the largest in the UK outside London, is  to the southeast of the town.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="dc0a89bb77bf1b419ca44944e25e0557" name="Altrinchamstation" sectnum="9#1">../img/dc0a89bb77bf1b419ca44944e25e0557.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>