<document id="c412e1ec8d2bc397f4fa0db5579a0368-6.3" name="Altrincham" cat="11">
<text>
On the outskirts of Altrincham is the 18th-century Dunham Massey Hall Retrieved on 4 February 2007. and its  deer park, both now owned by the National Trust. The hall is early Georgian in style, and it, along with its stables and carriage house, are Grade I listed buildings. Retrieved on 11 July 2007. Another of Altrincham's attractions is the historic market, set up over 800 years ago when the town was first established.

Stamford Park is a  park designed by landscape gardener John Shaw. It was opened to the public in 1880, as a sports park with areas for cricket and football and is now owned and run by Trafford Council. The land was donated by George Grey, the 7th Earl of Stamford. The park is listed as Grade II on the Register of Parks and Gardens of Special Historic Interest in England, Retrieved on 10 July 2007.• Retrieved on 10 July 2007. as well as having won a bronze award from the Greenspace award scheme. Retrieved on 5 September 2008. Trafford council intend to build a £7,000 skate park in Stamford Park as part of a scheme to reduce crime by providing youths with activities. CCTV will be installed to monitor the skate park. Retrieved on 5 September 2008.

The clock outside the main transport interchange was built in 1880, and has been a Grade II listed building since 1985. Retrieved on 4 February 2007. Royd House was built between 1914 and 1916 by local architect Edgar Wood as his own residence. It has a flat concrete roof and a concave façade and is faced in Portland red stone and Lancashire brick. Retrieved on 10 July 2007. It is regarded as one of the most advanced examples of early 20th-century domestic architecture, and is referenced in architectural digests. The house has been a Grade I listed building since 1975, one of six such buildings in Trafford. Retrieved on 4 February 2007. Retrieved on 14 December 2007.

The Old Market Place is thought to stand on the site of the original town settlement. Now a registered conservation area it consists of a series of part timber-framed buildings echoing the wattle and daub constructions of the original houses and burgage plots. The cobblestone paving was replaced in 1896. The Buttermarket which stood in the area near the Old Market Place from the 17th century until the late 19th century was also the site for dispensing early local justice. A courtroom, stocks and whipping post saw public floggings take place there until the early 19th century. The whipping post and stocks were restored as a tourist attraction by local traders in the 1990s. However the Buttermarket area was also a site of religious importance, since prospective brides and grooms are thought to have declared their intentions here. Retrieved on 3 January 2008. In 1814 Thomas de Quincey described the Old Market Place in his ''Confessions of an English Opium Eater'' while travelling from Manchester to Chester. He noted how little the place had changed since he had visited 14 years earlier, when he was three, and that "fruits, such as can be had in July, and flowers were scattered about in profusion: even the stalls of the butchers, from their brilliant cleanliness, appeared attractive: and bonny young women of Altrincham were all tripping about in caps and aprons coquettishly disposed".De Quincey (1994), pp. 75&ndash;76.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b5df1c9c1a634ab96bdb5315ecadd9de" name="Rear_of_Dunham_Massey_Hall_2007" sectnum="6.3#1">../img/b5df1c9c1a634ab96bdb5315ecadd9de.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>