<document id="c412e1ec8d2bc397f4fa0db5579a0368-8" name="Altrincham" cat="11">
<text>
During the medieval and post-medieval period, the township of Altrincham was part of the Bowdon parish. Before the English Reformation, the inhabitants of Sale were predominantly Catholic, but afterwards were members of the Church of England. Altrincham did not have a church until the late 18th century because of a low population density in the area.Bayliss (1992), p. 58. A growing population in led to the Anglican church establishing a chapel of ease in the town in 1799. Nonconformists were also present in Altrincham, Methodists set up a chapel in 1790 Baptists built one in the 1870s.Nevell (1997) pp. 106&ndash;107. Irish immigrants in the 1830s and 1840s brought Catholicism back to the area, and the first Catholic church built in Trafford was St Vincent's in 1860 AltrinchamNevell (1997) pp. 107&ndash;108.

There are five Grade II listed churches in Altrincham: Christ Church, Retrieved on 4 February 2007. the Church of St Alban, Retrieved on 4 February 2007. the Church of St George, Retrieved on 4 February 2007. the Church of St John the Evangelist, Retrieved on 4 February 2007. and Trinity United Reformed Church. Retrieved on 4 February 2007. All these churches have been listed buildings since 1985. There are three Grade II* listed churches in Altrincham out of only nine Grade II* buildings in Trafford: the Church of St Margaret, Retrieved on 4 February 2007. the Church of St John the Divine, Retrieved on 4 February 2007. and Hale Chapel in Hale Barns. Retrieved on 4 February 2007. As of the 2001 UK census, 78.8% of Altrincham's residents reported themselves as being Christian, 1.1% Jewish, 1.1% Muslim, 0.4% Hindu, 0.2% Buddhist and 0.1% Sikh. The census recorded 12.1% as having no religion, 0.2% with an alternative religion, and 6.1% not stating their religion. Retrieved on 30 December 2008. Altrincham is in the Catholic Diocese of Shrewsbury, Retrieved on 7 May 2007. and the Church of England Diocese of Chester. Retrieved on 4 June 2007. The nearest synagogue, belonging to Hale and District Hebrew Congregation, is on Shay Lane in Hale, Retrieved on 6 January 2009. and there are plans to build another close by to cater for Jews of Sephardi origin.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="358599dd5fa8d902afada5db9beee6b7" name="Stgeorgeschurch" sectnum="8#1">../img/358599dd5fa8d902afada5db9beee6b7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>