<document id="c4233b0929e7877777f33026748507b2-1.8" name="James_Russell_Lowell" cat="17">
<text>
He returned to the United States by June 1885, living with his daughter and her husband in Southboro, Massachusetts.Heymann, 145 He then spent time in Boston with his sister before returning to Elmwood in November 1889.Wagenknecht, 18 By this time, most of his friends were dead, including Quincy, Longfellow, Dana, and Emerson, leaving him depressed and contemplating suicide again.Duberman, 339 Lowell spent part of the 1880s delivering various speechesDuberman, 352 and his last published works were mostly collections of essays, including ''Political Essays'', and a collection of his poems ''Heartsease and Rue'' in 1888. His last few years he traveled back to England periodicallyDuberman, 351 and when he returned to the United States in the fall of 1889, he moved back to ElmwoodHeymann, 150 with Mabel, while her husband worked for clients in New York and New Jersey.Duberman, 364–365 That year, Lowell gave an address at the centenary of George Washington's inauguration. Also that year, the Boston ''Critic'' dedicated a special issue to Lowell on his seventieth birthday to recollections and reminiscences by his friends, including former presidents Hayes and Benjamin Harrison and British Prime Minister William Gladstone as well as Alfred Tennyson and Francis Parkman.

In the last few months of his life, Lowell struggled with gout, sciatica in his left leg, and chronic nausea; by the summer of 1891, doctors believed that Lowell had cancer in his kidneys, liver, and lungs. His last few months, he was administered opium for the pain and was rarely fully conscious.Duberman, 370 He died on August 12, 1891, at ElmwoodDuberman, 371 and, after services in the Harvard chapel, was buried in Mount Auburn Cemetery.Sullivan, 223 After his death, Norton served as his literary executor and published several collections of Lowell's works and his letters.Heymann, 152
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="75fcbab0f71c5933fe13069c8b15340f" name="James_Russell_Lowell_grave" sectnum="1.8#1">../img/75fcbab0f71c5933fe13069c8b15340f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>