<document id="c4233b0929e7877777f33026748507b2-1.1" name="James_Russell_Lowell" cat="17">
<text>
The first of the Lowell family ancestors to come to the United States from Britain was Percival Lowle, who settled in Newbury, Massachusetts in 1639.Sullivan, 204 James Russell Lowell was born February 22, 1819,Nelson, 39 the son of the Rev. Charles Russell Lowell, Sr. (1782&ndash;1861), a minister at a Unitarian church in Boston who had previously studied theology at Edinburgh, and Harriett Brackett Spence Lowell.Sullivan, 205 By the time James Russell Lowell was born, the family owned a large estate in Cambridge called Elmwood.Heymann, 55 He was the youngest of six children; his older siblings were Charles, Rebecca, Mary, William, and Robert.Wagenknecht, 11 Lowell's mother built in him an appreciation for literature at an early age, especially in poetry, ballads, and tales from her native Orkney. He attended school under Sophia Dana, who would later marry George Ripley, and, later, studied at a school run by a particularly harsh disciplinarian, where one of his classmates was Richard Henry Dana, Jr.Duberman, 14–15

Beginning in 1834, at the age of 15, Lowell attended Harvard College, though he was not a good student and often got into trouble.Duberman, 17 In his sophomore year alone, he was absent from required chapel attendance 14 times and from classes 56 times.Sullivan, 208 In his last year there, he wrote, "During Freshman year, I did nothing, during Sophomore year I did nothing, during Junior year I did nothing, and during Senior year I have thus far done nothing in the way of college studies". In his senior year, he became one of the editors of ''Harvardiana'' literary magazine, to which he contributed prose and poetry that he admitted was of low quality. As he said later, "I was as great an ass as ever brayed & thought it singing".Duberman, 20 Lowell was elected the poet of the class of 1838Duberman, 26 and, as was tradition, was asked to recite an original poem on Class Day, the day before Commencement, on July 17, 1838. Lowell, however, was suspended and not allowed to participate. Instead, his poem was printed and made available thanks to subscriptions paid by his classmates.

Not knowing what vocation to choose after graduating, he vacillated among business, the ministry, medicine and law. Having decided to practice law, he enrolled at the Harvard Law School in 1840 and was admitted to the bar two years later.Sullivan, 209 While studying law, however, he contributed poems and prose articles to various magazines. During this time, Lowell was admittedly depressed and often had suicidal thoughts. He once confided to a friend that he held a cocked pistol to his forehead and considered killing himself at the age of 20.Wagenknecht, 50
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9189f8f17df4cd1f78383a275976855d" name="Elmwood,_Cambridge,_Massachusetts" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/9189f8f17df4cd1f78383a275976855d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>