<document id="c4233b0929e7877777f33026748507b2-1.7" name="James_Russell_Lowell" cat="17">
<text>
Lowell resigned from his Harvard professorship in 1874, though he was convinced to continue teaching through 1877. It was in 1876 that Lowell first stepped into the field of politics. That year, he served as a delegate to the Republican National Convention in Cincinnati, Ohio, speaking on behalf of presidential candidate Rutherford B. Hayes.Heymann, 136 Hayes won the nomination and, eventually, the presidency. In May 1877, President Hayes, an admirer of ''The Biglow Papers'', sent William Dean Howells to Lowell with a handwritten note proffering an ambassadorship to either Austria or Russia; Lowell declined, but noted his interest in Spanish literature.Duberman, 282 Lowell was then offered and accepted the role of Minister to the court of Spain at an annual salary of $12,000. Lowell sailed from Boston on July 14, 1877, and, though he expected he would be away for a year or two, he would not return to the United States until 1885, with the violinist Ole Bull renting Elmwood for a portion of that time.Duberman, 282–283 The Spanish media referred to him as "José Bighlow".Heymann, 137 Lowell was well-prepared for his political role, having been trained in law, as well as being able to read in multiple languages. He had trouble socializing while in Spain, however, and amused himself by sending humorous dispatches to his political bosses in the United States, many of which were later collected and published posthumously in 1899 as ''Impressions of Spain''.Heymann, 136–138 Lowell's social life improved when the Spanish Academy elected him a corresponding member in late 1878, allowing him input in preparing a new dictionary.Duberman, 294

In January 1880, Lowell was informed he was appointed Minister to England, his nomination made without his knowledge as far back as June 1879. He was granted a salary of $17,500 with about $3,500 for expenses.Duberman, 298–299 While serving in this capacity, he addressed an importation of allegedly diseased cattle and made recommendations that predated the Pure Food and Drug Act.Wagenknecht, 168 Queen Victoria commented that she had never seen an ambassador who "created so much interest and won so much regard as Mr. Lowell".Sullivan, 219 Lowell held this role until the close of Chester A. Arthur's presidency in the spring of 1885, despite his wife's failing health. Lowell was already well known in England for his writing and, during his time there, he befriended fellow author Henry James, who referred to him as "conspicuously American". Lowell also befriended Leslie Stephen during this time and became the godfather to his daughter, future writer Virginia Woolf.Duberman, 447 Lowell was popular enough that he was offered a professorship at Oxford after his recall by president Grover Cleveland, though the offer was declined.Sullivan, 218–219

His second wife, Frances, died on February 19, 1885, while still in England.Heymann, 143
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="61e726a85054e6e7e612f6881ab93d34" name="James_Russell_Lowell,_1819-1891" sectnum="1.7#1">../img/61e726a85054e6e7e612f6881ab93d34.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>