<document id="c476619114d976603cad64beec1ce27c-1.4" name="Alison_Krauss" cat="20">
<text>
Krauss has made multiple guest appearances on other records with lead vocals, harmony vocals, or fiddle playing. In 1997 she contributed harmony vocals in both English and Irish to Irish traditional band Altan's ''Runaway Sunday'' album. She has contributed to numerous motion picture soundtracks, most notably the soundtrack ''O Brother, Where Art Thou?'' in 2000.''O Brother, Where Art Thou?'' soundtrack. Originally released by Lost Highway on December 5, 2000. She and co-vocalist Dan Tyminski contributed multiple tracks to the soundtrack, including "I'll Fly Away" (with Gillian Welch), "Down to the River to Pray", and "I Am a Man of Constant Sorrow." 

In the film, Tyminski's vocals on "I Am a Man of Constant Sorrow" became the singing voice of George Clooney. for BBC News on February 28, 2002. Retrieved June 25, 2006. The soundtrack sold over seven million copies and won the Grammy for Album of the Year in 2002. by Parke Puterbaugh for the Attache in February 2005. Retrieved June 5, 2006. The unexpected success of the album has been partially credited, as was Krauss herself, on East Coast Entertainment. Retrieved June 24, 2006.Interview on NPR ''Morning Edition'' with Bob Edwards on February 15, 2002. . Retrieved July 10, 2006. with bringing a new interest in bluegrass to the United States. on Musicians Guide.com. Retrieved July 26, 2008. She has said, however, that she believes Americans already liked bluegrass and other less-heard musical genres, and that the film merely provided easy exposure to the music. with PBS via the Wayback Machine May 3, 2002. Retrieved July 28, 2009. She did not appear in the movie, at her own request, as she was nine months pregnant during its filming. on BarnesAndNoble.com August 14, 2001. Retrieved June 24, 2006. 

In 2007, Krauss released the anthology ''A Hundred Miles Or More: A Collection'' which was a collection of soundtrack work, duets with artists such as John Waite, James Taylor, Brad Paisley and esteemed fiddle player Natalie MacMaster, and newer tracks. The album was very commercially successful, but was received with a lukewarm reception from critics. One of the tracks, "Missing You", a duet with Waite (and a cover of his hit single from 1984), was similarly received as a single. On August 11, television network Great American Country aired a one-hour special, "Alison Krauss: A Hundred Miles or More" based on the album and featured many of the album's duets and solo performances.

Other soundtracks for which Krauss has performed include ''Twister'', ''The Prince of Egypt'',''The Prince of Egypt'' "Nashville" soundtrack. Originally released by One Way Records October 1, 2001. ''Eight Crazy Nights'', ''Mona Lisa Smile'', ''Divine Secrets of the Ya-Ya Sisterhood'', ''Alias'', ''Bambi II'' and ''Cold Mountain''. from the SoundtrackINFO project. Retrieved June 5, 2006. She also contributed the song "Jubilee" to the 2004 documentary ''Paper Clips''. The ''Cold Mountain'' songs "The Scarlet Tide" by T-Bone Burnett and Elvis Costello, and "You Will Be My Ain True Love", by herself and Sting were nominated for an Academy Award, and she performed both songs at the 76th Academy Awards, the first one with Costello and Burnett and the other with Sting. by Toni Thompson for the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences via the Wayback Machine on February 14, 2004. Retrieved July 28, 2009. She also worked as a producer for Nickel Creek on their debut self-titled album in 2000 and the follow-up ''This Side'' in 2002, which won Krauss her first Grammy as a music producer.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6dcf4040b3d837f0c1c832fd5e228f10" name="KraussPlantNIA2008" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/6dcf4040b3d837f0c1c832fd5e228f10.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>