<document id="c4b608d19f3136d5cf4fa2cec9525a8a-3" name="Hovhannes_Bagramyan" cat="29">
<text>
Following the toppling of the Provisional Government by the Bolsheviks in October 1917, the Red Army invaded the southern Caucasus republics of Azerbaijan, Georgia and Armenia. In May 1920, Bagramyan initiated a local rebellion against the Dashnak-led government of Armenia and joined the 11th Soviet Army.Salisbury, Harrison E. ''The 900 Days: The Siege of Leningrad''. Cambridge: Da Capo Press, 2003 p. 112 ISBN 0-3068-1298-3 Победа.py . Accessed April 8, 2007. He was appointed a cavalry regiment commander, taking part in several battles during the Russian Civil War, and also fighting against Armenian and Georgian nationalist forces. In 1923, he was appointed commander of the Alexandropol Cavalry Regiment, a position he held until 1931. Two years later, Bagramyan graduated from the Leningrad Cavalry School and, in 1934, from the Frunze Military Academy.

In his memoirs, Pyotr Grigorenko, a Ukrainian commander who attended Frunze, wrote about how Bagramyan was expelled from the academy by his superiors after they learned he had been a secret member of the banned Dashnak Armenian nationalist party for more than a decade. Pending his arrest, Grigorenko described Bagramyan "deeply depressed, saying he only wished they'd arrest him soon so that he could get it over with."Grigorenko, Pyotr. ''Memoirs''. New York: W. W. Norton & Company, 1984, p. 90 ISBN 0-3930-1570-X Grigorenko advised that he appeal the arrest warrant which Bagramyan reluctantly did and, with the help of Armenian politburo member Anastas Mikoyan, the arrest warrant was revoked and he accepted to be "rehabilitated."Wegner, Bernd ed. ''From Peace to War: Germany, Soviet Russia and the World, 1939–1941''. Providence, RI: Berghahn Books, 1997 p. 402 ISBN 1-5718-1882-0 From 1934 to 1936, he served as the chief of staff of the 5th Cavalry Division, and from 1938, he worked as a senior instructor and lecturer at the Military Academy of the Soviet General Staff. Concurrently, Soviet leader Joseph Stalin had purged much of the Soviet officer corps of its veteran commanders. While fellow students from the military academy, Andrei Yeremenko and Georgy Zhukov, had seen their careers rise, Bagramyan's had remained stagnant.Jukes. ''Stalin's Generals'', p. 25

In 1940, when General Zhukov was promoted to commander of the Kiev Military District in the Ukraine, Bagramyan wrote a letter asking to serve under his command. Zhukov agreed, and in December asked for his help writing a paper to be presented to the commanders of the Soviet Military Districts. Bagramyan's paper, ''Conducting a Contemporary Offensive Operation,'' apparently impressed Zhukov, as he promoted Bagramyan to become the head of Operations for the Soviet 12th Army based in the Ukraine.Ibid., p. 25 Within three months however, Bagramyan, then a colonel, was appointed deputy chief of staff of the Southwestern Front, headquartered in Kiev.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="84b153b9ae70422dc449a853d5a3eeb7" name="Bagramyan1938" sectnum="3#1">../img/84b153b9ae70422dc449a853d5a3eeb7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>