<document id="c4b608d19f3136d5cf4fa2cec9525a8a-4.1" name="Hovhannes_Bagramyan" cat="29">
<text>
In June 1941, Nazi Germany violated the Molotov-Ribbentrop non-aggression pact and invaded the Soviet Union. Unlike many of the border troops who were caught off guard by the offensive, Bagramyan and his commander, General Mikhail Kirponos believed an invasion by Germany was inevitable.Erickson, John. ''The Road to Stalingrad: Stalin's War with Germany, Volume One''. New Haven, Connecticut: Yale University Press, 1999 p. 359 ISBN 0-3000-7812-9 However, Kipronos chose to ignore Bagramyan's viewpoint that the German offensive would employ the lightning speed Blitzkrieg tactics like those used in the campaigns in Poland in 1939 and Western Europe in 1940.Jukes. ''Stalin's Generals'', p. 26 Since the winter of 1939–40, Bagramyan had been busy devising a battle plan that would counter threats from the western Ukraine that was approved after numerous revisions on May 10, 1940.Salisbury. ''The 900 Days'', p. 71

On the morning of June 22, he was tasked with the overseeing of a transfer of a military convoy to Ternopol. While his column was passing the Soviet airfields near the city of Brody, German air strikes hit the aircraft on the ground. Several hours later, they arrived in Ternopol, having been strafed twice by the planes.Salisbury. ''The 900 Days'', p. 73 Three days after the invasion, the plans for the counter-offensive were implemented, but disorder engulfed the troops, and the counter-attack collapsed. Bagramyan, Ivan K. ''Тak Шли Mы K Пoбeдe'' (Thus We Went to Victory). Moscow: Voenizdat, 1977 pp. 129–130 Bagramyan took part in the great tank battles in western Ukraine and the defensive operation around Kiev, in which Kirponos was killed and the entire Front captured by the Germans. He was one of a handful of senior officers who escaped from the encircled Front.

Bagramyan was then appointed chief of staff to Marshal Semyon Timoshenko and along with future Soviet premier Nikita Khrushchev, then a political officer, coordinated the fighting around Rostov. In his memoirs, Khrushchev described Bagramyan as a "very precise person who reported on everything just as it was. How many troops we had, their positions, and the general situation."Khrushchev, Nikita. ''Memoirs of Nikita Khrushchev: Volume 1, Commissar (1918–1945)''. Philadelphia: Pennsylvania State University Press, 2005 p. 322 ISBN 0-2710-2332-5

Khrushchev went on to detail an account in where Marshal Semyon Budyonny, sent by the chief of the operations department from the Soviet capital of Moscow to Kiev and representing the STAVKA, courtmartialed Bagramyan,Khrushchev. ''Memoirs'', p. 321 who protested and stated that if he was an incapable staff officer, then he should instead be given a field unit to command. To Bagramyan's astonishment, Budyonny went on to attempt to convince him to agree to his execution. Khrushchev remarked that the argument was essentially sparked arbitrarily and had taken place after an "abundant feast with cognac" and that "in those days we didn't take that kind of conversation seriously."Khrushchev. ''Memoirs'', pp. 321–322 According to him, at the time however, the Soviet military was especially suspicious of the men in its ranks, itself judging that there were "enemies of the people...everywhere, especially the Red Army."Khrushchev. ''Memoirs'', p. 317

Bagramyan was instrumental in the planning of two Soviet counter-offensives against the Germans, including the major push made by Soviet forces in December during the battle of Moscow, and for this was promoted to the rank of Lieutenant General. In the same month, he was made the chief of staff of a military operations group that would oversee three Army Groups: the Southern, the Southwestern and Bryansk Fronts. In March 1942, he went along with Khrushchev and Timoshenko to Moscow to present the plans of a new counter-offensive in the Ukrainian city of Kharkov to Stalin. Stalin, impressed with his plan, approved the operation and on April 8, promoted Bagramyan as Chief of Staff of the Southwestern Front. On May 12, 1942, armies of the Southwestern Front attacked Kharkov but the launch of the offensive came at an inopportune moment since they were attacking from the Barvenkovo Salient, a region that German forces were near closing.Jukes. ''Stalin's Generals'', pp. 26–27

While Soviet forces were initially successful in recapturing Kharkov, they found themselves trapped by the German army after the closing of Barvenkovo. On May 18, Bagramyan asked Timoshenko to alter the plans but Timoshenko along with Stalin refused to approve his request. Baghramyan, Hovhannes. ''Այսպես է Սկսվել Պատերազմը'' (This is How the War Began). Trans. from Russian. Yerevan, Armenian SSR, 1975 pp. 116–117 Soviet losses were heavy as the 6th, 9th and 57th armies (approximately 18–20 divisions) comprising a large portion of the Southwestern Front, were all destroyed and Bagramyan was removed from his post on June 28 by STAVKA. According to Khrushchev, Bagramyan was so devastated from the immense loss of men that after the operation was called off, "he burst into tears. His nerves cracked...He was weeping for our army."Taubman, William. ''Khrushchev: The Man and His Era''. New York: W. W. Norton & Company, 2003 p. 166 ISBN 0-393-32484-2 Held responsible for the failure of the operation and "poor staff work", he was demoted to chief of staff of the Soviet 28th Army.Tompson, William J. ''Khrushchev: A Political Life''. New York: Palgrave MacMillan, 1995 p. 80 ISBN 0-3121-6360-6 Several days later, he wrote a letter to Stalin asking to "serve at the front at any capacity, however modest."Jukes. ''Stalin's Generals'', p. 27 British military historian John Erickson however contends that Bagramyan was unfairly scapegoated by Stalin in his attempts to "hunt for  culprits" of the mismanagement of operations.Erickson. ''The Road to Stalingrad'', p. 359
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a8443dbc70cac073790ec85b6d76536d" name="Bagramyan%26commanders" sectnum="4.1#1">../img/a8443dbc70cac073790ec85b6d76536d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>