<document id="c4b9c5f77993b1a782249c699c79b871-2.9" name="Operation_Ke" cat="29">
<text>
On February 4, Patch ordered the 161st Infantry Regiment to replace the 147th at the front and resume the advance westward.  The Yano battalion retreated to new positions at the Segilau River and troops were sent to block the advance of George's force along the south coast.  Meanwhile, Halsey's carrier and battleship task forces remained just beyond Japanese air attack range about  south of Guadalcanal.Frank, p. 589–590, Jersey, p. 378–380, 383, 400–401, Miller p. 342–343, 346.  The Japanese knew the approximate size of George's force after extracting the information from two American soldiers captured in a skirmish near Titi on the south coast.  After their interrogations, the two Americans were summarily executed.  Assisting the Yano Battalion, now numbering about 350 men after battle losses, were about 60 men from the 124th and 28th Infantry Regiments.  On February 3, the Japanese lost five G4M bombers from an abortive attack on Halsey's fleet, including one carrying Lieutenant Commander Genichi Mihara, commander of the 705th Air Group.  The US 161st Regiment at this time was under the command of Colonel James Dalton II (Miller, p. 346).

Kondo sent two of his force's destroyers, ''Asagumo'' and ''Samidare'', to the Shortlands to replace the two destroyers lost in the first evacuation run.  Hashimoto led the second evacuation mission with 20 destroyers south towards Guadalcanal at 11:30 on February 4.  The CAF attacked Hashimoto in two waves beginning at 15:50 with a total of 74 aircraft.  Bomb near-misses heavily damaged ''Maikaze'', and Hashimoto detached ''Nagatsuki'' to tow her back to Shortland.  The CAF lost 11 aircraft in the attack while the Japanese lost one Zero.Frank, p. 590–591, Morison, p. 369–370, Jersey, p. 395, Dull, p. 268.  US aircraft losses included four TBFs, three SBDs, three Wildcats, and one P-40.  ''Maikaze'' went to Japan for repairs which were completed in July 1943 (Nevitt, ''CombinedFleet.com'').

The US PT boats did not sortie to attack Hashimoto's force this night and the loading went uneventfully.  The Reinforcement Force embarked Hyakutake, his staff, and 3,921 men, mainly from the 2nd Division, and reached Bougainville without incident by 12:50 on February 5.  A CAF airstrike launched that morning failed to locate Hashimoto's force.Griffith, p 285, Frank, p. 591, Morison, p. 370.  The evacuees included Masao Maruyama, commander of the 2nd Division.  Japanese aircraft harassed Henderson Field and one PBY Catalina and five SBDs from the CAF tried to attack Hashimoto without success during the loading.

Believing that the Japanese operations on February 1 and 4 had been reinforcement, not evacuation missions, the American forces on Guadalcanal proceeded slowly and cautiously, advancing only about  each day.  George's force halted on February 6 after advancing to Titi on the south coast.  On the north coast, the 161st finally began their attack westward at 10:00 on February 6 and reached the Umasani River the same day.  At the same time, the Japanese were withdrawing their remaining 2,000 troops to Kamimbo.Jersey, p. 391, 394, Frank, p. 592–591, Miller, p. 345–346.  The Japanese rear guard was commanded by a Colonel Yutaka Matsuda.

On February 7, the 161st crossed the Umasani and reached Bunina, about  from Cape Esperance.  George's force, now commanded by George F. Ferry, advanced from Titi to Marovovo and dug in for the night about  north of the village.Jersey, p. 383, Frank, p. 593–594, Miller, p. 345–347.

Aware of the presence of Halsey's carriers and other large warships near Guadalcanal, the Japanese considered canceling the third evacuation run, but decided to go ahead as planned.  Kondo's force closed to within  of Guadalcanal from the north to be ready in case Halsey's warships attempted to intervene.  Hashimoto departed the Shortlands with 18 destroyers midday of February 7, this time taking a course south of the Solomons instead of down the Slot.  A CAF strike force of 36 aircraft attacked Hashimoto at 17:55, heavily damaging ''Isokaze'' with a bomb near miss.  ''Isokaze'' retired escorted by ''Kawakaze''.  The Allies and the Japanese each lost one aircraft in the attack.Frank, p. 594–595, Morison, p. 370, Jersey, p. 396, Dull, p. 268.  The CAF strike force consisted of 15 SBDs, 20 Wildcats, and one F5A.  The F5A and one of the 49 Zeros escorting the convoy were shot down.  Ten crewmembers were killed on ''Isokaze'', which was repaired at Truk and returned to action in March 1943 (Nevitt, ''CombinedFleet.com'').

Arriving off Kamimbo, Hashimoto's force loaded 1,972 soldiers by 00:03 on February 8, unhindered by the US Navy.  For an additional hour and a half, destroyer crewmen rowed their boats along the shore calling out again and again to make sure no one was left behind.  At 01:32 the Reinforcement Group left Guadalcanal in its wake and reached Bougainville without incident at 10:00, completing the operation.Griffith, p 285–286, Frank, p. 595, Morison, p. 370, Jersey, p. 396–400, Dull, p. 268. According to Jersey, the Yano Battalion had lost a total of 101 men covering the withdrawal.  ''Yūgumo'' and ''Akigumo'' retrieved the Japanese troops from the Russells.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c218fdca4076120902de57ba5ac9deec" name="Asagumo-1" sectnum="2.9#1">../img/c218fdca4076120902de57ba5ac9deec.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>