<document id="c4b9c5f77993b1a782249c699c79b871-3" name="Operation_Ke" cat="29">
<text>
At dawn on February 8, the US Army forces on both coasts resumed their advances, encountering only a few sick and dying Japanese soldiers.  Patch now realized that the Tokyo Express runs over the last week were evacuation, not reinforcement missions.  At 16:50 on February 9, the two American forces met on the west coast at the village of Tenaro.  Patch sent a message to Halsey stating, "Total and complete defeat of Japanese forces on Guadalcanal effected 16:25 today...the Tokyo Express no longer has a terminus on Gudalcanal."Jersey, p. 383, Frank, p. 596–597, Morison, p. 371, Miller, p. 346–348.

The Japanese had successfully evacuated a total of 10,652 men from Guadalcanal, about all that remained of the 36,000 total troops sent to the island during the campaign.  Six hundred of the evacuees succumbed to their injuries or illnesses before they could receive sufficient medical care.  Three thousand more required lengthy hospitalization or recuperation.  After receiving word of the completion of the operation, Yamamoto commended all the units involved and ordered Kondo to return to Truk with his warships.  The 2nd and 38th Divisions were shipped to Rabaul and partially reconstituted with replacements.  The 2nd Division was relocated to the Philippines in March 1943 while the 38th was assigned to defend Rabaul and New Ireland.  The 8th Area Army and Southeast Area Fleet reoriented their forces to defend the central Solomons at Kolombangara and New Georgia and prepared to send the reinforcements, mainly consisting of the 51st Infantry Division, originally detailed for Guadalcanal to New Guinea.  The 17th Army was rebuilt around the 6th Infantry Division and headquartered on Bougainville.  A few Japanese stragglers remained on Guadalcanal, many of whom were subsequently killed or captured by Allied patrols.  The last known Japanese survivor surrendered in October 1947.Frank, p. 596–597, Morison, p. 370–371, Rottman, p. 64–65, D'Albas, p. 238, Griffith, p. 269, 286, Jersey, p. 400–401, Hayashi, p. 65–66.  Morison and D'Albas say 11,706 were evacuated.  Hayashi says 11,083.  More recent historical accounts use the 10,652 number.  Among the last soldiers evacuated were 264 members of the 28th Infantry Regiment, all that remained of the 1,945 landed in August and September, 1942.  Of the approximately 4,000 members of the 35th Infantry Brigade landed in August and September, 1942, 618 were evacuated during ''Ke''.  IJN personnel evacuated numbered 870, the rest were IJA.  Jersey says that "hundreds" of stragglers were left behind on Guadalcanal.  The Japanese 51st Infantry Division was almost completely wiped out en route to New Guinea during the Battle of the Bismarck Sea in March 1943.

In hindsight, historians have faulted the Americans, especially Patch and Halsey, for not taking advantage of their ground, aerial, and naval superiority to prevent the successful Japanese evacuation of most of their surviving forces from Guadalcanal.  Said Chester Nimitz, commander of Allied forces in the Pacific, of the success of Operation Ke, "Until the last moment it appeared that the Japanese were attempting a major reinforcement effort.  Only the skill in keeping their plans disguised and bold celerity in carrying them out enabled the Japanese to withdraw the remnants of the Guadalcanal garrison.  Not until all organized forces had been evacuated on 8 February did we realize the purpose of their air and naval dispositions."Griffith, p. 285–286, Frank, p. 597, Zimmerman, p. 162.

Nevertheless, the successful campaign to recapture Guadalcanal from the Japanese was an important strategic victory for the US and its allies.  Building on their success at Guadalcanal and elsewhere, the Allies continued their campaign against Japan, ultimately culminating in Japan's defeat and the end of World War II.Frank, p. 597, Rottman, p. 64, Miller, p. 348–350.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="25216b189ee5b90e163c4be451313c46" name="OperationKeEvacPainting" sectnum="3#1">../img/25216b189ee5b90e163c4be451313c46.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>