<document id="c4b9c5f77993b1a782249c699c79b871-1.3" name="Operation_Ke" cat="29">
<text>
On January 3, IGH informed the 8th Area Army and the Combined Fleet of the decision to withdraw from Guadalcanal.  By January 9, the Combined Fleet and 8th Area Army staffs together completed the plan, officially called Operation ''Ke'' after a mora in Japanese Kana vocabulary, to execute the evacuation.Miller, p. 338, Frank, p. 540–541, Morison, p. 333–334, Rottman, p. 64, Griffith, p. 269, Jersey, p. 384, Hayashi, p. 64.  Imamura and Jinichi Kusaka, IJN commander at Rabaul, at first objected to the withdrawal order but accepted it on being reminded that it had the Emperor's endorsement.

The plan called for a battalion of army infantry to land by destroyer on Guadalcanal around January 14 to act as a rear guard during the evacuation.  The 17th Army was to begin withdrawing to the western end of the island about January 25 or 26.  An air superiority campaign around the southern Solomons would begin on January 28.  The 17th Army would be picked up in three lifts by destroyers the first week of February with a target completion date of February 10.  At the same time, Japanese air and naval assets would conduct conspicuous maneuvers and minor attacks around New Guinea and the Marshall Islands along with deceptive radio traffic to try to confuse the Allies as to the Japanese intentions.Frank, p. 541, Morison, p. 340.

Yamamoto detailed aircraft carriers ''Junyō'' and ''Zuihō'', battleships ''Kongō'' and ''Haruna'', and four heavy cruisers plus a destroyer screening force under Nobutake Kondo to provide distant cover for ''Ke'' around Ontong Java in the northern Solomons.  The evacuation runs were to be carried out by Mikawa's 8th Fleet, consisting of heavy cruisers ''Chōkai'' and ''Kumano'', light cruiser ''Sendai'', and 21 destroyers.  Mikawa's destroyers were charged with conducting the actual evacuation.  Yamamoto expected that at least half of Mikawa's destroyers would be sunk during the operation.Frank, p. 542, 547–550, Morison, p. 338, 363, Rottman, p. 64, Griffith, p. 278, Jersey, p. 392–393.   The 21 destroyers do not include ''Suzukaze'' and ''Hatsukaze'' which were damaged on Tokyo Express runs to Guadalcanal on January 2 and 10.  ''Suzukaze'' was damaged in the Slot by a near miss from a bomb dropped by a CAF aircraft.  ''Hatsukaze'' was damaged by a PT boat torpedo between Doma Cove and Tassafaronga at Guadalcanal.  Both Express missions together were able to successfully deliver about 80 tons of supplies, a significant boost for the 17th Army's depleted stores.  Kondo's force consisted of carriers ''Zuiho'' and ''Junyō'', battleships ''Kongo'' and ''Haruna'', heavy cruisers ''Atago'', ''Takao'', ''Myōkō'', and ''Haguro'', light cruisers ''Jintsū'', ''Agano'', and ''Nagara'', destroyers ''Kagero'', ''Asagumo'', ''Shigure'', ''Suzumaze'', ''Samidare'', ''Ōshio'', ''Hatsuyuki'', ''Shikinami'', ''Arashio'', and ''Arashi'', and support ships ''Nippon Maru'' and ''Kenyo Maru''.

Supporting the air superiority portion of the operation were the IJN's 11th Air Fleet and the IJA's 6th Air Division, based at Rabaul with 212 and 100 aircraft, respectively.  In addition, 64 aircraft from carrier ''Zuikaku's'' air group were temporarily assigned to Rabaul.  An additional 60 floatplanes from the IJN's "R" Area Air Force, based at Rabaul, Bougainville, and the Shortland Islands, brought the total number of Japanese aircraft involved in the operation to 436.  The combined Japanese warship and naval air units in the area formed the Southeast Area Fleet, commanded by Jinichi Kusaka at Rabaul.Frank, p. 543.

Opposing the Japanese and under the command of US Navy Admiral William Halsey, Jr., commander of Allied forces in the South Pacific, were fleet carriers ''Enterprise'' and ''Saratoga'', six escort carriers, three fast battleships, four old battleships, 13 cruisers, and 45 destroyers.  In the air, the 13th Air Force numbered 92 fighters and bombers under US Army Brigadier General Nathan F. Twining and the CAF on Guadalcanal counted 81 aircraft under US Marine Brigadier General Francis P. Mulcahy.  Rear Admiral Aubrey Fitch was overall commander of Aircraft South Pacific.  The air units of the fleet and escort carriers added another 339 aircraft.  In addition, 30 heavy bombers were stationed in New Guinea with sufficient range to conduct missions over the Solomon Islands.  In total, the Allies possessed around 539 aircraft available to oppose the ''Ke'' operation.Frank, p. 542–543.  The four old battleships in Halsey's fleet were ''Maryland'', ''Colorado'', ''New Mexico'' and ''Mississippi'' (Frank, p. 751).  Fifty-five B-17 and 60 B-24 bombers with the range to reach Guadalcanal were assigned to the Fifth Air Force in New Guinea but only about 30 of them were operational at any one time (Frank, p. 752).

By the first week of January, disease, starvation, and battle had reduced Hyakutake's command to about 14,000 troops, with many of them too sick and malnourished to fight. The 17th Army possessed three operable field cannon and a severe shortage of artillery shells. In contrast, the Allied commander on the island, US Army Major General Alexander Patch, fielded a combined force of US Army and US Marines, designated the XIV Corps, totaling 50,666 men. At Patch's disposal were 167 artillery weapons, including 75mm, 105mm, and 155mm guns, and plentiful stocks of shells.Frank, p. 543–544, Rottman, p. 64.  American artillery totals do not include anti-aircraft or coastal defense guns (Frank, p. 752).  At this time the Japanese 2nd Division was down to 3,700 still alive of the original 12,000 delivered to Guadalcanal.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fa12dedfbbda76d334bb7c357c272a52" name="Gunichi_Mikawa" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/fa12dedfbbda76d334bb7c357c272a52.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>