<document id="c4f1d24899f46e19ee21819f3e56b7c3-5.5" name="Columbia_Slough" cat="11">
<text>
Historically Fairview Creek flowed north into the Columbia River through a wetlands slightly upstream of Big Four Corners. In the early 20th century, water managers dug an artificial channel connecting the Fairview Creek wetlands to the slough. In 1960, they built a dam on the west side of the wetlands to create Fairview Lake for water storage and recreation. It covers about  and is  deep. Fairview Creek forms in a wetland near Grant Butte and flows north for  through the cities of Gresham and Fairview to reach the lake. Fairview Creek has two named tributaries, No Name Creek, and Clear Creek. A smaller stream, Osborn Creek, also flows into the lake, which empties through a weir and culvert system into the upper slough. 

With one exception, the streams feeding Fairview Lake are the watershed's only remaining creeks, although springs also reach the surface.Portland Bureau of Environmental Services, "Chapter 5: Stream Flow and Hydrology", p. 5. Wilkes Creek, the slough's only free flowing tributary, is about  long and enters the upper slough from the south.Portland Bureau of Environmental Services, "Chapter 5: Streamflow and Hydrology", p. 8 Dozens of similar streams that once flowed into the slough from the south have all been piped or filled.

Many bodies of water in addition to the main slough channel lie within the drainage basin. The area around the middle slough contains several slough arms and small lakes, including Buffalo Slough, Whitaker Slough, Johnson Lake, Whitaker Ponds, and Prison Pond. In the lower slough, Smith and Bybee Wetlands Natural Area at  is one of the largest urban freshwater wetlands in the United States. A  side slough called North Slough connects Bybee Lake and the main slough channel. A water control structure at the outlet from Bybee Lake to the North Slough regulates the lakes' levels.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ecf0689982c612dbcf1bd6eea9316bd3" name="Smith_lake" sectnum="5.5#1">../img/ecf0689982c612dbcf1bd6eea9316bd3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>