<document id="c4f1d24899f46e19ee21819f3e56b7c3-5.4" name="Columbia_Slough" cat="11">
<text>
Until the 20th century, the slough and its side channels and associated ponds and lakes were part of the active Columbia River floodplain. When the historic river was high, the slough received water from it near Big Four Corners, about  from the slough's mouth.Portland BES, "Chapter 5: Stream Flow and Hydrology", p. 2  In 1917, property owners formed three drainage districts&mdash;Peninsula Drainage District No. 1 (Pen 1), Peninsula Drainage District No. 2 (Pen 2), and Multnomah County Drainage District No. 1 (MCDD)&mdash;to control flooding. A fourth district, the Sandy Drainage Improvement Company (SDIC), formed in 1939 to manage water flow between the east side of Fairview Lake and the Sandy River further east. By 2008, the districts maintained  of levees as well as water pumps, floodgates and other water control devices. 

The upper slough extends from the slough's source at Fairview Lake, roughly  from the mouth, to a gated levee known as the ''mid-dike levee'' about  downstream. This sector, managed by MCDD, covers  completely surrounded by levees. A northern side channel extends from the mid-dike levee to MCDD Pump Station No. 4 on the Columbia River (Marine Drive) levee near Big Four Corners. Water usually exits this sector through the open gates of the mid-dike levee, but to control threatening flows the MCDD can close the gate and pump water from the northern side channel directly into the Columbia. The pump's maximum capacity is  per minute.Portland Bureau of Environmental Services, "Chapter 5: Stream Flow and Hydrology", pp. 6&ndash;8. 

The middle slough, also managed by MCDD, lies between the mid-dike levee and the ''Pen 2 levee'',  from the mouth. This sector covers , is completely surrounded by levees, and contains many side sloughs, ponds, small lakes, and springs. Pump Station No. 1 rests on the Pen 2 levee, which is gated across the course of the slough. To control flows, MCDD can open or close the gates, and it can pump water from the middle slough to the lower slough when its flow is reversed by the tide or when gravity flow is insufficient. The pump's capacity is 250,000 U.S. gallons per minute (16,000 L/s).

Water levels in the lower slough, managed by Pen 2 and Pen 1, depend more on Willamette River conditions than on pumping by MCDD. Incoming tides cause a variation in water surface elevation of between  and  roughly twice per day along the entire lower slough. Flow direction varies with the tide. Pen 2 and Pen 1, separated by Interstate 5, border the north side of the lower slough. Pen 2 manages  east of the highway, and Pen 1 manages  to the west (downstream). Multiple pump stations move water from lesser sloughs in both districts into the main slough. Parts of this subwatershed are unprotected by levees and are vulnerable to 100-year floods.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c5f33010f84f5533b1c7bf7970c800fc" name="Upper_ColumbiaSlough" sectnum="5.4#1">../img/c5f33010f84f5533b1c7bf7970c800fc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>