<document id="c51ec5e5956385c9e8ad08453f1e7db6-2.5" name="Battle_of_Savo_Island" cat="29">
<text>
Map of the action northeast of Savo.When Mikawa's ships attacked the Allied southern force, the captains of all three U.S. northern force cruisers were asleep, with their ships steaming quietly at .Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', pp. 40–47. Although crewmen on all three ships observed flares or gunfire from the battle south of Savo or else received ''Patterson''’s warning of threatening ships entering the area, it took some time for the crews to go from Condition II to full alert.Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', pp. 217–221. At 01:44, the Japanese cruisers began firing torpedoes at the northern force. At 01:50, they aimed powerful searchlights at the three northern cruisers and opened fire with their guns.

''Astoria''’s bridge crew called general quarters upon sighting the flares south of Savo, around 01:49. At 01:52, shortly after the Japanese searchlights came on and shells began falling around the ship, ''Astoria''’s main gun director crews spotted the Japanese cruisers and opened fire. ''Astoria''’s captain, awakened to find his ship in action, rushed to the bridge and ordered a cease fire, fearful that his ship might be firing on friendly forces. As shells continued to cascade around his ship, the captain ordered firing resumed less than a minute later. However, ''Chōkai'' had found the range, and ''Astoria'' was quickly hit by numerous shells and set afire.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', pp. 41–44. ''Astoria''’s captain's exact words upon arriving on the bridge were, "Topper, I think we are firing on our own ships. Let's not get excited and act too hasty! Cease firing!" ''Astoria''’s gunnery officer replied to this command with, "For God's sake give the word to commence firing!" The captain, after witnessing ''Chōkai''’s fourth salvo straddle his ship, declared, "Whether our ships or not, we will have to stop them. Commence firing!" (Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', pp. 226–227.) Between 02:00 and 02:15, ''Aoba'', ''Kinugasa'', and ''Kako'' joined ''Chōkai'' in pounding ''Astoria'', destroying the cruiser's engine room and bringing the flaming ship to a halt. At 02:16, one of ''Astoria''’s remaining operational main gun turrets fired at ''Kinugasa''’s searchlight, but missed and hit ''Chōkai''’s forward turret, causing moderate damage.Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', p. 231.

''Quincy'' had also seen the aircraft flares over the southern ships, received ''Patterson''’s warning, and had just sounded general quarters and was coming alert when the searchlights from the Japanese column came on. ''Quincy''’s captain gave the order to commence firing, but the gun crews were not ready. Within a few minutes, ''Quincy'' was caught in a crossfire between ''Aoba'', ''Furutaka'', and ''Tenryū'', and was hit heavily and set afire. ''Quincy''’s captain ordered his cruiser to charge towards the eastern Japanese column, but as she turned to do so ''Quincy'' was hit by two torpedoes from ''Tenryū'', causing severe damage. ''Quincy'' managed to fire a few main gun salvos, one of which hit ''Chōkai''’s chart room 6 meters (20 ft) from Admiral Mikawa and killed or wounded 36 men, although Mikawa was not injured. At 02:10, incoming shells killed or wounded almost all of ''Quincy''’s bridge crew, including the captain. At 02:16, the cruiser was hit by a torpedo from ''Aoba'', and the ship's remaining guns were silenced. ''Quincy''’s assistant gunnery officer, sent to the bridge to ask for instructions, reported on what he found: ''Quincy'' sank, bow first, at 02:38.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', pp. 111–113.

 Like ''Quincy'' and ''Astoria'', ''Vincennes'' also sighted the aerial flares to the south, and furthermore, actually sighted gunfire from the southern engagement. At 01:50, when the U.S. cruisers were illuminated by the Japanese searchlights, ''Vincennes'' hesitated to open fire, believing that the searchlight's source might be friendly ships. Shortly thereafter, ''Kako'' opened fire on ''Vincennes'' which responded with her own gunfire at 01:53.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 47. As ''Vincennes'' began to receive damaging shell hits, her commander, U.S. Captain Frederick L. Riefkohl, ordered an increase of speed to , but shortly thereafter, at 01:55, two torpedoes from ''Chōkai'' hit, causing heavy damage. ''Kinugasa'' now joined ''Kako'' in pounding ''Vincennes''. ''Vincennes'' scored one hit on ''Kinugasa'' causing moderate damage to her steering engines. The rest of the Japanese ships also fired and hit ''Vincennes'' up to 74 times, and, at 02:03, another torpedo hit her, this time from ''Yubari''. With all boiler rooms destroyed, ''Vincennes'' came to a halt, burning "everywhere" and listing to port. At 02:16, Riefkohl ordered the crew to abandon ship, and ''Vincennes'' sank at 02:50.Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', pp. 225–228.

During the engagement, the U.S. destroyers ''Helm'' and ''Wilson'' struggled to see the Japanese ships. Both destroyers briefly fired at Mikawa's cruisers but caused no damage and received no damage to themselves.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 114.

At 02:16, the Japanese columns ceased fire on the northern Allied force as they moved out of range around the north side of Savo Island. ''Ralph Talbot'' encountered ''Furutaka'', ''Tenryū'', and ''Yubari'' as they cleared Savo Island. The Japanese ships fixed the U.S. destroyer with searchlights and hit her several times with gunfire, causing heavy damage, but ''Ralph Talbot'' escaped into a nearby rain squall, and the Japanese ships left her behind.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', pp. 50–51.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c774d015e3f7829e1015c5aaec94a2ea" name="SavoIslandYubariSearchlight" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/c774d015e3f7829e1015c5aaec94a2ea.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>