<document id="c51ec5e5956385c9e8ad08453f1e7db6-2.4" name="Battle_of_Savo_Island" cat="29">
<text>
To avoid ''Blue'', Mikawa changed course to pass north of Savo Island.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 36. He also ordered his ships to slow to , to reduce wakes that might make his ships more visible.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 103. Four minutes later, Mikawa's lookouts spied either ''Ralph Talbot'' about 16 kilometres (10 mi) away or a small schooner of unknown nationality.Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', p. 171.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 103. Morison claims that ''Blue'' later sighted a "Japanese auxiliary schooner" in that same area but gives no supporting evidence for why he or ''Blue'' believed that the schooner was of Japanese nationality (''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 55). Loxton states that ''Blue'' found the schooner to be "harmless" (Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', p. 216). The Japanese ships held their course while pointing more than 50 guns at ''Blue'', ready to open fire at the first indication that ''Blue'' had sighted them. When ''Blue'' was less than 2 kilometres (1 mi) away from Mikawa's force, she suddenly reversed course, having reached the end of her patrol track, and steamed away, apparently oblivious to the long column of large Japanese ships sailing by her.Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', pp. 171–173. Seeing that his ships were still undetected, Mikawa turned back to a course south of Savo Island and increased speed, first to , and then to . At 01:25, Mikawa released his ships to operate independently of his flagship, and at 01:31, he ordered, "Every ship attack."Dull, ''Imperial Japanese Navy'', p. 197.

At about this time, ''Yunagi'' detached from the Japanese column and reversed direction, perhaps because she lost sight of the other Japanese ships ahead of her, or perhaps she was ordered to provide a "rear guard" for Mikawa's force. One minute later, Japanese lookouts sighted a warship to port. This ship was the destroyer ''Jarvis'', heavily damaged the day before and now departing Guadalcanal independently for repairs in Australia. Whether ''Jarvis'' sighted the Japanese ships is unknown, since her radios had been destroyed. ''Furutaka'' launched torpedoes at ''Jarvis'', which all missed.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', pp. 103–104. The Japanese ships passed as close to 1,100 metres of ''Jarvis'', close enough for officers on ''Tenryū'' to look down onto the destroyer's decks without seeing any of her crew moving about. If ''Jarvis'' was aware of the Japanese ships passing by, she did not respond in any noticeable way.Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', pp. 176–177.

Two minutes after sighting ''Jarvis'', the Japanese lookouts sighted the Allied destroyers and cruisers of the southern force about 12,500 metres away, silhouetted by the glow from the burning ''George F. Elliot''.Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', p. 178. Several minutes later, at about 01:38, the Japanese cruisers began launching salvos of torpedoes at the Allied southern force ships.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', pp. 36–37. At this same time, lookouts on ''Chōkai'' spotted the ships of the Allied northern force at a range of 16 kilometres (10 mi).Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 104. ''Chōkai'' turned to face this new threat, and the rest of the Japanese column followed, while still preparing to engage the Allied southern force ships with gunfire.Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', pp. 179–180.

''Patterson''’s crew was alert because the destroyer's captain had taken seriously the earlier daytime sightings of Japanese warships and evening sightings of unknown aircraft, and told his crew to be ready for action. At 01:43, ''Patterson'' spotted a ship, probably ''Kinugasa'', 5,000 meters dead ahead and immediately sent a warning by radio and signal lamp: "Warning! Warning! Strange ships entering the harbor!" ''Patterson'' increased speed to full, and fired star shells towards the Japanese column. Her captain ordered a torpedo attack, but his order was not heard over the noise from the destroyer's guns.Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', pp. 206–207.

At about the same moment that ''Patterson'' sighted the Japanese ships and went into action, the Japanese floatplanes overhead, on orders from Mikawa, dropped aerial flares directly over ''Canberra'' and ''Chicago''.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 37. ''Canberra'' responded immediately, with Captain Frank Getting ordering an increase in speed, a reversal of an initial turn to port, which kept ''Canberra'' between the Japanese and the Allied transports, and for her guns to train out and fire at any targets that could be sighted.Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', pp. 180–184. Less than one minute later, as ''Canberra''’s guns took aim at the Japanese, ''Chōkai'' and ''Furutaka'' opened fire on her, scoring numerous hits within a few seconds. ''Aoba'' and ''Kako'' joined in with gunfire, and within the next three minutes ''Canberra'' took up to 24 large caliber hits. Early hits killed her gunnery officer, mortally wounded Getting, and destroyed both boiler rooms, knocking out power to the entire ship before ''Canberra'' could fire any of her guns or communicate a warning to other Allied ships. The cruiser glided to a stop, on fire, with a 5- to 10-degree list to starboard, and unable to fight the fires or pump out flooded compartments because of lack of power. Since all of the Japanese ships were on the port side of ''Canberra'', the damage to the ship's starboard side occurred either from shells entering low on the port side and exiting below the waterline on the starboard side, or from one or two torpedo hits on the starboard side.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 105. Frank does not believe that Japanese torpedoes hit ''Canberra'' and does not discuss the possibility that Allied torpedoes hit the ship. If torpedoes did hit ''Canberra'' on the starboard side, then they may have come from a nearby Allied ship, and at this time the U.S. destroyer ''Bagley'' was the only ship on that side of the Australian cruiser and had fired torpedoes moments earlier.Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', pp. 185–205. Loxton firmly believes that ''Canberra'' was hit by a torpedo from ''Bagley'', citing survivor accounts, ship's records, and damage assessments. Morison (''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', pp. 37–38.) states that ''Canberra'' was hit by two torpedoes on the starboard side but believes they were of Japanese origin.

The crew of ''Chicago'', observing the illumination of their ship by air-dropped flares and the sudden turn by ''Canberra'' in front of them, came alert and awakened Captain Bode from "a sound sleep". Bode ordered his five-inch (127 mm)  guns to fire star shells towards the Japanese column, but the shells did not function.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 39. At 01:47, a torpedo, probably from ''Kako'', hit ''Chicago''’s bow, sending a shock wave throughout the ship that damaged the main battery director. A second torpedo hit but failed to explode, and a shell hit the cruiser's mainmast, killing two crewmen. ''Chicago'' steamed west for 40 minutes,Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', p. 213. leaving behind the transports she was assigned to protect. The cruiser fired her secondary batteries at the trailing ships in the Japanese column and may have hit ''Tenryū'', causing slight damage. Bode did not try to assert control over any of the other Allied ships in the southern force, of which he was still technically in command. More significantly, Bode made no attempt to warn any of the other Allied ships or personnel in the Guadalcanal area as his ship headed away from the battle area.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', pp. 105–106.

During this time, ''Patterson'' engaged in a gun duel with the Japanese column. ''Patterson'' received a shell hit aft, causing moderate damage and killing 10 crew members. ''Patterson'' continued to pursue and fire at the Japanese ships and may have hit ''Kinugasa'', causing moderate damage.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 107. ''Patterson'' then lost sight of the Japanese column as it headed northeast along the eastern shore of Savo Island.Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', p. 207. ''Bagley'', whose crew sighted the Japanese shortly after ''Patterson'' and ''Canberra'', circled completely around to port before firing torpedoes in the general direction of the rapidly disappearing Japanese column; one or two of which may have hit ''Canberra''. ''Bagley'' played no further role in the battle.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', pp. 38–39. ''Yunagi'' exchanged non-damaging gunfire with ''Jarvis'' before exiting the battle area to the west with the intention of eventually rejoining the Japanese column north and west of Savo Island.Dull, ''Imperial Japanese Navy'', p. 199. ''Chicago''’s crew witnessed the gun battle between ''Jarvis'' and ''Yunagi'' (Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', p. 208).

At 01:44, as Mikawa's ships headed towards the Allied northern force, ''Tenryū'' and ''Yubari'' split from the rest of the Japanese column and took a more westward course. ''Furutaka'', either because of a steering problem,Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', p. 208. or to avoid a possible collision with ''Canberra'', followed ''Yubari'' and ''Tenryū''. Thus, the Allied northern force was about to be enveloped and attacked from two sides.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', pp. 107–108.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4c2a821ddb673f3a24469ac1e3bace9e" name="SavoIslandChokaiView" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/4c2a821ddb673f3a24469ac1e3bace9e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>