<document id="c51ec5e5956385c9e8ad08453f1e7db6-1.1" name="Battle_of_Savo_Island" cat="29">
<text>
On August 7, 1942, Allied forces (primarily U.S. Marines) landed on Guadalcanal, Tulagi, and Florida Island in the eastern Solomon Islands. The landings were meant to deny their use to the Japanese as bases. From the eastern Solomons, Japanese forces threatened the supply routes between the U.S. and Australia. The Allies also wanted to use the islands as starting points for a campaign to recapture the Solomons, isolate or capture the major Japanese base at Rabaul, and support the Allied New Guinea campaign. The landings initiated the six-month-long Guadalcanal campaign.Hogue, ''Pearl Harbor to Guadalcanal'', p. 235–236.

The overall commander of Allied naval forces in the Guadalcanal and Tulagi operation was U.S. Vice Admiral Frank Jack Fletcher. He also commanded the carrier task groups providing air cover. U.S. Rear Admiral Richmond K. Turner commanded the amphibious fleet that delivered the 16,000 Allied troops to Guadalcanal and Tulagi.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 14. Also under Turner was British Admiral Victor Crutchley's screening force of eight cruisers, fifteen destroyers, and five minesweepers. This force was to protect Turner's ships and provide gunfire support for the landings. Crutchley commanded his force of mostly American ships from his flagship, the Australian heavy cruiser HMAS ''Australia''.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', pp. 621–624.

The Allied landings took the Japanese by surprise. The Allies secured Tulagi, nearby islets Gavutu and Tanambogo, and the airfield under construction on Guadalcanal by nightfall on August 8.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', pp. 14–15. On August 7 and August 8, Japanese aircraft based at Rabaul attacked the Allied amphibious forces several times, setting afire the U.S. transport ship ''George F. Elliott'' (which sank later) and heavily damaging the destroyer ''Jarvis''.Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', pp. 90–103. In these air attacks, the Japanese lost 36 aircraft, while the U.S. lost 19 aircraft, including 14 carrier fighter aircraft.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 80.



Concerned over the losses to his carrier fighter aircraft strength, anxious about the threat to his carriers from further Japanese air attacks, and worried about his ships' fuel levels, Fletcher announced that he would be withdrawing his carrier task forces on the evening of August 8.Hammel, ''Carrier Clash'', p. 99.

Some historians contend that Fletcher's fuel situation was not at all critical but that Fletcher implied that it was to justify his withdrawal from the battle area.Loxton, ''Shame of Savo'', pp. 104–105; Frank ''Guadalcanal'' p. 94; and Morison ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 28. Fletcher's biographer notes that Fletcher concluded that the landing was a success and that no important targets for close air support were at hand. But concerned over the loss of 21 of his carrier fighters, he assessed that his carriers were threatened by torpedo-bomber strikes and wanting to refuel before Japanese naval forces arrived, withdrew as he had previously forewarned Turner and Vandegrift. Turner, however, believed that Fletcher understood that he was to provide air cover until all the transports were unloaded on August 9.Lundstrom, ''Black Shoe Carrier Admiral'', p. 368–385.

Even though the unloading was going slower than planned, Turner decided that without carrier air cover, he would have to withdraw his ships from Guadalcanal. He planned to unload as much as possible during the night and depart sometime during the next day.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 59.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e3f9bd76234cc6f1c3e3fcb564734ac5" name="CanberraTulagi" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/e3f9bd76234cc6f1c3e3fcb564734ac5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>