<document id="c529f9144e9e576ada84e6f63a8efce4-1.2" name="Jogaila" cat="25">
<text>
:''See also: Jadwiga of Poland''

When the time came for Jogaila to choose a wife, it became clear that he intended to marry a Christian. His Russian mother urged him to marry Sofia, daughter of Prince Dmitri of Moscow, who required him first to convert to Orthodoxy.The historian John Meyendorff suggests Jogaila may have already been an Orthodox Christian: "In 1377, Olgerd of Lithuania died, leaving the Grand Principality to his son Jagiello, an Orthodox Christian...". ''Byzantium and the Rise of Russia'', 205. Dmitri, however, made it a condition of the marriage that Jogaila "should be baptized in the Orthodox faith and that he should proclaim his Christianity to all men". Document quoted by Dvornik, 221. That option, however, was unlikely to halt the crusades against Lithuania by the Teutonic Order, who regarded Orthodox Christians as schismatics and little better than heathens.



Jogaila chose therefore to accept a Polish proposal to become a Catholic and marry the eleven-year-old Queen Jadwiga of Poland.Jadwiga had actually been crowned king of Poland (''rex poloni''), because the Polish political system made no provision for a queen regnant. Stone, 8.The nobles of Malopolska, not without suspicion from the nobles of Wielkopolska, made this offer to Jogaila for many reasons. For example, they were "concerned to neutralize the dangers from Lithuania itself and to secure the fertile territories of Halych-Rus'." Lukowski and Zawadzki, 42. Dvornik suggests that the Polish nobles saw the offer as an "opportunity for increasing their privileges". Dvornik, 129. They also wished to avoid Austrian influence, Jogaila agreeing to "pay off" Jadwiga's previous fiancé Wilhelm von Habsburg. Lukowski and Zawadzki, 37.
He was also to be legally adopted by Jadwiga's mother, Elizabeth of Bosnia, so retaining the throne in the event of Jadwiga's death. On these and other terms, on 14 August 1385 at the castle of Kreva, Jogaila agreed to adopt Christianity, repatriate lands "stolen" from Poland by its neighbours, and ''terras suas Lithuaniae et Russiae Coronae Regni Poloniae perpetuo applicare'', a clause interpreted by historians to mean anything from a personal union between Lithuania and Poland to a prenuptial agreement superseded when the marriage took place.Lukowski and Zawadzki read the clause to imply that "The Kreva Act seemingly promised that he would incorporate Lithuania into Poland." Lukowski and Zawadzki, 41. Sruogienė-Sruoga points out in  that "Lithuanians probably reasoned that this agreement was only temporary, a kind of wedding formality." The Krėva Union was short-lived and was succeeded by several other agreements between Lithuania and Poland. According to modern historian G. Rhode, and other researchers, the Krėva Union did not annihilate Lithuanian sovereignty, as interpreted by most Polish historians. G.Rhode. ''Grundzuge der Geschichte Litauens'', 141, 1966. Daniel Z. Stone says, "The exact intent of this union has been hotly debated by historians, but it seems likely that Jogaila and the Poles both intended to unite the realms fully". Stone, 8. The agreement at Krėva has been described both as far-sighted and as a desperate gamble.It "reflects the exceptional far-sightedness of the political elites ruling both countries."  It was "a desperate gamble by Jogaila to avert a seemingly inevitable subjugation." 

Jogaila was duly baptised at the Wawel Cathedral in Kraków on 15 February 1386 and from then on formally used the name Władysław or Latin versions of it."...was given the Christian name Vladislovas (Wladyslaw)". Vanda Sruogienė-Sruoga, . A Slavic name that roughly translates as ''glorious rule'', Władysław is often Latinised into either Wladislaus or Ladislaus. The choice evoked both Władysław I of Poland, the Elbow-high, who unified the kingdom a century before, and Saint Ladislaus I of Hungary, a king who sided with the pope against the emperor Henry IV and Christianised Transylvania. ''New Cambridge Medieval History'', 709–712. An official declaration of the baptism was sent to Grand Master Ernst von Zöllner, who had declined an invitation to become the new Christian's godfather, at the Order's capital, Marienburg.Lukowski and Zawadzki, 33–45; Stone, 16. The royal baptism triggered the conversion of most of Jogaila's court and knights, as well as mass baptisms in Lithuanian rivers, a beginning of the final Christianization of Lithuania. Though the ethnic Lithuanian nobility were the main converts to Catholicism—both paganism and the Orthodox rite remained strong among the peasants—the king's conversion and its political implications created lasting repercussions for the history of both Lithuania and Poland.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1d639b67e0fc687ebe839c947428427e" name="Wieże_katedry_na_wawelu" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/1d639b67e0fc687ebe839c947428427e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>