<document id="c566c5b6ebc2439ef1fe86f780e7a959-3" name="Vivien_Leigh" cat="19">
<text>
Olivier had been attempting to broaden his film career. Despite his success in Britain, he was not well known in the United States and earlier attempts to introduce him to the American market had failed. Offered the role of Heathcliff in Samuel Goldwyn's production of ''Wuthering Heights'' (1939), he travelled to Hollywood, leaving Leigh in London. Goldwyn and the film's director, William Wyler, offered Leigh the secondary role of Isabella, but she refused it, saying she would only play Cathy, a role already assigned to Merle Oberon. Berg, A. Scott. ''Goldwyn'', Sphere Books, 1989. ISBN 0-7474-0593-X, p 323

Hollywood was in the midst of a widely publicised search to find an actress to portray Scarlett O'Hara in David O. Selznick's production of ''Gone with the Wind'' (1939). Leigh's American agent was the London representative of the Myron Selznick Agency (Myron was David's brother), and in February 1938, she asked that her name be placed in consideration for the role of Scarlett. That month, David Selznick watched her in ''Fire Over England'' and ''A Yank at Oxford'', and from that time she became a serious contender for the part. Between February and August, Selznick screened all of her English pictures, and by August he was in negotiation with producer Alexander Korda, to whom Leigh was under contract, for her services later that year. On 18 October, Selznick wrote in a confidential memo to director George Cukor, "I am still hoping against hope for that new girl." Leigh travelled to Los Angeles, ostensibly to be with Olivier. When Myron Selznick, who also represented Olivier, met Leigh, he felt that she possessed the qualities his brother David O. Selznick was searching for. Myron Selznick took Leigh and Olivier to the set where the burning of the Atlanta Depot scene was being filmed, and introduced Leigh. The following day, Leigh read a scene for Selznick, who organised a screen test and wrote to his wife, "She's the Scarlett dark horse and looks damn good. Not for anyone's ear but your own: it's narrowed down to Paulette Goddard, Jean Arthur, Joan Bennett and Vivien Leigh". The director, George Cukor, concurred and praised Leigh's "incredible wildness"; she  received the part soon after.Haver, Ronald. ''David O. Selznick's Hollywood'', Bonanza Books, New York, 1980. ISBN 0-517-47665-7; p 259

Filming proved difficult for Leigh; Cukor was dismissed and replaced by Victor Fleming, with whom Leigh frequently quarrelled. She and Olivia de Havilland secretly met with Cukor at night and on weekends for his advice about how they should play their parts. She befriended Clark Gable, his wife Carole Lombard and de Havilland, but she clashed with Leslie Howard, with whom she was required to play several emotional scenes. Adding to her distress, she was sometimes required to work seven days a week, often late into the night, and she missed Olivier, who was working in New York. She wrote to Leigh Holman, "I loathe Hollywood  I will never get used to this &ndash; how I ''hate'' film acting." Taylor, John Russell. ''Vivien Leigh'', Elm Tree Books, 1984. ISBN 0-241-11333-4, pp 22–23

In 2006, de Havilland responded to claims of Leigh's manic behaviour during filming ''Gone with the Wind'', published in a biography of Olivier. She defended Leigh, saying, "Vivien was impeccably professional, impeccably disciplined on ''Gone with the Wind''. She had two great concerns: doing her best work in an extremely difficult role and being separated from Larry , who was in New York."  Bob Thomas, ''The Associated Press'', published 3 January 2006. Retrieved 7 January 2006, quoting Olivia de Havilland

''Gone with the Wind'' brought Leigh immediate attention and fame, but she was quoted as saying, "I'm not a film star &ndash; I'm an actress. Being a film star &ndash; just a film star &ndash; is such a false life, lived for fake values and for publicity. Actresses go on for a long time and there are always marvellous parts to play." Taylor, pp 22–23
Among the 10 Academy Awards won by ''Gone with the Wind'' was a Best Actress award for Leigh, who also won a New York Film Critics Circle Award for Best Actress.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="84a94e5f988681fd59a2c3bfd0ed1316" name="Vivien_Leigh_as_Scarlett_OHara_in_Gone_With_the_Wind_trailer" sectnum="3#1">../img/84a94e5f988681fd59a2c3bfd0ed1316.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>