<document id="c566c5b6ebc2439ef1fe86f780e7a959-6" name="Vivien_Leigh" cat="19">
<text>
Merivale proved to be a stabilizing influence for Leigh, but despite her apparent contentment she was quoted by Radie Harris as confiding that she "would rather have lived a short life with Larry  than face a long one without him". Walker, Alexander. ''Vivien, The Life of Vivien Leigh'', Grove Press, 1987. ISBN 0-8021-3259-6 p290 
Her first husband, Leigh Holman, also spent considerable time with her. Merivale joined her for a tour of Australia, New Zealand and Latin America that lasted from July 1961 until May 1962, and Leigh enjoyed positive reviews without Olivier sharing the spotlight with her. Though she was still beset by bouts of depression, she continued to work in the theatre and in 1963 won a Tony Award for Best Actress in a Musical for her role in the Broadway musical ''Tovarich''. She also appeared in the films ''The Roman Spring of Mrs. Stone'' (1961) and ''Ship of Fools'' (1965).Edwards, pp 266–272 

In May 1967, she was rehearsing to appear with Michael Redgrave in Edward Albee's ''A Delicate Balance'' when she became ill with a recurrent bout of the tuberculosis from which she had been suffering for more than twenty years but, after resting for several weeks, had seemed to be recovering. On the night of 7 July, Merivale left her as usual, to perform in a play, and returned home around midnight to find her asleep. About thirty minutes later (by now 8 July), he returned to the bedroom and discovered her body on the floor.  She had been attempting to walk to the bathroom, and as her lungs filled with liquid, she had collapsed.Edwards, pp 304–305  Merivale contacted Olivier, who was receiving treatment for prostate cancer in a nearby hospital. In his autobiography, Olivier described his "grievous anguish" as he immediately travelled to Leigh's residence, to find that Merivale had moved her body onto the bed. Olivier paid his respects, and "stood and prayed for forgiveness for all the evils that had sprung up between us",Olivier, pp 273–274 before helping Merivale make funeral arrangements.

She was cremated at the Golders Green Crematorium, and her ashes were scattered on the lake at her home, Tickerage Mill, near Blackboys, East Sussex, England. A memorial service was held at St Martin-in-the-Fields, with a final tribute read by John Gielgud. In the United States, she became the first actress honoured by "The Friends of the Libraries at the University of Southern California". The ceremony was conducted as a memorial service, with selections from her films shown and tributes provided by such associates as George Cukor.Edwards, p 306
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="04d390cc2aaae567dbac14b65a13d284" name="Vivien_Leigh_1958" sectnum="6#1">../img/04d390cc2aaae567dbac14b65a13d284.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>