<document id="c637311fb41f31cccf109a0ddb77309f-2.3" name="Battle_of_Ceresole" cat="29">
<text>
The French infantry—mostly Gascons—had meanwhile started down the slope towards Sanseverino. Montluc, noting that the disorder of the Italians had forced them to a standstill, suggested that De Tais attack Madruzzo's advancing column of landsknechts instead; this advice was accepted, and the French formation turned left in an attempt to strike the landsknechts in the flank.Oman, ''Art of War'', 236.  The source for Montluc's role in this incident is his own narrative. Madruzzo responded by splitting his column into two separate portions, one of which moved to intercept the French while the other continued up the slope towards the Swiss waiting at the crest.Hall, ''Weapons and Warfare'', 187; Oman, ''Art of War'', 237.  Oman, praising Madruzzo's tactical skill in effecting the division, quotes Du Bellay's description of the movement: "Seeing that the French had changed their plan, the Imperialists made a parallel change, and of their great battalion made two, one to fight the Swiss, the other the French, yet so close to each other that seen sideways they still looked one great mass."  Hall calls the movement "an extremely difficult maneuver".



The pike and shot infantry had by this time adopted a system in which arquebusiers and pikemen were intermingled in combined units; both the French and the Imperial infantry contained men with firearms interspersed in the larger columns of pikemen.Hall, ''Weapons and Warfare'', 186–187.  Hall notes that the later 16th-century system of arranging the infantry in square formations, with the arquebusiers drawn back into the center for protection, was probably not fully in place at Ceresole. This combination of pikes and small arms made close-quarters fighting extremely bloody.Hall, ''Weapons and Warfare'', 187. The mixed infantry was normally placed in separate clusters, with the arquebusiers on the flanks of a central column of pikemen; at Ceresole, however, the French infantry had been arranged with the first rank of pikemen followed immediately by a rank of arquebusiers, who were ordered to hold their fire until the two columns met.Hall, ''Weapons and Warfare'', 187–188; Oman, ''Art of War'', 237. Montluc, who claimed to have devised the scheme, wrote that: In this way we should kill all their captains in the front rank.  But we found that they were as ingenious as ourselves, for behind their first line of pikes they had put pistoleers. Neither side fired till we were touching—and then there was a wholesale slaughter: every shot told: the whole front rank on each side went down.Oman, ''Art of War'', 237.  Hall gives a similar translation of Montluc's quote (but uses "a great slaughter" for ''"une grande tuerie"''); he notes that it is unclear how Montluc "escaped the carnage he helped create" (Hall, ''Weapons and Warfare'', 187). The Swiss, seeing the French engage one of the two columns of landsknechts, finally descended to meet the other, which had been slowly moving up the hillside.Oman, ''Art of War'', 237.  The Swiss waited until the French were "within twelve pike-lengths of their immediate adversaries" before starting from their position. Both masses of infantry remained locked in a push of pike until the squadron of heavy cavalry under Boutières charged into the landsknechts' flank, shattering their formation and driving them down the slope.Black, "Dynasty Forged by Fire," 43; Hall, ''Weapons and Warfare'', 187; Oman, ''Art of War'', 237–238. The Imperial heavy cavalry, which had been on the landsknechts' right, and which had been ordered by d'Avalos to attack the Swiss, recoiled from the pikes and fled to the rear, leaving Carlo Gonzaga to be taken prisoner.Oman, ''Art of War'', 238.  Oman notes that the actions of the Imperial cavalry are not mentioned in any French chronicle of the battle, but that Giovio records that they "disgraced themselves".

The Swiss and Gascon infantry proceeded to slaughter the remaining landsknechts—whose tight order precluded a rapid retreat—as they attempted to withdraw from the battlefield.Hall, ''Weapons and Warfare'', 187; Oman, ''Art of War'', 238. The road to Ceresole was littered with corpses; the Swiss, in particular, showed no mercy, as they wished to avenge the mistreatment of the Swiss garrison of Mondovì the previous November. Most of the landsknechts' officers were killed; and while contemporary accounts probably exaggerate the numbers of the dead, it is clear that the German infantry had ceased to exist as a fighting force.Oman, ''Art of War'', 238.  Oman suggests that the contemporary casualty figure of 5,000 out of 7,000 is exaggerated, but notes that Giovio's list of casualties records that "practically all their captains were killed".  Black merely notes the landsknechts' casualties as "more than 25 percent" (Black, "Dynasty Forged by Fire," 43). Seeing this, Sanseverino decided that the battle was lost and marched away to Asti with the bulk of the Italian infantry and the remnants of Baglioni's Florentine cavalry; the French light cavalry, meanwhile, joined in the pursuit of the landsknechts.Oman, ''Art of War'', 238.  Baglioni's Florentines had been able to reform without incident, as they were not pursued by the French after the initial clash.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a7a225ec50649ea230735de2f6a49543" name="Bad-war" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/a7a225ec50649ea230735de2f6a49543.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>