<document id="c64ba28dcba8f65d738cc111ddd66d0d-4" name="Theatre_Royal,_Drury_Lane" cat="17">
<text>
The present Theatre Royal in Drury Lane, designed by Benjamin Dean Wyatt on behalf of the committee led by Whitbread, opened on 10 October 1812 with a production of ''Hamlet'' featuring Robert Elliston in the title role. The new theatre made some concessions toward intimacy, seating 3,060 people, about 550 fewer than the earlier building (though this size is still considered an extremely large theatre). In 1820 the portico that still stands at the theatre's front entrance on Catherine Street was added, and in 1822, five years after gas lighting was installed, the interior underwent a significant remodelling. The colonnade running down the Russell Street side of the building was added in 1831.All details in this paragraph are from Thomson p. 310.

Productions relying more on scenery and effects than on dialogue and acting remained commonplace in the new facility. The 1823 production of ''Cataract of the Ganges'' had a finale featuring a horseback escape up a flowing cataract "with fire raging all around."Bradby et al. pp. 103&ndash;104. Effects for an 1829 production were produced by hydraulic apparatus that reportedly could discharge 39 tons of water.Bradby et al. p. 103.

There were those concerned that the theatre was failing in its role as one of the very few permitted to show legitimate drama. Management of the theatre after it reopened in 1813 fell to Samuel Arnold, overseen by an amateur board of directors and a subcommittee focusing on the theatre as a centre for national culture. (Lord Byron was briefly on this subcommittee, from June 1815 until leaving England in April 1816.) Actor Edmund Kean was the on-stage highlight; like Macklin before him, he made his reputation as Shylock, premiering in the role in 1814. Kean remained until 1820, but despite his popularity, the committee-led efforts to appeal to culture yet still turn a profit eventually proved a failure, and in 1819 the theatre and all its accompanying rights were leased to Robert Elliston.

Elliston went bankrupt and was unable to renew his lease in 1826. An American, Stephen Price, followed (1826&ndash;1830); then through most of the remainder of the 19th century, Drury Lane passed quickly from one set of hands to another. A colonnade was added to the Russell Street frontage, in 1831, by architect Samuel Beazley.Earl, John and Michael Sell pp. 268 (2000) In 1833, Alfred Bunn gained control of both Drury Lane and Covent Garden, managing the former from 1833 to 1839, and again from 1843 to 1850. In 1837, actor-manager Samuel Phelps (1804–1878) joined the company at Drury Lane, appearing with William Charles Macready, the gifted actor-manager in a number of Shakespeare plays. He also created the role of Captain Channel in Douglas Jerrold's melodrama, ''The Prisoner of War'' (1842), and of Lord Tresham in Robert Browning's ''A Blot in the 'Scutcheon'' (1843).  Macready was briefly manager in 1841&ndash;1843, putting significant reforms in place. Nevertheless, most productions there were financial disasters.Thomson p. 310. 
The last scene of a critically-acclaimed 1865 performance of Shakespeare's ''King John'' at the theatre, as depicted in the ''Illustrated London News''.
The theatrical monopoly first bestowed by Royal Letters Patent 183 years earlier was abolished by the Theatres Act 1843, but the patent had been largely toothless for decades and this had little immediate effect. On the other hand, other theatres, used to presenting musical entertainments, continued to do so, and Drury Lane continued as one of the most accepted venues for legitimate theatre. The 19th-century run of financial and artistic failures at Drury Lane was interrupted by four plays produced over a twenty-five-year period by the actor-playwright Dion Boucicault: ''The Queen of Spades'' (1851), ''Eugenie'' (1855), ''Formosa'' (1869), and ''The Shaughraun'' (1875). But this period of general decline culminated with F. B. Chatterton's 1878 resignation; in his words, "Shakespeare spells ruin, and Byron bankruptcy."  During the 19th century, Drury Lane staged ballet as well, with performers including Italy's Carlotta Grisi.

One famous musical director of Drury Lane was the eccentric French conductor and composer of light music Louis-Antoine Jullien (1812–1860), who successfully invited Berlioz to visit London and give concerts in the Theatre.


The house's fortune's rose again under the management of Augustus Harris from 1879. In the 1880s and 1890s, the theatre hosted many of the productions of the Carl Rosa Opera Company. Productions relying on spectacle became even more the norm at Drury Lane in the later parts of the century, under the managements first of Augustus Harris (1879&ndash;1896) and then of Arthur Collins (1896&ndash;1923).  Examples include the successful 1909 ''The Whip'', which featured not only a train crash complete with hissing steam, but also a horserace: twelve real horses jockeying on an on-stage treadmill. Harris instituted an annual pantomime in 1889; starring already well-known comedian Dan Leno, the performances were a major success. Many of the designs under Harris were created by the imaginative designer C. Wilhelm, including the spectacular drama, ''Armada'' (1888), and many pantomimes."Mr. Pitcher's Art" - Obituary ''The Times'' 3 March 1925

The last major interior renovation was in 1922, leaving a four-tiered theatre able to seat between 2,200 and 2,300 people., from show-and-stay.co.uk. URL accessed on 28 April 2006. It was decorated with one of the most notable interiors produced by the specialist ornamental plasterwork company of Clark and Fenn., Friends of West Norwood cemetery Composer and performer Ivor Novello, immensely popular in his time though little-remembered today, presented his musicals in Drury Lane from 1931 until the theatre was closed in 1939 because of World War II. During the war the theatre served as the headquarters for the Entertainments National Service Association; it sustained some minor bomb damage as well. The theatre reopened with Noel Coward's ''Pacific 1860'' in 1946.
Oliver! bill board at the theatre in 2009.
In the post-war years, a number of Rodgers and Hammerstein musicals made their London debuts in Drury Lane, including ''Oklahoma!'' (1946), ''South Pacific'' (1951) and ''The King and I'' (1953). American imports also included Lerner and Loewe's ''My Fair Lady'', which began a five-year run in 1958. Comedy troupe Monty Python also performed one of their reunion shows here. Today, the theatre is part of the West End theatre scene, still generally staging popular musical productions. It is owned and managed by Really Useful Theatres, a division of Andrew Lloyd Webber's Really Useful Group. Long-running recent productions include ''42nd Street'' (1984&ndash;89) and ''Miss Saigon'' (1989&ndash;1999). A staging of Mel Brooks' musical ''The Producers'', closed in January 2007, and the theatre hosted a musical adaptation of ''The Lord of the Rings''. The show closed on 19 July 2008, to make way for Cameron Mackintosh's new production of ''Oliver!'', which continues to play.

The present building was Grade I listed by English Heritage in February 1958. accessed 28 April 2007
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1217340440eb46dd76f744682d37dd65" name="Theatre_Royal_Drury_Lane_-_The_Producers_1" sectnum="4#1">../img/1217340440eb46dd76f744682d37dd65.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>