<document id="c7bc3e0955055325f7442933b4118f5f-1.4" name="Wales_national_rugby_union_team" cat="26">
<text>
Wales won two matches in each Five Nations championship between 1980 and 1984, and in 1983 were nearly upset by Japan; winning by 24&ndash;29 at Cardiff. In 1984, Australia defeated Wales 28&ndash;9 at Cardiff Arms Park. This was the most points scored against Wales at Cardiff by a team from outside the Five Nations, and the first time they conceded a push-over try there; Australia went on to win their first Grand Slam.

Wales were still respected by the time of the first official Rugby World Cup in 1987. After defeating England in the quarter-finals, Wales faced hosts the All Blacks. Although the All Blacks won 49&ndash;6, Wales managed to beat Australia in the third place play-off game to claim third. The next year Wales won the Triple Crown for the first time since 1979, but heavy defeats on tour to New Zealand later that year saw the end of a number of Welsh players' careers, as many converted to rugby league. 

In 1990, Wales suffered their first Five Nations championship whitewash and, in 1991 narrowly avoided the same fate by earning one point for a draw with Ireland at Cardiff Arms Park. In the 1991 World Cup, Wales lost their first group phase game against Manu Samoa. They subsequently beat Argentina's ''Pumas'' but lost heavily to eventual champions Australia and were thus knocked out before reaching the quarter-finals. After winning two Five Nations games in 1992, and one in 1993, Wales won the Championship in 1994.Wales won this Championship on points difference as both Wales and England won three games each. After again not qualifying for the World Cup quarter-finals in 1995, Kevin Bowring became Wales' first professional coach when he replaced Alex Evans that year. 

Wales' performances improved with the appointment of coach Graham Henry in 1998, and the return of several internationals from rugby league. Henry coached Wales to a record run of ten consecutive victories, including Wales' first ever victory over the then-world champions, South Africa, by 29&ndash;19 in the opening match of the Millennium Stadium, and was nicknamed "the great redeemer" by the Welsh media. Hosting the 1999 World Cup, Wales qualified for the quarter-finals for the first time since 1987, but lost 9&ndash;24 to eventual champions Australia. Defeats to Argentina and Ireland in 2001 and 2002 led to Henry's resignation in February 2002; his assistant Steve Hansen took over. Further defeats led to perhaps Wales' biggest ever shake-up in 2003. At the 2003 World Cup, Wales scored four tries in their 53&ndash;37 loss to New Zealand and also lost (28&ndash;17) to the eventual tournament winners, England, in their quarter-final.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f58c6066c84fd9e8201bb01f1362d344" name="Michael_Owen_takes_a_lineout" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/f58c6066c84fd9e8201bb01f1362d344.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>