<document id="c81c6fb808fe7eb37d2b127f25e33f03-2" name="Big_Star" cat="20">
<text>
Big Star returned in 1993 with a new line-up when guitarist Jon Auer and bassist Ken Stringfellow joined Chilton and Stephens. Auer and Stringfellow remain members of The Posies, founded by the pair in 1986. Stringfellow is also known for his work with R.E.M. and The Minus 5. First-era material dominates Big Star's performances, with the occasional addition of a song from the 2005 album ''In Space''; Stringfellow recalled that during the 1990s, "We were working out the set list and we went to this little cafe. Little did I know we'd be playing that set for the next ten years". The resurrected band made its debut at the 1993 University of Missouri spring music festival. A recording of the performance was issued on CD by Zoo Records as ''Columbia: Live at Missouri University''. The concert was followed by tours of Europe and Japan, as well as an appearance on ''The Tonight Show''.. Rollingstone.com. Accessed June 11, 2009. 



''In Space'' was released on 27 September 2005 on the Rykodisc label. Recorded during 2004, the album consists of new material mostly co-written by all four current members. Reviewing ''In Space'', ''Rolling Stone'''s David Fricke first points out the context for its release: "a world expecting that American Beatles ideal all over again" from a band that "achieved its power-pop perfection when no one else was looking".. Rollingstone.com. Accessed July 18, 2009. In Fricke's estimation, the seemingly unrealistic expectation is in part met: "It's here&mdash;in the jangly longing and ice-wall harmonies of 'Lady Sweet'"; Fricke finds though that such songs are interleaved with "the eccentric R&B and demo-quality glam rock that have made Chilton's solo records a mixed blessing", and that "'A Whole New Thing' starts out like old T.Rex, then goes nowhere special". Warming nevertheless to "the rough sunshine" of "Best Chance",  Fricke says in conclusion: "''In Space'' is no ''#1 Record'', but at its brightest, it is Big Star in every way".

The band appeared at San Francisco's Fillmore Auditorium on 20 October 2007. San Francisco-based band Oranger, performed as opening act.. Ardent Music. Accessed July 22, 2009. Big Star performed at the 2008 Rhythm Festival, staged from 29&ndash;31 August in Bedfordshire, UK. On 16 June 2009, the ''#1 Record''/''Radio City'' double album was reissued in remastered form.. Amazon.com. Accessed July 8, 2009. The same month, it was announced that a film of Big Star's history, based on Rob Jovanovic's book ''Big Star: The Story of Rock's Forgotten Band'', is in pre-production.. ''Billboard''. Accessed June 11, 2009. On 1 July 2009, Big Star performed at a concert in Hyde Park, London, UK.. Ardent Studios, July 15, 2009. Accessed July 22, 2009. On 15 September 2009, Rhino Records issued a four-CD box set containing 98 previously unreleased recordings made between 1968 and 1975. ''Keep An Eye On The Sky'' includes live and demo versions of Big Star songs, solo work, and material from Bell's earlier bands Rock City and Icewater.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4e49d5bb68789b6c2ff983dc2934a7c0" name="Big_Star_at_Hyde_Park_2" sectnum="2#1">../img/4e49d5bb68789b6c2ff983dc2934a7c0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>