<document id="c82f0a2bc3817b90ba8a808803f86f24-4" name="Anglo-Zanzibar_War" cat="29">
<text>
At 08:00 on the morning of 27 August, after a messenger sent by Khalid requested parley from Cave, the consul replied that he would only have salvation if he agreed to the terms of the ultimatum..  At 08.30 a further messenger from Khalid declared that "We have no intention of hauling down our flag and we do not believe you would open fire on us"; Cave replied that "We do not want to open fire, but unless you do as you are told we shall certainly do so."  At 08:55, having received no further word from the palace, aboard ''St George'' Rawson hoisted the signal "prepare for action"..

At exactly 09:00, General Lloyd Mathews ordered the British ships to commence the bombardment.. At 09:02 Her Majesty's Ships ''Racoon'', ''Thrush'' and ''Sparrow'' opened fire at the palace simultaneously, ''Thrush's'' first shot immediately dismounted an Arab 12-pounder cannon. 3,000 defenders, servants and slaves were present in the largely wooden palace and even with barricades of crates, bales and rubber, there were many casualties from the high explosive shells. Despite initial reports that he had been captured and was to be exiled to India, Sultan Khalid escaped from the palace.. A Reuters news correspondent reported that the Sultan had "fled at the first shot with all the leading Arabs, who left their slaves and followers to carry on the fighting", but other sources state that he remained in the palace for longer. The shelling ceased at around 09:40, by which time the palace and attached harem had caught fire, the enemy artillery had been silenced and the Sultan's flag cut down.


During the bombardment a small naval engagement occurred when, at 09:05, the obsolete ''Glasgow'' fired upon the ''St George'' using her armament of 7 nine-pounder guns and a Gatling gun which had been a present from Queen Victoria to the Sultan..  The return fire caused ''Glasgow'' to sink, though the shallow harbour meant that her masts remained out of the water.  ''Glasgow'''s crew hoisted a British flag as a token of their surrender and they were all rescued by British sailors in launches. ''Thrush'' also sank two steam launches whose Zanzibari crews shot at her with rifles. Some land fighting occurred when Khalid's men fired on Raikes' askaris, with little effect, as they approached the palace.  The fighting ceased with the end of the shelling. The British controlled the town and the palace and by the afternoon Hamud bin Muhammed, an Arab favourable to the British, had been installed as Sultan with much reduced powers..  The British ships and crews had fired around 500 shells, 4,100 machine gun rounds and 1,000 rifle rounds during the engagement..
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="18a4f4f11ac8460ec660f6a84163b6d2" name="Zanzibar_palace_after_low" sectnum="4#1">../img/18a4f4f11ac8460ec660f6a84163b6d2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>