<document id="c868914ed31a10c967ca501fb61fad44-3" name="Meshuggah" cat="20">
<text>
Meshuggah has become known for its technical prowess and innovative musical style that evolves between each release and pushes heavy metal into new territory. Hagström comments: "We try never to repeat ourselves." Rockdetector stated about ''Destroy Erase Improve'': "he band...stripped Metal down to the bare essentials before completely rebuilding it in a totally abstract form". Official Meshuggah biography criticizes ''Chaosphere'' with: "Some fans felt that Meshuggah had left their dynamic and progressive elements behind; while others thought they were only progressing naturally and focusing on their original sound" and ''Nothing'' with: "t displayed a very mature and convincing Meshuggah, now focusing on groove and sound...Meshuggah once again divided their fans into the 'ecstatic' and the 'slightly disappointed'". The music's complexity combined with aggression can make the music sound cacophonous; the polyrhythms can make it sound like band members are playing different songs simultaneously.

''Rolling Stone'' labeled Meshuggah as "one of the ten most important hard and heavy bands", and the ''Alternative Press'' named it the "most important band in metal." Meshuggah has been described as highly skilled, virtuoso or genius-bordering musicians with "incredible abilities recognized by mainstream music magazines, especially those dedicated to particular instruments". Tom Service from guardian.co.uk stated about Meshuggah: "There's as much rhythmic obsessiveness and intricacy in the relentless polyrhythms of Swedish metal maestros Meshuggah as there is in Reich or Ligeti – with the difference that Meshuggah use the supreme technical sophistication and overpowering volume of their 5-in-the-time-of-4 patterns to serve rather different expressive ends: Terminal Illusions as opposed to Different Trains". In 2007, Meshuggah earned an in-depth analysis by the academic journal ''Music Theory Spectrum''. Meshuggah has found little mainstream success but is a significant act in extreme underground music and an influence for many modern metal bands.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="235d7e9de5a8b7f8e7bb0ab8d0b93d8c" name="Tomas_Haake_2005" sectnum="3#1">../img/235d7e9de5a8b7f8e7bb0ab8d0b93d8c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>