<document id="c868914ed31a10c967ca501fb61fad44-1.4" name="Meshuggah" cat="20">
<text>
In 2003, Hagström hinted at the direction of the band's next album by saying, "There's only one thing I really feel that is important. We've never measured our success in terms of sales, because we're quite an extreme band. It's more that people understand where we're coming from. I get more out of a fan coming up and saying that we've totally changed their way of looking on metal music, than having like 200 kids buy it. I mean, it would be nice for the money, but that's not why we're in it. So what I'd like to see is that we keep progressing. Keeping the core of what Meshuggah has always been, but exploring the bar, so to speak. ''Destroy Erase Improve'' was like exploring the dynamics of the band, ''Chaosphere'' was exploring the aggressiveness, the all-out side, and ''Nothing'' is more of a sinister, dark, pretty slow album, actually. So honestly, now I don't know where we're going. It might be a mix of all of them."


In February 2004, bassist Dick Lövgren joined Meshuggah. The band then recorded and released the ''I'' EP, which contains a single, 21-minute track, released on Fractured Transmitter Records. Meshuggah spent about six months in total on recording the EP. ''Catch Thirtythree'', the only album on which programmed drums have been used, was released the following year in May 2005. Seven thousand copies of ''Catch Thirtythree'' were sold the first week, and it debuted at No. 170 on the ''Billboard'' 200 chart in June 2005. The video for the track "Shed" was released in June, and the previous album ''Nothing'' sold approximately 80,000 copies in the United States to that date, according to Nielsen SoundScan. ''Catch Thirtythree'' earned the band a Swedish Grammy nomination.

In December 2005, 10 years after inking its first record deal with the publishing company Warner/Chappell Music Scandinavia, Meshuggah extended its cooperation with the company. In November 2005, Haake said in an interview that the band was not content with the productions of ''Chaosphere'' and ''Nothing'', because, being on tour, they had little time to devote to them.

A remixed and remastered version of ''Nothing'' with rerecorded guitars was released in a custom-shaped slipcase featuring a three-dimensional hologram card on October 31, 2006, via Nuclear Blast Records. The release also includes a bonus DVD featuring the band's appearance at the Download 2005 festival and the official music videos of "Rational Gaze", "Shed" and "New Millennium Cyanide Christ".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c8d2792e26d3744912cc4f2b51560990" name="Meshuggah_-_Dick_Lövgren_-_2008_Melbourne" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/c8d2792e26d3744912cc4f2b51560990.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>