<document id="c868914ed31a10c967ca501fb61fad44-2.6" name="Meshuggah" cat="20">
<text>
When describing Meshuggah's experimentation, stylistic variation and changes during its career, journalists have categorized its sound within several musical subgenres. Heavy metal subgenres avant-garde metal or experimental metal are umbrella terms that enable description of the career of the band in general. Extreme metal crosses both thrash metal (or post-thrash metal) and death metal (or technical death metal), which are at root of the sound of Meshuggah's music. The band is often labelled as math metal (for using elements of math rock) and progressive metal. The music of the band has also been described as grindcore, a fusion of extreme metal and hardcore punk. Meshuggah also incorporates elements of experimental jazz. Rockdetector uses the term hi-tech metal to describe their style. In its review of ''Nothing'', Allmusic describes Meshuggah as "masterminds of cosmic calculus metal—call it Einstein metal if you want". Meshuggah creates a recognizable sonic imprint and distinct style.

Trademarks and characteristics that define Meshuggah's sound and complex songwriting include polyrhythmic structure, odd riff cycles, complex "rotating" time signatures, rhythmic syncopation, rapid key and tempo changes and neo-jazz chromatics. Hagström notes that "it doesn’t really matter if something is hard to play or not. The thing is, what does it do to your mind when you listen to it? Where does it take you?" A trademark of Thordendal is free jazz-like soloing and lead guitar. He is also known for the usage of a "breath controller" device. Haake is known for his precise cross-rhythm drumming with "jazzlike cadence". The vocal style of Jens Kidman varies between hardcore-style shouts and "robotic" death metal vocals.

In a typical polyrhythm by Meshuggah, the guitars might play in odd meters such as 5/16 or 17/16, while drums play in normal 4/4. An example of Haake's dual rhythms is a 4/4 and 23/16 rhythm. He keeps the hi-hat and ride cymbal in simple 4/4 time but uses the snare and double bass drums for 23/16 rhythm. On "Rational Gaze" (from ''Nothing''), Haake plays simple 4/4 time, hitting the snare on each third beat, for 16 bars. At the same time, the guitars and bass are playing the same quarter notes, albeit in a different time signature, and eventually both sides meet up again at the 64th beat. Hagström notes about the polyrhythms, "We’ve never really been into the odd time signatures we get accused of using. Everything we do is based around a 4/4 core. It’s just that we arrange parts differently around that center to make it seem like something else is going on."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6af3b40c4fcfb279b166f5d1c513d418" name="Meshuggah_Thordendal_2008_Prague" sectnum="2.6#1">../img/6af3b40c4fcfb279b166f5d1c513d418.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>