<document id="c868914ed31a10c967ca501fb61fad44-1.1" name="Meshuggah" cat="20">
<text>
In 1985, guitarist Fredrik Thordendal formed a band in Umeå, a college town in northern Sweden with a population of 105,000. The band, originally named Metallien, recorded a number of demo tapes, after which it disbanded. Thordendal, however, continued playing under a different name with new band members.

Meshuggah was formed in 1987 by vocalist and guitarist Jens Kidman, and took the name Meshuggah from the Yiddish word for "crazy". The band recorded several demos before Kidman left, which prompted the remaining members to disband. Kidman then formed a new band, Calipash, with guitarist Thordendal, bassist Peter Nordin and drummer Niclas Lundgren. Kidman, who also played guitar, and Thordendal decided to restore the name Meshuggah for the new band.

In 1989, Meshuggah released the self-titled, three-song EP ''Meshuggah'', which is commonly known as ''Psykisk Testbild'' (a title that could be translated as "Psychological Test-Picture"). This 12" (30 cm) vinyl EP had only 1,000 copies released, sold by local record store Garageland. The EP's back cover features the band members with cheese doodles on their faces.

After replacing drummer Niclas Lundgren with Tomas Haake in 1990, Meshuggah signed a contract with German heavy metal record label Nuclear Blast and recorded its debut full-length album, ''Contradictions Collapse''. The LP, originally entitled ''(All this because of) Greed'', was released in 1991. The album received positive reviews, but was not a commercial success. Soon after, Kidman decided to concentrate on vocals, and rhythm guitarist Mårten Hagström, who had already played in a band with Haake when they were in the sixth grade, was recruited. The new lineup recorded the EP ''None'' at Tonteknik Recordings in Umeå in 1994 for release later that year. A Japanese version was also released, including lyrics printed in Japanese.

During this period, Thordendal, who was working as a carpenter, severed the tip of his left middle finger, while Haake injured his hand in a grinder accident. As a result, the band was unable to perform for several months. Thordendal's fingertip was later reattached, and he went on to make a full recovery. The ''Selfcaged'' EP was recorded in April and May 1994, but its release was delayed to later in 1995 due to the accidents.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4633441c4af88b70c8be2704b28d90b2" name="Jens_Kidman" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/4633441c4af88b70c8be2704b28d90b2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>