<document id="c86cb686ffb837f7299f7e670a84808c-2.4" name="Jack_Warner" cat="19">
<text>
As the 1930s came to an end, both Jack and Harry Warner became increasingly alarmed over the rise of Nazism.Thomas (1990), p. 129. As Bernard F. Dick observed, the Warners, "as sons of Polish Jews who fled their homeland because of anti-Semitic pogroms. . .had a personal interest in exposing Nazism." Moreover, the attraction to films critical of German militarism had a long history with the Warners that predated their production in 1918 of ''My Four Years in Germany''. In 1917, while still in distribution, the Warners had secured the rights for ''War Brides'', a film that featured Alla Nazimova as "a woman who kills herself rather than breed children for an unidentified country whose army looks suspiciously Teutonic."Dick (1985), p. 55.    

Beyond this, Jack Warner was shaken by the 1936 murder of studio salesman Joe Kaufman, who was beaten to death by Nazi stormtroopers in Berlin.Dick (1985), pp. 55-56.Friedman (1982), p. 82. Warner later described the incident in the following terms: "Like many an outnumbered Jew he was trapped in an alley. They  hit him with fists and clubs and then kicked the life out of him with their boots and left him dying there."Warner and Jennings (1964), p. 249. Hence, while other Hollywood studios sidestepped the issue, fearing domestic criticism and the loss of European markets, Warner Bros. produced films openly critical of Germany's fascist government. In 1939, the studio released ''Confessions of a Nazi Spy'', starring Edward G. Robinson. The film project, which was recommended to Jack Warner by FBI Director J. Edgar Hoover, drew on the real-life experiences of agent Leon Turrou, who had worked as an undercover agent. Despite legal ramifications preventing the use of actual names, the studio aimed for an "aura of authenticity", and Hall Wallis initially recommended eliminating credits to give the film "the appearance of a newsreel."Dick (1985), p. 56. Upon its release, ''Confessions of a Nazi Spy'' created a firestorm. Critic Pare Lorentz wrote, "The Warner brothers have declared war on Germany with this one." The German ambassador responded by issuing a protest to U.S. Secretary of State Cordell Hull, and German dictator Adolf Hitler, who screened the film at Berchtesgaden, was outraged.Thomas (1990). pp. 129-130. Meanwhile, the studio received stern warnings from U.S. lawmaker Martin Dies about defaming a "friendly country."Buhle and Wagner (2002), p. 211.

Initially, the studio bowed to pressure from the Roosevelt Administration, the Hays Office, and isolationist lawmakers to desist from similar projects. Jack Warner announced that the studio would release no more "propaganda pictures" and promptly ordered the shelving of several projects with an anti-Nazi theme.Ceplair and Englund (1980), p. 310. In time, however, Warner Bros. produced more films with anti-Nazi messages, including ''Underground'' and ''All Through the Night''. In 1940, the studio produced shorts that dramatically documented the devastation wrought by the German bombing raids on London. Meanwhile, the studio celebrated the exploits of the Canadian Air Force, with films such as ''Captains of the Clouds''.Thomas (1990), p. 130. In 1941, Warner also produced the influential pro-war film ''Sergeant York''.Sperling, Millner, and Warner (1998), p. 246. Contemporary reports that Jack Warner had banned the use of the German language throughout the company's Burbank studio were denied by studio representatives, who indicated this move would have prevented scores of studio employees from communicating with each other. ''Time''. June 10, 1940.  

In 1943, Warner, at the advice of President Roosevelt, produced a film adaption of the controversial book ''Mission to Moscow'';Thomas (1990), p. 146. a film intended to inspire public support for the uneasy military alliance the United States had with the Soviet Union.Buhle and Wagner (2002), p. 240. Later, while testifying before the House Un-American Activities Committee on October 27, 1947,Sperling, Millner, and Warner (1998), p. 272 Warner dismissed Cold War allegations that the film was subversive, arguing that ''Mission to Moscow'' was produced "only to help a desperate war effort and not for posterity."Buhle and Wagner (2002), p. 241. After the film's lackluster release, the Republican National Committee accused Warner of releasing the film as "New Deal propaganda."Thomas (1990), p. 147.

In line with the Warner brothers' early opposition to Nazism, Warner Bros. produced more pictures about the war than any other studio, covering every branch of the armed services.Thomas (1990), p. 132. In addition, the studio produced patriotic musicals such as ''This is the Army'' and ''Yankee Doodle Dandy''. At the close of the war, Jack Warner was drafted by the U.S. armed forces and made a lieutenant colonel.Thomas (1990), p. 130-132.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7387e46540c8530dbc191299164695ea" name="Warnerestate" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/7387e46540c8530dbc191299164695ea.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>