<document id="c86cb686ffb837f7299f7e670a84808c-2.2" name="Jack_Warner" cat="19">
<text>
The Warner brothers pooled their resources and moved into film production in 1910.Warner and Jennings (1964), p. 73. Then, in 1912, they lent their support to filmmaker Carl Laemmle's Independent Motion Picture Company, which challenged the monopolistic control of the Edison Trust. That same year, Jack Warner acquired a job as a film splicer in New York,Sperling, Millner, and Warner (1998), p. 47. where he assisted brother Sam with the production of the film, ''Dante's Inferno''.Sperling, Millner, and Warner (1998), p. 48. Despite the film's success at the box office, Harry Warner remained concerned about the economic threat presented by the Edison Trust. He subsequently broke with Laemmle and sent Jack to establish a film exchange in San Francisco, while Sam did the same in Los Angeles.Sperling, Millner, and Warner (1998), p. 54. The brothers were soon poised to exploit the expanding California movie market.Thomas (1990), p. 29. In 1917, Jack was sent to Los Angeles to open another film exchange company.Sperling, Millner, and Warner (1998), p. 59. Their first opportunity to produce a major film came in 1918, when they purchased the film rights for ''My Four Years in Germany'', a bestselling novel that condemned German wartime atrocities. The film proved to be a commercial and critical success,Thomas (1990), pp. 34&ndash;35. and the four brothers were able to establish a studio in Hollywood, California.Sperling, Millner, and Warner (1998), p. 65-66. In the new Hollywood studio, Jack became co-head of production along with his older brother, Sam.Sperling, Millner, and Warner (1998), p. 100-101. In this capacity, the two brothers secured new scripts and story lines, managed film production, and looked for ways to reduce production costs.  


Warner Bros. followed up the success of ''My Four Years in Germany'' with a popular serial titled ''The Tiger's Claw'' in 1919.  That same year, the studio was less successful in its efforts to promote ''Open Your Eyes'', a tract on the dangers of venereal disease that featured Jack Warner's sole screen appearance.Thomas (1990), p. 37. During this period, the studio earned few profits,Sperling, Millner, and Warner (1998), p. 71-73. and in 1920, the Warners secured a bank loan to settle outstanding debts. Shortly thereafter, the Warners relocated their production studio from Culver City, California, to Hollywood, where they purchased a lot on the corner of Sunset Boulevard and Bronson Avenue.Thomas (1990), p. 38. The new location and upgraded facilities did not significantly improve the studio's image, which remained defined by its low-budget comedies and racy films on declining morality.Thomas (1990), p. 39.  

The studio discovered a trained German Shepherd named Rin Tin Tin in 1923. The canine made his debut in ''Where the North Begins'', a film about an abandoned pup who is raised by wolves and befriends a fur trapper.Thomas (1990), p. 42.  According to one biographer, Jack Warner's initial doubts about the project were quelled when he met Rin Tin Tin, "who seemed to display more intelligence than some of the Warner comics." Rin Tin Tin proved to be the studio's most important commercial asset until the introduction of sound.Behlmer (1985), p. 4. Screenwriter Darryl F. Zanuck produced several scripts for Rin Tin Tin vehicles and, during one year, wrote more than half of the studio's features.Thomas (1990), p. 45. Between 1928 and 1933, Zanuck served as Jack Warner's right-hand man and executive producer, a position whose responsibilities included the day-to-day production of films.Behlmer (1985), p. xii. Despite the success of Rin Tin Tin and other projects, however, Warner Bros. was unable to compete with Hollywood's "Big Three" &ndash; Paramount, Universal, and First National studios.   

In 1925, the studio expanded its operations and acquired the Brooklyn-based theater company, Vitagraph.Sperling, Millner, and Warner (1998), p. 86 Later that year, Sam Warner urged his brother, Harry, to sign an agreement with Western Electric to develop a series of talking "shorts" using the newly developed Vitaphone technology.Thomas (1990), 52&ndash;55. Sam died of pneumonia in 1927 (just before the premiere of the first feature-length talking picture, ''The Jazz Singer''),
 and Jack became sole head of production.Warner and Jennings (1964), pp. 180&ndash;181. Sam's death left Jack unconsolable. One biographer writes, "Throughout his life, Jack had been warmed by Sam's sunshiny optimism, his thirst for excitement, his inventive mind, his gambling nature. Sam had also served as a buffer between Jack and his stern eldest brother, Harry.Thomas (1990), p. 62. In the years to come, Jack ran the Warner Bros. Burbank studio with an iron hand. Following his brother's death, he became increasingly difficult to deal with and inspired the resentment of many of his employees. 

As the family grieved over Sam's sudden passing, the success of ''The Jazz Singer'' helped establish Warner Bros. as a major studio. While Warner Bros. invested only $500,000 in the film, the studio reaped $3 million in profits.Sperling, Millner, and Warner (1998), p. 142-145  Hollywood's five major studios, which controlled most of the nation's movie theaters, initially attempted to block the growth of "talking pictures".Thomas (1990), p. 63.  In the face of such organized opposition, Warner Bros. produced 12 "talkies" in 1928 alone. The following year, the newly formed Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences recognized Warner Bros. for "revolutionizing the industry with sound".Thomas (1990), p. 66.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="87c965fb6f6678f360c01f2a7bd4ca10" name="Hollywood-Studios-1922" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/87c965fb6f6678f360c01f2a7bd4ca10.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>