<document id="c8b287075ce4f11c834d2a0ada967ddc-2.4" name="Virginia" cat="11">
<text>
The first people arrived in Virginia about 5,000 years ago, and farming began there by 900 CE. By 1500, the Algonquian peoples had founded towns such as Werowocomoco in the Tidewater region, which they referred to as ''Tsenacommacah''. The other major language groups in the area were the Siouan to the west, and the Iroquoians, who included the Nottoway and Meherrin, to the north and south. After 1570, the Algonquians consolidated under Chief Powhatan in response to threats from these other groups on their trade network. In 1607, the native Tidewater population was between 13,000 to 14,000. Powhatan controlled more than 30 smaller tribes and over 150 settlements, who shared a common Virginia Algonquian language.

In 1583, Queen Elizabeth I of England granted Walter Raleigh a charter to explore and plant a colony north of Spanish Florida. In 1584, Raleigh sent an expedition to the Atlantic coast of North America. The name "Virginia" may have been suggested by Raleigh or Elizabeth, perhaps noting her status as the "Virgin Queen", and may also be related to a native phrase, "Wingandacoa", or name, "Wingina". Initially the name applied to the entire coastal region from South Carolina to Maine, plus the island of Bermuda. The London Company was incorporated as a joint stock company by the proprietary Charter of 1606, which granted land rights to this area. The Company financed the first permanent English settlement in the "New World", Jamestown. Named for King James I, it was founded in May 1607 by Christopher Newport. In 1619, colonists established an elected legislature called the House of Burgesses. With the bankruptcy of the London Company in 1624, the settlement was taken into royal authority as a British crown colony.


Life in the colony was perilous, and many died during the "starving time" in 1609 and the Indian massacre of 1622, led by Opchanacanough. By 1624, only 3,400 of the 6,000 early settlers had survived., Stahle, D. W., M. K. Cleaveland, D. B. Blanton, M. D. Therrell, and D. A. Gay. 1998. ''Science'' 280:564–567. However, European demand for tobacco fueled the arrival of more settlers and servants. African workers were first imported in 1619, and slavery was codified after 1660. After 1618, the headright system led to more indentured servants from Europe. In this system, settlers received land for each servant they transported. Colonists appropriated land from Native Americans by force and treaty, including the Treaty of 1677, which made the signatory tribes tributary states. The colonial capital was moved in 1699 to Williamsburg, where the College of William and Mary had been founded in 1693.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bee95a59e69590f2e3a50394c3fa21f1" name="Colonial_Williamsburg_Governors_Palace_Front_Dscn7232" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/bee95a59e69590f2e3a50394c3fa21f1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>