<document id="c8b287075ce4f11c834d2a0ada967ddc-5" name="Virginia" cat="11">
<text>
alt=High-rise hotels line the ocean front covered with colorful beach-goers.
Virginia's economy is balanced, with diverse sources of income, including government and military, farming, and business. Virginia has 4.1 million civilian workers, and one-third of the jobs are in the service sector. In 2008, ''Forbes Magazine'' named Virginia the best state in the nation for business for the third year in a row. The Gross Domestic Product of Virginia was $397 billion in 2008. As of 2000, Virginia had the highest number of counties in the top 100 wealthiest jurisdictions in the United States based upon median income. Virginia is home to 18 Fortune 500 companies, ranking the state tenth nationwide.

Virginia has the highest concentration of technology workers of any state. Computer chips became the state's highest-grossing export in 2006, surpassing its traditional top exports of coal and tobacco combined. Northern Virginia, once considered the state's dairy capital, now hosts software, communication technology, and consulting companies, particularly in the Dulles Technology Corridor. Northern Virginia's data centers currently carry more than 50% of the nation's Internet traffic, and by 2012 Dominion Power expects that 10% of all its electricity in Northern Virginia will be used by data centers. Fairfax and Loudoun counties in Northern Virginia have the highest and second highest median household income, respectively, of all counties in the United States as of 2006.

As of 2007, about 357,000 Virginian jobs were in agriculture, with over 47,000 farms, averaging , in a total farmland area of 8.1 million acres (12,656 sq mi; 32,780 km2). Though agriculture has declined significantly since 1960 when there were twice as many farms, it remains the largest single industry in Virginia. Tomatoes surpassed soy as the most profitable crop in Virginia in 2006, with peanuts and hay as other agricultural products. Though its no longer the primary crop, Virginia is still the fifth-largest producer of tobacco nationwide. Eastern oyster harvests are an important part of the Chesapeake Bay economy, but declining oyster populations from disease, pollution, and overfishing have diminished catches. Wineries and vineyards in the Northern Neck and along the Blue Ridge Mountains also have begun to generate income and attract tourists.


Many of Northern Virginia's well-educated population work directly for federal agencies. Many others work for government contractors, including defense and security firms. Government agencies headquartered in Northern Virginia include the Central Intelligence Agency and the Department of Defense, as well as the National Science Foundation, the United States Geological Survey and the United States Patent and Trademark Office. The Hampton Roads area has the largest concentration of military bases and facilities of any metropolitan area in the world. The largest of the bases is Naval Station Norfolk. Virginia has more veterans than any other state, with over 800,000, and is second only to Alaska in per capita defense spending.

Virginia collects personal income tax in five income brackets, ranging from 3.0% to 5.75%. The sales and use tax rate is 5%, while the tax rate on food is 2.5%. There is an additional 1% local tax, for a total of a 5% combined sales tax on most Virginia purchases. Virginia's property tax is set and collected at the local government level and varies throughout the Commonwealth. Real estate is also taxed at the local level based on 100% of fair market value. Tangible personal property also is taxed at the local level and is based on a percentage or percentages of original cost.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1bb66033e24e154aa26a493d3d252e4d" name="The_Pentagon_January_2008" sectnum="5#1">../img/1bb66033e24e154aa26a493d3d252e4d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>