<document id="c8b287075ce4f11c834d2a0ada967ddc-8" name="Virginia" cat="11">
<text>
alt=An entrance to a school below a white concrete overhang with red brick walls. National and local flags fly next to a circle of five rocks.

Virginia's educational system consistently ranks in the top ten states on the U.S. Department of Education's National Assessment of Educational Progress, with Virginia students outperforming the average in all subject areas and grade levels tested. The 2009 ''Quality Counts'' report ranked Virginia's K–12 education fourth best in the country. All school divisions must adhere to educational standards set forth by the Virginia Department of Education, which maintains an assessment and accreditation regime known as the Standards of Learning to ensure accountability. In 2008, 81% of high school students graduated on-time after four years.

Public K–12 schools in Virginia are generally operated by the counties and cities, and not by the state. As of Fall 2008, a total of 1,236,546 students were enrolled in 1,890 local and regional schools in the Commonwealth, including four charter schools, and an additional 106 alternative and special education centers across 134 school divisions. Besides the general public schools in Virginia, there are Governor's Schools and selective magnet schools. The Governor's Schools are a collection of more than 40 regional selective magnet high schools and summer programs intended for gifted students. The Virginia Council for Private Education oversees the regulation of 294 state accredited and 141 non-accredited private schools. An additional 6,948 students receive homeschooling.


Nine high schools in the Northern Virginia region are ranked in the top 100 nationwide by ''Newsweek'' magazine. In addition, Thomas Jefferson High School for Science and Technology, which requires an application, listed as the best public high school in the nation according to ''U.S. News & World Report''. All Northern Virginia schools pay the test fees for students to take Advanced Placement and International Baccalaureate exams, and Alexandria and Arlington lead the nation in college course tests.

As of 2009, there are 163 colleges and universities in Virginia. In the ''U.S. News and World Report'' ranking of public colleges, the University of Virginia is second and the College of William and Mary is sixth. James Madison University has been the number one public master's university in The South since 1993. The Virginia Military Institute is the oldest state military college and a top ranked public liberal arts college. Virginia Commonwealth University is the largest university in Virginia with over 32,000 students, followed closely by Virginia Tech and George Mason University. Virginia Tech and Virginia State University are the state's land-grant universities. Virginia also operates 23 community colleges on 40 campuses serving over 260,000 students. There are 116 private institutions.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e1a9147be2c7c7d369e7fdf82e07a516" name="University-of-Virginia-Rotunda" sectnum="8#1">../img/e1a9147be2c7c7d369e7fdf82e07a516.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>