<document id="c9334d55b2014eff7ba9e0d1922d75ba-5" name="Symphony_No._3_(Górecki)" cat="20">
<text>
Symphony No. 3 was written in 1976, when Górecki was, in the words of the music critic Jane Perlez, "a fiery figure, fashionable only among a small circle of modern-music aficionados".Perlez, Jane. "". ''New York Times'', 27 February, 1994. Retrieved 29 March, 2008.  The symphony was first recorded in Poland in 1978 by the soprano Stefania Woytowicz. During the late 1970s and early 1980s, recordings and performances of the work were widely criticised by the press outside Poland.Howard (1998), 136 The symphony drew hostility from critics who felt that Górecki had moved too far away from the established avant-garde style and was, according to Dietmar Polaczek (writing for ''Österreichische Musikzeitschrift''), "simply adding to the decadent trash that encircled the true pinnacles of avant-gardism".Polaczek, Dietmar. "Neue Musik in Royan", ''Österreichische Musikzeitschrift'', July&ndash;August, 1977. 358 The world première at the Royan Festival, Ernest Bour conducting, was reviewed by six western critics, all of them harshly dismissive. Heinz Koch, writing for ''Musica'', said that the symphony "drags through three old folk melodies (and nothing else) for an endless 55 minutes".Koch, Heinz. "Mit wichtigen bundesdeutschen Beiträgen". Musica 31, no. 4. 1977. p 332. ''Da schleift einer drei alte Volksliedmelodien (und sonst nichts) 55 endlose Minuten lang.'' 



In 1985, the French filmmaker Maurice Pialat featured a section of the third movement in the ending credits of his movie ''Police''. When the work was later repackaged as a "soundtrack album", it sold well, although the sleeve notes provided little information about the work,Howard (1998), 137 and Górecki's name appeared in smaller type than those of the main actors.Wierzbicki, James. "". ''St. Louis Post-Dispatch'', July 7, 1991. Retrieved 29 May, 2007. In the mid-1980s, British industrial music group Test Dept used Symphony No. 3 as a backdrop for video collages during their concerts, recasting the symphony as a vehicle for the band's sympathy with the Polish Solidarity movement,Howard (1998), p. 138. which Górecki also supported (his 1981 piece ''Miserere'' was composed in part as a response to government opposition of Solidarity trade unions).Thomas, Adrian. "Górecki, Henryk Mikolaj". ''The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians'', ed. Stanley Sadie. (London): Macmillan, 2001, v.10, p. 160. During the late 1980s, the symphony received increasing airplay on US and British classical radio stations, notably BBC Radio 3. The fall of communism helped to spread the popularity of Polish music generally, and by 1990 the symphony was being performed in major cities such as New York, London and Sydney. A 1991 recording with the London Sinfonietta, conducted by David Zinman and featuring the soloist Dawn Upshaw, was released in 1992 by the Elektra imprint Nonesuch Records. Within two years, the recording had sold more than 700,000 copies worldwide;Blum, Ronald. "The Impact of Górecki's Symphony No. 3". ''Chicago Sun-Times'', 26 June, 1994. the recording climbed to number 6 on the mainstream UK album charts,Howard (1998),  144 and while it did not appear on the US Billboard 200, it stayed at the top of the US classical charts for 38 weeks and stayed on for 138 weeks.
"". Billborad.com . Retrieved 16 October, 2008Howard (1998), 145 The Zinman/Upshaw recording has sold over a million copies.

The writer Michael Steinberg described the symphony's success as essentially a phenomenon of the compact disc, and while live performances are still given, they do not always sell out. Some critics, wondering at the sudden success of the piece nearly two decades after its composition, suggest that it resonated with a particular mood in the popular culture at the time. Stephen Johnson, writing in ''A guide to the symphony'', wondered whether the commercial success of the work was "a flash in the pan" or would turn out to have lasting significance.Layton (1995), 401 In 1998, the critic Michael Steinberg asked, " really listening to this symphony? How many CD buyers discover that fifty-four minutes of very slow music with a little singing in a language they don't understand is more than they want? Is it being played as background music to Chardonnay and brie?" Steinberg compared the success of Górecki's symphony to the ''Doctor Zhivago'' phenomenon of 1958: "Everybody rushed to buy the book; few managed actually to read it. The appearance of the movie in 1965 rescued us all from the necessity." Górecki was as surprised as any one else at the recording's success, and later speculated that "perhaps people find something they need in this piece of music…. Somehow I hit the right note, something they were missing. Something, somewhere had been lost to them. I feel that I instinctively knew what they needed." 

At least a dozen recordings were issued in the wake of the success of the Nonesuch recording, and the work enjoyed significant exposure in a number of artistic media worldwide. The work was repeatedly used by filmmakers in the 1990s to elicit a sense of pathos or sorrow, including as an accompaniment to a plane crash in Peter Weir's ''Fearless'' (1993), and in the soundtrack to Julian Schnabel's ''Basquiat'' (1996).Howard (1998), 152 An art gallery in Santa Fe, New Mexico opened an exhibit in 1995 dedicated entirely to visual art inspired by the piece. In 1997, the symphony was sampled for the song "Gorecki" by the English trip-hop act Lamb, which peaked at number 30 on the UK singles charts in 1997."". gorecki.co.uk. Retrieved 19 June, 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="823d488aac11cc90562ec2f36c4baac8" name="Gallen_Kallela_Lemminkainens_Mother" sectnum="5#1">../img/823d488aac11cc90562ec2f36c4baac8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>