<document id="c952e888ff380b35d44f2a5da0068686-4" name="Michael_Jordan" cat="26">
<text>
After his third retirement, Jordan assumed that he would be able to return to his front office position of Director of Basketball Operations with the Wizards.Wise, Mike. , ''The New York Times'', May 4, 2003, accessed February 12, 2009. However, his previous tenure in the Wizards' front office had produced the aforementioned mixed results and may have also influenced the trade of Richard "Rip" Hamilton for Jerry Stackhouse (although Jordan was not technically Director of Basketball Operations in 2002). On May 7, 2003, Wizards owner Abe Pollin fired Jordan as Washington's President of Basketball Operations. Jordan later stated that he felt betrayed, and that if he knew he would be fired upon retiring he never would have come back to play for the Wizards.

Jordan kept busy over the next few years by staying in shape, playing golf in celebrity charity tournaments, spending time with his family in Chicago, promoting his Jordan Brand clothing line, and riding motorcycles.Grass, Ray. , deseretnews.com, June 22, 2006, accessed October 3, 2008. Since 2004, Jordan has owned Michael Jordan Motorsports, a professional closed-course motorcycle road racing team that competes with two Suzukis in the premier Superbike class sanctioned by the American Motorcyclist Association (AMA).Martin, Chris. , moto-racing.speedtv.com, June 25, 2007, accessed November 10, 2008. Jordan and his then-wife Juanita pledged $5 million to Chicago's Hales Franciscan High School in 2006,Meyer, Gregory. , chicagobusiness.com, March 13, 2006, accessed July 28, 2008. and the Jordan Brand has made donations to Habitat for Humanity and a Louisiana branch of the Boys & Girls Clubs of America., ''Reuters'', February 14, 2008, accessed July 28, 2008. On June 15, 2006, Jordan became a part-owner of the Charlotte Bobcats and was named "Managing Member of Basketball Operations." He has the largest individual holding in the team after majority owner Robert L. Johnson., nba.com, June 15, 2006, accessed January 15, 2007. Despite Jordan's previous success as an endorser, he has made an effort not to be included in Charlotte's marketing campaigns.Associated Press. , espn.com, June 15, 2006, accessed February 21, 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="533e6f842fb3732c69378db306035ae9" name="MJ_golf_course" sectnum="4#1">../img/533e6f842fb3732c69378db306035ae9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>