<document id="c98d8230ab2f948422a219f1eca33658-3.6" name="Diplodocus" cat="3">
<text>
The head of ''Diplodocus'' has been widely depicted with the nostrils on top due to the position of the nasal openings at the apex of the skull. There has been speculation over whether such a configuration meant that ''Diplodocus'' may have had a trunk.Bakker, Robert T. (1986) The Dinosaur Heresies: New Theories Unlocking the Mystery of the Dinosaurs and their Extinction. New York: Morrow. A recent studyKnoll, F., Galton, P.M., López-Antoñanzas, R. (2006). "Paleoneurological evidence against a proboscis in the sauropod dinosaur ''Diplodocus''." ''Geobios'', '''39''': 215–221 surmised there was no paleoneuroanatomical evidence for a trunk. It noted that the facial nerve in an animal with a trunk, such as an elephant, is large as it innervates the trunk. The evidence suggests that the facial nerve is very small in ''Diplodocus''. Studies by Lawrence Witmer (2001) indicated that, while the nasal openings were high on the head, the actual, fleshy nostrils were situated much lower down on the snout.Lawrence M. Witmer et al., "Nostril Position in Dinosaurs and other Vertebrates and its Significance for Nasal Function." Science '''293''', 850 (2001)

Recent discoveries have suggested that ''Diplodocus'' and other diplodocids may have had narrow, pointed keratinous spines lining their back, much like those on an iguana.Czerkas, S. A. (1993). "Discovery of dermal spines reveals a new look for sauropod dinosaurs." Geology '''20''', 1068–1070Czerkas, S. A. (1994). "The history and interpretation of sauropod skin impressions." In ''Aspects of Sauropod Paleobiology'' (M. G. Lockley, V. F. dos Santos, C. A. Meyer, and A. P. Hunt, Eds.), ''Gaia'' '''No. 10'''. (Lisbon, Portugal). This radically different look has been incorporated into recent reconstructions, notably ''Walking with Dinosaurs''. It is unknown exactly how many diplodocids had this trait, and whether it was present in other sauropods.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4aee0648c5e6b4b15e411b9f0a7dcfec" name="diploheads" sectnum="3.6#1">../img/4aee0648c5e6b4b15e411b9f0a7dcfec.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>