<document id="c9e90a118f1e221d5f2407d83b14c86b-2.2" name="Phil_Hartman" cat="19">
<text>
After appearing in the 1986 films ''Jumpin' Jack Flash'' and ''¡Three Amigos!'', Hartman joined the cast and writing staff of NBC's variety show ''Saturday Night Live'' (''SNL''). He told the ''Los Angeles Times'', "I wanted to do  because I wanted to get the exposure that would give me box-office credibility so I can write movies for myself." In his eight seasons with the show Hartman became known for his impressions, and performed as over 70 different characters. These included Frank Sinatra, Ronald Reagan, Ed McMahon, Barbara Bush, Charlton Heston, Phil Donahue and Bill Clinton; the last was often considered his most well-known impression. 



Hartman's original ''Saturday Night Live'' characters included Eugene, the Anal Retentive Chef and Unfrozen Caveman Lawyer. Hartman first performed his Clinton impression on an episode of ''The Tonight Show''. When he met Clinton in 1993 Hartman remarked, "I guess I owe you a few apologies", adding later that he "sometimes  a twinge of guilt about ". Clinton showed good humor and sent Hartman a signed photo with the text: "You're not the president, but you play one on TV. And you're OK, mostly." One of Hartman's more famous sketches as Clinton saw the president visit a McDonald's restaurant and explain his policies by eating other customers' food. The writers told him that he was not eating enough during rehearsals for the sketch &ndash; by the end of the live performance, Hartman had eaten so much he could barely speak.

Backstage at ''SNL'', Hartman was called "the Glue", a name coined by Adam Sandler, according to Jay Mohr's book ''Gasping for Airtime''. ''SNL'' creator Lorne Michaels explained the reason for the name: "He kind of held the show together. He gave to everybody and demanded very little. He was very low-maintenance." Michaels added that Hartman was "the least appreciated" cast member by commentators outside the show, and praised his ability "to do five or six parts in a show where you're playing support or you're doing remarkable character work". Hartman was nominated for three Emmy Awards for his work on ''SNL'', winning in 1989 for Outstanding Writing for a Variety, Music or Comedy Program.


After his co-stars Jon Lovitz, Dennis Miller, Jan Hooks and Dana Carvey had left, Hartman said he felt "like an athlete who's watched all his World Series teammates get traded off into other directions ... It was hard to watch them leave because I sort of felt we were all part of the team that saved the show." This cast turnover contributed to his leaving the show in 1994. Hartman had originally planned to leave the show in 1991, but Michaels convinced him to stay to raise his profile; his portrayal of Clinton contributed to this goal. NBC persuaded him to stay on ''SNL'' by promising him his own comedy–variety show entitled ''The Phil Show''. He planned to "reinvent the variety form" with "a hybrid, very fast-paced, high energy  with sketches, impersonations, pet acts, and performers showcasing their talents". Hartman was to be the show's executive producer and head writer. Before production began, however, the network decided that variety shows were too unpopular and scrapped the series. In a 1996 interview, Hartman noted he was glad the show had been scrapped, as he "would've been sweatin' blood each week trying to make it work". In 1998, he admitted he missed working on ''SNL'', but had enjoyed the move from New York City to Southern California.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="77788f5e13fdf6a12de1dad11a2fbdf5" name="ClintonHartman" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/77788f5e13fdf6a12de1dad11a2fbdf5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>