<document id="ca276a4820652ccb1becafb164b9aa2c-1.4" name="Powderfinger" cat="20">
<text>
''Vulture Street'' was released on 4 July 2003. The album, recorded in January and February 2003, was named after a street in Woolloongabba, Queensland, which was the location of the band's first recording room. The album was described by critics as "a rawer, louder, but by no means unrefined, album", and that it featured guitarists Middleton and Haug dominating in a way they had not since their 1994 debut. Simon Evans of musicOMH.com described the band as having "opted for a visceral live feel, adding a real punch to songs".

"(Baby I've Got You) On My Mind", "Since You've Been Gone", "Love Your Way", and "Sunsets" from ''Vulture Street'' were released as singles.  Like earlier Powderfinger albums, ''Vulture Street'' won several ARIA Awards. It won "Album of the Year", "Best Group", "Best Rock Album" and "Best Cover Art" in 2003. Several songs on the album were also nominated for awards in 2003 and 2004.

''These Days: Live in Concert'' was the first live release by Powderfinger. Both the CD and DVD versions were released in late-2004. One single,"Stumblin'" a song which originally appeared on ''Vulture Street'' as a normal track, was also released from the album. Powderfinger released a "best of" album entitled ''Fingerprints: The Best of Powderfinger, 1994-2000'' a few weeks later. It included many of the band's singles to-date as well as non-singles "Thrilloilogy" and "Belter" and a re-release of "These Days". "These Days", although never officially released as a single, was ranked at #1 on the Triple J Hottest 100 poll of 1999. The album also included two new songs; "Bless My Soul" and "Process This", although only "Bless My Soul" was released as a single. 

Following the 2004 Indian Ocean earthquake, Powderfinger appeared at the WaveAid fund raising concert in Sydney, to raise funds for aid organisations working in the disaster affected areas. Fanning sang for The Wrights when they performed "Evie" at the concert and released a studio version of the song as a single, with the proceeds from the sale also going to tsunami relief efforts.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="23425daa3bddb3f2f8d462e60c268cc9" name="John_Collins" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/23425daa3bddb3f2f8d462e60c268cc9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>