<document id="ca363feb861358e331c7fdd80bca5984-7" name="Right_whale" cat="3">
<text>
The leading cause of death among the North Atlantic Right Whale, which migrates through some of the world's busiest shipping lanes whilst journeying off the east coast of the United States and Canada, is injury sustained from being struck by ships. At least 16 deaths due to ship strikes were reported between 1970 and 1999, and probably many more remain unreported. Recognising that this toll could tip the balance of the already delicately poised species towards extinction, the United States government introduced measures to curb the decline. The National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's (NOAA) ''Atlantic Large Whale Take Reduction Plan'' was introduced in 1997. A key part of the plan was the introduction of mandatory reporting of large whale sightings by ships using U.S. ports. This requirement was implemented in July 1999. 

While environmental campaigners were, as reported in 2001, pleased that the reporting plan has a positive effect, they wanted the government to do more. In particular, they demanded that ships within  of U.S. ports in times of known high right whale conservation be forced to maintain a speed of no more than . The United States government, citing concerns about excessive disruption to trade, did not enforce such measures. The conservation groups Defenders of Wildlife, the Humane Society of the United States and the Ocean Conservancy thus sued the National Marine Fisheries Service (a sub-agency of the NOAA) in September 2005 for "failing to protect the critically endangered North Atlantic Right Whale, which the agency acknowledges is 'the rarest of all large whale species' and which federal agencies are required to protect by both the Marine Mammal Protection Act and the Endangered Species Act", and demanded that emergency measures be put in place to protect the whales. Both the North Atlantic and North Pacific species are listed as a "species threatened with extinction which  or may be affected by trade" (Appendix I) by CITES, and as Conservation Dependent by the IUCN Red List, and as endangered under the U.S. Endangered Species Act. 

A second major cause of morbidity and mortality in the North Atlantic Right Whale is entanglement in fishing gear. Right whales filter feed plankton with their mouths wide open, exposing themselves to the risk of entanglement in any rope or net fixed in the water column. They commonly wrap rope around their upper jaws, flippers and tails. Most manage to escape with minor scarring, but some get seriously and persistently entangled. Such cases if sighted are sometimes successfully disentangled, but others are not and they die a most gruesome death over a period of months. There has been a major focus on the conservation status of the right whale in terms of an endangered species. However, equally significant is the extreme animal welfare concern such chronic fatal entanglements represent.

The Southern Right Whale, listed as "endangered" by CITES and "lower risk - conservation dependent" by the IUCN, is protected in the jurisdictional waters of all countries with known breeding populations (Argentina, Australia, Brazil, Chile, New Zealand, South Africa and Uruguay). In Brazil, a federal Environmental Protection Area encompassing some  and  of coastline in Santa Catarina State was established in 2000 to protect the species' main breeding grounds in Brazil and promote regulated whale watching.Petrobras, Projeto Baleia Franca.  

On 2006-06-26, NOAA proposed the ''Strategy to Reduce Ship Strikes to North Atlantic Right Whales''.NOAA.   The proposal, which was opposed by some shipping interests, envisaged imposing a speed cap of  on specific routes during calving season for vessels  or longer. According to the NOAA, 25 of the 71 right whale deaths reported since 1970 resulted from ship strikes. The proposal was implemented in 2008. On December 8, 2008, NOAA issued a press release that included the following: 

:"A landmark regulation going into effect on Dec. 9 will require ships 65 feet or longer to travel at 10 knots or less in certain areas where right whales gather. These new speed restrictions will take effect in waters off New England beginning in January 2009 when whales begin gathering in this area as part of their annual migration. The goal is to reduce the chances ships will collide with whales, injuring or killing them. 

:"The 10-knot speed restriction will extend out to 20 nautical miles around major mid-Atlantic ports.  According to NOAA researchers, about 83 percent of right whale sightings in the mid-Atlantic region occur within 20 nautical miles of shore.  The speed restriction also applies in waters off New England and the southeastern U.S., where whales gather seasonally.. 

:"The speed restrictions apply in the following approximate locations at the following times; they are based on times whales are known to be in these areas: 
 
:- Southeastern U.S. from St. Augustine, Fla. to Brunswick, Ga. from Nov. 15 to April 15
:- Mid-Atlantic U.S. areas from Rhode Island to Georgia from Nov. 1 to April 30.
:- Cape Cod Bay from Jan. 1 to May 15
:- Off Race Point at northern end of Cape Cod from March 1 to April 30
:- Great South Channel of New England from April 1 to July 31 
 
:"NOAA will also call for temporary voluntary speed limits in other areas or times when a group of three or more right whales is confirmed. Scientists will assess whether the speed restrictions are effective before the rule expires in 2013." 

The Stellwagen Bank area has implemented an autobuoy (AB) program to acoustically detect right whales in the Boston Approaches and notify mariners of right whale detections via the  website.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="64e49b262c1d065329c39625c8adc08c" name="Eubalaena_glacialis_dead" sectnum="7#1">../img/64e49b262c1d065329c39625c8adc08c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>