<document id="ca3a68dab06975c2cdcb787ceed44e6e-3" name="Dalek" cat="19">
<text>
Dalek in-universe history has seen many retroactive changes, which have caused continuity problems.Peel (1998), p. 78 When the Daleks first appeared in ''The Daleks'', they were presented as the descendants of the Dals, mutated after a brief nuclear war between the Dal and Thal races.''The Daleks.'' Writer Terry Nation, Director Christopher Barry, Producer Verity Lambert. ''Doctor Who''. BBC, London. 21 December 1963–1 February 1964. In 1975, Terry Nation revised the Daleks' origins in ''Genesis of the Daleks'', where the Dals were now called Kaleds (of which "Daleks" is an anagram), and the Dalek design was attributed to one man, the crippled Kaled chief scientist and evil genius, Davros.''Genesis of the Daleks.'' Writer Terry Nation, Director David Maloney, Producer Philip Hinchcliffe. ''Doctor Who''. BBC. BBC1, London. 8 March–12 April 1975. Instead of a short nuclear exchange, the Kaled-Thal war was portrayed as a thousand-year-long war of attrition, fought with nuclear, biological and chemical weapons causing widespread mutations among the Kaled race. Davros experimented on living Kaled cells to find the ultimate mutated form of the Kaled species and placed the subjects in tank-like "travel machines" whose design was based on his own life-support chair.

''Genesis of the Daleks'' marked a new era for the depiction of the species, with most of their previous history either forgotten or barely referred to again. Future stories in the original ''Doctor Who'' series, which followed a rough story arc,Parkin (2006), p. 237 would also focus more on Davros, much to the dissatisfaction of some fans who felt that the Daleks should take centre stage. rather than merely becoming minions of their creator. Davros made his last televised appearance for 20 years in ''Remembrance of the Daleks'', which depicted a civil war between two factions of Daleks. One, the "Imperial Daleks", were loyal to Davros, who had become their Emperor, whilst the other, the "Renegade Daleks", followed a black Supreme Dalek.

A single Dalek appeared in "Dalek", written by Robert Shearman, which was broadcast on BBC One on 30 April 2005. This Dalek appeared to be the sole Dalek survivor of the Time War which had destroyed both the Daleks and the Time Lords. A Dalek Emperor returned at the end of the 2005 series, having rebuilt the Dalek race with genetic material harvested with human subjects. It saw itself as a god, and the new Daleks were shown worshipping it. These Daleks and their fleet were destroyed in "The Parting of the Ways".


The 2006 series finale "Army of Ghosts"/"Doomsday" featured a squad of four Dalek survivors from the old Empire, known as the Cult of Skaro, led by a black Dalek named "Sec", that had survived the Time War by escaping into the Void between dimensions. They emerged, along with a Time Lord prison vessel containing millions of Daleks, at Canary Wharf due to the actions of the Torchwood Institute and Cybermen from a parallel world. This resulted in a Cyberman-Dalek clash in London, which was resolved when the Tenth Doctor caused both factions to be sucked back into the Void. The Cult survived by utilising an “emergency temporal shift" to escape. They would later appear in the two-part story "Daleks in Manhattan"/"Evolution of the Daleks", in which whilst stranded in 1930’s New York, they set up a base in the partially built Empire State Building and attempt to rebuild the Dalek race. To this end Dalek Sec merges with a human being to become a Human/Dalek hybrid. The Cult then set about creating 'Human Daleks' by 'formatting' the brains of a few thousand of captured humans, with the intention of producing hybrids which remain fully human in appearance but with Dalek minds.

The plot is ultimately foiled due to interference by the Doctor, and Cult members Daleks Sec, Jast and Thay are destroyed. The remaining Cult member, Dalek Caan, once again escapes using a temporal shift.

The Daleks returned in the 2008 series' two-part finale, "The Stolen Earth"/"Journey's End", accompanied once again by their creator Davros. The story reveals that Caan's temporal shift sent him into the Time War where he rescued Davros. The episode depicts a Dalek invasion of Earth led by Caan, Davros, and a red Supreme Dalek, who has kept Caan and Davros imprisoned in a section of the Dalek flagship, the ''Crucible'', called "The Vault". Davros and the Daleks plan to destroy all creation with a "reality bomb". The plan fails due to the interference of the Doctor, his companions and Caan himself, who has been manipulating events to destroy the Daleks after realising the severity of the atrocities they have committed.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6f1616045670a91936ed3c32849d09a3" name="Human_dalek" sectnum="3#1">../img/6f1616045670a91936ed3c32849d09a3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>