<document id="ca3a68dab06975c2cdcb787ceed44e6e-2" name="Dalek" cat="19">
<text>
Wishing to create an alien creature that did not look like a "man in a suit", Terry Nation stated in his script for the first Dalek serial that they should have no legs.Howe (1997), p. 80  He was also inspired by a performance by the Georgian State Ballet, in which dancers in long skirts appeared to glide across the stage.Howe (1997), p. 80 For many of the shows, the Daleks were "played" by retired ballet dancers wearing black socks while sitting inside the Dalek. Raymond Cusick was given the task of designing the Daleks when Ridley Scott, then a designer for the BBC, proved unavailable after having been initially assigned to their debut serial.Howe (1994), p. 61 An account in Jeremy Bentham's ''Doctor Who — The Early Years'' (1986) says that after Nation wrote the script, Cusick was given only an hour to come up with the design for the Daleks, and was inspired in his initial sketches by a pepper shaker on a table. Cusick himself, however, states that he based it on a man seated in a chair, and only used the pepper shaker to demonstrate how it might move.Walker (2006), p. 61 

In 1964 Nation told a ''Daily Mirror'' reporter that the Dalek name came from a dictionary or encyclopedia volume, the spine of which read "Dal - Lek".Peel (1988), pp. 21–22  He later admitted that this book and the origin of the Dalek name was completely fictitious, and that anyone bothering to check out his story would have found him out. The name had in reality simply rolled off his typewriter.Howe (1998), p. 13  Later, Nation was pleasantly surprised to discover that in Serbo-Croatian the word "dalek" means "far", or "distant".Davies, Kevin (director) (1993). ''More than 30 Years in the TARDIS'' London, UK: BBC Video.

Nation grew up during World War II, and remembered the fear caused by German bombings. He consciously based the Daleks on the Nazis, conceiving the species as faceless, authoritarian figures dedicated to conquest and complete conformity.Howe (1992), p. 31 The allusion is most obvious in the Dalek stories penned by Nation, in particular ''The Dalek Invasion of Earth'' (1964) and ''Genesis of the Daleks'' (1975).Miles (2006), pp. 105–109Howe (1998), p. 280

Prior to writing the first Dalek serial, Nation was chief scriptwriter for comedian Tony Hancock. The two fell out and Nation either resigned or was fired.Miles (2006), p. 40 When Hancock left the BBC, he worked on several series proposals, one of which was called ''From Plip to Plop'', a comedic history of the world which would have ended with a nuclear apocalypse, the survivors being reduced to living in dustbin-like robot casings and eating radiation to stay alive. According to biographer Cliff Goodwin, when Hancock saw the Daleks, he allegedly shouted at the screen, "That bloody Nation — he's stolen my robots!"

The naming of early ''Doctor Who'' stories is complex and sometimes controversial.  The first Dalek serial is called, variously, ''The Survivors'' (the pre-production title), ''The Mutants'' (its official title at the time of production and broadcast, later taken by another unrelated story), ''Beyond the Sun'', ''The Dead Planet'', or simply ''The Daleks''.

The instant appeal of the Daleks caught the BBC off guard, and transformed ''Doctor Who'' from a Saturday tea-time children's educational programme to a must-watch national phenomenon. Children were alternately frightened and fascinated by the alien look of the monsters, and the ''Doctor Who'' production office was inundated by letters and calls asking about the creatures. Newspaper articles focused attention on the series and the Daleks, further enhancing their popularity.

Nation jointly owned the intellectual property rights to the Daleks with the BBC, and the money-making concept proved nearly impossible to sell to anyone else; he was dependent on the BBC wanting to produce stories featuring the creatures.On-screen production notes, ''The Dalek Invasion of Earth'' London, UK: BBC Video, 2003. Despite fans' adoration, the Daleks were clearly associated with ''Doctor Who'' and several attempts to market the Daleks outside of the series were unsuccessful.Peel (1988), p. 56Howe (1997), p. 86 Since Nation's death in 1997, his share of the rights now belong to his estate and are administered by his former agent, Tim Hancock.

Early plans for what eventually became the 1996 ''Doctor Who'' television movie included radically redesigned Daleks whose cases unfolded like spiders' legs.Segal (2000), pp. 48–53  The concept for these "Spider Daleks" was abandoned, but picked up again in several ''Doctor Who'' spin-offs.

When the new series was announced, many fans hoped the Daleks would return once more to the programme.  After much negotiation between the BBC and the Nation estate (which at one point appeared to break down completely), an agreement was reached. According to media reports, the initial disagreement was due to the Nation estate demanding levels of creative control over the Daleks' appearances and scripts that were unacceptable to the BBC. Eventually talks between Hancock and the BBC progressed more productively, and the Daleks were cleared to appear in the first series.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="654f3516445b7a0403057b01456f8598" name="TheDalekChronicles-004" sectnum="2#1">../img/654f3516445b7a0403057b01456f8598.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>