<document id="ca4b68d231c4389802524a464fc74ef5-2.4" name="History_of_Poland_(1945–1989)" cat="14">
<text>
The Polish Communists were divided into two informal factions, named ''Natolin'' and ''Puławy'' after the locations where they held their meetings: the Palace of Natolin near Warsaw and Puławska Street in Warsaw. Natolin consisted largely of ethnic Poles of peasant origin who in large part had spent the war in occupied Poland, and had a peculiar nationalistic-communistic ideology. Headed by Władysław Gomułka, the faction underlined the national character of Polish local communist movement. Puławy faction included Jewish Communists, as well as members of the old Communist intelligentsia, who in large part spent the war in the USSR and supported the Sovietization of Poland. 

In June 1956, workers in the industrial city of Poznań went on strike. Demonstrations by striking workers turned into huge riots, in which 80 people were killed. Cyrankiewicz tried to repress the riots at first, threatening that "any provocateur or lunatic who raises his hand against the people's government may be sure that this hand will be chopped off." Radio Free Europe Background Reports.  1976-12-02 Retrieved on 2007-04-07 But soon the hard-liners realized that they had lost the support of the Soviet Union, and the regime turned to conciliation: it announced wage rises and other reforms. Voices began to be raised in the Party and among the intellectuals calling for wider reforms of the Stalinist system.

Realizing the need for new leadership, in what became known as Polish October, the PZPR chose Władysław Gomułka, a moderate who had been purged after losing his battle with Bierut, as First Secretary in October 1956; who convinced the Soviet Union that he would not allow its influence on Eastern Europe to diminish. Even so, Poland's relations with the Soviet Union were not nearly as strained as Yugoslavia's. As a further sign that the end of Soviet influence in Poland was nowhere in sight, the Warsaw Pact was signed in the Polish capital of Warsaw on 14 May 1955, to counteract the establishment of the Western NATO.

Hard-line Stalinists such as Berman were removed from power, and many Soviet officers serving in the Polish Armed Forces were dismissed, but almost no one was put on trial for the repressions of the Bierut period. The ''Puławy'' faction argued that mass trials of Stalin-era officials, many of them Jewish, would incite animosity toward the Jews. Konstantin Rokossovsky and other Soviet advisors were sent home, and Polish Communism took on a more independent orientation. However, Gomułka knew that the Soviets would never allow Poland to leave the Warsaw Pact because of Poland's strategic position between the Soviet Union and Germany. He agreed that Soviet troops could remain in Poland, and that no overt anti-Soviet outbursts would be allowed. In this way, Poland avoided the risk of the kind of Soviet armed intervention that crushed the revolution in Hungary that same month.

There were also repeated attempts by some Polish academics and philosophers, many related to the pre-war Lwow-Warsaw School and later Poznań School - such as Kazimierz Ajdukiewicz, Tadeusz Czeżowski, Leszek Kołakowski, Tadeusz Kotarbiński, Stanisław Ossowski, Adam Schaff - to develop a specific form of Polish Marxism. Their attempts to create a bridge between Poland's history and Soviet Marxist ideology were mildly successful, although always stifled due to the regime's unwillingness to risk the wrath of the Soviet Union for going too far from the Soviet party line.. Archived on 2008-02-02. Retrieved on 2007-04-05.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8aceca9b8e9a35f93099aa6fd5fa8089" name="Wladyslaw_Gomulka" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/8aceca9b8e9a35f93099aa6fd5fa8089.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>