<document id="ca934b6890d1ff2c5c5ac51e668647e9-1" name="Authentic_Science_Fiction" cat="17">
<text>
In 1950, science fiction (sf) magazines had been published successfully in North America for over twenty years, but little progress had been made in establishing British equivalents. The bulk of British sf was published as paperback books, rather than magazines; a situation opposite of that in the US.Ashley (''Transformations'', p. 82.) quotes the figures for 1952 as 95 sf books to 33 issues of sf magazines in the UK, whereas in the US that year there were 16 sf books and 152 sf magazine issues.  Several short-lived magazines had come and gone, both before and after the war. John Spencer launched four very poor quality juvenile magazines in 1950, which continued into the mid-1950s,Ashley, ''History of SF Magazine Vol. 3'', pp. 65&ndash;66. while one magazine, ''New Worlds'', had survived since 1946.Brian Stableford & Peter Nicholls, "New Worlds", in Nicholls & Clute, ''Encyclopedia of Science Fiction'', p. 867 Since 1939, Atlas, a British publisher, had been producing a reprint edition of ''Astounding Science Fiction'', one of the most well-regarded American sf magazines. During the war the contents had often been cut severely, and the schedule had not been regular, but it was reputed to sell 40,000 copies a month. This was enough to attract the attention of Hamilton & Co., a British publisher looking for new markets.Ashley, ''History of SF Magazine Vol. 3'', pp. 68&ndash;71

In 1949, Hamilton hired Gordon Landsborough as an editor. Landsborough did his best to improve the quality of the science fiction he was publishing, and was allowed to offer £1 per 1,000 words for selected material. He also was joined at Hamilton by H.J. Campbell, who was hired as a technical editor. Campbell was a London science fiction fan who had been brought on by Hulton Press (publisher of the very successful comic the ''Eagle'') to create a science fiction magazine, but the project had been abandoned before seeing print.

By the start of 1951, Hamilton's science fiction titles were being published every two weeks. On 1 January 1951, Hamilton published ''Mushroom Men from Mars'', by Lee Stanton, which was a pseudonym for Richard Conroy. A banner was added to the base of the cover reading "Authentic Science Fiction Series"; the same banner appeared on the 15 January novel, ''Reconnoitre Krellig II'', by Jon J. Deegan, also a pseudonym, this time for Robert G. Sharp. With the next book, Roy Sheldon's ''Gold Men of Aureus'', Landsborough changed the banner to read "Science Fiction Fortnightly No. 3", thinking that the caption might help sales.Ashley, ''Transformations'', pp. 82&ndash;86. In addition to the banner, a contents page (including a date and issue number), a letter column, an editorial, and an advertisement for subscriptions were inserted.  According to Landsborough, the banner was only intended to indicate the publishing schedule to readers, but combined with the other changes the appearance became much more magazine-like.  These changes established the sequence in the minds of readers and collectors, and retroactively determined that ''Mushroom Men from Mars'' had been the first in the series: the first two issues had carried no issue number. Issue 3 was also the first issue to carry the editors' names:See the individual issues. Landsborough used the pseudonym L.G. Holmes ("Holmes" was his middle name) for his editing role on the magazine.

The caption did apparently help sales: Landsborough subsequently commented that while Hamilton's other titles were selling perhaps 15,000 copies, ''Authentic'' managed to sell 30,000. After the banners were in place, Hamilton proposed launching a monthly sf magazine. Landsborough was concerned about the workload, and also felt it would be difficult to find enough good material; Hamilton refused to increase the pay rate, which was not high enough to attract the best stories. A compromise was reached, and ''Authentic'' was born as a monthly magazine in paperback format, with a single novel and a short editorial feature in each issue, plus an occasional short story. The eighth issue was the last on the fortnightly schedule. Issues 9&ndash;12 were titled "Science Fiction Monthly" in the footer of the cover. In mid-1951, Landsborough left Hamilton, and Campbell replaced him as editor of ''Authentic'' with the thirteenth issue, which was also the first one on which the title changed to "Authentic Science Fiction".

Under Campbell ''Authentic'' improved somewhat, and continued its metamorphosis into a magazine, with additional non-fiction writing, and short fiction in addition to the main novel in each issue. Hamilton also ran a science fiction paperback imprint, Panther Books, which would go on to become one of the leading British sf houses. By 1953 the British sf market was going through a metamorphosis similar to the one going in the US at the same time: poor quality sf markets were failing, and the result was a reduced but active market, with four active magazines: ''Authentic'', ''New Worlds'', ''Science Fantasy'', and ''Nebula Science Fiction''.Ashley, ''Transformations'', p. 93.

At the end of 1955 Campbell decided to give up editing in favour of his scientific career as a research chemist. He was replaced in the February 1956 issue by E.C. Tubb, who remained editor to the end of the magazine's life. Tubb had contributed a great deal of material to the magazine under various pseudonyms, often amounting to more than half of an issue's fiction, and he later recalled that Campbell's way of hiring him as editor was to say to him, "As you're practically writing it, you may as well edit it."Ashley, ''History of SF Magazine Part 4'', pp. 40&ndash;42. The quote is given as "You write most of it, you might as well edit it" in ''Transformations'', p. 99.

The quality of material submitted to Tubb was "dreadful", in the words of sf historian Michael Ashley,Ashley, ''History of SF Magazine Part 4'', p. 40 and included many stories that had previously been rejected by Campbell: he was able to recognize these because Campbell had kept a log of all submissions. One story was rejected that had been plagiarized from one that had appeared twelve years earlier in ''Astounding Science Fiction''. Tubb's overall acceptance rate was about one in twenty-five submissions. As a result, he found it difficult to keep standards up, often finding himself forced to write material under pseudonyms to fill an issue.Ashley, ''History of SF Magazine Part 4'', pp. 40&ndash;42

In early 1957, Tubb persuaded Hamilton to switch the magazine from pocket-book to digest size format, in the hope that this would improve the magazine's visibility on bookstalls. The circulation did indeed rise, to about 14,000 copies per month&mdash;a surprisingly low figure given Landsborough's assertion that ''Authentic'' had been selling 30,000 copies in the early days. However, later that year, Hamilton made the decision to invest a substantial sum in the UK paperback rights of an American best-seller: it is not known for certain which book this was, but it is thought to have been Evan Hunter's ''The Blackboard Jungle''. Hamilton could no longer afford to have cash tied up in ''Authentic'', and in the summer of 1957 Tubb was given two months to close down the magazine, printing stories that had already been paid for. The last issue was dated October 1957.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="017e2a0744463622c1601cce84694900" name="Authentic_cover_banners" sectnum="1#1">../img/017e2a0744463622c1601cce84694900.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>