<document id="cad13f6799773899b9e615089e05ff5c-6" name="Ann_Arbor,_Michigan" cat="11">
<text>
The ''Ann Arbor News'', owned by the Michigan-based Booth Newspapers chain, was the major daily newspaper serving Ann Arbor and the rest of Washtenaw County; the newspaper ended its 174-year print run on July 23, 2009, due to economic difficulties, and has been replaced by AnnArbor.com, which has a bi-weekly print operation, in addition to its website. Other established publications in the city include the ''Ann Arbor Observer'', a monthly magazine with features covering local culture, politics, family life, business and history, as well as a comprehensive calendar of events; ''Current'', an entertainment guide; the ''Communicator'', a local high school paper; and ''Ann Arbor Paper'', a free monthly that has ceased production. The University of Michigan campus area is served by many student publications, including the independent ''Michigan Daily''. The ''Ann Arbor Business Review'' covers local business in the area. The ''Ann Arbor Chronicle'' is an online newspaper that covers local news, including meetings of the library board, county commission, and DDA. ''Car and Driver'' magazine and ''Automobile Magazine''"Vile Gossip", Jean Jennings, ''Automobile Magazine'', November, 2007 are also based in Ann Arbor.

Four major AM radio stations based in or near Ann Arbor are WAAM 1600, a news and talk station; WLBY 1290, an Air America Radio affiliate; WDEO 990, Catholic radio; and WTKA 1050, which is primarily a sports station. The city's FM stations include NPR affiliate WUOM 91.7; country station WWWW 102.9; adult-alternative station WQKL 107.1. Freeform station WCBN-FM 88.3 is a local community radio station operated by the students of the University of Michigan featuring noncommercial, eclectic music and public-affairs programming. The city is also served by public and commercial radio broadcasters in Ypsilanti, the Lansing/Jackson area, Detroit, Windsor, and Toledo.

WPXD channel 31, an affiliate of the ION Television network, is licensed to the city. Community Television Network (CTN) is a city-provided cable television channel with production facilities open to city residents and nonprofit organizations. Detroit and Toledo-area radio and television stations also serve Ann Arbor, and stations from Lansing and Windsor, Ontario, can be heard in parts of the area.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0f853030d6bed41990af5ac8c64d15d1" name="AnnArborHydrant" sectnum="6#1">../img/0f853030d6bed41990af5ac8c64d15d1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>