<document id="cbcef8bacac0863a097520edcc0dd9ed-2.2.6" name="Benjamin_Morrell" cat="14">
<text>
''Antarctica'' left New York in September 1829 on the fourth of Morrell's voyages, bound for the Pacific. At her own insistence Morrell's wife accompanied him, and on her return prepared a memoir of her experiences (ghostwritten by Samuel Knapp), her declared purpose being "the amelioration of the condition of the American seaman". She was Morrell's second wife; his first, to whom he was married in 1819, had died  along with her two children while Morrell was at sea in 1822–24.Morrell does not name his first wife, nor the two children. See American National Biography, p. 879 He had then speedily married his 15-year-old  cousin, Abbey Jane Wood. 

The first port of call was the Auckland Islands, south of New Zealand, where Morrell had hoped for a rich harvest of seal, but found the waters empty.W.J.Mills, p. 39 He sailed north for the Pacific islands where, during the following months, ''Antarctica'' was involved in violent skirmishes with the inhabitants of islands in the archipelago now known as Micronesia. One of these encounters developed into a major battle, described by Morrell as a "massacre".Morrell, pp. 410–14 His account has been dismissed as fanciful, while a more straightforward record was given by one of his injured crewmen. This experience apparently did not deter Morrell from returning to these islands in order to exploit what he saw as their unrivalled commercial potential.Morrell, p. 416 After subduing a further attack on the ''Antarctic'' from the natives of Nukuoro, he purchased an island from them, for cutlery, trinkets and other artefacts, including possibly the first metal tools they had seen.Morrell, p. 440 (Section 5) His intention was to gather a harvest of ''biche-de-mer'', an edible sea-slug common in these waters which evidently commanded a great price in the Chinese market. Chapter 12, line 32  Following a brief interval of peace, Morrell's stronghold on the island was attacked again, after which Morrell decided to abandon the enterprise, due to the "unappeasable vindictiveness and incessant hostilities" of the native population.Morrell, p. 452

On his return home, despite the lack of commercial success, Morrell remained optimistic about his future prospects in the Pacific. "I could, with only a modest share of patronage  open a new avenue of trade more lucrative than any that our country has ever yet enjoyed, and further, it would be in my power, and mine alone, to secure the monopoly for any term I pleased."Morrell, p. 341 In the final paragraph of his account Morrell records that his wife's father, her aunt and her aunt's child had all died during his absence, as had one of Morrell's cousins and her husband.Morrell, p. 492
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ff4c4834f64a42fe6c2dc48ebe193fb7" name="EarleWarSpeech" sectnum="2.2.6#1">../img/ff4c4834f64a42fe6c2dc48ebe193fb7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>