<document id="cbcef8bacac0863a097520edcc0dd9ed-2.2.5" name="Benjamin_Morrell" cat="14">
<text>
In 1828 Morrell records that  he was engaged by Messrs. Christian Berg & Co. to take command of the schooner ''Antarctic'' (named, he claims, in honour of his earlier Antarctic achievements).Morrell, pp. 253–54  ''Antarctic'' left New York on 25 June 1828, bound for Western Africa. During the following months Morrell carried out an extensive survey of the African coast between the Cape of Good Hope and Benguela, and led several short excursions inland. He was impressed by the commercial potential of this coast, recording that "many kinds of skins may be procured about here, including those of the leopard, fox, bullock, together with ostrich feathers and valuable minerals".Morrell, p. 294 At Ichaboe Island he discovered huge deposits of guano, twenty-five feet thick, he reported. In the face of such opportunity he records his belief that a $30,000 investment would produce in two years a profit "from ten to fifteen hundred per cent."

During the voyage Morrell records several encounters with the slave trade, first at the Cape Verde Islands, then a centre for the trade due to their unique position equidistant from Europe, Africa and America. He found the slaves' conditions wretched, but observes their passion for music which, he writes,  "can alleviate even the pangs caused by the galling fetters of slavery".Morrell, p. 261 Later in the voyage he witnessed what he describes as "horrid barbarity", including the spectacle of two women slaves in their death agonies as a result of floggings. After a lengthy soliloquy in his journal on the evils of slavery, he gives his conclusion that "the root, the source, the foundation of the evil is the ignorance and superstition of the poor negroes themselves".Morrell, pp. 328–33 From a trading standpoint the voyage had evidently proved prosperous beyond all expectation, so on 8 June 1829 Morrell decided to head for home. They arrived in New York on 14 July.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="296d4e1dfb0dc76725ed66781a79f95d" name="ST-slaves" sectnum="2.2.5#1">../img/296d4e1dfb0dc76725ed66781a79f95d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>