<document id="cbcef8bacac0863a097520edcc0dd9ed-2.2.4" name="Benjamin_Morrell" cat="14">
<text>
For his second voyage Morrell took charge of a new ship, ''Tartar'', which sailed from New York on 19 July 1824 for the Pacific Ocean. In the next two years ''Tartar'' first explored  the American coastline from the Straits of Magellan to Cape Blanco (now in Oregon).Morrell, pp. 203–15 He then sailed westward to the islands of Hawaii,  known at that time as the Sandwich Islands, where Captain James Cook had  met his death nearly 40 years earlier. Thereafter ''Tartar'' returned to the American coast and tracked slowly southwards back to the Straits of Magellan.

Among the events witnessed and recorded in Morrell's journal were the siege of Callao, the main port of Peru, by Simón Bolívar's liberators,Rodriguez, p. 232Morrell, pp. 177–78 and a spectacular volcanic eruption on Fernandina Island in the Galápagos archipelago, which ''Tartar'' visited during February 1825. Fernandina, then known as Narborough Island, exploded on 14 February. In Morrell's words "The heavens appeared to be one blaze of fire, intermingling with millions of falling stars and meteors; while the flames shot upward from the peak of Narborough to the height of at least two thousand feet."Kricher, p. 57  Morrell reports that the air temperature reached 123 °F (51 °C), and as ''Tartar'' approached the river of lava flowing into the sea, the water temperature rose to 150 °F (66 °C). Some of the crew collapsed in the heat.

Morrell also records how a hunting trip ashore in California led to a skirmish with the locals which turned into a  full-scale battle ending, he says, with seventeen natives dead and seven of ''Tartar'''s men wounded. Morrell claims that he was among the casualties, with an arrow in his thigh. Of a visit to San Francisco Morrell writes: "The inhabitants are principally Mexicans and Spaniards who are very indolent and consequently very filthy." After revisiting the Galapagos Islands and gathering a harvest of fur seal and terrapin,Morrell uses the word "terrapin", presumably referring to the Galapagos tortoise. The terms were used interchangeably in Morrell's day; for example see Charles Darwin in , p. 312  ''Tartar'' began a slow journey home on 13 October 1825. As they left the Pacific Morrell claimed to have personally inspected and identified every danger existing along the American Pacific coast.Morrell, p. 231 ''Tartar'' finally reached  New York Harbour on 8 May 1826 with a main cargo of 6,000 fur seals. This haul did not please Morrell's employers, who had evidently expected rather more. "The reception I met from my owners was cold and repulsive", he wrote. "The ''Tartar'' did not return home laden with silver and gold, and therefore my toils and dangers counted for nothing".Morrell, p. 251
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4b37abe8403f7fd778d27e398273c083" name="Fernandina_isabela" sectnum="2.2.4#1">../img/4b37abe8403f7fd778d27e398273c083.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>