<document id="cc16b0773c5b1a2554a397fd3127a753-7.8" name="Lage_Raho_Munna_Bhai" cat="19">
<text>
After the release of the film, Gandhigiri-style protests began to take place in the United States and India. In the United States during July 2007, Aman Kapoor, founder of the'' Immigration Voice'' forum, initiated a Gandhigiri protest inspired by ''Lage Raho Munna Bhai.'' Over a three day period, hundreds of flower bouquets were sent to the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services office by Indians who were legally in the U.S. but caught in a green card backlog. In response, the USCIS shipped the flowers to the Walter Reed Army Medical Center and Bethesda Naval hospitals. On 17 July, the USCIS announced that "it will accept applications from foreign professionals seeking permanent residency through an expedited process, reversing its earlier decision." USCIS Director Emilio T. Gonzalez noted, "The public reaction to the July 2 announcement made it clear that the federal government's management of this process needs further review ... I am committed to working with Congress and the State Department to implement a more efficient system in line with public expectations." 

There have also been a number of protests in India which were inspired by the film. Farmers staged a protest with flowers in the Vidarbha region, and people who organised a protest in Lucknow claimed to have been inspired by ''Lage Raho Munna Bhai'' to use roses to convey their message. Indian Greenpeace activists delivered thousands of roses to Ratan Tata, Chairman of Tata Motors, to reconsider his plans of building a port at the nesting grounds of Olive Ridley sea turtles. In Lucknow, students claimed to have been inspired by ''Lage Raho Munna Bhai'' to do volunteer work, planting trees "to conserve nature which is bound to benefit public health." The “Send Pramod Muthalik a Valentine’s Day card” campaign was inspired by the film. Mafia don Babloo Srivastava claimed to have been inspired by ''Lago Raho Munna Bhai'' to distribute roses as a "message of love and peace".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9168887aa6a8b22bae73a3cc0fe0ae44" name="Marche_sel" sectnum="7.8#1">../img/9168887aa6a8b22bae73a3cc0fe0ae44.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>