<document id="cc2b6c39477e75891ec2b24d942f1f3e-2.3" name="SMS_Moltke_(1910)" cat="29">
<text>
''Moltke'' was to have taken part in what would have amounted to the "death ride" of the High Seas Fleet shortly before the end of World War I. The bulk of the High Seas Fleet was to have sortied from their base in Wilhelmshaven to engage the British Grand Fleet; Scheer&mdash;by now the ''Großadmiral'' of the fleet&mdash;intended to inflict as much damage as possible on the British navy, in order to retain a better bargaining position for Germany, whatever the cost to the fleet.Tarrant, pp. 280&ndash;281 However, while the fleet was consolidating in Wilhelmshaven, war-weary sailors began deserting en masse. As ''Von der Tann'' and ''Derfflinger'' passed through the locks that separated Wilhelmshaven's inner harbour and roadstead, some 300 men from both ships climbed over the side and disappeared ashore. Massie, p. 775 

On 24 October 1918, the order was given to sail from Wilhelmshaven. Starting on the night of 29 October, sailors on several battleships mutinied; three ships from the III Squadron refused to weigh anchors, and acts of sabotage were committed on board the battleships  and . The order to sail was rescinded in the face of this open revolt. A month later, the German Revolution  began; it toppled the monarchy and led to the Armistice that ended the war.Tarrant, pp. 281&ndash;282

The vessel was surrendered with the rest of the High Seas Fleet on 24 November 1918 and interned at Scapa Flow, under the command of ''Kapitän-Leutnant'' Wollante.Reuter, p. 154 Believing that the Treaty of Versailles had been signed and his fleet was about to be seized by the British, Rear Admiral von Reuter ordered the scuttling of the High Seas Fleet on 21 June 1919, while the British Grand Fleet was away on exercises.  The ship sank in two hours and fifteen minutes.Reuter, p. 153 ''Moltke'' was raised in 1927 and scrapped at Rosyth in 1929.Hore, p. 72
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="32659cba31c2a85f3d02ecbfda5d0227" name="German_battlecruisers_steaming_to_Scapa" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/32659cba31c2a85f3d02ecbfda5d0227.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>