<document id="cc3471ba62dc677884b143b8ba0c66eb-1.3" name="Roman_Vishniac" cat="1">
<text>
The Vishniac family fled from Lisbon to New York City in 1940, arriving on New Year's Eve. Vishniac tried for days to get a job but failed: "For me, it was a time of distraction and fear." Vishniac struggled. He was multilingual, speaking at least German, Russian and Yiddish, but he could speak no English yet and thus had a difficult time.Weiner, Jonathan (circa 1981). "Field of Vision". Moment. pg 37. He managed to do some portraiture work with mostly foreign clients; but business was poor. It was during this time, in 1942, that Roman took one of his most celebrated portraits, that of Albert Einstein. Vishniac arrived at Einstein's home in Princeton, New Jersey, getting into the scientist's study with the ruse of bringing regards from mutual friends in Europe, and photographed him while the scientist was not paying attention to him, occupied in thought. Einstein later called this portrait his favourite one of him. In 1946, Roman Vishniac divorced Luta, and the next year he married Edith Ernst, an old family friend. A few years later, he gave up portraiture and went on to do freelance work in the field of photomicroscopy.

Once in the United States, Roman Vishniac tried desperately to earn sympathy for impoverished Jews in Eastern Europe. When his work was exhibited at Teachers College, Columbia University in 1943,"Studies in Misery Shown". ''New York Times (1859-Current file);'' 2 February 1943; ProQuest Historical Newspapers pg. 21. Vishniac wrote to Eleanor Roosevelt (First Lady at the time), asking her to visit the exhibit, but she did not do so. He also sent some of his photographs to the president for which he was politely thanked.Edited by Kohn, Mara Vishniac and Flacks, Miriam Hartman. ''Roman Vishniac: Children of a Vanished World''. University of California Press. Berkeley and Los Angeles, California. 1999. ISBN 0-520-22187-7"absolutearts.com" . Accessed October 18, 2005.

Of the 16,000 taken in Eastern Europe by Roman Vishniac, only 2,000 photographs reached America.UCSB Arts & Lectures (2000). . Accessed October 18, 2005. Most of these negatives were carefully hidden by Roman and his family; others were smuggled in by Vishniac's good friend Walter Bierer through Cuba. In the photographer's own words,
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a58835c90466a7959268f16b1d6ebca3" name="EinsteinVishniac" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/a58835c90466a7959268f16b1d6ebca3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>