<document id="cc3471ba62dc677884b143b8ba0c66eb-1.1" name="Roman_Vishniac" cat="1">
<text>
Roman  was born in his grandparents' ''dacha'' outside of Saint Petersburg, in the town of Pavlovsk, and grew up in Moscow.Kohn, Mara Vishniac, Biographical Note (1992). ''To Give them Light: The Legacy of Roman Vishniac''. Simon & Schuster. New York, New York 10020. 1993. ISBN 0-671-63872-6. To live in this city was a right granted to few Jews but Roman could live there because his father, Solomon Vishniac, was a wealthy manufacturer of umbrellas, and his mother, Manya, was the daughter of affluent diamond dealers (Roman also had a sister, KatjaJüdisches Museum Berlin (2005). ''Roman Vishniac's Berlin''. Editors: Mara Vishniac Kohn, James Howard Fraser and Aubrey Pomerance. Published by Nicolaische Verlagsbuchhandlung.). During the summer months; however, the Vishniacs would leave: Moscow often became uncomfortably hot and the family would retreat to a ''dacha'' a few miles outside of that city.

As a child, Roman Vishniac was fascinated by biology and photography, and his room was filled with "plants, insects, fish and small animals".Vishniac, Roman. ''The Concerns of Roman Vishhniac: Man, Nature and Science''. On his seventh birthday, Roman got a microscope from his grandmother, to which he promptly hooked up a camera, and by which he photographed the muscles in a cockroach's leg at 150 times magnification. Young Vishniac used this microscope extensively, viewing and photographing everything he could find, from dead insects to animal scales, to pollen and protozoa. 

Until the age of ten, Vishniac was homeschooled; from ten to seventeen, he attended a private school at which he earned a gold medal for scholarship.''Roman Vishniac''. Current Biography (1967). Beginning in 1914, he spent six years at Shanyavsky Institute (now University) in Moscow. While enrolled there, he served in the Tsarist, Kerensky and Soviet armies. At the Institute, he earned a Ph.D. in zoology and became an assistant professor of biology. As a graduate student, he worked with prestigious biologist Nikolai Koltzoff, experimenting with inducing metamorphosis in axolotl, a species of aquatic salamander. While his experiments were a success, Dr. Vishniac was not able to publish a paper detailing his findings due to the chaos in Russia and his results were eventually independently duplicated. In spite of this, he went on to take a three year course in medicine.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7136aaee01f08adf33a9feb14f227fce" name="VishniacBerlin" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/7136aaee01f08adf33a9feb14f227fce.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>