<document id="cc3471ba62dc677884b143b8ba0c66eb-3" name="Roman_Vishniac" cat="1">
<text>
Roman Vishniac always had strong ties with his ancestry, especially the Jewish aspect of it, "From earliest childhood, my main interest was my ancestors". He was a Zionist and a strong sympathizer with Jews who had suffered because of anti-Semitism, "Oh yes, I could be a professor of anti-Semitism", also stating then that he had one hundred and one relatives who died during the Holocaust. A famous photo of his (''pictured right'') of a store in Berlin selling devices for separating Jews and non-Jews by skull shape was used by him to criticize the pseudoscience of German anti-Semites.

Vishniac associated much of his work with religion, though not specifically Judaism. "Nature, God, or whatever you want to call the creator of the Universe comes through the microscope clearly and strongly," he remarked in his laboratory one day.

Living with the memory of hardship, Vishniac was, "an absolute optimist filled with tragedy. His humanism is not just for Jews, but for every living thing." While he was alive, Roman probably believed in God or some similar concept, but he was non-denominational and did not adhere strictly to the principles of any religion. He even clashed with Orthodox Jews in one well-known instance: The religious Jews he met on his trek around Europe would not let themselves be photographed, quoting the Bible and its prohibition of making of graven images. Vishniac's famous response was, "the Torah existed for thousands of years before the camera had been invented."

Roman Vishniac was known for having great respect for all living creatures. Whenever possible, he returned a specimen to its precise home before it was captured and one time lent, "his bathtub to tadpoles for weeks until he could return them to their pond". In accordance with this philosophy, he photographed almost exclusively living subjects."The saved faces of Roman Vishniac." (Photography) (Currents) (obituary) U.S. News & World Report, February 5, 1990 v108 n5 p11(1). Science Resource Center. Thomson Gale. . Accessed January 3, 2006.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bae0a6721329a692a720996dffcddd61" name="VishniacMara" sectnum="3#1">../img/bae0a6721329a692a720996dffcddd61.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>