<document id="cc3471ba62dc677884b143b8ba0c66eb-2.5.1" name="Roman_Vishniac" cat="1">
<text>
Vishniac is best known for his dramatic photographs of Jews in cities and ''shtetlach'' of Eastern Europe. He was commissioned to take these pictures initially by the American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee as part of a fundraising initiative; but, Vishniac took a personal interest in this photography. He traveled back and forth from Berlin to the ghettos of Russia, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia and Lithuania for years after he worked for the Committee.

While touring Europe, Roman Vishniac posed as a traveling fabric salesman, seeking aid where he could and bribing anyone who got in his way.Murray, Schumach. "Vishniac's Lost World Of the Jews". ''New York Times (1859-Current file);'' 25 November 1983; ProQuest Historical Newspapers The New York Times (1851–2002) pg. C1. During his touring of Eastern Europe (1935–1939), he was often arrested by police for taking these pictures, sometimes because he was thought to be spying, (Jews were not allowed to take pictures or even carry cameras). Later, when published, these photographs made him popular enough for his work to be showcased as one-man shows at Columbia University, the Jewish Museum, International Center of Photography and other such institutions.



Vishniac, being a Jew, had to struggle immensely to take the 16,000 photos he did. Every one of his photos from this period was a candid shot; the subjects never even knew his camera existed. He also could not take more than one shot of a scene or buy two rolls of film at a time because he was not of Aryan descent.Roman Vishniac. ''Polish Jews: A Pictorial Record''. Schoken Books Inc. New York. 1976. Vishniac sometimes developed his film in Berlin, other times he was forced to do it out on the countryside, in rivers of the Carpathian Mountains on moonless nights. 

In order to reach some of the small villages in these mountains, he had to carry heavy equipment (Leica, Rolleiflex, movie camera, tripods etc.), 115 pounds (52 kilograms) by his estimate, on his back, up steep roads, trekking many miles. With a concealed Leica wrapped in a scarf at his forehead or a  RolleiflexKeppler, Herbert. "A vanished world". Modern Photography, Sept 1984 v48 p92(1). Accessed January 3, 2006, from InfoTrac Web: OneFile A3409487 peeking out through an enlarged button hole of his coat, Vishniac captured tens of thousands of impoverished Jews on film, " to preserve – in pictures, at least – a world that might soon cease to exist".Mendoza, Bernard (2003). . Accessed September 3, 2005. This Leica was acquired through a non-Jewish friend, but he had to give the camera back often (the police were trying to make sure that no Jews were using the camera, and they usually checked with his friend in the evenings).

For indoor shots, when the Leica was used, there was the problem of insufficient lighting: there would rarely be artificial light in the home of a poor Jew. Vishniac could not use a tripod (for the camera had to remain concealed) to get long exposures, so he had to bring a kerosene lamp (visible in some of his work), keep his back to a wall for support, and hold his breath. The Rolleiflex was used mostly for outdoor scenes.

Roman Vishniac did not just want to preserve the memories of the Jews; he actively fought to increase awareness in the West of the worsening situation in Eastern Europe. "Through his photographs, he sought to alert the rest of the world to the horrors ", Mitgang. In late 1938, for example, he sneaked into Zbaszyn, an internment camp in Germany near the border, where Jews awaited deportment to Poland. After photographing the "filthy barracks", as he described it, for two days, Levin, Eric. "A fateful photo from the Holocaust leads photographer and subject to an emotional reunion in the Bronx" People Weekly, April 23, 1984 v21 p74(2). Retrieved January 3, 2006, from InfoTrac Web InfoTrac OneFile A3233313. he escaped by jumping from the second floor at night and creeping away, avoiding broken glass and barbed wire. He then used photographs taken to prove the existence of such camps to the League of Nations.

After Roman's death, more photographs were discovered, and the current exhibit in Berlin showcases such newly discovered photographs. The negatives of these were found at the end of rolls of film used by him in his scientific pursuits.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="23fa056932a7cb63797e65dba89162d1" name="VanishedWorldCover" sectnum="2.5.1#1">../img/23fa056932a7cb63797e65dba89162d1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>