<document id="cc4ae1288559a1edf173dfb6a0c5b9f2-2.2" name="Lockdown_(2008)" cat="26">
<text>
The next match pitted Booker T and Sharmell against Robert Roode and Payton Banks in an intergender tag team match. Towards the end of the match, Roode held Sharmell for Banks to slap her; Sharmell kicked Roode in the groin and jumped out of the way, causing Banks to slap Roode by mistake. Sharmell followed up on this by rolling-up Banks of for the pinfall victory.


The Lethal Lockdown match between Team Cage (Christian Cage, Kevin Nash, Rhino, Sting, and Matt Morgan) and Team Tomko (Tomko, A.J. Styles, Team 3D , and James Storm, accompanied by Jacqueline) followed. The match was supposed to begin with the team captains (Cage and Tomko); it instead began with Cage and Styles, when Styles climbed up the cage wall behind Cage into the ring and jumped from the top of a padded turnbuckle to strike Cage in the back of the head with a flying forearm strike. Styles and Cage fought back and forth for five minutes. At this point, Ray entered from Team Tomko and members from each team followed at two-minute intervals until the final member, Sting, entered the match. A retractable ceiling was then lowered, covered in weapons including a ladder, a table, trash cans, and kendo sticks, which the competitors immediately began to use. In the final minutes of the match, while Styles and Cage were on the roof standing on top of a ladder, Storm pushed the ladder over, causing them both to fall and crash through a table, which was set up on the roof by Cage earlier in the match. Storm then climbed down into the cage and hit Morgan over his head with a beer bottle, given to him by Jacqueline from outside the ring. After Storm turned around, Rhino performed a running shoulder block to Storm's stomach to gain the pinfall victory for Team Cage.

In the main event, Kurt Angle defended the TNA World Heavyweight Championship against Samoa Joe. Throughout the match, each man countered the other's submission holds in an attempt to make them concede defeat. Late in the match, Joe placed Angle on the top of a padded turnbuckle, lifted Angle up, and slammed Angle's back and neck into his shoulder and the mat by using a maneuver dubbed the Muscle Buster. He then pinned Angle to win his first World Heavyweight Championship. Marcus Davis presented him with the championship belt, and Joe celebrated as the event came to a close.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c89b4e87296a9f5dfcf147ce68a72656" name="Kurt_Angle_TNA" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/c89b4e87296a9f5dfcf147ce68a72656.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>