<document id="cc4ae1288559a1edf173dfb6a0c5b9f2-2.1" name="Lockdown_(2008)" cat="26">
<text>
The Xscape match for the TNA X Division Championship was the first match at Lockdown to air live on PPV. The participants were Jay Lethal, Curry Man, Shark Boy, Johnny Devine, Sonjay Dutt, and Consequences Creed. Devine and Lethal were the last two participants in the match. Devine and Lethal fought back and forth for a few minutes, until Lethal escaped the cage with help from Dutt and Lethal's on-screen girlfriend, SoCal Val, to retain the championship.


The Queen of the Cage match to become the number one contender to the TNA Women's Knockout Championship followed, which involved Roxxi Laveaux, Angelina Love, Velvet Sky, Salinas, Rhaka Khan, Traci Brooks, Christy Hemme, and Jacqueline. In this match, the participants fought to climb up the cage and into the ring, where the first two to do so had a standard wrestling match. The two women that entered the cage were Love and Laveaux. In the final minutes, Laveaux picked up Love, placed her arm over Love's head, and then fell to a seat position to execute what Laveaux dubbed as The Voodoo Drop; Laveaux then pinned Love to earn the opportunity to compete for the TNA Women's Knockout Title.

The third bout was a Six Sides of Steel cage match between B.G. James and Kip James. B.G. was victorious in the match when grabbed Kip's legs and achieved a position with his shoulders spread to win by pinfall in a pinning attempt called a roll-up.

The Cuffed in the Cage match for a future TNA World Tag Team Championship match against the tag team champions, A.J. Styles and Tomko, involved the teams of Kaz and Eric Young, The Motor City Machine Guns (Chris Sabin and Alex Shelley), Rellik and Black Reign, The Latin American Xchange (Homicide and Hernandez), Scott Steiner and Petey Williams, and The Rock 'n Rave Infection (Lance Hoyt and Jimmy Rave) (RNRI). In this match, six two-man teams were locked inside the Six Sides of Steel until eleven of the wrestlers were handcuffed to the cage, while the remaining competitor won the future championship match for his team. While the RNRI were making their way to the ring, Young was injured in a backstage assault by Rellik and Reign and, as a result, Kaz competed in the match alone until Young recovered from his scripted injuries. Rellik, Reign, and RNRI were the last competitors in the match, before Eric Young entered the arena in another persona named "Super Eric". Super Eric then ran to the ring, climbed up to the top of the cage, and jumped off to perform a splash onto all of his opponents, who were standing together in a group. Afterwards he stood up and handcuffed all of the remaining participants to win Kaz and himself the future championship match.

Awesome Kong and Raisha Saeed fought the team of Gail Kim and ODB in the next match. The match ended when Kong attempted to perform a spinning back fist on O.D.B., but she ducked, causing Kong to accidentally hit her partner Saeed. Kim then performed a dropkick from the top of a padded turnbuckle on Kong, which allowed O.D.B. to climb to the center of the top rope and execute a splash on Saeed for the pinfall victory.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c32b0704614c23a8db21f298f0cae3cb" name="JaylethalLockdown07" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/c32b0704614c23a8db21f298f0cae3cb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>