<document id="cc726d8ba07859dc74addc6961852500-7" name="George_III_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
In late 1810, at the height of his popularityBrooke, p.381; Carretta, p.340 but already virtually blind with cataracts and in pain from rheumatism, George III became dangerously ill. In his view the malady had been triggered by the stress he suffered at the death of his youngest and favourite daughter, Princess Amelia.Hibbert, p.396 The Princess's nurse reported that "the scenes of distress and crying every day ... were melancholy beyond description."Hibbert, p.394 He accepted the need for the Regency Act 1811,Brooke, p.383; Hibbert, pp.397–398 and the Prince of Wales acted as Regent for the remainder of George III's life. By the end of 1811, George III had become permanently insane and lived in seclusion at Windsor Castle until his death.Fraser, p.285; Hibbert, pp.399–402

Perceval was assassinated in 1812 (the only British Prime Minister to have suffered such a fate) and was replaced by Lord Liverpool. Liverpool oversaw British victory in the Napoleonic Wars. The subsequent Congress of Vienna led to significant territorial gains for Hanover, which was upgraded from an electorate to a kingdom.

Meanwhile, George's health deteriorated, and eventually he became completely blind and increasingly deaf. He never knew that he was declared King of Hanover in 1814, or of the death of his wife in 1818. Over Christmas 1819, he spoke nonsense for 58 hours, and for the last few weeks of his life was unable to walk. On 29 January 1820, he died at Windsor Castle. His favourite son, Frederick, Duke of York, was with him.Hibbert, p.408 His death came six days after that of his fourth son, the Duke of Kent. George III was buried on 15 February in St. George's Chapel, Windsor Castle.

George was succeeded by two of his sons George IV and William IV, who both died without surviving legitimate children, leaving the throne to their niece, Victoria, the last monarch of the House of Hanover and the only legitimate child of the Duke of Kent.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2f32b3dbbe5a8cb965394dc03afa4b3a" name="Courtprivatelife-_George_III" sectnum="7#1">../img/2f32b3dbbe5a8cb965394dc03afa4b3a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>