<document id="cca017687d11e7f50ca0ba0ab8691608-3.9" name="Iowa_class_battleship" cat="29">
<text>
The primary armament of an ''Iowa''-class battleship is nine  / 50-caliber Mark 7 naval guns,Originally the armament was to be nine 16"/50 Mark 2 Naval Guns intended for the canceled ''South Dakota''-class battleships; however, a miscommunication between the design bureaus left the class barbettes too small to fit the Mark 2 guns; so the ''Iowa'' class was equipped with the Mark 7 Naval Guns instead. See: DiGiulian, ''United States of America 16"/50 (40.6 cm) Mark 7''. which are housed in three 3-gun turrets: two forward and one aft in a configuration known as "2-A-1". The guns are  long (50 times their  bore, or 50 calibers, from breechface to muzzle). About  protrudes from the gun house. Each gun weighs about 239,000 pounds (108,000 kg) without the breech, or  with the breech. They fire projectiles weighing from 1,900 to 2,700 pounds (850 to 1,200 kg) at a maximum speed of 2,690 ft/s (820 m/s) up to 20 miles (32 km). At maximum range the projectile spends almost 1½ minutes in flight. The maximum firing rate for each gun on an ''Iowa''-class battleship is two rounds per minute.Poyer, pp. 50–53. When firing two ''broadsides'' per minute, a single ''Iowa''-class battleship can put  of ordnance on a designated target every minute, a figure that can only be matched by a single B-52 Stratofortress of the United States Air Force. A B-52 can carry up to  of bombs, missiles, and mines, or any combination thereof.

RADAR range estimation provided a significant accuracy advantage over earlier ships with optical rangefinders.  A United States Navy officer who spent months towing 5- to  surface targets for various warships during World War II recalled long range practice firing from over the horizon and stated: "The ''Iowa''s always fired nine-gun salvos, and the opening one usually straddled the target."Hoskins (September 1983) p.103    

Each gun rests within an armored turret, but only the top of the turret protrudes above the main deck. The turret extends either four decks (Turrets 1 and 3) or five decks (Turret 2) down. The lower spaces contain rooms for handling the projectiles and storing the powder bags used to fire them. Each turret required a crew of between 85 and 110 men to operate. The turrets are not actually attached to the ship, but sit on rollers, which means that if the ship were to capsize the turrets would fall out.During his investigation of the wreck of the German battleship ''Bismarck'' oceanographer Robert D. Ballard and his team found four large empty barbettes that had once held the turrets Anton, Bruno, Caesar, and Doris. Ballard noted in his book ''Exploring the Bismarck'' that, "None of the four big turrets  still attached to the ship", each having fallen out when the battleship capsized and sank.  The original cost for each turret was US$1.4 million, but this number does not take into account the cost of the guns themselves.

The turrets are "three-gun", not "triple", because each barrel can be elevated independently; they can also be fired independently. The ship could fire any combination of its guns, including a broadside of all nine. Contrary to myth, the ships do not move noticeably sideways when a broadside is fired. The guns can be elevated from &minus;5° to +45°, moving at up to 12° per second. The turrets can be rotated about 300° at about four degrees per second and can even be fired back beyond the beam, which is sometimes called "over the shoulder". Within each turret, a red stripe on the wall of the turret, just inches from the railing, would have marked the boundary of the gun's recoil, providing the crew of each gun turret with a visual reference for the minimum safe distance range. The guns are never fired directly forward because of the shape of the bow and risk that firing the guns forward would damage the ship; in addition to this concern, a satellite up-link antenna was mounted at the bow of each battleship when they were reactivated in the 1980s.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="79c739328826e5ff87b1c22a3f07a230" name="Uss_iowa_bb-61_pr" sectnum="3.9#1">../img/79c739328826e5ff87b1c22a3f07a230.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>