<document id="cca017687d11e7f50ca0ba0ab8691608-4" name="Iowa_class_battleship" cat="29">
<text>
Aside from its firepower, a battleship's other defining feature is its armor. Battleships are usually armored to withstand an attack from guns the size of their own, but the exact design and placement of the armor—factors inextricably linked with the ship's stability and performance—is a complex science honed over decades.

Unlike modern warships, which operate on the concept of eliminating an incoming threat (anti-ship missiles or enemy aircraft) before the given threat strikes a ship and thus carry lighter armor, the ''Iowa''-class was designed and built in an age when ships were expected to withstand an onslaught of naval shells from enemy ships, emplaced coastal defenses from fortified enemy positions near the coast, and the increasing threat of gunfire and armour piercing/incendiary bombs dropped by enemy fighter and bomber aircraft. Like most World War II era battleships, the ''Iowa''-class was equipped with class B armor plate designed to a post-Jutland configuration (the "all or nothing" armor scheme), but unlike earlier WWII-era battleship, the ''Iowas'' benefited from advances in steel technology that allowed mills to forge the steel at higher temperatures and heat treatment, which produced a much higher-quality, stronger and more ductile armor. The metal was a nickel-steel compound, classified as a stainless steel, that can bend easily and resists corrosion. Most of the armor was manufactured at Bethlehem Steel’s main mill in Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, and Luken Steel’s Coatesville mill just outside Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. The exception was the turret plating, which was forged at a plant built especially for the ''Iowas'': the Charleston Ordnance Works in Charleston, West Virginia.



The ''Iowa''-class battleships' armor can be divided into the part above the waterline, which is designed to protect the ship against gunfire and aerial bombing, and that below the waterline, intended to protect the vessel from mines, near-miss bombs, and torpedoes. 

Overall, ''Iowa''-class armor is essentially the same as on the earlier ''South Dakota''-class battleships. Both have an internal main belt, a change from the previous two s that was reluctantly adopted because it was difficult to install and repair. An external belt that could ward off   shells would have required a belt incline of 19° and a beam too wide for the Panama Canal.

The underwater armor includes side protection and a triple bottom, both multi-layered systems designed to absorb the energy from an underwater explosion equivalent to  of TNT—the Navy's best guess in the 1930s about Japanese weapons.  However, unbeknownst to U.S. Naval Intelligence, the Japanese  "Long Lance" torpedo carried a  warhead. 

The ''Iowa''-class torpedo defense is virtually the same as the ''South Dakota'''s. Each side of the ship is protected by one tank mounted outside the hull and loaded with fuel oil or other liquid ballast, and an empty inboard tank, all running from the third deck to the bottom of the ship. The liquid tanks are to deform and absorb the shock from the explosion and contain most of the shards from the damaged structure. The inner void is expected to contain any leakage into the interior ship spaces. The armor belt is designed to stop fragments that penetrate the second torpedo bulkhead; however, tests in 1943 showed structural defects in the system.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a9ab2ec015ffc412877ee8bca814bad2" name="USS_New_Jersey_armor_citadel" sectnum="4#1">../img/a9ab2ec015ffc412877ee8bca814bad2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>