<document id="cca017687d11e7f50ca0ba0ab8691608-1.1" name="Iowa_class_battleship" cat="29">
<text>
The ''Iowa'' class, like the ''South Dakota'' class and ''North Carolina'' class, began in response to the need for fast escorts for the s. Plans for fast battleships that displaced 45,000 tons had been under development since 1935, beginning with a study of the idea of creating an extended ''South Dakota'' class that would take full advantage of the escalator clause of the Second London Naval Treaty. When the Second Vinson Act was passed by the United States Congress in 1938, the U.S. Navy moved quickly to develop a 45,000-ton battleship that would pass through the 110 ft (34 m) wide Panama Canal. Drawing on the earlier speed equations and a newly developed empirical theorem that related waterline length to maximum beam, the Navy drafted plans for a battleship class with a maximum beam of 108 ft (33 m), which when multiplied by 7.96 produced a waterline length of 860 ft (262 m), permitting a maximum speed of . The Navy also called for the class to have a lengthened forecastle and amid-ship, which would increase speed, and a bulbous bow.Davis, p. 10.

As with the preceding battleship classes, the ''Iowa''-class battleships were "Panamax" ships&mdash;built within the size limits required to transition the Panama Canal. The main reason for this was logistical: the largest U.S. shipyards were located on the East Coast of the United States, while the United States had territorial interests in both oceans. Requiring the battleships to fit within the Panama Canal saved days off the transition time from the Atlantic Ocean to the Pacific Ocean by allowing ships to move through the canal instead of sailing all the way around South America.Sailing a battleship around South America was unusual, but had been done by the battleship  during the Spanish-American War in 1898. See Modern supercarriers face this same problem: they are unable to pass through the canal and must circumnavigate South America to move from the Atlantic Ocean to the Pacific Ocean.



Originally, the ships were to mount the Mark 2  / 50-caliber gun, which had been intended to arm the ''South Dakota''-class battleships and ''Lexington''-class battlecruisers canceled in 1922. But due to a miscommunication between the Bureau of Ordnance and the Bureau of Construction and Repair that left the ship's barbettes too small, the Mark 2 guns were replaced in the design by the new, lighter Mark 7 16-inch/50-caliber gun.DiGiulian, ''United States of America 16"/50 (40.6 cm) Mark 7''. The Mark 7 was heavier and had a greater range than the 16"/45 Caliber Mark 6 guns used on the preceding ''North Carolina''- and ''South Dakota''-class ships. The Mark 7 was originally intended to fire the same  shell as the 16-in/45-caliber gun, but as the design was being completed a new "super-heavy"  shell was developed for both guns. However, the ''Iowa''s armor was only designed to resist 2,240 lb (1,016 kg) shells, as adding armor would have pushed the ship's weight over the 45,000-ton limit.

At the time the ''Iowa'' class had been cleared for construction, the United States Congress had allocated only enough money to construct the first two ships (''Iowa'' and ''New Jersey''). Congress had not expected the ''Iowa'' class to be so costly; with a price tag of $125 million per ship, the ''Iowa''s were 60% more expensive than the previously authorized battleship classes.Adjusted for inflation using the Consumer Price Index, each individual ''Iowa''-class battleship would cost US$1.8 billion in 2008 dollars. The total cost of the four completed ships of the class in 2008 dollars was just under $7.4 billion, but if all six ships of the ''Iowa'' class been completed the total cost in 2008 dollars would have been $11 billion. This estimation does not take into account the price of the various specialty items that the U.S. Navy would have needed for the battleships. (). Moreover, some policymakers were not sold on the U.S. need for more battleships, and proposed turning the ships into aircraft carriers by retaining the hull design but switching their decks to carry and handle aircraft.This had already been done with two of the s&mdash; and &mdash;back in the 1920's.Friedman, ''U.S. Aircraft Carriers'', 190.In the end, the ''Cleveland''-class light cruisers were selected for the aircraft carrier conversion. Nine of these light cruisers would be rebuilt as ''Independence''-class light aircraft carriers. Friedman, ''U.S. Aircraft Carriers'', 191. The proposal to build the ''Iowas'' as aircraft carriers was countered by Admiral Ernest King, the Chief of Naval Operations,On the issue of redesigning the ''Iowa''-class to be aircraft carriers, Admiral Earnest King is quoted as saying "I cannot acquiesce in a complete cessation of BB construction", to President Franklin Roosevelt. See:  and Congress' position on the funding for the ''Iowa'' class changed after the Fall of France, when Roosevelt demanded that Congress fund a two-ocean navy to meet the threats posed in the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans. Concern over the German invasion prompted Congress to respond by allotting enough money to complete the last four ''Iowa''-class battleships (''Missouri'', ''Wisconsin'', ''Illinois'', and ''Kentucky'').

Under the direction of Secretary of the Navy Charles Edison, the design was finalized and a contract was signed with the shipyards in July 1939 for the construction of BB-61, BB-62, BB-63, and BB-64 (all ''Iowa''-class battleships) along with BB-65 and BB-66, the first two ships of the ''Montana'' class of battleships.At the time, the  was planned to begin with hull number BB-65, but following the success of carrier combat at the Battle of Coral Sea and, to a greater extent, the Battle of Midway, BB-65 and BB-66 were reordered as ''Iowa'' class battleships and assigned the names ''Illinois'' and ''Kentucky'', respectively. See:  By 1942, however, the United States Navy shifted its building focus from battleships to aircraft carriers after the successes of carrier combat in both the Battle of Coral Sea and, to a greater extent, the Battle of Midway.

As a result, the construction of the U.S. fleet of s had been given the highest priority for completion in the U.S. shipyards by the U.S. Navy. (Convenience copy from .) The ''Essex''-class carriers required escorts that could steam with the carriers at a comparable speed, which prompted the U.S. Navy to reorder BB-65 and BB-66 as ''Iowa''-class battleships, enabling both battleships to steam at a comparable speed with the ''Essex''-class and provide the carriers with the maximum amount of anti-aircraft protection.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="26afe828432289eeffd26acd7167ad53" name="USS_Iowa_Pedro_Miguel_Locks_cropped" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/26afe828432289eeffd26acd7167ad53.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>