<document id="cca017687d11e7f50ca0ba0ab8691608-1.2" name="Iowa_class_battleship" cat="29">
<text>
When brought into service during the final years of World War II, the ''Iowa''-class battleships were assigned to operate in the Pacific, primarily to provide anti-aircraft screening for U.S. aircraft carriers and perform shore bombardment. None of the completed ''Iowa''-class battleships engaged an enemy capital ship during World War II, although ''Iowa'' and ''New Jersey'' did engage enemy surface ships operating in the Pacific Ocean during World War II. At the end of the war, ''Iowa'', ''New Jersey'' and ''Wisconsin'' were decommissioned and placed in the mothball fleet;As part of the post World War II drawdown, three of the ''Iowa''-class battleships had been de-activated and decommissioned; however, President Truman refused to allow ''Missouri'' to be decommissioned. Against the advice of Secretary of Defense Louis Johnson, Secretary of the Navy John L. Sullivan, and Chief of Naval Operations Louis E. Denfeld, Truman ordered ''Missouri'' to be maintained with the active fleet partly because of his fondness for the battleship and partly because the battleship had been commissioned by his daughter Margaret Truman. See:   construction was halted on the two incomplete ships, ''Illinois'' and ''Kentucky''.Construction on ''Illinois'' never resumed after this cancellation, but construction work on ''Kentucky'' was resumed in 1944 and continued until 1947, then resumed again in 1948 and continued until her final cancellation in 1950.

The ''Iowa''s were recalled in 1950 with the outbreak of the Korean War, and provided naval artillery support for U.N. forces for the entire duration of the war before being returned to mothballs in 1955 after hostilities had ceased. In 1968, to help alleviate US air losses over North VietnamNeubeck, p. 42 as well as delivering the ordnance necessary for the escalating war in Vietnam, ''New Jersey'' was recommissioned, and as the only active battleship in the world in 1968, departed for the gunline off the Vietnamese coast. From approximately 6 April 1968 until 17 December 1969, ''New Jersey'' operated in the waters off the Vietnamese Demilitarized Zone, firing nearly 6,000  shells and well over 14,000 rounds of  shells at communist targets, before departing the gunline;Polmar, p. 129 she was decommissioned the following year.

In the 1980s, all of the ''Iowa''s were recommissioned as part of President Ronald Reagan's plan to rebuild the U.S. military and create a 600-ship Navy. With the  heavy cruisers worn out, the relatively low mileage ''Iowas'' were brought back to fill the offshore bombardment role. The ships also provided a counter to the new Soviet ''Orlan''-class large missile cruisers, better known in the West as the ''Kirov''-class battlecruisers.Bishop, p. 80.Miller and Miller, p. 114. Each battleship was modernized to carry electronic warfare suites, CIWS self-defense systems, and missiles.During this reactivation, the Navy played with various ideas to remove the #3 gun turrets from the battleships and replace them with servicing facilities for 12 AV-8B Harrier STOVL jumpjets. Plans for such a conversion were dropped in 1984. See:  They became the centerpieces of their own battleship battle groups (BBBGs).A Battleship Battle Group consisted of one , one  or , one , three , and one support ship.  Their missions in the 1980s and early 1990s included the U.S. intervention in the Lebanese Civil War following the 1983 Beirut barracks bombing and ''Desert Storm'' in 1991, first as part of Operation ''Desert Shield'' in 1990 and then as part of Operation ''Desert Storm'' in January through February 1991. Decommissioned for the last time due to budgetary restraintsA Government Accountability Office report on the operating cost for each individual ''Iowa''-class battleship in 1991 reported that it cost the United States Navy $58 million to operate each individual battleship. Adjusted for inflation on the , each individual battleship would cost just over $88.5 million to operate in 2008 dollars. This number does not take into consideration the cost of specialty items and other unique components that may be needed to keep a battleship operational.  in the early 1990s, the ''Iowa''s were split into two groups: those retained in the United States Navy reserve fleets (better known as the "mothball fleet") and those donated for use as museum ships. 

In 1996, the National Defense Authorization Act led ''Iowa'' and ''Missouri'' to be struck from the Naval Vessel Register. ''Missouri'' was donated to the Missouri Memorial Association of Pearl Harbor, Hawaii, for use as a museum ship. ''Iowa'' was set to be donated with ''Missouri'', but was reinstated to the Naval Vessel Register after the Strom Thurmond National Defense Authorization Act of 1999 allowed ''New Jersey'' to be donated as a museum ship. The last two ''Iowa''-class battleships were removed from the mothball fleet in 2006, and are currently awaiting transfer for use as museum ships. -->
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1db18d7574e2ccd0d4ba2ee01ad5e63e" name="All_Four_Iowas" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/1db18d7574e2ccd0d4ba2ee01ad5e63e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>