<document id="cca017687d11e7f50ca0ba0ab8691608-2.3" name="Iowa_class_battleship" cat="29">
<text>
was ordered 1 July 1939, laid down 27 June 1940, launched 27 August 1942, and commissioned 22 February 1943. ''Iowa'' conducted a shakedown cruise in the Chesapeake Bay before sailing to Naval Station Argentia, Newfoundland to counter the German battleship ''Tirpitz''. Transferred to the Pacific Fleet in 1944, ''Iowa'' made her combat debut in the campaign for the Marshall Islands. The ship escorted U.S. aircraft carriers conducting air raids in the Marianas campaign, then was present at the Battle of Leyte Gulf. During the Korean War, ''Iowa'' bombarded enemy targets at Songjin, Hungnam, and Kojo, North Korea. ''Iowa'' returned to the U.S. for operational and training exercises before being decommissioned. Reactivated in the early 1980s, ''Iowa'' made several operation cruises in European waters. On 19 April 1989, an explosion of undetermined origin ripped through her No. 2 turret, killing 47 sailors. The turret remained inoperable when ''Iowa'' was decommissioned for the last time in 1990. In 1999, ''Iowa'' was placed in the mothball fleet as a replacement for sister ship ''New Jersey''. Stricken from the Naval Vessel Register on 17 March 2006. Even though Congress was concerned with the loss of surface support that a battleship provided, they passed Pub. L. 109-163, the National Defense Authorization Act 2006, to allow the ''Iowa'' to be struck from the Naval Vessel Register for donation.109th Congress, House of Representatives. Report 109-163.  However, whoever receives the ''Iowa'' must maintain her in a state of readiness should she ever be needed by the Navy again. If such an emergency arises, ''Iowa'' would be immediately transferred back to the Navy for use. ''Iowa'' is currently berthed at Suisun Bay in San Francisco, California.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="73071cc1a9db715447425fc2faa54190" name="USSIowa" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/73071cc1a9db715447425fc2faa54190.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>