<document id="cca017687d11e7f50ca0ba0ab8691608-5.17" name="Iowa_class_battleship" cat="29">
<text>
In December 1983, U.S. aircraft carriers operating off the coast of Lebanon sent out 28 aircraft to bomb targets in the Bekaa Valley in retaliation for anti-aircraft fire directed at F-14 reconnaissance flights operating from the carriers. The main target of the bombing run was a Syrian radar station, but before the aircraft could reach the site, two American planes were shot down by Syrian guns. In an analysis of the incident, U.S. Navy Secretary John Lehman determined that the targeted SAM sites had been within the range of the battleship ''New Jersey'' and her  guns, but there had been no way for the battleship to accurately target the sites without an aerial observer to direct the ship's rounds to the target.Newcome, p. 96.

In part because of Israeli success with their deployment of the Mastiff unmanned aerial vehicles, the U.S. Navy made a covert request for a Mastiff drone system. Israel responded by lending a drone to the U.S. in 1984. The success of the Mastiff system in tests ultimately led the Navy to develop its own UAV system, resulting in the creation of the RQ-2 Pioneer UAV. The Pioneer made its first deployment in December 1986 aboard the ''Iowa''.

Launched from the fantail using a rocket-assist booster that was discarded shortly after takeoff, a Pioneer used an aft-mounted, push-propeller engine to achieve speeds of up to  with a mission endurance of about four hours. The Pioneer carried a video camera in a pod under the belly of the aircraft, which transmitted live video back to the ship so that the operators could observe enemy actions or fall of shot during naval gunnery. Because it was difficult to land the Pioneer without damaging itself or the ship, a large net was strung up for recovery as for a volleyball game, and the aircraft is flown into it. Each battleship could carry as many as eight Pioneers, sometimes referred to as remote piloted vehicles (RPVs).

Pioneer garnered international attention for its use during the 1991 Gulf War, when it saw extensive use from the ''Missouri'' and ''Wisconsin''. The latter became the first ship to have enemy forces surrender to one of its remotely controlled observation drones.When Navy officials offered to transfer a Pioneer to the Smithsonian Institution, curators at the National Air and Space Museum specifically asked for the UAV that Iraqi troops surrendered to during the Gulf War, as a result, this particular Pioneer is now on display for the public to view. See:
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="337f729685dde025ba324d79cdba9876" name="Iowa_drone" sectnum="5.17#1">../img/337f729685dde025ba324d79cdba9876.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>