<document id="cca017687d11e7f50ca0ba0ab8691608-8" name="Iowa_class_battleship" cat="29">
<text>
After World War II, the United States maintained the four ''Iowa''-class battleships in the United States Navy reserve fleets, better known as the "mothball fleet", and on several occasions reactivated these battleships for naval gunfire support. The U.S. Navy has held onto its battleships long after the expense and the arrival of aircraft and precision guided munitions led other nations to scrap their big-gun fleets.Government Accountability Office, ''Naval Surface Fire Support Program Plans and Costs'' (NSIAD-99-91). The United States Congress is largely responsible for this. The lawmakers argue that the battleships' large-caliber guns have a militarily useful destructive power lacking in the smaller, cheaper, and faster guns mounted by U.S. cruisers and destroyers.Government Accountability Office. ''Information on Options for Naval Surface Fire Support'' (GAO-05-39R).

The Navy, which sees the battleships as too costly, is working to persuade Congress to allow it to remove ''Iowa'' and ''Wisconsin'' from the Naval Vessel Register by developing extended-range guided munitions and a new ship to fulfill Marine Corps requirements for naval surface fire support (NSFS). 

The Navy plan originally called for the extension of the range of the  guns on the Flight I  guided missile destroyers ( to ) with Extended Range Guided Munitions (ERGMs) that would enable the ships to fire precision guided projectiles about  inland. The program was initiated in 1996 with a preliminary cost of $78.6 million; however, the cost of the program increased 400% during its research and development phase. The results of the program had been similarly disappointing: the original expected operational capability date was pushed from 2001 to 2011 before being cancelled by the navy in March 2008 for budget-related reasons and an apparent shift by the navy from the ERGM program to the Ballistic Trajectory Extended Range Munition (BTERM) program. These weapons are not intended or expected to satisfy the full range of the Marine Corps NSFS requirements.Government Accountability Office, ''Evaluation of the Navy’s 1999 Naval Surface Fire Support Assessment'' (NSAID-99-225). 

The result of the latter effort to design and build a replacement ship for the two battleships was the ''Zumwalt''-class destroyer program, also known either as the DD(X) or DDG-1000 (in reference to ''Zumwalt''’s hull number). The DD(X) was to mount a pair of Advanced Gun System turrets capable of firing specially designed Long Range Land Attack Projectiles some  inland. Originally, the navy had planned to build a total of 32 of these destroyers, however the increasing cost of the program led the navy to reduce the overall number of destroyers built from 32 to 24. In 2007 the total procurement of ''Zumwalt''-class destroyers was further reduced to a total of seven, before being discontinued at a total of two destroyers in July 2008 as a result of the high cost of building each of the two ships.The Navy has stated that it may ask for construction of a third ''Zumwalt''-class destroyer, but has not specified when or if it will exercise such an option.  



On 17 March 2006 the Secretary of the Navy exercised his authority to strike ''Iowa'' and ''Wisconsin'' from the Naval Vessel Register, which cleared the way for both ships to be donated for use as museums. The United States Navy and the United States Marine Corps had both certified that battleships would not be needed in any future war, and turned their attention to development and construction of the next generation  guided missile destroyers, production of which was later capped at two vessels in July 2008. 

This move has drawn fire from a variety of sources familiar with the subject; among them are dissenting members of the United States Marine Corps, who feel that battleships are still a viable solution to naval gunfire support,Marine Corps supports the strategic purpose of reactivating two battleships in accordance with the National Defense Authorization Act of 1996 and supports the Navy's modernization efforts to deliver a sufficient NSFS capability that exceeds that of the Iowa class battleships. See: Government Accountability Office. ''Information on Options for Naval Surface Fire Support''. members of the United States Congress who remain "deeply concerned" over the loss of naval surface gunfire support that the battleships provided, and number of independent groups such as the United States' Naval Fire Support Association (USNFSA) whose ranks frequently include former members of the armed service and fans of the battleships. Although the arguments presented from each group differ, they all agree that the United States Navy has not in good faith considered the potential of reactivated battleships for use in the field, a position that is supported by a 1999 Government Accountability Office report regarding the United States Navy's gunfire support program. 

In response, the Navy has pointed to the cost of reactivating the two ''Iowa'' class battleships to their decommissioned capability. The Navy estimates costs in excess of $500 million,This number is based on 1999 estimate with a 4% annual inflation rate. See: Government Accountability Office. ''Information on Options for Naval Surface Fire Support''.The U.S. Navy reported in the April 1987 edition of ''All Hands'' that the original cost of bringing the battleships back in the 1980s was $110 million per ship, but the actual cost after modernization and recommissioning was $455 million. See: Bureau of Naval Personnel, "Back on the battle line". but this does not include an additional $110 million needed to replenish the gunpowder for the  guns because a survey found the powder to be unsafe. In terms of schedule, the Navy's program management office estimates that reactivation would take 20 to 40 months, given the loss of corporate memory and the shipyard industrial base.



Reactivating the battleships would require a wide range of battleship modernization improvements, according to the Navy's program management office. At a minimum, these modernization improvements include command and control, communications, computers, and intelligence equipment; environmental protection (including ozone-depleting substances); a plastic-waste processor; pulper/shredder and wastewater alterations; firefighting/fire safety and women-at-sea alterations; a modernized sensor suite (air and surface search radar); and new combat and self-defense systems. The Navy's program management office also identified other issues that would strongly discourage the Navy from reactivating and modernizing the battleships. For example, personnel needed to operate the battleships would be extensive, and the skills needed may not be available or easily reconstituted.The U.S. Navy reported in the April 1987 edition of ''All Hands'' that while battleships have larger crews than other vessels the level of training required and the criticality of that training were less than that required of a crew aboard an ''Oliver Hazard Perry''-class frigate. See: Bureau of Naval Personnel, "Back on the battle line". Other issues include the age and unreliability of the battleships' propulsion systems and the fact that the Navy no longer maintains the capability to manufacture their  gun system components and ordnance.

Although the Navy firmly believes in the capabilities of the DD(X) destroyer program, members of the United States Congress remain skeptical about the efficiency of the new destroyers when compared to the battleships. Partially as a consequence the US House of Representatives have asked that the battleships be kept in a state of readiness should they ever be needed again."Report 109–452. National Defense Authorization Act of 2007." 109th Congress, House of Representatives. p. 68. Congress has asked that the following measures be implemented to ensure that, if need be, ''Iowa'' and ''Wisconsin'' can be returned to active duty:
#''Iowa'' and ''Wisconsin'' must not be altered in any way that would impair their military utility;
#The battleships must be preserved in their present condition through the continued use of cathodic protection, dehumidification systems, and any other preservation methods as needed;
#Spare parts and unique equipment such as the  gun barrels and projectiles be preserved in adequate numbers to support ''Iowa'' and ''Wisconsin'', if reactivated; 
#The Navy must prepare plans for the rapid reactivation of ''Iowa'' and ''Wisconsin'' should they be returned to the Navy in the event of a national emergency.
These four conditions closely mirror the original three conditions that the Nation Defense Authorization Act of 1996 laid out for the maintenance of ''Iowa'' and ''Wisconsin'' while they were in the Mothball Fleet.. 104th Congress, House of Representatives. p. 237. Retrieved on 17 December 2006.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="437a52a1f4f555aafd020f45ca993f06" name="Wisconsin_museum" sectnum="8#1">../img/437a52a1f4f555aafd020f45ca993f06.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>