<document id="cca017687d11e7f50ca0ba0ab8691608-2.6" name="Iowa_class_battleship" cat="29">
<text>
was ordered 12 June 1940, laid down 25 January 1942, launched 7 December 1943, and commissioned 16 April 1944. After trials and initial training in the Chesapeake Bay, ''Wisconsin'' transferred to the Pacific Fleet in 1944 and assigned to protect the U.S. fleet of aircraft carriers involved in operations in the Philippines until summoned to Iwo Jima to bombard the island in advance of the Marine landings. After the landings on Iwo Jima she turned her attention to Okinawa, bombarding the island in advance of the allied amphibious assault. In mid-1945 ''Wisconsin'' turned her attention to pounding the Japanese home islands, a job she retained until the surrender of Japan. Reactivated in 1950 for the Korean War, ''Wisconsin'' served two tours of duty assisting South Korean and UN forces by providing call fire support and shelling targets of opportunity. In 1956, the bow of the uncompleted USS Kentucky was removed and grafted on the Wisconsin, which had collided with the destroyer USS ''Eaton''. Decommissioned in 1958, ''Wisconsin'' was placed in the reserve fleet at the Philadelphia Naval Yard until reactivated in 1986 as part of the 600-ship Navy plan. In 1991, ''Wisconsin'' participated in Operation Desert Storm, firing 24 Tomahawk Missiles at Iraqi targets, and expending 319  shells at Iraqi troop formations along the coast. Decommissioned for the last time 30 September 1991 ''Wisconsin'' was placed in the reserve fleet until struck from the Naval Vessel Register 17 March 2006 so she could be transferred for use as a museum ship. Even though Congress was concerned with the loss of surface support that a battleship provided, they passed Pub. L. 109-163, the National Defense Authorization Act 2006, to allow the ''Wisconsin'' to be struck from the Naval Vessel Register for donation. ''Wisconsin'' must be maintained in a state of readiness should she ever be needed by the Navy again. If such an emergency arises, ''Wisconsin'' would be immediately transferred back to the Navy for use. ''Wisconsin'' is currently berthed at the Nauticus maritime museum in Norfolk, Virginia.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ab636486e860ccbdd0113ddeda772cc3" name="USS_Wisconsin_(BB-64)_launching_Tomahawk" sectnum="2.6#1">../img/ab636486e860ccbdd0113ddeda772cc3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>