<document id="cdadb6b9c506d4bbc6184973877dfe4f-2.2" name="The_Third_of_May_1808" cat="1">
<text>
Goya's series of aquatint etchings ''The Disasters of War'' () was not completed until 1820, although most of the prints were made in the period 1810&ndash;1814.  The album of proofs given by Goya to a friend, however, now in the British Museum, provides many indications of the order in which both the preliminary drawings and the prints themselves were composed. There were probably preliminary drawings for all of the prints. The album shows a preliminary numbering system, different from the one Goya finally settled on, which probably relates to the order of composition. For example  is no. 15 in the first sequence, and no. 44 in the final sequence. After the earlier no. 19 Goya ran out of good drawing paper from the Netherlands, and began to use whatever he could find. See Bareau, p. 50.  The groups identified as the earliest clearly seem to predate the commission for the two paintings, and include two prints with obviously related compositions (illustrated), as well as ''I saw this'', which is presumably a scene witnessed during Goya's trip to Saragossa.Bareau, pp. 49&ndash;50.   (''One cannot look at this'') is clearly related compositionally and thematically;Spivey, pp. 193&ndash;195.  the female central figure has her arms outstretched, but pointing down, while another figure has his hands clasped in prayer, and several others shield or hide their faces. This time the soldiers are not visible even from behind; only the bayonets of their guns are seen.

 (''And it cannot be helped'') is another of the early prints, from a slightly later group apparently produced at the height of the war when materials were unobtainable, so that Goya had to destroy the plate of an earlier landscape print to make this and another piece in the ''Disasters'' series.  It shows a shako-wearing firing-squad in the background, this time seen receding in a frontal rather than a rear view.Bareau, pp. 48&ndash;50.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="77ddd7dc1d4db897c1ecf223b42f9e1e" name="Goya_No_se_puede_mirar" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/77ddd7dc1d4db897c1ecf223b42f9e1e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>