<document id="cdadb6b9c506d4bbc6184973877dfe4f-3" name="The_Third_of_May_1808" cat="1">
<text>
Despite the work's commemorative value, no details about its first exhibition are known, and it is not mentioned in any surviving contemporaneous accounts.  This lack of commentary may be due to Fernando VII's preference for neoclassical art,Tomlinson, pp. 137&ndash;139. and to the fact that popular revolts of any kind were not regarded as suitable subject matter by the restored Bourbons. A monument to the fallen in the uprising, also commissioned in 1814 by the provisional government, "was stopped by Ferdinand VII, in whose eyes the senators and heroes of the war of independence found small favour, on account of their reforming tendencies".Ford, p. 678.

According to some accounts the painting lay in storage for thirty to forty years before being shown to the public.Hughes, Robert. "". ''The Guardian'', October 04, 2003. Retrieved on April 18, 2008. But see also Gautier. Ford, p. 686, mentions only a couple of Goya's in the Prado, and is generally dismissive: "he delighted in dirty subjects from which others revolt. Those who admire him should visit his son Don Javier (No. 9, ), who has many of his father's sketches and paintings." Its mention in an 1834 Prado inventory shows that the painting remained in the possession of the government or monarchy; much of the royal collection had been transferred to the museum upon its opening in 1819. Théophile Gautier mentioned seeing "a massacre" by Goya during a visit to the museum in 1845, and a visitor in 1858 noted it as well, though both accounts refer to the work as depicting the events of the second of May, perhaps because  continues to be the Spanish name for the whole episode.The phrase in full is , but this celebrated sequence of events in the nation's history is normally referred to simply as .

In 1867, Goya's biographer Charles Emile Yriarte considered the painting important enough to  warrant its own special exhibition, but it was not until 1872 that ''The Third of May'' was listed in the Prado's published catalog, under the title ''Scene of the Third of May 1808''.  Both the ''Third'' and ''Second of May'' suffered damage in a road accident while being transported by truck to Valencia for safety during the Spanish Civil War,Prado, p. 140. apparently the only time they have left Madrid.  Significant paint losses to the left side of the ''Second of May'' have been deliberately left unrepaired.  Restoration work to both paintings was done in 2008 in time for an exhibition marking the bicentennial of the uprising.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1f350345c5ce7d0809fd2109c981b541" name="Francisco_de_Goya_y_Lucientes_054" sectnum="3#1">../img/1f350345c5ce7d0809fd2109c981b541.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>