<document id="cdf5e094a57f4c677abf8ec5eb1dec4e-3" name="Pre-dreadnought_battleship" cat="29">
<text>
Pre-dreadnought battleships carried a considerable weight of steel armour. Experience showed that rather than giving the ship uniform armour protection, it was best to concentrate armour over critical areas. The central section of the hull, which housed the boilers and engines, was protected by the main belt, which ran from just below the waterline to some distance above it. This 'central citadel' was intended to protect the engines from even the most powerful shells. The main armament and the magazines were protected by projections of thick armour from the main belt. The beginning of the pre-dreadnought era was marked by a move from mounting the main armament in open barbettes to an all-enclosed, turret mounting.Roberts, p. 117.

The main belt armour would normally taper to a lesser thickness along the side of the hull towards bow and stern; it might also taper up from the central citadel towards the superstructure. The deck was typically lightly armoured with 2 in to 4 in of steel.Roberts, pp. 132–133. This lighter armour was to prevent high-explosive shells from wrecking the superstructure of the ship.''The Eclipse of the Big Gun'', p. 8.



The battleships of the late 1880s, for instance the ''Royal Sovereign'' class, were armoured with iron and steel compound armour. This was soon replaced with more effective case hardened steel armour made using the Harvey process developed in the United States. First tested in 1891, Harvey armour was commonplace in ships laid down in 1893–5. However, its reign was brief; in 1895, the German ''Kaiser Friedrich III'' pioneered the even better Krupp armour; Europe adopted Krupp plate within five years, only the United States persisted in using Harvey steel into the 20th Century. The improving quality of armour plate meant that new ships could have better protection from a thinner and lighter armour belt. Twelve inches of compound armour provided the same protection as just 7.5 inches of Harvey or 5.75 inches of Krupp.Sondhaus, p. 166.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6948019ef00d5f16e48271d1ea300888" name="BB05_Kearsarge_BB06_Kentucky_U.S._Naval_Historical_Center._NH_76632" sectnum="3#1">../img/6948019ef00d5f16e48271d1ea300888.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>