<document id="ce04d9924bf3e1c0e840bd219554d8a9-4" name="Sheerness" cat="11">
<text>
Sheerness is located at  (51.441, 0.7605), in the northwest corner of the Isle of Sheppey in North Kent. To the north, sandy beaches run along the coast of the Thames Estuary. To the west, the outlet of the River Medway flows into the Estuary. An area of wetlands known as The Lappel lies between the river and the southwestern part of town. Marshland lies to the south and the east. The main rock type of the Isle of Sheppey is London Clay, which covers most of North Kent. Along with most of the Kent coast, the uninhabited coastal areas of the island have been designated Sites of Special Scientific Interest, due to their wildlife and geological features. 

The nearest towns to Sheerness are Minster,  to the east, and Queenborough,  to the south. The villages of Minster-on-Sea and Halfway Houses are  to the southeast, and the village of Grain is  to the west, across the River Medway. 

The main commercial and leisure areas of the town are located around the north coast, where there is easy access to the pleasure beach. The industrial areas are in the west, beside the wetlands and the River Medway. The Bluetown industrial area and the Port of Sheerness are in the northwestern part of the town. The residential districts of Mile Town and Marine Town are in the central and the eastern areas respectively.

The mean annual temperature in Sheerness is . The average annual maximum temperature is , and the average annual minimum temperature is . The warmest time of the year is July and August, when maximum temperatures average . The coolest time of the year is January and February, when minimum temperatures average .

The average annual rainfall in Sheerness is . The average annual duration of sunshine is 1,700 hours; the months May to August have the most hours of sunshine. On average, there are fewer than six days of lying snow per year, and 16 days with thunder per year.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c331b26587597ded79a9c37b4a2d6683" name="Sheerness_beach" sectnum="4#1">../img/c331b26587597ded79a9c37b4a2d6683.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>