<document id="ce370f7c7e2457bf172d891f9407ee2d-1" name="Catherine_de'_Medici" cat="25">
<text>
According to a contemporary chronicler, when Catherine de' Medici was born in Florence on Wednesday 13 April 1519, her parents, were "as pleased as if it had been a boy".Goro Gheri, 15 April 1519, quoted by Frieda, 14. Their pleasure, however, was short-lived. Catherine's mother, Madeleine de la Tour d'Auvergne, Countess of Boulogne, died on 28 April. Catherine's father, Lorenzo II de' Medici, Duke of Urbino, died on 4 May, probably from syphilis. The young couple had been married the year before at Amboise as part of the alliance between King Francis I of France and Lorenzo's uncle Pope Leo X against the Holy Roman Emperor Maximilian I. King Francis now asked for Catherine to be raised at the French court, but Pope Leo had other plans for her.Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 8. He intended to marry her to his brother's illegitimate son, Ippolito de' Medici, and set the pair up as rulers of Florence.    
   
Catherine was first cared for by her grandmother, Alfonsina Orsini. After Alfonsina died in 1520, Catherine was brought up with her cousins by her aunt, Clarissa Strozzi. The death of Pope Leo in 1521 interrupted Medici power briefly, until Cardinal Giulio de' Medici was elected Pope Clement VII in 1523. Clement housed Catherine in the Palazzo Medici in Florence, where she lived in state. The Florentine people called her "''duchessina''", the little duchess. Frieda, 23–24.   
  
In 1527, the Medici were overthrown in Florence by a faction opposed to the regime of Clement's representative, Cardinal Passerini, and Catherine was taken hostage and placed in a series of convents.Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 11. Clement had no choice but to crown Charles as Holy Roman Emperor in return for his help in retaking the city.Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 10–11. In October 1529, Charles's troops laid siege to Florence. As the siege dragged on, voices called for Catherine to be killed and exposed on the city walls. Soldiers made her ride through the streets on a donkey, jeered by an angry crowd.Frieda, 29–30. The city finally surrendered on 12 August 1530. Clement called Catherine to Rome and greeted her with open arms and tears in his eyes. Then he set about the business of finding her a husband.Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 12.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7fe44eadaf23bfdcdffec91f3aa2a44b" name="Clement_VII._Sebastiano_del_Piombo._c.1531." sectnum="1#1">../img/7fe44eadaf23bfdcdffec91f3aa2a44b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>