<document id="ce370f7c7e2457bf172d891f9407ee2d-2" name="Catherine_de'_Medici" cat="25">
<text>
Catherine was not destined to be a beauty. On her visit to Rome, the Venetian envoy described her as "small of stature, and thin, and without delicate features, but having the protruding eyes peculiar to the Medici family".Frieda, 31; Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 14. Suitors, however, lined up for her hand; and when in early 1531 Francis I of France proposed his second son, Henry, Duke of Orléans. Clement jumped at the offer. Henry was a prize catch for Catherine, who despite her wealth was a commoner.Frieda, 35.

The wedding, a grand affair marked by extravagant display and gift-giving, took place in Marseille on 28 October 1533. Frieda, 52.  The contract was signed on the 27th and the religious ceremony took place the next day. Prince Henry danced and jousted for Catherine. The fourteen-year-old couple left their wedding ball at midnight to perform their nuptial duties. Henry arrived in the bedroom with King Francis, who is said to have stayed until the marriage was consummated. He noted that "each had shown valour in the joust".Frieda, 53; Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 16. Clement visited the newlyweds in bed the next morning and added his blessings to the night's proceedings.Frieda, 53.

Catherine saw little of her husband in their first year of marriage, but the ladies of the court treated her well, impressed with her intelligence and keenness to please.Frieda, 54. The death of Pope Clement on 25 September 1534, however, undermined Catherine's standing in the French court. The next pope, Paul III, broke the alliance with France and refused to pay her huge dowry. King Francis lamented, "The girl has come to me stark naked.""''J'ai reçu la fille toute nue.''" Frieda, 54.

Prince Henry showed no interest in Catherine as a wife; instead, he openly took mistresses. For the first ten years of the marriage, Catherine failed to produce any children. In 1537, on the other hand, Philippa Duci, one of Henry's mistresses, gave birth to a daughter, whom he publicly acknowledged.Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 29–30. Henry legitimised the child under the name Diane de France; he also produced at least two sons by other women. This proved that Henry was fertile and added to the pressure on Catherine to produce a child.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="48419a4151bcc702eb566bba0319d7dc" name="Corneille_de_Lyon_001" sectnum="2#1">../img/48419a4151bcc702eb566bba0319d7dc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>