<document id="ce370f7c7e2457bf172d891f9407ee2d-3.4.1" name="Catherine_de'_Medici" cat="25">
<text>
On 17 August 1563, Charles IX was declared of age at the Parlement of Rouen, but he was never able to rule on his own and showed little interest in government.Frieda, 268; Sutherland, ''Ancien Régime'', 20. Catherine decided to launch a drive to enforce the Edict of Amboise and revive loyalty to the crown. To this end, she set out with Charles and the court on a progress around France that lasted from January 1564 until May 1565.Sutherland, ''Ancien Régime'', 15. Catherine held talks with the Protestant Queen Jeanne d'Albret of Navarre at Mâcon and Nérac. She also met her daughter Queen Elisabeth of Spain at Bayonne near the Spanish border, amidst lavish court festivities. Philip II excused himself from the occasion. He sent the Duke of Alba to tell Catherine to scrap the Edict of Amboise and to find punitive solutions to the problem of heresy.Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 104, 107–8; Frieda, 224.

On 27 September 1567, in a swoop known as the Surprise of Meaux, Huguenot forces attempted to ambush the king, triggering renewed civil war.Wood, 17. Taken unawares, the court fled to Paris in disarray.Frieda, 234; Sutherland, ''Secretaries of State'', 147. The war was ended by the Peace of Longjumeau of 22–23 March 1568, but civil unrest and bloodshed continued.Frieda, 239; Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 118. The Surprise of Meaux marked a turning point in Catherine's policy towards the Huguenots. From that moment, she abandoned compromise for a policy of repression.Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 120. She told the Venetian ambassador in June 1568 that all one could expect from Huguenots was deceit, and she praised the Duke of Alba's reign of terror in the Netherlands, where Calvinists and rebels were put to death in the thousands.Frieda, 232.



The Huguenots retreated to the fortified stronghold of La Rochelle on the west coast, where Jeanne d'Albret and her fifteen-year-old son, Henry of Bourbon, joined them.Bryson, 204. "We have come to the determination to die, all of us," Jeanne wrote to Catherine, "rather than abandon our God, and our religion".Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 132. Catherine called Jeanne, whose decision to rebel posed a dynastic threat to the Valois, "the most shameless woman in the world".Frieda, 241. Nevertheless, the Peace of Saint-Germain-en-Laye, signed on 8 August 1570 because the royal army ran out of cash, conceded wider toleration to the Huguenots than ever before.Wood, 28.

Catherine looked to further Valois interests by grand dynastic marriages. In 1570, Charles IX married Elisabeth of Austria, daughter of Maximilian II, Holy Roman Emperor. Catherine was also eager for a match between one of her two youngest sons and Elizabeth I of England.Holt, 77; Frieda, 397. In 1579, François, Duke of Alençon, visited Elizabeth, who affectionately dubbed him "her frog" but, as always, proved elusive. After Catherine's daughter Elisabeth died in childbirth in 1568, she had touted her youngest daughter Margaret as a bride for Philip II of Spain. Now she sought a marriage between Margaret and Henry of Navarre, with the aim of uniting Valois and Bourbon interests. Margaret, however, was secretly involved with Henry of Guise, the son of the late Duke of Guise. When Catherine found this out, she had her daughter brought from her bed. Catherine and the king then beat her, ripping her nightclothes and pulling out handfuls of her hair.Frieda, 257; Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 135.

Catherine pressed Jeanne d'Albret to attend court. Writing that she wanted to see Jeanne's children, she promised not to harm them. Jeanne replied: "Pardon me if, reading that, I want to laugh, because you want to relieve me of a fear that I've never had. I've never thought that, as they say, you eat little children".Bryson, 282. When Jeanne did come to court, Catherine pressured her hard,Jeanne d'Albret wrote to her son, Henry: "I am not free to talk with either the King or Madame, only the Queen Mother, who goads me  ... You have doubtless realized that their main object, my son, is to separate you from God, and from me". Quoted by Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 148–49. playing on Jeanne's hopes for her beloved son. Jeanne finally agreed to the marriage between her son and Margaret, so long as Henry could remain a Huguenot. When Jeanne arrived in Paris to buy clothes for the wedding, she was taken ill and died, aged forty-four. Huguenot writers later accused Catherine of murdering her with poisoned gloves.Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 151. An autopsy revealed tuberculosis and an abscess. The wedding took place on 18 August 1572 at Notre-Dame, Paris.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9c1c4f488bb348e534a743a7a2cfb327" name="Jeanne-Albret" sectnum="3.4.1#1">../img/9c1c4f488bb348e534a743a7a2cfb327.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>