<document id="ce370f7c7e2457bf172d891f9407ee2d-3.4.2" name="Catherine_de'_Medici" cat="25">
<text>
Three days later, Admiral Coligny was walking back to his rooms from the Louvre when a shot rang out from a house and wounded him in the hand and arm.Sutherland, ''Massacre of St Bartholomew'', 313. A smoking arquebus was discovered in a window, but the culprit had made his escape from the rear of the building on a waiting horse.Frieda, 254, 304–5; Holt, 83. The investigators traced the house and horse to the Guises and claimed to have found evidence that the would-be killer was Charles de Louviers de Maurevert. Coligny was carried to his lodgings at the Hôtel de Béthisy, where the surgeon Ambroise Paré removed a bullet from his elbow and amputated a damaged finger with a pair of scissors. Catherine, who was said to have received the news without emotion, made a tearful visit to Coligny and promised to punish his attacker. Many historians have blamed Catherine for the attack on Coligny. Others point to the Guise family or a Spanish-papal plot to end Coligny's influence on the king.Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 154–57. Coligny was lobbying the king to intervene against the empire in the Netherlands.• Frieda, 292. The Duke of Anjou was later reported as saying that he and Catherine had planned the assassination with Anne d'Este, who longed to avenge her husband, Francis, Duke of Guise.• For an overview of historians' various interpretations, see Holt, 83–4. Whatever the truth, the bloodbath that followed was soon beyond the control of Catherine or any other leader.Pettegree, 159–60.

The St. Bartholomew's Day massacre, which began two days later, has stained Catherine's reputation ever since. There is no reason to believe she was not party to the decision when on 23 August Charles IX ordered, "Then kill them all! Kill them all!".Holt, 84.• Marshal Tavannes recalled that Catherine had summoned a war council in the Tuileries Gardens (so as not to be overheard) to plan the next move: "Because the attempt on the Admiral would cause a war, she, and the rest of us, agreed that it would be advisable to bring battle in Paris".  It is almost certain, however, that when Charles gave the order "Kill them all!", he meant those drawn up on a list by Catherine, and not, as has often been claimed, all Huguenots. Frieda, 306–8. The thinking was clear. Catherine and her advisers expected a Huguenot uprising to revenge the attack on Coligny. They chose therefore to strike first and wipe out the Huguenot leaders while they were still in Paris after the wedding.Holt, 84.

The slaughter in Paris lasted for almost a week. It spread to many parts of France, where it persisted into the autumn. In the words of historian Jules Michelet, "St Bartholomew was not a day, but a season".Quoted by Morris, 252. On 29 September, when Navarre knelt before the altar as a Roman Catholic, having converted to avoid being killed, Catherine turned to the ambassadors and laughed.Frieda, 324. From this time dates the legend of the wicked Italian queen. Huguenot writers branded Catherine a scheming Italian, who had acted on Machiavelli's principles to kill all enemies in one blow.Knecht, ''Catherine de' Medici'', 163–64; Heller, 117; Manetsch, 60–61. The misogyny and anti-Italianism in Huguenot "histories" proved seductive not only to Protestants but to Catholics seeking a scapegoat for France's woes.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fcc90f89f3d5745f688558833bbdcfba" name="Anjou_1570louvre" sectnum="3.4.2#1">../img/fcc90f89f3d5745f688558833bbdcfba.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>