<document id="ce3ebe94976062adda049cf60ac95edc-6.14" name="Thespis_(opera)" cat="20">
<text>
"Climbing over rocky mountain" is the best known piece from ''Thespis'', as it was transplanted in 1879 into one of Gilbert and Sullivan's most successful operas, ''The Pirates of Penzance''. In 1902, Gilbert told a correspondent that this had happened accidentally. He and Sullivan had arrived in New York to produce the new opera, but the composer discovered that he had left his sketches behind in England. Fortunately, the entrance chorus from ''Thespis'' fitted the situation almost exactly, so it was substituted instead.

Several scholars have doubted that explanation. In Sullivan's autograph score for the later work, the first part of "Climbing over rocky mountain" is actually taken from a ''Thespis'' copyist score, with the ''Thespis'' words cancelled and the new words written in, which raises the question of why Sullivan had a ''Thespis'' score to hand, if not for that purpose.March, Jerry. "Part of Thespis Score Discovered", ''The Savoyard'', Vol. XX, No. 1 (March 1981), p. 25. Also cited in Stedman, p. 95, n. 52.

Some suggest that other music from ''Thespis'' could have been used in ''Pirates''. Goldberg suggests that "It is reasonable to believe that Sullivan made generous use of his ''Thespis'' music in other operettas: perhaps owing to the circumstances under which ''The Pirates of Penzance'' was written, it contains more than one unacknowledged borrowing from the unlucky firstling of the lucky pair." Reginald Allen says that "it seems certain" from its "rhythmic structure" that part of the Act I finale of ''Thespis'', "Here's a pretty tale for future Iliads and Odysseys" became the original Act II finale in ''Pirates'', "At length we are provided with unusual felicity", which was later deleted.Allen (''First Night''), p. 6 Tillett and Spencer propose that most of Act I of ''Pirates'' was taken from ''Thespis''.Tillett & Spencer (2002). However, there is only circumstantial evidence for these suggestions. Except for "Climbing over rocky mountain", neither author admitted to borrowing from ''Thespis'' for later works.Stedman, pp. 95–96.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6b6ad2e9573f6fc96f89c8c5e1ac4501" name="Drawing_of_Act_I_Finale" sectnum="6.14#1">../img/6b6ad2e9573f6fc96f89c8c5e1ac4501.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>