<document id="ce3ebe94976062adda049cf60ac95edc-3.4" name="Thespis_(opera)" cat="20">
<text>
Gilbert had a busy autumn. His play ''On Guard'' had an unsuccessful run at the Court Theatre, opening on 28 October 1871,Ainger, p. 92. while his most successful play to date, ''Pygmalion and Galatea'', opened on 9 December, only a few days before rehearsals for ''Thespis'' were to begin. Sullivan, however, had more time on his hands after a Manchester production of ''The Merchant of Venice'', for which he supplied incidental music, had its première on 9 September.Ainger, p. 91.


Both Gilbert and Sullivan recalled that ''Thespis'' was written in some haste. Sullivan recalled, simply, that "both music and ''libretto'' were very hurriedly written".Lawrence, p. 85. In his 1883 autobiography, Gilbert wrote:


By 1902, Gilbert's recollection of the time frame had expanded to five weeks:
 


Gilbert's five-week estimate is "in conflict with other apparently incontrovertible facts".Rees, pp. 23–24. See also Allen (''First Night''), p. 2, who concludes that "these four or five weeks of ''Thespis'' preparation were not consecutive."  Sullivan's nephew, Herbert Sullivan, wrote that the libretto was already in existence before his uncle became involved in the project: "Gilbert showed  the libretto of an operatic Extravaganza ''Thespis'', and Hollingshead forthwith sent it to Sullivan to set."Sullivan & Flower, p. 68. Also, Goldberg, p. 143.  But Gilbert generally did not write a libretto until he had a firm commitment to produce it, and the libretto appears to have been "published and circulated" during the pre-Christmas period,Allen (''First Night''), p. 2. which is consistent with the date of 14 December, when Gilbert first read it to the cast.Rees, p. 24. 

At the very least, a "rough draft of the plot"Rees, p. 25 must have existed by 30 October, in light of a letter on that date from Gilbert's agent to R. M. Field of the Boston Museum Theatre, which reads:
 Gilbert did, in fact, conclude an agreement with Field, and the first published libretto advised: "Caution to American Pirates.—The Copyright of the Dialogue and Music of this Piece, for the United States and Canada, has been assigned to Mr. Field, of the Boston Museum, by agreement, dated 7th December, 1871." If Field mounted the work, however, the production has not been traced. Gilbert's concern about American pirates foreshadowed the difficulties he and Sullivan would later encounter with unauthorized "pirated" productions of ''H.M.S. Pinafore'', ''The Mikado'' and their other popular works.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5fbbb25c58efb699a5116fe853dc7eb7" name="Pygmalion_and_Galatea" sectnum="3.4#1">../img/5fbbb25c58efb699a5116fe853dc7eb7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>