<document id="ce3ebe94976062adda049cf60ac95edc-4.7" name="Thespis_(opera)" cat="20">
<text>
Many writers in the early 20th century perpetuated a myth that ''Thespis'' ran only a month and was considered a failure.Wyndham, p. 119; Walbrook, p. 35; Dark & Grey, p. 63; Dunhill, p. 45; Fitz-Gerald, p. 2; Sullivan & Flower, p. 68; Pearson, p. 89. In fact, it remained open until 8 March. Of the nine London pantomimes that appeared during the 1871–72 holiday season, five closed before ''Thespis'' did. By its nature, the genre did not lend itself to long runs, and all nine had closed by the end of March.Rees, p. 78.

As they would do with all their operas, Gilbert and Sullivan made cuts and alterations after the first performance. Two days after the opening, Sullivan wrote to his mother, "I have rarely seen anything so beautiful put upon the stage. The first night I had a great reception, but the music went badly, and the singer sang half a tone sharp, so that the enthusiasm of the audience did not sustain itself towards me. Last night I cut out the song, the music went very well, and consequently I had a hearty call before the curtain at the end of Act II."Sullivan & Flower, pp. 68–69.  The piece eventually settled into a respectable state, and later critics were much more enthusiastic than those on opening night. 

By the third night, the ''London Figaro'' could report: "I must say that not a single hitch in the performance is now to be perceived, and that the applause and evident delight of the audience from beginning to end, the piece occupying a space of time within two hours." On 6 January 1872, the ''Penny Illustrated Paper'' commented that "Mr. Gilbert's Gaiety extravaganza grows in public favour and deservedly so". On 9 January, the ''Daily Telegraph'' reported a visit by His Royal Highness, the Duke of Edinburgh. By 27 January, the ''Illustrated Times'' noted that "a chance playgoer will certainly not find a seat at the Gaiety.... ''Thespis'' can, after all, boast the success which was predicted". ''Land and Water'' reported on 3 February that "Thespis is now in capital working order."Rees, p. 79. 

Performances of ''Thespis'' were interrupted on 14 February 1872, Ash Wednesday, since London theatres refrained from presenting costumed performances out of respect for the religious holiday. Instead, a "miscellaneous entertainment" was given at the Gaiety, consisting of ventriloquists, performing dogs and, coincidentally, a sketch parodying a penny reading by the young George Grossmith, who, several years later, became Gilbert and Sullivan's principal comedian.

On 17 February, Henry Sutherland Edwards wrote in the ''Musical World'': "In almost all conjunctions of music and words, there is a sacrifice of one to the other; but in ''Thespis''... Sufficient opportunities have been given for music; and the music serves only to adorn the piece." Similar reports continued to appear through early March, when ''Thespis'' closed. The final performance during the authors' lifetimes was given less than two months later, on 27 April, at a matinée for the benefit of Mlle. Clary, the original Sparkeion. On such an occasion, a performer would normally choose a piece likely to sell well, as the beneficiary was entitled to the income (after expenses), and tickets were generally offered at "inflated prices".Rees, pp. 81–82. The actress was a Gaiety favourite, "not only in respect of her voice but also her delicious French accent and, of course, her figure."Rees, p. 14. Others recalled "the charm of Mlle. Clary, with her pretty face and piquant broken English".Walbrook, p. 34.  She had been particularly successful as Sparkeion,Allen (''First Night''), p. 5; Walbrook, chapter II; ''The Observer'', 31 December 1871 and her song in Act II, "Little Maid of Arcadee", was the only one chosen for publication.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bc46841b3c920ea097a617aec7e6385f" name="Sparkion" sectnum="4.7#1">../img/bc46841b3c920ea097a617aec7e6385f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>