<document id="ce3ebe94976062adda049cf60ac95edc-4.8" name="Thespis_(opera)" cat="20">
<text>
After the production of ''Thespis'', Gilbert and Sullivan went their separate ways, reuniting three years later, with Richard D'Oyly Carte as their manager, to produce ''Trial by Jury'' in 1875. When that work was a surprise success, there were discussions of quickly reviving ''Thespis'' for the 1875 Christmas season. Gilbert wrote to Sullivan:
 The proposed revival was mentioned in several more letters throughout the autumn of 1875, until on 23 November Gilbert wrote, "I have heard no more about ''Thespis''. It is astonishing how quickly these capitalists dry up under the magic influence of the words 'cash down'."Ainger, p. 114. In 1895, with Richard D'Oyly Carte struggling to rediscover success at the Savoy, he once again proposed a revival of ''Thespis'', but the idea was not pursued.Stedman, p. 95.  No mention of the whereabouts of the music of ''Thespis'' exists since 1897, and scholars have searched for it among many of the extant collections.Tillett & Spencer, p. 3.  Except for two songs and some ballet music, it is presumed lost. 

The reasons why ''Thespis'' went unrevived are not known. Some commentators speculate that Sullivan used the music in his other operas.Walbrook, p. 27; Fitz-Gerald, p. 2; Dunhill, p. 45; Allen (''First Night''), p. 6. If this were true, then "for this reason alone a revival would have become impossible".Rees, p. 88. However, evidence that Sullivan did so has eluded discovery.Tillett & Spencer, p. 3; Stedman, pp. 95–96. Another possible explanation is that Gilbert and Sullivan came to regard ''Thespis'', with its "brazen girls in tights and short skirts", and broad burlesque-style humour, as "the kind of work they wished to avoid". 

In 1879, Sullivan, Gilbert and Carte were in the midst of a legal battle with the former directors of the Comedy Opera Company, which had produced ''H.M.S. Pinafore''. Sullivan wrote to Hollingshead, saying: "You once settled a precedent for me which may just at present be of great importance to me. I asked you for the band parts of the ''Merry Wives of Windsor''... and  said, 'They are yours, as our run is over....' Now will you please let me have them, and the parts of ''Thespis'' also at once. I am detaining the parts of ''Pinafore'', so that the directors shall not take them away from the Comique tomorrow, and I base my claim on the precedent ''you'' set."Rees, p. 89.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b7b0e3d3fd0c9442bbaedd9fc2018f13" name="RichardD'OylyCarte" sectnum="4.8#1">../img/b7b0e3d3fd0c9442bbaedd9fc2018f13.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>