<document id="ce8121c95ae8e26d52a96067c7dfb60a-1" name="Cane_toad" cat="3">
<text>
Originally, cane toads were used to eradicate pests from sugar cane, giving rise to their common name. The cane toad has many other common names, including "Giant Toad" and "Marine Toad"; the former refers to its size and the latter to the binomial name, ''Bufo marinus''. It was one of many species described by Linnaeus in his 18th-century work ''Systema Naturae'' (1735). Linnaeus based the specific epithet ''marinus'' on an illustration by Dutch zoologist Albertus Seba, who mistakenly believed the cane toad to inhabit both terrestrial and marine environments. Other common names include "Giant Neotropical Toad", "Dominican Toad", "Giant Marine Toad", and "South American Cane Toad". In Trinidadian English they are commonly called "Crapaud".


In Australia, the adults may be confused with native species such as the ''Limnodynastes'', ''Cyclorana'' and ''Mixophyes''. These species can be distinguished from the cane toad by the absence of large parotoid glands behind their eyes and the lack of a ridge between the nostril and the eye. Cane toads have been confused with the Giant Burrowing Frog (''Heleioporus australiacus''), because both are large and warty in appearance; however, the latter can be readily distinguished from the former by its vertical pupils and its silver-grey (as opposed to gold) iris. Juvenile cane toads may be confused with species of the ''Uperoleia'' genus, but their adult colleagues can be distinguished by the lack of bright colouring on the groin and thighs.

In the United States, the cane toad closely resembles many Bufonid species. In particular, it could be confused with the Southern toad (''Bufo terrestris''), which can be distinguished by the presence of two bulbs in front of the parotoid glands.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bc71db27f1d4df850c2653d68b853917" name="Cane-toad" sectnum="1#1">../img/bc71db27f1d4df850c2653d68b853917.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>