<document id="ced2af5f4d479613bc7ab0a2f46c8fdf-1" name="Phagocyte" cat="3">
<text>
The Russian zoologist Ilya Ilyich Mechnikov (1845–1916) first recognized that specialized cells were involved in defense against microbial infections. In 1882, he studied motile (freely moving) cells in the larvae of starfishes, believing they were important to the animals' immune defenses. To test his idea, he inserted small thorns from a tangerine tree into the larvae.  After a few hours he noticed that the motile cells had surrounded the thorns. Mechnikov traveled to Vienna and shared his ideas with Carl Friedrich Claus who suggested the name ‘‘phagocyte’’ (from the Greek words ''phagein'', meaning "to eat or devour", and ''kutos'', meaning "hollow vessel") for the cells that Mechnikov had observed.

A year later, Mechnikov studied a fresh-water crustacean called ''Daphnia'', a tiny transparent animal that can be examined directly under a microscope. He discovered that fungal spores that attacked the animal were destroyed by phagocytes. He went on to extend his observations to the white blood cells of mammals and discovered that the bacterium ''Bacillus anthracis'' could be engulfed and killed by phagocytes, a process that he called phagocytosis. Mechnikov proposed that phagocytes were a primary defense against invading organisms.

In 1903, Amroth Wright discovered that phagocytosis was reinforced by specific antibodies which he called opsonins, from the Greek ''opson'', a dressing or relish. Mechnikov  was awarded (jointly with Paul Ehrlich) the 1908 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine for his work on phagocytes and phagocytosis.

Although the importance of these discoveries slowly gained acceptance during the early twentieth century, the intricate relationships between phagocytes and all the other components of the immune system were not known until the 1980s.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="000023fbee1f2fafc7221590dbe496f6" name="Dr_Metchnikoff_in_his_Laboratory" sectnum="1#1">../img/000023fbee1f2fafc7221590dbe496f6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>