<document id="ced2af5f4d479613bc7ab0a2f46c8fdf-6.10" name="Phagocyte" cat="3">
<text>
Mature macrophages do not travel far but stand guard over those areas of the body that are exposed to the outside world. There they act as garbage collectors, antigen presenting cells, or ferocious killers depending on the signals they receive. They derive from monocytes, granulocyte stem cells, or the  cell division of pre-existing macrophages. Human macrophages are about 21 micrometers in diameter.

This type of phagocyte does not have granules but contains many lysosomes. Macrophages are found throughout the body in almost all tissues and organs (e.g., microglial cells in the brain and  alveolar macrophages in the lungs) where they silently lie in wait. A macrophage's location can determine its size and appearance. Macrophages  cause inflammation through the production of interleukin-1, interleukin-6, and TNF-alpha. Macrophages are usually only found in tissue and are rarely seen in blood circulation. The life-span of tissue macrophages has been estimated to range from four to fifteen days.

Macrophages can be activated to perform functions that a resting monocyte cannot. T helper cells (also known as effector T cells or Th cells), a sub-group of lymphocytes, are responsible for the activation of macrophages. Th1 cells activate macrophages by signaling with IFN-gamma and displaying the protein CD40 ligand. Other signals include TNF-alpha and lipopolysaccharides from bacteria. Th1 cells can recruit other phagocytes to the site of the infection in several ways. They secrete cytokines that act on the bone marrow to stimulate the production of monocytes and neutrophils, and they secrete some of the cytokines that are responsible for the migration of monocytes and neutrophils out of the bloodstream. Th1 cells come from the differentiation of CD4+ T cells once they have responded to antigen in the secondary lymphoid tissues.  Activated macrophages play a potent role in tumor destruction  by producing TNF-alpha, IFN-gamma, nitric oxide, reactive oxygen compounds, cationic proteins, and hydrolytic enzymes.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f55d7cd61c7c9b8d033257fa255da154" name="Cutaneous_abscess_MRSA_staphylococcus_aureus_7826_lores" sectnum="6.10#1">../img/f55d7cd61c7c9b8d033257fa255da154.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>