<document id="cf8f8c3c30d887816b55aec2d4be0a8b-3.2" name="Princess_Beatrice_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
When Beatrice, after returning from Darmstadt, told her mother that she planned to marry, the Queen reacted with frightening silence. Although they remained side by side, the Queen did not talk to her for seven months, instead communicating by note.Dennison, p. 130
Victoria's behaviour, unexpected even by her family,Dennison, p. 128 seemed prompted by the threatened loss of her daughter.Dennison, pp. 127–128 The Queen regarded Beatrice as her “Baby”&mdash;her innocent child&mdash;and viewed the physical sex that would come with marriage as an end to innocence.Dennison, p. 129 Subtle persuasions by the Princess of Wales and the Crown Princess of Prussia, who reminded her mother of the happiness that Beatrice had brought the Prince Consort, induced the Queen to resume talking to Beatrice. Victoria consented to the marriage on condition that Henry give up his German commitments and live permanently with Beatrice and the Queen.


Beatrice and Henry were married at St. Mildred's Church at Whippingham, near Osborne,Beatrice and her siblings were confirmed here on 23 July 1885. Beatrice, who wore her mother's wedding veil of Honiton lace, was escorted by the Queen and Beatrice's eldest brother, the Prince of Wales.Dennison, pp. 152–153 The ceremony—which was not attended by her eldest sister and brother-in-law, the Crown Prince and Princess of Prussia, who were detained in Germany; William Gladstone; or Beatrice's cousin, Princess Mary Adelaide, Duchess of TeckThe duchess was in mourning for her father-in-lawDennison, p. 153—ended with the couple's departure for their honeymoon at Quarr Abbey House, a few miles from Osborne. The Queen, taking leave of them, “bore up bravely till the departure and then fairly gave way”, as she later admitted to the Crown Princess.Hibbert, p. 94
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4feced08432108987171140b8a86f5ab" name="Princess_Beatrice_coloured_bookplate" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/4feced08432108987171140b8a86f5ab.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>