<document id="cf8f8c3c30d887816b55aec2d4be0a8b-3.1" name="Princess_Beatrice_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
Although the Queen was set against Beatrice marrying anyone in the expectation that she would always stay at home with her, a number of possible suitors were put forward before Beatrice's marriage to Prince Henry of Battenberg. One of these was Napoleon Eugene, the French Prince Imperial, son and heir of the exiled Emperor Napoleon III of France and his wife, The Empress Eugénie. After Prussia defeated France in the Franco-Prussian War, Napoleon was deposed and moved his family to England in 1870.Corley, p. 349 After the Emperor's death in 1873, Victoria and Empress Eugénie formed a close attachment, and the newspapers reported the imminent engagement of Beatrice to the Prince Imperial.Dennison, pp. 86–87 These rumours ended with the death of the Prince Imperial in the Anglo-Zulu War on 1 June 1879. Victoria's journal records their grief: “Dear Beatrice, crying very much as I did too, gave me the telegram... It was dawning and little sleep did I get... Beatrice is so distressed; everyone quite stunned.”Quoted in Dennison, p. 89

After the death of the Prince Imperial, Beatrice's brother, Albert Edward, the Prince of Wales, suggested that she marry their sister Alice's widower, Louis IV, the Grand Duke of Hesse, who had lost his wife to diphtheria in 1878. Albert Edward argued that Beatrice could act as replacement mother for Louis's young children and spend most of her time in England looking after her mother.Dennison, p. 103–104 He further suggested that the Queen could oversee the upbringing of her Hessian grandchildren with greater ease.Dennison, p. 104 However, at the time, it was forbidden by law for Beatrice to marry her sister's widower.
 This was countered by the Prince of Wales, who vehemently supported passage by the Houses of Parliament of the Deceased Wife's Sister Bill, which would have removed the obstacle.Dennison, p. 104 Despite popular support for this measure and although it passed in the House of Commons, it was rejected by the House of Lords because of opposition from the bishops.
 Although the Queen was disappointed that the bill had failed, she was happy to keep her daughter at her side.Dennison, p. 106

Other candidates, including two of Prince Henry's brothers, Prince Alexander (“Sandro”) and Prince Louis of Battenberg, were put forward to be Beatrice's husband, but they did not succeed.  Although Alexander never formally pursued Beatrice, merely claiming that he “might even at one time have become engaged to the friend of my childhood, Beatrice of England”,Quoted in Dennison, p. 126 Louis was more interested. Victoria invited him to dinner but sat between him and Beatrice, who had been told by the Queen to ignore Louis to discourage his suit.Dennison, p. 116 Louis, not realising for several years the reasons for this silence, married Beatrice's niece, Princess Victoria of Hesse and by Rhine. Although her marriage hopes had been dealt another blow, while attending Louis's wedding at Darmstadt, Beatrice fell in love with Prince Henry, who returned her affections.Dennison, p. 124
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bfaa0ac1fa237db6b5d4cf2bf0320cc8" name="Napoléon_Eugène_Bonaparte,_sitting" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/bfaa0ac1fa237db6b5d4cf2bf0320cc8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>