<document id="cf9f662fbdb8f6449021652c1a45b0cc-2.14" name="Stephen_Crane" cat="17">
<text>
Crane wrote many different types of fictional pieces while indiscriminately applying to them terms such as "story", "tale" and "sketch".  For this reason, critics have found clear-cut classification of Crane's work problematic.  While "The Open Boat" and "The Bride Comes to Yellow Sky" are often considered short stories, others are variously identified.Schaefer, p. ix


In an 1896 interview with Herbert P. Williams, a  reporter for the Boston ''Herald'', Crane stated that he did "not find that short stories are utterly different in character from other fiction.  It seems to me that short stories are the easiest things we write."Wolford, p. 90  During his brief literary career, he wrote more than a hundred short stories and fictional sketches.  Crane's early fiction stemmed from camping expeditions in his teen years; these stories would eventually become known as ''The Sullivan County Tales and Sketches''.Wolford, p. 3  He considered these "sketches", which are mostly humorous and not of the same caliber of work as his later fiction, to be "articles of many kinds" in that they are part fiction and part journalism.  The subject matter for these stories and others varied extensively.  His early New York City sketches and Bowery tales accurately described the results of industrialization, immigration and the growth of cities and their slums.  His collection of six short stories, ''The Little Regiment'', covered familiar ground with the American Civil War, a subject that made him famous with ''The Red Badge of Courage''.Wolford, p. x  Although similar to Crane's famous novel, ''The Little Regiment'' lacks vigor and originality.  Realizing the limitations of these tales, Crane wrote: "I have invented the sum of my invention with regard to war and this story keeps me in internal despair."Knapp, p. 163

''The Open Boat and Other Tales of Adventure'' (1898) contains thirteen short stories that deal with three periods in Crane's life: his Asbury Park boyhood, his trip to the West and Mexico in 1895 and his Cuban adventure in 1897.Knapp, p. 145  This collection was well received and included several of his most critically successful works.  His 1899 collection, ''The Monster and Other Stories'', was similarly well received.  Two posthumously published collections, however, were not as successful.  August 1900 saw the publication of ''The Whilomville Stories'', which consists of thirteen stories that Crane wrote during the last year of his life.  The work deals almost exclusively with boyhood, and the stories are drawn from events occurring in Port Jervis, where Crane lived from the age of seven to twelve.Knapp, p. 178  Focusing on small-town America, the stories tend toward sentimentality, but remain perceptive of the lives of children.  ''Wounds in the Rain'', published in September 1900,Schaefer, p. 89 contains fictional tales based on Crane's reports for the ''World'' and the ''Journal'' during the Spanish-American War.  These stories, which Crane wrote while desperately ill, include "The Price of the Harness" and "The Lone Charge of William B. Perkins" and are dramatic, ironic and sometimes humorous.Knapp, p. 170

Despite his prolific output, the majority of scholarly attention to Crane's short fiction has centered on four specific stories: "The Open Boat", "The Blue Hotel", "The Bride Comes to Yellow Sky", and "The Monster".Wolford, p. 115  H. G. Wells considered "The Open Boat" to be "beyond all question, the crown of all his work", and it is one of the most frequently discussed works in Crane's canon.Schaefer, p. 314
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="45a6de1c4bdbc935f29d87fd3ab2c05a" name="StephenCrane1899" sectnum="2.14#1">../img/45a6de1c4bdbc935f29d87fd3ab2c05a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>