<document id="cf9f662fbdb8f6449021652c1a45b0cc-3" name="Stephen_Crane" cat="17">
<text>
In four years, Stephen Crane published five novels, two volumes of poetry, three short story collections, two books of war stories, and numerous works of short fiction and reporting.Davis, p. 332  Today, however, he is mainly remembered for ''The Red Badge of Courage'', which is heralded as an American classic.  The novel has been adapted several times for the screen, including a successful 1951 film by John Huston.  By the time of his death, Crane had become one of the best known writers of his generation.  His eccentric lifestyle, frequent newspaper reporting, association with other famous authors, and self-expatriation made him somewhat of an international celebrity.Weatherford, p. 2  Although most stories about his life tended toward the romantic, rumors about his alleged drug use and alcoholism persisted long after his death.Davis, p. 333  

By the early 1920s, however, Crane and his work were nearly forgotten.  It was not until Thomas Beer published his biography in 1923, which was followed by editor Wilson Follett's ''The Work of Stephen Crane'' (1925&ndash;1927), that Crane's writing came to the attention of a scholarly audience.Cazemajou, p. 5  Crane's reputation was then enhanced by faithful support from friends such as Joseph Conrad, H. G. Wells and Ford Maddox Ford, all of whom either published recollections or commented upon their time with Crane.  John Berryman's 1950 biography of Crane further established him as an important American author.  Since 1951 there has been a steady outpouring of articles, monographs and reprints in Crane scholarship.Cazemajou, p. 6  

Today, Crane is considered one of the most innovative writers of the 1890s.Benfey, p. 3 His peers, including Conrad and James, as well as later writers such as Robert Frost, Ezra Pound and Willa Cather, hailed Crane as one of the finest creative spirits of his time.Knapp, p. 2  His work was described by Wells as "the first expression of the opening mind of a new period, or, at least, the early emphatic phase of a new initiative."Knapp, p. 1  Wells also went farther in saying that "beyond dispute", Crane was "the best writer of our generation, and his untimely death was an irreparable loss to our literature."Davis, p. 334  Conrad wrote that Crane was an "artist" and "a seer with a gift for rendering the significant on the surface of things and with an incomparable insight into primitive emotions".Conrad, p. 123  Crane's work has proved inspirational for future writers; not only have scholars drawn similarities between Hemingway's ''A Farewell to Arms'' and ''The Red Badge of Courage'',Stallman, p. 176 but Crane's fiction is thought to have been an important inspiration for Hemingway and his fellow Modernists.Robertson, p. 9  In 1936, Hemingway wrote in ''The Green Hills of Africa'' that "The good writers are Henry James, Stephen Crane, and Mark Twain.  That's not the order they're good in.  There is no order for good writers."Gibson (1988), p. 14  Crane's poetry is thought to have been a precursor to the Imagist movement,Hoffman, p. 63 and his short fiction has also left an impression on American literature; "The Open Boat", "The Blue Hotel", "The Monster" and "The Bride Comes to Yellow Sky" are generally considered by critics to be examples of Crane's best work.Weatherford, p. 27  

Several institutions and places have endeavored to keep Crane's legacy alive.  Badenweiler and the house where he died became something of a tourist attraction for its fleeting association with the American author; Alexander Woolcott attested to the fact that, long after Crane's death, tourists would be directed to the room where he died.Davis, p. 337  Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library has a collection of Crane and Taylor's personal correspondence dating from 1895 to 1908.  The Stephen Crane House in Asbury Park, New Jersey, where the author lived with his family for nine years, serves as a museum dedicated to his life and work.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="79934a113f05e39fcff33a0941f3be72" name="StephenCrane-PortJervisMarker" sectnum="3#1">../img/79934a113f05e39fcff33a0941f3be72.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>