<document id="cf9f662fbdb8f6449021652c1a45b0cc-1.2" name="Stephen_Crane" cat="17">
<text>
Crane wrote his first known story, "Uncle Jake and the Bell Handle", when he was 14.Davis, p. 20  In the fall of 1885, he enrolled at Pennington Seminary, a ministry-focused coeducational boarding school  north of Trenton,Davis, p. 21 where his father had been principal from 1849 to 1858.  Soon after her youngest son left for school, Mrs. Crane began suffering what the ''Asbury Park Shore Press'' reported as "a temporary aberration of the mind."Wertheim (1994), p. 34  She had apparently recovered by early 1886, but later that year a fourth death in six years occurred in Stephen's immediate family when the twenty-three year old Luther died after falling in front of an oncoming train while working as a flagman for the Erie Railroad.Davis, p. 22 

 
After two years, Crane left Pennington for Claverack College, a quasi-military school.  He would later look back on his time at Claverack as "the happiest period of my life although I was not aware of it."Davis, p. 23  A classmate remembered him as a highly literate but erratic student, lucky to pass examinations in math and science, and yet "far in advance of his fellow students in his knowledge of History and Literature", his favorite subjects.Davis, p. 24  Not having a middle name like the other students, he took to signing his name "Stephen T. Crane" in order "to win recognition as a regular fellow".  Crane was seen as friendly, but also moody and rebellious.  He sometimes skipped class in order to play baseball, a game in which he starred as catcher,Stallman, p. 19 although he was also greatly interested in the school's military training program.  He rose rapidly in the ranks of the student battalion.Wertheim (1994), p. 41  One classmate described him as "indeed physically attractive without being handsome," but he was aloof, reserved and not generally popular at Claverack.Davis, p. 28         

In the summer of 1888, Crane became his brother Townley's assistant at a New Jersey shore news bureau, working there every summer until 1892.Wertheim (1994), p. 44  Crane's first signed publication was an article on the explorer Henry M. Stanley's famous quest to find the English missionary David Livingstone in Africa.  It appeared in the February 1890 Claverack College ''Vidette''.Stallman, p. 24  Within a few months, however, Crane was persuaded by his family to forgo a military career and transfer to Lafayette College in Easton, Pennsylvania, in order to pursue a mining engineering degree.Wertheim (1994), p. 51  He registered at Lafayette on September 12 and promptly became involved in extracurricular activities; he took up baseball once more and joined the largest fraternity, Delta Upsilon, and two rival groups: the Washington Literary Society and the Franklin Literary Society.Davis, p. 30  Crane infrequently attended classes and ended the semester with grades for four of the seven courses he had taken.Davis, p. 31  After only one semester, Crane transferred to Syracuse University where he enrolled as a non-degree candidate in the College of Liberal Arts.Wertheim (1994), p. 56  He roomed in the Delta Upsilon fraternity house and joined the baseball team.  Attending merely one class (English Literature) during the middle trimester, he remained in residence while taking no courses in the third trimester.Wertheim (1994), p. 59  

Putting more emphasis on his writing, Crane began to experiment with tone and style while trying out different subjects.Davis, p. 35  A fictional story of his called "Great Bugs of Onondaga" ran simultaneously in the ''Syracuse Daily Standard'' and the ''New York Tribune''.Wertheim (1994), p. 61  Declaring college "a waste of time", Crane decided to become a full-time writer and reporter.  He attended a Delta Upsilon chapter meeting on June 12, 1891, but shortly afterwards left college for good.Davis, p. 37
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fd940bb100e72e5f734746f8a7e82d51" name="Craneinuniform" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/fd940bb100e72e5f734746f8a7e82d51.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>