<document id="cf9f662fbdb8f6449021652c1a45b0cc-1.7" name="Stephen_Crane" cat="17">
<text>
Given $700 in Spanish gold by the Bacheller-Johnson syndicate to work as a war correspondent in Cuba, Crane left New York on November 27 on a train bound for Jacksonville, Florida.Davis, p. 168  Upon arrival in Jacksonville, he registered at the St. James Hotel under the alias of Samuel Carleton to maintain anonymity while seeking passage to Cuba.Wertheim (1994), p. 222  While waiting for a boat, he toured the city and visited the local brothels.  Within days he met 31-year-old Cora Taylor, proprietor of the downtown bawdy house Hotel de Dream.  Born into a respectable Boston family,Benfey, p. 187 Taylor (whose legal name was Cora Ethel Stewart) had already had two brief marriages; her first husband, Vinton Murphy, divorced her on grounds of adultery.  In 1889, she had married Captain Donald William Stewart, whom she left in 1892 for another man.Davis, p. 176  By the time Crane arrived, Taylor had been in Jacksonville for two years.  She lived a bohemian lifestyle but was also a well-known and respected local figure.  The two spent much time together while Crane awaited his departure.  He was finally cleared to leave for the Cuban port of Cienfuegas on New Year's Eve aboard the ''SS Commodore''.Davis, p. 178  


The ship sailed from Jacksonville with 27 or 28 men and a cargo of supplies and ammunition for the Cuban rebels.Wertheim (1994), p. 232  On the St. John's River and less than  from Jacksonville, ''Commodore'' struck a sandbar in a dense fog and damaged its hull.  Although towed off the sandbar the following day, it was again beached in Mayport and again damaged.Wertheim (1994), p. 233  A leak began in the boiler room that evening and as a result of malfunctioning water pumps, the ship came to a standstill about  from Mosquito Inlet.  As the ship took on more water, Crane described the engine room as resembling "a scene at this time taken from the middle kitchen of hades."Wertheim (1994), p. 234  ''Commodore'''s lifeboats were lowered in the early hours of the morning on January 2, 1897 and the ship ultimately sank at 7 a.m.  Crane was one of the last to leave the ship in a  dinghy.  In an ordeal that he would recount in the short story "The Open Boat", Crane and three other men (including the ship's Captain) floundered off the coast of Florida for a day and a half before attempting to land the dinghy at Daytona Beach.  The small boat, however, overturned in the surf, forcing the exhausted men to swim to shore; one of them died.Wertheim (1994), p. 236  Having lost the gold given to him for his journey, Crane wired Cora Taylor for help.  She traveled to Daytona and returned to Jacksonville with Crane the next day, only four days after he had left on the ''Commodore''.Davis, p. 186  

The disaster was widely reported on the front pages of newspapers across the country.  Rumors that the ship had been sabotaged were widely circulated but never substantiated.Davis, p. 187  Portrayed favorably and heroically by the press, Crane emerged from the ordeal with his reputation enhanced, if not restored, after the battering he received during the Dora Clark affair.  Meanwhile, Crane's affair with Taylor quickly blossomed.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="935412a31a6710adf528e351c0eb4a8d" name="Commodore_photo" sectnum="1.7#1">../img/935412a31a6710adf528e351c0eb4a8d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>