<document id="cfc4979249ade1b95b13a8e577f32c3e-1" name="Dixie_(song)" cat="20">
<text>
"Dixie" is structured into 32 measure groups of alternating verses and refrains, following an AABC pattern.Crawford 266. As originally performed, a soloist or small group stepped forward and sang the verses, and the whole company answered at different times; the repeated line "look away" was probably one part sung in unison like this. As the song became widely popular, the audience likely joined the troupe in singing the chorus.Warburton 230. Traditionally, another eight measures of unaccompanied fiddle playing followed, coming to a partial close in the middle; since 1936, this part has rarely been printed with the sheet music.Sacks and Sacks 194.

The song was traditionally played at a slower tempo than most listeners are familiar with today. Rhythmically, the music is "characterized by a heavy, nonchalant, inelegant strut",Nathan 247. and is in duple meter, which makes it suitable for both dancing and marching. "Dixie" employs a single rhythmic motive (two sixteenth note pickups followed by a longer note), which is integrated into long, melodic phrases. The melodic content consists primarily of arpeggiations of the tonic triad, firmly establishing the major tonality. The melody of the chorus emulates natural inflections of the voice (particularly on the word "away"), and may account for some of the song's popularity.Nathan 249–50



According to musicologist Hans Nathan, "Dixie" resembles other material that Dan Emmett wrote for Bryant's Minstrels, and in writing it, the composer drew on a number of earlier works. The first part of the song is anticipated by other Emmett compositions, including "De Wild Goose-Nation" (1844), itself a derivative of "Gumbo Chaff" (1830s) and ultimately an 18th-century English song called "Bow Wow Wow". The second part is probably related to even older material, most likely Scottish folk songs.Nathan 259–60. The chorus follows portions of "Johnny Roach", an Emmett piece from earlier in 1859.Nathan 254.

As with other blackface material, performances of "Dixie" were accompanied by dancing. The song is a walkaround, which originally began with a few minstrels acting out the lyrics, only to be joined by the rest of the company (a dozen or so individuals for the Bryants).Nathan 260. According to a musician named Oscar Coon, Bryant's Minstrels performed a jig to "Dixie" called Beans of Albany. This is probably Albany Beef, the Scots-Irish dance that Emmett refers to in a book on fife instruction. Dancers probably performed between verses, and a single dancer used the fiddle solo at the end of the song to "strut, twirl his cane, or mustache, and perhaps slyly wink at a girl on the front row."Wootton, Ada Bedell (1936). "Something New about Dixie." ''The Etude.'' Quoted in Sacks and Sacks 194.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f016ea3badaa040f79e522ea82795e4f" name="Bryant's_Minstrels_walkaround_1" sectnum="1#1">../img/f016ea3badaa040f79e522ea82795e4f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>