<document id="d008bbe7a948c37e58de4827105b94c5-4.4" name="Larrys_Creek" cat="11">
<text>
There are at least two camps along Larrys Creek. "Camp Kiwanis" has a main lodge, four cabins, picnic pavilion, and various recreational facilities on  on Route 287,  south of Salladasburg in Mifflin Township. It is operated as a service by the Williamsport Kiwanis and rented out for fire department training, Girl Scouts, weddings, church, and other groups. Further south along the creek in Piatt Township is the New Tribes Mission camp for preparing Christian missionaries for field work with indigenous peoples in remote parts of the world. The training at the camp lasts one year. 

Edward Gertler writes in ''Keystone Canoeing'' that Larrys Creek "has an exceptionally scenic, ultra-highwater, whitewater run that is really worthy of your attention". Canoeing and kayaking on Larrys Creek are possible when the water is high enough (in Spring and after hard rain), with  of Class 3 whitewater from Township Road 786 south through the State Game Lands to Route 973, and  of Class 1 to 2 whitewater south from PA 973 to U.S. 220.

In addition to the  in State Game Lands No. 114, opportunities for hunting and fishing are available in the areas of Tiadaghton State Forest in the western part of the watershed, along the First and Second Forks. In 2002, a Pennsylvania Department of Conservation and Natural Resources (DCNR) report on "State Forest Waters with Special Protection" rated the First Fork as a "High Quality-Cold Water Fishery". A stretch of Larrys Creek from the water company filtration plant (near the border between Mifflin and Anthony Townships) to  downstream of the confluence with the First Fork has been designated as approved trout waters by the Pennsylvania Fish and Boat Commission. This means the waters will be stocked with trout and may be fished during trout season. 

There are also private hunting and fishing clubs and cabins along Larrys Creek and its tributaries. The largest is the "Larrys Creek Fish and Game Club", incorporated August 1, 1906, which owns over  along Route 287 on the Second Fork. As of 2006, the club has 55 active and 15 honorary members (all male). The club promotes conservation and stocks its  of trout stream with three to four thousand brook and brown trout each year. The club's facilities include a trapshooting range and a helipad, to aid in medical evacuations from its remote location.

Another large private club is the Ogontz Lodge on the First Fork, established by banker Jay Cooke about 1884 for fishing and hunting. ''Note'': This book is somewhat confused about the location, saying the lodge was "near Salidasburg (''sic'') in Lycoming county on the Susquehanna River above Williamsport, Pa.".  Cooke owned nearly the whole First Fork,  long, with the main "Lodge"  from the mouth, and a smaller "Upper Cabin"  upstream of that. Herbert Hoover found solitude at the Ogontz Lodge as a guest of Jay Cooke III three times: in June, 1918 (just before leaving for Europe as head of the American Food Administration), mid-May, 1928 (just before his selection as the Republican presidential candidate), and finally in late May, 1930 (as President of the United States). ''Note'': This book refers to the stream as "Larry Creek" (''sic''). Other notable guests at the Ogontz Lodge include Theodore Roosevelt, Jr. and Katharine Hepburn, and it is still in operation as of 2007. ''Note'': This web site claims the lodge was founded in 1876, but the other sources all agree it was founded ''circa'' 1884.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a8e2dce1cabca19e1ec28d02f226941c" name="Larrys_Creek_in_Salladasburg" sectnum="4.4#1">../img/a8e2dce1cabca19e1ec28d02f226941c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>