<document id="d06386787296abf8f75ba78c8cc0a70a-1.4" name="Strapping_Young_Lad" cat="20">
<text>
''The New Black'', Strapping Young Lad's fifth and final studio album, was released on July 11, 2006. Century Media imposed a strict deadline on the release date of the album; it was to be ready before the 2006 Ozzfest festival. Despite this, Townsend stated the recording was not rushed, and ''The New Black'' became a critical, as well as a commercial, success. It was more melodic than any of the band's previous albums and brought back the debut album's tongue-in-cheek humor. Having sold more than 4,000 copies during its first week, ''The New Black'' reached #200 on the ''Billboard'' 200 chart, #15 on the Top Independent Albums, and #8 on the Top Heatseekers charts. Stylus Magazine's Cosmo Lee described it as "heavy, catchy, and with no filler", and About.com's Chad Bowar was also positive, stating that "this is a CD that's dense and heavy, but also has some memorable hooks".

A music video was shot in late May to accompany the sole single from the album, "Wrong Side". In June 2006 Strapping Young Lad embarked on a short festival tour of Europe, including performances at the Rock am Ring and Rock im Park festivals in Germany and the Download Festival in England, which was followed by a second stage appearance at Ozzfest in July and August, where they played to some of their largest audiences in their career.

In an interview conducted by ''Terrorizer'' in August 2006, Townsend explained why he decided to put the band on hold:''Terrorizer''. August 17, 2006, Vol. 147.
At the end of the day, man, I'm just tired, and old, and bald, and fat, and grouchy, and bored. You know? So I was just like, I'm going to make this record, and do this stupid Ozzfest thing, and tell a bunch of stupid jokes in front of a lot of people at Download, then I'm just going to fuck off for a while. The bigger this gets, the less I care, to the point where I just need to go spend some time with my family. I don't wanna bastardise Strapping and all these other projects by doing it for the money. Strapping was about the big middle finger, and it still is, but I don't think it needs to go any further than this.
Although Hoglan initially denied the definitive break-up of the band, saying they would go on tour in March 2007, he later stated Strapping Young Lad is on "extended hiatus", and might never reunite again. In May 2007, during a press conference held to promote his new solo album, ''Ziltoid the Omniscient'', Townsend announced his plans to retreat from public view, including giving interviews and touring, to concentrate on his family, and producing solo albums, as well as other people's music. As a result, Strapping Young Lad were effectively disbanded. Townsend discussed his future projects in a May 2007 ''Metal Hammer'' interview, where he stated "there may be some stuff I do in the future that is as brutal and heavy as Strapping, it's just not going to be Strapping".

The remastered 10th anniversary edition of ''City'' was released on June 7, 2007, in similar vein to the 2006 remaster of ''Heavy as a Really Heavy Thing'', with bonus tracks and extended liner notes by Townsend. A career spanning best of album, entitled ''1994–2006 Chaos Years'', was released on March 31, 2008, with a bonus DVD of live performances and all of the band's music videos.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="248b30bbbbb82af063a9fc2f91818e5f" name="Strapping_Young_Lad_1" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/248b30bbbbb82af063a9fc2f91818e5f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>