<document id="d0a1b77240d99319d899b6e8f73bcf2f-1" name="Bald_Eagle" cat="3">
<text>
The plumage of an adult Bald Eagle is evenly brown with a white head and tail. The tail is moderately long and slightly wedge-shaped. Males and females are identical in plumage coloration, however females display sexual dimorphism in that they are 25 percent larger than males. The beak, feet, and irises are bright yellow. The legs are feather-free, and the toes are short and powerful with large talons. The highly developed talon of the hind toe is used to pierce the vital areas of prey while it is held immobile by the front toes. The beak is large and hooked, with a yellow cere.

The plumage of the immature is brown, speckled with white until the fifth (rarely fourth, very rarely third) year, when it reaches sexual maturity. Immature Bald Eagles are distinguishable from the Golden Eagle in that the former has a more protruding head with a larger beak, straighter edged wings which are held flat (not slightly raised) and with a stiffer wing beat, and feathers which do not completely cover the legs.Sibley, D. (2000). ''The Sibley Guide to Birds''. National Audubon Society ISBN 0-679-45122-6 p.127 

Body length ranges from . Adult females have a wingspan of up to , while adult males may be as small as . Adult females weigh approximately , males weigh . The size of the bird varies by location; the smallest specimens are those from Florida, where an adult male may barely exceed  and a wingspan of . The largest are Alaskan birds, where large females may exceed  and have a wingspan of over . 

The call consists of weak chirping whistles, harsher and more shrill from young birds than adults.

The average lifespan of Bald Eagles in the wild is around 20 years, with the oldest living to be about 30. In captivity, they often live somewhat longer. In one instance, a captive individual in New York lived for nearly 50 years. As with size, the average lifespan of an eagle population appears to be influenced by its location.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f1a0885ecd05f11f173a4db0069308b8" name="Juvenile_Bald_Eagle_Sand" sectnum="1#1">../img/f1a0885ecd05f11f173a4db0069308b8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>