<document id="d0c5ab6bebe308a495693e990a2947bc-1.2" name="Nauru" cat="11">
<text>
On the 6th and 7th of December, 1940, the German auxiliary cruisers ''Komet'' and ''Orion'' sunk four supply ships in the vicinity of Nauru. On the next day, ''Komet'' shelled Nauru's phosphate mining areas, oil storage depots, and the shiploading cantilever.  The attacks seriously disrupted phosphate supplies to Australia and New Zealand (mostly used for munition and fertilizer purposes.)

Japanese troops occupied Nauru on 26 August 1942.Lundstrom, John B., ''The First Team and the Guadalcanal Campaign'', Naval Institute Press, 1994, p. 175. The Japanese troops built an airfield on Nauru which was bombed for the first time on 25 March 1943, preventing food supplies from being flown to Nauru. The Japanese deported 1,200 Nauruans to work as laborers in the Chuuk islands.Haden, J. D. 2000.  ''Pacific Magazine'' URL Accessed 2006-05-05 Nauru, which had been bypassed and left to "wither on the vine" by American forces, was finally set free from the Japanese on 13 September 1945, when Captain Solda, the commander of all the Japanese troops on Nauru, surrendered the island to the Royal Australian Navy and Army. This surrender was accepted by the brigadier J. R. Stevenson, who represented Lieutenant General Sturdee, the commander of the First Australian Army, on board the warship HMAS ''Diamantina''The Times, 14 September 1945 Arrangements were made to repatriate from Chuuk the 737 Nauruans who survived Japanese captivity there. They were returned to Nauru by the BPC ship ''Trienza'' in January 1946.Garrett, J. 1996. ''Island Exiles''. ABC. ISBN 0-7333-0485-0. pp176–181  In 1947, a trusteeship was established by the United Nations, and Australia, New Zealand, and the United Kingdom became the U.N. trustees of the island.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d4c61034be9856c66e3829528c09f390" name="Nauru_Island_under_attack_by_Liberator_bombers_of_the_Seventh_Air_Force." sectnum="1.2#1">../img/d4c61034be9856c66e3829528c09f390.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>