<document id="d145d40761be8d33d14a33a5f82f6ace-3.5" name="Brownsea_Island_Scout_camp" cat="11">
<text>
The campsite is compartmentalised, with the memorial stone, shop, flags, destination signs, all in one area on the south-west corner of the island. Radiating off from this are many small camp zones, perhaps a dozen acres each, surrounded by trees and fences. The area set aside for camping now covers  and there is room for between 300 and 400 campers on the site. The Scout campsite and parts of the island have been cleared, and Scouts have been able to camp there since 1964.  

The National Trust maintains the Scout and Guide campsite, South Shore Lodge and the Baden-Powell Outdoor Centre where members of Brownsea Island Scout Fellowship and Friends of Guiding, Brownsea Island operate a small trading post.  The Baden-Powell Outdoor Centre was opened on 14 September 2007. It contains a new camp reception, new washrooms and toilet facilities.   The centre  also hosts a small Scouting museum. 
The altar of St. Mary's Church (about  from the camp) is lined with a Scout and a Guide flag. In 2007, to coincide with the Scouting centenary, about 40 new kneelers or hassocks were given to the church, decorated with the 21 World Scout Jamboree badges and other Scouting, Guiding and island badges . It is often used for services during large camps. Baden-Powell and his wife are buried in Kenya, there is  no memorial to them in the Church. 

Brownsea Island is generally open to the public from March to October, via ferry from Poole. By exception, the island was reserved for Scouts and Scouters on 1 August 2007 during the Sunrise Camp. The National Trust is operating a number of events throughout the summer months including guided tours, trails and activities in the visitor centre.

Scouts and Guides often do an "act of duty" whilst on the island; often this involves cutting back the rhodedendron added by a previous owner of the island, maintaining the Baden-Powell Outdoor centre by stacking rhodedendron in the wood-piles or raking the dead leaves, twigs and pine-needles from underneath pine trees so more plants that red squirrels eat can grow.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b45f17662a8ae7b94662211bf95cb7ce" name="Brownsea_Island_Scout_Camp_Church" sectnum="3.5#1">../img/b45f17662a8ae7b94662211bf95cb7ce.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>