<document id="d15d7ea67999319eb893420dbae4226e-4.12" name="Domitian" cat="25">
<text>
Domitian was murdered on 18 September 96, in a palace conspiracy organized by court officials.Jones (1992), p. 193 A highly detailed account of the plot and the assassination is provided by Suetonius, who alleges that Domitian's chamberlain Parthenius was the chief instigator behind the conspiracy, citing the recent execution of Domitian's secretary Epaphroditus as the primary motive.Grainger (2003), p. 16Suetonius, Life of Domitian  The murder itself was carried out by a freedman of Parthenius named Maximus, and a steward of Domitian's niece Flavia Domitilla, named Stephanus. The precise involvement of the Praetorian Guard is less clear. At the time the Guard was commanded by Titus Flavius Norbanus and Titus Petronius Secundus and the latter was almost certainly aware of the plot.Grainger (2003), p. 19 Cassius Dio, writing nearly a hundred years after the assassination, includes Domitia Longina among the conspirators, but in light of her attested devotion to Domitian&mdash;even years after her husband had died&mdash;her involvement in the plot seems highly unlikely.Jones (1992), p. 37 

Dio further suggests that the assassination was improvised, while Suetonius implies a well organised conspiracy.Grainger (2003), p. 5 For some days before the attack took place, Stephanus feigned an injury so as to be able to conceal a dagger beneath his bandages. On the day of the assassination the doors to the servants' quarters were locked while Domitian's personal weapon of last resort, a sword he concealed beneath his pillow, had been removed in advance.Grainger (2003), pp. 1&ndash;3 In accordance with an astrological prediction the emperor believed that he would die around noon, and was therefore restless during this time of the day. On his last day, Domitian was feeling disturbed and asked a servant several times what time it was. The boy, included in the plot, lied, saying that it was much later than noon. More at ease, the emperor went to his desk to sign some decrees, where he was suddenly approached by Stephanus:



Domitian and Stephanus wrestled on the ground for some time, until the emperor was finally overpowered and fatally stabbed by the conspirators. Around noon Domitian, just one month short of his 45th birthday, was dead. His body was carried away on a common bier, and unceremoniously cremated by his nurse Phyllis, who later mingled the ashes with those of his niece Julia, at the Flavian temple.Jones (1992), p. 38 According to Suetonius, a number of omens had foretold Domitian's death. Several days prior to the assassination, Minerva had appeared to him in a dream, announcing she had been disarmed by Jupiter, and would no longer be able to protect him.Suetonius, Life of Domitian
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a3b699ef4de9b11609f04904a08db96a" name="Athena_ciste" sectnum="4.12#1">../img/a3b699ef4de9b11609f04904a08db96a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>