<document id="d15d7ea67999319eb893420dbae4226e-2.4" name="Domitian" cat="25">
<text>
Although the war had officially ended, a state of anarchy and lawlessness pervaded in the first days following the demise of Vitellius. Order was properly restored by Mucianus in early 70, but Vespasian did not return to Rome until September of that year. In the meantime Domitian acted as the representative of the Flavian family in the Roman Senate. In addition to receiving the title of ''Caesar'', he was appointed praetor with consular power.Jones (1992), p. 15 Domitian's authority was merely nominal however, foreshadowing what was to be his role for at least ten more years. By all accounts, Mucianus held the real power in Vespasian's absence, and he was careful to ensure that Domitian, still only eighteen years old, did not overstep the boundaries of his function. The ancient historian Tacitus describes Domitian's first speech in the Senate as brief and measured, at the same time noting his ability to elude awkward questions.Tacitus, ''Histories'' IV.40 Strict control was also maintained over the young Caesar's entourage, promoting away influential generals such as Arrius Varus, Praetorian prefect, and Antonius Primus, who had led the Flavian forces at Bedriacum, and replacing them by more reliable men such as Arrecinus Clemens.

Equally curtailed by Mucianus were Domitian's military ambitions. The civil war of 69 had severely destabilized the provinces, leading to several local uprisings such as the Batavian revolt in Gaul. Batavian auxiliaries of the Rhine legions, led by Gaius Julius Civilis, had rebelled with the aid of a faction of Treveri under the command of Julius Classicus. Seven legions were sent from Rome, led by Vespasian's brother-in-law Quintus Petillius Cerialis. Although the revolt was quickly suppressed, exaggerated reports of disaster prompted Mucianus to depart the capital with reinforcements of his own. Domitian eagerly sought the opportunity to attain military glory, and joined the other officers with the intention of commanding a legion of his own. According to Tacitus, Mucianus was not keen on this prospect, but he considered Domitian a liability in any capacity that was entrusted to him and therefore preferred to keep him close at hand rather than in Rome.Tacitus, ''Histories'' IV.68 When news arrived of Cerialis' victory over Civilis, Mucianus tactfully dissuaded Domitian from pursuing further military endeavours. Domitian then wrote to Cerialis personally, suggesting he hand over command of his army but, once again, he was snubbed. With the return of Vespasian in late September, his political role was rendered all but obsolete, and Domitian withdrew from government devoting his time to arts and literature.Jones (1992), p. 17
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9e7c34e666cf1752ec05032ee4eadc21" name="Rembrandt_Harmensz._van_Rijn_047b" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/9e7c34e666cf1752ec05032ee4eadc21.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>