<document id="d15d7ea67999319eb893420dbae4226e-2.5" name="Domitian" cat="25">
<text>
Where his political and military career had ended in disappointment, Domitian's private affairs were more successful in 70. Vespasian attempted to arrange a dynastic marriage between his youngest son and the daughter of Titus, Julia Flavia,Jones (1992), p. 33 but Domitian was adamant in his love for Domitia Longina, going so far as to persuade her husband, Lucius Aelius Lamia, to divorce her so that Domitian could marry her himself. 


Despite its initial recklessness, the alliance was very prestigious for both families. Domitia Longina was the younger daughter of Gnaeus Domitius Corbulo, a respected general and honoured politician. Following the failed Pisonian conspiracy against Nero in 65, he had been forced to commit suicide. The new marriage not only re-established ties to senatorial opposition, but also served the  broader Flavian propaganda of the time, which sought to diminish Vespasian's political success under Nero. Instead connections to Claudius and Britannicus were emphasised, and Nero's victims, or those otherwise disadvantaged by him, rehabilitated.Jones (1992), p. 34 

In 73, Domitia and Domitian's only attested son was born. It is not known what the boy's name was, but he died in childhood sometime between 77 and 81.Jones (1993), p. 36 Shortly following his accession as Emperor, Domitian bestowed the honorific title of ''Augusta'' upon Domitia, while their son was deified, appearing as such on the reverse of coin types from this period.Jones (1992), pp. 161&ndash;162 Nevertheless, the marriage appears to have faced a significant crisis in 83. For reasons unknown, Domitian briefly exiled Domitia, and then soon recalled her, either out of love or due to rumours that he was carrying on a relationship with his niece Julia Flavia.Jones (1992), p. 39 Jones argues that most likely he did so for her failure to produce an heir.

By 84, Domitia had returned to the palace,Varner (1995), p. 200 where she lived for the remainder of Domitian's reign without incident.Jones (1992), pp. 34&ndash;35 Little is known of Domitia's activities as Empress, or how much influence she wielded in Domitian's government, but it seems her role was limited. From Suetonius, we know that she at least accompanied the Emperor to the amphitheatre, while the Jewish writer Josephus speaks of benefits he received from her.Jones (1992), p. 37 It is not known whether Domitian had other children, but he did not marry again. Despite allegations by Roman sources of adultery and divorce, the marriage appears to have been happy.Jones (1992), p. 35
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="91127b85927f86236a8ae8792a7d9a22" name="Domitia" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/91127b85927f86236a8ae8792a7d9a22.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>