<document id="d15d7ea67999319eb893420dbae4226e-3.9" name="Domitian" cat="25">
<text>
The military campaigns undertaken during Domitian's reign were generally defensive in nature, as the Emperor rejected the idea of expansionist warfare. His most significant military contribution was the development of the Limes Germanicus, which encompassed a vast network of roads, forts and watchtowers constructed along the Rhine river to defend the Empire.Jones (1992), p. 131 Nevertheless, several important wars were fought in Gaul, against the Chatti, and across the Danube frontier against the Suebi, the Sarmatians, and the Dacians. The conquest of Britain continued under the command of Gnaeus Julius Agricola, who expanded the Roman Empire as far as Caledonia, or modern day Scotland. Domitian also founded a new legion in 82, the Legio I Minervia, to fight against the Chatti. Domitian is also credited on the easternmost Roman evidence known, the rock inscription near Boyukdash mountain, in present-day Azerbaijan. As judged by the carved titles of Caesar, Augustus and Germanicus, the related march took place between 84 and 96.

Domitian's administration of the Roman army was characterized by the same fastidious involvement he exhibited in other branches of the government. His competence as a military strategist was criticised by his contemporaries however.Jones (1992), p. 127 Although he claimed several triumphs, these were largely propaganda manoeuvres. Tacitus derided Domitian's victory against the Chatti as a "mock triumph", and criticised his decision to retreat from Britain following the conquests of Agricola.Tacitus, ''Agricola'' 39Tacitus, ''Histories'' I.2 Nevertheless, Domitian appears to have been very popular amongst the soldiers, spending an estimated three years of his reign among the army on campaigns&mdash;more than any emperor since Augustus&mdash;and raising their pay by one-third.Syme (1930), p. 64 While the army command may have disapproved of his tactical and strategic decisions, the loyalty of the common soldier was unquestioned.Jones (1992), p. 144
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f6ce341bfd223c8bb9c3ba812d9371e5" name="Wachtposten_1_1x_Rheinbrohl" sectnum="3.9#1">../img/f6ce341bfd223c8bb9c3ba812d9371e5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>