<document id="d15d7ea67999319eb893420dbae4226e-1.2" name="Domitian" cat="25">
<text>
By 66, Domitian's mother and sister had long died,Waters (1964), pp. 52&ndash;53 while his father and brother were continuously active in the Roman military, commanding armies in Germania and Judaea. For Domitian, this meant that a significant part of his adolescence was spent in the absence of his near relatives. During the Jewish-Roman wars, he was likely taken under the care of his uncle Titus Flavius Sabinus II, at the time serving as city prefect of Rome; or possibly even Marcus Cocceius Nerva, a loyal friend of the Flavians and the future successor to Domitian.Jones (1992), p. 13Murison (2003), p. 149 

He received the education of a young man of the privileged senatorial class, studying rhetoric and literature. In his biography in the ''Lives of the Twelve Caesars'', Suetonius attests to Domitian's ability to quote the important poets and writers such as Homer or Virgil on appropriate occasions,Suetonius, Life of Domitian Suetonius, Life of Domitian  and describes him as a learned and educated adolescent, with elegant conversation.Suetonius, Life of Domitian  Among his first published works were poetry, as well as writings on law and administration. Unlike his brother Titus, Domitian was not educated at court. Whether he received formal military training is not recorded, but according to Suetonius, he displayed considerable marksmanship with the bow and arrow.Jones (1992), p. 16Suetonius, Life of Domitian  A detailed description of Domitian's appearance and character is provided by Suetonius, who devotes a substantial part of his biography to his personality.



Domitian was allegedly extremely sensitive regarding his baldness, which he disguised in later life by wearing wigs.Morgan (1997), p. 214 According to Suetonius, he even wrote a book on the subject of hair care.Suetonius, Life of Domitian  With regard to Domitian's personality, however, the account of Suetonius alternates sharply between portraying Domitian as the emperor-tyrant, a man both physically and intellectually lazy, and the intelligent, refined personality drawn elsewhere.Jones (1992), p. 198 Brian Jones concludes in ''The Emperor Domitian'' that assessing the true nature of Domitian's personality is inherently complicated by the bias of the surviving sources. Common threads nonetheless emerge from the available evidence. He appears to have lacked the natural charisma of his brother and father. He was prone to suspicion, displayed an odd, sometimes self-deprecating sense of humour,Morgan (1997), p. 209Suetonius, Life of Domitian  and often communicated in cryptic ways. This ambiguity of character was further exacerbated by his remoteness, and as he grew older, he increasingly displayed a preference for solitude, which may have stemmed from his isolated upbringing. Indeed, by the age of eighteen nearly all of his closest relatives had died by war or disease. Having spent the greater part of his early life in the twilight of Nero's reign, his formative years would have been strongly influenced by the political turmoil of the 60s, culminating with the civil war of 69, which brought his family to power.Waters (1964), p. 54
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="52cd851d3f89858631e1b717cffaf875" name="Vespasianus03_pushkin" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/52cd851d3f89858631e1b717cffaf875.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>