<document id="d15d7ea67999319eb893420dbae4226e-2.6" name="Domitian" cat="25">
<text>
Prior to becoming Emperor, Domitian's role in the Flavian government was largely ceremonial. In June of 71, Titus returned triumphant from the war in Judaea. Ultimately, the rebellion had claimed the lives of over 1 million people, a majority of which were Jewish.Josephus, ''The Wars of the Jews'' VI.9.3 The city and temple of Jerusalem were completely destroyed, its most valuable treasures carried off by the Roman army, and nearly 100,000 people were captured and enslaved. For his victory, the Senate awarded Titus a Roman triumph. On the day of the festivities, the Flavian family rode into the capital, preceded by a lavish parade which displayed the spoils of the war.Josephus, ''The Wars of the Jews'' VII.5.5 The family procession was headed by Vespasian and Titus, while Domitian, riding a magnificent white horse, followed with the remaining Flavian relatives.Suetonius, Life of Domitian  Leaders of the Jewish resistance were executed in the Forum Romanum, after which the procession closed with religious sacrifices at the Temple of Jupiter. A triumphal arch, the Arch of Titus, was erected at the south-east entrance to the Forum to commemorate the successful end of the war.Jones (1992), p. 93

Yet the return of Titus further highlighted the comparative insignificance of Domitian, both militarily and politically. As the eldest and most experienced of Vespasian's sons, Titus shared tribunician power with his father, received seven consulships, the censorship, and was given command of the Praetorian Guard; powers which left no doubt he was the designated heir to the Empire.Jones (1992), p. 18 As a second son, Domitian held honorary titles, such as ''Caesar'' or ''Princeps Iuventutis'', and several priesthoods, including those of ''augur'', ''pontifex'', ''frater arvalis'', ''magister frater arvalium'',  and ''sacerdos collegiorum omnium'', but no office with ''imperium''. He held six consulships during Vespasian's reign but only one of these, in 73, was an ordinary consulship. The other five were less prestigious suffect consulships, which he held in 71, 75, 76, 77 and 79 respectively, usually replacing his father or brother in mid-January. While ceremonial, these offices no doubt gained Domitian valuable experience in the Roman Senate, and may have contributed to his later reservations about its relevance.Jones (1992), p. 19 Under Vespasian and Titus, non-Flavians were virtually excluded from the important public offices. Mucianus himself all but disappeared from historical records during this time, and it is believed he died sometime between 75 and 77. Real power was unmistakably concentrated in the hands of the Flavian faction; the weakened Senate only maintained the facade of democracy.Jones (1992), p. 163

Because Titus effectively acted as co-emperor with his father, no abrupt change in Flavian policy occurred when Vespasian died on 23 June 79. Titus assured Domitian that full partnership in the government would soon be his, but neither tribunician power nor ''imperium'' of any kind was conferred upon him during Titus' brief reign.Jones (1992), p. 20 Understandably, the new emperor was not eager to alter this arrangement: he would have expected to rule for at least another twenty or thirty years, and urgent attention was required to address the multitude of disasters which struck during 79 and 80. On 24 August 79, Mount Vesuvius erupted,Cassius Dio, ''Roman History''  burying the  surrounding cities of Pompeii and Herculaneum under metres of ash and lava; the following year, a fire broke out in Rome which lasted three days and which destroyed a number of important public buildings.Jones (1992), p. 80 Consequently, Titus spent much of his reign coordinating relief efforts and restoring damaged property. On 13 September 81 after barely two years in office, he unexpectedly died of fever during a trip to the Sabine territories.

Ancient authors have implicated Domitian in the death of his brother, either by directly accusing him of murder,Philostratus, ''The Life of Apollonius  of Tyana''  or implying he left the ailing Titus for dead,Cassius Dio, ''Roman History''  even alleging that during his lifetime, Domitian was openly plotting against his brother. It is difficult to assess the factual veracity of these statements given the known bias of the surviving sources. Brotherly affection was likely at a minimum, but this was hardly surprising, considering that Domitian had barely seen Titus after the age of seven. Whatever the nature of their relationship, Domitian seems to have displayed little sympathy when his brother lay dying, instead making for the Praetorian camp where he was proclaimed emperor. The following day, 14 September, the Senate confirmed Domitian's powers, granting tribunician power, the office of Pontifex Maximus, and the titles of ''Augustus'', and ''Pater Patriae''.Jones (1992), p. 21
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="82e0f54ab166927a83e166ebca489b72" name="The_Triumph_of_Titus_Alma_Tadema" sectnum="2.6#1">../img/82e0f54ab166927a83e166ebca489b72.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>