<document id="d163d23e4420033b682fbfcf6c573e2d-1.1" name="Boydell_Shakespeare_Gallery" cat="1">
<text>
The rise in Shakespeare's popularity coincided with Britain's accelerating change from an oral to a print culture.  Towards the end of the century, the basis of Shakespeare's high reputation changed. He had originally been respected as a playwright, but once the theatre became associated with the masses, Shakespeare's status as a "great writer" shifted. Two strands of Shakespearean print culture emerged: bourgeois popular editions and scholarly critical editions.Dobson, 100–30; Merchant, 43; Taylor, 62. 

In order to turn a profit, booksellers chose well-known authors, such as Alexander Pope and Samuel Johnson, to edit Shakespeare editions. According to Shakespeare scholar Gary Taylor, Shakespearean criticism became so "associated with the dramatis personae of 18th-century English literature ...  he could not be extracted without uprooting a century and a half of the national canon".Taylor, 71. The 18th century's first Shakespeare edition, which was also the first illustrated edition of the plays, was published in 1709 by Jacob Tonson and edited by Nicholas Rowe.Taylor, 74. The plays appeared in "pleasant and readable books in small format" which "were supposed ... to have been taken for common or garden use, domestic rather than library sets".Franklin, 11–12.  Shakespeare became "domesticated" in the 18th century, particularly with the publication of family editions such as Bell's in 1773 and 1785&ndash;86, which advertised themselves as "more instructive and intelligible; especially to the young ladies and to youth; glaring indecencies being removed".Qtd. in Dobson, 209.

Scholarly editions also proliferated. At first, these were edited by author-scholars such as Pope (1725) and Johnson (1765), but later in the century this changed.  Editors such as George Steevens (1773, 1785) and Edmund Malone (1790) produced meticulous editions with extensive footnotes.  The early editions appealed to both the middle class and to those interested in Shakespeare scholarship, but the later editions appealed almost exclusively to the latter.  Boydell's edition, at the end of the century, tried to reunite these two strands.  It included illustrations but was edited by George Steevens, one of the foremost Shakespeare scholars of the day.See Sherbo's study of Steevens and Taylor, 70ff.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="13980e84771a92801b5e3ae6de841f0a" name="George_Steevens" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/13980e84771a92801b5e3ae6de841f0a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>