<document id="d163d23e4420033b682fbfcf6c573e2d-6" name="Boydell_Shakespeare_Gallery" cat="1">
<text>
By 1796, subscriptions to the edition had dropped by two-thirds. The painter and diarist Joseph Farington recorded that this was a result of the poor engravings:

West said He looked over the Shakespeare prints and was sorry to see them of such inferior quality.  He said that excepting that from His Lear by Sharpe, that from Northcote's children in the Tower, and some small ones, there were few that could be approved.  Such a mixture of dotting and engraving, and such a general deficiency in respect of drawing which He observed the Engravers seemed to know little of, that the volumes presented a mass of works which He did not wonder many subscribers had declined to continue their subscription.Qtd. in Friedman, 85.

The mix of engraving styles was criticised; line engraving was considered the superior form and artists and subscribers disliked the mixture of lesser forms with it.Bruntjen, 113–14; Lennox-Boyd, 45. Moreover, Boydell's engravers fell behind schedule, delaying the entire project. He was forced to engage lesser artists, such as Hamilton and Smirke, at a lower price to finish the volumes as his business started to fail.Merchant, 65–67; Boase, 96. Modern art historians have generally concurred that the quality of the engravings, particularly in the folio, was poor. Moreover, the use of so many different artists and engravers led to a lack of stylistic cohesion.Merchant, 66–67; Lennox-Boyd,  45, 49.

Although the Boydells ended with 1,384 subscriptions,Lennox-Boyd, 46. the rate of subscriptions dropped, and remaining subscriptions were also increasingly in doubt.  Like many businesses at the time, the Boydell firm kept few records. Only the customers knew what they had purchased.Friedman, 68.  This caused numerous difficulties with debtors who claimed they had never subscribed or had subscribed for less.  Many subscribers also defaulted, and Josiah Boydell spent years after John's death attempting to force them to pay.

The Boydells focused all their attention on the Shakespeare edition and other large projects, such as ''The History of the River Thames'' and ''The Complete Works of John Milton'', rather than on lesser, more profitable ventures.Bruntjen, 113.  When both the Shakespeare enterprise and the Thames book failed, the firm had no capital to fall back upon. Beginning in 1789, with the onset of the French revolution, John Boydell's export business to Europe was cut off.  By the late 1790s and early 1800s, the two-thirds of his business which depended upon the export trade was in serious financial difficulty.Friedman, 87–88.

John Boydell decided to appeal to Parliament for a private bill to authorise a lottery to dispose of everything in his business. He died before the lottery was held but lived long enough to see each of the 22,000 tickets purchased at three guineas apiece. The lottery was drawn on 28 January 1805: there were 64 winning tickets, the highest prize being the Gallery itself and its collection of paintings.  This went to William Tassie, a gem engraver and cameo modeller, of Leicester Fields (now Leicester Square).  Josiah offered to buy the gallery and its paintings back from Tassie for £10,000, but Tassie refused and auctioned the paintings at Christie's.Friedman, 4, 87–90; Merchant, 70–75.  The painting collection and two reliefs by Anne Damer fetched a total of £6,181 18s. 6d. The Banks sculpture group from the façade was initially intended to be kept as a monument for Boydell's tomb. Instead, it remained part of the façade of the building in its new guise as the British Institution until the building was torn down in 1868–69. The Banks sculpture was then moved to Stratford-upon-Avon and re-erected in New Place Garden between June and November 1870. The lottery saved Josiah from bankruptcy and earned him £45,000, enabling him to begin business again as a printer.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="24bb76ce66ed99cc8012c8d1c09f401b" name="Northcote-MurderPrinces" sectnum="6#1">../img/24bb76ce66ed99cc8012c8d1c09f401b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>