<document id="d163d23e4420033b682fbfcf6c573e2d-7" name="Boydell_Shakespeare_Gallery" cat="1">
<text>
From the outset, Boydell's project inspired imitators. In April 1788, after the announcement of the Shakespeare Gallery, but a year before its opening, Thomas Macklin opened a Gallery of the Poets in the former Royal Academy building on the south side of Pall Mall. The first exhibition featured one work from each of 19 artists, including Fuseli, Reynolds, and Thomas Gainsborough. The gallery added new paintings of subjects from poetry each year, and from 1790 supplemented these with scenes from the Bible. The Gallery of the Poets closed in 1797, and its contents were offered by lottery.McCalman, 194. This did not deter Henry Fuseli from opening a Milton Gallery in the same building in 1799. Another such venture was the Historic Gallery opened by Robert Bowyer in Schomberg House at 87 Pall Mall in about 1793. The gallery accumulated 60 paintings (many by the same artists who worked for Boydell) commissioned to illustrate a new edition of David Hume's ''The History of Great Britain''.Bruntjen, 118–21. Ultimately, Bowyer had to seek parliamentary approval for a sale by lottery in 1805, and the other ventures, like Boydell's, also ended in financial failure.Graham-Vernon, Deborah.  (subscription required). ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography''. Oxford University Press. 2004. Retrieved on 31 January 2008. 
alt=At right, a man stands in a long robe with his arms upraised. A woman clings to him. At left, a crew of men attempt to save a ship from a storm. 
The paintings and engravings that were part of the Boydell Gallery affected the way Shakespeare's plays were staged, acted, and illustrated in the 19th century. They also became the subject of criticism in important works such as Romantic poet and essayist Samuel Taylor Coleridge's "Lectures on Shakespeare" and William Hazlitt's dramatic criticism. Despite Charles Lamb's criticism of the Gallery's productions, Charles and Mary Lamb's children's book, ''Tales from Shakespeare'' (1807), was illustrated using plates from the project.Burwick, "Romantic Reception", 144–45.

The Boydell enterprise's most enduring legacy was the folio. It was reissued throughout the 19th century, and in 1867, "by the aid of photography the whole series, excepting the portraits of their Majesties George III. and Queen Charlotte, is now presented in a handy form, suitable for ordinary libraries or the drawing-room table, and offered as an appropriate memorial of the tercentenary celebration of the poet's birth".Shakespeare Gallery, xx. Scholars have described Boydell's folio as a precursor to the modern coffee table book.Bruntjen, 160.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1eda99bf4c2fbd32fcf1580375a66a31" name="BowyerBible" sectnum="7#1">../img/1eda99bf4c2fbd32fcf1580375a66a31.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>