<document id="d228a8121be181bb89ecc2a537b5260c-7" name="Georg_Forster" cat="3">
<text>
Forster had partial Scottish roots and was born in Polish Royal Prussia. He worked in Russia, England, Poland and in several German countries of his times. Finally, he finished his life in France. He worked in different milieus and travelled a lot from his youth on. It was his view that this, together with his scientific upbringing based on the principles of the Enlightenment, gave him a wide perspective on different ethnic and national communities:




In his opinion all human beings have the same abilities with regard to reason, feelings and imagination, but these basic ingredients are used in different ways and in different environments, which gives rise to different cultures and civilisations. According to him it is obvious that the culture on Tierra del Fuego is at a lower level of development than the European culture, but he also admits that the conditions of life there are much more difficult and this gives people very little chance to develop a higher culture. Based on these opinions he was classified as one of the main examples of 18th century German cosmopolitanism.Pauline Kleingeld, ''Six Varieties of Cosmopolitanism in Late Eighteenth-Century Germany'', in Journal of the History of Ideas, 1999 ()

In contrast to the attitude expressed in these writings and to his Enlightenment background, he used insulting terms expressing prejudices against Poles in his private letters during his stay in Vilnius and in a diary from the journey through Poland, Lawaty, Andreas, ''„Polnische Wirtschaft“ und „deutsche Ordnung“: Nachbarbilder und ihr Eigenleben'', in: Der Fremde, Interdisziplinäre Beiträge zu Aspekten von Fremdheit, Hg. Bernhard Oestreich, Peter Lang Verlag 2003, p. 156–166. Krause, Hans-Thomas, ''Georg Forster und Polen. In: Georg Forster (1754–1794). Ein Leben für den wissenschaftlichen und politischen Fortschritt'', in: Wissenschaftliche Beiträge der Martin-Luther-Universität Halle-Wittenberg T 42, Beiträge zur Universitätsgeschichte). Halle/S. 1981, p. 79-85. (accessed on September 1st, 2005). In the review of: ''"Czarna legenda Polski: Obraz Polski i Polaków w Prusach 1772–1815" (The black legend of Poland: the image of Poland and Poles in Prussia between 1772–1815)'', by Dariusz Łukasiewicz. Poznań: Wydawnictwo Poznańskiego Towarzystwa Przyjaciół Nauk, 1995. Vol. 51 of the history and social sciences series (English and German summaries). ISBN 83-7063-148-7. but he never published any manifestation of this attitude. Bömelburg, Hans-Jürgen, ''Georg Forster und das negative deutsche Polenbild. Ein Kosmopolit als Architekt von nationalen Feindbildern?'', in: Mainzer Geschichtsblätter 8 (1993), p. 79–90. These insults only became known after his death, when his private correspondence and diaries were released to the public. Since Forster's published descriptions of other nations were seen as impartial scientific observations, Forster's disparaging description of Poland in his letters and diaries was often taken at face value in Imperial and Nazi Germany, where it was used as a means of science-based support for a purported German superiority.Michael Burleigh, Wolfgang Wippermann, ''The Racial State: Germany 1933–1945'', Cambridge University Press, ISBN 0-521-39802-9 The spreading of the ''"Polnische Wirtschaft"'' (Polish economy) stereotype Hubert Orłowski: ''"Polnische Wirtschaft": Zum deutschen Polendiskurs der Neuzeit'' (Studien der Forschungsstelle Ostmitteleuropa an der Universität Dortmund). ISBN 3-447-03877-2.  Also in Polish as ISBN 83-900380-8-0 is most likely due to the influence of his letters. Stasiewski, Bernhard, ''"Polnische Wirtschaft" und Johann Georg Forster, eine wortgeschichtliche Studie.'', in: Deutsche Wissenschaftliche Zeitschrift im Wartheland 2 (1941), H. 3/4, p. 207–216. Salmonowicz, Stanisław: ''Jerzy Forster a narodziny stereotypu Polaka w Niemczech XVIII/XIX wieku''. In: ''Zapiski Historyczne'' 52 (1987), vol. 4, 135–147. - Germ.: ''Georg Forster und sein Polenbild: Kosmopolitismus und nationales Stereotyp.''  Medizinhistorisches Journal 23 (1988), 277–290.

Forster's attitude brought him into conflict with people of different nations he encountered and made him welcome nowhere, as he was too revolutionary and antinational for Germans,Gordon A. Craig, ''Engagement and Neutrality in Germany: The Case of Georg Forster, 1754–94'', The Journal of Modern History, Vol 41, no 1, March 1969, p. 1–16; page 2 proud and opposing in his dealings with Englishmen,Allan Arlidge, ''Cook As A Commander - Cook and His Supernumeraries'', In: ''Cook's Log'',  too unconcerned about Polish science for Poles, Wanda Grębecka, ''Stanisław Bonifacy Jundziłł'' (1761–1847), Warszawa-Lida 2003, Retro-Art  and too insignificant politically and ignored while in France.Gordon A. Craig, ''Engagement and Neutrality in Germany: The Case of Georg Forster, 1754–94'', The Journal of Modern History, Vol 41, no 1, March 1969, p. 1–16; page 12
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bd1ed51cfe4d68d9c050a2c226aaea4f" name="Forsterundsohn" sectnum="7#1">../img/bd1ed51cfe4d68d9c050a2c226aaea4f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>