<document id="d23db7de8727e426691b49f1234532f2-4" name="Make_Way_for_Ducklings" cat="17">
<text>
The city of Boston, the setting of the book, has whole-heartedly embraced the story. In the Public Garden, where the Mallards eventually settled, a bronze statue has been erected of Mrs. Mallard and her eight ducklings. While the tallest statue stands only 38 inches (.97 meters) tall, the caravan of bronze ducks set in Boston cobblestone spans 35 feet (10.67 m) from front to back. The statue, installed October 4, 1987, was a tribute to Robert McCloskey "whose story ... has made the Boston Public Garden familiar to children throughout the world."

Since 1978, the city has hosted an annual Duckling Day parade each spring, with children dressed as ducklings and their parents.  Part of the route retraces the path taken by Mrs. Mallard and her ducklings to get to the Public Garden.

In 2000, schoolchildren from Canton, Massachusetts decided that the book was worthy of being the official children's book of the Commonwealth of Massachusetts and went to their state legislature to get a bill passed declaring it so. However, legislators from Springfield, Massachusetts blocked the legislation on the grounds the official book should be by Springfield native Dr. Seuss. Legislators reached a compromise when they agreed to make Dr. Seuss the official children's author of the commonwealth and ''Make Way for Ducklings'' the official children's book.

A statue similar to the one in the Boston Public Garden was erected in Novodevichy Park in Moscow as part of the START Treaty on July 30, 1991. The statue, which was  long, was presented by then United States First Lady Barbara Bush to Russian First Lady Raisa Gorbachev as a gift to the children of the Soviet Union. Four of the ducks were stolen, three in February 2000 and one in 1991. Thieves hoping to sell the ducks as scrap metal cut the statues off at the legs. The ducks were replaced in September 2000 at a rededication ceremony attended by former President of the Soviet Union Mikhail Gorbachev.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="aa65308439787e442ae9b632acd69c2e" name="Make_way_for_ducklings_statue" sectnum="4#1">../img/aa65308439787e442ae9b632acd69c2e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>