<document id="d280e0f028346a2cc7012012c9a8fde3-4.5" name="HMS_Ark_Royal_(91)" cat="29">
<text>
''Ark Royal'' and ''Glorious'' arrived at Scapa Flow on 23 April, and were immediately redeployed as part of Operation DX. Sailing to Norway with the cruisers ''Curlew'' and ''Berwick'' and screened by the destroyers ''Hyperion'', ''Hereward'', ''Hasty'', ''Fearless'', ''Fury'' and ''Juno'', this was the first time the Royal Navy had deployed carriers with the primary purpose of providing fighter protection for other warships. The ships took up position on 25 April off the coast; ''Ark Royal'' positioned  offshore to reduce the chance of air attacks. The carrier's aircraft conducted anti-submarine patrols, provided fighter support for other ships, and carried out strikes against shipping and shore targets. ''Ark Royal'' returned to Scapa Flow on 27 April to refuel and replace lost and damaged aircraft, before heading back on the same day with the battleship HMS ''Valiant'' as escort. During the return, ''Ark Royal'' came under air attack from German Junkers Ju 88 and Heinkel He 111 aircraft operating from Norway. The carrier was undamaged, and resumed position on 29 April.


By this point, the British high command had realised that they could not hold the Germans in southern Norway. The evacuation of Allied troops from Molde and Åndalsnes began, with ''Ark Royal'' providing air cover from 30 April. On 1 May, the Germans tried to sink the carrier, with numerous air attacks through the day. ''Ark Royal''’s fighters and a heavy anti-aircraft barrage drove off the enemy, and although several bombs were dropped at the carrier, none impacted. The evacuation was completed on 3 May, and the carrier was recalled to Scapa Flow to refuel and rearm before returning to Norway. While in port, Captain Arthur Power left the ship for a promotion to the Admiralty, and was replaced by Captain Cedric Holland. On return to Norway, ''Ark Royal'' was told to provide air cover for operations around Narvik, including the landing of French troops on 13 May. She was joined on 18 May by the carriers ''Glorious'' and ''Furious''.

Despite these efforts, it was clear by the end of May that French forces were on the verge of collapse and Norway was a sideshow compared to the German advance to the English Channel. Operation Alphabet was instigated to move Allied troops from Narvik and Britain. ''Ark Royal'' and ''Glorious'', screened by the destroyers ''Highlander'', ''Diana'', ''Acasta'', ''Ardent'', and ''Acheron'', sailed from Scapa Flow on 1 June to cover the evacuation, which commenced the next day. ''Ark Royal'' carried out air patrols and bombing raids from 3 June to 6 June, before redeploying to Narvik on 7 June. Disaster struck the next day, when ''Glorious'', escorted by ''Acasta'' and ''Ardent'', were detached to return to the UK. The three ships were attacked and sunk by the German battlecruisers ''Scharnhorst'' and ''Gneisenau''. A search by ''Ark Royal''’s aircraft failed to locate the German ships, which had returned to Trondheim.

The last evacuation convoy left Narvik on 9 June. Before the British ships could withdraw, a raid on Trondheim located ''Scharnhorst''. An attack by ''Ark Royal''’s Skuas took place at midnight on 13 June. The attack was a disaster: the escort destroyers ''Antelope'' and ''Electra'' collided while ''Ark Royal'' was launching aircraft in fog and returned to England for repairs, eight of the fifteen attacking Skuas were shot down, while ''Scharnhorst'' escaped damage. ''Ark Royal'' returned to Scapa Flow the following day, and was reassigned to the Mediterranean Fleet.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0a8d25d4a4c1312071bc8acb161abc9c" name="HMS_Ark_Royal_Skua_landing" sectnum="4.5#1">../img/0a8d25d4a4c1312071bc8acb161abc9c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>