<document id="d280e0f028346a2cc7012012c9a8fde3-4.1" name="HMS_Ark_Royal_(91)" cat="29">
<text>
The outbreak of the Second World War on 3 September 1939 had been presaged by Germany's U-boat fleet taking up positions off the British coast, where they could intercept British shipping. Within hours of the war starting, the passenger ship SS ''Athenia'' was torpedoed by ''U-30'', the first of over 65,000 tons of shipping sunk by U-boats during the first week of the war. ''Ark Royal'' was deployed with the Home Fleet in the North Western Approaches as part of a "hunter-killer" group, consisting of a flotilla of destroyers and other anti-submarine vessels grouped around an aircraft carrier; either HMS ''Courageous'', HMS ''Hermes'' or ''Ark Royal''. Carrier-borne aircraft could increase the area searched for U-boats, but made the carriers into tempting targets.

On 14 September, ''Ark Royal'' received a distress call from SS ''Fanad Head'', which was  away under pursuit from the surfaced ''U-30''. ''Ark Royal'' launched aircraft to aid the merchant ship, but was spotted by ''U-39'', which launched two torpedoes. Lookouts spotted the torpedo tracks and ''Ark Royal'' turned towards the attack, reducing her cross-section and causing the torpedoes to miss and explode harmlessly astern. Three F class destroyers escorting the carrier began to depth charge ''U-39'', and forced her to the surface. The German crew abandoned ship before ''U-39'' sank—the first U-boat lost in World War II. ''Ark Royal''’s aircraft reached ''Fanad Head'', which was in the hands of a German boarding party. The Skuas unsuccessfully attacked ''U-30'': two crashed when caught by the blast of their own bombs. The U-boat escaped after rescuing the boarding party and the pilots of the downed aircraft (both observers had drowned), and torpedoing the ''Fanad Head''.

''Ark Royal'' returned to base in Loch Ewe, where she and her crew were inspected by Winston Churchill. The sinking of ''U-39'' was hailed as important to morale. However, the failed attack on ''Ark Royal'', and the successful attack on HMS ''Courageous'' on 17 September, convinced the Admiralty it was too dangerous to risk aircraft carriers in this way, and carrier-centred hunter-killer groups were abandoned.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="54dcc1740d6530736519ffef393d9707" name="Declaration_of_war_naval_message" sectnum="4.1#1">../img/54dcc1740d6530736519ffef393d9707.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>