<document id="d280e0f028346a2cc7012012c9a8fde3-4.8" name="HMS_Ark_Royal_(91)" cat="29">
<text>
''Ark Royal'' spent April alternating between covering convoys and delivering aircraft to Malta and forays into the Atlantic to hunt commerce raiders. By May 1941, Rommel's Afrika Korps were driving through North Africa towards the Suez Canal, pushing the Western Desert Force before them. With British forces close to collapse and strategic locations threatened, the British High Command risked sending a reinforcement convoy across the Mediterranean to Alexandria. The convoy consisted of five large transport ships, escorted by ''Ark Royal'', the battleships HMS ''Renown'' and HMS ''Queen Elizabeth'', the cruisers HMS ''Sheffield'', HMS ''Naiad'', HMS ''Fiji'', and HMS ''Gloucester'', and screened by destroyers of the 5th Destroyer Flotilla. Prior to ''Ark Royal''’s departure, Captain Holland left to recuperate from stress and poor health, and was replaced by Captain Loben Maund. The convoy left Gibraltar on 6 May, and was detected by Italian aircraft. The convoy, limited to  and escorted by so many capital ships, was such a tempting target that Italian and German aircraft were mobilised.

The British convoy came under air attack on 8 May, first by the Italian air force, then German Luftwaffe. Over the day, twelve of ''Ark Royal''’s Fairey Fulmars (the maximum number available) drove off over fifty aircraft, with the assistance of targeting information from HMS ''Sheffield''’s radar and anti-aircraft fire from the escorts. During the initial waves, one Fulmar was lost, killing Flight Lieutenant Rupert Tillard and Lieutenant Mark Somerville, Admiral Somerville's nephew; another was destroyed with the aircrew recovered, while several others were damaged. Consequently, only seven were able to face the main Luftwaffe force of thirty-four aircraft, while an attack just before dark was driven off by two aircraft and heavy fire from the ships. The convoy survived without serious damage: the only casualties were to mines, with the ''Empire Song'' sunk and the ''New Zealand Star'' damaged but able to reach port.

''Ark Royal'' underwent another aerial attack on 12 May, during her return to Gibraltar. Later that month, she and fellow aircraft carrier HMS ''Furious'' delivered Hawker Hurricanes to support Malta.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="35ce61b7c7a032a934123c79abc202bc" name="HMS_Ark_Royal_AA_fire" sectnum="4.8#1">../img/35ce61b7c7a032a934123c79abc202bc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>