<document id="d280e0f028346a2cc7012012c9a8fde3-4.9" name="HMS_Ark_Royal_(91)" cat="29">
<text>
On 18 May, the German battleship ''Bismarck'' and the cruiser ''Prinz Eugen'' began Operation Rheinübung by breaking into the Atlantic to raid shipping. After sinking HMS ''Hood'' and damaging HMS ''Prince of Wales'' during the Battle of the Denmark Strait, ''Bismarck'' shook off her pursuers and headed for the French Atlantic coast. ''Ark Royal'', ''Renown'', and ''Sheffield'', accompanied by HM Ships ''Faulknor'', ''Foresight'', ''Forester'', ''Fortune'', ''Foxhound'', and HMS ''Fury'', were despatched to the Atlantic on 23 May to search for the battleship. On 26 May, a Fairey Swordfish from ''Ark Royal'' located ''Bismarck'' and began to shadow her, while the Home Fleet was mobilised to pursue.


At the time of detection, the British ships were  away and would not catch ''Bismarck'' before the battleship reached Saint-Nazaire. Fifteen Swordfish bombers were armed with torpedoes and sent to delay the ship. HMS ''Sheffield'' was also shadowing ''Bismarck'', and was between ''Ark Royal'' and ''Bismarck''. The aircraft falsely identified the British cruiser as their target and fired torpedoes. The torpedoes were fitted with unreliable magnetic detonators, which caused most to explode on contact with the water, while ''Sheffield'' evaded the rest. After realising his mistake, one of the pilots signalled 'Sorry for the kipper' to ''Sheffield''.

On return to the carrier, the Swordfishes were re-armed with contact-detonator warheads, and launched at 19.15 hours for a second attack; locating and attacking ''Bismarck'' just before sunset. Three torpedoes hit the battleship: two impacted forward of the engine rooms, while the third struck the port steering room and jammed her rudder in a 15° port turn. ''Bismarck'' was forced to sail in circles until the disabled rudder was reset to neutral, at which point she was sailing towards the British warships with almost no manoeuvring capability. The German battleship suffered heavy attack during the night of 26–27 May, and sank at 10:39 hours on 27 May.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fd90ff8f7a484d59d6c1cb4af73c0b17" name="HMS_Ark_Royal_swordfish" sectnum="4.9#1">../img/fd90ff8f7a484d59d6c1cb4af73c0b17.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>