<document id="d29b89b6157c476dba9cb3dd3a9c7a96-1" name="Ace_Books" cat="17">
<text>
Editor Donald A. Wollheim was working at Avon Books in 1952, but disliked his job. While looking for other work, he tried to persuade A. A. Wyn to begin a new paperback publishing company. Wyn was already a well-established publisher of books and pulp magazines under the name A. A. Wyn's Magazine Publishers. His magazines included ''Ace Mystery'' and ''Ace Sports'', and it is perhaps from these titles that Ace Books got its name. Wyn liked Wollheim's idea but delayed for several months; meanwhile, Wollheim was applying for other jobs, including assistant editor at Pyramid Books. Pyramid mistakenly called Wyn's wife Rose for a reference, thinking Wollheim had worked for her. When Rose told her husband that Wollheim was applying for another job, Wyn made up his mind: he hired Wollheim immediately as an editor.

The first book published by Ace was a pair of mysteries bound ''tête-bêche'': Keith Vining's ''Too Hot for Hell'', backed with Samuel W. Taylor's ''The Grinning Gismo'', priced at 35 cents, with serial number D-01. A ''tête-bêche'' book has the two titles bound upside-down with respect to each other, so that there are two front covers and the two texts meet in the middle (sometimes with advertising pages in between). This format is generally regarded as an innovation of Ace's; it was not, but since Ace published hundreds of titles bound this way over the next twenty-one years, it became the best-known publisher using the format. Books by established authors were often bound with those by lesser-known writers, on the premise that this would help new writers gain readers. The main drawback of the "Ace Double" format was that the two books had to fit a fixed page length (usually totalling between 256 and 320 low-height pages); thus one or both novels might be cut or revised to fit. Despite the tag "Complete and Unabridged" on the cover, books so labeled were sometimes still abridged.

Some important titles in the early D-series novels are D-15, which features William S. Burroughs's first novel, ''Junkie'' (written under the pseudonym "William Lee"), and many novels by Philip K. Dick, Robert Bloch, Harlan Ellison, Harry Whittington, and Louis L'Amour, including those written under his pseudonym "Jim Mayo".Canja, Jeff. (2002) ''Collectable Paperback Books, Second Edition'', East Lansing, MI: Glenmoor Publishing. ISBN 0-9673639-5-0

The last Ace Double in the first series was John T. Phillifent's ''Life with Lancelot'', backed with William Barton's ''Hunting on Kunderer'', issued August 1973 (serial #48245). Although Ace resumed using the "Ace Double" name in 1974, the books were arranged conventionally rather than ''tête-bêche''. In 1988, the last Ace Double was released. All told, Ace published nearly 650 doubles, more than 600 of which were in ''tête-bêche'' format.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="14342f0ac43283654fdf2f9ffddb7916" name="AceD-36ConanCover" sectnum="1#1">../img/14342f0ac43283654fdf2f9ffddb7916.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>