<document id="d335d71431520b2e6f1a2e53ee97f96c-5" name="Sasha_(DJ)" cat="20">
<text>
Influenced by the early sound of The Haçienda, Sasha began his career playing records of the rough, danceable genre of acid house. By the early 1990s, he had moved towards a more dark European house music style, though by the time of his Shelley's residency he had begun to experiment more with American house. His tastes further developed as he moved to Renaissance, and he began to incorporate the pop-based sounds of Moby, Spooky, and Leftfield. Sasha's second Digweed collaboration, 1997's ''Northern Exposure'', was described as "epic house", and subsequent releases featured the spacey and atmospheric progressive trance sound of artists such as Sven Väth, Matt Darey, Tilt, and Armin Van Buuren. A rhythmic and bassy progressive house influence distinguished his ''Xpander EP'' and the mix albums of the late 1990s.  At the time, Sasha's music rotation included records by artists such as Space Manoeuvres, BT, and Breeder, and Sander Kleinenberg's single "My Lexicon".

With the 2000 album ''Communicate'', the duo's work moved towards a deeper and darker house music sound. The album featured tracks by Morel, Mainline, and Jimmy Van M. The focus shifted from the melodic themes of previous releases in favour of a stronger emphasis on the bassline.  The Delta Heavy Tour and ''Airdrawndagger'' marked a dramatic shift in style, and reflected the influences of relaxed ambient and breakbeat music on Sasha's work. These influences inspired the  album's strong melodies, occasional breakbeat loops, and limited use of percussion.  ''Involver'' was primarily a fusion of the musical style of house and ambient breakbeat music characterised by UNKLE and Lostep. With 2005's ''Fundacion'', Sasha's style was mostly progressive house and electro-house music, with work by James Holden, Tiefschwarz, and Swayzak.  With his success in progressive house, Sasha has commented that he feels people try to "pigeon-hole" him into playing that genre. Rather than calling it progressive house, Sasha considers his most recent material to be between house, trance, and breaks, though he has stated that he prefers not to associate himself with a specific genre of music.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="19c15912904547be744b69ce8d4dffed" name="Sasha2" sectnum="5#1">../img/19c15912904547be744b69ce8d4dffed.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>