<document id="d44f7295a4c4656200a0c882cde807f6-3.2" name="Bobcat" cat="3">
<text>
Bobcat activities are confined to well-defined territories, which vary in size depending on gender and the distribution of prey. The home range is marked with feces, urine scent, and by clawing prominent trees in the area. In its territory the Bobcat will have numerous places of shelter: usually a main den, and several auxiliary shelters on the outer extent of its range, such as hollow logs, brush piles, thickets, or under rock ledges. Its den smells strongly of the Bobcat.

The sizes of Bobcat's home ranges vary significantly; a World Conservation Union (IUCN) summary of research suggests ranges anywhere from . One study in Kansas found resident males to have roughly an  range and females less than half that area. Transient Bobcats were found to have both a larger (roughly ) and less well-defined home range. Kittens had the smallest range at about . Research has shown that dispersal from the natal range is most pronounced with males.

Reports on seasonal variation in range size have been equivocal. One study found a large variation in male range sizes, from  in summer up to  in winter. Another found that female Bobcats, especially those which were reproductively active, expanded their home range in winter, but that males merely shifted their range without expanding it, which was consistent with numerous earlier studies. Other research in various American states has shown little or no seasonal variation.

Like most felines, the Bobcat is largely solitary but ranges will often overlap. Unusually for a cat, males are more tolerant of overlap, while females rarely wander into others' ranges. Given their smaller range sizes, two or more females may reside within a male's home range. When multiple male territories overlap a dominance hierarchy is often established resulting in the exclusion of some transients from favored areas.

In line with widely differing estimates of home range size, population density figures are divergent: anywhere from 1 to 38 Bobcats per  in one survey. The average is estimated at one Bobcat per every , or slightly less. A link has been observed between population density and sex ratio. One study noted that a dense, unharvested population in California had a sex ratio of 2.1 males per female. When the density decreased, the sex ratio skewed to 0.86 males per female. Another study observed a similar ratio, and suggested that males may be better able to cope with the increased competition, and that this would help limit reproduction until various factors lowered the density.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c8b32900228d6762384fa2ab30d79cc2" name="Calero_Creek_Trail_Bobcat" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/c8b32900228d6762384fa2ab30d79cc2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>