<document id="d44f7295a4c4656200a0c882cde807f6-2" name="Bobcat" cat="3">
<text>
The Bobcat resembles other species of the ''Lynx'' genus but is on average the smallest of the four. Its coat is variable, though generally tan to grayish brown, with black streaks on the body and dark bars on the forelegs and tail. Its spotted patterning acts as camouflage. The ears are black-tipped and pointed, with short black tufts. There is generally an off-white color on the lips, chin, and underparts. Bobcats in the desert regions of the southwest have the lightest colored coats, while those in the northern, forested regions are darkest. Kittens are born well-furred and already have their spots.  A few melanistic Bobcats have been sighted and captured in Florida. They appear black, but may actually still exhibit a spot pattern.

The face appears wide due to ruffs of extended hair beneath the ears. The fur is brittle but quite long and dense. The nose of the Bobcat is pinkish-red, and it has a base color of gray or yellowish- or brownish-red on its face, sides, and back. Bobcat eyes are yellow with black pupils. The pupils are round black circles and will widen during nocturnal activity to maximize light reception. The cat has sharp hearing and vision, and a good sense of smell. It is an excellent climber, and will swim when it needs to, but will normally avoid water.

The adult male Bobcat is  long, averaging ; with a stubby  tail, which has a "bobbed" appearance and gives the species its name. An adult stands about  at the shoulders. Adult males usually range from ; females average about . The largest bobcat on record weighed .http://www.uwsp.edu/wildlife/carnivore/Bobcat%20Natural%20History_files/Bobcat%20Natural%20History.htm The Bobcat is muscular, and its hind legs are longer than its front legs, giving it a bobbing gait. At birth it weighs  and is about  in length. By its first year it will reach about .

The cat is larger in its northern range and in open habitats. Nowell, K. and Jackson, P. (1996). ''Wild Cats. Status Survey and Conservation Action Plan.'' (). IUCN/SSC Cat Specialist Group. IUCN, Gland, Switzerland. A morphological size comparison study in the eastern United States found a divergence in the location of the largest male and female specimens, suggesting differing selection constraints for the sexes.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="430bc2b807ef9c0925ba6123bcd69dd2" name="Bobcat500" sectnum="2#1">../img/430bc2b807ef9c0925ba6123bcd69dd2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>