<document id="d48813041376add08c9e7251d3b1547b-2" name="Zhou_Tong_(archer)" cat="14">
<text>
Zhou Tong's fictional life story can be pieced together from two sources: ''The Story of Yue Fei'' and ''Iron Arm, Golden Sabre''. ''The Story of Yue Fei'' is a fictionalized retelling of Yue Fei's young life, military exploits, and execution. It was written by a native of Renhuo named Qian Cai (钱彩), who lived sometime during the reigns of Qing Dynasty Emperor Kangxi and Emperor Qianlong. A dating symbol in its preface points either to the year 1684 or to 1744.Degkwitz, Jochen. ''Yue Fei und sein Mythos. Die Entwicklung der Yue-Fei-Saga bis zum, Shuo Yue quan zhuan'', Chinathemen 13, edited by Helmut Martin, Volker Klapsch and Martin Krott (Bochum: N Brockmeyer, 1983 (ISBN 3883393215), pg. 69 It was deemed a threat by the Qing emperors and banned during the Qianlong era.Degkwitz: pp. 116-131 In the novel, Zhou is portrayed as an elderly widower and Yue's only military arts tutor. The General's historical spear master Chen Guang is never mentioned. Zhou teaches Yue Fei and his sworn brothers military and literary arts from chapters two through five, before his death.Qian: pp. 24-57

In the writing of his novel, Qian Cai used a different character when spelling Zhou's given name. Instead of the original character meaning "similar," it was changed to 侗, meaning "rude or rustic." So, "周侗" represents Zhou's distinct ''fictional'' persona. This spelling has even been carried over into modern day martial arts manuals.Liang, Shou-Yu and Dr. Yang, Jwing-Ming. ''Xingyiquan: Theory, Applications, Fighting Tactics and Spirit.'' Boston: YMAA Publication Center, 2002. (ISBN 978-0-940871-41-0), pg. 15Yuen, Man Kai. ''Northern Mantis Black Tiger Intersectional Boxing''. Wanchai, Hong Kong: Yih Mei Book Co. Ltd., 1991 (ISBN 962-325-195-5), pg. 5-6

''Iron Arm, Golden Sabre'' was written by Wang Yun Heng and Xiao Yun Long and published in 1986. This novel, which serves as Zhou's own fictional biography, is a prequel to ''The Story of Yue Fei'' because it details his adventures decades prior to taking Yue Fei as his student. It follows his life as a young martial arts instructor in the Song army's Imperial guard, his struggles against the Xixia and Liao Tartar barbarian tribes and his tutelage of ''Water Margin'' outlaws. The last few chapters incorporate the storyline from the four chapters that he appears in ''The Story of Yue Fei.'' This was later adapted into a ten volume Lianhuanhua-style comic book called ''The Legend of Zhou Tong'' in 1987.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d5682faa8dcf648bbde0e4d5820b54c6" name="Zhou_Tong_Cover" sectnum="2#1">../img/d5682faa8dcf648bbde0e4d5820b54c6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>