<document id="d48813041376add08c9e7251d3b1547b-3" name="Zhou_Tong_(archer)" cat="14">
<text>
Zhou has appeared in various kinds of media including novels, comic books, and movies. Apart from ''The Story of Yue Fei'' and ''Iron Arm, Golden Sabre'', he appears in a novel based around his older martial arts brother, Jin Tai. A recent graphic novel of ''The Story of Yue Fei'', deletes all mythological elements from the storyline and presents it in a historical manner. Instead of traveling from Hebei to Hubei to inspect land, Zhou travels from Shaanxi to Kaifeng City in Henan to visit an old friend who had been promoted to General. While in route to the capital city, Zhou takes note of a great famine plaguing the peasantry and even hears stories of some people resorting to Cannibalism. However, when he arrives in Kaifeng, he sees the empire is wasting money on the construction of large imperial gardens, the court officials Cai Jing and Wang Pu have extravagant residencies, and hears that even eunuchs are rich because they are given high government posts. Upon locating his friend, Zhou is distressed to find him in stocks and shackles and being escorted to the farthest reaches of China by imperial guards. He later learns that the General had accidentally offended some court officials and was sentenced to permanent exile on some trumped up charges. Apparently having little or no money, Zhou decides to visit Wang Ming in Hubei (mistakenly called Hebei) and becomes the estate's tutor.Low, C.C., Ed. ''Yue Fei – Pictorial Stories of the Great Chinese National Hero in English and Chinese (Vol. 1)''. Singapore: Canfonian PTE LTD., 2004 (ISBN 981-05-1195-7), pp. 25-27

Another noticeable difference in the storyline takes place when Zhou travels with his teenage disciples to visit his friend the Abbot. Instead of Yue wandering behind the temple to battle the magical snake, he stays with Zhou and the Abbot, while the other disciples go off to explore. Zhou watches as the Abbot tests Yue's strength by asking him to move an ornate three-hundred pound copper stove dating from the Han Dynasty. The abbot then lifts a stone floor tile and presents the boy with a large book on military strategy. He goes on to tell Yue how he was once a great soldier who fought in campaigns against the Liao and Western Xia empires, but became a monk after the Song agreed to become a vassal of each state. He later made a name for himself by teaching military skills to youths from the surrounding area. Since he has no heir of his own, the Abbot presents Yue with his own personal spear and instructs him in the proper use of the weapon. Zhou kindly protests the gift at first, but allows Yue to keep it out of friendship.Low: pp. 40-43

A second graphic novelization drastically changes the storyline involving Zhou. Like the original, Zhou becomes the tutor of the Wang estate, but, when news of his arrival prompts rich families to send their sons to learn from him, he is forced to accept droves of these students on a trial basis. He eventually chooses his friends' sons as his indoor disciples and Yue as his “godchild”. Years later, he takes his now teenage students not to see the Buddhist abbot, but to teach them military strategy out in the mountain wilderness. Yue senses trouble after his martial brothers separate to explore the forest and rushes off to rescue them, only to be confronted by a monstrous snake. After vanquishing the beast with his sword, Yue discovers a magic glowing spear within a cave and reports back to Zhou. Following their training, Zhou becomes ill from overexposure to the cold mountain air on the return trip home and dies soon after. Instead of just Yue, all of his students live beside his grave for a mourning period of one hundred days before returning home to their families. These events take place three years before Zhou originally died in ''The Story of Yue Fei''.Koh, Kok Kiang (tr.). ''Yue Fei: Glory and Tragedy of China’s Greatest War Hero''. Singapore: Asiapac Publication, 1994 (ISBN 9813029242), pp. 11-19

Stories including Zhou have also been used to educate. The Secondary School system of Hong Kong teaches children the value of mentorship by making them read about the close teacher-pupil relationship between Zhou and Yue.David W. Chan. “.” Roeper Review. Retrieved on 2008-12-11. A morale tale called "Yue Fei Studies Archery" in ''Children's Pictorial'', a Chinese magazine tailored for children ages two through seven, demonstrates how great achievements are only made possible via diligent practice. The story states how young Yue stumbles upon Zhou's training hall in a neighboring town while gathering fire wood. Yue applies to become a student, but Zhou tells him he must first practice the art of the "far-sighted person" by staring into the morning sun to improve his eyesight. After years of unrelenting practice, Yue is able to spot a lone goose flying off in the distance and two cicadas on a tree far into the forest. Zhou then officially takes him as his disciple and adopted son. Under his tutelage, Yue is able to master the eighteen weapons of war and to shoot a falling leaf from one-hundred paces away. "." ''Children's Pictorial Magazine''. Retrieved on 2008-12-12.

He is mentioned numerous times in author Robert Liparulo's newest thriller ''Deadlock'' (2009). Zhou is first featured in chapter eight during a conversation between the main character John "Hutch" Hutchinson, a journalist bent on stopping the maniacal plans of a billionaire madman, and his friend’s young son Dillon, an archery enthusiast. When Hutch asks him if he had ever heard of the archery-champion-turned-actor Howard Hill, Dillon replies: “I don’t think so…You told me about Zhou Tong.”Liparulo, Robert. ''Deadlock''. Thomas Nelson, 2009 (ISBN 1595541667), p. 54 Hutch then says: “Oh, yeah. Zhou Tong was something. Taught the Song Dynasty to be the best military archers in history. But Howard Hill .” Later in chapter fifty, while Hutch is trailing a killer through an airport, a page goes out over the intercom system for a “Mr. Zhou Tong.”Liparulo: p. 314 When the page goes out again, Hutch muses: “Zhou Tong had been a famous archery teacher and military arts tutor in the Song Dynasty.   had long telephone conversations about him, because of Tong’s blending of archery skills and self-discipline. He was an inspiration to . Dillon had sensed that and wanted to known everything about him.”Liparulo: p. 315 He finally realizes that the page had to have been left by Dillon’s mother Laura to catch his attention. The page is sent to warn him of a trap, but Hutch receives it too late.Liparulo: p. 316

Screen actors who have portrayed Zhou in film's from the 1940s and 1960's include Wong Sau Nin,  Li Ming,  and Jing Ci Bo. Jing starred alongside a ten year old Sammo Hung, who played young Yue Fei. Veteran martial arts actor Yu Cheng Hui, who played the sword-wielding antagonist in Jet Li's ''Shaolin Temple'', stated in a 2005 newspaper interview that he never shaved his trademark beard, even at the request of movie producers, because he wanted to portray Zhou in a future film. He went on to say "He is an outstandingly able person from the northern and southern Song Dynasties and many ''Water Margin'' heroes are his disciples. This person is very important in the martial arts and many people want to portray him in films."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2ea97c8d07f6834e0d5eaa197d4ca231" name="Jowtong" sectnum="3#1">../img/2ea97c8d07f6834e0d5eaa197d4ca231.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>