<document id="d48813041376add08c9e7251d3b1547b-1.2" name="Zhou_Tong_(archer)" cat="14">
<text>
Despite being literate, giving him a chance to become a scholar, young Yue Fei chose the military path because there had never been any tradition of full-fledged Confucian civil service in his family history. He would stay up all night reading military strategy books and idolized such great historical heroes as Guan Yu.Wilhelm: pg. 149 However, the Yue family was much too poor to afford military lessons for their son, so, Yao Dewang, the boy's maternal grandfather, hired Chen Guang (陈广) to teach the eleven year old how to wield the Chinese spear. Yao was very surprised when his grandson quickly mastered the spear by the age of thirteen.Kaplan: pg. 13 Zhou was then brought in to continue Yue's military training in archery.Qian, Ru Wen (钱汝雯). ''Biography of Song Yue, Prince of E'' (宋岳鄂王年), 1924 Dr. Kaplan describes Zhou as the "most important" of the two teachers.Kaplan: pg. 10

A section of the ''Jin Tuo Xu Pian'', the second part of Yue Ke's original published memoir, describes one of Zhou's archery lessons and reveals that he took other children as his pupils:
 
"One day,  T'ung gathered his pupils for an archery session and to display his ability put three arrows in succession into the center of the target. Pointing to the target to show grandfather , he said: 'After you can perform like this, you can say you are an archer.' Grandfather, thanked him and asked to be allowed to try. He drew his bow, let fly his arrow and struck the end of T'ung's arrow. He shot again and again hit the mark. T'ung was greatly amazed and subsequently presented to grandfather his two favorite bows. Thereafter grandfather practiced still more  he was able to shoot to the left and right, accurately letting fly the arrow as he moved. When he became a general he taught this to his officers and men so that his whole army became skilled at shooting to the left and right and frequently used this technique to crush the enemy's spirit."Kaplan: pg. 11Li, Hanhuan (李汉魂). ''Chronology of Yue Wumu'' (岳武穆年谱). Shanghai: Shangwu Press, 1947 - Chapter 4, pg. 3b

The last sentence of the passage is similar to one from the Republican era ''Biography of Song Yue, Prince of E''. But instead of teaching them his own technique, it states Yue taught what he had learned from Zhou to his soldiers who were victorious in battle.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d6c3c5c356214c7d8ada1e466210e162" name="Zhoutong%26students" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/d6c3c5c356214c7d8ada1e466210e162.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>