<document id="d48813041376add08c9e7251d3b1547b-2.9" name="Zhou_Tong_(archer)" cat="14">
<text>
There is insufficient historical evidence to support the claim he knew any skills beyond archery. Contemporary records never once mention Zhou teaching Yue boxing. Despite this, various wuxia novels and folk legends have attributed many different military and supernatural skills to Zhou. These range from mastery of the bow, double swords and Chinese spear to that of Wudang hard qigong, Chuojiao boxing and even X-ray vision. Børdahl, 1996: pp. 373–374 Wang Shaotang's folktale even represents him as a master of Drunken Eight Immortals boxing.

Zhou can also be linked to these combat arts through his historical and folklore students. Practitioners of Eagle Claw, Chuojiao and Xingyi commonly include him within their lineage history because of his association with Yue Fei, the supposed progenitor of these styles. Yuen Mankai believes Zhou taught Lin Chong and Lu Junyi the "same school" of martial arts that was later combined with seventeen other schools to create Mantis fist.Yuen: pg. 7 This combination of various schools refers to an eighteenth century martial arts manual that describes the gathering of eighteen masters at the Shaolin Monastery that supposedly took place during the early years of the Song Dynasty."Luohan Xinggong Duan Da". ''Journal of Sport History and Culture'' (体育文史), No. 1, (2001). pg. 36-37,9 (ISSN 1671-1572) Lin Chong and Yan Qing are listed as two of the eighteen masters invited, which means their skills of Mandarin Duck Leg and ground fighting are treated as two separate schools, instead of one. But he believes Mantis fist was created during the Ming Dynasty, and was therefore influenced by these eighteen schools from the Song. He also says Lu Junyi taught Yan Qing the same martial arts as he learned from Zhou.Yuen: pg. 8 

Very few references are made to the people who supposedly taught martial arts to Zhou. In ''The Legend of Zhou Tong'', he learns as a child from a Shaolin master named Tan Zhengfang.Xiong: Vol. 1, pg. 8 Practitioners of Chuojiao claim he learned the style from its creator, a wandering Taoist named Deng Liang. Practitioners of Geok Gar Kuen, a style attributed to Yue Fei, believe he studied under Han De, a "chivalrous person" from Shaanxi.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1575d64784111530def333c06f0adc91" name="Zhoupic7" sectnum="2.9#1">../img/1575d64784111530def333c06f0adc91.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>