<document id="d48813041376add08c9e7251d3b1547b-2.6" name="Zhou_Tong_(archer)" cat="14">
<text>
According to ''The Story of Yue Fei'', Zhou was married with a son.Qian: pg. 24 But Zhou comments that his "old wife" died and his "small son" was killed in battle against the Liaos after leaving with the outlaw Lu Junyi to fight in the war.Qian: pg. 25 In ''The Legend of Zhou Tong'', his wife is named Meng Cuiying (孟翠英) and his son is named Zhou Yunqing (周云清).Xiong: Vol. 2 and 8 He defeats Meng in a lei tai martial arts contest and wins her as his wife.Xiong: Vol. 2, pp. 68-75 But she is shortly thereafter kidnapped by the wicked monks of the Stone Buddha temple. Both Zhou and Meng eventually defeat the monks with their combined martial skills and later marry at the Miaochuan Pass in Hubei province.Xiong: Vol. 2-6


Zhou Yunqing first appears as a fierce, impulsive young man who rides his horse into the thick of enemy encampments wielding a long spear.Xiong: Vol. 6 He later dies in battle against the Liao Dynasty. After his son's death, Zhou retreats to the  for a long morning period.Xiong: Vol. 8 He later takes seven year old Yue Fei as his adopted son and sole heir years after the boy's father drowns in a great flood:

"I see that he  is clever and handsome and I, an old man, wish to have him as my adopted son ... He need change neither his name nor his surname. I only want him to call me father temporarily so that I can faithfully transmit all the skills I have learned in my life to a single person. Later, when I die, all he has to do is to bury my old bones in the earth and not allow them to be exposed, and that is all."Qian: pp. 33-34

However, after comparing events from ''The Story of Yue Fei'' and a account of Yue's life from the sixteenth century ''Popular Elucidation of the Restoration of the Song Dynasty'',Chang, Shelley Hsueh-lun. ''History and Legend: Ideas and Images in the Ming Historical Novels''. University of Michigan Press, 1990 (ISBN 047210117X), pg. 10 literary critic C.T. Hsia concluded "that his father did not  die in the flood and that, although Yueh Fei showed almost filial regard for the memory of his teacher Chou T’ung 同 (not 侗), the latter had not been his adopted father." The ''Popular Elucidation'' was one of the earliest of four “historical novels” (fictionalized dynastic chronologies) written about Yue during the Ming Dynasty, all of which predate ''The Story of Yue Fei''.Chang: pg. 103 Despite the addition of popular legends, Xiong Damu (fl. 1552), the author of this work, relied heavily on historical chronologies including Zhu Xi’s (1130-1200) ''Outlines and Details Based on the T'ung-chien'',Doniger, Wendy. ''Merriam-Webster's Encyclopedia of World Religions''; Wendy Doniger, Consulting Editor. Springfield, Mass: Merriam-Webster, 1999 (ISBN 0877790442), pg. 238 Yue Ke’s family memoir, and the Yuan Dynasty’s official ''Yue Fei Biography'' to write his story. So, ''The Story of Yue Fei'' was the first full-blown fictionalized novel to introduce the adoption storyline.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5bc68ac9517f77d36844cacb8f1f8aff" name="Zhou_adopts_Yue" sectnum="2.6#1">../img/5bc68ac9517f77d36844cacb8f1f8aff.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>