<document id="d48813041376add08c9e7251d3b1547b-2.7" name="Zhou_Tong_(archer)" cat="14">
<text>
He is generally portrayed as a large elderly man with a powerful voice. A modern folktale by noted Yangzhou storyteller Wang Shaotang (1889-1968), whom folklore researcher Vibeke Børdahl called "the unrivaled master of this  century,"Børdahl, 1996: xxv describes Zhou thus, 

"He was beyond the age of fifty, he was more than fifty, and standing upright he measured about eight feet. His face had a golden tan, arched brows, a pair of bright eyes, a regular head form, a square mouth, a pair of protruding ears, and under his chin there were three locks of beard, a grizzled beard. On his head he wore a sky-blue satin scarf, and he was dressed in a stately sky-blue satin coat with a silken girdle, a pair of wide black trousers without crotch and satin boots with thin soles."Børdahl, 1996: pp. 366-367 

Heroes and religious masters with above normal height are a recurring theme in Chinese folklore. For instance, his student Wu Song is said to be over nine feet tall in the same folktale.Børdahl, 1996: pg. 370 In ''The Story of Yue Fei'', the General simultaneously duels with two other warriors vying for first place in a military exam; one is nine feet tall and the other is eight feet tall.Qian: pg. 102 A Hagiography of the Taoist saint Zhang Daoling states he was over seven feet tall.Wong, Eva. ''Tales of the Taoist Immortals.'' Boston, Massachusetts: Shambhala Publications, Inc., 2001 (ISBN 1-57062-809-2), pg. 77

When Zhou is vocalized in "Yangzhou storytelling," he speaks in "Square mouth public talk," which is a manner of speaking reserved for martial heroes, highly respected characters, or, sometimes, lesser characters that pretend to be an important hero.Børdahl, 1996: pp. 92 and 94 Square mouth public talk is actually a mixture of two forms of dialogue: ''Fangkou'' and ''Guanbai''. ''Fangkou'' (square mouth) is a manner of steady, yet forceful over pronunciation of dialogue that was possibly influenced by Northern Chinese opera.Børdahl, 1996: pg. 84 ''Guanbai'' (public talk) is monologue and dialogue that is sometimes used for "imposing heroes."Børdahl, 1996: Footnote #38, pg. 84 This mixture of styles means Zhou Tong is treated as a highly regarded hero.

In her analysis of Yangzhou storytelling, Børdahl noted that the aforementioned tale about Zhou and Wu Song uses different forms of dialogue for both characters. Wu speaks square mouth utilizing standard mandarin without rusheng (short glottal syllables). On the contrary, Zhou speaks squaremouth using the Yangzhou tone system, which ''does'' utilize rusheng syllables. Therefore, she believes “square mouth dialogue should at least be divided into two subcategories, namely the Wu Song variant—without rusheng, and the Zhou Tong variant—with rusheng.", pp. 27 and 38–39
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="773833b31eaf2643fbb64c3842d778b9" name="Jowtongbook" sectnum="2.7#1">../img/773833b31eaf2643fbb64c3842d778b9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>