<document id="d4ca4f87da296f410bc1405b724aa842-4.7" name="William_Speirs_Bruce" cat="14">
<text>
With financial support from the Coats family, Bruce had acquired a Norwegian whaler, ''Hekla'', which he transformed into a fully equipped Antarctic research ship, renamed ''Scotia''.Rudmose Brown et al. pp. 6&ndash;7 He then appointed an all-Scottish crew and scientific team.For full listing of ship's and shore parties, see Speak, pp. 67&ndash;68 ''Scotia'' left Troon on 2 November 1902, and headed south towards Antarctica, where Bruce intended to set up winter quarters in the Weddell Sea quadrant, "as near to the South Pole as is practicable".Speak, p. 79. The largely unexplored Antarctica continent had been divided by the RGS for convenience into four distinct geographic quadrants: Ross, Victoria, Enderby and Weddell Sea. On 22 February the ship reached 70°25&prime;S, but could proceed no further because of heavy ice.Rudmose Brown et al. p. 33 She retreated to Laurie Island in the South Orkneys chain, and wintered there. A meteorological station, Omond House, was established as part of a full programme of scientific work.Rudmose Brown et al., pp. 56&ndash;65

In November 1903 ''Scotia'' retreated to Buenos Aires for repair and reprovisioning. While in Argentina, Bruce negotiated an agreement with the government whereby Omond House became a permanent weather station, under Argentinian control.Rudmose Brown et al., p. 98 Renamed Orcadas Base, the site has been continuously in operation since then.Speak, pp. 85&ndash;86 In January 1904 ''Scotia'' sailed south again, to explore the Weddell Sea. On 6 March, new land was sighted, part of the sea’s eastern boundary; Bruce named this Coats Land after the expedition’s chief backers.Rudmose Brown et al., p. 121 On 14 March, at 74°01&prime;S and in danger of becoming icebound, Scotia turned north.Rudmose Brown et al., p. 122 The long voyage back to Scotland, via Cape Town, was completed on 21 July 1904.

This expedition assembled a large collection of animal, marine and plant specimens, and carried out extensive hydrographic, magnetic and meteorological observations. One hundred years later it was recognised that the expedition’s work had "laid the foundation of modern climate change studies",and that its experimental work had showed this part of the globe to be crucially important to the world’s climate. According to oceanographer Tony Rice, it fulfilled a more comprehensive programme than any other Antarctic expedition of its day. At the time, however, its reception in Britain was relatively muted; although its work was highly praised within sections of the scientific community, Bruce struggled to raise the funding to publish his scientific results, and blamed Markham for the lack of national recognition.Speak, p. 96
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9ff2c6f9bc29be92efef7e1ae82ee6bc" name="Scotia_on_Laurie_Island" sectnum="4.7#1">../img/9ff2c6f9bc29be92efef7e1ae82ee6bc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>