<document id="d4ca4f87da296f410bc1405b724aa842-2.5" name="William_Speirs_Bruce" cat="14">
<text>
On his return from Franz Josef Land, Bruce worked in Edinburgh as an assistant to his former mentor John Arthur Thomson, and resumed his duties at the Ben Nevis observatory. In March 1898 he received an offer to join Major Andrew Coats on a hunting voyage to the Arctic waters around Novaya Zemlya and Spitsbergen, in the private yacht ''Blencathra''. This offer had originally been made to Mill, who was unable to obtain leave from the Royal Geographical Society, and once again suggested Bruce as a replacement.Speak, pp. 52&ndash;57 Andrew Coats was a member of the prosperous Coats family of thread manufacturers, who had founded the Coats Observatory at Paisley.Bruce’s association with this family would be of great future benefit to him, through their financial backing for his main Antarctic venture a few years later. Bruce joined ''Blencathra'' at Tromsø, Norway in May 1898, for a cruise which explored the Barents Sea, the dual islands of Novaya Zemlya, and the island of Kolguyev, before a retreat to Vardø in north-eastern Norway to re-provision for the voyage to Spitsbergen.Speak, p. 54 In a letter to Mill, Bruce reported: "This is a pure yachting cruise and life is luxurious". But his scientific work was unabated: "I have been taking 4-hourly observations in meteorology and temperature of the sea surface  have tested salinity with Buchanan’s hydrometer; my tow-nets  have been going almost constantly".Speak, pp. 54&ndash;55

''Blencathra'' sailed for Spitsbergen, but was stopped by ice, so she returned to Trømsø. Here she encountered the research ship ''Princesse Alice'', purpose-built for Prince Albert I of Monaco, a leading oceanographer. Bruce was delighted when the Prince invited him to join ''Princesse Alice'' on a hydrographic survey around Spitsbergen. The ship sailed up the west coast of the main island of the Spitsbergen group, and visited Adventfjorden and Smeerenburg in the north. During the latter stages of the voyage Bruce was placed in charge of the voyage's scientific observations.Speak, pp. 56&ndash;57

In the following summer Bruce was invited to join Prince Albert on another oceanographic cruise to Spitsbergen. At Red Bay, latitude 80°N, Bruce ascended the highest peak in the area, which the Prince named "Ben Nevis" in his honour.Speak, p. 57 When ''Princesse Alice'' ran aground on a submerged rock and appeared stranded, Prince Albert instructed Bruce to begin preparations for a winter camp, in the belief that it might be impossible for the ship to escape. Fortunately she floated free, and was able to return to Trømsø for repairs.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f29efa009346f5576bc3deeefdadd1e1" name="Prince_Albert_I_of_Monaco_and_a_sperm_whale" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/f29efa009346f5576bc3deeefdadd1e1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>