<document id="d4ca4f87da296f410bc1405b724aa842-2.4" name="William_Speirs_Bruce" cat="14">
<text>
From September 1895 to June 1896 Bruce worked at the Ben Nevis summit meteorological station, where he gained further experience in scientific procedures and with meteorological instruments.Speak, pp. 41&ndash;45 In June 1896, again on the recommendation of Mill, he left this post to join the Jackson-Harmsworth Expedition, then in its third year in the Arctic on Franz Josef Land.Speak, p. 44 This expedition, led by Frederick George Jackson and financed by newspaper magnate Alfred Harmsworth, had left London in 1894. It was engaged in a detailed survey of the Franz Josef archipelago, which had been discovered, though not properly mapped, during an Austrian expedition 20 years earlier.Fleming, pp. 261&ndash;62 Jackson's party was based at Cape Flora on Northbrook Island, the southernmost island of the archipelago. It was supplied through regular visits from its expedition ship ''Windward'',Fleming, p. 261 on which Bruce sailed from London on 9 June 1896.



''Windward'' arrived at Cape Flora on 25 July where Bruce unexpectedly found, in addition to Jackson's expedition party, Fridtjof Nansen and his companion Hjalmar Johansen. The two Norwegians had been living on the ice for more than a year since leaving their ship ''Fram'' for a dash to the North Pole, and it was pure chance that had brought them to the one inhabited spot among thousands of square miles of Arctic wastes.Fleming. pp. 261&ndash;62 Bruce mentions meeting Nansen in a letter to Mill,Speak, pp. 49&ndash;51 and his acquaintance with the celebrated Norwegian would be a future source of much advice and encouragement.Speak, p. 50

During his year at Cape Flora Bruce collected around 700 zoological specimens, in often very disagreeable conditions. According to Jackson: "It is no pleasant job to dabble in icy-cold water, with the thermometer some degrees below zero, or to plod in the summer through snow, slush and mud many miles in search of animal life, as I have known Mr Bruce frequently to do".Speak, pp. 50&ndash;51 Jackson named Cape Bruce after him, on the northern edge of Northbrook Island, at 80°55&prime;N.Speak, p. 51 Jackson was less pleased with Bruce's proprietarial attitude to his personal specimens, which he refused to entrust to the British Museum with the expedition's other finds. This "tendency towards scientific conceit", and lack of tact in interpersonal dealings, were early demonstrations of character flaws that in later life would be held against him.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1d63db8cd5b96d0775a78361580ef9cb" name="Fridtjof_Nansen_LOC_03377u" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/1d63db8cd5b96d0775a78361580ef9cb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>