<document id="d7c764e39b819b2b6432987320c1303e-4.8" name="Winfield_Scott_Hancock" cat="29">
<text>
Hancock's time in the West was brief. President Johnson, unhappy with the way Republican generals were governing the South under Reconstruction, sought replacements for them.Trefousse, pp. 289–90. The general who offended Johnson the most was Philip Sheridan, and Johnson soon ordered General Grant to switch the assignments of Hancock and Sheridan, believing that Hancock, a Democrat, would govern in a style more to Johnson's liking.Jordan, pp. 200–201. Although neither man was pleased with the change, Sheridan reported to Fort Leavenworth and Hancock to New Orleans.

Hancock's new assignment found him in charge of the Fifth Military District, encompassing Texas and Louisiana. Almost immediately upon arriving, Hancock ingratiated himself with the white conservative population by issuing his General Order Number 40 of November 29, 1867. In that order, written while traveling to New Orleans, Hancock expressed sentiments in support of President Johnson's policies, writing that if the residents of the district conducted themselves peacefully and the civilian officials perform their duties, then "the military power should cease to lead, and the civil administration resume its natural and rightful dominion."Jamieson, pp. 152–53. Hancock's order encouraged white Democrats across the South who hoped to return to civilian government more quickly, but discomforted blacks and Republicans in the South who feared a return to the antebellum ways of conservative white dominance.Jordan, pp. 204–05; Tucker, pp. 279–284.

Hancock's General Order Number 40 was quickly condemned by Republicans in Washington, especially by the Radicals, while President Johnson wholeheartedly approved.Jordan, pp. 206–08; Walker, pp. 301–303. Heedless of the situation in Washington, Hancock soon put his words into action, refusing local Republican politicians' requests to use his power to overturn elections and court verdicts, while also letting it be known that open insurrection would be suppressed. Hancock's popularity within the Democratic party grew to the extent that he was considered a potential presidential nominee for that party in the 1868 election.Jordan, 213–228; Warner, p. 204. Although Hancock collected a significant number of delegates at the 1868 convention, his presidential possibilities went unfulfilled. Even so, he was henceforth identified as a rare breed in politics: one who believed in the Democratic Party's principles of states' rights and limited government, but whose anti-secessionist sentiment was unimpeachable.Jordan, p. 212; Walker pp. 301–302.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4b5cf007b728050e29e3e21e87273f89" name="Andrew_Johnson" sectnum="4.8#1">../img/4b5cf007b728050e29e3e21e87273f89.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>