<document id="d8ab30b5702bc83d480fe9f0ddc30fe3-1.2" name="The_Illuminatus!_Trilogy" cat="17">
<text>
The titles of the three volumes or parts (the front covers were titled ''Illuminatus! Part I The Eye in the Pyramid'', ''Illuminatus! Part II The Golden Apple'' and ''Illuminatus! Part III Leviathan'') refer to recurring symbols of elements of the plot. ''The Eye in the Pyramid'' refers to the Eye of Providence, which in the novel represents particularly the Bavarian Illuminati, and makes a number of appearances (for example, as an altar and a tattoo).  

''The Golden Apple'' refers to the Golden apple of discord, from the Greek myth of the Judgement of Paris. In the trilogy it is used as the symbol of the Legion of Dynamic Discord, a Discordian group; the golden apple makes a number of appearances, for example, on a black flag, and as an emblem on a uniform. 

''Leviathan'' refers to the Biblical sea monster Leviathan, which is a potential danger to Hagbard's submarine ''Leif Erickson'' (from the name of the Icelandic discoverer of America). 

The three parts of the trilogy are subdivided into five "books" named after the five seasons of the Discordian calendar.  These books are also subdivided into ten "trips" named after the ten Sephirot.  The last trip's conclusion is followed by fourteen appendices named after letters of the Hebrew Alphabet, which share their names with paths on the Tree of Life. The first page of the Appendix includes this mysterious note: "There were originally 22 appendices explaining the secrets of the Illuminati. Eight of the appendices were removed due to the paper shortage. They will be printed in heaven", while "Appendix Mem" states: "Where are the missing eight appendices? Answer: Censored."  This appears to be another of the authors' jokes, although it is true that eight letters of the Hebrew Alphabet are missing, and the publisher required the authors to cut 500 pages from the book.Wilson has stated in an online forum for his Maybe Logic Academy "Missing appendices among the 500 pages cut when Dell announced they wd only risk investment in 800 pages."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2662376d11c42c22f63999bdf2d7612b" name="Illum_EitP-1975" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/2662376d11c42c22f63999bdf2d7612b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>