<document id="d8b00929dec65d422303256336ada04f-10" name="Germany" cat="11">
<text>
Responsibility for educational oversight in Germany lies primarily with the federal states individually, whilst the federal government only has a minor role. Optional kindergarten education is provided for all children between three and six years old, after which school attendance is compulsory for at least nine years. Primary education usually lasts for four years and public schools are not stratified at this stage. U.S. Library of Congress. December 2005. Retrieved 2006, 12-04. In contrast, secondary education includes four types of schools based on a pupil's ability as determined by teacher recommendations: the ''Gymnasium'' enrols the most gifted children and prepares students for university studies, and attendance lasts eight or nine years depending on the state; the ''Realschule'' has a broader range of emphasis for intermediate students and lasts six years; the ''Hauptschule'' prepares pupils for vocational education, and the ''Gesamtschule'' or comprehensive school combines the three approaches.

The University of Heidelberg was established in 1386.

The Programme for International Student Assessment, coordinated by the OECD, assesses the skills of 15-year-olds in OECD countries and a number of partner countries. In 2006, German schoolchildren improved their position compared to previous years, being ranked (statistically) significantly above average (rank 13) in science skills and statistically not significantly above or below average in mathematical skills (rank 20) and reading skills (rank 18). The socio-economic gradient was very high in Germany, the pupils' performance in Germany being more dependent on socio-economic factors than in most other countries.

A special system of apprenticeship called ''Duale Ausbildung'' ("dual education") allows pupils in vocational training to learn in a company as well as in a state-run vocational school.

To enter a university in Germany, high school students are generally required to take the ''Abitur'' examination, which is similar to A-levels in the UK and typically done in the ''Gymnasium'' at the age of 18 or 19. However, students possessing a diploma from a vocational school may also apply for matriculation in certain subjects. Germany's universities are recognised internationally, indicating the high education standards in the country. In the ARWU ranking for 2008, six of the top 100 universities in the world are in Germany, and 18 in the top 200. Nearly all German universities are public (i.e. non-private) institutions, charging tuition fees ranging from €50–500 per semester for each student. German Academic Exchange Service. Retrieved 2006, 11-30.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2b3c564c3cfa37be460c6d14196a56df" name="Kindergartenfrankfurt" sectnum="10#1">../img/2b3c564c3cfa37be460c6d14196a56df.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>