<document id="d8b00929dec65d422303256336ada04f-8.15" name="Germany" cat="11">
<text>
With its central position in Europe, Germany is an important transportation hub. This is reflected in its dense and modern transportation networks. The extensive motorway (Autobahn) network that ranks worldwide third largest in its total length and features a lack of blanket speed limits on the majority of routes. 

Germany has established a polycentric network of high-speed trains. The InterCityExpress or ''ICE'' is the most advanced service category of the Deutsche Bahn and serves major German cities as well as destinations in neighbouring countries. The train maximum speed varies between 160 km/h and 300 km/h. Connections are offered at either 30-minute, hourly, or two-hourly intervals., Deutsche Bahn, Retrieved 19 October 2007.

The ICE 3 trainset

Germany is the world's fifth largest consumer of energy, and two-thirds of its primary energy was imported in 2002. In the same year, Germany was Europe's largest consumer of electricity, totaling 512.9 terawatt-hours. Government policy promotes energy conservation and the development of renewable energy sources, such as solar, wind, biomass, hydroelectric, and geothermal energy. As a result of energy-saving measures, energy efficiency has been improving since the beginning of the 1970s. The government has set the goal of meeting half the country's energy demands from renewable sources by 2050. 

In 2000, the government and the German nuclear power industry agreed to phase out all nuclear power plants by 2021., BBC, Accessed 13 April 2007 Renewable energy still plays a more modest role in energy consumption. In 2006, energy consumption was met by the following sources: oil (35.7%); coal, including lignite (23.9%); natural gas (22.8%); nuclear (12.6%); hydro and wind power (1.3%); and other (3.7%). However, the share of renewable energy in electricity supply has been rapidly increasing, reaching 14% in 2007. The German government has set a new target to increase this share to 27% by 2020.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d8691c171159e2cf2062f656a2a6b91e" name="Two_Ships-Hamburg" sectnum="8.15#1">../img/d8691c171159e2cf2062f656a2a6b91e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>