<document id="d960854c7e89d575e9ef7678d2eb2011-3" name="USS_Kentucky_(BB-66)" cat="29">
<text>
''Kentucky'' was never completed, instead serving as a supply cache of sorts while in the mothball fleet at the Philadelphia Naval Shipyard from about 1950 to 1958. It was during this time that several plans were proposed to complete ''Kentucky'' as a guided missile battleship (BBG) by removing the aft turret and installing a missile system. Since the battleship was already 73.1% complete (construction had been halted at the 1st deck), installation of the missile system would have involved only adding the necessary equipment without any need to rebuild the battleship to accommodate the system.The addition of missiles to a battleship had already been done aboard the battleship  (BB-41/AG-128) to test the terrier missile after World War II. () More recently, this was done to the four completed ''Iowa''-class battleships to allow them to carry and launch BGM-109 Tomahawk Missiles and RGM-84 Harpoon Missiles. () Concept artwork of the proposed missile conversion for ''Kentucky'' shows her aft end fitted with a pair of RIM-2 Terrier missile launchers. 

In May or June 1956, ''Kentucky''s bow was removed and transported on a large crane barge from Newport News, Virginia, where she had been towed, back to Norfolk Naval Shipyard, to be used in the repair of , which had been damaged in a collision with  on 6 May 1956. A new bow was fabricated but never installed; it was stored on her deck until the hulk was towed away. USS Kentucky (BB-66) Accessed 2007-11-03

When the first two of the s,  and , were laid down in 1961 and 1964, the Navy turned to ''Kentucky''s four turbine sets to power the ships. This would later prove to be a beneficial move: when the Navy switched from 600 psi (4.1 MPa) boilers to 1,200 psi (8.3 MPa) boilers, sailors who had served aboard these ''Sacramentos'' were called upon to operate the older boilers aboard  during her combat tour in the Vietnam War and aboard all four of the ''Iowas'' when recalled and modernized in the 1980s as part of the 600-ship Navy plan.

''Kentucky'' was struck from the Naval Vessel Register on 9 June 1958 and her incomplete hulk was sold for scrapping to Boston Metals Company of Baltimore, Maryland, on 31 October.  ''Kentucky'' was the second-to-last battleship under construction by the US Navy, and holds the title of being the highest numbered battleship hull to have been under construction but not completed for the United States Navy.  is numerically the highest numbered US battleship built, although she was actually completed before , making ''Missouri'' the last completed US battleship.''Wisconsin'' was commissioned 16 April 1944 while USS ''Missouri'' was commissioned 11 June 1944
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b0d9d48c7a86033c6bfb26113b67dd02" name="USS_Kentucky_(BBG-1)_concept_artwork" sectnum="3#1">../img/b0d9d48c7a86033c6bfb26113b67dd02.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>