<document id="da0af75d37f2d4965959eeb9bbd42d97-2.2" name="Bernard_Quatermass" cat="19">
<text>
At roughly the same time as ''Quatermass II'' was being transmitted by the BBC, Hammer Film Productions released their film adaptation of the first serial in British cinemas.Pixley, p. 21. Directed by Val Guest, it was retitled ''The Quatermass Xperiment'', and starred American actor Brian Donlevy as part of a deal to help the film find US distribution.Murray, p. 45. Kneale, who had little involvement with the film, was unimpressed with this casting. "I may have picked Quatermass's surname out of a phone book, but his first name was carefully chosen: Bernard, after Bernard Lovell, the creator of Jodrell Bank. Pioneer, ultimate questing man. Donlevy played him as a mechanic, a creature with a completely closed mind."Hearn & Rigby, p. 7. Val Guest has praised Donlevy's performance, saying that "he gave it absolute reality."Kinsey, p. 35.

Despite Kneale's reservations about the casting, ''The Quatermass Xperiment'' was the highest-grossing film Hammer had made up to that point in their history, and has since been described by one academic as "the key British science fiction film of the 1950s."Hunter, p. 8. Hammer were keen to make an immediate follow-up, and wanted to use Quatermass in their 1956 film ''X the Unknown''; however, Kneale refused them the rights, and they created their own substitute character, Doctor Adam Royston.Kinsey, p. 41. They did release an adaptation of ''Quatermass II'' in 1957, called ''Quatermass 2'' and this time with Kneale's involvement in the script.Kinsey, p. 50. To the writer's displeasure, Donlevy returned as Quatermass.

Hammer also purchased the film rights to ''Quatermass and the Pit'' (released in the USA as ''Five Million Years to Earth''), as it had done with the previous two TV serials, although they did not release their version until 1967.Pixley, p. 39. This time the film was directed by Roy Ward Baker and starred Scottish actor Andrew Keir, after Morell had been offered and declined the chance to play the part again.Murray, p. 95. Keir's performance was well-received, particularly in contrast to Donlevy's portrayal. ''The Guardian'' newspaper wrote in 1997 that: "Keir also made many films... most gratifyingly, perhaps, the movie version of ''Quatermass and the Pit'' (1967), when he finally replaced the absurdly miscast Brian Donlevy."

Soon after the release of the ''Quatermass and the Pit'' film, Kneale was approached by Hammer about writing a fourth Quatermass story directly for them, but the idea came to nothing. 

Possible remakes of one or more of the Hammer film adaptations were also mooted at various points during the 1990s, with Dan O'Bannon scripting a potential new version of ''The Quatermass Experiment'' in 1993, but again nothing was eventually filmed.Murray, pp. 183&ndash;185.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="43684708be9e7fa80b6000e765ec4aa3" name="Andrewkeir" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/43684708be9e7fa80b6000e765ec4aa3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>