<document id="da15f8147f310160cc8d271885f8ee9a-1" name="Monarchy_of_the_United_Kingdom" cat="25">
<text>
In the uncodified Constitution of the United Kingdom, the Monarch (otherwise referred to as The Sovereign, The Crown, or His/Her Majesty, abbreviated H.M.) is the ceremonial Head of State. Oaths of allegiance are made to the Queen and her lawful successors.e.g.  ''God Save the Queen'' (or ''God Save the King'') is the British national anthem, and the monarch appears on postage stamps, coins, and banknotes. 

The Monarch takes no part in Government. The decisions to exercise Sovereign powers are entirely delegated from the Monarch, either by statute or by constitutional convention, to Ministers or Officers of the Crown, or other public bodies, exclusive of the Monarch personally. Thus the acts of state done in the name of the Crown, such as Crown Appointments Crown Appointments Act 1661 c.6, and even if personally performed by the Monarch, such as the Queen's Speech and the State Opening of Parliament, depend upon decisions made elsewhere:
*Legislative power is exercised by the Crown in Parliament, by and with the advice and consent of Parliament, the House of Lords and the House of Commons. 
*Executive power is exercised by H.M. Government, which comprises Her Majesty's Ministers, primarily the Prime Minister and the Cabinet. They have the direction of the Armed Forces of the Crown, Her Majesty's Civil Service and other Crown Servants such as the Diplomatic and Secret Services.
*The Judicial power is vested in H.M. Judges, who by constitution and statutes3. Constitutional Reform Act 2005 have judicial independence of the Government
*The Church of England, of which the Monarch is the head, has its own legislative, judicial and executive structures.
*powers independent of government are legally granted to other public bodies by statute such as the Police Acts, statutory instrument such as an Order-in-Council, Royal Commission or otherwise.
*Apart from members of parliament and local authorities, no public officers are elected.
 
As a constitutional monarch, the Sovereign's role is largely limited to non-partisan functions, such as granting honours. This role has been recognised since the 19th century; the constitutional writer Walter Bagehot identified the monarchy in 1867 as the "dignified part" rather than the "efficient part" of government. Constitutionally, the Crown will act only upon the advice of H.M. Government; its practical functions in that regard are only "to advise, to be consulted, and to warn".Bagehot, p.9.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="297f6ab47f7b998ad3a5d563bbe70e14" name="English_Bill_of_Rights_of_1689" sectnum="1#1">../img/297f6ab47f7b998ad3a5d563bbe70e14.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>