<document id="daf0b358283d6876ace0fb89db9d12d9-2.2" name="Kirsten_Dunst" cat="19">
<text>
The breakthrough role in Dunst's career came in ''Interview with the Vampire'', a 1994 film based on Anne Rice's novel, in which she played the child vampire Claudia, a surrogate daughter to Tom Cruise and Brad Pitt's characters in the film. The film received generally unfavorable reviews, but many film critics complimented Dunst's performance. Roger Ebert commented that Dunst's creation of the child vampire Claudia was one of the "creepier" aspects of the film, and mentioned her ability to convey the impression of great age inside apparent youth. Todd McCarthy in ''Variety'' noted that Dunst was "just right" for the family. The film featured a scene in which Dunst received her first kiss from Brad Pitt, who was 18 years her senior. In an interview with ''Interview'' magazine, she revealed, while questioned about her kissing scene with Pitt, that kissing him had made her feel uncomfortable: "I thought it was gross, that Brad had cooties. I mean, I was 10." Her performance earned her the MTV Movie Award for Best Breakthrough Performance, the Saturn Award for Best Young Actress, and her first Golden Globe Award nomination.


She then appeared in the adaptation of the drama ''Little Women'' (1994), Dunst portrayed Amy March, opposite Winona Ryder and Claire Danes. The film received favorable reviews; critic Janet Maslin of ''The New York Times'' wrote that the film was the greatest adaptation of the novel and remarked on Dunst's performance: "The perfect contrast to take-charge Jo comes from Kirsten Dunst's scene-stealing Amy, whose vanity and twinkling mischief make so much more sense coming from an 11-year-old vixen than they did from grown-up Joan Bennett in 1933. Ms Dunst, also scarily effective as the baby bloodsucker of ''Interview With the Vampire,'' is a little vamp with a big future."

In 1995, she appeared in the fantasy movie ''Jumanji'', loosely based on Chris Van Allsburg's 1981 book of the same name. The story is about a supernatural and ominous board game which makes animals and other jungle hazards appear upon each roll of the dice. She was part of an ensemble cast that included Robin Williams, Bonnie Hunt, and David Alan Grier. The movie grossed $100 million worldwide. That same year, and again in 2002, she was named one of ''People'' magazine's 50 Most Beautiful People. In 1996, Dunst had a recurring role in the third season of NBC's medical drama ''ER''. She portrayed a child prostitute, Charlie Chiemingo, taken under the guidance of Dr. Doug Ross, played by George Clooney. In 1997, she was the voice of Young Anastasia in the animated musical film ''Anastasia''. Also in 1997, Dunst appeared in the political satire ''Wag the Dog'', opposite Robert De Niro and Dustin Hoffman. The following year she was the voice of the title character, Kiki, a 13-year-old apprentice witch who leaves her home village to spend a year on her own, in the anime movie ''Kiki's Delivery Service'' (1998).

Dunst was offered the role of Angela in the 1999 drama film ''American Beauty'', but turned it down because she did not want to appear in the film's suggestive sexual scenes or kiss co-star Kevin Spacey. She later explained: "When I read it, I was 15 and I don't think I was mature enough to understand the script's material." That same year, she appeared in the comedy ''Dick'', alongside Michelle Williams. The film is a parody retelling the events of the Watergate scandal which lead to the resignation of U.S. president Richard Nixon.

In Sofia Coppola's independent film ''The Virgin Suicides'' (1999), Dunst played the role of troubled adolescent Lux Lisbon. The film was screened as a special presentation at the 43rd San Francisco International Film Festival in 2000. The movie received generally favorable reviews, and ''San Francisco Chronicle'' critic Peter Stack noted in his review that Dunst "beautifully balances innocence and wantonness".

In 2000, she played Torrance Shipman, the captain of a cheerleading squad in ''Bring It On''. The film generated mostly critical reviews, with Charles Taylor of Salon.com writing that the film had failed to provide Dunst with as good a role as she had either in ''Dick'' or in ''The Virgin Suicides.'' However, Jessica Winter of ''The Village Voice'' complimented Dunst, stating that her performance was "as sprightly and knowingly daft as her turn in ''Dick''. She provides the only major element of ''Bring It On'' that plays as tweaking parody rather than slick, strident, body-slam churlishness." The movie grossed $68 million worldwide.

The following year, Dunst had the lead in the teen comedy ''Get Over It'' (2001). She later explained that one of the reasons for accepting the role was that it gave her the opportunity to sing. Also in 2001, Dunst depicted the late American actress Marion Davies in ''The Cat's Meow'' (2001). The film, directed by Peter Bogdanovich, was described by Derek Elley of ''Variety'' as "playful and sporty", saying of Dunst that this was her best performance to date. "Believable as both a spoiled ingenue and a lover to two very different men, Dunst endows a potentially lightweight character with considerable depth and sympathy." In the ''Esquire'' review, Tom Carson called her performance "terrific". For her work, she won the Best Actress Silver Ombú category award at the 2002 Mar del Plata Film Festival.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="56e054b8f8cc65a98d570a6b683b506e" name="Kirsten_Dunst2_2005" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/56e054b8f8cc65a98d570a6b683b506e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>