<document id="db3b91602672910e57e2688ac39f23aa-10" name="Maximian" cat="25">
<text>
After the death of Constantius on July 25, 306, Constantine assumed the title of Augustus. This displeased Galerius, who instead offered Constantine the title of Caesar, which Constantine accepted. The title of Augustus then went to Severus.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 27–28; Barnes, ''New Empire'', 5; Lenski, 61–62; Odahl, 78–79. Maxentius was jealous of Constantine's power, and on October 28, 306, he persuaded a cohort of imperial guardsmen to declare him emperor. Uncomfortable with sole leadership, Maxentius sent a set of imperial robes to Maximian and saluted him as "Augustus for the second time", offering him theoretic equal rule but less actual power and a lower rank.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 30–32. 

Galerius refused to recognize Maxentius and sent Severus with an army to Rome to depose him. As many of Severus' soldiers had served under Maximian, and had taken Maxentius' bribes, most of the army defected to Maxentius. Severus fled to Ravenna, which Maximian besieged. The city was strongly fortified so Maximian offered terms, which Severus accepted. Maximian then seized Severus and took him under guard to a public villa in southern Rome, where he was kept as a hostage. In the autumn of 307, Galerius led a second force against Maxentius but he again failed to take Rome, and retreated north with his army mostly intact.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 30&ndash;31; Elliott, 41&ndash;42; Lenski, 62&ndash;63; Odahl, 86&ndash;87; Potter, 348&ndash;49.



While Maxentius built up Rome's defenses, Maximian made his way to Gaul to negotiate with Constantine. A deal was struck in which Contantine would marry Maximian's younger daughter Fausta and be elevated to Augustan rank in Maxentius' secessionist regime.  In return, Constantine would reaffirm the old family alliance between Maximian and Constantius, and support Maxentius' cause in Italy but would remain neutral in the war with Galerius. The deal was sealed with a double ceremony in Trier in the late summer of 307, at which Constantine married Fausta and was declared Augustus by Maximian.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 31; Lenski, 64; Odahl, 87&ndash;88; Pohlsander, ''Emperor Constantine'', 15&ndash;16. 

Maximian returned to Rome in the winter of 307&ndash;8 but soon fell out with his son and in the spring of 308 challenged his right to rule before an assembly of Roman soldiers. He spoke of Rome's sickly government, disparaged Maxentius for having weakened it, and ripped the imperial toga from Maxentius' shoulders. He expected the soldiers to recognize him but they sided with Maxentius, and Maximian was forced to leave Italy in disgrace.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 32; Lenski, 64; Odahl, 89, 93.

On November 11, 308, to resolve the political instability, Galerius called Diocletian (out of retirement) and Maximian to a general council meeting at the military city of Carnuntum on the upper Danube. There, Maximian was forced to abdicate again and Constantine was again demoted to Caesar. Licinius, a loyal military companion to Galerius, was appointed Augustus of the West.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 32&ndash;34; Elliott, 42&ndash;43; Lenski, 65; Odahl, 90&ndash;91; Pohlsander, ''Emperor Constantine'', 17; Potter, 349&ndash;50; Treadgold, 29. In early 309 Maximian returned to the court of Constantine in Gaul, the only court that would still accept him.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 32.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="aa639521141b01e85fb2f3fcc9bbbc10" name="Maxentius02_pushkin" sectnum="10#1">../img/aa639521141b01e85fb2f3fcc9bbbc10.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>