<document id="db3b91602672910e57e2688ac39f23aa-6.1" name="Maximian" cat="25">
<text>
Maximian realized that he could not immediately suppress Carausius and campaigned instead against Rhenish tribes.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 7; Bowman, 71; Corcoran, "Before Constantine", 40. These tribes were probably greater threats to Gallic peace than Carausius in any case and included many supporters of Carausius.Southern, 141; Williams, 50. Although Maximian had many enemies along the river, they were more often in dispute with each other than in combat with the empire.Williams, 50. Few clear dates survive for Maximian's campaigns on the Rhine beyond a general range of 285 to 288.Southern, 142. Barnes' ''New Empire'' records five dates for the period: the first, February 10, 286 at Milan (''Codex Justinianus'' 8.53(54).6; ''Fragmenta Vaticana'' 282); June 21, 286 at Mainz (''Fragmenta Vaticana'' 271); January 1, 287 Trier or Cologne or Mainz (date of consular assumption, ''Panegyrici Latini'' 10(2).6.2 ff.); and 287, his "expedition across the Rhine" (''Panegyrici Latini'' 10(2).7.1ff.) (Barnes, ''New Empire'', 57). 
While receiving the consular ''fasces'' on January 1, 287, Maximian was interrupted by news of a barbarian raid. Doffing his toga and donning his armor, he marched against the barbarians and, although they were not entirely dispersed, he celebrated a victory in Gaul later that year.Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 7; Bowman, 72.

Maximian believed the Burgundian and Alemanni tribes of the Moselle-Vosges region to be the greatest threat, so he targeted them first. He campaigned using scorched earth tactics, laying waste to their land and reducing their numbers through famine and disease. After the Burgundians and Alemanni, Maximian moved against the weaker Heruli and Chaibones. He cornered and defeated them in a single battle. He fought in person, riding along the battle line until the Germanic forces broke. Roman forces pursued the fleeing tribal armies and routed them. With his enemies from starvation, Maximian launched a great invasion across the Rhine.Barnes, ''New Empire'', 57; Williams, 50. He moved deep into Germanic territory, bringing destruction to his enemies' homelands, and demonstrating the superiority of Roman arms. By the winter of 287, he had the advantage and the Rhenish lands were free of Germanic tribesmen. Maximian's panegyrist declared: "All that I see beyond the Rhine is Roman."''Panegyrici Latini'' 10(2).7.7, translated by Nixon in Nixon and Rodgers, quoted in Bowman, 72.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="edb2f3459a312fcea67e92fb8671e1d1" name="Const.chlorus02_pushkin" sectnum="6.1#1">../img/edb2f3459a312fcea67e92fb8671e1d1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>