<document id="db8eacdbea2bd08ff85e82015abf7465-7.6" name="USS_New_Jersey_(BB-62)" cat="29">
<text>
In 1986 ''New Jersey'' began her next deployment, this time operating as part of the Pacific Fleet and as the centerpiece of her own battleship battle group (BBBG). This was first time that ''New Jersey'' had operational control of her own battleship battle group since the Korean War, and she cruised with her escorts from Hawaii to Thailand in 1986, freeing up U.S. aircraft carriers for other missions and in the process becoming the only major U.S. naval presence in the region from May to October. Although in command of her own Battleship Battlegroup ''New Jersey'' did sail with the aircraft carriers  and  while deployed in 1986.

Following an overhaul at Long Beach which lasted in to 1988 ''New Jersey'' returned to the Pacific Ocean, this time operating as part of a surface action group. The battleship operated near the coast of Korea prior to the opening of the 1988 Summer Olympics in Seoul, South Korea, then departed for Australia to participate in the Australian bicentennial celebrations.

In April 1989, as ''New Jersey'' was preparing for her last operational cruise, sister ship  suffered a catastrophic explosion in her #2 gun turret; fallout from the incident led U.S. Naval officials to freeze live fire exercises with the guns until the investigation in to the explosion was concluded. Eventually, the ban was lifted and ''New Jersey'' was allowed to use her big guns again.

The last cruise of the battleship ''New Jersey'' began in 1989 as part of Pacific Exercise '89. Upon completion of the exercise ''New Jersey'' sailed through the Indian Ocean and into the Persian Gulf, in the process becoming the centerpiece for various battle groups and surface action groups. ''New Jersey'' remained in the Persian Gulf for the rest of the year, returning to the United States in February 1990.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c6267b3a9ff92446f0460baaa9f396fb" name="New_Jersey_Shoots" sectnum="7.6#1">../img/c6267b3a9ff92446f0460baaa9f396fb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>