<document id="dba0eab005b946df4f00b09fb83913bc-10" name="Harbhajan_Singh" cat="26">
<text>
While Harbhajan was batting during the third day of the Second Test at the Sydney Cricket Ground, he became involved in an altercation with Australia's Andrew Symonds. As a result of this, he was charged with a Level 3 charge of racially abusing Symonds. Harbhajan was alleged to have called Symonds a "monkey". Harbhajan and his batting partner at the time of the incident, Sachin Tendulkar, denied this. At a hearing after the conclusion of the Test, match referee Mike Procter found Harbhajan guilty of the charge and imposed a ban of three Test matches. This decision generated controversy because no audio or video evidence was used, instead relying on the testimony of Australian players. The Indian team initially threatened to withdraw from the series pending an appeal against Harbhajan's suspension, however BCCI president Sharad Pawar later claimed that the tour would proceed even if Harbhajan's appeal was unsuccessful.  

Harbhajan (left), batting with Tendulkar during the Second Test at the SCG. the altercation with Symonds occurred during their partnership.

On January 29, following the Fourth Test, the appeal hearing was conducted in Adelaide by ICC Appeals Commissioner Justice John Hansen. The appeal hearing determined that the racism charge against Harbhajan was not proved, resulting in the revocation of the three Test ban imposed by match referee Mike Procter. However, Harbhajan was found guilty of using abusive language and fined 50% of his match fee. Hansen later admitted he "could have imposed a more serious penalty if he was made aware by the ICC of the bowler's previous transgressions"&mdash;including a suspended one Test ban.
It was reported that senior players from both sides had written a letter to John Hansen requesting that the charge be downgraded. The letter was signed by Sachin Tendulkar and Ricky Ponting and counter-signed by Michael Clarke, Hayden and Symonds. 

In the aftermath of the hearing, Hayden called Harbhajan an "obnoxious weed" during a radio interview, which earned him a code of conduct violation charge from Cricket Australia.

Following the hearing, Harbhajan played in all eight of India's round-robin matches in the Commonwealth Bank series, which also involved Sri Lanka, taking five wickets at 39.00. In the two finals matches, Australia suffered a top-order collapse and lost their first three wickets with only 24 and 32 on the board. Symonds and Hayden&mdash;with whom Harbhajan clashed during the summer&mdash;led a recovery with stands of 100 and 89 respectively. In both matches, Harbhajan had a hand in removing both Australians. In the first final in Sydney, he removed both in the space of four overs. In the second final in Brisbane, he completed the run out of Hayden after a mix-up, and then trapped Symonds leg before wicket in the same over. Australia lost the momentum and their run-rate slowed, with India going on to win the series 2&ndash;0.

Following the tour of Australia, India hosted South Africa in a three-Test series. The First Test in Chennai was a high-scoring draw in which 1498 runs were scored for 25 wickets. Harbhajan was the top wicket-taker for the match, with figures of 5/161 and 3/101. In the Second Test in Ahmedabad, he was India's leading wicket-taker for the third consecutive innings, taking 4/135 as the home team lost by an innings. With India needing a win in the Third Test in Kanpur to avoid series defeat, Harbhajan again took the leading bowling figures in both innings, with 3/52 and 4/44. His second innings effort helped bowl out the tourists for 121 and set up an eight-wicket win. As a result of his efforts, Harbhajan was named man-of-the-series.


Harbhajan was involved in further controversy after an 2008 Indian Premier League (IPL) match between Mumbai Indians and Kings XI Punjab at Mohali in April 2008. While the teams were shaking hands, he slapped Punjab paceman and Indian team-mate Sreesanth. The Kings XI Punjab lodged an official compliant to the IPL. The match referee Farokh Engineer found Harbhajan guilty of a level 4.2 offence, banning him from the remainder of the IPL and fining him all of his match fee. Harbhajan made up with Sreesanth, and said that "I have been punished for the wrong I did". On May 14, the BCCI disciplinary committee found Harbhajan guilty under Rule 3.2.1 of the BCCI regulations and handed down the maximum punishment of five-match ban from ODIs. Harbhajan faces the prospect of a life ban if he commits further disciplinary breaches. As a result, Harbhajan missed the tri-series in Bangladesh and the 2008 Asia Cup in Pakistan.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b363934286ed92bde0310da9a24eff90" name="Sreesanth" sectnum="10#1">../img/b363934286ed92bde0310da9a24eff90.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>