<document id="dce4e4fb7e394b49ac6c59ec7cecf5a0-4" name="Arthur_Henry_Cobby" cat="29">
<text>
alt=Half length portrait of three military men behind a desk, all with pilot's wings on left breast pocket. One of the men, seated, has a large dark moustache and is wearing a dark winter uniform. The other two, standing on either side of the seated figure, wear short-sleeved tropical uniforms; one of them has a small moustache, the other has a holster on his belt and is clean-shaven and smoking a pipe
Cobby was a member of the RAAF Reserve (also known as the Citizen Air Force) during his time with the Civil Aviation Board, and rejoined the Permanent Air Force following the outbreak of World War II in September 1939.Odgers,  Promoted Group Captain, he officially returned to active service on 25 July 1940 as Director of Recruiting, a role that traded on his public image. at . Retrieved on 21 February 2009. On 25 August 1942, he took over from Air Commodore Frank Lukis as Air Officer Commanding (AOC) North-Eastern Area Command in Townsville, Queensland.Gillison,  1942 also saw the publication of ''High Adventure'', Cobby's account of his experiences in World War I; the foreword was written by Air Vice Marshal George Jones, newly appointed Chief of the Air Staff and fellow No. 4 Squadron veteran.Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp.20&ndash;21,320 By April 1943, Cobby had been promoted Air Commodore,Odgers,  and later in the year was posted to Point Cook as Commandant of the RAAF Staff School (RAAF Staff College from 1949).Dennis et al., ''The Oxford Companion to Australian Military History'', pp.135&ndash;136 On 7 September 1943, he was travelling as a passenger on a Catalina flying boat when it crashed at Townsville. Although himself injured, Cobby helped rescue two other survivors, and was recommended for the George Medal for his "outstanding bravery". at Australian War Memorial. Retrieved on 14 April 2009.
The award was gazetted on 10 March 1944. On 16 June that year, he was appointed a Commander of the Order of the British Empire (CBE) for his "conspicuous service" conducting air operations in New Guinea as AOC North-Eastern Area.


In August 1944, Cobby became AOC of No. 10 Operational Group (10OG), soon to be renamed the Australian First Tactical Air Force (1TAF). In this role he commanded 20,000 personnel in the RAAF's major mobile strike force in the South West Pacific, consisting of fighter, close support, and airfield construction units.Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp.168&ndash;169 Cobby expressed misgivings concerning the command arrangements that saw RAAF Headquarters in Melbourne responsible for 10OG's administration, while its operational tasking was to be passed down through RAAF Command, the United States Thirteenth Air Force and Headquarters South West Pacific Area. He believed this required him to "try and serve two masters", a situation he found "unworkable".Odgers,  By early 1945, Japanese air power in the South West Pacific had been virtually destroyed, and 1TAF was increasingly assigned to garrison duties and harassing enemy bases on islands bypassed by US forces in their advance on the Philippines.Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp.123&ndash;125 In the period 22&ndash;25 December 1944, 1TAF had flown 513 Kittyhawk and Beaufighter sorties against targets in Halmahera. A further 661 sorties against targets in Halmahera, Celebes, Morotai and the Vogelkop took place in January 1945.Odgers, ''100 Years of Australians at War'', pp.214&ndash;215 During March and April, 1TAF prepared for the invasion of Tarakan, an operation based around a mistaken judgement made by officers at Cobby's headquarters that the island's airstrip could be rapidly repaired and used to support the Borneo Campaign.Stanley, ''Tarakan. An Australian Tragedy'', p.60


The relegation of fighter units to what appeared to be strategically unimportant ground attack missions led to a crisis in morale that precipitated the so-called "Morotai Mutiny" in April 1945, when eight of Cobby's senior pilots, including Australia's leading ace in the war, Group Captain Clive Caldwell, tendered their resignations in protest. Although one of the "mutineers", Group Captain Wilf Arthur, had earlier voiced his concerns to Cobby and his headquarters staff regarding the efficacy of 1TAF's tasking, the AOC was taken aback by the resignations.Alexander, "Cleaning the Augean stables" He spoke to the officers individually and as a group, asking them, "Is this something against me, or having a go against me in this, because if so, if you feel that I have fallen down in my job, I will straight away ask to be recalled," to which they replied, "It has nothing to do with you."Odgers,  Cobby reported the incident to his immediate superior, Air Vice Marshal Bill Bostock, who informed the Chief of the Air Staff, Air Vice Marshal Jones, and the Allied Air Forces Commander, Lieutenant General George Kenney. All made their way to Morotai and interviewed the pilots involved, and all concluded that Cobby should be relieved of his command. 

Bostock held Cobby responsible for the "dangerously low level" of morale in 1TAF, but also noted "it is clear that he has been badly served by his senior staff".Odgers,  In the event, Jones transferred not only Cobby but also his staff officers, Group Captains Gibson and Simms, and Air Commodore Frederick Scherger took over command on 10 May.Odgers,  Cobby's departure was greeted with relief by Australian Army commanders, who were frustrated by the poor working relationship between 1TAF and the Army units at Tarakan.Stanley, ''Tarakan. An Australian Tragedy'', p.96 Cobby defended his leadership of 1TAF at the subsequent inquiry before Judge John Vincent Barry. During his testimony he declared that while his officers "wished to do more in the war than they were doing ... it was not within the power of 1st T.A.F. to give them that more important or more interesting work".Odgers,  However, Barry found that Cobby had "failed to maintain proper control over his command", and that his removal as 1TAF commander was justified. Air Force historian Dr Alan Stephens later described it as "a personal and institutional tragedy that a genuinely great figure in RAAF history had to end his career in such circumstances". Similarly, ''The Oxford Companion to Australian Military History'' contends that Cobby's "gallant service flying career ... became another victim of the weaknesses and feuding within the RAAF's senior leadership during the Pacific War".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="37796382f2be63bfde064787bca6d603" name="Cobby_Caldwell_(AWM_OG3380)" sectnum="4#1">../img/37796382f2be63bfde064787bca6d603.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>