<document id="dd083fdc5a4f9f82597d7b1f46a6c594-2" name="Anarky" cat="17">
<text>
Over the course of the character's existence, Anarky has under gone several shifts in his characterization. These were largely decided upon by Alan Grant, who for several years after the character's creation, was largely the sole author of the character. In an interview for Darkhorse.com, Grant summarized Anarky as "...a serious-beyond-his-years teenager who wants to set the world to rights." Norm Breyfogle, while having no input into the character's creation, was heavily invested in the development of the character during the ''Anarky'' limited series. In a 1998 introductory essay composed for ''Batman: Anarky'', Breyfogle characterized Anarky as not being a villain, but rather a "misunderstood hero", and continued "he's a ''philosophical'' action hero, an Aristotle in tights, rising above mere 'crime-fighter' status into the realm of incisive social commentary." However, Breyfogle later contradicted this description, reconsidering the character in more ambiguous terms for a 2005 interview. "Anarky isn’t a villain, he’s his own character. He’s definitely not a superhero, although it depends on who you talk to."

Having been created as a vehicle for Grant's personal political beliefs, Anarky was created as a reflection of anarchist philosophy, and later transformed into a vehicle for Neo-tech. This has caused his characterization to shift in stages between socialist and market based philosophies. In the 1997 ''Anarky'' series, atheism and rationalism also took new prominence as important character traits. Grant laid out his reasoning in an interview just before the first issue's publication. "I felt he was the perfect character" to express Neo-Tech philosophy, Grant explained, "because he's human, he has no special powers, the only power he's got is the power of his own rational consciousness". This new characterization was later carried on in the 1999 ''Anarky'' ongoing series.

While the ''Anarky'' limited series led the character away from the philosophy he had espoused previously, the primary theme of the character remained anti-statism. In one issue of the 1999 series, a character asked what the nature of Anarky's politics were. The response was that Anarky was neither right-wing, nor left-wing, and that he "transcends the political divide". Despite taking part in multiple interviews regarding the character, Grant has never specified the nature of Anarky's political categorization, preferring to state which philosophies inspired his characterization. Norm Breyfogle has said that he believes the Neo-Tech influence allows Anarky to be classified as an "objectivist".

As the character was based on a theme of ideas, he had been given no personal, tragic past; a common motivator in comic books. This was to contrast with Batman, who fought crime due to personal tragedy, while Anarky would do so in the name of ideals and beliefs. As the character was further developed, he was also intended to contrast with common teenage superheroes. Referring to the tradition established by Stan Lee and Jack Kirby of saddling teenagers with personal problems, Grant purposely gave Anarky none, nor did he develop a girlfriend or social life for the character. As Grant wrote for the ''Batman: Anarky'' introduction, this was intended to convey the idea that Anarky was single minded in his goals. "The Kid's whole life is dedicated to self-improvement, with the sole aim of destroying the parasitic elites who he considers feast off ordinary folks."

On two occasions Grant nearly went against Dennis O'Neil's early wish that Anarky not kill opponents. These events include his appearance during the Knightfall saga, in which Grant briefly portrayed Anarky as preparing to kill both the Scarecrow and Batman-Azrael.  Grant also implied Anarky was a lethal figure in "The Last Batman Story", part of ''Armageddon 2001'' crossover event. Grant later expressed relief that he had not fully committed to portraying Anarky as a potential murderer, as he felt "Anarky would have compromised his own beliefs if he had taken the route of the criminal-killer." Despite Anarky's non-lethal portrayal, entries for the character in ''Who's Who in the DC Universe'' and ''The DC Comics Encyclopedia'' have falsely referred to Anarky as having killed criminals in early appearances. Norm Breyfogle was also under the false impression that Anarky had killed for several years, having failed to realize the original script for Anarky's debut storyline had been rewritten. Grant eventually explained the situation to Breyfogle in 2006, during a joint interview.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8fb26c3ef85fe5d6ea93a2eef5cf6218" name="Detective_Comics_-609" sectnum="2#1">../img/8fb26c3ef85fe5d6ea93a2eef5cf6218.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>