<document id="dd083fdc5a4f9f82597d7b1f46a6c594-2.6" name="Anarky" cat="17">
<text>
Originally, Grant created Anarky as an anarchist with socialist and populist leanings. In this early incarnation, Anarky was designed as an avatar for Grant's personal meditations on political philosophy, and specifically for his burgeoning sympathy for anarchism. However, according to Grant, anarchists with whom he associated were hostile to his creation of the character, seeing it as an act of recuperation for commercial gain.

Within the books, the nature of the character's political opinions were often expressed through the character's rhetoric, and by heavy use of the circle-A as a character gimmick. Other themes were occasionally used whenever Anarky was a featured character in a comic. During the Anarky limited series, fluttering newspapers were used to bear headlines alluding to social problems. Occasionally, the titles of books found in Anarky's room would express the character's philosophical, political, or generally esoteric agenda. In ''Detective Comics'' #620, a copy of ''V For Vendetta'' can be seen on Lonnie Machin's bookshelf as homage. Other books in his room at different times have included ''Apostles of Revolution'' by Max Nomad, ''The Anarchists'' by James Joll, books labeled "''Proudhon''" and "''Bakunin''", and an issue of ''Black Flag''; various books labeled "Plato", "Aristotle", and "Swedenborg"; and ''Synergetics'', by Buckminster Fuller. The character also made references to ''Universe'' by Scudder Klyce, an extremely rare book. When asked if he was concerned readers would be unable to follow some of the more obscure literary references, Grant responded that he didn't expect many to do so, but was "pleased" that some had.

During the early years of the character's development, virtually no writers other than Grant used Anarky in DC publications. In a rare portrayal by an author other than Grant, writer Kevin Dooly used Anarky in an issue of ''Green Arrow'', producing an explicitly anti-firearm themed story.

Over the course of several years, Grant's political opinions shifted from libertarian socialism to free market based philosophies. This could be detected within stories including the Anarky character. In a story that preceded the Anarky series, Anarky's father comments on the political books in the teenager's room, referring to Bakunin, Marx, and Ayn Rand."He's fifteen years old, for pity's sake! Look at these books--!  He should be sneaking copies of ''Playboy'' around, not Bakunin and Marx and Ayn Rand!"  By 1997, Grant's philosophy settled on Neo-Tech, a variant of neo-objectivism, and when given the opportunity to write an ''Anarky'' mini-series, he decided to redesign the character accordingly.

The limited and ongoing series were both heavily influenced by Neo-Tech, despite the term never appearing in a single issue. New emphasis was placed on previously unexplored themes, such as the depiction of Anarky as an atheist and a rationalist. Grant also expressed a desire to use the comic as a vehicle for his thoughts concerning the mind, consciousness, and made bicameralism a major theme of both series.  

In the years following the ''Anarky'' publications of the late 90s, the character and series have garnered praise from reviewers and commentators. Following the cancellation of the ongoing series, Roderick Long, an anarchist/libertarian political commentator and Senior Scholar at the Ludwig von Mises Institute, praised Anarky as "an impressive voice for liberty in today's comics".

With the publication in 2005 of an issue of ''Green Arrow'' in which Anarky guest-starred, writer James Peatty juxtaposed Anarky's radical philosophy with the liberal progressive beliefs of Green Arrow. "Everyone always goes on about what a radical Ollie is and I wanted to show that maybe that isn’t the case ... especially as Ollie’s radical credentials are pretty antiquated ... Anarky as a character &ndash; and as a broader idea &ndash; is much more radical than Ollie ..."

In a review of the ''Anarky'' mini-series, Anarky was dubbed an "anti-villain", as opposed to "anti-hero", due to his highly principled philosophy, which runs counter to most villains. "In the age of the anti-hero, it only makes sense to have the occasional anti-villain as well. But unlike sociopathic vigilante anti-heroes like the Punisher, an anti-villain like Anarky provides some interesting food for thought. Sure, he breaks the law, but what he really wants is to save the world... and maybe he's ''right''."(Original emphasis.) Greg Burga, of ''PopCultureShock.com'', critiqued Anarky as "one of the more interesting characters of the past fifteen or twenty years ... because of what he wants to accomplish". He also analyzed the appeal of the character, considering the philosophy of anarchy "radical and untenable, yet still noble".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7c5a05956831de2c85b0ee3418477f3b" name="Clip_-_Detective_Comics_-620_(August_1990)" sectnum="2.6#1">../img/7c5a05956831de2c85b0ee3418477f3b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>