<document id="dd083fdc5a4f9f82597d7b1f46a6c594-1.2" name="Anarky" cat="17">
<text>
In the years following Anarky's creation, the character was rarely incorporated into Batman stories by Grant, being reserved for stories in which the author felt the need to make a philosophical point. 

Lonnie Machin is introduced as "Anarky" as early as his first appearance in ''Detective Comics'' #608, withholding his origin story for a later point.  He is established as an uncommonly philosophical and intelligent twelve-year-old.  The debut story of the character failed to provide a back story to explain his behavior, but a narrative from Batman reveals that he is a socially conscious and arrogant child who believes he knows how to solve societies' problems.  Convinced that only he can do so, he becomes a vigilante and fashions weapons &ndash; a stun baton and smoke bombs &ndash; in labs at school.  He goes to lengths to disguise his age and appearance by creating a costume with a false head to increase his height.  This was in fact intended as a ruse on the part of writer Alan Grant to disguise the character's true identity, and to confuse the reader into believing Anarky to be Lonnie Machin's father, Mike Machin.

The character made his debut as "Anarky" by responding to complaints in the newspaper and attacking the offending sources, such as the owner of a factory whose byproduct waste is polluting local river water. Anarky and Batman ultimately come to blows, and during their brief fight, Batman deduces that Anarky is actually a young child.  During this first confrontation, he is aided by a band of homeless men, including Legs, a homeless cripple who became loyal to him and would assist him in later appearances.  After being caught, Lonnie is locked away in a juvenile detention center.

Anarky's next appearance came in ''Detective Comics'' #620, approximately a few months after his initial appearance, according to the DC Universe sliding timescale. During his detention, he increases his computer skills to the point of becoming an advanced grey hat computer hacker.  He takes on the online user alias "Moneyspider" to steal millions of dollars from western corporations, including Wayne Enterprises, outmaneuvering Batman's own data security in the process. He then uses the money to create bank accounts for poor farmers in third world countries.  He is caught by Tim Drake in the latter's first solo detective case.

In the following years, Anarky is portrayed as frequently escaping from the center and peregrinating around Gotham City.  At this time Anarky was a lesser known, but established antagonist in the Batman franchise.  However, his back-story had still yet to be elaborated upon.  Grant provided hints to Anarky's origin in ''Robin Annual'' #1, ''The Anarky Ultimatum'', part of ''Eclipso: The Darkness Within'' crossover event.  Within the story it is revealed that Lonnie Machin was a highly intelligent child who from an early age read prodigiously at local bookstores, but had few friends.  It wouldn't be until 1995 that Grant would finally reveal Lonnie Machin's history.

In one of his more notable appearances, during the "Knightfall" saga from ''Shadow of The Bat'' #16–18 , he takes on both Scarecrow and Batman-Azrael.  Grant made use of Anarky at this time to advance a theory influenced by ''Batman: The Dark Knight Returns'', suggesting that Batman indirectly encourages super-villains to come into existence.

In 1995, Grant began the slow increase in Anarky's abilities that would culminate in the ''Anarky'' series.  In the ''Anarky'' story arc from ''Batman: Shadow of the Bat'' #40–41, Lonnie is released from juvenile detention, and builds a machine that allows him to fuse both hemispheres of his brain, giving him increased intelligence, and what he perceives as enlightenment.  Creating an online bookstore, ''Anarco'', to propagate radical literature, he begins to accumulate funds that he donates through another front company, ''The Anarkist Foundation'', to radical organizations, such as eco-warriors and gun protesters, or kept for his own projects.  These story devices served to further improve Anarky's skill set, and increase his intelligence and financial independence.

During the ''Anarky'' storyline, Grant finally revealed Lonnie Machin's origins in full, using a farewell letter to his parents to provide exposition into the character's motivations.

Lonnie Machin is an ordinary child who, while abnormally intelligent, is apolitical and socially unaware.  At eleven he gains a foreign pen pal, Xuasus, as part of a school program.  Every month they would write to each other about their lives; Lonnie about how wonderful the United States is; Xuasus about the poverty and political repression that made up his nation.  After a year of contact, Xuasus stops writing, and all of Lonnie's letters are returned as undeliverable.  A year later Lonnie learns of Xuasus' fate.  He writes Lonnie a final letter explaining that his father has been arrested, his mother has taken ill, his sister has died of malnutrition, and at age eleven, he is homeless and fending for himself.  Driven with worry for his friend, Lonnie fervently learns about Xuasus' country, discovering it to be a Third World dictatorship at war with Marxist guerrillas, with arms dealers from The West making millions in profits from the conflict.

Further studies into war and political violence leads him to hold radical sympathies.  He comes to view all wars as being caused by political elites, with common individuals forced or cajoled into fighting on behalf of the former.  He also began to read more into esoteric studies regarding science and philosophy, laying the groundwork for his advanced intelligence, and leading to his cover as a straight-A student with a normal job as a paper-boy.  Eventually he discovers the extremely rare book, ''Universe'' by Scudder Klyce, which attempted to unify all knowledge.  Within it he finds several passages that convince him of the need to reshape society.  He becomes convinced that if he cannot help Xuasus, he can fight on in his memory and give the oppressed people of Gotham City hope.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="284e10cd107cf5b8f4bdeff1352e8458" name="Detective_Comics_-608_(November_1989)" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/284e10cd107cf5b8f4bdeff1352e8458.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>