<document id="dd44b52e63503b680293577f5f306412-4.9" name="Nancy_Drew" cat="17">
<text>
Rudy Nappi, the artist from 1953 to 1979, illustrates a more average teenager. Nappi was asked by Grosset & Dunlap's art director to update Nancy's appearance, especially her wardrobe. Nappi gave Nancy Peter Pan collars, a flip haircut, and the occasional pair of jeans. Nancy's hair color was changed from blonde to strawberry-blond, reddish-blond or titian by the end of the decade. The change, due to a printing ink error, was considered so favorable that it was adopted in the text.Plunkett-Powell (1993), 48.

In 1962, all Grosset & Dunlap books become "picture covers," books with artwork and advertising printed directly on their covers, as opposed to books with a dust jacket over a tweed volume.  The change was to reduce production costs. Several of the 1930s and 1940s cover illustrations were updated by Rudy Nappi for this change, though the stories themselves were not updated. Internal illustrations, which were dropped in 1937, were returned to the books beginning in 1954, as pen and ink line drawings.

Unlike Tandy, Nappi did not read the books before illustrating them; instead, his wife read them and provided him with a brief plot summary before Nappi began painting.Plunkett-Powell (1993), 49. Nappi's first cover was for ''The Clue of the Velvet Mask'', where he began a trend of portraying Nancy as "bobby-soxer ... a contemporary sixteen-year-old. This Nancy was perky, clean-cut, and extremely animated. In the majority of his covers Nancy looks startled – which, no doubt, she was."Plunkett-Powell (1993), 47.

Earlier Nappi covers show Nancy in poses similar to those in the covers by Tandy and Gillies. Later Nappi covers show only Nancy's head, surrounded by smaller pictures of people and clues from the story. Often, "Nancy's face wears the blank expression of one lost in thought,"Stowe (1999), 35. making her appear passive.Stowe (1999), 36. On the cover of ''The Strange Message in the Parchment'' (1977), for example, in contrast to earlier covers, Nancy "is not shown in the midst of danger or even watching a mystery unfold from a distance. Instead, Nancy is shown thinking about the clues;"Stowe (1999), 33. in general, Nancy becomes less confident and more puzzled.Stowe (1999), 35.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="60c8aeba3d560a82f46ce637b6ac629f" name="Ndtsmitpbkcvr" sectnum="4.9#1">../img/60c8aeba3d560a82f46ce637b6ac629f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>