<document id="dd44b52e63503b680293577f5f306412-4.10" name="Nancy_Drew" cat="17">
<text>
''See also: Girl Detective''


Ruth Sanderson and Paul Frame provided cover art and interior illustrations for the first Nancy Drew paperbacks, published under the Wanderer imprint. Other artists, including Aleta Jenks and others whose names are unknown,Plunkett-Powell (1993), 52. provided cover art, but no interior illustrations, for later paperbacks. Nancy is portrayed as "a wealthy, privileged sleuth who looks pretty and alert.... The colors, and Nancy's facial features, are often so vivid that some of the covers look more like glossy photographs than paintings."Plunkett-Powell (1993), 51.

Nancy is frequently portrayed pursuing a suspect,Stowe (1999), 36. examining a clue, or observing action. She is often also shown in peril:Stowe (1999), 38. being chased, falling off a boat, or hanging by a rope from rafters. These covers are

characterized by frenetic energy on Nancy's part; whether she is falling, limbs flailing, an alarmed look on her face, or whether she is running, hair flying, body bent, face breathless. Nancy does not have any control over the events that are happening in these covers. She is shown to be a victim, being hunted and attacked by unseen foes.Stowe (1999), 40.

Nancy is also sometimes pursued by a visibly threatening foe, as on the cover of ''The Case of the Vanishing Veil'' (1988).

The covers of the Nancy Drew Files and Girl Detective series represent further departures from the bold, confident character portrayed by Tandy. The Nancy portrayed on the covers of the Nancy Drew Files is "a markedly sexy Nancy, with a handsome young man always lurking in the background. Her clothes often reveal an ample bustline and her expression is mischievous."Plunkett-Powell (1993), 51. In the Girl Detective series, Nancy's face is depicted on each cover in fragments. Her eyes, for example, are confined to a strip across the top of the cover while her mouth is located near the spine in a box independent of her eyes. The artwork for Nancy's eyes and mouth is taken from Rudy Nappi's cover art for the revised version of ''The Secret of the Old Clock''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0db3de3bf41c9f8f61d6eec0d07d6f03" name="Ndtcotvv" sectnum="4.10#1">../img/0db3de3bf41c9f8f61d6eec0d07d6f03.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>