<document id="dd44b52e63503b680293577f5f306412-3.5" name="Nancy_Drew" cat="17">
<text>
After Harriet Adams died in 1982, her protegé, Nancy Axelrad, oversaw production of the Nancy Drew books briefly before the Stratemeyer Syndicate was sold to Simon and Schuster. Simon and Schuster turned to book packager Mega-Books for new writers.Plunkett-Powell (1993), 29. The books and Nancy's character began to change as a result, although there is disagreement on the nature of this change. Some contend that Nancy's character becomes "more like Mildred Wirt Benson's original heroine than any  since 1956."Caprio (1992), 27. Others criticize the series for its increasing incorporation of romance and " of pre-feminist moxie."Torrance (2007), D01. For example, volume 78 in the series ''The Phantom of Venice'' (1985) opens with Nancy wondering in italics, "''Am I or am I not in love with Ned Nickerson?''"Keene (1985), 1. Nancy begins dating other young men and acknowledges sexual desires: "'I saw  ... You don't have to apologize to me if some guy turns you on.' 'Gianni ''doesn't'' turn me on! ... Won't you please let me explain.'"Keene (1985), 111-112. Cited by Shangraw Fox.

In 1986, the character of Nancy Drew was used in a new series, the Nancy Drew Files, which lasted until 1997. The Nancy of the Nancy Drew Files is also interested in romance and boys, a fact which led to much criticism of the series: "Millie  purists tend to look askance upon the Files series, in which  fleeting pecks bestowed on Nancy by her longtime steady, Ned Nickerson, give  way to lingering embraces in a Jacuzzi."Leigh Brown (1993), 1D. Cover art for Files titles, such as ''Hit and Run Holiday'' (1986), reflects these changes; Nancy is often dressed provocatively, in short skirts, shirts that reveal her stomach or breasts, or a bathing suit. She is always pictured with an attentive, handsome male in the background, and frequently appears aware of and interested in that male. Nancy also becomes more vulnerable, being often chloroformed into unconsciousness, or defenseless against chokeholds. The books place more emphasis on violence and character relationships.Foster (1986), 31.

Nancy Drew finally went to college in the Nancy Drew On Campus series, which ran from 1995 to 1998. Again, the books focused on romance plots, and, by reader request, Nancy broke off her long-term relationship with boyfriend Ned Nickerson in the second volume of the series, ''On Her Own'' (1995).Drew (1997), 185.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0c8ad3d30b8d007a89d967417b0520b4" name="Ndharh" sectnum="3.5#1">../img/0c8ad3d30b8d007a89d967417b0520b4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>