<document id="dd6c16e8bec53cbf20f35661f2f2ed68-3.5" name="Krazy_Kat" cat="17">
<text>
The comic strip was animated several times.  The earliest ''Krazy Kat'' shorts were produced by William Randolph Hearst in 1916. They were produced under Hearst-Vitagraph News Pictorial and later the International Film Service (IFS), though Herriman was not involved. In 1920, after a two-year hiatus, the John R. Bray studio began producing a series of ''Krazy Kat'' shorts.Crafton.

In 1925, animation pioneer Bill Nolan decided to bring Krazy to the screen again.  Nolan intended to produce the series under Associated Animators, but when it dissolved, he sought distribution from Margaret J. Winkler. Unlike earlier adaptations, Nolan did not base his shorts on the characters and setting of the Herriman comic strip. Instead, the feline in Nolan's cartoons was an explicitly male cat whose design and personality both reflected Felix the Cat.  This is probably due to the fact that Nolan himself was a former employee of the Pat Sullivan studio.Maltin 205–06.

Winkler's husband, Charles B. Mintz, slowly began assuming control of the operation. Mintz and his studio began producing the cartoons in sound beginning with 1929's ''Ratskin.'' In 1930, he moved the staff to California and ultimately changed the design of Krazy Kat. The new character bore even less resemblance to the one in the newspapers. Mintz's Krazy Kat was, like many other early 1930s cartoon characters, imitative of Mickey Mouse, and usually engaged in slapstick comic adventures with his look-alike girlfriend and loyal pet dog.Maltin 207. In 1936, animator Isadore Klein, with the blessing of Mintz, set to work creating the short, ''Lil' Ainjil'', the only Mintz work that was intended to reflect Herriman's comic strip. However, Klein was "terribly disappointed" with the resulting cartoon, and the Mickey-derivative Krazy returned.Maltin 210–11.  In 1939, Mintz became indebted to his distributor, Columbia Pictures, and subsequently sold his studio to them.Maltin 213.  Under the name Screen Gems, the studio produced only one more Krazy Kat cartoon, ''The Mouse Exterminator'' in 1940., The Columbia Crow's Nest — Columbia Cartoon History.

Gene Deitch's Rembrandt Films in Prague, Czechoslovakia (now the Czech Republic) produced ''Krazy Kat'' cartoons for King Features from 1962 to 1964, helping to introduce Herriman's cat to the baby boom generation. The Deitch shorts were made for television and have a closer connection to the comic strip; the backgrounds are drawn in a similar style, and Ignatz and Officer Pupp are both present. However, this incarnation of Krazy was made explicitly female. Penny Phillips voiced Krazy while Paul Frees voiced Ignatz and Offisa Pupp. Jerky animation and poorly-synchronized voices are common in these ''Krazy Kat'' shorts. Jay Livingston and Ray Evans did the music for most of the episodes.  Most of the episodes are available on DVD.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7209de6111a484473e53968537f8af62" name="mintz-krazy" sectnum="3.5#1">../img/7209de6111a484473e53968537f8af62.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>