<document id="ddf73c493765ae8142f29dc57711f18c-1.1" name="Kit_(association_football)" cat="26">
<text>
The Laws of the Game set out the basic equipment which must be worn by all players in Law 4: The Players' Equipment.  Five separate items are specified: shirt (also known as a jersey), shorts, socks (also known as stockings), footwear and shin pads.  Goalkeepers are allowed to wear tracksuit bottoms instead of shorts.  While most players wear studded football boots ("soccer shoes"



 or "cleats" in U.S. English), the Laws do not specify that these are required.  Shirts must have sleeves (both short and long sleeves are accepted), and goalkeepers must wear shirts which are easily distinguishable from all other players and the match officials.  Thermal undershorts may be worn, but must be the same colour as the shorts themselves.  Shin pads must be covered entirely by the stockings, be made of rubber, plastic or a similar material, and "provide a reasonable degree of protection".  The only other restriction on equipment defined in the Laws of the Game is the requirement that a player "must not use equipment or wear anything that is dangerous to himself or another player".  

It is normal for individual competitions to specify that all outfield players on a team must wear the same colours, though the Law states only "The two teams must wear colours that distinguish them from each other and also the referee and the assistant referees". In the event of a match between teams who would normally wear identical or similar colours the away team must change to a different colour.  Because of this requirement a team's second-choice is often referred to as its "away kit" or "away colours", although it is not unknown, especially at international level, for teams to opt to wear their away colours even when not required to by a clash of colours, or to wear them at home.  The England national team sometimes plays in red shirts even when it is not required, as this was the strip worn when the team won the 1966 FIFA World Cup.  Many professional clubs also have a "third kit", ostensibly to be used if both their first-choice and away colours are deemed too similar to those of an opponent.  Most professional clubs have retained the same basic colour scheme for several decades, and the colours themselves form an integral part of a club's culture.  Teams representing countries in international competition generally wear national colours in common with other sporting teams of the same nation.  These are usually based on the colours of the country's national flag, although there are exceptions—the Italian national team, for example, wear blue as it was the colour of the House of Savoy.


Shirts are normally made of a polyester mesh, which does not trap the sweat and body heat in the same way as a shirt made of a natural fibre.  Most professional clubs have sponsors' logos on the front of their shirts, which can generate significant levels of income, and some also offer sponsors the chance to place their logos on the back of their shirts.  Depending on local rules, there may be restrictions on how large these logos may be or on what logos may be displayed. Competitions such as the Premier League may also require players to wear patches on their sleeves depicting the logo of the competition.  A player's number is usually printed on the back of the shirt, although international teams often also place numbers on the front, and professional teams generally print a player's surname above his number.  The captain of each team is usually required to wear an elasticated armband around the left sleeve in order to identify him as the captain to the referee and supporters.


Most current players wear specialist football boots, which can be made either of leather or a synthetic material. Modern boots are cut slightly below the ankles, as opposed to the high-ankled boots used in former times, and have studs attached to the soles. Studs may be either moulded directly to the sole or be detachable, normally by means of a screw thread.  Modern boots such as the Adidas Predator, originally designed by former Liverpool player Craig Johnston, feature increasingly intricate, scientifically aided designs and features such as air pockets in the soles and rubber "blades" on the sole rather than studs.  The blades have been the subject of controversy as several top managers have blamed them for injuries both to opposition players and to the wearers themselves.  Some players choose to deliberately wear boots which are slightly too small for them, as they feel this increases their ability to control the ball. However, this too has been blamed for injuries suffered by players.


The Laws of the Game specify that all players, regardless of gender, must wear the same kit, however in September 2008 the Dutch women's team FC de Rakt made international headlines by swapping its old strip for a new one featuring short skirts and tight-fitting shirts.  This innovation, which had been requested by the team itself, was initially vetoed by the KNVB, Dutch football's governing body, but this decision was reversed when it was revealed that the FC de Rakt team were wearing hot pants under their skirts, and were therefore technically in compliance.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="95270b04dc77f41f63ab9af1cea42717" name="Nike_Zoom_Air_Football_Boots_2" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/95270b04dc77f41f63ab9af1cea42717.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>