<document id="ddf854dc2ffaa52126beecfe6e573986-7" name="Oldham" cat="11">
<text>
The geography of Oldham constrained the development of major transport infrastructure. It has been put that "if it had not grown substantially before the railway age it would surely have been overlooked". Oldham has never been on a main line railway route, and canals too have only been able to serve it from a distance, meaning that "Oldham has never had a train service worthy of a town of its size".

A principal destination along the former Oldham Loop Line, Oldham once had seven railway stations but this was reduced to four once Clegg Street, Oldham Central and Glodwick Road closed in the mid-20th century; Oldham Werneth, Oldham Mumps, Derker and Hollinwood closed on 3 October 2009. Trains from Manchester Victoria station to Oldham had to climb steeply through much of its  route, from around  at Manchester city centre to around  at Oldham Mumps. The stretch near Werneth, with its gradient of 1 in 27, made the Oldham Loop the steepest regular passenger line in the country. Oldham Mumps, what was the oldest station on the line, took its name from the locality of Mumps area of Oldham, which itself probably derived from the archaic word "mumper" which was slang for a beggar. The former Oldham Loop Line is to be converted for use with an expanded Manchester Metrolink tram network, planned to open in 2012. 

Oldham had electric tramways to Manchester in the early-20th century; the first tram was driven from Manchester into Oldham in 1900 by the Lord Mayor of Manchester. The system came to an end on 3 August 1946, however.
The £3.3m Oldham Bus Station has frequent bus services to Manchester, Rochdale, Ashton-under-Lyne and Middleton with other services to the Metropolitan Borough of Oldham, Tameside, and across the Pennines to Huddersfield in West Yorkshire. The roof canopy is supported internally on two rows of steel trees. The extensive use of glass and stainless steel maximises visibility, and there is a carefully co-ordinated family of information fittings, posters and seating, using robust natural materials for floors and plinths. The bus station is used by National Express coaches. First Manchester, FirstGroup plc's bus operator for north-Greater Manchester, has its headquarters in Oldham.

Oldham is about  south of the major M62 motorway, but is linked to it by the M60 at Hollinwood, and A627(M) via Chadderton. There are major A roads to Ashton-under-Lyne, Huddersfield, Manchester, and Rochdale.

The Hollinwood Branch of the Ashton Canal was a canal that ran from Fairfield in Droylsden, through Littlemoss and Daisy Nook Country Park to the Hollinwood area of Oldham, with a branch from Daisy Nook to the Fairbottom Branch Canal. The canal was mainly used for the haulage of coal until it fell into disuse for commercial traffic in the 1930s. It included four aqueducts and a two-rise lock staircase.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="816eb9bdc9e63ec4025fd48a92f3f3b4" name="Bus_in_Oldham" sectnum="7#1">../img/816eb9bdc9e63ec4025fd48a92f3f3b4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>