<document id="de6ae888618d868f1a7e2c181a93f6e0-1.2" name="Nine_Inch_Nails_live_performances" cat="20">
<text>
After the 1994 release of ''The Downward Spiral'', the live band embarked on the Self-Destruct tour in support of the album.  Vrenna and Woolley returned on drums and keyboards respectively. Robin Finck replaced Patrick on guitar, while bassist Danny Lohner was added to the line-up. The tour included a mud-drenched performance at Woodstock '94, which was broadcast on Pay-per-view and seen in as many as 24 million homes. Nine Inch Nails received considerable mainstream success thereafter, performing with significantly higher production values and the addition of various theatrical visual elements. The band's performance of "Happiness in Slavery" from the Woodstock concert earned the group a Grammy Award for Best Metal Performance in 1995. ''Entertainment Weekly'' described the band's Woodstock '94 performance by saying "Reznor unstrings rock to its horrifying, melodramatic core--an experience as draining as it is exhilarating".  ''New Musical Express'' had a similar sentiment after the band's Lollapalooza performance in 1991, describing the show as "genuinely frightening", and asking the reader to "decide for yourself if it's choreographed chaos or unbridled grievous bodily harm".  


The main leg of the tour featured Marilyn Manson as the supporting act, who Reznor had recently signed to his Nothing Records label. At the time, Marilyn Manson featured bassist Jeordie White (then playing under the pseudonym "Twiggy Ramirez"), who would later play bass with Nine Inch Nails from 2005 to 2007.  After another tour leg supporting the remix album ''Further Down the Spiral'', Nine Inch Nails contributed to the Alternative Nation Festival in Australia.  Following the three-date alternative music festival, Nine Inch Nails embarked on the Dissonance Tour, which included 26 separate performances with co-headliner David Bowie.  This tour observed a format placing Nine Inch Nails as the opening act, transitioning into Bowie's set with joint performances of both bands' songs.  However, the crowds reportedly did not respond positively to the combination.

The tour concluded with a three-night Nothing Records showcase called Nights of Nothing which included performances from Nothing bands Marilyn Manson, Prick, Meat Beat Manifesto, and Pop Will Eat Itself, and concluded with an 80-minute set from Nine Inch Nails.  ''Kerrang!'' described the Nine Inch Nails set during the Nights of Nothing showcase as "tight, brash and dramatic", but was disappointed at the lack of new material.  On the second of the three nights, Richard Patrick was briefly reunited with the band, as he contributed guitar to a performance of "Head Like a Hole".  After the Self-Destruct tour, Chris Vrenna, member of the live band since 1988 and frequent contributor to Nine Inch Nails studio recordings, left the band permanently to pursue a career in producing and to form the band Tweaker.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="480f3fc92cdc9b7ad39f64acca4cb6d9" name="Trent_Reznor_Self-Destruct" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/480f3fc92cdc9b7ad39f64acca4cb6d9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>