<document id="de6ae888618d868f1a7e2c181a93f6e0-1.5" name="Nine_Inch_Nails_live_performances" cat="20">
<text>
Having taken a break from touring to complete work on ''Year Zero'', Nine Inch Nails began a world tour in 2007, including their first ever performance in China.  Reznor continued to tour with the same band he concluded the Live: With Teeth tour, which was composed of North, White, Freese, and Cortini. Supporting acts included Ladytron, Unkle, The Dandy Warhols, Alec Empire, and Serena Maneesh.


The ''Year Zero'' project included an alternate reality game of the same name, with much of the game revolving around various live shows.  
During a Nine Inch Nails concert in Lisbon, Portugal, a USB flash drive was found in a bathroom stall containing a high-quality MP3 of the track "My Violent Heart", a song from the then-unreleased album.  A second USB drive was found after a concert in Barcelona, containing the track "Me, I'm Not". Following the release of ''Year Zero'' the focus of the tour shifted towards debuting and promoting tracks from the new album. While some of these songs were performed by all 5 band members as conventional guitar-driven rock songs, two of them (''Me, I'm Not'' and ''The Great Destroyer'') were played by Reznor, guitarist North and keyboard player Cortini as a 3 piece, using a combination of live guitars and pre-programmed samples triggered onstage with computers and manipulated in real time using Ableton software.

In April 2007, Nine Inch Nails fans received in-game telephone-calls in which they were invited to a "resistance meeting" in Los Angeles.  At the meeting, fans attended a fictional Art is Resistance meeting, and were later rewarded by an unannounced performance by Nine Inch Nails.  The concert was cut short as the meeting was raided by a fictional SWAT team and the audience was rushed out of the building.

Later that year, the ''Honolulu Star-Bulletin'' reported that the September 18 show in Honolulu would be the last performance of the current incarnation of the Nine Inch Nails live band. Reznor told the newspaper "at this point, I want to switch things around a bit.  Nine Inch Nails as a rock band configuration, we've done it and we've done it again.  I see other ways I can present the material in concert, more challenging, something new.  I don't want it to go stale".  In the same article, Reznor also admitted that "the idea of five guys playing loud music  two hours ... has got to change once finances come into play, especially performing in markets outside of the mainland U.S. I want to whittle things down".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="53fb1b6fbb28ef48a89882868e590842" name="NIN_Munich_2007" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/53fb1b6fbb28ef48a89882868e590842.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>