<document id="de7489c6644fe51f739521e2f28ddb53-4.1" name="Elizabeth_Bowes-Lyon" cat="25">
<text>
In summer 1938, the French press praised the demeanour and charm of the royal couple during a succesful State Visit to France, augmented by an 'all white trousseau' created by Norman Hartnell for the Queen. In June 1939, Elizabeth's husband became the first reigning King to tour Canada, as well as the United States. According to the official Royal Tour historian Gustave Lanctot, George VI was to be present in Canada as a living example of Canada's status as an independent kingdom. During the tour of the United States, the King and Queen were accompanied by Canadian Prime Minister Mackenzie King, as the sole Minister in Attendance, rather than by a British minister, by way of reinforcing that their visit to the United States was a visit from Canada.

The extensive tour took them across Canada from coast to coast and back, with a brief detour into the United States, where they visited the Roosevelts in the White House and at their Hudson Valley estate. According to an often-told story, during one of the earliest of the royal couple's repeated encounters with the crowds,  a Second Boer War veteran asked Elizabeth, "Are you Scots or are you English?" She replied, "I am a Canadian!"Speech delivered by Her Majesty the Queen at the Fairmont Hotel, Vancouver, Monday, 7 October 2002 as reported in e.g. Joyce, Greg (8 October 2002) "Queen plays tribute to Canada, thanks citizens for their support", The Canadian Press Their reception by the Canadian and U.S. public was extremely enthusiastic,Vickers, p. 187 and dissipated in large measure any residual feeling that George and Elizabeth were in any way a lesser substitute for Edward. Elizabeth told Prime Minister Mackenzie King, "that tour made us",Bradford, p.281 and she returned to Canada frequently both on official tours and privately.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c1c52cc315f1939f752c659b8d174daf" name="H.R.H._King_George_VI_and_Queen_Elizabeth_visit_the_Canadian_Pavilion_at_the_World's_Fair" sectnum="4.1#1">../img/c1c52cc315f1939f752c659b8d174daf.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>