<document id="de8dbff8cde950770af850c8e547de69-6" name="The_Turk" cat="26">
<text>
Upon the return of the ship on which Mälzel died, his various machines, including the Turk, fell into the hands of a friend of Mälzel's, the businessman John Ohl. He attempted to auction off the Turk, but owing to low bidding ultimately bought it himself for $400.Levitt, 92–93. Only when Dr. John Kearsley Mitchell from Philadelphia, Edgar Allan Poe's personal physician and an admirer of the Turk, approached Ohl did the Turk change hands again. Mitchell formed a restoration club and went about the business of repairing the Turk for public appearances, completing the restoration in 1840.Levitt, 94–95.

As interest in the Turk outgrew its location, Mitchell and his club chose to donate the machine to the Chinese Museum of Charles Willson Peale. While the Turk still occasionally gave performances, it was eventually relegated to the corners of the museum and forgotten about until 5 July 1854, when a fire that started at the National Theater in Philadelphia reached the Museum and destroyed the Turk.Levitt, 97. Mitchell believed he had heard "through the struggling flames . . . the last words of our departed friend, the sternly whispered, oft repeated syllables, 'echec! echec!!'"Silas Weir Mitchell, "The Last of a Veteran Chess Player," ''The Chess Monthly,'' January 1857; reprinted in Levitt's ''The Turk, Chess Automaton.''

John Gaughan, an American manufacturer of equipment for magicians based in Los Angeles, spent $US120,000 building his own version of Kempelen's machine over a five-year period from 1984.Levitt, 243. The machine uses the original chessboard, which was stored separately from the original Turk and was not destroyed in the fire. The first public display of Gaughan's Turk was in November 1989 at a history of magic conference. The machine is presented much as Kempelen presented the original, except that it is now controlled by a computer.Standage, 216–217.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6f86edc8a3ca110e85b14c54f1e249c2" name="TurkSColes" sectnum="6#1">../img/6f86edc8a3ca110e85b14c54f1e249c2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>