<document id="def357c70d76966825a022775fc2ae6d-2.3" name="Australian_Defence_Force" cat="29">
<text>
Australia has maintained military forces since federation as a nation in January 1901. Upon Federation, the Australian Government established the Australian Army and Commonwealth Naval Force. In 1909, the Government established the Royal Australian Navy, which absorbed the Commonwealth Naval Force. The Army established the Australian Flying Corps in 1912 although this separated to form the Royal Australian Air Force in 1921. The services were not linked by a single chain of command, as they each reported to their own separate Minister and had separate administrative arrangements. The three services saw action around the world during World War I and World War II.

The importance of 'joint' warfare was made clear to the Australian Military during World War II when Australian naval, ground and air units frequently served as part of single commands. Following the war, several senior officers lobbied for the appointment of a commander in chief of the three services. The government rejected this proposal and the three services remained fully independent. Horner (2001). Page 42. The absence of a central authority resulted in poor coordination between the services with each service organising and operating on the basis of a different military doctrine.Horner (2001). Page 44.

The need for an integrated command structured received more emphasis during the Australian military's experiences in the Vietnam War. In 1973, the Secretary of the Department of Defence, Arthur Tange, submitted a report to the Government that recommended the unification of the separate departments supporting each service into a single Department of Defence and the creation of the post of Chief of the Defence Force Staff. The government accepted these recommendations and the Australian Defence Force was established on 9 February 1976.Horner (2001). Page 47.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4820b63755117ed503679dafac5b1d26" name="Melbourne_Midway_small" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/4820b63755117ed503679dafac5b1d26.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>