<document id="def357c70d76966825a022775fc2ae6d-4" name="Australian_Defence_Force" cat="29">
<text>
The Australian Defence Force's logistics are managed by the Defence Material Organisation and the Joint Logistics Command. The DMO was created in 2000 by merging the ADF's Support Command Australia with the Department of Defence's Defence Acquisition Organisation and National Support Division.Horner (2001). Page 278–279. The DMO purchases all forms of equipment and services used by the ADF and is also responsible for maintaining this equipment throughout its life of type. 

The DMO is not responsible for directly supplying deployed ADF units; this is the responsibility of the Joint Logistics Command and the single service logistic units.Defence Directory  Joint Logistics Command. Accessed 7 November 2007. These units include the Navy's Systems Command and replenishment ships, the Army's 17th Combat Service Support Brigade and Combat Service Support Battalions, and the RAAF's Combat Support Group.Horner (2001). Page 273. 

The increasing role of the private sector forms an important trend in the ADF's logistics arrangements. During the 1990s many of the ADF's support functions were transferred to the private sector to improve the efficiency with which they were provided. Since these reforms most of the 'garrison' support services at military bases have been provided by private firms. The reforms also led to many of the ADF's logistics units being disbanded or reduced in size.Horner (2001). Pages 265–279. 

Private firms have increasingly been contracted to provide critical support to ADF units deployed outside Australia. This support has included transporting equipment and personnel and constructing and supplying bases.Mark Thomson (2005). . Australian Strategic Policy Institute, Canberra. Pages 30–32. The ADF's use of contractors to support military operations is not as extensive as that of the United States and British militaries, however, and there may be scope for further 'outsourcing'.Thomson (2005). Pages 33–34.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bb90607f8debcebd36c0bb8249858edb" name="RAAF_S76a_SAR" sectnum="4#1">../img/bb90607f8debcebd36c0bb8249858edb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>