<document id="def357c70d76966825a022775fc2ae6d-5" name="Australian_Defence_Force" cat="29">
<text>
The Australian Defence Force's intelligence collection and analysis capabilities include each of the services' intelligence systems and units, two joint civilian-military intelligence gathering agencies and two strategic and operational-level intelligence analysis organisations.

Each of the three services has its own intelligence assets.Horner (2001). Page 150. RAN doctrine states that "all maritime units" contribute to the collection of intelligence and many of the RAN's ships are capable of collecting communications and electronic transmissions. The Collins class submarines are particularly effective in this role.Sea Power Centre - Australia (2005). Page 56. The Army's intelligence units include the 1st Intelligence Battalion, 7th Signals Regiment (Electronic Warfare), three Regional Force Surveillance Units and the Special Air Service Regiment.Australian Department of Defence (2006). . Accessed 6 May 2007. The RAAF's intelligence assets include the Jindalee Operational Radar Network and other air defence radars, AP-3 Orion and RF-111 aircraft and No. 87 Squadron.

The Defence Intelligence and Security Group within the Department of Defence supports the services. This Group consists of the Defence Imagery and Geospatial Organisation (DIGO), Defence Signals Directorate (DSD) and Defence Intelligence Organisation (DIO). The DIGO is responsible for geospatial intelligence and producing maps for the ADF, the DSD is Australia's signals intelligence agency and the DIO is responsible for the analysis of intelligence collected by the other intelligence agencies.Australian Government (2006) . The DIO and the Joint Operations Intelligence Centre within Headquarters Joint Operations Command are responsible for analysing the information collected and disseminating this analysis to the relevant sections of the ADF and the Australian Government.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="08bf85ac5362fa3dd8dd1f7d6a640489" name="RAAF_radar" sectnum="5#1">../img/08bf85ac5362fa3dd8dd1f7d6a640489.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>