<document id="def357c70d76966825a022775fc2ae6d-2.4" name="Australian_Defence_Force" cat="29">
<text>
Until the 1970s, Australia's military strategy centred on the concept of 'forward defence', in which the role of the Australian military was to cooperate with Allied forces to counter threats in Australia's region. In 1969, when the United States began the Guam Doctrine and the British withdrew 'east of Suez', Australia developed a defence policy emphasising self-reliance of the Australian continent. This policy was the Defence of Australia (DOA) Policy. Under DOA, the focus of Australian defence planning was to protect Australia's northern maritime approaches (the 'air-sea gap') against enemy attack.Tewes, Rayner and Kavanaugh (2004). In line with this goal, the ADF was restructured to increase its ability to strike at enemy forces from Australian bases and to counter raids on continental Australia. The ADF achieved this by increasing the capabilities of the RAN and RAAF and relocating regular Army units to northern Australia.Horner (2001). Page 72.

At this time, the ADF had no military units on operational deployment outside Australia. In 1987, the ADF made its first operational deployment as part of Operation Morris Dance, in which several warships and a rifle company deployed to the waters off Fiji in response to the 1987 Fijian coups d'état. While broadly successful, this deployment highlighted the need for the ADF to improve its capability to rapidly respond to unforeseen events.Horner (2001). Pages 225–227. 

Since the late 1980s, the Government has increasingly called upon the ADF to contribute forces to peacekeeping missions around the world. While most of these deployments involved only small numbers of specialists, several led to the deployment of hundreds of personnel. Large peacekeeping deployments were made to Namibia in early 1989, Cambodia between 1992 and 1993, Somalia in 1993, Rwanda between 1994 and 1995 and Bougainville in 1994 and from 1997 onwards.Horner (2001). Pages 228–255. 

The Australian contribution to the 1991 Gulf War was the first time Australian personnel were deployed to an active war zone since the establishment of the ADF. Although the warships and clearance diving team deployed to the Persian Gulf did not see combat, the deployment tested the ADF's capabilities and command structure. Following the war the Navy regularly deployed a frigate to the Persian Gulf or Red Sea to enforce the trade sanctions imposed on Iraq.Horner (2001). Pages 231–237.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="321c3fa8fd0cabb8d9b715a4e3f13846" name="Kangaroo_89" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/321c3fa8fd0cabb8d9b715a4e3f13846.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>