<document id="def357c70d76966825a022775fc2ae6d-2.5" name="Australian_Defence_Force" cat="29">
<text>
In 1996, John Howard led the Liberal Party's election campaign and became Prime Minister. Subsequently, there were significant reforms to the ADF's force structure and role. The new government's defence strategy placed less emphasis on defending Australia from direct attack and greater emphasis on working in cooperation with regional states and Australia's allies to manage potential security threats.Australian Army (2008). Page 81. In line with this new focus, the ADF's force structure changed in an attempt to increase the proportion of combat units to support units and to improve the ADF's combat effectiveness.

The ADF's experiences during the deployment to East Timor in 1999 led to significant changes in Australia's defence policies and to an enhancement of the ADF's ability to conduct operations outside Australia. This successful deployment was the first time a large Australian military force had operated outside of Australia since the Vietnam War and revealed shortcomings in the ADF's ability to mount and sustain such operations.. See also Australian National Audit Office (2002). . ANAO, Canberra. 

In 2000, the Government released a new Defence White Paper, ''Defence 2000 - Our Future Defence Force'' that placed a greater emphasis on preparing the ADF for overseas deployments. The Government committed to improve the ADF's capabilities by improving the readiness and equipment of ADF units, expanding the ADF and increasing real Defence expenditure by 3% per year.Thomson (2005b). Page 11. In 2003 and 2005, the ''Defence Updates'' emphasised this focus on expeditionary operations and the result has been an expansion and modernisation of the ADF.Thomson (2006a). Pages 7–8.

Since 2000, the ADF's expanded force structure and deployment capabilities have been put to the test on a number of occasions. Following the September 11, 2001 terrorist attacks on the United States, Australia committed a special forces task group and an air-to-air refuelling aircraft to operations in Afghanistan, and naval warships to the Persian Gulf as Operation Slipper. In 2003, approximately 2000 ADF personnel, including a special forces task group, three warships and 14 F/A-18 Hornet aircraft, took part in the invasion of Iraq. 

Later in 2003, elements of all three services deployed to the Solomon Islands as part of the Regional Assistance Mission to the Solomon Islands. In late 2004, over 1000 ADF personnel deployed to Indonesia in Operation Sumatra Assist following the 2004 Indian Ocean earthquake.Australian Minister for Defence media release . 24 March 2005. In May 2006, approximately 2000 ADF personnel deployed to East Timor in Operation Astute following unrest between elements of the Timor Leste Defence Force.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e363a12eb31b183853bb204e5dfb6e4e" name="RAAF_C-130_Iraq_2008" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/e363a12eb31b183853bb204e5dfb6e4e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>