<document id="df376caf7432a13d6d49e0641463dfcc-2" name="History_of_Norwich_City_F.C." cat="26">
<text>
The 1930s began with a brush with disaster &ndash; the side finished bottom of the League in 1931, but were successful in their bid for re-election. The rest of the decade proved more successful for Norwich, with a club-record victory, 10&ndash;2,Canary Citizens, p265. On 15 March 1930, Thomas Hunt (footballer) scored five goals. The half-time score was 4&ndash;0; the 8,230 supporters saw eight second-half goals over Coventry City and promotion to the Second Division as champions in the 1933&ndash;34 season under the management of Tom Parker.  

With rising crowds and the Football Association raising concerns over the suitability of The Nest, the club considered renovation, but ultimately decided on a move to Carrow Road.  The original stadium was terraced on three sides, with only one stand (along Carrow Road) having wooden bench seating and a roof. The inaugural match at the new ground, held on 31 August 1935, against West Ham United, ended in a 4&ndash;3 victory for the home team and set a new record attendance of 29,779.  A highlight of the fourth season at Carrow Road was the visit of King George VI on 29 October 1938; this was the first occasion a reigning monarch attended a second tier football match.  The club was relegated back to the Third Division at the end of the season. Norwich's anguish was exacerbated by the closeness of the relegation fight; having finished second from bottom of Division Two, they were demoted on a goal average difference of just 0.05.

The league was suspended the following season as a result of the outbreak of the Second World War, and professional play did not resume until the 1946&ndash;47 season.  City finished this and the following season in 21st place, the poor results forcing the club to apply for re-election to the league. The lacklustre performances did not deter the crowds, and, in 1948, Carrow Road attracted its record attendance; 37,863 spectators watched City play Notts County.  The club narrowly missed out on promotion under the guidance of manager Norman Low in the early 1950s, but following the return of Tom Parker as manager, Norwich finished bottom of the football league in the 1956&ndash;57 season. Events off the field were to overshadow the team's performances as the club faced financial difficulties severe enough to render them non-viable. With debts amounting to more than £20,000, the club was rescued by the formation of a new Board, chaired by Geoffrey Watling and the creation of an appeal fund chaired by the Lord Mayor of Norwich, Arthur South, which raised more than £20,000. For these and other services to the club, both men (now deceased) were later honoured by having stands named after them at Carrow Road.The South Stand was, however, recently renamed the Jarrold Stand. See Carrow Road#Stands

Archie Macaulay became manager when the club was reformed and he oversaw one of the club's greatest achievements, its run to the semi-final of the 1958&ndash;59 FA Cup. Competing as a Third Division side, Norwich defeated two First Division opponents along the way, notably a 3&ndash;0 win against the Manchester United "Busby Babes". City lost the semi-final only after a replay against another First Division side, Luton Town. The team of 1958-59—including Terry Bly who scored seven goals in the run, and Ken Nethercott who played most of the second half of one match in goal despite a dislocated shoulder—is today well-represented in the club Hall of Fame. The "59 Cup Run" as it is now known locally, "remains as one of the truly great periods in Norwich City's history". Norwich were the third-ever Third Division team to reach the FA Cup semi-final.  In the 1959&ndash;60 season, Norwich were promoted to the Second Division after finishing second to Southampton, and achieved a fourth place finish in the 1960&ndash;61 season. From 1960, Norwich spent the next 12 seasons in the second tier, with finishes of fourth in 1961 and sixth in 1965 being among the most notable.

In 1962, Ron Ashman guided  Norwich to their first trophy, defeating Rochdale 4&ndash;0 on aggregate in a two-legged final to win the League Cup.  Norwich finally achieved promotion from Division Two when they finished as champions in the 1971&ndash;72 season under manager Ron Saunders; Norwich City had reached the highest level of English football for the first time.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="23567bad53b606f6216197588228054d" name="Under21june07" sectnum="2#1">../img/23567bad53b606f6216197588228054d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>