<document id="df376caf7432a13d6d49e0641463dfcc-1" name="History_of_Norwich_City_F.C." cat="26">
<text>
Norwich City F.C. was formed following a meeting at the Criterion Cafe in Norwich on 17 June 1902 by a group of friends led by two former Norwich CEYMS players, Norwich City FC and played their first competitive match against Harwich & Parkeston, at Newmarket Road on 6 September 1902.
  Originally, the club was nicknamed the ''Citizens'', and played in light blue and white halved shirts. The popular pastime of canary rearing had given rise to the team's nickname of "The Canaries" by April 1905, and by February 1907 this moniker had been adopted by the national press. The following season, inspired by the nickname, City played for the first time in Canary livery; yellow shirts with green collars and cuffs. A local paper reported that "The Cits are dead but the Canaries are very much alive".

Norwich played for just over two seasons as an amateur club under the Football Association (FA). However, following an FA Commission of inquiry, the club was informed on the last day of 1904 that they had been deemed a professional organisation and hence ineligible to compete in amateur football. The main allegations were:  
fees ... paid for the use of a gymnasium and also for the training and massage of players. The sum of £8 was also paid to a player when he left the club. Payments were made to players without a receipt being taken. The club advertised for players ...  secretary ... spent considerable sums of money in travelling to other towns in East Anglia ... complete outfits ... were bought for players out of club funds ... there was no adequate system for checking gate money ... travelling expenses were ... excessive.
 The club officials, including founding chairman Robert Webster, had to be removed from office and Norwich were to be ousted from the amateur game at the end of the season. The response was swift: at a meeting, just two days later, Wilfrid Lawson Burgess became the first chairman of the professional club and it was resolved to find a place in the professional game. The decision was endorsed at a public meeting in March 1905, a meeting that, significantly, was attended by Nat Whitaker, secretary of the Southern League. He seconded a motion proposed by a local businessman that endorsed the club's "... determination to run a first class professional team". Whitaker actively supported Norwich, as he wanted the League's influence to spread eastwards. On 30 May 1905, they were elected to play in the Southern League, in place of Wellingborough.

With increasing attendances at matches and strict new clauses included in a proposed lease extension, Norwich were forced to leave Newmarket Road and move to a converted disused chalk pit in Rosary Road which became known as "The Nest". Works at The Nest, which included dismantling and moving the stands from Newmarket Road, were complete in time for the start of the 1908&ndash;09 season.  On 10 December 1917, with football suspended during the First World War and the club facing spiralling debts, City went into voluntary liquidation.  The club was officially reformed on 15 February 1919; a key figure in the events was a Mr C Watling, father of future club Chairman, Geoffrey Watling. In May 1920, The Football League formed a Third Division, to which Norwich was admitted for the following season.  Their first league fixture, against Plymouth, on 28 August 1920, ended in a 1&ndash;1 draw.  The club endured a mediocre first decade in the League, finishing no higher than eighth but no lower than 18th. It was during this period that the players began to wear a canary emblem on their shirts. A simple canary badge was first adopted in 1922; a variation is used to this day.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f83e2e59ca67a3bf8ce41037ecb03d8c" name="NorwichCity1905" sectnum="1#1">../img/f83e2e59ca67a3bf8ce41037ecb03d8c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>