<document id="df8f6df05c6d12dc8e050c570f14eea8-1.1" name="Genesis_(band)" cat="20">
<text>
Genesis was formed in 1967 when Peter Gabriel and Tony Banks were students at Charterhouse School in Godalming. Formed out of school bands Garden Wall and The Anon,. genesis-news.com, 15 May 2005. Retrieved on 27 May 2007. Genesis's original line-up consisted of Peter Gabriel (vocals), Anthony Phillips (guitar), Tony Banks (keyboards), Mike Rutherford (bass & guitar) and Chris Stewart (drums).Welch, Chris (1995). The Complete Guide to the Music of Genesis. London: Omnibus Press. The group originally formed as a songwriting partnership with no intention of performing, but decided to start playing their own music when they were unable to find anyone else willing to record it.

Charterhouse School alumnus Jonathan King hosted a concert at Charterhouse in 1968 while the band was still in school. Following the concert, Gabriel gave King a tape of songs the band had recorded and King thought enough of them to sign them to a recording contract. King was a songwriter and record producer who had a hit single at the time, "Everyone's Gone to the Moon". King named the band Genesis (after previously suggesting the name Gabriel's AngelsTracy, John.  genesis-path.net. Retrieved on 15 March 2007. 
), recalling that he had "thought it was a good name... it suggested the beginning of a new sound and a new feeling."



The resulting album, ''From Genesis to Revelation'', was released on Decca Records in March 1969. During the sessions, Stewart was replaced by John Silver on drums. The band recorded a series of songs influenced by the light pop style of the Bee Gees, one of King's favourite bands at the time. King assembled the tracks as a concept album, and added string arrangements during the production. Their first single, "The Silent Sun", was released in February 1968. The album sold poorly but the band, on advice from King, decided to pursue a career in music.King, Jonathan. "In the Beginning". ''From Genesis to Revelation'' (sleeve notes). 1993 release King holds the rights to the songs on the ''From Genesis to Revelation'' album and has re-released it many times under a variety of names, including ''In the Beginning'', ''Where the Sour Turns to Sweet'', ''Rock Roots: Genesis'', ''...And the Word Was'' and, most recently, ''The Genesis of Genesis''.

Silver was replaced by John Mayhew before the recording of ''Trespass''. Genesis then secured a new recording contract with Charisma Records.Cromelin, Richard. "Genesis: Short on Hair, Long on Gimmicks". ''Rolling Stone'', 28 March 1974. The band built a following through live performances which featured the band's hypnotic, dark and haunting melodies and Gabriel's numerous eye-catching costumes.

''Trespass'' was the template for the band's albums in the 1970s &ndash; lengthy, sometimes operatic, pieces, and occasional short, humorous numbers resembling the style of progressive rock bands such as King Crimson, Yes and Gentle Giant. ''Trespass'' included progressive rock elements such as elaborate arrangements and time signature changes, as in the nine-minute song "The Knife".

Ill health and recurring stage fright caused Phillips to leave the band in 1970.Ostrich, Michael . ProgScape Entertainment, 21 December 1998. Retrieved on 23 March 2007. Phillips later recorded many solo albums, of which ''The Geese and the Ghost'' features Phil Collins on vocals. Phillips's departure traumatised Banks and Rutherford, causing the band to doubt whether it could continueYoung, John. . Trouser Press Magazine, March 1982. Retrieved on 23 March 2007. However, the remaining members decided to carry on, replacing Mayhew with Phil Collins on drums and Steve Hackett, formerly of Quiet World, on guitar to replace Phillips.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0bae68d9751ded60809b1c0b6b0257de" name="Genesis_1967_lineup" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/0bae68d9751ded60809b1c0b6b0257de.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>