<document id="dfd42e51c1529480efc6251d03a2fbc6-3" name="Princess_Alice_of_Battenberg" cat="25">
<text>
With the advent of the Balkan Wars, Prince Andrew was reinstated to the army and Princess Andrew acted as a nurse, assisting at operations and setting up field hospitals, for which work George V of the United Kingdom awarded her the Royal Red Cross in 1913. During World War I, her brother-in-law, King Constantine of Greece, followed a neutrality policy despite the democratically elected government of Venizelos supporting the Allies. Princess Andrew and her children were forced to shelter in the palace cellars during the French bombardment of Athens on 1 December 1916.Vickers, p. 121 By June 1917, the King's neutrality policy had become so untenable that she and other members of the Greek royal family were forced into exile when her brother-in-law abdicated. For the next few years most of the Greek royal family lived in Switzerland.Van der Kiste, pp. 96 ff.

The global war effectively ended much of the political power of Europe's dynasties. The naval career of her father, Prince Louis of Battenberg, had collapsed at the beginning of the war in the face of anti-German sentiment in Britain. At the request of King George V, on 14 July 1917, he relinquished the title Prince of Battenberg in the Grand Duchy of Hesse and the style Serene Highness, and Anglicized the family name to Mountbatten. The following day, the King created him Marquess of Milford Haven in the peerage of the United Kingdom.Princess Alice of Battenberg never used the Mountbatten surname nor did she assume the courtesy title as a daughter of a British marquess since she had married into the Royal House of Greece in 1903. The following year, two of her aunts, Alix, Tsarina of Russia, and Grand Duchess Elizabeth Fyodorovna were murdered by Bolsheviks after the Russian revolution. At the end of the war the Russian, German and Austro-Hungarian empires had fallen, and Princess Andrew's uncle, Ernest Louis, Grand Duke of Hesse, was deposed.Vickers, pp. 137–138



On King Constantine's restoration in 1920, they briefly returned to Greece, taking up residence at Mon Repos on Corfu.Inherited by Prince Andrew on his father’s assassination in 1913. But after the defeat of the Hellenic Army in the Greco-Turkish War, a Revolutionary Committee under the leadership of Colonels Nikolaos Plastiras and Stylianos Gonatas seized power and forced King Constantine into exile once again.Vickers, p. 162 Prince Andrew, who had served as commander of the Second Army Corps during the war, was arrested. Several former ministers and generals arrested at the same time were shot, and British diplomats assumed that Prince Andrew was also in mortal danger. After a show trial he was sentenced to banishment, and Prince and Princess Andrew and their children fled Greece aboard a British cruiser, HMS ''Calypso'', under the protection of the British naval attaché, Commander Gerald Talbot.Vickers, p. 171

The family settled in a small house loaned to them by Princess George of Greece at Saint-Cloud, on the outskirts of Paris, where Princess Andrew helped in a charity shop for Greek refugees.Vickers, pp. 176–178 She became deeply religious, and on 20 October 1928 entered the Greek Orthodox Church. That winter, she translated her husband's defence of his actions during the Greco-Turkish War into English.Vickers, pp. 198–199 Soon afterward, she began claiming that she was receiving divine messages, and that she had healing powers.Vickers, p. 200 In 1930, after suffering a severe nervous breakdown, Princess Andrew was diagnosed with paranoid schizophrenia at Dr Ernst Simmel's sanatorium at Tegel, Berlin.Vickers, p. 205 She was forcibly removed from her family and placed in Dr Ludwig Binswanger's sanatorium in Kreuzlingen, Switzerland.Vickers, p. 209 It was a famous and well-respected institution with several celebrity patients, including Vaslav Nijinsky, the ballet dancer and choreographer, who was there at the same time as Princess Andrew.Vickers, p. 213

During Princess Andrew's long convalescence, she and Prince Andrew drifted apart, her daughters all married German princes in 1930 and 1931 (she did not attend any of the weddings), and Prince Philip went to England to stay with his uncles, Lord Louis Mountbatten and George Mountbatten, 2nd Marquess of Milford Haven, and his grandmother, the Dowager Marchioness of Milford Haven.Ziegler, p. 101

Princess Andrew remained at Kreuzlingen for two years, but after a brief stay at a clinic in Meran, was released and began an itinerant, incognito existence in Central Europe. She maintained contact with her mother, but broke off ties to the rest of her family until the end of 1936.Vickers, pp. 245–256 In 1937, her daughter Cécile, son-in-law and two of her grandchildren were killed in an air accident at Ostend; she and Prince Andrew met for the first time in six years at the funeral (Prince Philip, Lord Louis Mountbatten and Hermann Göring also attended).Vickers, p. 273 Henceforth, she remained in contact with her family, and returned to Athens alone to work with the poor in 1938, living in a two-bedroomed flat near the Benaki Museum.Vickers, pp. 281, 291 She attempted to resume maternal responsibility toward her teenaged son, welcomed his visit to Athens and explained to her brother why she felt Philip should now repatriate to Greece, apparently oblivious to the fact that Louis had already introduced Philip to the British royal family and was steering him toward a future in Britain's service.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="21323f48fad2bbe74320b2552ff02ab8" name="Laszlo_-_Princess_Andrew_of_Greece" sectnum="3#1">../img/21323f48fad2bbe74320b2552ff02ab8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>