<document id="e006297b09575effcdd2165fbb41ce1b-4.11" name="Restoration_literature" cat="17">
<text>
The return of the stage-struck Charles II to power in 1660 was a major event in English theatre history. As soon as the previous Puritan regime's ban on public stage representations was lifted, the drama recreated itself quickly and abundantly. Two theatre companies, the King's and the Duke's Company, were established in London, with two luxurious playhouses built to designs by Christopher Wren and fitted with moveable scenery and thunder and lightning machines."" in ''Encyclopædia Britannica'' (2007). Encyclopædia Britannica Online (subscription required). Retrieved on February 27, 2007.  See also Restoration spectacular.

Traditionally, Restoration plays have been studied by genre rather than chronology, more or less as if they were all contemporary, but scholars today insist on the rapid evolvement of drama in the period and on the importance of social and political factors affecting it. (Unless otherwise indicated, the account below is based on Hume's influential ''Development of English Drama in the Late Seventeenth Century'', 1976.) The influence of theatre company competition and playhouse economics is also acknowledged, as is the significance of the appearance of the first professional actresses (see Howe).

In the 1660s and 1670s, the London scene was vitalised by the competition between the two patent companies. The need to rise to the challenges of the other house made playwrights and managers extremely responsive to public taste, and theatrical fashions fluctuated almost week by week. The mid-1670s were a high point of both quantity and quality, with John Dryden's ''Aureng-zebe'' (1675), William Wycherley's ''The Country Wife'' (1675) and ''The Plain Dealer'' (1676), George Etherege's ''The Man of Mode'' (1676), and Aphra Behn's ''The Rover'' (1677), all within a few seasons.

From 1682 the production of new plays dropped sharply, affected both by a merger between the two companies and by the political turmoil of the Popish Plot (1678) and the Exclusion crisis (1682). The 1680s were especially lean years for comedy, the only exception being the remarkable career of Aphra Behn, whose achievement as the first professional British woman dramatist has been the subject of much recent study. There was a swing away from comedy to serious political drama, reflecting preoccupations and divisions following on the political crisis. The few comedies produced also tended to be political in focus, the whig dramatist Thomas Shadwell sparring with the tories John Dryden and Aphra Behn.

In the calmer times after 1688, Londoners were again ready to be amused by stage performance, but the single "United Company" was not well prepared to offer it. No longer powered by competition, the company had lost momentum and been taken over by predatory investors ("Adventurers"), while management in the form of the autocratic Christopher Rich attempted to finance a tangle of "farmed" shares and sleeping partners by slashing actors' salaries. The upshot of this mismanagement was that the disgruntled actors set up their own co-operative company in 1695.Milhous details two separate, but connected events: the capitalist machinations that gutted the company (pp. 37&ndash;43), and the unique, startling reaction of the actors, who fought back by setting up their own cooperative and revitalizing London theatre life (pp. 51&ndash;68). A few years of re-invigorated two-company competition followed which allowed a brief second flowering of the drama, especially comedy. Comedies like William Congreve's ''Love For Love'' (1695) and ''The Way of the World'' (1700), and John Vanbrugh's ''The Relapse'' (1696) and ''The Provoked Wife'' (1697) were "softer" and more middle class in ethos, very different from the aristocratic extravaganza twenty years earlier, and aimed at a wider audience. If "Restoration literature" is the literature that reflects and reflects upon the court of Charles II, Restoration drama arguably ends before Charles II's death, as the playhouse moved rapidly from the domain of courtiers to the domain of the city middle classes. On the other hand, Restoration drama shows altogether more fluidity and rapidity than other types of literature, and so, even more than in other types of literature, its movements should never be viewed as absolute. Each decade has brilliant exceptions to every rule and entirely forgettable confirmations of it.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7ced85015e97bb9034e23204977c6011" name="Dorset_Gardens_riverfront" sectnum="4.11#1">../img/7ced85015e97bb9034e23204977c6011.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>