<document id="e024b4a8dda91645c5c6cc66ef089561-1" name="Majungasaurus" cat="3">
<text>
''Majungasaurus'' was a medium-sized theropod that typically measured 6&ndash;7 meters (20&ndash;23 ft) in length, including its tail. Fragmentary remains of larger individuals indicate that some adults reached lengths of more than 8 meters (26 ft).  Scientists estimate that an average adult ''Majungasaurus'' weighed more than 1100 kilograms (2400 lb), although the largest animals would have weighed more. Its 8&ndash;9 meter (26&ndash;30 ft) relative ''Carnotaurus'' has been estimated to weigh 1500 kilograms (3300 lb).

The skull of ''Majungasaurus'' is exceptionally well-known compared to most theropods and generally similar to that of other abelisaurids. Like other abelisaurid skulls, its length was proportionally short for its height, although not as short as in ''Carnotaurus''. The skulls of large individuals measured 60&ndash;70 centimeters (24&ndash;28 in) long.  The tall premaxilla (frontmost upper jaw bone), which made the tip of the snout very blunt, was also typical of the family. However, the skull of ''Majungasaurus'' was markedly wider than in other abelisaurids. All abelisaurids had a rough, sculptured texture on the outside faces of the skull bones, and ''Majungasaurus'' was no exception. This was carried to an extreme on the nasal bones of ''Majungasaurus'', which were extremely thick and fused together, with a low central ridge running along the half of the bone closest to the nostrils. A distinctive dome-like horn protruded from the fused frontal bones on top of the skull as well. In life, these structures would have been covered with some sort of integument, possibly made of keratin. Computed tomography (CT scanning) of the skull shows that both the nasal structure and the frontal horn contained hollow sinus cavities, perhaps to reduce weight. The teeth were typical of abelisaurids in having short crowns, although ''Majungasaurus'' bore 17 teeth in both the maxilla of the upper jaw and the dentary of the lower jaw, more than in any other abelisaurid except ''Rugops''.

The postcranial skeleton of ''Majungasaurus'' closely resembles those of ''Carnotaurus'' and ''Aucasaurus'', the only other abelisaurid genera for which complete skeletal material is known. ''Majungasaurus'' was bipedal, with a long tail to balance out the head and torso, putting the center of gravity over the hips. Although the cervical (neck) vertebrae had numerous cavities and excavations (pleurocoels) to reduce their weight, they were robust, with exaggerated muscle attachment sites and ribs that interlocked for strength. Ossified tendons attached to the cervical ribs, giving them a forked appearance, as seen in ''Carnotaurus''. All of these features resulted in a very strong and muscular neck. Uniquely, the cervical ribs of ''Majungasaurus'' had long depressions along the sides for weight reduction. The humerus (upper arm bone) is the only bone of the forelimb yet described, but it was short and curved,  closely resembling those of ''Aucasaurus'' and ''Carnotaurus''. This may indicate that ''Majungasaurus'' had similar very short forelimbs with four digits. Like other abelisaurids, the hindlimbs were stocky and short compared to body length. The tibia (lower leg bone) of ''Majungasaurus'' was even stockier than that of its relative ''Carnotaurus'', with a prominent crest on the knee. The astragalus and calcaneum (ankle bones) were fused together, and the feet bore three functional digits, with a smaller first digit that did not contact the ground.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="09fb94dd44b50a2f8b2f5d8b10ecca13" name="Majungasaurus_DB" sectnum="1#1">../img/09fb94dd44b50a2f8b2f5d8b10ecca13.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>