<document id="e04312cd3ba3d17c287138a53a9d3f34-3.6" name="Halloween_III:_Season_of_the_Witch" cat="19">
<text>
As part of a merchandising campaign, the producers requested Don Post to mass-produce the skull, witch, and jack-o'-lantern masks. Producers had given exclusive merchandising rights to Post as part of his contract for working on the film, and Post Studios had already successfully marketed tie-in masks for the classic Universal monsters, ''Planet of the Apes'' (1968), ''Star Wars'' (1977), and ''E.T.: The Extra-Terrestrial'' (1981). Post used the original molds for the masks in the film to mass produce masks for retail sale. He speculated, "Because the masks are so significant to the movie, they could become a cult item, with fans wanting to wear them when they go to see the movie." Post gave mask-making demonstrations for a Universal Studio tour in Hollywood. The masks retailed for $25 when they finally appeared in stores.  Each mask also included a small metal button that contained a crystal pinned to the inside.

The script was adapted as a mass market paperback novelization in 1982 by science-fiction writer Dennis Etchison writing under the pseudonym Jack Martin. The book was a best seller and was reissued in 1984.Jack Martin, ''Halloween III: Season of the Witch'', (New York: Jove Books, 1982), ISBN 0-515-06885-3; 1984 reissue, ISBN 0-515-08594-4.''Halloween III'' trivia information at ; accessed January 21, 2008. Etchison had written the novelization to ''Halloween II'' only a year before.

The film was later released on the VHS, Betamax, LaserDisc, and RCA Selectavision Videodisc formats in 1983 by MCA/Universal Home Video. Subsequent videotape re-issues were released in 1984, 1987, and again in 1996. GoodTimes Home Video owned the rights at one point and released a VHS in 1996. DVD versions were distributed by Goodtimes in 1998 (with a re-issue release in 2001) and by Universal in 2003. 

''Halloween III's'' score, composed by John Carpenter and Alan Howarth, was released by MCA Records at the time of the film's debut on LP and was re-issued briefly on compact disc in 1989 by Varese Sarabande. The original CD issue is considered a rarity and commands high collector prices. In 2007, for the film's 25th Anniversary, Alan Howarth's record label AHI, in association with buysoundtrax.com, re-issued the score again on CD with additional unreleased material.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="17d2ea02a513c87e1b73def73d13b27d" name="HalloweenIII_Fangoria" sectnum="3.6#1">../img/17d2ea02a513c87e1b73def73d13b27d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>