<document id="e04312cd3ba3d17c287138a53a9d3f34-2.5" name="Halloween_III:_Season_of_the_Witch" cat="19">
<text>
Music remained an important element in establishing the atmosphere of ''Halloween III''. Just as in ''Halloween'' and ''Halloween II'', there was no symphonic score. Much of the music was composed to solicit "false startles" from the audience.


The soundtrack was composed by John Carpenter  and Alan Howarth, who had worked on the score for ''Halloween II''. The score of ''Halloween III'' differed greatly from the familiar main theme of the original and sequel. Carpenter replaced the familiar piano melody with a slower, electronic theme played on a synthesizer with beeping tonalities."Soundtrack" of ''Halloween III'' at ; last accessed April 27, 2006.  Howarth explains how he and Carpenter composed the music for the third film:''The music style of John Carpenter and myself has further evolved in this film soundtrack by working exclusively with synthesizers to produce our music. This has led to a certain procedural routine. The film is first transferred to a time coded video tape and synchronized to a 24 track master audio recorder; then while watching the film we compose the music to these visual images. The entire process goes quite rapidly and has "instant gratification," allowing us to evaluate the score in synch to the picture. This is quite an invaluable asset.''Alan Howarth, quoted at ; last accessed April 27, 2006

One of the more memorable aspects of the film's soundtrack was the jingle from the Silver Shamrock Halloween mask commercial. Set to the tune of "London Bridge is Falling Down," the commercial in the film counts down the days until Halloween beginning with day eight followed by an announcer's voice (Tommy Lee Wallace) encouraging children to purchase a Silver Shamrock mask to wear on Halloween night:
:''Eight more days 'til Halloween,'' 
:''Halloween, Halloween.'' 
:''Eight more days 'til Halloween,''
:''Silver Shamrock.''Plot, ''Halloween III'' at ; last accessed April 27, 2006.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="14d92cac3f70b2b0a7390db70f65ecb8" name="Carpenter_Howarth" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/14d92cac3f70b2b0a7390db70f65ecb8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>