<document id="e0656490bbbcf643a78f7ad882a90ee2-2.1.3" name="Campaign_history_of_the_Roman_military" cat="29">
<text>
After recovering surprisingly swiftly from the sack of Rome,Pennell, ''Ancient Rome'', Ch. IX, para. 4 the Romans immediately resumed their expansion within Italy. Despite their successes so far, their mastery of the whole of Italy was by no means assured at this point: the Samnites were a people just as martialPennell, ''Ancient Rome'', Ch. IX, para. 23 and as richFlorus, ''The Epitome of Roman history'', Book 1, ch. 16 as the Romans and with an objective of their own of securing more lands in the fertile Italian plains on which Rome itself lay.Lane Fox, ''The Classical World'', p. 282 The First Samnite War of between 343 BC and 341 BC that followed widespread Samnite incursions into Rome's territoryPennell, ''Ancient Rome'', Ch. IX, para. 8 was a relatively short affair: the Romans beat the Samnites in both the Battle of Mount Gaurus in 342 BC and the Battle of Suessola in 341 BC but were forced to withdraw from the war before they could pursue the conflict further due to the revolt of several of their Latin allies in the Latin War.Grant, ''The History of Rome'', p. 48Pennell, ''Ancient Rome'', Ch. IX, para. 13

Rome was therefore forced to contend by around 340 BC against both Samnite incursions into their territory and, simultaneously, in a bitter war against their former allies. Rome bested the Latins in the Battle of Vesuvius and again in the Battle of Trifanum, after which the Latin cities were obliged to submit to Roman rule.Grant, ''The History of Rome'', p. 49Pennell, ''Ancient Rome'', Ch. IX, para. 14 Perhaps due to Rome's lenient treatment of their defeated foe, the Latins submitted largely amicably to Roman rule for the next 200 years.

The Second Samnite War, from 327 BC to 304 BC, was a much longer and more serious affair for both the Romans and Samnites,Grant, ''The History of Rome'', p. 52 running for over twenty years and incorporating twenty-four battles that led to massive casualties on both sides. The fortunes of the two sides fluctuated throughout its course: the Samnites seized Neapolis in the Capture of Neapolis in 327 BC, which the Romans then re-captured before losing at the Battle of the Caudine ForksLane Fox, ''The Classical World'', p. 290 and the Battle of Lautulae. The Romans then proved victorious at the Battle of Bovianum and the tide turned strongly against the Samnites from 314 BC onwards, leading them to sue for peace with progressively less generous terms. By 304 BC the Romans had effectively annexed the greater degree of the Samnite territory, founding several colonies. This pattern of meeting aggression in force and almost inadvertently gaining territory in strategic counter-attacks was to become a common feature of Roman military history.

Seven years after their defeat, with Roman dominance of the area looking assured, the Samnites rose again and defeated the Romans at the Battle of Camerinum in 298 BC, to open the Third Samnite War. With this success in hand they managed to bring together a coalition of several previous enemies of Rome, all of whom were probably keen to prevent any one faction dominating the entire region. The army that faced the Romans at the Battle of Sentinum in 295 BC therefore included Samnites, Gauls, Etruscans and Umbrians.Grant, ''The History of Rome'', p. 53 When the Roman army won a convincing victory over these combined forces it must have become clear that little could prevent Roman dominance of Italy. In the Battle of Populonia in 282 BC Rome finished off the last vestiges of Etruscan power in the region.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5e40dc8f4b6f80ecd898a0eb74518655" name="Pietra_bismantova" sectnum="2.1.3#1">../img/5e40dc8f4b6f80ecd898a0eb74518655.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>