<document id="e0656490bbbcf643a78f7ad882a90ee2-3.5.23" name="Campaign_history_of_the_Roman_military" cat="29">
<text>
Many theories have been advanced in explanation of the decline of the Roman Empire, and many dates given for its fall, from the onset of its decline in the third centuryGoldsworthy, ''In the Name of Rome'', p. 361 to the fall of Constantinople in 1453.Matyszak, ''The Enemies of Rome'', p. 231 Militarily, however, the Empire finally fell after first being overrun by various non-Roman peoples and then having its heart in Italy seized by Germanic troops in a revolt. The historicity and exact dates are uncertain, and some historians do not consider that the Empire fell at this point.

The Empire became gradually less Romanised and increasingly Germanic in nature: although the Empire buckled under Visigothic assault, the overthrow of the last Emperor Romulus Augustus was carried out by federated Germanic troops from within the Roman army rather than by foreign troops. In this sense had Odoacer not renounced the title of Emperor and named himself "King of Italy" instead, the Empire might have continued in name. Its identity, however, was no longer Roman – it was increasingly populated and governed by Germanic peoples long before 476. The Roman people were by the fifth century "''bereft of their military ethos''"Matyszak, ''The Enemies of Rome'', p. 285 and the Roman army itself a mere supplement to federated troops of Goths, Huns, Franks and others fighting on their behalf.

Rome's last gasp began when the Visigoths revolted around 395 AD.Jordanes, ''The Origins and Deeds of the Goths'', 147 Led by Alaric I,Procopius, ''History of the Wars'', Book 3, Pt 1, Ch. 2 they attempted to seize Constantinople,Gibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', p. 551 but were rebuffed and instead plundered much of Thrace in northern Greece.Matyszak, ''The Enemies of Rome'', p. 260 In 402 AD they besieged Mediolanum, the capital of Roman Emperor Honorius, defended by Roman Gothic troops. The arrival of the Roman Stilicho and his army forced Alaric to relieve the siege and move towards Hasta (modern Asti) in western Italy, where Stilicho attacked it at the Battle of Pollentia,Gibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', p. 563Jordanes, ''The Origins and Deeds of the Goths'', 154 capturing Alaric's camp. Stilicho offered to return the prisoners in exchange for the Visigoths returning to Illyricum but upon arriving at Verona, Alaric halted his retreat. Stilicho again attacked at the Battle of VeronaGibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', p. 565 and again defeated Alaric,Matyszak, ''The Enemies of Rome'', p. 263 forcing him to withdraw from Italy.

In 405 AD, the Ostrogoths invaded Italy itself, but were defeated. However, in 406 AD an unprecedented number of tribes took advantage of the freezing of the Rhine to cross ''en masse'': Vandals, Suevi, Alans and Burgundians swept across the river and met little resistance in the Sack of Moguntiacum and the Sack of Treviri,Grant, ''The History of Rome'', p. 324 completely over-running Gaul. Despite this grave danger, or perhaps because of it, the Roman army continued to be wracked by usurpation, in one of which Stilicho, Rome's foremost defender of the period, was put to death.Grant, ''The History of Rome'', p. 327

It is in this climate that, despite his earlier setback, Alaric returned again in 410 and managed to sack Rome.Jordanes, ''The Origins and Deeds of the Goths'', 156Matyszak, ''The Enemies of Rome'', p. 267Gibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', p. 589 The Roman capital had by this time moved to the Italian city of Ravenna,Gibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', p. 587 but some historians view 410 as an alternative date for the true fall of the Roman Empire.Wood, ''In Search of the First Civilizations'', p. 177 Without possession of Rome or many of its former provinces, and increasingly Germanic in nature, the Roman Empire after 410 had little in common with the earlier Empire. By 410 AD, Britain had been mostly denuded of Roman troops,Gibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', p. 560Churchill, ''A History of the English-Speaking Peoples'', p. 16 and by 425 AD was no longer part of the Empire, and much of western Europe was beset "''by all kinds of calamities and disasters''",Churchill, ''A History of the English-Speaking Peoples'', p. 17 coming under barbarian kingdoms ruled by Vandals, Suebians, Visigoths and Burgundians.Santosuosso, ''Storming the Heavens'', p. 187



The remainder of Rome's territory, if not its nature, was defended for several decades following 410 largely by Flavius Aëtius, who managed to play off each of Rome's barbarian invaders against one another. In 436 he led a Hunnic army against the Visigoths at the Battle of Arles, and again in 436 at the Battle of Narbonne. In 451 he led a combined army, including his former enemy the Visigoths, against the Huns at the Battle of the Catalaunian Plains,Matyszak, ''The Enemies of Rome'', p. 276Gibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', p. 489Jordanes, ''The Origins and Deeds of the Goths'', 197 beating them so soundly that although they later sacked Concordia, Altinum, Mediolanum,Jordanes, ''The Origins and Deeds of the Goths'', 222 Ticinum, and Patavium, they never again directly threatened Rome. Despite being the only clear champion of the Empire at this point Aëtius was slain by the Emperor Valentinian III's own hand, leading Sidonius Apollinaris to observe, "''I am ignorant, sir, of your motives or provocations; I only know that you have acted like a man who has cut off his right hand with his left''".Gibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', ch. 35

Carthage, the second largest city in the empire, was lost along with much of North Africa in 439 AD to the Vandals,Gibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', p. 618Procopius, ''History of the Wars'', Book 3, Pt 1, Ch. 4 and the fate of Rome seemed sealed. By 476, what remained of the Empire was completely in the hands of federated Germanic troops and when they revolted led by Odoacer and deposed Emperor Romulus AugustusJordanes, ''The Origins and Deeds of the Goths'', 243 there was nobody to stop them. Odoacer happened to hold the part of the Empire around Italy and Rome but other parts of the Empire were ruled by Visigoths, Ostrogoths, Franks, Alans and others. The Empire in the West had fallen, and its remnant in Italy was no longer Roman in nature. The Byzantine Empire and the Goths continued to fight over Rome and the surrounding area for many years, though by this point Rome's importance was negligible. Following years of grinding war the city was by 540 AD near-abandoned and desolate with much of its environment turned into an unhealthy marsh, an inglorious end for a city that once ruled much of the known world.

At this point in time, the Eastern Roman Empire stands alone, and events in Roman military history fall under the category of Byzantine military history.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4b738efef45a0bb3a85866a0979cdb60" name="476eur" sectnum="3.5.23#1">../img/4b738efef45a0bb3a85866a0979cdb60.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>