<document id="e0656490bbbcf643a78f7ad882a90ee2-1" name="Campaign_history_of_the_Roman_military" cat="29">
<text>
Rome is almost unique in the ancient world in that its history, military and otherwise, is documented often in great detail almost from the city's very foundation right through to its eventual demise. Although some histories have been lost, such as Trajan's account of the Dacian Wars, and others, such as Rome's earliest histories, are at least semi-apocryphal, the extant histories of Rome's military history are extensive.

The very earliest history, from the time of Rome's founding as a small tribal village,Pennell, ''Ancient Rome'', first page of Chapter III. through to the downfall of Rome's kings, is the least well preserved. This is because, although the early Romans were literate to some degree,Grant, ''The History of Rome'', p. 23 either they lacked the will to record their history at this time or else such histories as they did record were lost.Pennell, ''Ancient Rome'', Ch. IX, para. 3

Although the Roman historian Livy (59 BC &ndash; AD 17Ronald Syme, following G. M. Hirst, has argued for 64 BC&ndash;AD 12. For a presentation on the dates see Livy.) lists a series of seven kings of early Rome in his work ''Ab Urbe Condita'', from its establishment through its earliest years, the degree to which the first four kings  (Romulus,Florus, ''Epitome of Roman History'', Book 1, ch. 1 Numa,Florus, ''Epitome of Roman History'', Book 1, ch. 2Cassius Dio, ''The Roman History'', Vol. 1, VII, 6 Tullus HostiliusFlorus, ''Epitome of Roman History'', Book 1, ch. 3 and Ancus MarciusFlorus, ''Epitome of Roman History'', Book 1, ch. 4) are apocryphal is certainly open to question. A number of points of view have been proposed over the long run of time. Grant and others argue that prior to the time when the Etruscan kingdom of Rome was established under the traditional fifth king, Tarquinius Priscus,Pennell, ''Ancient Rome'', Ch. V, para. 1 Rome would have been led by a religious leader of some sort.Grant, ''The History of Rome'', p. 21 Very little is known of Rome's military history during this era, and what history has come down to us is of a legendary rather than a known factual nature. Traditionally, Romulus fortified one of the first-settled of Rome's seven hills, the Palatine Hill, after founding the city, and Livy states that shortly after its founding Rome was "''equal to any of the surrounding cities in her prowess in war''".Livy, ''The Rise of Rome'', p. 13



The first campaigns that were fought by the Romans in this legendary account are the wars with various Latin cities and the Sabines after the Rape of the Sabine Women. According to Livy, the Latin village of Caenina responded to the event first by invading Roman territory, but were routed and their village captured. The Latins of Antemnae and those of Crustumerium were defeated next in a similar fashion. The remaining main body of the Sabines attacked Rome and briefly captured the citadel, but were then convinced to conclude a treaty with the Romans under which the Sabines became Roman citizens.Cassius Dio, ''The Roman History'', Vol. 1, VII, 9; Livy, ''Ab urbe condita'', 1:10-13

There was a further war in the 8th century BC against Fidenae and Veii.  In the 7th century BC there was a war with Alba Longa, a second war with Fidenae and Veii and a second Sabine War.  Ancus Marcius led Rome to victory against the Latins and, according to the Fasti Triumphales, over the Veientes and Sabines also.

Under the Etruscan kings Tarquinius Priscus,Florus, ''Epitome of Roman History'', Book 1, ch. 5 Servius TulliusFlorus, ''Epitome of Roman History'', Book 1, ch. 6 and Tarquinius Superbus,Florus, ''Epitome of Roman History'', Book 1, ch. 7 Rome expanded to the north-west, coming into conflict again with the Veientes after the expiry of the treaty that concluded their earlier war.Livy, ''The Rise of Rome'', p. 56 There was a further campaign against the Gabii,Livy, ''The Rise of Rome'', p. 61Cassius Dio, ''The Roman History'', Vol. 1, VII, 10 and later against the Rutuli.Livy, ''The Rise of Rome'', p. 66 The Etruscan kings were overthrownFlorus, ''Epitome of Roman History'', Book 1, ch. 9 as part of a wider reduction in Etruscan power in the region during this period, and Rome reformed itself as a republic,Grant, ''The History of Rome'', p. 31Pennell, ''Ancient Rome'', Ch. VI, para. 1 a form of government based on popular representation and in contrast to its previous autocratic kingship.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fe4d46d2c0a7b86f801be1cd2a0bb21f" name="Poussin_RapeSabineLouvre" sectnum="1#1">../img/fe4d46d2c0a7b86f801be1cd2a0bb21f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>