<document id="e0656490bbbcf643a78f7ad882a90ee2-3.5.21" name="Campaign_history_of_the_Roman_military" cat="29">
<text>
A military that was often willing to support its commander over its emperor meant that commanders could establish sole control of the army they were responsible for and usurp the imperial throne. The so-called Crisis of the Third Century describes the turmoil of murder, usurpation and in-fighting that is traditionally seen as developing with the murder of the Emperor Alexander Severus in 235.Grant, ''The History of Rome'', p. 280 However, Cassius Dio marks the wider imperial decline as beginning in 180 AD with ascension of Commodus to the throne,Matyszak, ''The Enemies of Rome'', p. 226 a judgement with which Gibbon concurred,Gibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', p. 113 and Matyszak states that ''"the rot... had become established long before"'' even that.

Though the crisis of the third century was not the absolute beginning of Rome's decline, nevertheless it did mark a severe strain on the empire as Romans waged war on one another as they had not done since the final days of the Republic. Within the space of a single century, twenty-seven military officers claimed themselves emperors and reigned over parts of the empire for months or days, all but two meeting with a violent end.Matyszak, ''The Enemies of Rome'', p. 227 The time was characterised by a Roman army that was as likely to be attacking itself as an outside invader, reaching a low point around 258 AD.Gibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', p. 133 Ironically, while it was these usurpations that led to the break up of the Empire during the crisis, it was the strength of several frontier generals that helped reunify the empire through force of arms.

The situation was complex, often with 3 or more usurpers in existence at once. Septimius Severus and Pescennius Niger, both rebel generals promoted as emperors by the troops they commanded, clashed for the first time in 193 AD at the Battle of Cyzicus, in which Niger was defeated. However, it took two further defeats at the Battle of Nicaea later that year and the Battle of Issus the following year, for Niger to be definitively defeated. Almost as soon as Niger's hopes of the imperial crown had been laid to rest, Severus was forced to deal with another rival for the throne in the person of Clodius Albinus, who had originally been allied to Severus. Albinus was proclaimed emperor by his troops in Britain and, crossing over to Gaul, defeated Severus' general Virius Lupus in battle, before being in turn defeated and killed himself in the Battle of Lugdunum by Severus himself.

After this turmoil, Severus faced no more internal threats for the rest of his reign,Gibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', p. 129 and the reign of his successor Caracalla passed uninterrupted for a while until he was murdered by Macrinus, who proclaimed himsef emperor in his place. Despite Macrinus having his position ratified by the Roman senate, the troops of Varius Avitus declared him to be emperor instead, and the two met in battle at the Battle of Antioch in 218 AD, in which Macrinus was defeated.Gibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', p. 130 However, Avitus himself – taking the imperial name Elagabalus – was murdered shortly afterwards and Alexander Severus was proclaimed emperor by both the Praetorian Guard and the senate who, after a short reign, was murdered in turn. His murderers were working on behalf of the army who were unhappy with their lot under his rule and who raised in his place Maximinus Thrax. However, just as he had been raised by the army, Maximinus was also brought down by them and despite winning the Battle of Carthage against the senate's newly-proclaimed Gordian II, he was murderedGibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', p. 131 when it appeared to his forces as though he would not be able to best the next senatorial candidate for the throne, Gordian III.

Gordian III's fate is not certain, although he may have been murdered by his own successor, Philip the Arab, who ruled for only a few years before the army again raised a general to proclaimed emperor, this time Decius, who defeated Philip in the Battle of Verona to seize the throne.Gibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', p. 135 Several succeeding generals avoided battling usurpers for the throne chiefly by virtue of being murdered by their own troops before battle could commence, which at least relieved the empire momentarily of manpower losses to internal strife. The lone exception to this rule was Gallienus, emperor from 260 AD to 268 AD, who saw a remarkable array of usurpers, most of whom he defeated in pitched battle. The army was therefore mostly spared further infighting until around 273 AD, when Aurelian defeated the Gallic usurper Tetricus in the Battle of Chalons. The next decade saw a barely credible number of usurpers, sometimes 3 at the same time, all vying for the imperial throne. Most of the battles are not recorded, primarily due to the turmoil of the time, until Diocletian, a usurper himself, defeated Carinus at the Battle of the Margus to become emperor.

Some small measure of stability again returned at this point, with the empire split into a Tetrarchy of two greater and two lesser emperors, a system that staved off civil wars for a short time until 312 AD. In that year, relations between the tetrarchy collapsed for good and Constantine I, Licinius, Maxentius and Maximinus jostled for control of the empire. In the Battle of Turin Constantine defeated Maxentius, and in the Battle of Tzirallum Licinius defeated Maximinus. From 314 AD onwards, Constantine defeated Licinius in the Battle of Cibalae, then the Battle of Mardia, and then again at the Battle of Adrianople, the Battle of the Hellespont and the Battle of Chrysopolis.

Constantine then turned to Maxentius, beating him in the Battle of Verona and the Battle of Milvian Bridge in the same year. Constantine's son Constantius II inherited his father's rule and later defeated the usurper Magnentius in first the Battle of Mursa Major and then the Battle of Mons Seleucus.

Successive emperors Valens and Theodosius I also defeated usurpers in, respectively, the  Battle of Thyatira, and the battles of the Save and the Frigidus.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="02576840af5234a902518e76b38d5c2d" name="Raphael-Constantine_at_Milvian_Bridge" sectnum="3.5.21#1">../img/02576840af5234a902518e76b38d5c2d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>