<document id="e0db2bab271606aefbf9610588076f62-2.2" name="The_Pit_and_the_Pendulum_(1961_film)" cat="19">
<text>
Corman has noted that making the film was a pleasurable experience: "I enjoyed ''The Pit and the Pendulum'' because I actually got the chance to experiment a bit with the movement of the camera.  There was a lot of moving camera work and interesting cutting in the climax of the film."  Filming went smoothly, and Corman attributed the ease of the production's shoot to the short but comprehensive pre-production planning he did with the major technicians. "We achieved what we did on a low budget because we carefully planned the whole production in advance of starting the cameras.  Thus, when we moved into the studio for fifteen days of scheduled shooting, we didn't have to start making decisions. Because of our pre-production conferences with Director of Photography Floyd Crosby and Art Director Daniel Haller, everyone knew exactly what to do, barring any last minute inspirations on the set."


To create the flashbacks revealing Nicholas's traumatic experiences,  Corman and Crosby attempted to shoot them in a manner that would convey to the audience the character's horror in dredging up nightmares trapped  in his subconscious. Corman insisted on these images having a dream-like quality, "twisted and distorted because they were being experienced by someone on the rim of madness".  Corman decided to film the flashbacks in monochrome, since he had read that some psychiatrists believe most people dream in "black-and white" imagery.  Crosby used wide-angle lenses, from the ''Internet Movie Database''. Crosby shot the film using the 35 mm anamorphic film process with Panavision cameras and lenses. violent camera movement, and tilted camera angles to represent the character's feeling of hysteria. The sequences were then printed on blue-tinted stock which was subsequently toned red during development, effectively producing a two-tone image. The highlights were blue, with the shadows rendered as red, producing a deep, bloody quality. The image was then run through an optical printer where the edges were vignetted and a twisted linear distortion was introduced.Lightman, Herb A.  "The Pit and the Pendulum: A Study In Horror Film Photography", ''American Cinematographer'', October 1961 issue.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="57ece09374ddb6c781f3cb72020f4011" name="PitFlash" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/57ece09374ddb6c781f3cb72020f4011.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>