<document id="e0e615fb5f0cc926ce63debe16c82b30-10" name="Ehime_Maru_and_USS_Greeneville_collision" cat="14">
<text>
Acting on a request from the Ehime government, the state of Hawaii established a non-profit group, the ''Ehime Maru'' Memorial Association, on 11 November 2001, to coordinate the activities of placing an ''Ehime Maru'' memorial at a site in Hawaii.  The monument to the ship was completed on 9 February 2002, at Kakaako Waterfront Park near Honolulu.  Each year since the accident, memorial ceremonies have been held on 9 February at Uwajima Fisheries High School in Ehime and at the ''Ehime Maru'' monument in Hawaii.Japan-America Society of Hawaii, ''Ehime Maru Memorial Association'', Kyodo, "School marks date of ship's sinking", "Dual memorials held for ''Ehime Maru''", Tyler, Greg, "Uwajima school remembers ''Ehime Maru''", ''Kyodo News'', "", ''Japan Times'', February 11, 2009, p. 2.

Shipbuilders in Imabari, Ehime Prefecture, began construction on a new ''Ehime Maru'' on 17 April 2002.  Upon completion, the new ship sailed to Hawaii, arriving on 17 June 2003. In a ceremony at the ''Ehime Maru'' monument, the principal of Uwajima Fishery at the time of the disaster, Kazumitsu Joko (上甲一光 ''Jōkō Kazumitsu''), read a message from Moriyuki Kato, the governor of Ehime Prefecture, addressed to the Hawaiian people.  The message stated, in part, "Since the ''Ehime Maru'' tragic accident two years ago, the people of Hawaii have shown compassion and warm support."Kyodo, "Work starts on ''Ehime Maru''s replacement", Kakesako, ''Tender Thoughts''.

The NTSB released its report on the accident on 19 October 2005.  The NTSB report largely confirmed the USN's inquiry findings, including that Waddle was primarily responsible for the collision.  The NTSB report, however, was more critical of the distractions caused by the DV civilians on ''Greeneville'' that contributed to the accident.  The report concluded that the USN had recognized the "detrimental operating conditions" aboard ''Greeneville'' and had taken "additional measures to address the safety of operations" on submarines, including additional restrictions on DVE visitors.Tyler, Greg, "Former USS ''Greeneville'' commander blamed for collision with fishing boat", NTSB, ''Marine Accident Brief''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="34087182622983ce8dfe720757103cb0" name="Ehime_Maru_memorial" sectnum="10#1">../img/34087182622983ce8dfe720757103cb0.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>