<document id="e10b143744c6e02c45d72e3ddff39eda-8" name="Guinea_pig" cat="3">
<text>
As a result of their widespread popularity in human domestic life, and especially because of their popularity in households with children, guinea pigs have shown a presence in culture and media. Some noted appearances of the animal in literature are ''The Fairy Caravan'', a novel by Beatrix Potter, and Michael Bond's Olga da Polga series for children, both of which feature guinea pigs as the central protagonist. Another appearance is in ''The Magician's Nephew'' by C. S. Lewis: in the first (chronologically) of his ''The Chronicles of Narnia'' series, a guinea pig is the first creature to travel to the Wood between the Worlds. The short story ''Pigs Is Pigs'' by Ellis Parker Butler is a tale of bureaucratic incompetence; two guinea pigs held at a train station breed unchecked while humans argue as to whether they are "pigs" for the purpose of determining freight charges. In the Golden Hamster Saga books, there are two guinea pigs named Enrico and Caruso who are modern-day thespians (named after Enrico Caruso) who serve as secondary characters, and often irritate the main character, Freddy Auratus who strongly dislikes their acting antics.

Guinea pigs have also been featured in film and television. In the TV movie Shredderman Rules, the main character and the main character's crush both have guinea pigs which both play a minor part in the plot. A guinea pig named Rodney, voiced by Chris Rock, was a prominent character in the 1998 film ''Dr. Dolittle'' and Linny the Guinea pig is a co-star on Nick Jr.'s ''Wonder Pets''. Guinea pigs were used in some major advertising campaigns in the 1990s and 2000s, notably for Egg Banking plc, Snapple, and Blockbuster Video. The Blockbuster campaign is considered by some guinea pig advocates to have been a factor in the rise of cohousing guinea pigs and rabbits.  In the South Park season 12 episode "Pandemic 2: The Startling", giant guinea pigs, and giant guinea pigs dressed in costumes, are portrayed as rampaging over the entire Earth. The Walt Disney Pictures movie G-Force, released in the United States on July 24, 2009, features a group of highly intelligent guinea pigs trained as operatives of the U.S. government.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="63c77c016bfd5a4a3f4fb69bb3695e5b" name="rene2" sectnum="8#1">../img/63c77c016bfd5a4a3f4fb69bb3695e5b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>