<document id="e1f1255ac70522fc2ed8b396b7bb8371-7.2" name="Daniel_Boone" cat="14">
<text>
Thanks to Filson's book, in Europe, Boone became a symbol of the "natural man" who lives a virtuous, uncomplicated existence in the wilderness. This was most famously expressed in Lord Byron's epic poem ''Don Juan'' (1822), which devoted a number of stanzas to Boone, including this one:
:Of the great names which in our faces stare,
::The General Boon, back-woodsman of Kentucky,
:Was happiest amongst mortals any where;
::For killing nothing but a bear or buck, he
:Enjoyed the lonely vigorous, harmless days
:Of his old age in wilds of deepest maze.Faragher, ''Daniel Boone'', 328.

Byron's poem celebrated Boone as someone who found happiness by turning his back on civilization. In a similar vein, many folk tales depicted Boone as a man who migrated to more remote areas whenever civilization crowded in on him. In a typical anecdote, when asked why he was moving to Missouri, Boone supposedly replied, "I want more elbow room!" Boone rejected such an interpretation of his life, however. "Nothing embitters my old age," he said late in life, like "the circulation of absurd stories that I retire as civilization advances…."Faragher, ''Daniel Boone'', 302, 325–26.

Existing simultaneously with the image of Boone as a refugee from society was, paradoxically, the popular portrayal of him as civilization's trailblazer. Boone was celebrated as an agent of Manifest Destiny, a pathfinder who tamed the wilderness, paving the way for the extension of American civilization. In 1852, critic Henry Tuckerman dubbed Boone "the Columbus of the woods", comparing Boone's passage through the Cumberland Gap to Christopher Columbus's voyage to the New World. In popular mythology, Boone became the first to explore and settle Kentucky, opening the way for countless others to follow. In fact, other Americans had explored and settled Kentucky before Boone, as debunkers in the 20th century often pointed out, but Boone came to symbolize them all, making him what historian Michael Lofaro called "the founding father of westward expansion".Faragher, ''Daniel Boone'', 321–22, 350–52; Lofaro, ''American Life'', 181–82.



In the 19th century, when Native Americans were being displaced from their lands and confined on reservations, Boone's image was often reshaped into the stereotype of the belligerent, Indian-hating frontiersman which was then popular. In John A. McClung's ''Sketches of Western Adventure'' (1832), for example, Boone was portrayed as longing for the "thrilling excitement of savage warfare." Boone was transformed in the popular imagination into someone who regarded Indians with contempt and had killed scores of the "savages". The real Boone disliked bloodshed, however. According to historian John Bakeless, there is no record that Boone ever scalped Indians, unlike other frontiersmen of the era. Boone once told his son Nathan that he was certain of having killed only one Indian, during the battle at Blue Licks, although he believed that others may have died from his bullets in other battles. Even though Boone had lost two sons in wars with Indians, he respected Indians and was respected by them. In Missouri, Boone often went hunting with the very Shawnees who had captured and adopted him decades earlier. Some 19th century writers regarded Boone's sympathy for Indians as a character flaw and therefore altered his words to conform to contemporary attitudes.Bakeless, ''Master of the Wilderness'', 162–62; Faragher, ''Daniel Boone'', 39, 86, 219, 313, 320, 333.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e8c33725f33ac396388f72abac988e3f" name="Daniel_Boone_protects_his_family" sectnum="7.2#1">../img/e8c33725f33ac396388f72abac988e3f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>