<document id="e237e3c6308d0867edab8cd3155b5a90-4" name="Jersey_Shore_shark_attacks_of_1916" cat="14">
<text>
Before 1916, American scholars doubted that sharks would attack a living person in the temperate waters of the United States without provocation. One skeptical scientist wrote, "There is a great difference between being attacked by a shark and being bitten by one." He believed that sharks tangled in fishing nets or feeding on carrion might accidentally bite a nearby human.Frederic Lucas, quoted in Fernicola, ''Twelve Days of Terror'', p. xxix. In 1891, millionaire banker and adventurer Hermann Oelrichs offered a $500 reward in the ''New York Sun'' "for an authenticated case of a man having been attacked by a shark in  temperate waters" north of Cape Hatteras, North Carolina.Hermann Oelrichs, quoted in Fernicola, ''Twelve Days of Terror'', p. xxv. He wanted proof that "in temperate waters even one man, woman, or child, while alive, was ever attacked by a shark."Oelrichs, quoted in Capuzzo, ''Close to Shore'', p. 22. The reward went unclaimed and scientists remained convinced that America's East Coast was inhabited by harmless sharks.Fernicola, ''Twelve Days of Terror'', xxv.Capuzzo, ''Close to Shore'', p. 26.



Academics were skeptical that a shark could produce fatal wounds on human victims. Ichthyologist Henry Weed Fowler and curator Henry Skinner of the Academy of Natural Sciences in Philadelphia asserted that a shark's jaws did not have the power to sever a human leg in a single bite.Fernicola, ''Twelve Days of Terror'', pp. xxvi–xxviii. Frederic Lucas, director of the American Museum of Natural History, questioned whether a shark even as large as 30 feet (9 m) could snap a human bone. He told the ''Philadelphia Inquirer'' in early 1916 that "it is beyond the power even of the largest Carcharodon to sever the leg of an adult man." Lucas summed up his argument by pointing to Oelrichs's unclaimed reward and that the chances of being attacked by a shark were "infinitely less than that of being struck by lightning and that there is practically '''no''' danger of an attack from a shark about our coasts."Frederic Lucas, quoted in Fernicola, ''Twelve Days of Terror'', p. xxx.

The Jersey Shore attacks compelled scientists in the United States to revise their assumptions that sharks were timid and powerless. In July 1916, ichthyologist and editor for the National Geographic Society Hugh McCormick Smith published an article in the ''Newark Star-Eagle'' describing some shark species as "harmless as doves and others the incarnation of ferocity." He continued, "One of the most prodigious, and perhaps the most formidable of sharks is the man-eater, ''Carcharodon carcharias''. It roams through all temperate and tropical seas, and everywhere is an object of dread. Its maximum length is forty feet and its teeth are three inches (76 mm)  long."Hugh M. Smith, "Great Shark May Have Swallowed Jonah: Scientist Shows Biblical 'Great Fish' Has Counterpart in Present-Day Monster," ''Newark Star-Eagle'', quoted in Fernicola, ''Twelve Days of Terror'', p. 160. 

By the end of July 1916, John Nichols and Robert Murphy were taking the great white more seriously. In ''Scientific American'', Murphy wrote that the "white shark is perhaps the rarest of all noteworthy sharks … their habits are little known, but they are said to feed to some extent on big sea turtles … Judging from its physical make-up, it would not hesitate to attack a man in open water." He concluded that "because it is evident that even a relatively small white shark, weighing two or three hundred pounds, might readily snap the largest human bones by a jerk of its body, after it has bitten through the flesh."Murphy, ''Scientific American'', July 1916, quoted in Fernicola, ''Twelve Days of Terror'', 171.

Robert Murphy and John Nichols wrote in October 1916: 



After the Matawan attacks, Frederic Lucas admitted on the front page of ''The New York Times'' that he had underestimated sharks. The paper reported that "the foremost authority on sharks in this country has doubted that any shark ever attacked a human being, and has published his doubts, but the recent cases have changed his view."  Nichols later documented the occurrence of the great white shark in his biological survey ''Fishes of the Vicinity of New York City'' (1918), "''Carcharodon carcharias'' (Linn.) White Shark. "Man-eater." Accidental in summer. June to July 14, 1916."John T. Nichols, ''Fishes of the Vicinity of New York City'', (New York: American Museum of Natural History, 1918), p. 101. See full text at the  .
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="48d2a61f18d6718fd78845e3ca69438b" name="AmericanMuseumofNaturalHistory" sectnum="4#1">../img/48d2a61f18d6718fd78845e3ca69438b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>