<document id="e2d6b5ad8b42586267b4c468fca715bd-2" name="California_Gold_Rush" cat="14">
<text>
The first people to rush to the gold fields, beginning in the spring of 1848, were the residents of California themselves&mdash;primarily agriculturally oriented Americans and Europeans living in Northern California, along with Native Americans and some ''Californios'' (Spanish-speaking Californians).Brands, H.W. (2003), pp. 43–46. These first miners tended to be families in which everyone helped in the effort.  Women and children of all races were often found panning next to the men.  Some enterprising families set up boarding houses to accommodate the influx of men; in such cases, the women often brought in steady income while their husbands searched for gold.Moynihan, Ruth B., Armitage, Susan, and Dichamp, Christiane Fischer (eds.) (1990). ''So Much to Be Done.'' Lincoln: U Nebraska, p. 3

Word of the Gold Rush spread slowly at first. The earliest gold-seekers to arrive in California during 1848 were people who lived near California, or people who heard the news from ships on the fastest sailing routes from California. The first large group of Americans to arrive were several thousand Oregonians who came down the Siskiyou Trail. Next came people from The Sandwich Islands, by ship, and several thousand Latin Americans, including people from Mexico, from Peru and from as far away as Australia and Chile,Brands, H.W. (2003), pp. 48–53. both by ship and overland.Starr, Kevin and Orsi, Richard J. (eds.) (2000), pp. 50–54. By the end of 1848, some 6,000 Argonauts had come to California. Only a small number (probably fewer than 500) traveled overland from the United States that year. Some of these "forty-eighters," as these very earliest gold-seekers were also sometimes called, were able to collect large amounts of easily accessible gold&mdash;in some cases, thousands of dollars worth each day.Brands, H.W. (2003), pp. 197–202.Holliday, J. S. (1999) p. 63. Holliday notes these luckiest prospectors were recovering, in short amounts of time, gold worth in excess of $1 million when valued at the dollars of today. Even ordinary prospectors averaged daily gold finds worth ten to fifteen times the daily wage of a laborer on the East Coast. A person could work for six months in the goldfields and find the equivalent of six years' wages back home,Starr, Kevin and Orsi, Richard J. (eds.) (2000), p. 28. which attracted people of all types and ethnicities including single men and women, families, and married men.  Some hoped to get rich quick and return home, and others wished to start businesses in California. 

By the beginning of 1849, word of the Gold Rush had spread around the world, and an overwhelming number of gold-seekers and merchants began to arrive from virtually every continent. The largest group of forty-niners in 1849 were Americans, arriving by the tens of thousands overland across the continent and along various sailing routesStarr, Kevin and Orsi, Richard J. (eds.) (2000), pp. 57–61. (the name "forty-niner" was derived from the year 1849).  Many came by way of the Isthmus of Panama and the steamships of the Pacific Mail Steamship Company.  AustraliansBrands, H.W. (2003), pp. 53–61. and New Zealanders picked up the news from ships carrying Hawaiian newspapers, and thousands, infected with "gold fever," boarded ships for California.Starr, Kevin and Orsi, Richard J. (eds.) (2000), pp. 53–56. Forty-niners came from Latin America, particularly from the Mexican mining districts near Sonora. Gold-seekers and merchants from Asia, primarily from China,Brands, H.W. (2003), pp. 61–64. began arriving in 1849, at first in modest numbers to ''Gum San'' ("Gold Mountain"), the name given to California in Chinese.Magagnini, Stephen (January 18, 1998)"", ''The Sacramento Bee''. Accessed 2009-10-22  The first immigrants from Europe, reeling from the effects of the Revolutions of 1848 and with a longer distance to travel, began arriving in late 1849, mostly from France,Brands, H.W. (2003), pp. 93–103. with some Germans, Italians, and Britons. Most of these national groups arrived from seafaring, costal regions.

It is estimated that approximately 90,000 people arrived in California in 1849&mdash;about half by land and half by sea.Starr, Kevin and Orsi, Richard J. (eds.) (2000), pp. 57–61. Other estimates range from 70,000 to 90,000 arrivals during 1849 (''ibid.'' p. 57). Of these, perhaps 50,000 to 60,000 were Americans, and the rest were from other countries. By 1855, it is estimated at least 300,000 gold-seekers, merchants, and other immigrants had arrived in California from around the world.Starr, Kevin and Orsi, Richard J. (eds.) (2000), p. 25. The largest group continued to be Americans, but there were tens of thousands each of Mexicans, Chinese, Britons, and Australians  French, and Latin Americans,Brands, H.W. (2003), pp. 193–194. together with many smaller groups of miners, such as Filipinos, BasquesStarr, Kevin and Orsi, Richard J. (eds.) (2000), p. 62. and Turks. .  The hill people from small villages near the Port of Genova, Italy were among the first to settle permanently in the Sierra Foothills who transplanted their cultural capacity of growing vegetables and food staples, using wheat for bread and traditional skills, to survive the isolated, cold winters. Freguli, Carolyn. (eds.) (2008), pp.8–9.. A modest number of miners of African ancestry (probably less than 4,000)Another estimate is 2,500 forty-niners of African ancestry. Rawls, James, J. and Orsi, Richard (eds.) (1999), p. 5. had come from the Southern States,African Americans who were slaves and came to California during the Gold Rush could gain . One of the miners was African American Edmond Edward Wysinger (1816-1891), see also Moses Rodgers (1835-1900) the Caribbean and Brazil.Starr, Kevin and Orsi, Richard J. (eds.) (2000), pp. 67–69.. 

A notable number of immigrants were from China. Several hundred Chinese arrived in California in 1849 and 1850, and in 1852 more than 20,000 landed in San Francisco.Out of Many, 5th Edition Volume 1, Faragher 2006 (p.411) Their distinctive dress and appearance was highly recognizable in the gold fields, and created a degree of animosity towards the Chinese.

There were also many women in the Gold Rush.  They held various roles including prostitutes, single entrepreneurs, married women, poor and wealthy women. They also were of various ethnicities including Anglo-American, Hispanic, Native, European, Chinese.  The reasons they came varied: some came with their husbands, refusing to be left behind to fend for themselves, some came because their husbands sent for them, and others came (singles and widows) for the adventure and economic opportunities.Moynihan, Ruth B., Armitage, Susan, and Dichamp, Christiane Fischer (eds.) (1990), pp. 3-8  On the trail many people died from accidents, cholera, fever, and myriad other causes, and many women became widows before even setting eyes on California.  While in California, women were widows quite frequently due to mining accidents, disease, or mining disputes of their husbands.  While it was not an easy place for anyone, life in the west did offer many opportunities for women to break from their typical work.Levy, Joann (1990). ''They saw the elephant: Women in the California Gold Rush.'' Archon:N.p., pp. xxii, 92
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9167170d3b233d10826ec53c05a8ea47" name="Panning_on_the_Mokelumne" sectnum="2#1">../img/9167170d3b233d10826ec53c05a8ea47.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>