<document id="e2d6b5ad8b42586267b4c468fca715bd-5" name="California_Gold_Rush" cat="14">
<text>
Although the conventional wisdom is that merchants made more money than miners during the Gold Rush, the reality is perhaps more complex. There were certainly merchants who profited handsomely. The wealthiest man in California during the early years of the Gold Rush was Samuel Brannan, the tireless self-promoter, shopkeeper and newspaper publisher.Holliday, J. S. (1999) pp. 69–70. Brannan alertly opened the first supply stores in Sacramento, Coloma, and other spots in the gold fields. Just as the Gold Rush began, he purchased all the prospecting supplies available in San Francisco and re-sold them at a substantial profit. However, substantial money was made by gold-seekers as well. For example, within a few months, one small group of prospectors, working on the Feather River in 1848, retrieved a sum of gold worth more than $1.5 million by 2006 prices.Holliday, J. S. (1999), p. 63.

On average, many early gold-seekers did perhaps make a modest profit, after all expenses were taken into account. Most, however, especially those arriving later, made little or wound up losing money.Holliday, J. S. (1999), p. 78.One estimate is that fewer than one in twenty prospectors profited financially from their California gold-seeking. Rawls, James J. and Orsi, Richard (eds.) (1999), p. 7. Similarly, many unlucky merchants set up in settlements that disappeared, or were wiped out in one of the calamitous fires that swept the towns springing up.For example, Joshua A. Norton at first acquired a fortune but was forced to declare bankruptcy in 1858, and he wandered the streets of San Francisco, styling himself "Emperor Norton I." By contrast, a businessman who went on to great success was Levi Strauss, who first began selling denim over-alls in San Francisco in 1853. (The famous Levi's jeans were not invented until the 1870s). Other businessmen, through good fortune and hard work, reaped great rewards in retail, shipping, entertainment, lodging,James Lick made a fortune running a hotel and engaging in land speculation in San Francisco. Lick's fortune was used to build Lick Observatory. or transportation.Four particularly successful Gold Rush era merchants were Leland Stanford, Collis P. Huntington, Mark Hopkins and Charles Crocker, Sacramento area businessmen (later known as the Big Four) who financed the western leg of the First Transcontinental Railroad, and became very wealthy as a result. Boardinghouses, food preparation, sewing, and laundry were highly profitable businesses often run by women (married, single, or widowed) who realized men would pay well for a service done by a woman.  Brothels also brought in large profits, especially when combined with saloons and gaming houses.Johnson, Susan Lee. ''Roaring Camp: The social world of the California Gold Rush.'' New York: W.W. Norton (2000), pp. 164-168.

By 1855, the economic climate had changed dramatically. Gold could be retrieved profitably from the goldfields only by medium to large groups of workers, either in partnerships or as employees.Rawls, James J. and Orsi, Richard (eds.) (1999), pp. 52–68. By the mid-1850s, it was the owners of these gold-mining companies who made the money. Also, the population and economy of California had become large and diverse enough that money could be made in a wide variety of conventional businesses.Rawls, James J. and Orsi, Richard (eds.) (1999), pp. 193–197.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3113a9e79edbb461bab392339ab3bbcd" name="P-1252" sectnum="5#1">../img/3113a9e79edbb461bab392339ab3bbcd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>