<document id="e322fc32e045bac8fbbffeab8a471b34-1" name="Ian_Craig" cat="26">
<text>
Shortly after his birth in the rural town of Yass, Craig's father John jokingly told his friends that "Australia's second Don Bradman has just been born".Robinson, p. 259.Haigh, p. 46. Having moved to Sydney from his home town at the age of three, Craig studied at North Sydney Boys High School, while his father rose to be chief manager of the Sydney office of the Bank of New South Wales.Haigh, p. 47. He showed his aptitude for ball sports from an early age. Craig was a member of Australia's schoolboy baseball team for three years, making his first team at only 13 years of age. He was also a member of the state's schoolboy rugby union team and captained the school team, but was only vice captain of the First XI cricket team behind Peter Philpott, another future Test player. At the time, cricket was only his third priority. He joined Mosman Cricket Club on Sydney's North Shore and scored a first-grade century at the age of 16. Craig was not coached heavily; the philosophy of the day was to supervise young players and to only intervene if mistakes were being made.Haigh, p. 30. He was selected to make his first-class debut for New South Wales at the age of 16 years and 249 days, during the 1951&ndash;52 season, making him the youngest ever Sheffield Shield player.Robinson, p. 260.Pollard, p. 54. He struck 91 against South Australia in his only first-class innings of the season, before falling leg before wicket. His first-class career started on a successful note as New South Wales completed an innings victory.

Craig found himself in the state team at the start of the 1952&ndash;53 season. He had moderate success in the first eight matches of the season, scoring 350 runs at 35.00, with three fifties. He was given a chance to push his claims for Test selection after being selected for the Australian XI to play South Africa, but he made only 38 and 11.

Soon after, Craig broke through. In January 1953, at the age of 17 years and 207 days and standing only 170 cm and weighing 63 kg, Craig became the youngest double centurion in the history of first-class cricket, in only his 13th first-class innings. In a match for New South Wales against the touring South Africans, Craig came in with the score at 3/80 and struggled to find the middle of the bat at the start of his innings. After reaching 105 not out by stumps, Craig went to work in the evening as an apprentice pharmacist.

The next day, he resumed and teammate Sid Barnes offered him a new bat if he reached 200. He compiled 213 not out in an innings marked by cover driving, helping to build a total of 416 runs for the loss of seven wickets (7/416). Craig scored his runs quickly, making 98 of the 159 runs scored in a partnership with captain Keith Miller, a Test player known for his attacking strokeplay. Craig brought up his double century by sweeping Hugh Tayfield for a boundary. He remains the youngest Australian to have achieved the feat, although it is no longer a world record. The innings generated comparisons with Don Bradman, widely regarded as the finest batsman in cricket history. Bradman had dominated Australian sports media coverage for two decades until his retirement in 1948 and the Australian public were eager for another sporting hero of his magnitude. Bradman was not playing first-class cricket at 17 and did not make his Test debut until the age of 20,Cashman, pp. 32&ndash;34. so Craig's quicker rise up the ranks caused much excitement. ''The Daily Telegraph'' said that Craig batted with "a grim purposefulness" that was "reminiscent of Bradman". Miller cautioned against heaping so much media pressure on Craig, but the newspapers persisted, even comparing Craig's batting grip to that of Bradman.Perry, pp. 206&ndash;207.

The double century caught the eye of Australian selectors and Craig was selected for the Test team. He was named twelfth man for the Fourth Test, before making his debut in the Fifth Test after Miller and Ray Lindwall were rested due to mild injuries.Cashman, p. 67.Pollard, p. 61. Australia were leading the series 2&ndash;1 heading into the deciding match.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="dacc36cd3c1c12c0aa0fa928c9cc4643" name="Young_sportspeople" sectnum="1#1">../img/dacc36cd3c1c12c0aa0fa928c9cc4643.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>