<document id="e36cb2223c685d1e2803e3f565f797c0-2" name="Birchington-on-Sea" cat="11">
<text>
Birchington-on-Sea is located at  (51.377, 1.305) in northeast Kent, on the coast of the Thames Estuary. The village is 14 kilometres (9 mi) to the east of Herne Bay and 6 kilometres (4 mi) to the west of Margate. The small town of Westgate-on-Sea lies between Birchington and Margate. The village/civil parish of Acol is 2 kilometres (1 mi) to the south and the villages/civil parishes of St Nicholas at Wade and Sarre are 5 kilometres (3 mi) to the southwest.




The village is built beside four sandy bays; Minnis Bay to the west, Grenham Bay and Beresford Gap towards the centre and Epple Bay to the east. The village is situated on the Isle of Thanet, which was a separate island from mainland Kent until around two hundred years ago, when the channel in between became silted up. The area to the west of the village, between Birchington and Herne Bay, was once part of the channel and is now low-lying marshland. In the east of the village the land rises, forming chalk cliffs and cliff stacks around the beaches at Grenham Bay, Beresford Gap and Epple Bay. A sea wall stretches along the foot of the cliffs to prevent further erosion. The geology of Thanet consists mainly of chalk, deposited when the area was below the sea. Isle of Thanet became exposed above sea-level once the English Channel broke through between Kent and France, causing the sea-level to fall. The whole of the northeast Kent coast has been designated a Site of Special Scientific Interest. 

The drinking water in the village is classed as being 'very hard', having just over 120 mg of calcium per litre. The hardness is due to water being obtained from underground chalk sources by the water company Southern Water. Waste water is discharged into the sea after being treated at a sewage works in Margate.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="168ce6658fa2f7a1bf001001655c81aa" name="StNicholasatWade" sectnum="2#1">../img/168ce6658fa2f7a1bf001001655c81aa.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>