<document id="e38896eeb61d78f4decf9e046dbd1427-1.3" name="Ziad_Jarrah" cat="14">
<text>
Jarrah apparently entered the United States on seven separate occasions, more than any other hijacker.  On May 25, 2000, he applied for and received a five-year US B-1/B-2
(tourist/business) visa in Berlin. On June 27, 2000, he came to the U.S. for the first time, arriving at Newark International Airport.  He then traveled to Florida, where he enrolled full-time at the Florida Flight Training Center in Venice.  Jarrah did not apply for a change in his status, from a tourist visa to a student visa, thus violating his immigration status.

Jarrah was enrolled in flight school for six months, from June 2000 to January 15, 2001.  At the flight school, many of his classmates remember him fondly, describing him as kind and trustworthy, and remember him drinking beer occasionally.. p. 163. Retrieved on 2006-09-19.  Jarrah was unique among the hijackers in that he did not live with any other hijackers, but rather lived with a German student named Thorsten Biermann. Biermann did not observe Jarrah acting particularly religiously or overtly politically. Jarrah occasionally flew back to Germany to visit his Turkish-German girlfriend, and called or e-mailed her nearly every day.

Jarrah had obtained his license to fly small planes, and began training to fly large jets late in 2000. He flew to Beirut to visit his family, and then to Germany to visit his girlfriend, Şengün. He brought her back to the United States for a ten-day visit, and she even attended a flight school session with him. In mid-January 2001, he again flew to Beirut to visit his father, who was to have open-heart surgery. He then visited his girlfriend, Şengün, in Germany, and came back to the United States again. His behavior was markedly different from the other hijackers, who broke off all familial and romantic relations.

On his way back to the U.S., he passed through the UAE, according to that country’s officials, where he was initially reported as having been interviewed by authorities on January 30, 2001, at the request of the CIA.
He allegedly admitted to having been to Afghanistan and Pakistan,  although the CIA has since denied the claim and the 9/11 Commission report does not mention it. The Florida flight school where Jarrah had been studying also said he was in school there until January 15, 2001.

On May 6, Jarrah registered for a two-month membership at the US1 Fitness Center, a gym in Dania Beach, Florida&mdash;he would later renew his membership for two more months, and eventually had lessons in close-quarters combat with Bert Rodriguez.  It is believed that sometime in that month Ahmed al-Haznawi, who arrived on June 8, moved in with Jarrah. Jarrah rented a new apartment in Lauderdale-by-the-Sea after both men gave the landlord photocopies of their German passports, which he later turned over to the FBI.

On June 25, Jarrah took al-Haznawi to Holy Cross Hospital in Fort Lauderdale, Florida, on the advice of his landlord, Charles Lisa. Al-Haznawi was treated by Dr. Christos Tsonas, who gave him antibiotics for a small gash on his left calf. While he told staff that he had bumped into a suitcase,  the media briefly reported it as a sign of cutaneous anthrax hoping to show a link to the 2001 anthrax attacks, although the FBI later addressed the rumors stating that, “Exhaustive testing did not support that anthrax was present anywhere the hijackers had been.”

In mid July 2001, some of the hijackers and members of the Hamburg cell gathered near Salou, Spain, for a period of a few days up to a couple of weeks. In late July, Jarrah flew to Germany and again met with his girlfriend, the last time she saw him.  He reportedly arrived back in the United States on August 5, though other sources indicate that he wrote his pilot’s test on August 2, having missed his sister’s wedding to do so.  On August 27, he checked into a Laurel, Maryland, motel, only a mile away from the Valencia where four other hijackers were staying.  ''CBC News'' (Originally aired 2001-10-10, Updated 2005-01-19, Retrieved on 2006-09-13) On September 7, 2001, all four of Flight 93 hijackers flew from Fort Lauderdale to Newark International Airport aboard Spirit Airlines.  Retrieved on 2006-09-13.

On September 9, in the early morning, Jarrah was pulled over for speeding in Maryland and received a US$200 ticket. Jarrah phoned his parents, mentioning that he had received the money order they'd sent five days earlier.  He told them he intended to see them on September 22 for his cousin's wedding, and that he had bought a new suit for the occasion.  His landlady later confirmed that Jarrah had shown off the suit to her days earlier.

On September 10, Jarrah spent the last evening of his life writing a letter to his girlfriend Aysel, the woman he had made marriage plans with. This letter is widely interpreted as a suicide note. Because of an error in the address, the letter was returned to the United States where it was discovered. Some have disputed whether the letter was a suicide note, since it referred to future meetings and the package also contained references to scuba diving instructions. ''CBC News'' (Originally aired 2001-10-10, Updated 2005-01-19, Retrieved on 2006-09-13.)

The note contained the phrases “I did what I was supposed to do” and “You ought to be very proud, because it is an honor and you will see the result(s) and everybody will be happy."


Image:ZiadLetter1.jpg|Page 1
Image:ZiadLetter2.jpg|Page 2
Image:ZiadLetter3.jpg|Page 3
Image:ZiadLetter4.jpg|Page 4


According to one source, Jarrah had set up a large mock cockpit made of cardboard boxes in his apartment just before the attacks.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="350ecedcebb826da9552308105f85fdd" name="May212000StudentVisa-Jarrah" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/350ecedcebb826da9552308105f85fdd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>