<document id="e3ee1c7ad1d30817a8c87665b61a0847-3.1" name="Lives_of_the_Most_Eminent_Literary_and_Scientific_Men" cat="17">
<text>
The ''Italian Lives'' constitute the first two volumes of ''Lives of the Most Eminent Literary and Scientific Men of Italy, Spain and Portugal''. The poet, journalist, and literary historian James Montgomery contributed the biographies of Dante, Ariosto, and Tasso. Historian of science Sir David Brewster contributed that of Galileo. Mary Shelley contributed the rest: Petrarch, Boccaccio, Lorenzo de'Medici, Marsiglio Ficino, Giovanni Pico della Mirandola, Angelo Poliziano, Bernardo Pulci, Luca Pulci, Luigi Pulci, Cieco Da Ferrara, Burchiello, Bojardo, Berni, Machiavelli, Guicciardini, Vittoria Colonna, Guarini, Chiabrera, Tassoni, Marini, Filicaja, Metastasio, Goldoni, Alfieri, Monti, and Ugo Foscolo.Mazzeo, xl, xlviii–li. Although there has been some confusion regarding the attribution of these biographies, the ''Lives'''s recent editor, Tilar Mazzeo, notes that Shelley claimed authorship of all of these and granted Montgomery and Brewster’s authorship of the others in her letters.Mazzeo, xl.

Shelley began the ''Italian Lives'' on 23 November 1833 and by December was working methodically: she wrote the ''Lives'' in the morning and read novels and memoirs in the evening. She added the revision of her novel ''Lodore'' (1835) and the checking of its proofs to this already busy schedule. She worked on the ''Italian Lives'' for two years and was probably paid £140 for each volume. By the time she began working on the ''Lives'', Shelley had spent 20 years studying Italian authors and had lived in Italy for five years.Mazzeo, xli. Her major sources for the biographies were first-person memoirs and literature by the authors, aided by scholarly works. Shelley had gained much of her knowledge of these authors in Italy when she was researching her historical novel ''Valperga'' (1823); the rest she obtained from her own books or those of her father, the philosopher William Godwin. She had limited access to books at this time and was thus restricted to those she owned or could borrow from friends.Mazzeo, xlii. Shelley copied sections from some of these works in a manner that would today be termed plagiarism, but, as Mazzeo explains, because the standards of intellectual property and copyright were so different in the early nineteenth century, Shelley's practice was common and not considered unethical. She writes, "Mary Shelley's objectives in the ''Italian Lives'' were to gather what had been said by these authors and about them and to infuse the work with her own judgements on their interest and credibility." 

To supplement her printed sources, Shelley interviewed Gabriele Rossetti and other Italian expatriates in London for the modern biographies. Mazzeo writes that "her lives of the contemporary Italian poets &ndash; Alfieri, Monti and Foscolo &ndash; are unquestionably the most personal and most inspired of the two volumes".Mazzeo, xliii. Of all of the volumes Shelley contributed to the ''Cabinet Cyclopaedia'', ''Italian Lives'' is, according to editor Nora Crook, the "most overtly political".Crook, xxx. Shelley was a friend to the Italian exiles and a proponent of the ''Risorgimento'';Mazzeo, xlvii. she reveals her republicanism by depicting Machiavelli as a patriot. She continually praises writers who resist tyranny by "cultivat private virtue and inner peace".Crook, xxxi; see also Guerra, 225. In the first volume of the ''Italian Lives'' her primary goal was to introduce lesser-known Italian writers to English readers and build up the reputation of those who were already known,Smith, 131. reflecting the view she expressed in her travel narrative ''Rambles in Germany and Italy'' (1844): "Italian literature claims, at present, a very high rank in Europe. If the writers are less numerous, yet in genius they equal, and in moral taste they surpass France and England".Qtd. in Mazzeo, xlvii. 


Shelley specifically addressed gender politics in her biography of the sixteenth-century poet Vittoria Colonna, highlighting her literary achievements, her "virtues, talents, and beauty", and her interest in politics.Smith, 135. However, Shelley was careful to describe feminine virtues in their historical context throughout the ''Italian Lives''. For example, her analysis of the ''cavalier servente'' system in Italy, which allowed married women to take lovers, was rooted in an understanding that many marriages at the time were made not for love, but for profit. She refused to indict any particular woman for what she saw as the faults of a larger system.

Little has been written on the contributions by Montgomery or Brewster. According to Mazzeo, Montgomery’s biographies, which draw a picture of the subject's character and incorporate autobiographical material, are written in a "digressive though not unengaging manner". He is less concerned with factual accuracy, although he identifies his sources, and more interested in developing "extended parallels between Italian and English literature". Brewster includes descriptions of sixteenth-century scientific experiments in his formally written biography of Galileo, as well as information on other Renaissance natural philosophers. According to Mazzeo, "Brewster’s pious religiosity infuses the work and his opinions".

Ninety-eight review copies of the first two volumes were distributed, eliciting five reviews. Some of these were simply short advertisements for the ''Cabinet Cyclopaedia''. Mazzeo writes that the "commentary on both volumes was mixed and often contradictory, but on balance positive; prose style, organisation and use of source materials were the three most often identified points of discussion".Mazzeo, xxxix. The first volume was declared to be unorganised, the second volume less so. Reviewers did not agree on the value of frequently using primary sources nor on the elegance of the writing style. The ''Monthly Review'' dedicated the most substantial review and extracts to the volumes, writing that "we by no means think highly of the volume as a whole", complaining that it presented facts and dates without context. However, the reviewer praised two of Mary Shelley’s biographies: Petrarch and Machiavelli. According to Mazzeo, the reviewer "notes, in particular, her efforts to question conventional assumptions about Machiavelli by returning to autobiographical materials and credits her with originality on this point". ''Graham's Magazine'', in a piece probably by its co-editor, Edgar Allan Poe, positively reviewed the pirated American edition.Mazzeo, xxxix–xl.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="52608bfa97fac81f25a9034cadcfc0d9" name="James_Montgomery" sectnum="3.1#1">../img/52608bfa97fac81f25a9034cadcfc0d9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>