<document id="e3f8085aa0f488853acaa00f7e5e8d17-7" name="Oceanic_whitetip_shark" cat="3">
<text>
It is a commercially important species to the extent that its fins are prized for soup and its meat and oil frequently used. It is used fresh, smoked, dried and salted for human consumption and its hide is used for leather. It is subject to fishing pressure throughout virtually its whole range &mdash; although it is more often taken as by-catch than by design, since it takes bait from longlines intended for other species.

Famed oceanographic researcher Jacques Cousteau described the oceanic whitetip as "the most dangerous of all sharks". Despite the greater notoriety of the great white shark and other sharks habitually found nearer the shore, the oceanic whitetip is considered responsible for more fatal attacks on humans than all other species combined, as a result of predation on those shipwrecked or from aircraft downed in the open ocean. These incidents are not included in common shark-attack indices for the 20th and 21st centuries, but would appear to total in the thousands worldwide, with one incident alone, the torpedoing of USS ''Indianapolis'' on 30 July 1945, giving a minimum figure of between 60 and 80 sailors killed by sharks. It is said by some that tiger sharks were responsible for some of the ''Indianapolis'' deaths, but this has never been confirmed.   
Also during World War II, the ''Nova Scotia'', a steamship carrying approximately 1,000 people near South Africa, was torpedoed and sunk by a German submarine. There were only 192 survivors, and many deaths were attributed to the oceanic whitetip shark.

The oceanic whitetip poses a minimal threat to bathers or inshore sportsman, but a high risk for humans caught in the open ocean in conditions in which they might be seen as prey.  

Although the oceanic whitetip is highly opportunistic and aggressive, and has been known to attack humans for food, divers have swum with this shark repeatedly without being harmed. Divers are advised to approach the shark only with extreme caution, not spear fish near this shark and, if the shark comes too close or gets too inquisitive, to get out of the water as soon as possible. It is suggested regarding sharks in general that if a shark begins to push a diver, it should be hit on the snout, gills or eyes; however, anecdotal evidence suggests that this may be less effective in deterring whitetips.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fdc36434438863a59274f73635010842" name="Oceanic_Whitetip_Shark" sectnum="7#1">../img/fdc36434438863a59274f73635010842.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>