<document id="e3f8085aa0f488853acaa00f7e5e8d17-5" name="Oceanic_whitetip_shark" cat="3">
<text>
The oceanic whitetip is usually solitary and slow-moving, and tends to cruise near the top of the water column, covering vast stretches of empty water scanning for possible food sources. Until the 16th century, sharks were known to mariners as 'sea dogs' and the oceanic whitetip, the most common ship-following shark, exhibits dog-like behavior when its interest is piqued: when attracted to something that appears to be food, its movements become more avid and it will approach cautiously but stubbornly, retreating and maintaining the minimum safe distance if driven off, but ready for a rush of boldness if the opportunity presents itself. Oceanic whitetips are not fast sharks, but they are capable of surprising bursts of speed. It is commonly found competing for food with silky sharks, making up for its comparatively leisurely swimming style with an aggressive attitude. 

Groups are often formed when nearby individuals converge on a food source, whereupon the fabled "feeding frenzy" may occur. This seems to be triggered not by blood in the water ''per se'', or by bloodlust, but by the species' highly strung and goal-directed nature (conserving energy between infrequent feeding opportunities when it is not slowly plying the open ocean). The oceanic whitetip is a competitive, opportunistic predator with great incentive to exploit the resource at hand, rather than avoiding trouble in favor of a possibly easier meal in the future. 

There does not seem to be a segregation by sex and size as with some other species. Whitetips will follow schools of tuna or squid, and will trail groups of cetaceans such as dolphins and pilot whales as scavengers of their prey. Their instinct to follow is so strongly imprinted, as the result of countless millennia of baitfish migrations, that they will accompany ocean-going ships. When whaling took place in warm waters, oceanic whitetips were often responsible for much of the damage to floating carcasses.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e4c1933237226c364ca1916cce12f7d7" name="Carcharhinus_longimanus_1" sectnum="5#1">../img/e4c1933237226c364ca1916cce12f7d7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>