<document id="e437793f642dbcf45b2bc0d88d1ce118-2.6" name="The_Stolen_Earth" cat="19">
<text>
"The Stolen Earth" features the first external location shots of the Daleks since the revival of ''Doctor Who'' in 2005, and the greatest proportion of filming undertaken at night since the show's revival: apart from the pre-credits sequence set in suburban London, all of the scenes set on Earth were filmed at night. 

The two-parter took approximately six weeks in 2008 to film; regular filming began on 18 February 2008 and ended on 29 March 2008. The first scene shot for "The Stolen Earth"—a news report featuring Lachele Carl as Trinity Wells—was filmed on 31 January 2008 in a news studio at BBC Wales' Broadcasting House.Broadcasting House Cardiff (Trinity Wells' news report):  The first week of filming took place entirely at the show's studios in Upper Boat, Rhondda Cynon Taff;BBC Studios, Upper Boat (TARDIS, Torchwood Hub, Dalek Crucible, Sarah Jane Smith's attic):  most of the scenes set in the Torchwood Hub and the TARDIS—including the regeneration scene—were filmed in the period.

The filming schedule of the second and third week alternated between "The Stolen Earth" and "Journey's End". Three days were allocated to filming for "The Stolen Earth": scenes in Donna's house were filmed on 26 February 2008 on Nant Fawr Road, Cyncoed, Cardiff;Nant Fawr Road, Cyncoed (Noble family home):  the ''Crucible'' Vault set in the Upper Boat Studios was used on 3 March 2008; and scenes at the Shadow Proclamation were filmed at the School of Optometry at Cardiff UniversityCardiff School of Optometry (The Shadow Proclamation):  on 8 March 2008.

Filming for the episode's outdoor scenes began in the afternoon of 11 March 2008, with filming of the cold open taking place on West Mound Cresent in Tonteg.West Mound Crescent, Tonteg (The Doctor and Donna exit the TARDIS; Rose teleports to Earth shortly after it is moved):  Two scenes were filmed in Pontypridd on 12 March: exterior scenes of the Noble household took place on Hawthorn Road—Hawthorn Road, Pontypridd (Noble household exterior):  rather than the usual location in Cyncoed—before relocating to Market Street in the town centreComputing Wales, Market Street, Pontypridd (Megabyte City computer store and exterior):  to film the scenes where Rose encounters members of the public looting shops. Tennant and Tate meanwhile filmed the trailer for the fourth series because they were not required on location.

The Doctor and Rose's reunion was filmed on 13 March 2008 in Penarth town centreHigh Street–Arcot Street–Queen's Road–Paget Road intersection, Penarth (The Doctor and Rose's reunion):  in front of two hundred people; consequently, the scene was leaked onto the Internet and reported in the next day's edition of ''The Sun''. Graeme Harper insisted that the scene appear "mystical" because the characters' reunion was "the most magical moment" in the entire episode; and Ernie Vincze, the Director of Photography for the show, compared the scene's feeling to 1980s science-fiction film ''Blade Runner''. Exterior filming for the week finished in Brook StreetBrook Street, Riverside, Cardiff (Dalek attack on suburbia):  and the adjoining Plantagenet StreetPlantagener Street, Riverside, Cardiff (Wilf shoot a paintball at a Dalek): ) in Riverside, Cardiff, for scenes depicting Daleks kidnapping humans for experimentation and Wilf shooting a Dalek with a paintball gun, respectively. Scenes in the UNIT headquarters in Manhattan were filmed on the evenings of 16 March and 19 March: the first night, depicting the Dalek invasion, was filmed in a traffic control centre on Junction 32 of the M4 motorwaySouth Wales Traffic Management Centre (UNIT HQ: Dalek invasion): , with the actual Dalek invasion of the building filmed in six minutes at 5:30am the following morning; and the second night, depicting Martha's escape from UNIT, was filmed in a warehouse in Nantgarw belonging to the National Museum Wales.National Museum Wales Collection Centre, Parc Nantgarw (UNIT HQ: Martha's escape):  Because of a traffic accident on the first night, the production team were prepared to postpone the shoot.

Penelope Wilton reprised her role as Harriet Jones to film a scene on 18 March 2008, in a cottage in Dinas Powys, Wales.Lower House Barn, Dinas Powys (Harriet Jones' house):  Filming was stalled because of difficulty transporting the Dalek props into the cottage—specifically, the raised patio doors made it difficult to balance and maneuver the props. The remainder of the fifth week was used to film Dalek-only scenes at Upper Boat Studios, when the Vault set was redressed as the ''Crucible'' command deck. Scenes depicting Martha and Sarah in their houses were filmed alternately during the sixth week—the former in the previously-regular location of Lower Cwrt-Y-Vil Road in PenarthLower Cwrt-Y-Vil Road, Penarth (Jones household):  and the latter primarily at Upper Boat—, ending on 28 March 2008 with scenes of Sarah and Luke in their attic. The last exterior scene filmed for the episode was recorded on 25 March in the regular ''The Sarah Jane Adventures'' filming location of Clinton Road in Penarth,Clinton Road (Bannerman Road: exterior shots of Sarah's house; and Sarah is accosted by the Daleks):  and consisted of external shots of Sarah's house and Sarah being accosted by two Daleks en-route to meeting the Doctor. General filming for the episode—and the two-parter—closed with Dawkins' and O'Grady's cameos: Dawkins was filmed at Upper Boat after shooting finished in the attic set; and O'Grady was filmed on 31 March 2008 alongside an episode of ''The Paul O'Grady Show'' at The London Studios on the South Bank of the River Thames.The London Studios, South Bank (The Paul O' Grady Show):
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f49f804a9527e02f141d48732f0942da" name="The_Stolen_Earth_filming,_13_March_2008" sectnum="2.6#1">../img/f49f804a9527e02f141d48732f0942da.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>