<document id="e437793f642dbcf45b2bc0d88d1ce118-3.10" name="The_Stolen_Earth" cat="19">
<text>
The episode was well received by the episode's viewers; most notably, the show's teenage fanbase. In ''Doctor Who Magazine'''s 2008 viewer poll, the episode won the awards for as "Best Story", "Best Guest Actor" for Julian Bleach, "Best Monster" for the Daleks, "Best Music", and "Best Villain" for Davros; the latter was won with a supermajority of the votes cast. The episode was the best-received episode of the fourth series among members of the Doctor Who Forum, with an approval rating of 92.4%.

''The Guardian'' published three reviews of the episode. Sam Wollaston gave the episode a positive review; he thought it was a "wonderful episode" that "would be hard to top".  Wollaston joked in his review about Richard Dawkins's cameo, comparing his anti-theological mannerisms to the Daleks.  Gareth McLean described the end of the episode as a "genuine, jaw-dropping, outta-nowhere cliffhanger".  He commended the production team for successfully suppressing information about the regeneration in an industry often stifled by leaks.  Stephen Brook of ''The Guardian''s media blog ''Organgrinder'', thought the episode was "unbelievably good" and "genuinely scary and exciting".  He theorised about the questionable regeneration: whether it was genuine and, if so, who would portray the next incarnation of the Doctor; and which companion will die in "Journey's End".

''The Independent's'' Thomas Sutcliffe gave the episode a negative review, expressing that the episode was "extermination without inspiration". Before the episode's transmission, he was excited about how Dawkins and O'Grady would appear, and was disappointed when they only appeared when Ianto was channel surfing. Sutcliffe expressed disbelief at the idea that O'Grady would continue to film his talk show, and with a studio audience, in the midst of planetary disaster, but nevertheless praised the cameos. After the cameos, he "began to lose interest" because he did not like the continuity and crossover elements of the episode. He criticised the re-occurrence of the lines "But... that's impossible!", "It can't be!", and "Exterminate!". He closed his review by requesting the producers to "change the record".

Mark Wright of ''The Stage'' posed the question: "How on Earth do you review that?". Wright put the episode as "the most bonkers, delicious, audacious, brilliant, silly, exciting and scary piece of Doctor Who seen in the 45-year history of  TV series", and described it as "Doctor Who at its most show stopping, entertaining and brilliant best." In his review, Wright explained his love of crossover fiction, and commended Davies for the direction he took ''Doctor Who'' into becoming what Wright considered to be a "small television industry". Wright complimented the way the episode was in-keeping with tradition, specifically aspects such as; "Daleks trundling around spaceships having shouty conversations with each other"; "UNIT  as useless as ever at repelling alien marauders", and the visual appearance of Davros. He described Bleach's portrayal as a "halfway house between the original version as played by Michael Wisher and the more exuberant...turn by Terry Molloy". He also thought positively of the final scenes, commenting that "the most flint-hearted must have had a misty eye as Rose found her Time Lord again and they ran towards each other in candy box slow-mo" and he cheered when the "outpouring of romance was brought to an end, as it should be in Doctor Who, by a big Dalek gun".

Ben Rawson-Jones of Digital Spy gave the episode five stars out of five. In his review, he states that "'The Stolen Earth' does a fine job in weaving components from the current series, former companions, and Davros together." He wrote that he admires Graeme Harper's direction of the scene where Sarah and Jack receive the continuous "Exterminate!" transmission from the Daleks, stating that "Harper's work ... is worthy of the big screen in terms of its breathtaking visual elements." He complimented the casting of Michael Brandon as General Sanchez, and expressed hope that Sanchez had survived the Dalek attack because he had the potential to be "the new Brigadier figure that UNIT so desperately needs". Rawson-Jones thought Briggs, as the voice of the Daleks, did a "superb job with Dalek Caan's crazy dialect, stemming from a very inventive and bold move by writer Russell T Davies to make this Dalek go doolally". He praised Bleach's performance as Davros, for his "controlled, sinister vocals" that "wonderfully evoke the brilliant but deranged mindset of the Dalek creator". Upon closing, he commended Davies for being "an expert at delivering jaw-dropping finales that give each season a sense of cohesion and up the stakes to almost unbearable levels", and thought that matching the episode's quality would be a "tough task".


Alan Stanley Blair of SyFy Portal was positive in his review. In his opinion, the episode never failed to deliver and "acts as a tribute to everything Russell T Davies put in place when he resurrected the series in 2005." He described the storyline as "fast-moving, bursting  excitement" and said that it contained "everything you would expect to see from an adventure comprising of all companions and a new Dalek empire, the episode acts as the ultimate climax to four years of storytelling and will leave you with goose bumps for the full 42 minutes." Blair was impressed about how ''Torchwood'' and ''Doctor Who'' crossed over when their original target demographics dictated it "should never have happened". Scenes depicting Gwen's concern for her husband Rhys, Ianto watching ''The Paul O'Grady Show'', and Sarah's and Jack's emotional response to the Dalek transmission, were praised by Blair. Although his review was positive, he did criticise two parts of the episode: the concept of the Time War being "time-locked", which was questioned because the Time Lords were annihilated in the conflict; and he complained that the Doctor's phone number was out of service.

Dan Wainwright of ''The Express & Star'' in Wolverhampton, expressed feelings of denial in response to the episode's ending. He asked: "Surely not even Russell T Davies, who seems obsessed with filling episodes with celebrity cameos and John Barrowman, wouldn’t be so maverick as to change his lead actor half way through a season finale?" In his review, Wainwright expressed feelings of amicability and hatred towards Davies for his role in reviving Doctor Who, particularly disliking Davies for romanticising the character. Although he admired Davies for making the series popular among children. Catherine Tuckewell, writing for Blogcritics, gave a positive review. She opened by saying "Russell T Davies has again extended the boundaries of most infuriating cliffhangers." She commended the cast for "top notch acting" that brought "a whole new level of emotion to the series", specifically Jack and Sarah's reaction to the Dalek warcry transmission, which "brought tears to her eyes". Tuckewell praised the production team for "the most beautiful  outside the Hubble telescope" and the direction which showed the Daleks "at their fearful best".  

Simon Brew of science-fiction blog ''Den of Geek'' commented that "If the aim of a really well done Doctor Who cliffhanger is to leaving you screaming 'noooooooooo' at the screen and frantically checking the calendar for the next episode, then it’s fair to say that Russell T Davies has just managed to tick that box." His review both criticised and praised the episode: he summarised the episode as "bursting with a breathless ambition that papered over its occasional cracks"; but lamented that the plot detail felt "muddled" because of how many plot devices were compressed into the episode. Brew thought the ensemble of companions "separated the great actors from the good": he complimented Sladen's and Cribbins's portrayal of fear; and he criticised UNIT, Torchwood, and the Doctor for uncharacteristically admitting defeat.  Brew's opinion of Davros and Caan was positive, commenting that "Julian Bleach nailed " and the appearance of Davros was "very reverential" to the classic series and that Caan " an interesting dynamic to the Dalek fight".  He closed his review by expressing hope that "Journey's End" didn't end like "Last of the Time Lords" and said: 

Charlie Jane Anders of the science fiction blog io9 called Davies "the gay Michael Bay" and "wished for the first time that Davies would stay on to produce a fifth season" of ''Doctor Who''. She "loved all the silly plot devices and loopy plot twists" such as Project Indigo, the Osterhagen Key, the concept of using "every telephone in England" to call the Doctor, and the fact that Davros was unable to cultivate a Dalek army "without slicing his own torso up". Anders in her review praised Bleach's portrayal of Davros for capturing "the character's mixture of curiosity, manipulativeness and mania better than anyone since ...Michael Wisher". She also commended the "super-heroics" in the episode, such as Wilf shooting a Dalek with a paint-ball gun, Gwen and Ianto's final scene, and the "glowing nobility" of Harriet Jones' sacrifice to help the Doctor: Closing her review, she expressed excitement for "Journey's End", saying the final scene left her with a "feeling like  no clue how it could be resolved, even using crazy RTD logic".

Dave Golder of science-fiction magazine ''SFX'' gave the episode four stars out of five. He noted that after two experimental and "edgy" scripts, "The Stolen Earth" used Davies' regular style of "crowd pleasing script pyrotechnics". He positively reviewed the special effects in the episode, Bleach's acting, the pace of the episode, and the cliffhanger, but  criticised the Shadow Proclamation for being "a severe disappointment after all the foreshadowing", and some character moments for being "dropped into the action like little 'emotion bombs'", such as Jack and Sarah's "melodramatic response" to the Dalek transmission. He closed his review by saying "there's no denying  all huge fun, like a tipsy romp on a bouncy castle with all the people you’ve ever loved."

Travis Flickett of IGN gave the episode 7.6/10 ("Enjoyable"). He opened his review by discussing the concept of "fan service":

His review focused primarily upon the Daleks. He initially criticised their appearance because of overuse; he discussed their previous appearances in ''Doctor Who'' since 2005: a singular enemy in "Dalek"; a Dalek empire against Rose in "The Parting of the Ways"; the Dalek Cult of Skaro against the Cybermen in "Doomsday"; and their appearance in 1930s Manhattan in "Daleks in Manhattan" and "Evolution of the Daleks". He cited Davros and the "year-and-a-half" break as the reason their appearance "sort-of worked"; Davros' appearance " the stakes", but he criticised the character for " little to enhance the mythology" and Bleach for a "way over the top" performance. Flickett criticised Rose's isolation from the other companions, but noted that she could defend against the Daleks on her own. He closed his review positively; he said "Whatever the conclusion of this season, Davies run on this series is an enormous achievement."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f6b4dca2e71921142fa0d78d37a31c0c" name="Russelltdaviescrop" sectnum="3.10#1">../img/f6b4dca2e71921142fa0d78d37a31c0c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>