<document id="e48a52440222eaa7c3b68b0b1ae9990f-5" name="TARDIS" cat="19">
<text>
Other TARDISes have appeared in the television series, starting with the TARDIS of the Meddling Monk in the 1965 serial ''The Time Meddler''. The Master had at least two TARDISes of his own, each a more advanced model than the Doctor's. The chameleon circuits on these were fully functional, and his TARDISes have been seen in various forms, including a fully functional spacecraft, a grandfather clock, a fireplace, an Ionic column, a lorry, a statue (able to move and walk around), a fir tree, and an iron maiden. In the reconstructed ''Shada'', the Time Lord known as Professor Chronotis has a TARDIS disguised as his quarters at Cambridge University. His was the only TARDIS ever seen in the TV series that was older than the Doctor's (or would have been had the story been finished as scheduled).

Other Time Lords with TARDISes included the Meddling Monk and the Rani. In ''The Armageddon Factor'', Time Lord Drax has a TARDIS, but it is in need of repair. The War Chief provided dimensionally transcendent time machines named SIDRATs (Space and Inter-Dimensional Robot All-purpose Transporter, according to the novelisation of ''The War Games'') to the alien race known as the War Lords. In the script for ''The Chase'', Dalek time machines are known as DARDISes. 

In the spin-off media, Gallifreyan Battle TARDISes have appeared in the comic books, novels and audio plays, which fire "time torpedoes" that freeze the target in time. The renegade Time Lady Iris Wildthyme's own TARDIS was disguised as a No. 22 London Bus, but was slightly smaller on the inside than it is on the outside. The Eighth Doctor Adventures novels have stated that future model Type 102 TARDISes will be fully sentient, and able to take on humanoid form (''Alien Bodies''). The Eighth Doctor's companion Compassion was the first Type 102 TARDIS (''The Shadows of Avalon''), and she was seen to have enough firepower to annihilate other TARDISes (''The Ancestor Cell''). Compassion and other humanoid timeships appear in the ''Faction Paradox'' spin-off material.  

The "unofficial" Ninth Doctor from the 40th anniversary animated webcast ''Scream of the Shalka'' had a TARDIS console room that looked similar to the Eighth Doctor's version.

In the Big Finish audio play ''The One Doctor'', confidence trickster Banto Zame impersonated the Doctor. However, due to incomplete information, his copy of the TARDIS (a short range transporter) was called a Stardis instead, resembled a portaloo rather than a police box, and was not dimensionally transcendental. In ''Unregenerate!'', the Seventh Doctor and Mel stopped a secret Time Lord project to download TARDIS minds into bodies of various alien species. This would have created living TARDIS pilots loyal to the Time Lords and ensuring that they would have ultimate control over any use of time travel technology by other races. Those created before the project was shut down departed on their own to explore the universe.

Since the destruction of Gallifrey and the Time Lords as stated in the 2005 series, the Doctor believes that his TARDIS is the last in the universe ("Rise of the Cybermen", 2006). The removal of Gallifrey—and by implication the Eye of Harmony—may also be why the TARDIS in "Boom Town" needed to refuel using radiation from a space-time rift. In "Rise of the Cybermen" the Doctor also states that the TARDIS draws power from "the universe", but is unable to do so while in an alternate reality.

The 28 October 2006 ''Radio Times'', in an image of the Torchwood Three headquarters, identified a piece of large coral on Captain Jack Harkness's desk as the beginnings of a TARDIS. John Barrowman, who plays Jack in ''Torchwood'' and ''Doctor Who'' confirmed that "Jack's growing a TARDIS... It's probably been there for 30 years. I suppose in 500 years he'll be able to begin the carving process".

In the 2008 Christmas special edition, ''The Next Doctor'', Jackson Lake (David Morrissey), while under the delusion that he is the Doctor, has a hot air balloon of the same colour and name as the TARDIS, which he explains as standing for "'''T'''ethered '''A'''erial '''R'''elease '''D'''eveloped '''I'''n '''S'''tyle". It is not capable of time travel.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1171d3f57fd6b4cdf2c198e15f13a983" name="Rani_TARDIS" sectnum="5#1">../img/1171d3f57fd6b4cdf2c198e15f13a983.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>