<document id="e48a52440222eaa7c3b68b0b1ae9990f-3.2" name="TARDIS" cat="19">
<text>
The TARDIS interior has a vast number of rooms and corridors. The exact dimensions of the interior have not been specified, but apart from living quarters, the interior includes an art gallery (which is actually an ancillary power station), a greenhouse, a bathroom with a swimming pool (which was jettisoned by the Seventh Doctor in "Paradise Towers" after it sprang a leak), a medical bay, several brick-walled storage areas (all seen in ''The Invasion of Time'', 1978), and a secondary control room (with ornate wood panels, and was used for a time by the Fourth Doctor).  Portions of the TARDIS can also be isolated or reconfigured; the Doctor was able to jettison 25% of the TARDIS's structure in ''Castrovalva'' to provide additional "thrust".

Despite a widespread assumption that the interior of the TARDIS is infinite, there are indications that it is not. In ''Full Circle'' (1980), Romana stated that the weight of the TARDIS in Alzarius' Earth-like gravity was 5 × 106 kilograms (5000 tonnes). This presumably refers to its internal weight, as the external part of the TARDIS is light enough for it to be lifted or otherwise moved with relative ease (although most real police boxes were concrete and hence quite difficult to move): several men lift it up in ''Marco Polo'', a group of small blue maintenance workers on Platform One push it along the ground in "The End of the World", and a quartet of Weeping Angels are able to rock it back and forth in "Blink", to name a few. If the exterior of the TARDIS is moved, the movement is transmitted to its interior.

In the tie-in novels, the interior of the TARDIS has been known to contain an entire city (''Cat's Cradle: Time's Crucible''), used to encompass an entire parallel Earth (''Blood Heat''), and is big enough to dwarf Gallifrey itself when turned inside out (''The Ancestor Cell''). It is also seen to exist in multiple timelines.

A distinctive architectural feature of the TARDIS interior is the "roundel". In the context of the TARDIS, a roundel is a circular decoration that adorns the walls of the rooms and corridors of the TARDIS, including the console room. Some roundels conceal TARDIS circuitry and devices, as seen in the serials ''The Wheel in Space'' (1968), ''Logopolis'', ''Castrovalva'' (1981), ''Arc of Infinity'' (1983), ''Terminus'' (1983), and ''Attack of the Cybermen'' (1985). The design of the roundels has varied throughout the show's history, from a basic circular cut-out with black background to a photographic image printed on wall board, to translucent illuminated discs in later serials. In the secondary console room, most of the roundels were executed in recessed wood panelling, with a few decorative ones in what appeared to be stained glass. In the new series, the roundels are built into hexagonal recesses in the walls of the new console room.

Other rooms seen include living quarters for many of the Doctor's companions, although the Doctor's own bedroom has never been mentioned or seen. The TARDIS also had a "Zero Room"—a chamber that was shielded from the rest of the universe and provided a restful environment for the Fifth Doctor to recover from his regeneration in ''Castrovalva''—which was among the 25% jettisoned. However, the Seventh Doctor spin-off novel ''Deceit'' indicated that the Doctor rebuilt the Zero Room shortly before the events of that novel. In some of the First Doctor serials, a nearby room contains a machine that dispenses food or nutrition bars to the Doctor and his companions. This machine disappears after the first few serials, although mention is occasionally made of the TARDIS kitchen.

Although the interior corridors were not seen in the 2005 series, the fact that they still exist was established in "The Unquiet Dead", when the Doctor gives Rose some very complicated directions to the TARDIS wardrobe. The wardrobe is mentioned several times in the original series and spin-off fiction, and seen in ''The Androids of Tara'' (1978), ''The Twin Dilemma'' (1984) and ''Time and the Rani'' (1987). The redesigned version, from which the Tenth Doctor chooses his new clothes, was seen in "The Christmas Invasion" (2005) as a large multi-levelled room with a helical staircase. Designer Ed Thomas has suggested that more rooms may be seen in coming episodes. The Doctor also mentions in "The Shakespeare Code" that the TARDIS has an attic.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a78b739044a455e66870caa0c8a8d208" name="TARDIS_wardrobe" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/a78b739044a455e66870caa0c8a8d208.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>