<document id="e497f7958ab3dea210df63f8323e5abf-5" name="North_Island_(Houtman_Abrolhos)" cat="11">
<text>
Most of North Island is dominated by chenopod shrubs, generally less than a metre (3 ft) high. The beach vegetation is largely ''Spinifex longifolius'' (Beach Spinifex), ''Salsola kali'' (Prickly Saltwort), ''Atriplex cinerea'' (Grey Saltbush) and naturalised ''Cakile maritima'' (Sea Rocket). Stable dunes are vegetated by ''Atriplex paludosa'' (Marsh Saltbush), ''Scaevola crassifolia'' (Thick-leaved Fan-flower), ''Olearia axillaris'' (Coastal Daisy-bush), ''Myoporum insulare'' (Blueberry Tree) and ''Exocarpos sparteus'' (Broom Ballart). Sheltered areas behind dunes support ''Salsola kali'' and ''Myoporum insulare'' and also ''Nitraria billardierei'' (Nitre Bush), the last of these being the only plant on the island to grow over  m (5 ft) high. In areas where limestone is close to the surface, the vegetation consists of ''Pimelea microcephala'' (Shrubby Rice-flower), ''Spyridium globulosum'' (Basket Bush) and ''Acanthocarpus preissii''.

The rim of the central plain is vegetated by a dense shrubland of ''Rhagodia baccata'' (Berry Saltbush), ''Atriplex paludosa'' and ''Threlkeldia diffusa'' (Coast Bonefruit). Nearer the centre, the vegetation consists of ''Frankenia pauciflora'' (Seaheath), ''Muellerolimon salicorniaceum'' and ''Tecticornia arbuscula'' (Bulli Bulli), although ''T. arbuscula'' is replaced by ''Tecticornia halocnemoides'' (Shrubby Samphire) where the soil is shallow. The most low-lying area of the central plain, south of the salt lake, is water-logged in winter; it is vegetated by a dense mat of ''Sarcocornia quinqueflora'' (Beaded Samphire), ''Sporobolus virginicus'' (Marine Couch) and ''Suaeda australis'' (Seablite).

The dune, limestone and salt lake vegetation communities on North Island are considered to have high conservation significance. The dune and limestone communities have high biodiversity, are highly sensitive to disturbance and regenerate slowly. The salt lake community is considered significant because of the rarity of salt lakes on offshore islands.

According to a survey published in 2001, the following vascular plants occur on North Island:
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e9407273304d3d26738f8ff3e983de47" name="Dunes,_North_Island,_Houtman_Abrolhos" sectnum="5#1">../img/e9407273304d3d26738f8ff3e983de47.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>