<document id="e4c792a4b6681bdee4e4f940376294d0-6" name="Tom_Crean_(explorer)" cat="14">
<text>
Upon returning to Britain in November 1916, Crean resumed naval duties.  He was specially promoted to the rank of Warrant Officer (as a Boatswain) in recognition of his service on the ''Endurance,'' on 15 December,Admiralty Certificate of Qualification for Warrant Officer, 17 August 1917, referenced in Smith, p. 300 and was awarded his third Polar Medal. Crean married Ellen Herlihy of Annascaul on 5 September 1917.  He saw quiet service in the First World War, at the Chatham barracks and then on HMS ''Colleen''.  

In early 1920, Shackleton was organising another Antarctic expedition, later to be known as the Shackleton-Rowett Expedition.  He invited Crean, along with other officers from the ''Endurance''.  By this time, Crean was married, his second daughter had arrived, and he had plans to open a business following his naval career.  He turned down Shackleton's invitation.Smith, p. 308

On his last assignment, with  HMS ''Hecla'', Crean suffered a bad fall which caused lasting effects to his vision. As a result, he was retired on medical grounds on 24 March 1920.Smith, p. 304 He and Ellen opened a small pub in Annascaul called the South Pole Inn.Smith, p. 309 They had three daughters, Mary, Kate, and Eileen,Smith, p. 306 although Kate died when she was four years old.  

Throughout his life, Crean remained an extremely modest man. When he returned to Kerry, he put all of his medals away and never again spoke about his experiences in the Antarctic. Indeed, there is no reliable evidence of Crean giving any interviews to the press.Smith, p. 312  It has been speculated that this may have been because Kerry had long been a centre for Irish nationalism, and it would have been inappropriate for an Irishman to speak of his achievements on British polar expeditions. Crean became ill with a burst appendix in 1938. He was taken to the nearest hospital in Tralee but as no surgeon was available there to operate he was transferred to Cork where his appendix was removed.  As the operation had been delayed an infection took over and after a week in the hospital he died on 27 July 1938, shortly after his sixty-first birthday.

Crean was buried in his family tomb at the cemetery in Ballynacourty.Smith, p. 314  He is commemorated in at least two place names: Mount Crean   in Victoria Land, and the Crean Glacier on South Georgia.Smith, p. 318 A one-man play about Crean's life, devised by Aidan Dooley, has been widely performed since 2001, including a special showing at the South Pole Inn, Annascaul, in October 2001. Present were Crean's daughters, Eileen and Mary, both in their 80s. Apparently he never told them his stories; according to Eileen: "He put his medals and his sword in a box  and that was that. He was a very humble man".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="af209f6bbd61d7406e2797019f73e29f" name="crean_statue" sectnum="6#1">../img/af209f6bbd61d7406e2797019f73e29f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>