<document id="e4c792a4b6681bdee4e4f940376294d0-2" name="Tom_Crean_(explorer)" cat="14">
<text>
Crean sailed with Captain Scott and the crew of the ''Discovery'' out of Port Chalmers, New Zealand on 21 December 1901, bound for the Antarctic. The ship anchored in McMurdo Sound on 8 February 1902, at a spot which was designated as "Hut Point". Hut Point was the name given to the location, alongside the ship's mooring, of the expedition's main storage hut. The hut was used in later expeditions as a shelter and storage depot. Here the men established the winter quarters from which they would launch scientific and exploratory sledging journeys.  Crean soon established himself as one of the most consistent man-haulers in the party, with only seven of the 48-member party logging more time in harness than Crean's 149 days.Smith, p. 46&ndash;47  Crean had a good sense of humour and was well-liked by the men.  Captain Scott's second-in-command, Albert Armitage, wrote in his book ''Two Years in the Antarctic'' that "Crean was an Irishman with a fund of wit and an even temper which nothing disturbed."Smith, p. 46 It was at this time that he formed close friendships with William Lashly and Edgar Evans: all three would establish themselves as seasoned polar explorers over the next decade.

Crean accompanied Lieutenant Michael Barne on three sledging trips across the Ross Ice Shelf, then known as the "Barrier".  These included the 12-man party led by Barne which set out on 30 October 1902 to lay depots in support of the main southern journey, undertaken by Captain Scott, Shackleton and Edward Wilson.  On 11 November the Barne party passed the previous furthest south mark,Smith, p. 55 set by Carsten Borchgrevink in 1900 at 78°50'S, a record which they held briefly until the southern party itself passed it on its way to 82°17'S.Crane, pp. 214&ndash;15. Modern re-calculations based on photographs have placed this furthest south at 82°11'S (Crane map, p. 215).
 
During the winter of 1902 ''Discovery'' became locked in the ice. Efforts to free her during the Antarctic summer of 1902&ndash;03 failed, so Crean and the rest of the men did not leave the Antarctic until the ship was finally freed in February 1904.  After returning to civilization, Crean was promoted to Petty Officer 1st Class, on Captain Scott's recommendation.Smith, p. 70
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="28487078456bb0ab721f7a135f0854a4" name="Hut_Point_Antarctica" sectnum="2#1">../img/28487078456bb0ab721f7a135f0854a4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>