<document id="e5206fe002d74e25bb73d4a92edc2e45-3" name="Ulm_Campaign" cat="29">
<text>
As the Austrians were marching out of Ulm to surrender, a combined Franco-Spanish fleet was being destroyed at the Battle of Trafalgar. This decisive British victory ended the naval threat from France and ensured British naval domination until World War I. Despite this setback, the Ulm Campaign had been a spectacular victory and had witnessed the elimination of an entire Austrian army at very little cost for the French. The 8th bulletin of the Grande Armée described the scale of the achievement:



Marshal Augereau's arrival from Brest with the newly formed VII Corps gave the French one more piece of good news when it destroyed Franz Jellacic's division at Dornbirn in the Voralberg. The Russians withdrew to the northeast after Mack's capitulation and Vienna fell on November 12. The Allies were thoroughly defeated at the Battle of Austerlitz in December and Austria was permanently knocked out of the Third Coalition a few weeks later. The French victory highlighted the effectiveness of ''la manoeuvre sur les arrières'', a special type of strategic envelopment first used by Napoleon in his Italian campaign in 1796. The maneuver called for a pinning force that would occupy a broad front of the enemy line while other supporting units positioned themselves at a specific location in the enemy's flank or rear.Chandler p. 186 As the enemy became more embroiled with the pinning force, the flanking troops would attack at a critical spot and seal the victory. In the Ulm Campaign, Murat's cavalry served as the pinning force that fooled the Austrians into thinking the main French attack would come from the Black Forest. As Murat lulled the Austrians towards Ulm, the main French forces crashed through Central Germany and separated Mack's army from the other theaters of the war.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e331939c04f4fd77aaf8d3a5e99d84a1" name="Austerlitz-baron-Pascal" sectnum="3#1">../img/e331939c04f4fd77aaf8d3a5e99d84a1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>