<document id="e52bbf7bf426bda9b65169b214e79b9d-3.4.8" name="Imperial_Trans-Antarctic_Expedition" cat="14">
<text>
After Shackleton left with the ''James Caird'', Frank Wild took command of the Elephant Island party, some of whom were in a low state, physically or mentally: Lewis Rickinson had suffered a suspected heart attack; Blackborow was unable to walk, due to frostbitten feet; Hudson was mentally depressed.Huntford, p. 533 The priority for the party was a permanent shelter against the rapidly approaching southern winter. On the suggestion of Marston and Lionel Greenstreet, a hut (nicknamed the "Snuggery") was improvised by upturning the two boats and placing them on low stone walls, to provide around five feet of headroom. By means of canvas and other materials the structure was made into a crude  but effective shelter.Mills, p. 239&ndash;40

Wild initially estimated that they would have to wait one month for rescue, and refused to allow long-term stockpiling of seal and penguin meat because this, in his view, was defeatist.Mills, p. 241 This policy led to sharp disagreements with Thomas Orde-Lees. Orde-Lees was not a popular man, and his presence apparently did little to improve the morale of his companions, unless it was by way of being the butt of their jokes.Mills, pp. 242&ndash;50

As the weeks extended well beyond his initial optimistic forecast, Wild established and maintained routines and activities to relieve the tedium. A permanent lookout was kept for the  arrival of the rescue ship, cooking and housekeeping rotas were established, and there were hunting trips for seal and penguin.Mills, pp. 250&ndash;52 Concerts were held on Saturdays, and anniversaries celebrated, but there were growing feelings of despondency as time passed with no sign of the ship. The toes on Blackborow's left foot became gangrenous from frostbite, and on 15 June had to be amputated by the surgeons Macklin and James McIlroy in the candle-lit hut. Using the very last of the chloroform that had survived in the medical supplies, the whole procedure took 55 minutes, and was a complete success.Huntford, pp. 532&ndash;33 

By 23 August, it seemed that Wild’s no-stockpiling policy had failed. The surrounding sea was dense with pack ice that would halt any rescue ship, food supplies were running out and no penguins were coming ashore. Orde-Lees wrote: "We shall have to eat the one who dies first  there’s many a true word said in jest".Huntford,  p. 541 Wild’s thoughts were now turning seriously to the possibility of a boat trip to Deception Island—he planned to set out on 5 October, in the hoping of meeting  a whaling ship—Alexander, p. 182 when, on 30 August 1916, the ordeal ended suddenly with the appearance of Shackleton and ''Yelcho''.Mills, p. 261
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a5158b2cde7e8c13ce8a884eacaf19aa" name="Elephant_island_party" sectnum="3.4.8#1">../img/a5158b2cde7e8c13ce8a884eacaf19aa.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>