<document id="e52bbf7bf426bda9b65169b214e79b9d-3.4.6" name="Imperial_Trans-Antarctic_Expedition" cat="14">
<text>
The arrival of the ''James Caird'' at King Haakon Bay was followed by a period of  rest and recuperation, while Shackleton pondered the next move.  The populated whaling stations of South Georgia lay on the northern coast.  To reach them would mean either another boat journey around the island, or a land crossing through its unexplored interior. The condition of the ''James Caird'', and the physical state of the party, particularly Vincent and McNish, meant that the crossing was the only realistic option.Shackleton, p. 185Fisher, p. 383 

After five days the party took the boat a short distance eastwards, to the head of a deep bay which would be the starting point for the crossing.  Shackleton, Worsley and Crean would undertake the land journey, the others remaining at what they christened "Peggotty Camp", to be picked up later after help had been obtained from the whaling stations.  A storm on 18 May delayed their start, but by two o'clock the following morning the weather was clear and calm, and an hour later the crossing party set out. 

Without a map, the route they chose was largely conjectural. By dawn they had ascended to  and could see the northern coast. They were above Possession Bay, which meant they would need to move eastward to reach their intended destination of Stromness. This meant the first of several backtrackings that would extend the journey and frustrate the men. At the close of that first day, needing to descend to the valley below them before nightfall, they risked everything by sliding down a mountainside on a makeshift rope sledge.Fisher, p. 384 There was no question of rest—they travelled on by moonlight, moving upwards towards a gap in the next mountainous ridge.  Early next morning, 21 May, seeing Husvik Harbour below them, they knew that they were on the right path. At seven o'clock in the morning they heard the steam whistle sound from Stromness, "the first sound created by an outside human agency that had come to our ears since we left Stromness Bay in December 1914".Shackleton, quoted in Fisher, p. 385 After a difficult descent, which involved passage down through a freezing waterfall, they at last reached safety.Fisher, p. 386

Shackleton wrote afterwards: "I have no doubt that Providence guided us…I know that during that long and racking march of thirty-six hours over the unnamed mountains and glaciers it seemed to me often that we were four, not three".Shackleton, South, p. 209 This image of a fourth traveller—echoed in the accounts of Worsley and Crean—was taken up by T. S. Eliot in his poem ''The Waste Land''.Huntford,  pp. 696&ndash;97
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c9f253e42225e989df388937c5535eb4" name="PanoramaOfSouthGeorgia" sectnum="3.4.6#1">../img/c9f253e42225e989df388937c5535eb4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>