<document id="e53eed464b8de4afa2c1316404780adc-2.1" name="Jack_Sheppard" cat="14">
<text>
Sheppard was first arrested after a burglary he committed with his brother, Tom, and his mistress, Lyon, in Clare Market on 5 February 1724.  Tom, also a carpenter, had already been convicted once for stealing tools from his master the previous autumn and burned in the hand.  Tom was arrested again on 24 April 1724.  Afraid that he would be hanged this time, Tom informed on Jack, and a warrant was issued for Jack's arrest.Lynch, para.11.  

Jonathan Wild was aware of Sheppard's thefts, as Sheppard had fenced some stolen goods through one of Wild's men, William Field.  Wild asked another of his men, James Sykes (known as "Hell and Fury") to challenge Sheppard to a game of skittles at Redgate's public house near Seven Dials.Moore, p.100.  Sykes betrayed Sheppard to a Mr Price, a constable from the parish of St Giles's, to gather the usual £40 reward for giving information leading to the conviction of a felon.  The magistrate, Justice Parry, had Sheppard imprisoned overnight on the top floor of St Giles's Roundhouse pending further questioning, but Sheppard escaped within three hours by breaking through the timber ceiling and lowering himself to the ground with a rope fashioned from bedclothes.Moore, p.104.  Still wearing irons, Sheppard coolly joined the crowd that had been attracted by the sounds of him breaking out.  He distracted their attention by pointing to the shadows on the roof and shouting that he could see the escapee, and then swiftly departed.



On 19 May 1724, Sheppard was arrested for a second time, caught in the act of picking a pocket in Leicester Fields (near present-day Leicester Square).  He was detained overnight in St Ann's Roundhouse in Soho and visited there the next day by Lyon; she was recognised as his wife and locked in a cell with him.  They appeared before Justice Walters, who sent them to the New Prison in Clerkenwell, but they escaped from their cell, known as the Newgate Ward, within a matter of days.  By 25 May, Whitsun Monday, Sheppard and Lyon had filed through their manacles; they removed a bar from the window and used their knotted bed-clothes to descend to ground level.  Finding themselves in the yard of the neighbouring bridewell, they clambered over the 22-foot-high (6.7 m) prison gate to freedom.  This feat was widely publicised, not least because Sheppard was only a small man, and Lyon was a large, buxom woman.Moore, p.105.Defoe's ''History'' reports that she was "more corpulent than himself".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="920139d7c8a1949282e479bc065886ad" name="Jackandbessescape" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/920139d7c8a1949282e479bc065886ad.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>