<document id="e53eed464b8de4afa2c1316404780adc-1" name="Jack_Sheppard" cat="14">
<text>
Sheppard was born in White's Row, in London's Spitalfields.Moore, p.31.Lynch, para.2. During the first two decades of the 18th century, Spitalfields was notorious for the presence of highwaymen and for being a tremendously economically depressed area, and so it is clear that his family was impoverished.  He was baptised on 5 March, the day after he was born, at St Dunstan's, Stepney, suggesting a fear of infant mortality by his parents, perhaps because the newborn was weak or sickly. His parents named him after an older brother, John, who had died before his birth.  In life, he was better known as Jack, or even "Gentleman Jack" or "Jack the Lad".  He had a second brother, Thomas, and a younger sister, Mary.  Their father, a carpenter, died while Sheppard was young, and his sister died two years later.

Unable to support her family without her husband's income, Jack's mother sent him to Mr Garrett's School, a workhouse near St Helen's Bishopsgate, when he was six years old.  Sheppard was sent out as a parish apprentice to a cane-chair maker, taking a settlement of 20 shillings, but his new master soon died.  He was sent out to a second cane-chair maker, but Sheppard was treated badly.Moore, p.38.  Finally, when Sheppard was 10, he went to work as a shop-boy for William Kneebone, a wool draper with a shop on the Strand.Moore, p.33.  Sheppard's mother had been working for Kneebone since her husband's death.  Kneebone taught Sheppard to read and write and apprenticed him to a carpenter, Owen Wood, in Wych Street, off Drury Lane in Covent Garden.  Sheppard signed his seven-year indenture on 2 April 1717.   

By 1722, Sheppard was showing great promise as a carpenter.  Aged 20, he was a small man, only 5'4" (1.63 m) tall and lightly built, but deceptively strong.  He had a pale face with large, dark eyes, a wide mouth and a quick smile.  Despite a slight stutter, his wit made him popular in the taverns of Drury Lane.Moore, p.96.  He served five unblemished years of his apprenticeship but then began to be led into crime.  

Joseph Hayne, a button-moulder who owned a shop nearby, also ran a tavern named the Black Lion off Drury Lane, which he encouraged the local apprentices to frequent.Moore, p.98.  The Black Lion was visited by criminals such as Joseph "Blueskin" Blake, Sheppard's future partner in crime, and self-proclaimed "Thief-Taker General" Jonathan Wild, secretly the linchpin of a criminal empire across London and later Sheppard's implacable enemy. 

According to Sheppard's "autobiography", he had been an innocent until going to Hayne's tavern, but there began an attachment to strong drink and the affections of Elizabeth Lyon, a prostitute also known as Edgworth Bess (or Edgeworth Bess) from her place of birth at Edgeworth in Middlesex.  In his ''History'', Defoe records that Bess was "a main lodestone in attracting of him up to this Eminence of Guilt."Defoe, ''History''.  Such, Sheppard claimed, was the source of his later ruin.Defoe's ''History'' reports that he called Edgworth Bess "the sole author of all his misfortunes" and said he "cared not what became of her". Peter Linebaugh offers a different view: that Sheppard's sudden transformation was a liberation from the dull drudgery of indentured labour and that he progressed from pious servitude to self-confident rebellion and Levelling.Linebaugh, Ch.1. "The Common Discourse of the Whole Nation: Jack Sheppard and the Art of Escape", in ''The London Hanged'', pp.7–42. On the comparison with the Levellers, see p.164.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="71273a050b6337985c323db7e5aa51a8" name="1870_WychStreet_Engraving" sectnum="1#1">../img/71273a050b6337985c323db7e5aa51a8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>