<document id="e54d0d69fa18681a8052dbe79e612c74-3.6" name="Sid_Barnes" cat="26">
<text>
‎ 
At the beginning of the 1951&ndash;52 season, Barnes had a change of heart and returned to the New South Wales team in a bid to play Test cricket again. He approached Aubrey Oxlade, the chairman of Australian cricket's Board of Control, to ask if there was any impediment to his return to the Australian team. Oxlade told Barnes that he would be judged solely on his batting performances. 

During his absence from the Test team, the Australian selectors had been unsuccessful in their attempts to find a reliable partner for Arthur Morris to open the batting. Barnes started the season solidly and, in the last match before the team for the third Test against the West Indies was chosen, he hit 107 against Victoria. The selectors duly picked him for the match, then passed the team list to the Board of Control for ratification. The Board vetoed the inclusion of Barnes and requested the nomination of a replacement player. Unwilling to accept the blame for Barnes’s omission, the selectors deliberately deferred their decision on the replacement. When the team was not announced at the scheduled time, journalists uncovered the story and Barnes became a ''cause célèbre'' for many weeks, missing all of the remaining Tests. Speculation abounded as to the nature of his supposed misdeeds. These included jumping the turnstile at a ground when he forgot his player’s pass; insulting the Royal Family; theft from team-mates; drunkenness; and stealing a car.Harte, pp. 422&ndash;423.

The Board of Control had granted themselves the power to exclude a player from the national team "on grounds other than cricket ability" following the poor behaviour of some members of the 1912 team that toured England.Harte, p. 256. They had a secret dossier, compiled during the season, documenting Barnes’s behaviour and they doctored the minutes of the meeting at which they discussed his selection. Publicly, the Board remained silent on their policy and how it related to Barnes. On the field, Barnes responded with an innings of 128 in three hours against Queensland; off the field, he sought answers from the administrators, but was frustrated by their evasiveness. His form tapered off during the closing stages of the season and he finished with 433 first-class runs at an average of 39.36. 

Just as the furore appeared to have died down, in April 1952 Sydney's ''Daily Mirror'' published a letter from a reader, Jacob Raith.Smith, p. 155. "Jacob Raith, a master baker, cricket lover from Sid's own suburb of Stanmore and a former president of Petersham Cricket Club ..." It continues down the same page, "Rather than support the player, whom he did not know despite their associations with the same area, he decided to back the board." Responding to a letter in support of Barnes, Raith sided with the Board and suggested that his character was to blame for the omission. Acting on legal advice, Barnes sued Raith for libel and engaged Sydney’s leading barrister, Jack Shand KC, as counsel. 

The case began in Sydney’s District Court on 21 August 1952. Shand’s examination of the various Board members appearing for the defendant revealed the Board’s maladministration, pettiness and its acceptance of rumour as fact. No firm reason was put forward for the omission of Barnes and a division within the Board was evident when several of its members spoke highly of him. As Barnes began his testimony on the second day of proceedings, Raith’s counsel announced settlement of the case and commented to the court, "... seldom in the history of libel actions has such a plea failed so completely and utterly". Barnes was vindicated with a full public apology. 

Although the court case portrayed "an awful image of the chaos and bigotry under which Australian cricket was administered", it did little to alter the Board’s culture. The next major court case involving Australian cricket, the World Series Cricket challenges of 1977&ndash;78 demonstrated that the Board was still run as a "closed shop", over 25 years later. In an analysis of the Barnes libel case, Gideon Haigh wrote, "... far from becoming a watershed in player-administrator relations, it may even have discouraged players contemplating defiance of the Board but lacking the wherewithal to retain a hotshot criminal barrister."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ec145eeb6108b1c158d2f09b91f54f55" name="Barnes_and_lawyer" sectnum="3.6#1">../img/ec145eeb6108b1c158d2f09b91f54f55.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>