<document id="e5e9a2116ce256748273e4a741a3cd26-4.8" name="Kingdom_of_Mysore" cat="14">
<text>
Under Maharaja Krishnaraja III and his successors &ndash; Chamaraja IX, Krishnaraja IV and the last ruler, Jayachamaraja, the Mysore court came to be the largest and most renowned patron of music.Weidman (2006), p. 66  While the Tanjore and Travancore courts also extended great patronage and emphasised preservation of the art, the unique combination of royal patronage of individual musicians, founding of music schools to kindle public interest and a patronage of European music publishers and producers set Mysore apart.Weidman (2006), p. 65  Maharaja Krishnaraja III, himself a musician and musicologist of merit, composed a number of ''javalis'' (light lyrics) and devotional songs in Kannada under the title ''Anubhava pancharatna''.  His compositions bear the nom de plume (''mudra'') "Chamundi'" or '"Chamundeshwari'", in honour of the Wodeyar family deity.Pranesh (2003), p. 54  His successor Chamaraja IX founded the Oriental Library in 1891 to house music books and also commissioned phonograph recordings of several musicians for the palace library.

Under Krishnaraja IV, art received further patronage.  A distinct school of music which gave importance to ''raga'' and ''bhava'' evolved.Pranesh (2003), p. xiii in author's noteKamath (2001), p282  The Royal School of Music founded at the palace helped institutionalise teaching of the art. Carnatic compositions were printed and the European staff notation came to be employed by royal musicians.  Western music was also encouraged &ndash; Margaret Cousins' piano concerto with the Palace Orchestra marked the celebrations of Beethoven's centenary in Bangalore. Maharaja Jayachamaraja, also a renowned composer of Carnatic ''kritis'' (a musical composition), sponsored a series of recordings of Russian composer Nikolas Medtner and others.  The court ensured that Carnatic music also kept up with the times. Gramophone recordings of the palace band were made and sold commercially.Weidman (2006), p. 67 Attention was paid to "technology of the concert".  Lavish sums were spent on acquiring various instruments including the unconventional horn violin, theremin and calliaphone, a mechanical music player.Weidman (2006), p. 68

The Mysore court was home to several renowned  experts (''vidwan'') of the time.  Veena Sheshanna, a court musician during the rule of  Maharaja Chamaraja IX,Pranesh (2003), p. 110 is considered one of the greatest exponents of the veena.Bakshi (1996), p. 12; Kamath (2001), p. 282  His achievements in classical music won Mysore a premier place in the art of instrumental Carnatic music and he was given the honorific ''Vainika Shikhamani'' by Maharaja Krishnaraja Wodeyar IV.Pranesh (2003), pp. 110&ndash;111 Mysore Vasudevacharya was a noted musician and composer in Sanskrit and Telugu from Mysore.Subramaniyan (2006), p. 199; Kamath (2001), p. 282  He holds the unique distinction of being patronised by four generations of Mysore kings and rulers and for being court musician to three of them.Pranesh (2003), p. 135Pranesh (2003), p. 140H.L. Muthiah Bhagavatar was another musician-composer who adorned the Mysore court.Subramaniyan (2006), p. 202; Kamath (2001), p. 282  Considered one of the most important composers of the post-Tyagaraja period,Pranesh (2003), p. 170 he is credited with about 400 compositions in Sanskrit, Kannada, Telugu and Tamil under the pen name "Harikesha".  Among violinists, T. Chowdiah emerged as one of the most accomplished exponents of the time. He is known to have mastered the seven-stringed violin.Pranesh (2003), p. 214, 216Kamath (2001), p. 282  Chowdiah was appointed court musician by Maharaja Krishnaraja Wodeyar IV in 1939 and received such titles as "Sangeeta Ratna" and "Sangeeta Kalanidhi". He is credited with compositions in Kannada, Telugu and Sanskrit under the pen name "Trimakuta".Pranesh (2003), p. 216
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="7c8f3b3e5564512e80eead1b91b94ce1" name="Veena_Subbanna_Seshanna_1902" sectnum="4.8#1">../img/7c8f3b3e5564512e80eead1b91b94ce1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>