<document id="e5e9a2116ce256748273e4a741a3cd26-1.2" name="Kingdom_of_Mysore" cat="14">
<text>
The kings who followed ruled as vassals of the Vijayanagara empire until the decline of the latter in 1565. By this time, the kingdom had expanded to thirty-three villages protected by a force of 300 soldiers.  King Timmaraja II conquered some surrounding chiefdoms,Kamath (2001), p. 227 and King ''Bola'' Chamaraja IV (''lit'', "Bald"), the first ruler of any political significance among them, withheld tribute to the nominal Vijayanagara monarch Aravidu Ramaraya Subrahmanyam (2001), p. 67.  After the death of Aravidu Ramaraya, the Wodeyars began to assert themselves further and King Raja Wodeyar I wrested control of Srirangapatna from the Vijayanagara governor (''Mahamandaleshvara'') Aravidu Tirumalla &ndash; a development which elicited, if only ''ex post facto'', the tacit approval of Venkatapati Raya, the incumbent king of the diminished Vijayanagar empire ruled from Chandragiri.Subrahmanyam (2001), p. 68  Raja Wodeyar I's reign also saw territorial expansion with the annexation of Channapatna to the north from Jaggadeva RayaSubrahmanyam (2001), p. 68Venkata Ramanappa, M. N. (1975), p. 200 – a development which made Mysore a regional political factor to reckon with.Shama Rao in Kamath (2001), p. 227Venkata Ramanappa, M. N. (1975), p.201

Consequently, by 1612&ndash;13, the Wodeyars exercised a great deal of autonomy and even though they acknowledged the nominal overlordship of the Aravidus, tributes and transfers of revenue to Chandragiri stopped. This was in marked contrast to the major chiefs (''Nayakas'') of Tamil country who continued to pay off Chandragiri well into the 1630s.Subrahmanyam (2001), p. 68 Chamaraja V and Kanthirava Narasaraja I attempted to expand further northward but were thwarted by the Bijapur Sultanate and its Maratha subordinates, though the Bijapur armies under Ranadullah Khan were effectively repelled in their 1638 siege of Srirangapatna.Subrahmanyam (2001), p. 68; Kamath (2001), p. 228Venkata Ramanappa, M. N. (1975), p. 201  Expansionist ambitions then turned southward into Tamil country where Narasaraja Wodeyar acquired Satyamangalam (in modern northern Coimbatore district) while his successor Dodda Devaraja Wodeyar expanded further to capture western Tamil regions of Erode and Dharmapuri, after successfully repulsing the chiefs of Madurai.  The invasion of the Keladi Nayakas of Malnad was also dealt with successfully.  This period was followed by one of complex geo-political changes, when in the 1670s, the Marathas and the Mughals pressed into the Deccan.Subrahmanyam (2001), p. 68; Kamath (2001), p. 228Venkata Ramanappa, M. N. (1975), p. 201  

Chikka Devaraja (r. 1672&ndash;1704), the most notable of Mysore's early kings, who ruled during much of this period, managed to not only survive the exigencies but further expanded territory.  He achieved this by forging strategic alliances with the Marathas and the Mughals.Subrahmanyam (2001), p. 71Kamath (2001), pp. 228&ndash;229 The kingdom soon grew to include Salem and Bangalore to the east, Hassan to the west, Chikkamagaluru and Tumkur to the north and the rest of Coimbatore to the south.Subrahmanyam (2001), p. 69; Kamath (2001), pp. 228&ndash;229 Despite this expansion, the kingdom, which now accounted for a fair share of land in the southern Indian heartland, extending from the Western Ghats to the western boundaries of the Coromandel plain, remained landlocked without direct coastal access.  Chikka Devaraja's attempts to remedy this brought Mysore into conflict with the ''Nayaka'' chiefs of Ikkeri and the kings (''Rajas'') of Kodagu (modern Coorg); who between them controlled the Kanara coast (coastal areas of modern Karnataka) and the intervening hill region respectively.Subrahmanyam (2001), p. 69 The conflict brought mixed results with Mysore annexing Periyapatna but suffering a reversal at Palupare.Subrahmanyam (2001), p. 70

Nevertheless, from around 1704, when the kingdom passed on to "Muteking" (''Mukarasu'') Kanthirava Narasaraja II, the survival and expansion of the kingdom was achieved by playing a delicate game of alliance, negotiation, subordination on occasion, and annexation of territory in all directions.  According to historians Sanjay Subrahmanyam and Sethu Madhava Rao, Mysore was now formally a tributary of the Mughal empire. Mughul records claim a regular tribute (''peshkash'') was payed by Mysore.  However, historian Suryanath Kamath feels the Mughals may have considered Mysore an ally, a situation brought about by Mughal&ndash;Maratha competition for supremacy in southern India.Subrahmanyam (2001), pp. 70&ndash;71; Kamath (2001), p. 229  By the 1720s, with the Mughal empire in decline, further complications arose with the Mughal residents at both Arcot and Sira claiming tribute.Subrahmanyam (2001), p. 71  The years that followed saw Krishnaraja Wodeyar I tread cautiously on the matter while keeping the Kodagu chiefs and the Marathas at bay.  He was followed by Chamaraja Wodeyar VI during whose reign power fell into the hands of prime minister (''Dalwai'' or ''Dalavoy'') Nanjarajiah (or Nanjaraja) and chief minister (''Sarvadhikari'') Devarajiah (or Devaraja), the influential brothers from Kalale town near Nanjangud who would rule for the next three decades with the Wodeyars relegated to being the titular heads.Pranesh (2003), pp. 44&ndash;45Kamath (2001), p. 230  The latter part of the rule of Krishnaraja II saw the Deccan Sultanates being eclipsed by the Mughals and in the confusion that ensued, Haider Ali, a captain in the army, rose to prominence.  His victory against the Marathas at Bangalore in 1758, resulting in the annexation of their territory, made him an iconic figure.  In honour of his achievements, the king gave him the title "Nawab Haider Ali Khan Bahadur".Kamath (2001), p. 230
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="16c1e8c9020e1bd9ccb55c9211cca04b" name="Tipu_Sultan_BL" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/16c1e8c9020e1bd9ccb55c9211cca04b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>