<document id="e671c5edc73ef98456d0a0c4df7defdb-3.4" name="SY_Aurora's_drift" cat="14">
<text>
When the ship passed Cape Adare, the direction of drift changed to north-westerly. On 10 August Stenhouse estimated that they were  north-east of the Cape, and that their daily drift was averaging just over .Shackleton, pp. 320–21 A few days later Stenhouse recorded that the ship was "backing and filling", meaning that it was drifting back and forth without making progress. "However, we cannot grumble and must be patient", he wrote, adding that from the crow's nest a distinct impression of open water could be seen. With the possibility that the edge of the pack was nearby, work on the construction of a jury rudder began. This first involved the removal of the wreckage of the smashed rudder, a task largely carried out by Engineer Donnelly.Haddelsey, p. 61 The jury rudder was constructed from makeshift materials, and by 26 August was ready for use as soon as ''Aurora'' cleared the ice. It would then be lowered over the stern and operated manually, "like a huge oar".Tyler-Lewis, p. 205 


On 25 August Hooke began picking up occasional radio signals being exchanged between Macquarie Island and New Zealand.Shackleton, pp. 322–24 By the end of August open leads were beginning to appear, and sometimes it was possible to discern a sea-swell under the ship. However, severe weather returned in September, when a hurricane-force wind destroyed the wireless aerial and temporarily halted Hooke's efforts. On 22 September, when ''Aurora'' was in sight of the uninhabited Balleny Islands, Stenhouse estimated that they had travelled over  from Cape Evans, in what he called a "wonderful drift". He added that regular observations and records of the nature and direction of the ice had been maintained throughout: "It  has not been in vain, and  knowledge of the set and drift of the pack will be a valuable addition to the sum of human knowledge".

Aurora's circumstances changed little during the following months. Stenhouse worked hard to maintain morale, keeping the crew working whenever possible and organising leisure activities, including games of football and cricket on the ice.Haddelsey, pp. 62–64 On 21 November ''Aurora'' crossed the Antarctic Circle, and it was at last evident that the ice around the ship was beginning to melt: "...one good hefty blizzard would cause a general break up", wrote Stenhouse. Christmas approached with the ice still holding firm; Stenhouse allowed the crew to prepare a feast, but noted in his journal: "I wish to God the blasted festivities were over  we are hogging in to the best while the poor beggars at Cape Evans have little or nothing!" A few days later the New Year was celebrated with an improvised band leading choruses of "Rule, Britannia" and "God Save the King."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1d5a77cc261d482cf4f5ce36af9f9de3" name="_Plan_of_Aurora" sectnum="3.4#1">../img/1d5a77cc261d482cf4f5ce36af9f9de3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>