<document id="e671c5edc73ef98456d0a0c4df7defdb-2.1" name="SY_Aurora's_drift" cat="14">
<text>
''Aurora'' arrived in McMurdo Sound in January 1915, late in the season due to her delayed departure from Australia. Because the party was three weeks behind schedule Mackintosh decided that the depot-laying work should begin at once,Tyler-Lewis, p. 66and took charge of this himself. By 25 January he was leading one of the early sledging parties, leaving Stenhouse in command of the ship. In the few weeks before the Sound froze over for the winter, Stenhouse had to supervise the landing of the remaining shore parties and stores. He had also to find a safe winter berth for the ship; Mackintosh's departing instruction had been explicit that this was Stenhouse's paramount duty.Tyler-Lewis, p. 112

The only known safe winter anchorage in McMurdo Sound was Scott's old Discovery Expedition headquarters at Hut Point, south of the projection known as Glacier Tongue which divided the Sound into two sectors. However, Scott's ship had been frozen in the ice for two years, requiring two rescue ships and several explosive charges to release her. Shackleton was determined to avoid this, and had given Mackintosh explicit instructions, relayed to Stenhouse, to winter ''Aurora'' north of the Tongue.Tyler-Lewis, pp. 114–16 No ship had previously wintered in the exposed northern section of the Sound, and the wisdom of doing this was questioned by the experienced seamen Ernest Joyce and James Paton in their private journals.Tyler-Lewis, p. 68Tyler-Lewis, pp. 120–21 and p.126 After the expedition was over, John King Davis, who was to lead the Ross Sea party relief mission, wrote that Shackleton's instruction should have been ignored and that Stenhouse should have taken ''Aurora'' to the safety of Hut Point, even at the risk of becoming frozen in.Tyler-Lewis, p. 221

Stenhouse first attempted to anchor the ship on the north side of Glacier Tongue itself.Haddelsey, p. 43 Disaster was only narrowly avoided when a change in the wind direction threatened to imprison ''Aurora'' between the Tongue and the advancing pack ice.Tyler-Lewis, pp. 118–19 With other options considered and rejected, Stenhouse finally decided to anchor at Cape Evans, site of Captain Scott's old Terra Nova headquarters, some six nautical miles (11 km) north of Glacier Tongue.Scott's ship ''Terra Nova'' had wintered in New Zealand after landing its shore parties here, as had ''Nimrod'' during Shackleton' 1907–09 expedition. Tyler-Lewis, p. 114 On 14 March, after numerous failed attempts,Fisher, p. 402Bickel, pp. 69–70 Stenhouse manoeuvred ''Aurora'' into position, stern-first towards the shore at Cape Evans, where two large anchors had been sunk and cemented into the ground. Cables and hawsers, together with a heavy chain, attached these to the ship's stern. Two bower anchors were also dropped. By 14 March the ship was settling into the shore ice with, according to second officer Leslie Thompson, "enough hawsers and anchors to hold a battleship".Tyler-Lewis, p. 123
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5651d4ed359690d4b886bff33ccfd942" name="Possible_Aurora_Mooring_Sites" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/5651d4ed359690d4b886bff33ccfd942.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>