<document id="e68fb922e5df3831df497f167e625ef8-3.12.3" name="Mount_St._Helens" cat="11">
<text>
Appearance of the "Whaleback" in February 2005

Magma reached the surface of the volcano about October 11, 2004, resulting in the building of a new lava dome on the existing dome's south side. This new dome continued to grow throughout 2005 and into 2006. Several transient features were observed, such as the "whaleback," which comprised long shafts of solidified magma being extruded by the pressure of magma beneath. These features were fragile and broke down soon after they were formed. On July 2, 2005, the tip of the whaleback broke off, causing a rockfall that sent ash and dust several hundred meters into the air.see 

Mount St. Helens showed significant activity on March 8, 2005, when a  plume of steam and ash emerged—visible from Seattle., March 8, 2005, USGS.gov (accessed 15 November 2006) This relatively minor eruption was a release of pressure consistent with ongoing dome building. The release was accompanied by a magnitude 2.5 earthquake.

The volcano continuously steams as seen here in late 2007.


Another feature to emerge from the dome was called the "fin" or "slab." Approximately half the size of a football field, the large, cooled volcanic rock was being forced upward as quickly as  per day.See  In mid-June 2006, the slab was crumbling in frequent rockfalls, although it was still being extruded. The height of the dome was , still below the height reached in July 2005 when the whaleback collapsed.

On October 22, 2006, at 3:13 p.m. PST, a magnitude 3.5 earthquake broke loose Spine 7. The collapse and avalanche of the lava dome sent an ash plume  over the western rim of the crater; the ash plume then rapidly dissipated.

On December 19, 2006, a large white plume of condensing steam was observed, leading some media people to assume there had been a small eruption. However, the Cascades Volcano Observatory of the USGS did not mention any significant ash plume. The volcano was in continuous eruption from October 2004, but this eruption in large part, consisted of a gradual extrusion of lava forming a dome in the crater.

On January 16, 2008, steam began seeping from a fracture on top of the lava dome. Associated seismic activity was the most noteworthy since 2004. Scientists suspended activities in the crater and the mountain flanks, but the risk of a major eruption was deemed low. By the end of January, the eruption paused; no more lava was being extruded from the lava dome.  On July 10, 2008 it was determined that the eruption had ended after more than six months of no volcanic activity.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5502210c500073878e41cd1882dd3366" name="Dacite-ThinSection-USGS" sectnum="3.12.3#1">../img/5502210c500073878e41cd1882dd3366.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>