<document id="e692114d22b5213312f432d21751d611-4" name="Deinosuchus" cat="3">
<text>
''Deinosuchus'' was classified in the family Crocodylidae by Colbert and Bird, primarily on the basis of dental features resembling those of modern crocodiles. However, a phylogenetic re-evaluation conducted in 1999 by Brochu determined that ''Deinosuchus'' was actually a primitive member of Alligatoroidea. Thus, ''Deinosuchus'' "is not the world's largest crocodile&mdash;it is one of the largest alligators." This classification was bolstered in 2005 by the discovery of a well-preserved ''Deinosuchus'' braincase from the Blufftown Formation of Alabama, which shows some features reminiscent of those in the modern American alligator. Although it was a prehistoric member of the same clade, ''Deinosuchus'' was not a direct ancestor of modern alligators. Its closest relatives may have been ''Leidyosuchus'' and ''Diplocynodon''.

Schwimmer (2002) considered all ''Deinosuchus'' specimens to belong to one species. He noted that there were more similarities than differences between the eastern and western populations, and that most of these differences related only to the larger size of the western specimens. Under the International Code of Zoological Nomenclature's rules of priority, this species would be named ''D. rugosus''. Lucas ''et al.'' (2006) also considered ''Deinosuchus'' a monospecific genus. However, Brochu (2003) questioned Schwimmer's analysis, suggesting that size might be a significant diagnostic feature and that several of the features used by Schwimmer to establish synonymy between the two populations are actually primitive traits shared by other genera as well. Schwimmer (2002) informally referred to the western populations as ''D. riograndensis'', and several other researchers, including Anglen and Lehman (2000) and Westgate ''et al.'' (2006) have also recently assigned western ''Deinosuchus'' remains to this species.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4fc39d29517b032421579dc5b1dac94c" name="Deinosuchus_at_the_CMNH" sectnum="4#1">../img/4fc39d29517b032421579dc5b1dac94c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>