<document id="e77e164489b673dcb8631c929bfae05b-2" name="Joseph_Szigeti" cat="20">
<text>
In 1918, while teaching in Geneva, Szigeti met and fell in love with Wanda Ostrowska, a young woman of Russian parentage who had been stranded by the Russian Revolution of 1917 with her sister at a finishing school in Geneva. In 1919 Szigeti and Ostrowska decided to get married, but due to the turbulent political situation in Europe, many unexpected bureaucratic obstacles were thrown up in their path. The first problem was the impossibility of contacting Ostrowska's family, and the couple were forced to go ahead without parental consent, with the permission only of Ostrowska's sister and the headmistress of the finishing school at which she had been left.Szigeti: ''With Strings Attached'', pp. 172–173 Further bureaucratic entanglements threatened to destroy the young couple's hopes of marriage entirely, but eventually the officials responsible for granting the marriage dispensation relented and agreed to ignore the problematic regulations. Szigeti recalls in his memoirs the words of Consul General Baron de Montlong at the critical moment: Let us not, if we can avoid it, fall victim to the dead letter of the law. I don't want to postpone the happiness of these two youngsters if we can help it. All laws have been twisted and tortured out of semblance of law, what with war and revolutions. For once let's twist and turn one for a good cause, yes?Szigeti: ''With Strings Attached'', p. 173


That incident was only the first time external political events would affect the couple's life together. Just before the birth of their only child, daughter Irene, Szigeti found himself stuck in Berlin during the Kapp Putsch of 1920, unable to return to Geneva. The entire city had been paralyzed by a general strike, and the trains were not running. His scheduled concert could not go on as planned, but he was nevertheless forced to stay in Berlin for "interminable days" while the Putsch ran its course. Worst of all, as Szigeti writes: "... the impossibility of communicating by phone or wire with my wife--whose condition I pictured with the somewhat lurid pessimism usual to young prospective fathers--was certainly a greater torment to me than all the other discomforts put together".Szigeti: ''With Strings Attached'', p. 203

By 1940, the outbreak of World War II forced the Szigetis to leave Europe for the United States. (Irene remained in Switzerland, having married pianist Nikita Magaloff earlier that year.) They settled in California, where Wanda, always fond of nature, was delighted to be able to raise her own garden. In a letter to a friend, Szigeti describes their California life: Wanda is happy, doing wonders with her gardening, chicken and rabbit raising, preserve and pâté de foie making. She doesn't budge from our place, doesn't want to come back to New York even for a visit, which I, for one, can well understand! Two dogs, an aviary full of exotic birds, tomatoes, grapes, strawberries, asparagus, artichokes, lovely flowers (camellias too!), right in our own little world.Hughes, p. xiii

Despite the attractions of California life, in 1960 the couple returned to Europe. They settled on Lake Geneva in Switzerland, near the home of their daughter and son-in-law, and remained there for the rest of their lives. Wanda died in 1971, predeceasing her husband by two years.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="76d5364646bb7e9890e3036bfeae1321" name="Joska_and_Wanda" sectnum="2#1">../img/76d5364646bb7e9890e3036bfeae1321.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>