<document id="e77e164489b673dcb8631c929bfae05b-1.5" name="Joseph_Szigeti" cat="20">
<text>
By 1930, Szigeti was established as a major international concert violinist. He performed extensively in Europe, the United States and Asia, and made the acquaintance of many of the era’s leading instrumentalists, conductors and composers. 


In 1939, to escape the war, Szigeti emigrated with his wife to the United States, where they settled in California. (A year later, Bartók also fled to America, and just two days after his arrival he and Szigeti played a sonata recital at the Library of Congress in Washington, D.C.)Review by Noel Straus, ''The New York Times'', 1940-04-22 In 1942 Szigeti was among four passengers who gave up their seats on TWA Flight 3 to allow Army members to return to their positions with Ferry Command. The flight later crashed, killing all aboard., ''TIME'' Magazine, January 26, 1942. Retrieved April 10, 2008.

During the 1930s, '40s and into the '50s, Szigeti recorded extensively, leaving a significant legacy.  Notable recordings include the above-mentioned Library of Congress sonata recital; the studio recording of Bartók's ''Contrasts'' with Benny Goodman on clarinet and the composer at the piano; the violin concertos of Beethoven, Brahms, Mendelssohn, Prokofiev (No. 1) and Bloch under the batons of such conductors as Bruno Walter, Hamilton Harty and Sir Thomas Beecham; and various works by J.S. Bach, Busoni, Corelli, Handel and Mozart. One of his last recordings was of the ''Six Sonatas and Partitas'' for solo violin by Bach; although his technique had deteriorated noticeably by that time, the recording is still prized for its insight and depth of interpretation.Schwarz, Boris: , Grove Music Online ed. L. Macy. Retrieved 2007-09-26

In 1950, Szigeti was detained at Ellis Island upon returning from a European concert tour and was held for several days, officially "temporarily excluded" from the country. The reasons for his detention remain unclear., ''The New York Times'', 1950-11-18 The following year, he received American citizenship.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d0c5c6cf51015637d3cf2f1bc70d0880" name="Bartók_Béla_1927" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/d0c5c6cf51015637d3cf2f1bc70d0880.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>