<document id="e784121d25e1519ea27ea45d5df0fbde-4.4" name="Operation_Epsom" cat="29">
<text>
With the weather improving over the United Kingdom and Normandy, Hausser's preparations for his counter stroke came under continual harassment from Allied aircraft and artillery fire, resulting in the start time being pushed back to the afternoon. From the number of German reinforcements arriving in VIII Corps' sector,Jackson, p. 44 and aerial reconnaissance, VIII Corps commander Lieutenant-General Richard O’Connor suspected that the Germans were organising a major offensive. XXX Corps was still some way to the north, leaving VIII Corps' right flank vulnerable, so O'Connor postponed the planned attacks by I Corps and ordered VIII Corps to adopt a defensive posture. Lieutenant-General Miles Dempsey, commanding the Second Army and privy to ULTRA decrypts of intercepted German signal traffic, knew of the planned counterattack and approved O'Connor's precautions.

Having moved to the defensive, VIII Corps began to reorganise in order to meet the attack when it came.Jackson, p. 45 Supply echelons for Hausser's divisions were located in the Évrecy&ndash;Noyers-Bocage&ndash;Villers-Bocage area, and were the focus of RAF fighter-bomber attention throughout the morning and early afternoon; the RAF claimed the destruction of over 200 vehicles. VIII Corps also launched spoiling moves. At 0800 a battalion of the 43rd Division assaulted Mouen. Without armour, but supported by an artillery barrage, by 1100 the battalion had evicted the 1st SS Panzer Division's panzergrenadiers, following which a second battalion moved up and dug in on the Caen&ndash;Villers-Bocage road.Clark, pp. 87&ndash;88 The 43rd Division's 129th Brigade swept the woods and orchards around Tourville-sur-Odon, before crossing the river north of Baron-sur-Odon and proceeding to clear the southern bank.Clark, p. 88 Other initiatives were less successful. An attempt by the 15th Division's 44th Brigade to advance towards the Odon and link up with the force holding the Gavrus bridges failed, leaving this position isolated,Clark, p. 89 and in the salient the 44th Battalion Royal Tank Regiment failed to capture Hill 113 (), north of Évrecy,Clark, p. 90 after clashing with 10th SS Panzer and losing 6 tanks.Jackson, p. 49 Endeavouring to strengthen their position, elements of the 11th Armoured Division launched a failed attack to take Esquay-Notre-Dame, west of Hill 112, but a combined infantry and tank attack on the southern slope of the hill was more successful, driving the Germans from the position.


Hausser intended for his II SS Panzer Corps' 9th SS Panzer Division&mdash;with Kampfgruppe Weidinger protecting its left flank&mdash;to cut right across the British salient north of the Odon, while the 10th SS Panzer Division was to retake Gavrus and Hill 112 south of the river.Clark, p. 92 9th SS Panzer's attack began at 1400, heavily supported by artillery. Two regiments of the division, supported by Panthers, Panzer IV's and assault guns, attacked Grainville, le Haut du Bosq, and le Valtru, aiming for Cheux as their final objective.Reynolds, p. 25 A British company was overrun and tanks and infantry penetrated into le Valtru, but anti-tank guns knocked out four German tanks within the village and artillery fire forced their supporting infantry to withdraw. Heavy and confused fighting, at times coming down to hand-to-hand combat, took place outside Grainville. Panzergrenadiers captured a tactically key wood, but were forced back after a British counterattack. The panzergrenadiers claimed they also captured Grainville, but no British sources support this, and by nightfall British infantry were in firm control of the village.

At around 1600Jackson, p. 50 the British captured an officer of the 9th SS Panzer DivisionWilmot, p. 345 who was conducting a reconnaissance mission. He was found to be carrying a map and notebook containing details of upcoming attacks. Nevertheless, at around 1830 the Germans launched renewed strikes against the 15th (Scottish) Infantry Division's right flank.Williams, p. 121 One unit was in the process of relieving another, and in the confusion German tanks and infantry slipped through the British defences, with some units advancing Williams, p. 122 before running into heavy resistance. By 2300, 9th SS Panzer had been stopped.Reynolds, p. 27 Additional supporting attacks against the British eastern flank had been planned, but the German tank concentrations assembling in the Carpiquet area had been so severely disrupted by RAF fighter-bombers during the afternoon that the attacks never materialised.

The 10th SS Panzer Division launched its attack, behind schedule, at 1430. Following clashes earlier in the day the British were ready and waiting, but after five hours of intense combat the Scottish infantry defending Gavrus had been pushed back into a pocket around the bridge north of the village. An artillery bombardment caused the Germans to withdraw, but the British did not reoccupy the village. Moving towards Hill 113, elements of 10th SS Panzer ran into British tanks and infantry within Évrecy, thwarting their attempt to occupy the hill. Dealing with this obstacle took the remainder of the day, so the division's planned attack on Hill 112 was postponed.Clark, p. 93 The Germans claimed the destruction of 28 tanks, while the British record the loss of only 12.Reynolds, pp. 27&ndash;28 

Believing the aggressive German actions throughout 29 June indicated further major counterattacks for the following day, Dempsey reinforced the Odon bridgehead with a brigade of the 43rd division and pulled in its perimeter. The 159th Infantry Brigade, of the 11th Armoured Division, was placed under the command of the 15th (Scottish) Infantry Division,Ellis, pp. 284&ndash;285 and acceding to O’Connor’s wishes for additional infantry, Dempsey attached the newly arrived 53rd (Welsh) Infantry Division to VIII Corps; the lead brigade arrived near the Epsom start line during the night.Jackson, p. 52 In order to retain possession of Hill 112, Dempsey recognised that he would also need to hold Évrecy and Hill 113; a task that, for the moment, he did not have the resources for.Hart, pp. 140&ndash;141 He therefore ordered the 29th Armoured Brigade to abandon the hill. Convinced that the key position to retain was between Rauray and the Odon,Hart, p. 141 after dark Dempsey withdrew the 29th Armoured Brigade north, across the river,Jackson, p. 51 to be in a position to meet the expected renewed German offensive.Ellis, p. 285
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b59879412a1cf5e9e10f883bbe238257" name="Jupiterpanzergrenadiers" sectnum="4.4#1">../img/b59879412a1cf5e9e10f883bbe238257.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>