<document id="e784121d25e1519ea27ea45d5df0fbde-2" name="Operation_Epsom" cat="29">
<text>
On 20 June Field Marshal Erwin Rommel, commanding German forces in Normandy, was ordered by Hitler to launch a counteroffensive against the Allied lines between the towns of Caumont and Saint-Lô.  The objective was to cut a corridor between the American and British armies by recapturing the city of Bayeux (taken by the British on 7 June) and the coastline beyond.Wilmot, p. 334  Four SS Panzer Divisions and one ''Heer'' Panzer Division were assigned this task.  The attack was to be spearheaded by the 9th and 10th SS Panzer Divisions of the II SS Panzer Corps, recently arrived from the Ukraine,Reynolds, p. 13 supported by the 1st and 2nd SS Panzer Divisions and the 2nd Panzer Division.Wilmot, map p. 321 The vast majority of the tanks used by these formations were Panzer IVs, supplemented by assault guns, Panthers and Tigers&mdash;the latter two among the most lethal and well-protected German armoured vehicles.Williams, p. 112

On 18 June General Bernard Montgomery, the commander of all Allied ground forces in Normandy, issued a directive to Lieutenant-General Miles Dempsey to capture CaenClark, pp. 20&ndash;21 by launching a new pincer attack.Ellis, p. 271 The initial plan called for I and XXX Corps to attack west of Caen for four days before VIII Corps would launch the main attack out of the Orne bridgehead, east of Caen, on 22 June. It was soon realised that VIII Corps would not be able to assemble within the small perimeter of the Orne bridgehead and the plan was revised on 19 June.

The new plan called for a preliminary operation to take place three days before the main assault. I Corp's 51st (Highland) Infantry Division was ordered to strike south from the Orne bridgehead, pinning down elements of the 21st Panzer Division. Operation MartletClark, p. 21 (also known as Operation Dauntless)Ellis, p. 275 was to commence on the day before Epsom; XXX Corp's 49th (West Riding) Infantry Division, supported by the 8th Armoured Brigade, was to secure VIII Corp's flank by capturing the high ground on the right of their axis of advance.

The main role in Operation Epsom was assigned to the newly arrived VIII Corps, consisting of 60,244 men under the command of Lieutenant-General Sir Richard O'Connor.Jackson, pp. 12, 22, 27 VIII Corps would launch their offensive from the beachhead gained by the 3rd Canadian Infantry Division. The operation, split into four phases, intended for the Corps to advance and capture the high ground near Bretteville-sur-Laize, south of Caen.Clark, pp. 31&ndash;32 It would be supported by fire from 736 artillery pieces, three cruisers, and the monitor H.M.S. Roberts. The Royal Air Force would additionally provide close air support and a preliminary bombardment by 250 bombers.Clark, p. 29

The 15th (Scottish) Infantry Division would lead the assault. During Phase I, codenamed ''Gout'', they were tasked with taking the villages of Sainte Manvieu and Cheux. Phase II, codenamed ''Hangover'', would see the division exploit forwards to capture several crossings over the Odon River, and the villages of Mouen and Grainville-sur-Odon. As a tactical alternative, should resistance during the opening phase prove light, the 11th Armoured Division would rush the bridges over the Odon River, seizing the crossings by ''coup de main''.Jackson, p. 29

During these opening two phases, the 43rd (Wessex) Infantry Division&mdash;to be reinforced on 28 June with the Guards Armoured Division's infantry brigade&mdash;was to remain on the start line to provide a "firm base".Jackson, pp. 30&ndash;31 In Epsom's third phase, ''Impetigo'', the 43rd Division would move forward to relieve all Scottish infantry north of the Odon.  The 15th Division would then assemble across the river, expanding the bridgehead by capturing several key villages. In the operation's final phase, codenamed ''Goitre'', elements of the 43rd Division would cross the river to hold the area taken, while the 15th Division would continue to expand their bridgehead. In addition, the 11th Armoured Division would attempt to force a crossing over the River Orne and advance on their final objective of Bretteville-sur-Laize. The 4th Armoured Brigade, although attached to the 11th Armoured Division, was restricted to operations between the Odon and Orne, both to protect the Corps flank and to be a position to attack westwards or towards Caen as necessary. 

Depending on the success of VIII Corps attack, I Corps would then launch two supporting operations, codenamed ''Aberlour'' and ''Ottawa''.  The former would see the 3rd Infantry Division, supported by a Canadian infantry brigade, attack north of Caen; the latter would be a move by the 3rd Canadian Infantry Division, supported by the 2nd Canadian Armoured Brigade, to take the village and airfield of Carpiquet.Stacey, p. 150

Originally planned for 22 June, Epsom was postponed until 26 June to make up deficiencies in manpower and material.Jackson, p. 22 The initial opposition to Epsom was expected to come from the already depleted 12th SS Panzer Division Hitlerjugend ("Hitler Youth"), along with elements of both the 21st Panzer Division and Panzer Lehr.Clark, p. 24
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d20a1a3a264d4f3681989551f1083388" name="Epsom_map" sectnum="2#1">../img/d20a1a3a264d4f3681989551f1083388.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>