<document id="e784121d25e1519ea27ea45d5df0fbde-4.3" name="Operation_Epsom" cat="29">
<text>
During the early hours of 28 June, a battle group of the 1st SS Panzer Division&ndash;Kampfgruppe Frey&mdash;arrived at the front and was placed under the command of the 12th SS Panzer Division. At 0810Clark, p. 73 General Dollmann, commanding the German Seventh Army, ordered SS-Obergruppenführer Paul Hausser to divert his II SS Panzer Corps to counterattack south of Cheux.Williams, pp. 111&ndash;112 Hausser replied that no counterattack could be launched until the following day, as so many of his units had yet to reach the front.Reynolds, p. 22 Before any plans could be finalised, the German command was thrown into disarray by Dollmann's sudden death; both Field Marshals Rommel and Gerd von Rundstedt (OB West) were en route to a conference with Hitler, and out of touch with the situation.Wilmot, p. 344 Consequently it was not until 1500 that Hausser was appointed the new commander of the Seventh Army, with Willi Bittrich, the former commander of the 9th SS Panzer Division, replacing him as commander of II SS Panzer Corps (although Hausser was advised to retain control of the Corps until the following morning). Pending the return of Rommel to Normandy, Hausser was also to assume the role of supreme commander in the invasion area.Reynolds, p. 23 At 1700 the command structure was again redrawn; Seventh Army, under Hausser, would be responsible for the invasion front facing the American army, while General von Schweppenburg's Panzer Group West would be responsible for the invasion front facing the Anglo-Canadian forces.


At 0530 elements of the 15th (Scottish) Infantry Division, with tank support, launched a new assault to capture the village of Grainville-sur-Odon. After shelling and close quarter street fighting, the Scots secured the village by 1300 hours; German counterattacks followed, but were repulsed.Clark, p. 74 At 0600 the Germans began two strong flanking attacks, with the intention of pinching out the British salient. Kampfgruppe Frey, on the salient's eastern flank, launched an attack north of the Odon supported by Panzer IVs of the 21st Panzer Division. This reached the villages of Mouen and Tourville, but the British counterattacked from the direction of Cheux, resulting in confused and heavy fighting throughout the day. Frey's battle group managed to gain control of Mouen;Clark, p. 79 British counterattacks supported by tanks halted any further advance, but were unable to retake the village.Clark, p. 80 Meanwhile British patrols found Marcelet partially abandoned, the German front line having been pulled back towards Carpiquet.Jackson, p. 42

On the western flank, Kampfgruppe Weidinger, supported by Panthers, aimed a thrust at recapturing Brettevillette, Grainville-sur-Odon and ultimately Mondrainville. The British defenders held their positions, launching local counterattacks to retake lost ground, and eventually the German offensive ground to a halt within  of linking up with the lead elements of Kampfgruppe Frey.

South of the Odon, at 0900 the Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders advanced out of the bridgehead with the aim of capturing a bridge north of the village of Gavrus. Heavy fighting took place into the afternoon before both village and bridge were in Scottish hands. Meanwhile infantry from the 11th Armoured Division expanded the bridgehead itself, by taking the village of Baron-sur-Odon, and the 23rd Hussars with infantry support advanced on Hill 112 (). Having secured its northern slope and dislodged the defenders from its crest, they were unable to advance further due to stiff resistance from forces dug in on the hill's reverse slope.Jackson, p. 41 Several unsuccessful counterattacks were launched by 12th SS Panzer,Saunders, pp. 27&ndash;30 and the battered hussars were relieved at 1500 by the 3rd Royal Tank Regiment, but neither side was able to take complete control of the hill. The 11th Armoured Division had lost nearly 40 tanks on its slopes by the end of the day, and was surrounded on three sides, but support troops had managed to reach and reinforce the position.Saunders, p. 32
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1e646ced9ccd04269a29c3bc46741777" name="7th_Royal_Tank_Regiment_supporting_8th_Royal_Scots_28-06-1944" sectnum="4.3#1">../img/1e646ced9ccd04269a29c3bc46741777.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>