<document id="e784121d25e1519ea27ea45d5df0fbde-4.2" name="Operation_Epsom" cat="29">
<text>
With no further attacks forthcoming during the night, the German command believed that the British offensive had been successfully halted, so during the early hours of 27 June, II SS Panzer Corps was ordered to resume preparations for its counter strike towards Bayeux.Wilmot, pp. 343&ndash;344

On the right of the British advance, the I SS Panzer Corps launched a counterattack employing 80 tanks; this was first disorganised by artillery fire before foundering on the anti-tank guns of the 49th (West Riding) Infantry Division, who then resumed their attempt to secure VIII Corps flank. The village of Rauray was finally taken by the 49th Division at 1600 on 27 June, after further heavy fighting against the 12th SS Panzer Division's panzergrenadiers. German forces had been diverted from opposing VIII Corps advance,Clark, p. 65 and the fall of Rauray denied the Germans an important observation point, although they remained in control of an area of high ground to the south.Clark, pp. 65&ndash;67

Epsom was resumed at 0445 by the 10th Battalion Highland Light Infantry of the 227 (Highland) Infantry Brigade. With support from Churchill tanks, the battalion intended to make a bid for the Odon crossing at Gavrus. However, the Highlanders immediately ran into stiff opposition from elements of 12th SS Panzer, and despite heavy artillery support were unable to advance all day. Casualties were heavy on both sides.Clark, p. 68

At 0730 the 2nd Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders, also of the 227 (Highland) Infantry Brigade, launched an attack aimed at capturing the Odon crossing at Tourmauville, northwest of the village of Baron-sur-Odon.Clark, p. 67  With the available German forces already engaged by the Highland Light Infantry, the Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders, supported by the 23rd Hussars, were able to advance as far as Colleville with relative ease. However, the small German garrison there, supported by 88 mm guns, inflicted heavy casualties upon the British and denied them the village until the afternoon. With this last obstacle dealt with, the battalion seized the bridge at Tourmauville at around 1700, and a bridgehead was established.Jackson, p. 39 By 1900, two depleted squadrons of the 23rd Hussars, and a company of the 8th Rifle Brigade, had crossed the Odon into the bridgehead.Saunders, p. 20

The remainder of the 15th (Scottish) Infantry Division was positioned around Cheux and Sainte Manvieu, and was in the process of being relieved by the 43rd (Wessex) Infantry Division. One battalion of the 43rd, on moving into the outskirts of Cheux, found the Scottish infantry had already moved on and the vacated position had been reoccupied by grenadiers of 12th SS Panzer. After battling to recapture the position,  at 0930 the battalion was counterattacked by six Panthers of the 2nd Panzer Division. The attack penetrated into the outskirts of Cheux, destroying several anti-tank guns before it was beaten off. Further attacks by 2nd Panzer were halted, but the entire front was "a mass of small engagements". For the rest of the morning, and afternoon, the Scottish infantry along with the 4th and 29th Armoured Brigades expanded the salient north of the Odon and secured the Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders' rear.Jackson, pp. 39&ndash;40 During late evening, the men of the 159th Infantry Brigade (11th Armoured Division) were transported in trucksJackson, p. 40 through the narrow "Scottish Corridor"Clark, p. 72 to Tourville, where they dismounted and crossed the Odon on foot to reinforce the bridgehead.

During the night Kampfgruppe Weidinger, a 2,500-strong battle group from the 2nd SS Panzer Division, arrived at the front and was initially placed under the command of the Panzer Lehr Division.Reynolds, p. 21
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1ff52e844b49508077893ad2eaec1f55" name="Epsom27June" sectnum="4.2#1">../img/1ff52e844b49508077893ad2eaec1f55.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>