<document id="e784121d25e1519ea27ea45d5df0fbde-5.6" name="Operation_Epsom" cat="29">
<text>
The II SS Panzer Corps resumed its counter offensive on 1 July, after spending most of the preceding 24 hours regrouping. Unaware that the British had ended their operation, and with overcast weather interfering with Allied air support,Jackson, p. 57 Bittrich believed he had an opportunity to prevent the 11th Armoured Division continuing its advance across the Orne.Clark, p. 101

Before dawn the 10th SS Panzer Division moved off, supported by heavy mortar and artillery fire.Reynolds, p. 30 The Germans took the village of Baron-sur-Odon quickly, but a counterattack by the 31st Tank Brigade won it back by noon. Heavy shelling broke up other attacks by 10th SS Panzer from Hill 112;Jackson, p. 58 British patrols later found an estimated 300&ndash;400 dead panzergrenadiers on the northern slope of the hill.

The 9th SS Panzer Division spent the day attempting to force the British lines between Rauray and the Odon. Supplemented by panzergrenadiers of the 2nd SS Panzer Division and following a preliminary bombardment, tanks and infantry of 9th SS Panzer advanced behind a smoke screen and succeeded in breaking through the outer British defences. However, the assault was halted by secondary positions in front of Rauray and on high ground to the south-east, although some elements penetrated as far as Haut du Bosq. Further German attacks throughout the day were met with intense artillery fire and made no progress, and in the early evening a British counterattack, utilising Sherman and flame-throwing Churchill Crocodile tanks, restored the front line to that at the start of the day. Casualties were heavy on both sides. Thirty German tanks were claimed destroyed, mostly by the 49th (West Riding) Infantry Division; elements of the 12th SS Panzer Division had been repulsed during the morning, and artillery fire halted attacks from other formations.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6043c35dcc1e0e8927542947ec12e510" name="German_80mm_Mortar" sectnum="5.6#1">../img/6043c35dcc1e0e8927542947ec12e510.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>