<document id="e784121d25e1519ea27ea45d5df0fbde-4.5" name="Operation_Epsom" cat="29">
<text>
Willi Bittrich was greatly concerned by the failure of II SS Panzer Corps to significantly reduce the British salient, and he ordered a resumption of the offensive during the night of 29&ndash;30 June, hoping to negate Allied air support. The 19th and 20th Regiments of the 9th SS Panzer Division renewed their attacks against Grainville-sur-Odon and le Valtru during the hours of darkness, but little progress was made in the face of opposition from the tanks of the 11th Armoured Division&mdash;now in position north of the Odon&mdash;and heavy artillery bombardments.Clark, p. 95 At 0120 the 10th SS Panzer Division started to move towards Hill 112 and at dawn, covered by a heavy artillery barrage, they assaulted the vacated British positions. Unaware that the British had pulled back, panzergrenadiers and tanks of the 10th SS Panzer advanced on the hill from the south and south-west, while infantry from 12th SS Panzer attacked from the east and south-east. Meeting no opposition, by noon the Germans had firmly installed themselves on the hill,Reynolds, p. 28 but a British counterattack and artillery fire broke up a follow-up attack towards Baron-sur-Odon.

With only limited results achieved thus far, Bittrich called off further offensive action against VIII Corps.Clark, p. 96 In the evening Hausser, now commanding the Seventh Army, informed Rommel's headquarters that his counterattacks had been temporarily suspended due to "tenacious enemy resistance" and intensive Allied artillery and naval gunfire.Wilmot, pp. 345&ndash;346 Unaware of this, and believing that more German attacks would follow, Dempsey closed down Operation Epsom. The front gradually settled down save for minor and inconclusive skirmishing, although both sides spent the remainder of the day heavily shelling one another.Clark, pp. 95&ndash;98 The battleship HMS ''Rodney'' contributed by bombarding villages suspected of containing German command centres; one was later confirmed to have housed the headquarters of the I SS Panzer Corps.Jackson, p. 55 With no further British offensive moves planned for the short term, during the afternoon the Gavrus bridges were given up&mdash;their Scottish defenders being withdrawn across the Odon.Clark, p. 98 At 2030 the town of Villers-Bocage, a vital traffic centre for the German forces, was destroyed by 250 RAF heavy bombers. It was hoped that German troops would be caught by the bombing, but only French civilians were present at the time.Jackson, p. 56
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a59b366c8db934c6e1207ea933114ae1" name="Villers-Bocage_destroyed" sectnum="4.5#1">../img/a59b366c8db934c6e1207ea933114ae1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>