<document id="e797a4c1590afa7afaa3a9bba656a58a-2.3" name="Nansen's_Fram_expedition" cat="14">
<text>
Section and Plan drawings for ''Fram'', as agreed between Nansen and shipbuilder Colin Archer
To design and build his ship Nansen chose Colin Archer, Norway's leading shipbuilder and naval architect. Archer was well-known for a particular hull design that combined seaworthiness with a shallow draught, and had pioneered the design of "double-ended" craft in which the conventional stern was replaced by a point, increasing manoeuvrability.Huntford, pp. 183–84  Nansen records that Archer made "plan after plan of the projected ship; one model after another was prepared and abandoned".Nansen, Vol. I pp. 59–60 Finally, agreement was reached on a design, and on 9 June 1891 the two men signed the contract.

Nansen wanted the ship in one year; he was anxious to get away before anyone else could adopt his ideas and forestall him.Huntford, p. 186  The ship's most significant external feature was the roundness of the hull, designed so that there was nothing upon which the ice could get a grip. Bow, stern and keel were rounded off, and the sides smoothed so that, in Nansen's words, the vessel would "slip like an eel out of the embraces of the ice".  To give exceptional strength the hull was sheathed in South American greenheart, the hardest timber available. The three layers of wood forming the hull provided a combined thickness of between 24 and 28 inches (60–70 cm), increasing to around 48 inches (1.25 metres) at the bow, which was further protected by a protruding iron stem. Added strength was provided by crossbeams and braces throughout the length of the hull.Nansen, Vol. I pp. 62–68

The ship was rigged as a three-masted schooner, with a total sail area of . Its auxiliary engine of 220 horse-power was capable of speeds up to .Nansen, Vol I. p. 69 However, speed and sailing qualities were secondary to the requirement of providing a safe and warm stronghold for Nansen and his crew during a drift that might extend for several years, so particular attention was paid to the insulation of the living quarters.Fleming, p. 240 At around 400 gross register tonnage, the ship was considerably larger than Nansen had first anticipated, with an overall length of  and a breadth of , a ratio of just over three to one, giving her an unusually stubby appearance.Huntford, pp. 192–97 This odd shape was explained by Archer: "A ship that is built with exclusive regard to its suitability for  object must differ essentially from any known vessel."Archer, quoted in Nansen, Vol. I p. 60 On 6 October 1892, at Archer's yard at Larvik, the ship was launched by Nansen's wife Eva after a brief ceremony. The ship was named ''Fram'', meaning "Forward".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="02d0a21afcd47ef8acda459238057eec" name="ColinArcher" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/02d0a21afcd47ef8acda459238057eec.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>