<document id="e856bf7cda266acbfc236c123cd8c802-2" name="The_Mummy_(1999_film)" cat="19">
<text>
* Brendan Fraser as Richard "Rick" O'Connell: An adventurer who served in the French Foreign Legion. Producer James Jacks offered the role of Rick O'Connell to Tom Cruise, Brad Pitt, Matt Damon and Ben Affleck but the actors were not interested or could not fit the role into their respective schedules. Jacks and Director Stephen Sommers were impressed with the money that ''George of the Jungle'' was making at the box office and cast Brendan Fraser as a result; Sommers also commented that he felt Fraser fit the Errol Flynn swashbuckling character he had envisioned perfectly. The actor understood that his character "doesn't take himself too seriously, otherwise the audience can't go on that journey with him".

* Rachel Weisz as Evelyn Carnahan: A clumsy yet intelligent Egyptologist. Evelyn undertakes the expedition to Hamunaptra to discover an ancient book, proving herself to her peers. Rachel Weisz was not a big fan of horror films but did not see this film as such. As she said in an interview, "It's hokum, a comic book world."

* John Hannah as Jonathan Carnahan: Evelyn's bumbling older brother, whose primary goal is to get rich; he signs on for the trip to Hamunaptra after learning from Evelyn that the city is supposed to be where the ancient pharaohs hid "the wealth of Egypt." Jonathan is also a thief; he steals the key needed to open the Book of Amun-Ra from Rick in prison, and manages to pickpocket the same key from Imhotep during the film's climactic battle.

* Arnold Vosloo as High Priest Imhotep: One of Pharaoh Seti I's most trusted advisers, Imhotep betrays his sovereign out of love for Anck-su-namun. He is cursed and slowly killed for his treachery, but is resurrected 3,000 years later to continue his plans. South African stage actor Vosloo understood the approach that Sommers was going for in his screenplay, but only agreed to take on the role of Imhotep "if I could do it absolutely straight. From Imhotep's point of view, this is a skewed version of 'Romeo and Juliet'."

* Kevin J. O'Connor as Beni Gabor: A former soldier in the Foreign Legion, like Rick. Beni is obsessed with wealth, but also extremely cowardly; he betrays his employers when faced with Imhotep's wrath, who takes him in as his servant when he prays to God in Hebrew, the language of those who were enslaved in his time.

* Oded Fehr as Ardeth Bay: A member of the Medjai, an ancient order dedicated to protecting the resting place of Imhotep. When the mummy is awakened, he and his warriors pledge to destroy the creature.

* Jonathan Hyde as Dr. Allen Chamberlain: An Egyptologist who leads a rival expedition to Hamunaptra, led by Beni. While Chamberlain tries to open the Book of the Dead, he knows not to read from it, and turns to the Medjai when Imhotep is brought to life. Since he opened the box that contained the Book of the Dead, he is cursed and eventually killed.

* Erick Avari as Dr. Terrence Bay: Evelyn's superior who works at a museum in Cairo. Bay deliberately tries to stop Evelyn and her brother from learning the location of Hamunaptra, knowing what evil lurks beneath the desert.

* Stephen Dunham, Corey Johnson, and Tuc Watkins as Henderson, Daniels, and Burns: Americans who travel to Hamunaptra in a treasure-hunting expedition. Opening a cursed box, they steal priceless canopic jars. They are all eventually killed by Imhotep, who fully regenerates by sucking the life out of each of them.

* Bernard Fox as Winston Havelock: a retired Royal Air Force pilot from World War I living at the fort Rick and the others hide at.  He later helps Rick, Jonathan, and Ardeth get to Hamunaptra, but is killed by the sandstorm Imhotep creates.

* Patricia Velásquez as Anck-Su-Namun: The mistress of Seti I; no other man is allowed to touch her. When Pharaoh learns of her affair with Imhotep, Anck-Su-Namun commits suicide rather than be caught for Seti's murder.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="905e64503cb466f39675754d4bdaae6d" name="Mummymovie1" sectnum="2#1">../img/905e64503cb466f39675754d4bdaae6d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>