<document id="e8c1e1cd9937a334aa69d7499477e2ad-3" name="Koli_Point_action" cat="29">
<text>
As Shōji's forces began their march to rejoin the main body of Japanese forces west of the Matanikau River, the US 2nd Marine Raider Battalion, under the command of Lieutenant Colonel Evans Carlson, which had been guarding an airfield construction effort underway at Aola Bay,  further east from Koli Point, set off in pursuit.  Over the next month, with the aid of native scouts, Carlson's raiders repeatedly attacked trailing elements and stragglers from Shōji's forces, killing almost 500 of them.  In addition, a lack of food and tropical diseases felled more of Shōji's men.  By the time the Japanese reached the Lunga River, about halfway to the Matanikau, only 1,300 men remained with Shōji's main body.  Several days later, when Shōji reached the 17th Army positions west of the Matanikau, only 700 to 800 survivors were still with him.  Survivors from Shōji's force later participated in the Battle of Mount Austen, the Galloping Horse, and the Sea Horse in December 1942 and January 1943.Hough, ''Pearl Harbor to Guadalcanal'', p. 350, Shaw, ''First Offensive'', p. 42–43, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 423–424, Griffith, ''Battle for Guadalcanal'', p. 246, Miller, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 200, Zimmerman, ''Guadalcanal Campaign'', p. 141–145, Jersey, p. 361.

Speaking of the Koli Point action, US Sergeant (later Brigadier General) John E. Stannard, who participated as a member of the 164th Regiment, stated that the battle for Koli Point was "the most complex land operation, other than the original landing, that the Americans had conducted on Guadalcanal up to that time."  He added, "The Americans learned once again that offensive operations against the Japanese were much more complicated and difficult than was defeating banzai charges."Jersey, ''Hell's Islands'', p. 299.  The Americans later abandoned the attempt to construct an airfield at Aola.  Instead, the Aola construction units moved to Koli Point where they successfully built an auxiliary airfield beginning on December 3, 1942.Miller, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 174.

The next major Japanese reinforcement effort failed during the Naval Battle of Guadalcanal, undertaken as Shōji and his troops struggled to reach friendly lines near the Matanikau.  Although most of Shōji's troops had escaped from Koli Point, the inability of the Japanese to keep their forces on Guadalcanal adequately supplied or reinforced prevented them from contributing effectively to what turned out to be Japan's ultimately unsuccessful effort to hold the island or retake Henderson Field from Allied forces.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 428–492, Rottman, ''Japanese Army'', p. 64, Dull, ''Imperial Japanese Navy'', p. 245–69, Hammel, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 144.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="06b7640118bd04e2b8d2754471facfde" name="Guad2MarineRaiderPatrol" sectnum="3#1">../img/06b7640118bd04e2b8d2754471facfde.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>