<document id="e8c1e1cd9937a334aa69d7499477e2ad-1.2" name="Koli_Point_action" cat="29">
<text>
Between October 1 and October 17, the Japanese delivered 15,000 troops to Guadalcanal, giving Hyakutake 20,000 total troops to employ for his planned offensive. Because of the loss of their positions on the east side of the Matanikau, the Japanese decided that an attack on the US defenses along the coast would be prohibitively difficult.  Thus, after observation of the American defences around Lunga Point by his staff officers, Hyakutake decided that the main thrust of his planned attack would be from south of Henderson Field.  His 2nd Division (augmented by troops from the 38th Division), under Lieutenant General Masao Maruyama and comprising 7,000 soldiers in three infantry regiments of three battalions each was ordered to march through the jungle and attack the American defences from the south near the east bank of the Lunga River.  The 2nd Division was split into three units; the Left Wing Unit under Major General Yumio Nasu containing the 29th Infantry Regiment, the Right Wing Unit under Major General Kiyotake Kawaguchi consisting of troops from the 230th Infantry Regiment (from the 38th Infantry Division), and the division reserve led by Maruyama comprising the 16th Infantry Regiment.Jersey, ''Hell's Islands'', p. 272 and 297, Shaw, ''First Offensive'', p. 34, and Rottman, ''Japanese Army'', p. 61–63, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 328–340, Hough, ''Pearl Harbor to Guadalcanal'', p. 329–330, Griffith, ''Battle for Guadalcanal'', p. 186–187.  Frank states that Kawaguchi's forces also included what remained of the 3rd Battalion, 124th Infantry Regiment which was originally part of the 35th Infantry Brigade commanded by Kawaguchi during the Battle of Edson's Ridge.  Jersey states that it was actually the 2nd Battalion of the 124th along with 1st and 3rd battalions of the 230th Infantry Regiment, parts of the 3rd Independent Trench Mortar Battalion, the 6th Independent Rapid-Fire Gun Battalion, the 9th Independent Rapid-Fire Gun Battalion, and the 20th Independent Mountain Artillery.


On October 23, Maruyama's forces struggled through the jungle to reach the American lines.  Kawaguchi, on his own initiative, began to shift his right wing unit to the east, believing that the American defenses were weaker in that area.  Maruyama, through one of his staff officers, ordered Kawaguchi to keep to the original attack plan.  When he refused, Kawaguchi was relieved of command and replaced by Colonel Toshinari Shōji, commander of the 230th Infantry Regiment.  That evening, after learning that the left and right wing forces were still struggling to reach the American lines, Hyakutake postponed the attack to 19:00 on October 24.  The Americans remained completely unaware of the approach of Maruyama's forces.Griffith, ''Battle for Guadalcanal'', p. 193, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 346–348, Rottman, ''Japanese Army'', p. 62.

Finally, late on October 24 Maruyama's forces reached the US Lunga perimeter. Over two consecutive nights Maruyama's forces conducted numerous, unsuccessful frontal assaults on positions defended by troops of the 1st Battalion, 7th Marines (1/7) under Lieutenant Colonel Chesty Puller and the US Army's 3rd Battalion, 164th Infantry Regiment, commanded by Lieutenant Colonel Robert Hall. US Marine and Army rifle, machine gun, mortar, artillery and direct canister fire from 37 mm anti-tank guns "wrought terrible carnage" on the Japanese.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 361–362.  More than 1,500 of Maruyama's troops were killed in the attacks while the Americans lost about 60 killed.  Shōji's right wing units did not participate in the attacks, choosing instead to remain in place to cover Nasu's right flank against a possible attack in that area by US forces that never materialized.Hough, ''Pearl Harbor to Guadalcanal'', p. 336, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 353–362, Griffith, ''Battle for Guadalcanal'', p. 197–204, and Miller, ''Guadalcanal: The First Offensive'', p. 160–162.


At 08:00 on October 26, Hyakutake called off any further attacks and ordered his forces to retreat. Maruyama's left wing and division reserve survivors were ordered to retreat back to the Matanikau River area while the right wing unit under Shōji was told to head for Koli Point,  east of the Lunga River.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', 363–406, 418, 424, and 553, Zimmerman, ''Guadalcanal Campaign'', p. 122–123, Griffith, ''Battle for Guadalcanal'', p. 204, Hough, ''Pearl Harbor to Guadalcanal'', p. 337 and 347, Rottman, ''Japanese Army'', p. 63, Miller, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 195.

To provide support for the right wing units (now called the Shōji Detachment) marching towards Koli, the Japanese dispatched a Tokyo Express run for the night of November 2 to land 300 fresh troops from a previously uncommitted company of the 230th Infantry Regiment, two mountain guns, provisions, and ammunition at Koli Point.  American radio intelligence intercepted Japanese communications concerning this effort and the Marine command on Guadalcanal determined to try to intercept it.  With many of the American units currently involved in an operation west of the Matanikau, Vandgrift could spare only one battalion.  The 2nd Battalion, 7th Marine Regiment (2/7), commanded by Lieutenant Colonel Herman H. Hanneken, marched east from Lunga Point at 06:50 on November 2 and reached Koli Point after dark the same day.  After crossing the Metapona River at its mouth, Hanneken deployed his troops along  in the woods facing the beach to await the arrival of the Japanese ships.Zimmerman, ''Guadalcanal Campaign'', p. 133–134, Griffith, ''Battle for Guadalcanal'', p. 217, Hough, ''Pearl Harbor to Guadalcanal'', p. 347, Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 414, Miller, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 195–196, Hammel, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 140, Shaw, ''First Offensive'', p. 41–42, Jersey, ''Hell's Islands'', p. 297.  Jersey states that the troops landed were from the 2nd Company, 230th Infantry commanded by 1st Lt Tamotsu Shinno plus the 6th Battery, 28th Mountain Artillery Regiment with the two guns.  The provisions included 650 bales of rice and ten bales of powdered miso.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="618980145a67b0fde936a5863b085a31" name="ToshinariShoji" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/618980145a67b0fde936a5863b085a31.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>