<document id="e8f64b142074f8d56456503a41caded3-4.6.4" name="First-move_advantage_in_chess" cat="26">
<text>
In a "reversed opening", White plays an opening typically played by Black, but with colors reversed and thus an extra  tempo.Hooper and Whyld 1992, p. 339. Evans writes of such openings, "If a defense is considered good for Black, it must be even better for White with a move in hand." Lasker acknowledges this idea, without actually adopting it, writing, "Since the Sicilian yields a fair game to the second player, one is tempted to think that it should be proportionately stronger when essayed by the first player, who has all the advantages of that Opening and a move into the bargain." Lasker 1960, p. 99. Former World Champion Mikhail Botvinnik reportedly expressed the same view.IMs Alexander Raetsky and Maxim Chetverik relate "an old anecdote" that, "In the Moscow Chess Club someone answered 1.c4 with 1...e5 and was immediately reprimanded by former World Champion Mikhail Botvinnik. Botvinnik carefully explained that White now had a Sicilian with a tempo more..." GM Bent Larsen recalled playing a blitz game where Bovinnik kibitzed after 1.c4 e5 that Black should take his move back because the "Sicilian is so strong that you cannot let your opponent play it with an extra tempo." Andrew Soltis, "Chess to Enjoy" column, "KIBITZER: ''one who gives good advice to your opponent''", ''Chess Life'', May 1995, p. 18. Watson questions this idea, citing Suba's thesis that Black, by moving second, has more complete information than White. He writes, "everyone has such difficulties playing as White against a Sicilian Defence (1.e4 c5), but ... leading masters have no qualms about answering 1.c4 with 1...e5."Watson 1998, p. 233. To explain this paradox, Watson discusses several different reversed Sicilian lines, showing how Black can exploit the disadvantages of various "extra" moves for White.Watson 1998, pp. 234–36. He concludes, "The point is, Black's set-up in the Sicilian is fine as a reactive system, but not worth much when trying to claim the initiative as White. This is true because Black is able to react to the specific plan White chooses; in Suba's terms, his information is indeed a move greater! Furthermore, he is able to take advantage of dead equal positions which White (hoping to retain the advantage of the first move) would normally avoid."Watson 1998, p. 236. In an earlier book, Watson wrote of the position after 1.c4 e5, "More often than not, the extra tempo brings with it the drawback of committing oneself before one's opponent, and thus opening oneself to possible counterattacks and equalizing plans."



Watson also observes, "Similarly, the Dutch Defence looks particularly sterile when White achieves the reversed positions a tempo up (it turns out that he has nothing useful to do!); and indeed, many standard Black openings are not very inspiring when one gets them as White, tempo in hand." GM Alex Yermolinsky likewise notes that GM Vladimir Malaniuk, a successful exponent of the Leningrad Dutch (1.d4 f5 2.g3 g6) at the highest levels, "once made a deep impression on me by casually dismissing someone's suggestion that he should try 1.f4 as White. He smiled and said, 'That extra move's gonna hurt me.' "

Yermolinsky also agrees with Alekhine's criticism of 1.g3 e5 2.Nf3,; a reversed Alekhine's Defense, in Réti-Alekhine, Baden-Baden 1925, writing that Alekhine "understood the difference in opening philosophies for White and Black, and realized they just can't be the same! White is supposed to try for more than just obtaining a comfortable game in reversed colour opening set-ups, and, as the statistics show—surprisingly for a lot of people, but not for me—White doesn't even score as well as Black does in the same positions with his extra tempo and all." Watson cites another example of an unsuccessful reversed opening for White: while the Meran Variation of the Semi-Slav Defense is considered a dynamic counterattacking system, with colors reversed it is the classical variation of the Colle System, one of the dullest queen-pawn openings. Howard Staunton, generally considered to have been the strongest player in the world from 1843 to 1851, made a similar point over 160 years ago, writing that Owen's Defense (1.e4 b6) is playable for Black, but that 1.b3 is inferior to "the more customary  moves, from its being essentially defensive".

Watson concludes that (a) "most moves have disadvantages as well as advantages, so an extra move is not always an unqualified blessing"; (b) "with his extra information about what White is doing, Black can better react to the new situation"; and (c) because a draw is likely to be more acceptable to Black than to White, White is apt to avoid lines that allow drawish simplifications, while Black may not object to such lines.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4e0fa9bf4c7db01666a83c6a1a0fdd84" name="Vladimir_Malaniuk_2009" sectnum="4.6.4#1">../img/4e0fa9bf4c7db01666a83c6a1a0fdd84.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>