<document id="e8f64b142074f8d56456503a41caded3-2" name="First-move_advantage_in_chess" cat="26">
<text>
Joseph Bertin wrote in his 1735 textbook ''The Noble Game of Chess'', "He that plays first, is understood to have the attack."Hooper and Whyld 1992, p. 38. This is consistent with the traditional view that White, by virtue of the first move, begins with the initiative and should try to extend it into the middlegame, while Black should strive to neutralize White's initiative and attain equality.Evans 1970, p. 89."Chess books have traditionally said that Black's goal in the opening is to obtain equality. A popular variant is that Black must first secure equality and only later search for chances to gain the advantage. ... Books from the first half of the 20th century particularly stressed the need for equalizing before all else." Watson 2006, p. 23. Because White begins with the initiative, a minor mistake by White generally leads only to loss of the initiative, while a similar mistake by Black may have more serious consequences."In most cases, if White goes slightly wrong, he is likely to face an equal or slightly worse position, but if Black goes wrong he is often significantly worse." Rowson 2005, p. 217. Thus, Sveshnikov wrote in 1994, "Black players cannot afford to make even the slightest mistake ... from a theoretical point of view, the tasks of White and Black in chess are different: White has to strive for a win, Black—for a draw!"Adorján 2004, pp. 69–70 (statement by Sveshnikov dated May 12, 1994). Adorján called Sveshnikov a "hypocrite" for making this statement (p. 72), noting that he is "the father of the Sveshnikov Variation" of the Sicilian Defense, which is one of the most dynamic, complex, and unbalanced openings (de Firmian 2008, p. 336).

Chess theorists have long debated how enduring White's initiative is and whether, if both sides play perfectly, the game should end in a win for White or a draw. George Walker wrote in 1846 that, "The first move is an advantage, ... but if properly answered, the first move is of little worth". Earlier in the book, Walker wrote, "He who has the first move has at least this advantage, that he may, in some measure, choose his own plan of attack, whereas the second player is generally forced in what are termed ''Regular Openings'', to act on the defensive for the few first moves; after which the advantage of the first move ceases." ''Id.'' at 5. Steinitz, the first World Champion, who is widely considered the father of modern chess, Kasparov quoted briefly from Emanuel Lasker's lengthy tribute to Steinitz, which appears in Lasker 1960, pp. 188-229.Saidy 1975, pp. 20–21. wrote in 1889, "It is now conceded by all experts that by proper play on both sides the legitimate issue of a game ought to be a draw." Lasker and Capablanca, the second and third World Champions, agreed."The resources on each side are so evenly balanced that the trifling advantage of the first move is not sufficient to force the defence to resignation." "Capablanca ... complain that soon, when all the foremost masters had absorbed the principles of modern technique, one could no longer hope to win a game from them; chess would be played out!" Saidy 1975, p. 24."Capablanca thought that chess was approaching its demise; that the human mind was achieving the ability to choose the best move among the multitude of combinations and variations to such an extent that two equally gifted in this respect, must always draw."  Reuben Fine, one of the world's leading players from 1936 to 1951,"From about 1936 to 1951, when he practically gave up competitive chess, Fine was among the strongest eight players in the world." Hooper and Whyld 1992, p. 135. explained that White's opening advantage is too intangible to be sufficient for a win without an error by Black."The unavoidable fact is that when both sides play perfectly a draw results. Even if an opening advantage can be demonstrated for White, it is still of such an intangible nature that without further error he cannot win." 

The view that a game of chess should end in a draw given best play prevails. Even if it cannot be proved, this assumption is considered "safe" by Rowson and "logical" by Adorján."We do not know for a fact that the starting position is drawn, but it does seem like a safe assumption from a hypertheoretical point of view." Rowson 2005, p. 227. By "hypertheoretical point of view", Rowson means the viewpoint of an omniscient observer, one with a perfect understanding of chess. Rowson 2005, pp. 201–06. At the level of "hypertheory", the concept of an "advantage" for either side is meaningless, since there are only three possible assessments of a position: win for White, win for Black, or draw. Rowson 2005, p. 202."The logical outcome of the game is a draw." Adorján 2004, p. 17. Watson agrees that "the proper result of a perfectly played chess game ... is a draw. ... Of course, I can't prove this, but I doubt that you can find a single strong player who would disagree. ... I remember Kasparov, after a last-round draw, explaining to the waiting reporters: 'Well, chess is a draw.' "Watson 1998, p. 232. Rowson also quotes Kasparov as having said that chess is a draw. Rowson 2005, p. 202. World Champion Bobby Fischer thought that was almost definitely so.Fischer said, "I think it's almost definite that the game is a draw theoretically." However, Pal Benko writes of Fischer:He believed—as have other players and theoreticians—that White's first-move advantage, properly exploited, should amount to virtually a forced win. (This idea may not be as exaggerated as it seems. Of the nineteen games I played against Fischer, I lost only one with White, missing a forced win, and seven with Black.).

Lasker and Capablanca both worried that chess would suffer a "draw death" as top-level players drew more and more of their games.Saidy 1975, p. 24. More recently, Fischer agreed, saying that the game has become played out. All three advocated changing the rules of chess to minimize the number of drawn games. Lasker suggested scoring less than half a point for a draw, and more than half a point for stalemating the opponent's king. Capablanca in the 1920s proposed Capablanca chess, a chess variant played on a larger board and with additional pieces. Fischer advocated Fischer Random Chess, another chess variant, in which the initial position of the pieces is determined at random.

Today some of the sharpest opening variations have been analyzed so deeply that they are often used as drawing weapons. For example, at the highest levels, Black often uses the Marshall Attack in the Ruy Lopez, a line where Black sacrifices a pawn for strong attacking chances, to obtain an endgame where Black is still a pawn down but is able to draw with correct play.Watson 2006, pp. 161–62.A 2009 article quoted Kasparov's view that the Marshall Attack " 'statistically, is like a dead end.' Another top level game, another draw, and 'White has nothing.' " GM Bogdan Lalic wrote that the Marshall Attack began to be called a drawing weapon after Boris Spassky successfully employed it in his 1965 Candidates Match against former World Champion Mikhail Tal. J. H. Donner wrote of the Marshall Attack, "This sacrifice of a pawn nowadays is only played for drawing purposes. Especially against the very strongest masters it has proved to be quite useful to this end." 


In 2007, GMs Kiril Georgiev and Atanas Kolev asserted that much the same was true of the so-called Poisoned Pawn Variation of the Najdorf Sicilian, which arises after 1.e4 c5 2.Nf3 d6 3.d4 cxd4 4.Nxd4 Nf6 5.Nc3 a6 6.Bg5 e6 7.f4 Qb6!? This has long been considered one of the sharpest and most problematic, or even foolhardy, opening lines.Watson observed that 7...Qb6 "is an astonishing move that those raised with classical chess principles would simply reject as a typical beginner's mistake. Black goes running after a pawn when he is undeveloped and already under attack." Watson 2006, p. 199."Referring to this Poisoned Pawn Variation ... the brilliant, classically-oriented grandmaster Salo Flohr commented, even as late as 1972: 'In chess, there is an old rule: in the opening, one must make haste to develop the pieces, and must not move the same piece several times, particularly the queen. This ancient law holds good even for Bobby Fischer'." Watson 1998, p. 18.The Poisoned Pawn Variation "was considered dubious by certain GMs and crazy by Bent Larsen". Siegbert Tarrasch wrote in his classic treatise ''The Game of Chess'', "It is very dangerous to make a raid with the Queen early on in the game. In particular the capture of the Queen's Knight's pawn with the Queen often brings its own revenge." See also  The game usually continues 8.Qd2 Qxb2 9.Rb1 Qa3.Watson 2006, p. 199. Georgiev and Kolev stated that 6.Bg5 is seldom seen at the highest level because the main line of this variation leads, with best play, to a draw by perpetual check.Georgiev and Kolev 2007, p. 10. They wrote that the following game "will probably remain the last word of theory":Georgiev & Kolev 2007, p. 11.

Francisco Vallejo Pons – Kasparov, Moscow 2004 Page 10 mentions the Vallejo Pons – Kasparov game. '''1.e4 c5 2.Nf3 d6 3.d4 cxd4 4.Nxd4 Nf6 5.Nc3 a6 6.Bg5 e6 7.f4 Qb6 8.Qd2 Qxb2 9.Rb1 Qa3 10.f5 Nc6 11.fxe6 fxe6 12.Nxc6 bxc6 13.e5 dxe5 14.Bxf6 gxf6 15.Ne4 Qxa2 16.Rd1 Be7 17.Be2 O-O 18.O-O Ra7 19.Rf3 Kh8 20.Rg3 Rd7 21.Qh6 Rf7 22.Qh5 Rxd1+ 23.Bxd1 Qa5 24.Kf1 Qd8 25.Qxf7 Qxd1+ 26.Kf2 Qxc2+ 27.Kf3 Qd1+ 28.Kf2 Qc2+ 29.Ke3 Bc5+ 30.Nxc5 Qxc5+ 31.Kd2 Qf2+ 32.Kc3 Qd4+ 33.Kc2 Qf2+ 34.Kc3''' 1/2–1/2 (After 34...Qd4+, White cannot escape the checks.)

However, Georgiev and Kolev's pessimistic assessment of 6.Bg5 has since been called into question, as White has succeeded with 10.e5 (another critical line) in several recent high-level games.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4bef63e4deeab00e104771854b20770e" name="Evgeny_Sveshnikov" sectnum="2#1">../img/4bef63e4deeab00e104771854b20770e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>