<document id="e953602af6514acc9fc2cf94289082a7-2.1" name="Sei_Whale" cat="3">
<text>
The Sei Whale feeds near the surface of the ocean, swimming on its side through swarms of prey to obtain its average of about 900 kilograms (2,000 lb) of food each day.  For an animal of its size, it is notable because for the most part, its preferred foods lie relatively low in the food chain, including zooplankton and small fish. The whale's preference for zooplankton has been determined from stomach analyses and direct observations of feeding behaviour.  It has also been determined from the analysis of fecal matter collected near Sei Whales, which appears as a thin brown cloud in the water.  The feces is collected in nets and DNA material in the wastes is separated out and individually identified, to be matched with known species.   The whale competes for food with a variety of other species, including clupeid fish (herring and its relatives), basking sharks, and right whales.  

In the North Atlantic, the Sei Whale feeds primarily on calanoid copepods, specifically ''Calanus finmarchicus'', with a secondary preference for euphausiids (krill), in particular ''Meganyctiphanes norvegica'' and ''Thysanoessa inermis''.  In the North Pacific, the Sei Whale feeds on similar zooplankton, including the copepod species ''Calanus cristatus'', ''Calanus plumchrus'', and ''Calanus pacificus'', and euphausid species ''Euphausia pacifica'', ''Thysanoessa inermis'', ''Thysanoessa longipes'', and ''Thysanoessa spinifera''.  In addition, it is known to eat larger organisms, such as the Japanese Flying Squid, ''Todarodes pacificus pacificus'', and small fish, including members of the ''Engraulis'' (anchovies), ''Cololabis'' (sauries), ''Sardinops'' (pilchards), and ''Trachurus'' (jack mackerels) genera.  Some of these fish in its diet are commercially important.  Off central California, the whale has been observed feeding on anchovies between June and August, and on krill (''Euphausia pacifica'') during September and October.   In the Southern Hemisphere, prey species include the copepods ''Calanus tonsus'', ''Calanus simillimus'', and ''Drepanopus pectinatus'' as well as the euphausids ''Euphausia superba'' and ''Euphausia vallentini''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="aea12676c8b5eba2bb20fd6a7edacbb3" name="Krill_swarm" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/aea12676c8b5eba2bb20fd6a7edacbb3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>