<document id="e953602af6514acc9fc2cf94289082a7-2" name="Sei_Whale" cat="3">
<text>
The Sei Whale is the third largest member of the Balaenopteridae family, after the Blue Whale (up to 180 tonnes, 200 tons) and the Fin Whale (up to 70 tonnes, 77 tons).  Mature adults typically measure between 12 and 15 metres (40&ndash;50 ft) and weigh 20&ndash;30 tonnes (22&ndash;33 tons).  The Southern Sei Whale is larger than the Northern Sei Whale, and females are considerably larger than males.   The largest known Sei Whale measured 20 metres (66 ft), and weighed between 40 and 45 tonnes (44&ndash;50 tons).  The largest specimens taken off Iceland were slightly longer than 16 metres (52 ft). At birth, a calf typically measures 4&ndash;5 metres (13&ndash;16 ft) in length. 

The whale's body is typically a dark steel grey with irregular light grey to white markings on the ventral surface, or towards the front of the lower body.  The whale has a series of 32&ndash;60 pleats or grooves along the bottom of the body that allow the throat area to expand greatly during feeding.   The snout is pointed and the pectoral fins are relatively short compared to other whales, with a length of only 9%&ndash;10% of the total body length, and pointed at the tips.  It has a single ridge extending from the tip of the snout to the paired blowholes that are a distinctive characteristic of baleen whales. 

The whale's skin is often marked by pits or wounds, which after healing become white scars.  These are believed to be caused by ectoparasitic copepods (''Penella'' spp.), lampreys (family Petromyzontidae), or possibly "cookie-cutter" sharks (''Isistius brasiliensis'').  It has a tall, sickle-shaped dorsal fin that ranges in height from 25&ndash;61 centimetres (10&ndash;24 in), and is set about two-thirds of the way back from the tip of the snout.   Dorsal fin shape, pigmentation pattern, and scarring have been used to a limited extent in photo-identification studies of Sei Whales.  The tail is thick and the fluke, or lobe, is relatively small in relation to the size of the whale's body.



This rorqual is a filter feeder, using its baleen plates to obtain its food from the water by opening its mouth, engulfing large amounts of the water containing the food, then straining the water out through the baleen, trapping any food items inside its mouth.  An adult has 300&ndash;380 ashy-black baleen plates on each side of the mouth, each about 48 centimetres (19 in) long.   Each plate is made of fingernail-like keratin that frays out into whitish fine hairs on the ends inside the mouth near the tongue.  The very fine bristles of the Sei Whale's baleen (about 0.1 mm, 0.004 in) are cited as the most reliable feature distinguishing it from all other baleen whales.

The Sei Whale looks similar to other large baleen whales.  The best way to distinguish between it and the Bryde's Whale, apart from differences in each whale's baleen, is by the presence of lateral ridges on the dorsal surface of the Bryde's Whale's head.   Large Sei Whales can be confused with Fin Whales unless the Fin Whale's asymmetrical head colouration is clearly seen; the right side of the lower jaw of the Fin Whale is white, and the left side is grey.  When viewed from the side, the upper edge of the Sei Whale's head has a small arch between the tip of the snout and the eye, whereas the Fin Whale's profile is relatively flat.

Sei Whales usually travel alone or in small groups of up to six individuals.  Larger groups have been seen at particularly abundant feeding grounds.  Very little is known about their social structure.  Males and females may form a bond, but there is insufficient research to know this for certain.

The Sei Whale is among the fastest of all cetaceans.  It can reach speeds of up to 50 kilometres per hour (31 mph, 27 knots) over short distances.  However, it is not a remarkable diver, diving only to relatively shallow depths for between five to fifteen minutes.  Between these dives, the whale swims near the surface for a few minutes, remaining visible in clear, calm waters, with blows occurring at intervals of about 40&ndash;60 seconds.    Unlike the Fin Whale, the Sei Whale tends not to rise high out of the water as it dives.  The blowholes and dorsal fin are often exposed above the water surface simultaneously.  The whale almost never extends its flukes above the surface, and it rarely breaches, or leaps high out of the water.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5f9ce6b6d5ae9ab6076d3a0332ae16e7" name="Baleen" sectnum="2#1">../img/5f9ce6b6d5ae9ab6076d3a0332ae16e7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>