<document id="e953602af6514acc9fc2cf94289082a7-3" name="Sei_Whale" cat="3">
<text>
Sei Whales are found worldwide, although they are only rarely found in polar or tropical waters.  The difficulty of distinguishing Sei Whales at seas from their close relatives, Bryde's Whales and in some cases from Fin Whales, has created confusion about their distributional limits and frequency of occurrence, especially in warmer waters where Bryde's Whales are most common.

In the North Atlantic, the range of the Sei Whale extends from southern Europe or northwestern Africa to Norway in the eastern North Atlantic, and from the southern United States to Greenland in the western.  The southernmost confirmed records are strandings along the northern Gulf of Mexico and in the Greater Antilles.  Throughout its range, the whale tends to avoid semi-enclosed bodies of water such as the Gulf of Mexico, the Gulf of Saint Lawrence, Hudson Bay, the North Sea, and the Mediterranean Sea.   It occurs predominantly in deep water, occurring most commonly over the continental slope, in basins situated between banks, or submarine canyon areas.

In the North Pacific, the Sei Whale is found from 20°N&ndash;23°N latitude in the winter, and from 35°N&ndash;50°N latitude in the summer.  Approximately 75% of the total population of Sei Whales in the North Pacific is found east of the International Date Line, but there is a significant lack of information regarding the overall distribution of the whales in the North Pacific.  Two whales tagged in deep waters off California were later recaptured off Washington and British Columbia, revealing a possible link between these areas, but the lack of other tag recovery data makes these two cases inconclusive.  In the Southern Hemisphere, summer distribution based upon historic catch data is between 40°S&ndash;50°S latitude, while winter distribution is unknown. 

In general, the Sei Whale migrates annually from cool and subpolar waters in summer to temperate and subtropical waters for winter, where food is more abundant.  In the northwest Atlantic, sightings and catch records suggest that the whale moves north along the shelf edge to arrive in the areas of Georges Bank, Northeast Channel, and Browns Bank by mid to late June.  They are present off the south coast of Newfoundland in August and September, and a southbound migration begins moving west and south along the Nova Scotian shelf from mid-September to mid-November.  Whales in the Labrador Sea as early as the first week of June may move farther northward to waters southwest of Greenland later in the summer.  In the northeast Atlantic, the Sei Whale winters as far south as West Africa and follows the continental slope northward in spring.  Large females lead the northward migration and reach the Denmark Strait earlier and more reliably than other sexes and classes, arriving in mid-July and remaining through mid-September.  In some years, males and younger females remain at lower latitudes during the summer months. 

Despite knowing some general trends in the migration patterns of the Sei Whale, exact migration routes are not known and scientists cannot readily predict exactly where groups will appear from one year to the next. A particular location may one year see an influx of many whales and none for several years afterwards.  F.O. Kapel noted a correlation between the occasional appearance of the Sei Whale west of Greenland and the occasional incursion of relatively warm waters from the Irminger Current into that area.  Some evidence from tagging data indicates that individual Sei Whales return off the coast of Iceland on an annual basis.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="40a7fb86b31541d8bbdf6cf283dcaae4" name="Faroe_stamp_403_sei_whale_(Balaenoptera_borealis)" sectnum="3#1">../img/40a7fb86b31541d8bbdf6cf283dcaae4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>