<document id="ea8c2ab6c0180fd6a74a58f1944aa316-4" name="Banksia_integrifolia" cat="3">
<text>
''B. integrifolia'' is widely distributed, in both geographical and ecological terms. According to Alex George, "it spans a wider geographical and climatic range than any other species." Thiele and Ladiges make a similar claim: that its distribution "is a broader latitudinal, altitudinal and ecological amplitude than any other species, with the possible exception of ''B. spinulosa''."

It occurs along almost the entire eastern coast of Australia, from Geelong, Victoria to Proserpine, Queensland. There was an isolated population on Long Island, Tasmania in 1999, and an 1876 record allegedly from King Island, although there has been speculation that that specimen was actually collected in the Furneaux Group. The species no longer occurs at any of these Tasmania locations, and has been declared extinct in Tasmania under that state's ''Threatened Species Protection Act 1995''. The range of latitude is thus about 20 to 38°S.


For most of its distribution, ''B. integrifolia'' occurs only within about 50 kilometres (30 mi) of the coast, where it typically occurs on poor quality sandy soils derived from sandstone. It grows near coastal cliffs and headlands, alongside river estuaries, and even on stabilised sand dunes. The temperature range for this area is around 0&ndash;30 °C (30&ndash;85 °F), with almost no frosts. The species can occur in pure stands, but is usually associated with other species such as ''Melaleuca quinquenervia'' (Broad-leaved Paperbark).

Between Sydney and Brisbane, ''B. integrifolia'' is found up to 200 kilometres (125 mi) inland, with ''B. integrifolia'' subsp. ''monticola'' occurring in the Blue Mountains at altitudes up to 1500 metres (5000 ft). There it grows on better quality volcanic or rocky soils derived from granites and basalts, and would experience up to 100 frosts per year. In this montane habitat, it occurs in association with ''Eucalyptus'' species such as ''E. viminalis'' (Manna Gum) and ''E. pauciflora'' (Snow Gum), and also rainforest species such as ''Nothofagus moorei'' (Antarctic Beech) and ''Orites excelsa'' (Prickly Ash).

Interestingly, no other species of tree occurs closer to the coast at Cape Byron, making ''B. integrifolia'' the most easterly tree on the Australian mainland.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4070e2b59f6a8b42666065b628ac4a81" name="Banksia_integrifolia_integrifolia_Manly2_email" sectnum="4#1">../img/4070e2b59f6a8b42666065b628ac4a81.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>