<document id="ea8c2ab6c0180fd6a74a58f1944aa316-6" name="Banksia_integrifolia" cat="3">
<text>
Hardy and versatile, ''B. integrifolia'' will grow in clay, sand, acid and even alkaline soils, and it shows good resistance to wind and salt, making it suitable for seaside planting. It is therefore highly regarded as a low-maintenance garden tree, although its large size makes it unsuitable for smaller gardens. Its hardiness may however forewarn weed potential, as some evidence of weediness has been seen in Western Australia and New Zealand. When growing near bushland within its native habitat, it is recommended to obtain local provenance seed or plants if available.

The most common form available in commercial nurseries is unimproved ''Banksia integrifolia'' subsp. ''integrifolia''. It prefers a sunny aspect without exposure to frosts, and tolerates fairly heavy pruning. Seeds do not require any treatment, and take 5 to 6 weeks to germinate. Flowering begins at around four to six years from seed. The other subspecies are less well known in cultivation, but are obtainable. Cultivation is presumably similar to ''B. integrifolia'' subsp. ''integrifolia'', except that ''B. integrifolia'' subsp. ''monticola'' may be assumed frost-tolerant. Dwarf forms of ''B. integrifolia'' are sometimes sold, and a registered prostrate cultivar, ''Banksia'' 'Roller Coaster', is available. The latter is a vigorous ground-hugging plant that can spread to 4 or 5 metres across yet remains only 50 centimetres high.

Because of its high resistance to ''P. cinnamomi'' dieback, the feasibility of using ''B. integrifolia'' as a rootstock for susceptible ''Banksia'' species in the cut flower trade is under investigation. Presently, the success rate for grafting is only 30–40%, and even with successful grafts there is a tendency for the union to fail under stress. More research is needed before the technique will be ready for commercial use.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c7e2294e7c29d8628daf9894c1192bf3" name="B_integrifolia_roller_coaster_sylvan1_email" sectnum="6#1">../img/c7e2294e7c29d8628daf9894c1192bf3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>