<document id="ea8fa10412c5e778e8117bd577cd5544-8" name="Cyathus" cat="3">
<text>
The genus ''Cyathus'' was first subdivided into two infrageneric groups (i.e., grouping species below the rank of genus) by the Tulasne brothers; the "eucyathus" group had fruiting bodies with inner surfaces folded into pleats (plications), while the "olla" group lacked plications. Later (1906), Lloyd published a different concept of infrageneric grouping in ''Cyathus'', describing five groups, two in the eucyathus group and five in the olla group.

In the 1970s, Brodie, in his monograph on bird's nest fungi, separated the genus ''Cyathus'' into seven related groups based on a number of taxonomic characteristics, including the presence or absence of plications, the structure of the peridioles, the color of the fruiting bodies, and the nature of the hairs on the outer peridium:Brodie pp. 150&ndash;80.
'''''Olla'' group: '''Species with a tomentum having fine flattened-down hairs, and no plications.
*''C. olla'', ''C. africanus'', ''C. badius'', ''C. canna'', ''C. colensoi'', ''C. confusus'', ''C. earlei'', ''C. hookeri'', ''C. microsporus'', ''C. minimus'', ''C. pygmaeus''
'''''Pallidus'' group:''' Species with conspicuous, long, downward-pointing hairs, and a smooth (non-plicate) inner peridium.
*''C. pallidus'', ''C. julietae''
'''''Triplex'' group: '''Species with mostly dark-colored peridia, and a silvery white inner surface.
*''C. triplex'', ''C. setosus'', ''C. sinensis''
'''''Gracilis'' group:''' Species with tomentum hairs clumped into tufts or mounds.
*''C. gracilis'', ''C. intermedius'', ''C. crassimurus'', ''C. elmeri''
'''''Stercoreus'' group:''' Species with non-plicate peridia, shaggy or wooly outer peridium walls, and dark to black peridioles.
*''C. stercoreus'', ''C. pictus'', ''C. fimicola''
'''''Poeppigii'' group:''' Species with plicate internal peridial walls, hairy to shaggy outer walls, dark to black peridioles, and large, roughly spherical or ellipsoidal spores.
*''C. poeppigii'', ''C. crispus'', ''C. limbatus'', ''C. gayanus'', ''C. costatus'', ''C. cheliensis'', ''C. olivaceo-brunneus''
'''''Striatus'' group:''' Species with plicate internal peridia, hairy to shaggy outer peridia, and mostly elliptical spores.
*''C. striatus'', ''C. annulatus'', ''C. berkeleyanus'', ''C. bulleri'', ''C. chevalieri'', ''C. ellipsoideus'', ''C. helenae'', ''C. montagnei'', ''C. nigro-albus'', ''C. novae-zeelandiae'', ''C. pullus'', ''C. rudis''
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bf403255f49d95cc69dc970c2e6e87c3" name="Cyathus_striatus_Uurrepesäsieni_H7618_C" sectnum="8#1">../img/bf403255f49d95cc69dc970c2e6e87c3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>