<document id="ea94a7ff1f4ca3aac0fbc78682a7801e-1.2.1" name="Baseball" cat="26">
<text>
In the mid-1850s, a baseball craze hit the New York metropolitan area.Rader (2008), pp. 9, 10. By 1856, local journals were referring to baseball as the "national pastime" or "national game".Tygiel (2000), p. 6. A year later, sixteen area clubs formed the sport's first governing body, the National Association of Base Ball Players. In 1863, the organization disallowed putouts made by catching a fair ball on the first bounce. Four years later, it barred participation by African Americans.Rader (2008), p. 27; Sullivan (1997), pp. 68, 69. The game's commercial potential was developing: in 1869 the first fully professional baseball club, the Cincinnati Red Stockings, was formed and went undefeated against a schedule of semipro and amateur teams.Sullivan (1997), pp. 43, 73. The first professional league, the National Association of Professional Base Ball Players, lasted from 1871 to 1875; scholars dispute its status as a major league.Sullivan (1997), p. 83–87.

The more formally structured National League was founded in 1876.  As the oldest surviving major league, the National League is sometimes referred to as the "senior circuit".Sullivan (1997), pp. 83, 130, 243. Several other major leagues formed and failed. In 1884, African American Moses Walker (and, briefly, his brother Welday) played in one of these, the American Association.Zoss (2004), p. 136. An injury ended Walker's major league career, and by the early 1890s, a gentlemen's agreement in the form of the baseball color line effectively barred black players from the white-owned professional leagues, major and minor.Zoss (2004), p. 102. Professional Negro leagues formed, but quickly folded; several independent African American teams succeeded as barnstormers.Sullivan (1997), p. 115. Also in 1884, overhand pitching was legalized.Rader (2008), p. 71. In 1887, softball, under the name of indoor baseball or indoor-outdoor, was invented as a winter version of the parent game.Heaphy, Leslie, "Women Playing Hardball", in ''Baseball and Philosophy: Thinking Outside the Batter's Box'', ed. Eric Bronson (Open Court, 2004), pp. 246–256: p. 247. Virtually all of the modern baseball rules were in place by 1893; the last major change—counting foul balls as strikes—was instituted in 1901. The National League's first successful counterpart, the American League, which evolved from the minor Western League, was established that year.Sullivan (1997), pp. 243–246. The two leagues, each with eight teams, were rivals that fought for the best players, often disregarding each other's contracts and engaging in bitter legal disputes.Sullivan (1997), p. 13.


A modicum of peace was eventually established, leading to the National Agreement of 1903. The pact formalized relations both between the two major leagues and between them and the National Association of Professional Base Ball Leagues, representing most of the country's minor professional leagues.Rader (2008), p. 110; Zimbalist (2006), p. 22. See  The World Series, pitting the two major league champions against each other, was inaugurated that fall, albeit without express major league sanction: The Boston Americans of the American League defeated the Pittsburgh Pirates of the National League.Sullivan (1997), pp. 13–16. The next year, the series was not held, as the National League champion New York Giants, under manager John McGraw, refused to recognize the major league status of the American League and its champion.Sullivan (1997), pp. 141–150; Sullivan (1998), pp. 8–10. In 1905, the Giants were National League champions again and team management relented, leading to the establishment of the World Series as the major leagues' annual championship event.Koppett (2004), p. 99.

As professional baseball became increasingly profitable, players frequently raised grievances against owners over issues of control and equitable income distribution. During the major leagues' early decades, players on various teams occasionally attempted strikes, which routinely failed when their jobs were sufficiently threatened. In general, the strict rules of baseball contracts and the reserve clause, which bound players to their teams even when their contracts had ended, tended to keep the players in check.Burk (2001), pp. 56, 100, 102, 103, 113, 143, 147, 170, et seq.; Powers (2003), pp. 17–21, 27, 83, 121, 122, 160–164, 177; Rader (2008), pp. 60–71. Motivated by dislike for particularly stingy owner Charles Comiskey and gamblers' payoffs, real and promised, members of the Chicago White Sox conspired to throw the 1919 World Series. The Black Sox Scandal led to the formation of a new National Commission of baseball that drew the two major leagues closer together.Powers (2003), pp. 39, 47, 48. The first major league baseball commissioner, Kenesaw Mountain Landis, was elected in 1920. That year also saw the founding of the Negro National League; the first significant Negro league, it would operate until 1931. For part of the 1920s, it was joined by the Eastern Colored League.Burgos (2007), pp. 117, 118.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d53ef8e22be2c63a3fbeaa91855a74cc" name="New_York_Giants_Opening_Day_line-up_at_the_Polo_Grounds_New_York._Left_to_right_Fred_Snodgrass,_Tillie_Shafer,_George_Burns,_Larry_Doyle,_Red_Murray,_Fred_Merkle,_Buck_Herzog,_Chief_Meyers_(baseball)_(LOC)" sectnum="1.2.1#1">../img/d53ef8e22be2c63a3fbeaa91855a74cc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>