<document id="eac3e89ac5cccee29646244e03a74ffe-2" name="Battle_of_Concepción" cat="29">
<text>
Bowie and Fannin were accompanied by ninety soldiers, divided into four companies led by Captains Andrew Briscoe, Robert Coleman, Michael Goheen, and Valentine Bennet.Todish et al. (1998), p. 23.   The group took a northerly route, following the San Antonio River past Missions San Juan and San José.  Along the way they encountered a small party of Mexican scouts, who retreated to Bexar after a brief skirmish.


Approximately  from San Antonio de Bexar and  from the Texian camp at Espada,Barr (1990), p. 23. the Texian scouting party stopped at Mission Concepción.Hardin (1994), p. 30. Five hundred yards (460 m) west of the mission, the San Antonio River curved in a small horseshoe shape, with the two sides of the river's curve approximately  apart.  According to historian Alwyn Barr, "trees shaded both sides of the broad riverbottom which lay about six feet below the level of the rolling praire nearby".  Rather than return immediately to Austin, as their orders specified, Bowie and Fannin instead sent a courier to bring Austin directions to Concepción.  The next day, an angry Austin issued a statement threatening officers who chose not to follow orders with court-martial. 

The Texian scouting party divided into two camps. Fannin supervised 49 men at the south part of the horseshoe bend,Edmondson (2000), p. 221. while Bowie and the remaining men camped at the northern part of the bend. Any Mexican force coming from the north would be caught in their cross-fire.  Pickets were stationed around the area and in the mission tower, which offered greater visibility. As they settled down for the evening, the Texians were surprised to see a Mexican cannonball, fired from one of the church towers in Bexar, hit just beyond their camp.  Many of the Texian soldiers believed that a priest from the mission had informed the Mexican Army of their position.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f7c6734f08731957e643eebf85ed3a89" name="Mission-Concepcion" sectnum="2#1">../img/f7c6734f08731957e643eebf85ed3a89.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>