<document id="eac3e89ac5cccee29646244e03a74ffe-4" name="Battle_of_Concepción" cat="29">
<text>
Austin had intended to reunite the two parts of his army early on October 28, but the group camping at Mission Espada had delayed their departure to unsuccessfully pursue a company that had deserted. Lieutenant Colonel William Barret Travis and his company of cavalry rode ahead of the main body of the army.  When they reached Concepción, the Mexican Army was still visible in the distance.Edmondson (2000), p. 223.  The small band of Texian cavalry pursued but the Mexican soldiers reached Bexar safely.

Less than 30 minutes after the battle ended, the rest of the Texian Army arrived.  Austin felt that the Mexican morale must be low after their defeat and wanted to proceed immediately to Bexar.  Bowie and other officers refused, as they believed Bexar was too heavily fortified.  The Texians searched the area for any Mexican equipment which had been abandoned during the retreat.  They found several boxes of cartridges.  Complaining that the Mexican powder was "little better than pounded charcoal", the Texians emptied the cartridges but kept the bullets.Hardin (1994), p. 34.

That evening, Austin allowed a local priest and men from Bexar to retrieve the bodies of the Mexican soldiers who had died in battle.Barr (1990), p. 26.  Barr estimated that at least 14 Mexican soldiers were killed, with an additional 39 wounded, several of whom died later.  Timothy Todish et al., in their book ''The Alamo Sourcebook'', estimated that 60 Mexican soldiers were killed, while historian Stephen Hardin claimed that 76 Mexican soldiers died.  The only Texian to die in battle was Andrews,Andrews County, Texas is named for Richard Andrews. and Jarvis was the only Texian classified as wounded.  

This battle, which historian J.R. Edmondson describes as "the first major engagement of the Texas Revolution",Edmondson (2000), p. 224. was the last offensive against the Texians that Cos would order.Barr (1990), p. 27.   Barr attributed the Texian victory to "able leadership, a strong position, and greater firepower".  The Mexican cavalry was unable to fight effectively in the wooded, riverbottom terrain, and the weapons of the Mexican infantry had a much lower range than that of the Texians.  Although Barr continues that the battle "should have taught ... lessons on Mexican courage and the value of a good defensive position",Barr (1990), p. 60. Hardin believes that "the relative ease of the victory at Concepción instilled in the Texians a reliance on their long rifles and a contempt for their enemies".Hardin (1994), p. 35.  A soldier who later served under Fannin complained that Fannin's "former experience in fighting Mexicans  had led him to neglect to take such precautionary measures as were requisite", which may have contributed to his defeat at the Battle of Coleto in March 1836.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="664b794214298ec7ab6a9a32f16ef588" name="JamesWFannin" sectnum="4#1">../img/664b794214298ec7ab6a9a32f16ef588.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>