<document id="eb4b24f717686b20ebb6ae0b58df0623-4" name="Operation_Brevity" cat="29">
<text>
Although the German and Italian commands in North Africa knew that a British offensive was imminent, Operation Brevity nevertheless caught them unprepared, and Rommel recorded in his diary that the initial attacks had caused him considerable losses.Rommel, p. 136 By midday on 15 May, Axis command was showing signs of confusion. It was erroneously believed that the offensive involved more than 100 tanks, and repeated requests were made to both the Luftwaffe and the Regia Aeronautica for a concerted effort to defeat it. Forces around Tobruk were redeployed east of the besieged city, to block any attempt at relief and to prevent the garrison from breaking out to meet the British advance.Jentz, pp. 132&ndash;133 Lieutenant-Colonel Hans Cramer was sent to reinforce Kampfgruppe von Herff with a tank battalion from Panzer Regiment 8 and a battery of Anti-Aircraft guns,Jentz, p. 132 and additional reinforcements under General von Esebeck were despatched the following day.Jentz, p. 140


The Germans concentrated their riposte against the central column. Von Herff, who had been prepared to fall back, instead launched a local counterattack towards Fort Capuzzo during the afternoon of 15 May with the 2nd Battalion Panzer Regiment 5.Playfair (1956), p. 161 At around 13:30, D Company 1DLI at the landing ground was overrun, and with no anti-tank support more capable than the Boys anti-tank rifle, the remaining troops of 1DLI were forced to fall back towards Musaid. A fortuitous dust cloud aided their withdrawal, but by 14:45 Panzer Regiment 5 was reporting that it had recaptured Capuzzo, inflicting heavy casualties on the British and taking 70 prisoners.Jentz, p. 133

On the desert flank, A Squadron 2RTR's patrol towards Sidi Azeiz was being monitored by Panzer Regiment 5, but the Germans misidentified the light cruiser tanks as heavily armoured Matilda infantry tanks, and reported that an attack was not possible. Colonel von Herff, believing the British had two divisions operating in the area, had grown uneasy. A Squadron's patrol was interpreted as an attempt to concentrate south of Sidi Azeiz, in preparation for a thrust north the next day&mdash;such a move threatened to sweep aside von Herff's force and completely unhinge the German front in the Sollum–Bardia area. In response, von Herff broke contact with the British; his plan was to join up with Cramer's Panzer Regiment 8 to mount a concentrated counterattack the following morning.Playfair (1956), p. 162Jentz, pp. 139&ndash;140
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="97bd1276038e028205075e21278a8bff" name="PanzersJune1941" sectnum="4#1">../img/97bd1276038e028205075e21278a8bff.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>