<document id="ebc1775b949e832d506693962c73c94d-2" name="Bride_of_Frankenstein" cat="19">
<text>
The studio considered making a sequel to ''Frankenstein'' as early as its 1931 preview screenings, following which the film's original ending was changed to allow for Henry Frankenstein's survival.Curtis, p. 154 James Whale initially refused to direct ''Bride'', believing he had "squeezed the idea dry"Vieria, p. 80 on the first film. Following the success of Whale's ''The Invisible Man'', producer Carl Laemmle, Jr. realized that Whale was the only possible director for ''Bride''; Whale took advantage of the situation in persuading the studio to let him make ''One More River''.Curtis, p. 234 Whale believed the sequel would not top the original, so he decided instead to make it a memorable "hoot". According to a studio publicist, Whale and Universal's studio psychiatrist decided "the Monster would have the mental age of a ten-year old boy and the emotional age of a lad of fifteen".

Screenwriter Robert Florey wrote a treatment entitled ''The New Adventures of Frankenstein &ndash; The Monster Lives!'' but it was rejected without comment early in 1932. Universal staff writer Tom Reed wrote a treatment under the title ''The Return of Frankenstein'', a title retained until filming began. Following its acceptance in 1933, Reed wrote a full script that was submitted to the Hays office for review. The script passed its review but Whale, who by then had been contracted to direct, complained that "it stinks to heaven".Curtis, p. 134 L. G. Blochman and Philip MacDonald were the next writers assigned, but Whale also found their work unsatisfactory. In 1934, Whale set John L. Balderston to work on yet another version, and it was he who returned to an incident from the novel in which the creature demands a mate. In the novel Frankenstein creates a mate, but destroys it without bringing it to life. Balderston also created the Mary Shelley prologue. After several months Whale was still not satisfied with Balderston's work and handed the project to playwright William J. Hurlbut and Edmund Pearson. The final script, combining elements of a number of these versions, was submitted for Hays office review in November 1934.Curtis, pp. 234–36 Kim Newman reports that Whale planned to make Elizabeth the heart donor for the bride, but film historian Scott MacQueen states that Whale never had such an intention.

Sources report that Bela Lugosi and Claude Rains were considered, with varying degrees of seriousness, for the role of Frankenstein's mentor, Pretorius;Lennig, p. 92 others report that the role was created specifically for Ernest Thesiger.Skal, p. 185 Because of Mae Clarke's ill health, Valerie Hobson replaced her as Henry Frankenstein's love interest, Elizabeth. Early in production, Whale decided that the same actress cast to play the Bride should also play Mary Shelley in the film's prologue, to represent how the story &ndash; and horror in general &ndash; springs from the dark side of the imagination.Vieira, p. 82 He considered Brigitte Helm and Phyllis Brooks before deciding on Elsa Lanchester. Lanchester, who had accompanied husband Charles Laughton to Hollywood, had met with only moderate success. while Laughton had achieved fame in several films (including Whale's own ''The Old Dark House'') and won an Academy Award for his role in ''The Private Life of Henry VIII''. Lanchester had returned alone to London when Whale contacted her to offer her the dual role.Curtis, pp. 243–44 Lanchester modeled the Bride's hissing on the hissing of swans. During filming of the hissing sequence, which Whale shot from multiple angles, Lanchester gave herself a sore throat, which she treated with codeine.Vieira, p. 86

Colin Clive and Boris Karloff reprised their roles from ''Frankenstein'' as creator and creation, respectively. Hobson recalled Clive's alcoholism had worsened since filming the original, but Whale did not recast the role because his "hysterical quality" was necessary for the film. Karloff strongly objected to the decision to allow the Monster to speak. "Speech! Stupid! My argument was that if the monster had any impact or charm, it was because he was inarticulate – this great, lumbering, inarticulate creature. The moment he spoke you might as well ... play it straight."Gifford, p. 55 This decision also meant that Karloff could not remove his dental plate, so his cheeks did not have the sunken look of the original film. Whale and the studio psychiatrist selected 44 simple words for the Monster's vocabulary by looking at test papers of ten-year olds working at the studio. Dwight Frye returned to play the doctor's assistant, Karl, having played the hunchback, Fritz in the original. Frye also filmed a scene as an unnamed villager and the role of "Nephew Glutz", a man who murdered his uncle and blamed the death on the Monster. Boris Karloff is credited simply as KARLOFF, which was Universal's custom during the height of his career. Elsa Lanchester is credited for Mary Shelley, but in a nod to the earlier film, the Monster's bride is credited only as "?" just as Boris Karloff had been in the opening credits of ''Frankenstein''.


Universal makeup artist Jack Pierce paid special attention to the Monster's appearance in this film. He altered his 1931 design to display the after-effects of the mill fire, adding scars and shortening the Monster's hair.Curtis, p. 237 Over the course of filming, Pierce modified the Monster's makeup to indicate that the Monster's injuries were healing as the film progressed. Pierce co-created the Bride's makeup with strong input from Whale, especially regarding the Bride's iconic hair style, based on Nefertiti. Lanchester's hair was given a Marcel wave over a wire frame to achieve the style. Lanchester disliked working with Pierce, who she said "really did feel that he made these people, like he was a god ... in the morning he'd be dressed in white as if he were in hospital to perform an operation."Vieira, p. 85 To play Mary Shelley, Lanchester wore a white net dress embroidered with sequins of butterflies, stars and moons, which the actress had heard required 17 women 12 weeks to make.

Kenneth Strickfaden created and maintained the laboratory equipment. Strickfaden recycled a number of the fancifully-named machines he had created for the original ''Frankenstein'' for use in ''Bride'', including the "Cosmic Ray Diffuser",Goldman, p. 165 and the "Nebularium".Goldman, p. 183 A lightning bolt generated by Strickfaden's equipment has become a stock scene, appearing in any number of films and television shows.Picart, ''et al.'', p. 40 The man behind the film's special photographic effects was John P. Fulton, head of the special effects department at Universal Studios at the time.Picart, ''et al.'', p. 39 Fulton and David S. Horsely created the homunculi over the course of two days by shooting the actors in full-size jars against black velvet and aligning them with the perspective of the on-set jars. The foreground film plate was rotoscoped and matted onto the rear plate. Diminutive actor Billy Barty is briefly visible from the back in the finished film as a homunculus infant in a high chair but Whale cut the infant's reveal before the film's release. 

Whale met Franz Waxman at a party and asked him to score the picture. "Nothing will be resolved in this picture except the end destruction scene. Would you write an unresolved score for it?" asked Whale. Waxman created three distinctive themes: one for the Monster; one for the Bride; and one for Pretorius. The score closes, at Whale's suggestion, with a powerful dissonant chord, intended to convey the idea that the on-screen explosion was so powerful that the theater where the film was being screened was affected by it.Curtis, p. 246 Constantin Bakaleinikoff conducted 22 musicians to record the score in a single nine-hour session.Curtis, p. 249

Shooting began on January 2, 1935Mank, p. xvii with a projected budget of US$293,750 ($ as of ) – almost exactly the budget of the original – and an estimated 36-day shooting schedule.Curtis, p. 241 On the first day, Karloff waded in the water below the destroyed windmill wearing a rubber suit under his costume. Air got into the suit and expanded it like an "obscene water lilly". Later that day, Karloff broke his hip, necessitating a stunt double. Clive had also broken his leg. Shooting was completed on March 7, 1935. The film was ten days over schedule because Whale shut down the picture for ten days until Heggie became available to play the Hermit.Curtis, pp. 248–49 With a final cost of $397,023 ($ as of ), ''Bride'' was more than $100,000 ($ as of ) over budget. As originally filmed, Henry and Elizabeth died fleeing the exploding castle. Whale re-shot the ending to allow for their survival, although Clive and Hobson are still visible on-screen in the collapsing laboratory. Whale completed his final cut, shortening the running time from about 90 minutes to 75 and re-shooting and re-editing the ending, only days before the film's scheduled premiere date.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="efdd6c3b67754acdb0fb2d3a55238dc9" name="Brideoffrankenstein" sectnum="2#1">../img/efdd6c3b67754acdb0fb2d3a55238dc9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>