<document id="ebc99fb8d80a280b534450affa7086c6-2" name="Mount_Rushmore" cat="11">
<text>
Mount Rushmore is controversial among Native Americans because the United States seized the area from the Lakota tribe after the Great Sioux War of 1876-77. The Treaty of Fort Laramie from 1868 had previously granted the Black Hills to the Lakota in perpetuity. The Lakota consider the hills sacred, although historians believe the Lakota also gained control of the hills by force, displacing the Cheyenne in 1776. Members of the American Indian Movement led an occupation of the monument in 1971, naming it "Mount Crazy Horse". Among the participants were young activists, grandparents, children and Lakota holy man John Fire Lame Deer, who planted a prayer staff atop the mountain. Lame Deer said the staff formed a symbolic shroud over the presidents' faces "which shall remain dirty until the treaties concerning the Black Hills are fulfilled."Matthew Glass, "Producing Patriotic Inspiration at Mount Rushmore," ''Journal of the American Academy of Religion'', Vol. 62, No. 2. (Summer, 1994), pp. 265–283.

In 2004, the first Native American superintendent of the park was appointed. Gerard Baker has stated that he will open up more "avenues of interpretation", and that the four presidents are "only one avenue and only one focus.", Indian Country Today. Accessed on April 3, 2006

The Crazy Horse Memorial is being constructed elsewhere in the Black Hills to commemorate a famous Native American leader and as a response to Mount Rushmore. It is intended to be larger than Mount Rushmore and has the support of Lakota chiefs; the Crazy Horse Memorial Foundation has rejected offers of federal funds. However, this memorial is likewise the subject of controversy, even within the Native American community.Lame Deer, John (Fire) and Richard Erdoes.  ''Lame Deer Seeker of Visions''.  Simon and Schuster, New York, New York, 1972. Paperback ISBN 0-671-55392-5  


The Monument also provokes controversy because some allege that underlying it is the theme of racial superiority legitimized by the idea of Manifest Destiny. The mountains were carved with Borglum's choice of four presidents active during the time of the acquisition of Indian land. Gutzon Borglum himself excites  controversy because he was an active member of the Ku Klux Klan. , PBS. Accessed on July 23 2007 , Accessed on August 11 2009

In 2009, author Ivan Eland released ''Recarving Rushmore: Ranking the Presidents on Peace, Prosperity, and Liberty'', a book that advocates a reappraisal of the greatness of three of the four presidents on the monument.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5e6fb2b015a9adeb06290498f9a51328" name="Air_Force_One_over_Mt._Rushmore" sectnum="2#1">../img/5e6fb2b015a9adeb06290498f9a51328.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>