<document id="ebc99fb8d80a280b534450affa7086c6-4" name="Mount_Rushmore" cat="11">
<text>
Mount Rushmore is largely composed of granite. The memorial is carved on the northwest margin of the Harney Peak granite batholith in the Black Hills of South Dakota, so the geologic formations of the heart of the Black Hills region are also evident at Mount Rushmore. The batholith magma intruded into the pre-existing mica schist rocks during the Precambrian period about 1.6 billion years ago.. National Park Service. However, the uneven cooling of the molten rock caused the formation of both fine and coarse-grained minerals, including quartz, feldspar, muscovite, and biotite. Fractures in the granite were sealed by pegmatite dikes. The light-colored streaks in the presidents' foreheads are due to these dikes. 

The Black Hills granites were exposed to erosion during the late Precambrian, but were buried by sandstones and other sediments during the Cambrian Period. The area remained buried throughout the Paleozoic Era, but was exposed again to erosion during the tectonic uplift about 70 million years ago. The Black Hills area was uplifted as an elongated geologic dome which towered some  above sea level, but erosion wore the area down to only .Irvin, James R.  (2001). URL accessed on March 16, 2006. The subsequent natural erosion of this mountain range allowed the carvings by stripping the granite of the overlying sediments and the softer adjacent schists. The contact between the granite and darker schist is viewable just below the sculpture of Washington.

Borglum selected Mount Rushmore as the site for several reasons. The rock of the mountain is composed of smooth, fine-grained granite. The durable granite erodes only  every 10,000 years, indicating that it was sturdy enough to support sculpting. In addition, it was the tallest mountain in the region, looming to a height of  above sea level. Because the mountain faces the southeast, the workers also had the advantage of sunlight for most of the day.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="15e9c503cae45311094c5ea03d06c11f" name="Mt_rushmore_07_27_2005" sectnum="4#1">../img/15e9c503cae45311094c5ea03d06c11f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>