<document id="ebe418ae757b121b0d636041981fc1d1-4.13" name="Bird" cat="3">
<text>
Birds communicate using primarily visual and auditory signals. Signals can be interspecific (between species) and intraspecific (within species).

Birds sometimes use plumage to assess and assert social dominance, to display breeding condition in sexually selected species, or to make threatening displays, as in the Sunbittern's mimicry of a large predator to ward off hawks and protect young chicks. Variation in plumage also allows for the identification of birds, particularly between species. Visual communication among birds may also involve ritualised displays, which have developed from non-signalling actions such as preening, the adjustments of feather position, pecking, or other behaviour. These displays may signal aggression or submission or may contribute to the formation of pair-bonds.  The most elaborate displays occur during courtship, where "dances" are often formed from complex combinations of many possible component movements; males' breeding success may depend on the quality of such displays.


Bird calls and songs, which are produced in the syrinx, are the major means by which birds communicate with sound. This communication can be very complex; some species can operate the two sides of the syrinx independently, allowing the simultaneous production of two different songs.
Calls are used for a variety of purposes, including mate attraction,  evaluation of potential mates, bond formation, the claiming and maintenance of territories,  the identification of other individuals (such as when parents look for chicks in colonies or when mates reunite at the start of breeding season), and the warning of other birds of potential predators, sometimes with specific information about the nature of the threat.  Some birds also use mechanical sounds for auditory communication. The ''Coenocorypha'' snipes of New Zealand drive air through their feathers, woodpeckers drum territorially, and Palm Cockatoos use tools to drum.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d155807c17ebe7fcedef60b37550904b" name="Stavenn_Eurypiga_helias_00" sectnum="4.13#1">../img/d155807c17ebe7fcedef60b37550904b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>