<document id="ebe418ae757b121b0d636041981fc1d1-6.17" name="Bird" cat="3">
<text>
Domesticated birds raised for meat and eggs, called poultry, are the largest source of animal protein eaten by humans; in 2003, 76 million tons of poultry and 61 million tons of eggs were produced worldwide.  Chickens account for much of human poultry consumption, though turkeys, ducks, and geese are also relatively common.  Many species of birds are also hunted for meat. Bird hunting is primarily a recreational activity except in extremely undeveloped areas.  The most important birds hunted in North and South America are waterfowl; other widely hunted birds include pheasants, wild turkeys, quail, doves, partridge, grouse, snipe, and woodcock.Simeone A, Navarro X (2002).  ''Rev. chil. hist. nat'' '''75''' (2): 423–31  Muttonbirding is also popular in Australia and New Zealand.Hamilton S (2000). "How precise and accurate are data obtained using. an infra-red scope on burrow-nesting sooty shearwaters ''Puffinus griseus''?" ''Marine Ornithology'' '''28''' (1): 1–6  Though some hunting, such as that of muttonbirds, may be sustainable, hunting has led to the extinction or endangerment of dozens of species. Keane A, Brooke MD, Mcgowan PJK (2005). "Correlates of extinction risk and hunting pressure in gamebirds (Galliformes)". ''Biological Conservation'' '''126''' (2): 216–33. 


Other commercially valuable products from birds include feathers (especially the down of geese and ducks), which are used as insulation in clothing and bedding, and seabird feces (guano), which is a valuable source of phosphorus and nitrogen. The War of the Pacific, sometimes called the Guano War, was fought in part over the control of guano deposits.

Birds have been domesticated by humans both as pets and for practical purposes. Colourful birds, such as parrots and mynas, are bred in captivity or kept as pets, a practice that has led to the illegal trafficking of some endangered species.Cooney R, Jepson P (2006). "The international wild bird trade: what's wrong with blanket bans?" ''Oryx'' '''40''' (1): 18–23.  Falcons and cormorants have long been used for hunting and fishing, respectively. Messenger pigeons, used since at least 1 AD, remained important as recently as World War II. Today, such activities are more common either as hobbies, for entertainment and tourism,Manzi M (2002). . ''Geographic Review'' '''92''' (4): 597–603. or for sports such as pigeon racing.

Amateur bird enthusiasts (called birdwatchers, twitchers or, more commonly, birders) number in the millions.Pullis La Rouche, G. (2006). Birding in the United States: a demographic and economic analysis. ''Waterbirds around the world.'' Eds. G.C. Boere, C.A. Galbraith & D.A. Stroud. The Stationery Office, Edinburgh, UK. pp. 841–46.  Many homeowners erect bird feeders near their homes to attract various species. Bird feeding has grown into a multimillion dollar industry; for example, an estimated 75% of households in Britain provide food for birds at some point during the winter.Chamberlain DE, Vickery JA, Glue DE, Robinson RA, Conway GJ, Woodburn RJW, Cannon AR (2005). "Annual and seasonal trends in the use of garden feeders by birds in winter". ''Ibis'' '''147''' (3): 563–75.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="25ca49547a537989610230b8c3bac15f" name="FishingCormorants" sectnum="6.17#1">../img/25ca49547a537989610230b8c3bac15f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>