<document id="ebe418ae757b121b0d636041981fc1d1-1.1" name="Bird" cat="3">
<text>
Based on fossil and biological evidence, most scientists accept that birds are a specialised sub-group of theropod dinosaurs. More specifically, they are members of Maniraptora, a group of theropods which includes dromaeosaurs and oviraptorids, among others. As scientists discover more non-avian theropods that are closely related to birds, the previously clear distinction between non-birds and birds has become blurred. Recent discoveries in the Liaoning Province of northeast China, which demonstrate that many small theropod dinosaurs had feathers, contribute to this ambiguity.

The consensus view in contemporary paleontology is that the birds, Aves, are the closest relatives of the deinonychosaurs, which include dromaeosaurids and troodontids. Together, these three form a group called Paraves. The basal dromaeosaur ''Microraptor'' has features which may have enabled it to glide or fly. The most basal deinonychosaurs are very small. This evidence raises the possibility that the ancestor of all paravians may have been arboreal, and/or may have been able to glide.

The Late Jurassic ''Archaeopteryx'' is well-known as one of the first transitional fossils to be found and it provided support for the theory of evolution in the late 19th century. ''Archaeopteryx'' has clearly reptilian characteristics: teeth, clawed fingers, and a long, lizard-like tail, but it has finely preserved wings with flight feathers identical to those of modern birds. It is not considered a direct ancestor of modern birds, but is the oldest and most primitive known member of Aves or Avialae, and it is probably closely related to the real ancestor.Mayr, G., Phol, B., Hartman, S. and Peters, D.S. (2007). "The tenth skeletal specimen of ''Archaeopteryx''." ''Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society'', '''149''': 97–116.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="99658b9b576a214ce1e81da1bb42437a" name="Confuchisornis_sanctus" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/99658b9b576a214ce1e81da1bb42437a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>