<document id="ebe418ae757b121b0d636041981fc1d1-6.18" name="Bird" cat="3">
<text>
Birds play prominent and diverse roles in folklore, religion, and popular culture. In religion, birds may serve as either messengers or priests and leaders for a deity, such as in the Cult of Makemake, in which the Tangata manu of Easter Island served as chiefs,Routledge S, Routledge K (1917). "The Bird Cult of Easter Island". ''Folklore'' '''28''' (4): 337–55. or as attendants, as in the case of Hugin and Munin, two Common Ravens who whispered news into the ears of the Norse god Odin.Chappell J (2006). . ''PLoS Biol'' '''4''' (1):e14.  Priests were involved in augury, or interpreting the words of birds while the "auspex" (from which the word "auspicious" is derived) watched their activities to foretell events.Ingersoll, Ernest (1923). "". Longmans, Green and co. p. 214  They may also serve as religious symbols, as when Jonah (Hebrew: '''יוֹנָה''', dove) embodied the fright, passivity, mourning, and beauty traditionally associated with doves.Hauser A (1985). "Jonah: In Pursuit of the Dove". ''Journal of Biblical Literature'' '''104''' (1): 21–37.  Birds have themselves been deified, as in the case of the Common Peacock, which is perceived as Mother Earth by the Dravidians of India.Nair P (1974). "The Peacock Cult in Asia". ''Asian Folklore Studies'' '''33''' (2): 93–170.  Some birds have also been perceived as monsters, including the mythological Roc and the Māori's legendary ''Pouākai'', a giant bird capable of snatching humans.Tennyson A, Martinson P (2006). ''Extinct Birds of New Zealand'' Te Papa Press, Wellington ISBN 978-0-909010-21-8

Birds have been featured in culture and art since prehistoric times, when they were represented in early cave paintings.Meighan C (1966). "Prehistoric Rock Paintings in Baja California". ''American Antiquity'' '''31''' (3): 372–92.  Birds were later used in religious or symbolic art and design, such as the magnificent Peacock Throne of the Mughal and Persian emperors.Clarke CP (1908). "A Pedestal of the Platform of the Peacock Throne". ''The Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin'' '''3''' (10): 182–83.  With the advent of scientific interest in birds, many paintings of birds were commissioned for books. Among the most famous of these bird artists was John James Audubon, whose paintings of North American birds were a great commercial success in Europe and who later lent his name to the National Audubon Society.Boime A (1999). "John James Audubon, a birdwatcher's fanciful flights". ''Art History'' '''22''' (5) 728–55.  Birds are also important figures in poetry; for example, Homer incorporated Nightingales into his ''Odyssey'', and Catullus used a sparrow as an erotic symbol in his Catullus 2.Chandler A (1934). "The Nightingale in Greek and Latin Poetry". ''The Classical Journal'' '''30''' (2): 78–84.  The relationship between an albatross and a sailor is the central theme of Samuel Taylor Coleridge's The Rime of the Ancient Mariner, which led to the use of the term as a metaphor for a 'burden'.Lasky E (1992). "A Modern Day Albatross: The Valdez and Some of Life's Other Spills". ''The English Journal'', '''81''' (3): 44–46.   Other English metaphors derive from birds; vulture funds and vulture investors, for instance, take their name from the scavenging vulture.Carson A (1998). "Vulture Investors, Predators of the 90s: An Ethical Examination". ''Journal of Business Ethics'' '''17''' (5): 543–55. 

Perceptions of various bird species often vary across cultures. Owls are associated with bad luck, witchcraft, and death in parts of Africa,Enriquez PL, Mikkola H (1997). "Comparative study of general public owl knowledge in Costa Rica, Central America and Malawi, Africa". Pp. 160–66 In: J.R. Duncan, D.H. Johnson, T.H. Nicholls, (Eds). ''Biology and conservation of owls of the Northern Hemisphere. General Technical Report NC-190'', USDA Forest Service, St. Paul, Minnesota. 635 pp. but are regarded as wise across much of Europe.Lewis DP (2005).  The Owl Pages. Retrieved on 15 September 2007 Hoopoes were considered sacred in Ancient Egypt and symbols of virtue in Persia, but were thought of as thieves across much of Europe and harbingers of war in Scandinavia.Dupree N (1974). "An Interpretation of the Role of the Hoopoe in Afghan Folklore and Magic". ''Folklore'' '''85''' (3): 173–93.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b5204eb92ac5ac3953c65b298390c6f4" name="Vogel_Drei_(Meister_der_Spielkarten)" sectnum="6.18#1">../img/b5204eb92ac5ac3953c65b298390c6f4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>