<document id="ec03aeaa0ab42b260796428bc24ddb38-7.9" name="H.M.S._Pinafore" cat="20">
<text>
According to musicologist Arthur Jacobs, Gilbert's plot "admirably sparked off Sullivan's genius".Jacobs, p. 118  Sullivan embraces the nautical setting; in "We Sail the Ocean Blue", for example, he "presents his twist on a traditional sea shanty".  In the Captain's opening song, "I am the Captain of the Pinafore", he admits that his gentlemanliness "never ... well, hardly ever" gives way to swearing at his men, and although he has experience at sea, he "hardly ever" suffers from seasickness. Edited Guide Entry from ''The Lives and Works of Gilbert and Sullivan'', BBC h2g2, 24 August 2001, accessed 10 March 2009  Sullivan "unerringly found the right musical setting for the key phrase 'What never?' ... cunningly sharpened ... through the chromatic touch on the bassoon."Jacobs, p. 119  Audrey Williamson argued that the music of ''Pinafore'' is quintessentially English and free of European influences throughout most of the score, from the "glee" for Ralph, the Boatswain and the Carpenter, to "For He Is an Englishman".Williamson, p. 63


The best-known songs from the operaShepherd, Marc.  at ''A Gilbert and Sullivan Discography'', 24 December 2003, accessed 10 March 2009Shepherd Marc.  at ''A Gilbert and Sullivan Discography'', 7 November 2001, accessed 10 March 2009 include "I'm called Little Buttercup", a waltz tune introducing the character, which Sullivan repeats in the entr'acte and in the Act II finale to imprint the melody on the mind of the audience;Jacobs, p. 119.  Gilbert had introduced this character in his 1870 Bab Ballad "The Bumboat Woman's Story". and "A British tar" (a glee for three men describing the ideal sailor), composed by Sir Joseph "to encourage independent thought and action in the lower branches of the service, and to teach the principle that a British sailor is any man's equal, excepting mine".  Sullivan's voicing advances the satiric lyric, which mocks the "equality" plays while underlining the hypocrisy of Sir Joseph.  Another popular number is Sir Joseph's song "When I was a Lad", recounting the meteoric rise of his career, which bears similarities to that of W. H. Smith, the civilian news entrepreneur who had risen to the position of First Lord of the Admiralty in 1877).

In ''Pinafore'', Sullivan exploits minor keys for comic effect, for instance in "Kind Captain, I've important information".Hughes, p. 53  Further, he achieves a musical surprise when he uses the subdominant minor in "Sorry her lot".Hughes, p. 55  Biographer Gervase Hughes was impressed with the introduction to the opening chorus which includes "a rousing nautical tune ... in a key of no nonsense, C major ... a modulation to the mediant minor, where to our surprise a plaintive oboe gives us the first verse of "Sorry her lot" in 2/4 .  After this closes on the local dominant B major the violins (still in 2/4) introduce us to Little Buttercup ... meeting her under these conditions one would hardly expect her to blossom out later as a queen of the waltz."  He continues, "the bassoon and basses ... assert vigorously who is the Captain of the Pinafore ... in the improbable key of A flat minor .... Buttercup makes a last despairing attempt to make herself heard in D flat minor, but the others have never known that such an outlandish key existed.  So in a flash they all go back to C major on a good old {}^6_4".Hughes, p. 133

According to Jacobs, "Ralph, Captain Corcoran, Sir Joseph and Josephine all live in their interactive music (particularly 'Never mind the why and wherefore'), and almost as much musical resource is lavished on two characters parodied from opera or melodrama, Little Buttercup with 'gypsy blood in her veins' and the heavy-treading Dick Deadeye."Jacobs, ''quoted'' in Holden, p. 1060 Jacobs also opined that the leading tone that begins "Never mind the why and wherefore" "serves to emphasize the phrase like a Johann Strauss-ian grace-note".  Sullivan scholar David Russell Hulme noted Sullivan's parody of operatic styles, "particularly the Handelian recitatives and the elopement scene (evocative of so many nocturnal operatic conspiracies), but best of all is the travesty of the patriotic tune in 'For he is an Englishman!'"Hulme, ''quoted'' in Sadie, vol. 2, p. 727  Buttercup's Act II song, in which she reveals the dark secret of the baby-switching is preceded by a quote from Franz Schubert's "The Erl-King" and also parodies the opera ''Il Trovatore''.  Jacobs notes that Sullivan also adds his own humorous touches to the music by setting commonplace expressions in "Donizettian recitative".  But on the serious side, he enhances the moments of true emotional climax, as in Josephine's Act II aria, and added musical interest to concerted numbers by "subtly shifting the rhythms and bar groupings."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="49308a81023f8fc556eea4d3a614b956" name="A_British_Tar" sectnum="7.9#1">../img/49308a81023f8fc556eea4d3a614b956.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>