<document id="ec03aeaa0ab42b260796428bc24ddb38-5.5" name="H.M.S._Pinafore" cat="20">
<text>
After the opera became successful in London, Richard D'Oyly Carte quickly sent touring companies into the British provinces.  At least one D'Oyly Carte company, and sometimes as many as three, played ''Pinafore'' under Carte's aegis every year between 1878 and 1888, including its first London revival in 1887.  The opera was then given a rest, returning to the touring repertory between 1894 and 1900 and again for most of the time between 1903 and 1940.Rollins and Witts, pp. 7–164  Gilbert directed all the revivals during his lifetime, and after his death, the D'Oyly Carte Opera Company had exclusive performing rights to the Savoy operas until 1962.  It continued to hew closely to Gilbert's directions throughout that period, as recorded in Gilbert's plot books, and it also required its licensees to follow them closely.Bradley (2005), p. 27


Until 1908, revivals of the opera were given in contemporary dress.Rollins and Witts, Appendix p. VII  After that, designers such as Percy Anderson, George Sheringham and Peter Goffin created Victorian costume designs.Mander, pp. 102–105  In the winter of 1940&ndash;41, the D'Oyly Carte Opera Company's scenery and costumes for ''Pinafore'' and three other operas were destroyed by German bombs during World War II.Rollins and Witts, p. 165  The opera was revived in London in the summer of 1947.Rollins and Witts, pp. 165–72  It was then included in the D'Oyly Carte repertory in every season from then on, until the company's closure in 1982.Rollins and Witts, pp. 172–86, and supplements  The D'Oyly Carte company performed ''Pinafore'' before Queen Elizabeth II and the royal family at Windsor Castle on 16 June 1977, the first royal command performance of a Gilbert and Sullivan opera since 1891.

The D'Oyly Carte Opera Company did not allow any other professional company to present the Savoy operas in Britain until the copyrights expired at the end of 1961, although it licensed many amateur and school societies to do so, beginning in the 19th century., reprinted from theatre programme of 29 January 1968, ''The Gilbert and Sullivan Archive'', Retrieved on 11 March 2009  After 1961, other professional companies mounted productions of the opera in Britain.  These have included Tyrone Guthrie's 1960 production from Stratford, Ontario, seen on Broadway in 1960 and in London in 1962Mander, p. 154 and a New Sadler's Wells Opera Company production first seen on 4 June 1984 at Sadler's Wells Theatre, production in 1987, collected at The Gilbert and Sullivan Archive, accessed 10 March 2009 which was seen also in New York.Traubner, Richard.  ''The New York Times'', 15 January 1989, accessed 10 March 2009  Scottish Opera, Welsh National Opera and many of the other British opera companies have mounted productions, as did the reconstituted D'Oyly Carte Opera Company between 1990 and its closure in 2003.Bradley (2005), chapters 3 and 4, ''passim''  In recent years, the Carl Rosa Opera Company has produced ''Pinafore'' several times, including in 2009,"Dido; Aeneas/ Acis; Galatea", ''The Times'', 28 March 2009 and Opera della Luna and other British companies continue to mount the piece.

The extraordinary initial success of ''Pinafore'' in America was seen first-hand by J. C. Williamson.  He soon made arrangements with D'Oyly Carte to present the opera's first authorised production in Australia, opening on 15 November 1879 at the Theatre Royal, Sydney.  Thereafter, his opera company played frequent seasons of the work (and the subsequent Savoy operas) until at least 1963. in the ''Sydney Morning Herald'', 17 November 1879, reproduced at the Gilbert and Sullivan Down Under website, accessed 10 March 2009Morrison, Robert.  at ''A Gilbert and Sullivan Discography'', 12 November 2001, accessed 10 March 2009  In the U.S., the piece never lost popularity.  The Internet Broadway Database links to forty productions on Broadway alone. Internet Broadway Database, accessed 13 June 2009 Among the professional repertory companies continuing to present ''Pinafore'' regularly in the U.S. are Opera a la Carte, based in California, Ohio Light Opera and the New York Gilbert and Sullivan Players, which tours the opera annually and often includes it in its New York seasons.Smith, Steve.  ''The New York Times'', June 9, 2008, accessed 10 March 2009  ''Pinafore'' is still performed around the world by opera companies such as the Royal Theatre, Copenhagen; Australian Opera (and Essgee Entertainment and others in Australia); in Kassel, Germany; and even Samarkand, Uzbekistan.Bradley (2005), chapter 4

The following table shows the history of the D'Oyly Carte productions (excluding tours) in Gilbert's lifetime:
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="18c7a7e4a0d52b82fe69e2a864a87649" name="Pin15_1" sectnum="5.5#1">../img/18c7a7e4a0d52b82fe69e2a864a87649.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>