<document id="ec03aeaa0ab42b260796428bc24ddb38-6.7" name="H.M.S._Pinafore" cat="20">
<text>
When ''Pinafore'' was first revived in London in 1887, it was already treated as a classic.  ''The Illustrated London News'' observed that the opera had not been updated with new dialogue, jokes and songs, but concluded that this was for the best, as the public would have missed the "time-honoured jokes, such as 'Hardly Ever.'  The Savoy has once more got a brilliant success.""The Playhouses", ''The Illustrated London News'', 19 November 1887, 91(2535): 580, col. 1  ''The Theatre'' concurred, stating that since the opera "has been heard in almost every part of this habitable globe and been enjoyed everywhere, there is not much occasion to descant".  It called the revival a "most brilliant" success and predicted another long run."Our Omnibus-Box", ''The Theatre'', New Series, 1 December 1887, 10: 337


Reviewing the 1899 revival, ''The Athenaeum'' managed to praise the piece while joining in the musical establishment's critique of Sullivan.  On the one hand, "The ''Pinafore'' ... sounds fresher than ever. The musical world has become serious – very serious – and it is indeed refreshing to hear a merry, humorous piece, and music, unassuming in character … it is delicately scored, and in many ways displays ability of a high order".  On the other hand, it wrote that if Sullivan had pursued the path of composing more serious music, like his symphony, "he would have produced still higher results; in like manner ''Pinafore'' set us wondering what the composer would have accomplished with a libretto of somewhat similar kind, but one giving him larger scope for the exercise of his gifts".''The Athenæum'', 10 June 1899, 3737: 730–731

In 1911, H. L. Mencken wrote: "No other comic opera ever written – no other stage play, indeed, of any sort – was ever so popular ....  ''Pinafore'' … has been given, and with great success, wherever there are theaters – from Moscow to Buenos Aires, from Cape Town to Shanghai; in Madrid, Ottawa and Melbourne; even in Paris, Rome, Vienna and Berlin."Mencken, H. L.  ''Baltimore Evening Sun'', 1911, reproduced at The Gilbert and Sullivan Archive, accessed 10 March 2009  After the deaths of Gilbert and Sullivan, the D'Oyly Carte Opera Company retained exclusive rights to perform their operas in Great Britain until 1962, touring throughout Britain for most of the year and, beginning in 1919, often performing in London for a season of about four months.  ''The Times'' gave the company's 1920 London production an enthusiastic review, saying that the audience was "enraptured", and regretting that ''Pinafore'' would be played for only two weeks.  It praised the cast, singling out Leo Sheffield as the Captain, Henry Lytton as Sir Joseph, Elsie Griffin as Josephine, James Hay as Ralph, Bertha Lewis as Little Buttercup and the "splendid" choral tone.  It concluded that the opera made a "rollicking climax to the season"."''H.M.S. Pinafore''. Revival at Princes Theatre, ''The Times'', 21 January 1920, p. 10  Two years later, it gave an even more glowing report of that season's performances, calling Derek Oldham an "ideal hero" as Ralph, noting that Sydney Granville "fairly brought down the house" with his song, that Darrell Fancourt's Deadeye was "an admirably sustained piece of caricature" and that it was a "great pleasure" to hear the returning principals."''H.M.S. Pinafore''. Sullivan Opera Season Nearing The End", ''The Times'', 3 January 1922, p. 8  A 1961 review of the company's ''Pinafore'' is much the same."Novelty and Tradition in Savoy Operettas", ''The Times'', 12 December 1961, p. 5

In 1879, J. C. Williamson acquired the exclusive performing rights to ''Pinafore'' in Australia and New Zealand.  His first production earned public and critical acclaim.  Williamson played Sir Joseph, and his wife, Maggie Moore played Josephine.  Praising the production and all the performers, the ''Sydney Morning Herald'' noted that the production though "abounding in fun" was dignified and precise, that many numbers were encored and that laughter and applause from the "immense audience ... was liberally bestowed".''Sydney Morning Herald'', 17 November 1879  Williamson's company continued to produce ''Pinafore'' in Australia, New Zealand and on tour into the 1960s with much success.  As Williamson said, "If you need money, then put on G&S".Bradley (2005), p. 73  Meanwhile, ''Pinafore'' continued to garner praise outside of Britain.  The 1950s Danish version in Copenhagen, for example, was revived repeatedly, playing for well over 100 performances to "packed houses"."H.M.S. Pinafore Again Delights the Danes", ''The Times'', 16 October 1959, p. 16  Translations into German, Yiddish and many other languages, and professional productions in places as remote as Samarkand in Uzbekistan have been successful.Bradley (2005), Chapter 4, describing numerous productions beginning with 1962.

In the U.S., where Gilbert and Sullivan's performance copyright was never in force,"A New Approach to ''H.M.S. Pinafore''", ''The Times'', 9 March 1960, p. 13 ''Pinafore'' continued to be produced continuously by both professional and amateur companies.  ''The New York Times'', in a 1914 review, called a large-scale production at the 6,000-seat New York Hippodrome a "royal entertainment" that "comes up smiling".  The opera had been turned into a "mammoth spectacle" at with a chorus of hundreds and the famous Hippodrome tank providing a realistic harbour.  Buttercup made her entrance to the three-masted Pinafore rowing into sight, and Dick Deadeye was later thrown overboard with a real splash.  The ''Times'' praised the hearty singing but noted that some subtlety is lost when the dialogue needs "fairly to be shouted".  The production took some liberties, including interpolating music from other Sullivan works.  The paper concluded, "the mild satire of ''Pinafore'' is entertaining because it is universal"."''H.M.S. Pinafore'' a la Hippodrome; They Sail the Ocean Tank and Their Saucy Ship's a Beauty", ''The New York Times'', 10 April 1914, p. 13  The same paper deemed Winthrop Ames' popular Broadway productions of ''Pinafore'' in the 1920s and 1930s "spectacular".Atkinson, J. Brooks, "G. & S., Incorporated", ''The New York Times'', 25 April 1926, p. X1  Modern productions in America continue to be generally well received.  ''The New York Times'' review of The New York Gilbert and Sullivan Players' 2008 season at New York City Center commented, "Gilbert's themes of class inequality, overbearing nationalism and incompetent authorities remain relevant, however absurdly treated.  But the lasting appeal of ''Pinafore'' and its ilk is more a matter of his unmatched linguistic genius and Sullivan’s generous supply of addictive melodies.Smith, Steve.  ''The New York Times'', 9 June 2008

With the expiry of the copyrights, companies around the world have been free to produce Gilbert and Sullivan works and to adapt them as they please for almost 50 years.  Productions of ''Pinafore'', both amateur and professional, range from the traditional, in the D'Oyly Carte vein, to the broadly adapted, such as that of the very successful Essgee Entertainment (formed by Simon Gallaher) in Australia and Opera della Luna in Britain.  Since its original production, ''H.M.S. Pinafore'' has remained one of Gilbert and Sullivan's most popular comic operas.Bradley (1996), p. 117Sobelsohn, David. , CultureVulture.net, June 11, 2005, accessed 10 March 2009  Productions continue in large numbers around the world.  In 2003 alone, The D'Oyly Carte Opera Company rented 224 sets of orchestra parts, mostly for productions of ''Pinafore'', ''Pirates'' and ''Mikado''.  This does not take into account other rental companies and the theatre companies that borrow scores or have their own, or that use only one or two pianos instead of an orchestra.  It is certainly true that hundreds of productions of ''Pinafore'' are presented every year worldwide.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d7cb4940f717128a935cc19ab3b396e4" name="BarringtonCaptain" sectnum="6.7#1">../img/d7cb4940f717128a935cc19ab3b396e4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>