<document id="ec03aeaa0ab42b260796428bc24ddb38-5.4" name="H.M.S._Pinafore" cat="20">
<text>
The unauthorised juvenile productions of ''Pinafore'' were so popular that Carte mounted his own children's version, played at matinees at the Opera Comique beginning on 16 December 1879.Kanthor, Hal. , ''Gilbert and Sullivan: From London to America'', online exhibition at University of Rochester Libraries, accessed 7 May 2009  François Cellier, who had taken over from his brother as Carte's music director in London, adapted the score for children's voices.Cellier and Bridgeman, chapter entitled , reproduced at The Gilbert and Sullivan Archive, accessed 10 March 2009  Between its two Christmas seasons in London, the children's production went on a provincial tour from 2 August 1880 to 11 December 1880.

Carte's children's production earned an enthusiastic review from critic Clement ScottScott, Clement.  ''The Theatre'', 1 January 1880, new  series 1: pp. 38–39, accessed 10 March 2009 and the other London critics, as well as the audiences, including children.  However, Captain Corcoran's curse "Damme!" was uncensored, shocking such prominent audience members as Lewis Carroll, who later wrote: "a bevy of sweet innocent-looking girls sing, with bright and happy looks, the chorus 'He said, Damn me! He said, Damn me!' I cannot find words to convey to the reader the pain I felt in seeing those dear children taught to utter such words to amuse ears grown callous to their ghastly meaning ....  How Mr. Gilbert could have stooped to write, or Sir Arthur Sullivan could have prostituted his noble art to set to music, such vile trash, it passes my skill to understand".Carroll, Lewis.  "The Stage and the Spirit of Reverence", ''Theatre'' magazine, 1 June 1888, reprinted in ''The Lewis Carroll Picture Book'', pp. 175–95, Stuart Dodgson Collingwood (ed.), London: T. Fisher Unwin (1899)Jacobs, p. 123
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="66ec8db16368af8f7e807f8ea48a20fb" name="Grattanpin" sectnum="5.4#1">../img/66ec8db16368af8f7e807f8ea48a20fb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>