<document id="ec3cf43d80b15857f60bc63c79cfeb7b-4.7" name="Pallid_sturgeon" cat="3">
<text>
Two populations of pallid sturgeons in the Missouri and Yellowstone Rivers of Montana are both at risk of extinction and current projections are that wild pallid sturgeon populations in Montana will be extinct by 2018. Though a vigorous stocking effort was implemented in 1996, until pallid sturgeon females reach reproductive maturity sometime after they are 15 years of age, recovery efforts in Montana will not be readily measurable. The U.S. Bureau of Reclamation has been conducting spring pulse water releases from the Tiber dam every four to five years to try and recreate a semblance of an annual spring flood to restore and rejuvenate downstream floodplains. These pulse releases are done in an effort to restore suitable habitat for numerous fish species.

In Nebraska, a small number of pallid sturgeons have been captured along the lower reaches of the Platte River. Unlike most rivers in the Mississippi-Missouri river system, the Platte River has only a few dams and they are well upstream from its confluence with the Missouri River. The lower Platte River is shallow with numerous sand bars and small islands. Though pallid sturgeons prefer more turbulent and deeper rivers than the Platte River, between 1979 and 2003 over a dozen pallid sturgeons, including some from hatcheries, have been captured from the Platte River. A number of these pallid sturgeons have been fitted with radio transmitters which track their return to the Platte River when water levels and turbidity conditions are favorable. Coinciding with the majority of the pallid sturgeons that have been captured, this period that is generally most favorable is during the spring and early summer months. By mid-summer, a reduction in water levels and turbidity on the Platte River encourages pallid sturgeons to return to the Missouri River. 

The lower reaches of the Platte River, a more than 30-mile (48 km) stretch from the Elkhorn River to its confluence with the Missouri River, has suitable spawning habitat for pallid sturgeons, although no conclusive evidence has been found that spawning is occurring in this region. Along with the lower Yellowstone River, the lower Platte River was identified as one of the best of the remaining regions with the potential for the  natural spawning. In an effort to help restore habitat, two large river water pulse releases are planned for the months of March and May 2009 from Gavins Point Dam, located on the border of Nebraska and South Dakota. Although the amount of water released from the dam will be dependent on both upstream reservoir levels and downstream river levels, and will be regulated to ensure that downstream flooding will not occur,  some restoration of the historic ebb and flow of the river will occur and that will benefit the spawning of the pallid sturgeon. 

In Missouri, at the Lisbon Bottoms section of the Big Muddy National Fish & Wildlife Refuge, wild pallid sturgeon larvae were collected in 1998. These non-hatchery raised larvae were the first recovered on the lower Missouri River in the previous 50 years. The recovery was made along a side channel of the Missouri River that had been developed to provide suitable habitat for pallid sturgeon and other fish spawning. The side channel was apparently being used by the larva pallid sturgeons for protection from the swifter currents of the Missouri River. 

In 2007, the  U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service concluded that hatchery-based reproduction efforts should be continued, along with monitoring of any population changes, to determine the effectiveness of human intervention. The 2007 findings also emphasized the need to determine the most likely areas of spawning, to identify  any parasite or disease that may be impacting the reproductive capabilities of pallid sturgeon and to examine engineering possibilities that may permit recreation of suitable habitats without reducing the USFWS ability to protect people from harmful and destructive flooding, and to  maintain its ability to provide adequate water impoundment for irrigation and recreation purposes.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bc66713f25bae8ceed36baaa1de034f7" name="Radio_transmitter_implant_in_pallid_sturgeon" sectnum="4.7#1">../img/bc66713f25bae8ceed36baaa1de034f7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>