<document id="ec5829a8407292b2edeaab3ab03617e1-4" name="Structural_history_of_the_Roman_military" cat="29">
<text>
In a process known as the Marian reforms, Roman consul Gaius Marius carried out a programme of reform of the Roman military. In 107 BC, all citizens, regardless of their wealth or social class, were made eligible for entry into the Roman army.Boak, ''A History of Rome to 565 A.D.'', p. 189* Santosuosso, ''Storming the Heavens'', p. 10 This move formalised and concluded a gradual process that had been growing for centuries, of removing property requirements for military service.Gabba, ''Republican Rome, The Army And the Allies'', p. 1 The distinction between ''hastati'', ''principes'' and ''triarii'', which had already become blurred, was officially removed,Cary & Scullard, ''A History of Rome'', p. 219 and the legionary infantry of popular imagination was created. Legionary infantry formed a homogeneous force of heavy infantry. These legionaries were drawn from citizen stock; by this time, Roman or Latin citizenship had been regionally expanded over much of ancient Italy and Cisalpine Gaul.Luttwak, ''The Grand Strategy of the Roman Empire'', p. 27 Lighter citizen infantry, such as the ''velites'' and ''equites'', were replaced by non-citizen ''auxilia'' that could consist of foreign mercenaries.Santosuosso, ''Storming the Heavens'', p. 16 Due to the concentration of the citizen legions into a force of heavy infantry Rome's armies depended on auxiliary cavalry attachments for support. As a tactical necessity, legions were almost always accompanied by an equal or greater number of lighter auxiliary troops,Tacitus, ''Annals'', IV, 5 which were drawn from the non-citizens of the Empire's territories. One known exception of legions being formed from non-citizen provinces during this period was the legion that was raised in the province of Galatia.

After Marius, the legions were drawn largely from volunteer citizens rather than citizens conscripted for duty.Luttwak, ''The Grand Strategy of the Roman Empire'', p. 16 Volunteers came forward and were accepted not from citizens of the city of Rome itself but from the surrounding countryside and smaller towns falling under Roman control.Santosuosso, ''Storming the Heavens'', p. 29 Whereas some long-term military professionals were classed as veterans, they were outnumbered by civilians with limited military experience who were in active service perhaps only for a few campaigns.Santosuosso, ''Storming the Heavens'', p. 51 The legions of the late Republic remained, unlike the legions of the later Empire, predominantly Roman in origin, although some small number of ex-auxiliary troops were probably incorporated.Smith, ''Service in the Post-Marian Roman Army'', p. 56 The army's higher-level officers and commanders were still drawn exclusively from the Roman aristocracy.

Unlike earlier in the Republic, legionaries were no longer fighting on a seasonal basis to protect their land.'''''' Instead, they received standard pay, and were employed by the state on a fixed-term basis. As a consequence, military duty began to appeal most to the poorest sections of society, to whom a guaranteed salary was attractive.Gabba, ''Republican Rome, The Army and The Allies'', p. 25 The army therefore consisted of a far higher proportion of the poor—particularly the rural poor—than it had previously.Boak, ''A History of Rome'', p. 189 A destabilising consequence of this development was that the proletariat "acquired a stronger and more elevated position" within the state. This professionalisation of the military was necessary to provide permanent garrisons for newly acquired and distant territories such as Hispania, something not possible under an army of seasonal citizen militia.

Historian R. E. Smith notes that there was a need to raise additional legions in an emergency to repel specific strategic threats. He argues that this may have resulted in two types of legion.Smith, ''Service in the Post-Marian Roman Army'', p. 29 Long-standing legions deployed overseas were probably professional troops forming a standing army. Quickly-formed new legions, in contrast, consisted of younger men, perhaps with little or no military experience, who hoped for adventure and plunder. However, no distinction in basic pay, discipline or armour is known of between the two types of legion. The practice of veteran troops signing up again voluntarily into newly-raised legions must have meant that no one army conformed exactly to one or other of these theoretical archetypes.

The legions of the late Republic were, structurally, almost entirely heavy infantry. The legion's main sub-unit was called a ''cohort'' and consisted of approximately 480 infantrymen.Luttwak, ''The Grand Strategy of the Roman Empire'', p. 14 The cohort was therefore a much larger unit than the earlier ''maniple'' sub-unit, and was divided into six centuriae of 80 men each. Each centuria was separated further into 10 "tent groups" (Latin: ''contubernia'') of 8 men each. Legions additionally consisted of a small body, typically 120 men, of Roman legionary cavalry (Latin: ''equites legionis''). The ''equites'' were used as scouts and dispatch riders rather than battlefield cavalry.Webster, ''The Roman Imperial Army'', p. 116 Legions also contained a dedicated group of artillery crew of perhaps 60 men, who would operate devices such as ''ballistae''.

Each legion was normally partnered with an approximately equal number of allied (non-Roman) ''auxiliae'' troops.Luttwak, ''The Grand Strategy of the Roman Empire'', p. 15 The addition of allied troops to the Roman army was a formalisation of the earlier arrangement of using light troops from the Socii and Latini, who had received Roman citizenship after the Social War.Smith, ''Service in the Post-Marian Roman Army'', p. 27 Auxiliary troops could be formed from either auxiliary light cavalry known as ''alae'', auxiliary light infantry known as ''cohors auxiliae'', or a flexible mixture of the two known as ''cohors equitata''. Cavalry types included mounted archers (Latin: ''sagittarii''), heavy shock cavalry (Latin: ''cataphracti'' or ''clibanarii''), or lancers (Latin: ''antesignani'' or ''lancearii''). Infantry could be armed with bows, slings, throwing spears, long swords, or thrusting spears. Auxiliary units were originally led by their own chiefs, and, in this period, their internal organisation was left to their commanders.Webster, ''The Roman Imperial Army'', p. 146

However, ''"the most obvious deficiency"'' of the Roman army remained its shortage of cavalry, especially heavy cavalry;Luttwak, ''The Grand Strategy of the Roman Empire'', p. 43 even auxiliary troops were predominantly infantry. Luttwak argues that auxiliary forces largely consisted of Cretan archers, Balearic slingers and Numidian infantry, all of whom fought on foot.Luttwak, ''The Grand Strategy of the Roman Empire'', p. 44 As Rome's borders expanded and its adversaries changed from largely infantry-based to largely cavalry-based troops, the infantry-based Roman army began to find itself at a tactical disadvantage, particularly in the East.

After having declined in size following the subjugation of the Mediterranean, the Roman navy underwent short-term upgrading and revitalisation in the late Republic to meet several new demands. Under Caesar, an invasion fleet was assembled in the English Channel to allow the invasion of ''Britannia''; under Pompey, a large fleet was raised in the Mediterranean Sea to clear the sea of Cilician pirates. During the civil war that followed, as many as a thousand ships were either constructed or pressed into service from Greek cities.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="41f0e1f472519e87cf01bfbb863be48b" name="Marius_Glyptothek_Munich_319" sectnum="4#1">../img/41f0e1f472519e87cf01bfbb863be48b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>