<document id="ec5829a8407292b2edeaab3ab03617e1-8" name="Structural_history_of_the_Roman_military" cat="29">
<text>
A distinction between frontier guard troops and more mobile reserve forces had emerged with the use of certain troops to permanently man frontiers such as Hadrian's Wall in ''Britannia'' in the second century AD, and may have extended as far back as the late Republic's use of "provincial" and "emergency" legions. By the late Empire the competing demands of manned frontiers and strategic reserve forces had led to a division of the military into four types of troops. Border fortifications were manned by a ''"settled and hereditary"'' militia (Latin: ''limitanei'' or ''riparienses'' ) that were ''"tied to their posts"''.Vogt, ''The Decline of Rome'', p. 178 In the rear lay more mobile troops in field armies known as the ''comitatenses'', which were held in strategic reserve.Boak, ''A History of Rome to 565 AD''. p. 452* Vogt, ''The Decline of Rome'', p. 177 Somewhere between the two were more local provincial reserves known as ''cunei'' (cavalry) and ''auxilia'' (by this time, referring to infantry alone) that may have evolved from earlier auxiliary cavalry units.Luttwak, ''The Grand Strategy of the Roman Empire'', p. 173 From the time of the emperor Constantine I there were also two small central reserves (Latin: ''scholae'') held to the strategic rear even of the ''comitatenses'', one each in the presence of the emperors of West and East respectively.Vogt, ''The Decline of Rome'', p. 177 Created and expanded from the core troops of the Emperor's personal bodyguards, the central field armies by 295 AD seem to have been too large to be accounted for as simple bodyguard forces, but were still too small to be able to campaign independently of legionary or vexillation support.Campbell, ''The Army'', p. 121

Of the four troop types, the ''limitanei'' (border guards) are generally considered to have been of the lowest quality,Boak, ''A History of Rome to 565 AD''. p. 452* Grant, ''A History of Rome'', p. 333* Santosuosso, ''Storming the Heavens'', p. 188 consisting largely of peasant-soldiers that were both ''"grossly inferior"'' to the earlier legions and inferior also to their counterparts in the mobile field armies.Luttwak, ''The Grand Strategy of the Roman Empire'', pp. 154, 173

While the ''limitanei'' were supposed to deal with policing actions and low-intensity incursions, the duty of responding to more serious incidents fell upon the provincial troops. The countering of the very largest scale incursions on a strategic scale was the task of the ''comitatenses'' or mobile field troops, possibly accompanied by the emperor's ''scholae''. Both border and field armies consisted of a mix of infantry and cavalry unitsCary & Scullard, ''A History of Rome'', p. 534 although the weight of cavalry was, according to some authorities, greater in the mobile field armies. Overall, approximately one quarter of the army consisted of cavalry troopsBoak, ''A History of Rome to 565 AD''. p. 451 but their importance is uncertain. Older works such as the Eleventh Edition of the ''Encyclopedia Britannica'' (1911) state that the Roman military of the late Empire was "marked by that predominance of the horseman which characterised the earlier centuries of the Middle Ages," but many more recent authors believe that the infantry remained predominant.Elton, ''Warfare in Roman Europe, A.D. 350–425'', pp. 103, 105–106* Treadgold, ''Byzantium and its Army'', pp. 44–59.

There is some dispute about whether this new military structure was put into place under the Emperor Diocletian or Constantine since both reorganised the Roman Army in the late 3rd and early 4th centuries to some degree.Southern & Dixon, ''The Late Roman Army'', pp. 15–38. Both Diocletian and even his predecessor of thirty years Gallienus may already have controlled mobile strategic reserves to assist the empire's border forces;Campbell, ''The Army'', p. 121* Southern & Dixon, ''The Late Roman Army'', pp. 11–17 either Diocletian or Constantine expanded this nascent force into permanent field armies.Southern & Dixon, ''The Late Roman Army'', pp. 15–20 & 37–38

Recruitment from amongst Roman citizens had become greatly curtailed as a consequence of a declining population,Boak, ''A History of Rome to 565 AD''. p. 451* Cary & Scullard, ''A History of Rome'', p. 537* Vogt, ''The Decline of Rome'', p. 25 ''"cripplingly numerous"'' categories of those exempted from military service and the spread of Christianity with its pacifist message.'''''' Gibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', Chapter XXXVIII, p. 622* Grant, A History of Rome, p. 333* Santosuosso, ''Storming the Heavens'', p. 229 Together, these factors culminated in "the withdrawal of the urban class from all forms of military activity."Vogt, ''The Decline of Rome'', p. 59 In their place, much of Rome's military were now recruited from non-Italian peoples living within the empire's borders. Many of these people were barbarians or semi-barbarians recently settled from lands beyond the empire,Alfoldi, ''The Crisis of the Empire'', p. 208* Boak, ''A History of Rome to 565 AD'', p. 451* Vogt, ''The Decline of Rome'', p. 178 including several colonies of ''Carpi'', ''Bastarnae'' and ''Sarmatians''.Gibbon, ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', Chapter VI, p. 188

Although units described as ''legiones'' existed as late as the 5th century in both the border and field armies,Luttwak, ''The Grand Strategy of the Roman Empire'', p. 171 the legionary system was very different from that of the principate and early empire. Since the term legion continued to be used, it is unclear exactly when the structure and role of the legions changed. Sometime during the third and fourth centuries, however, the legions' role as elite heavy infantry was substantially reducedBoak, ''A History of Rome to 565 AD''. p. 453* Vogt, ''The Decline of Rome'', p. 59 and may have evaporated entirely.Luttwak, ''The Grand Strategy of the Roman Empire'', p. 175 Instead, those "legions" that remained were no longer drawn exclusively (and perhaps hardly at all) from Roman citizens. Either DiocletianBrian Campbell, ''The Crisis of Empire'', p. 123 or Constantine reorganised the legions into smaller infantry units who, according to some sources, were more lightly armoured than their forebears. Their lighter armament may have been either because they "would not consent to wear the same weight of body armour as the legionaries of old"Cary & Scullard, ''A History of Rome'', p. 535 or, as in at least one documented instance, because they were prohibited from wearing heavy armour by their general in order to increase their mobility.Alfoldi, ''The Crisis of the Empire'', p. 209 Fourth-century legions were at times only one sixth the size of early imperial legions, and they were armed with some combination of spears, bows, slings, darts and swords, reflecting a greater contemporary emphasis on ranged fighting.Alfoldi, ''The Crisis of the Empire'', p. 209* Luttwak, ''The Grand Strategy of the Roman Empire'', p. 175 The ''auxilia'' and ''numeri'' had also largely disappeared.Alfoldi, ''The Crisis of the Empire'', p. 213 Constantine further increased the proportion of German troops in the regular army;Grant, ''A History of Rome'', p. 310 their cultural impact was so great that even legionaries began wearing German dress. At the start of Diocletian's reign, the Roman army numbered about 390,000 men, but by the end of his reign he successfully increased the number to 581,000 men.Treadgold, ''A History of Byzantine State and Society'', 19
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="cb2c2f3fd4dca4f75a65053dd17c90b9" name="Constantine_arch_troops" sectnum="8#1">../img/cb2c2f3fd4dca4f75a65053dd17c90b9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>