<document id="ec5829a8407292b2edeaab3ab03617e1-9" name="Structural_history_of_the_Roman_military" cat="29">
<text>
The non-federated mobile field army, known as the ''comitatenses'', was eventually split into a number of smaller field armies: a central field army under the emperor's direct control, known as the ''comitatensis palatina'' or ''praesentalis'', and several regional field armies. Historians Santosuosso and Vogt agree that the latter gradually degraded into low-quality garrison units similar to the ''limitanei'' that they either supplemented or replaced. By the 5th century, a significant portion of Western Rome's main military strength lay in rented barbarian mercenaries known as ''foederati''.

As the 5th century progressed, many of the Empire's original borders had been either wholly or partially denuded of troops to support the central field armySalway. ''Roman Britain'', 1981, p 437. In 395, the Western Roman Empire had several regional field armies in Italy, Illyricum, Gallia, Britannia and Africa, and about twelve border armies. By about 430, two more field armies were established in Hispania and Tingitania but the central government had lost control of BritanniaSalway. ''Roman Britain'', 1981, p 437 as well as much of Gaul, Hispania, and Africa. In the same period, the Eastern Roman Empire had two palatine field armies (at Constantinople), three regional field armies (in the East, in Thrace, and in Illyricum) and fifteen frontier armies.Treadgold, ''Byzantium and its Army, 284–1081'', pp. 43–59.


As Roman troops were spread increasingly thin over its long border, the Empire's territory continued to dwindle in size. Barbarian war bands increasingly began to penetrate the Empire's vulnerable borders, both as settlers and invaders. In 451, the Romans defeated Attila the Hun, but only with assistance from a confederation of ''foederatii'' troops, which included Visigoths and Alans. As barbarian incursions continued, some advancing as far as the heart of Italy, Rome's borders began to collapse, with frontier forces swiftly finding themselves cut off deep in the enemy's rear.Luttwak, ''The Grand Strategy of the Roman Empire'', p. 188

Simultaneously, barbarian troops in Rome's pay came to be ''"in a condition of almost perpetual turbulence and revolt"''Grant, ''A History of Rome'', p. 344 from 409 onwards. In 476 these troops finally unseated the last emperor of the Western Roman Empire.Vogt, ''The Decline of Rome'', p. 250 The Eastern Roman forces continued to defend the Eastern Roman (Byzantine) Empire until its fall in 1453.Runciman, ''The Fall of Constantinople: 1453.''
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d338e0eb29eacd81c37d8137e37967c9" name="Greatpalacemosaic" sectnum="9#1">../img/d338e0eb29eacd81c37d8137e37967c9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>