<document id="ec5829a8407292b2edeaab3ab03617e1-7" name="Structural_history_of_the_Roman_military" cat="29">
<text>
By the late Empire, enemy forces in both the East and West were "sufficiently mobile and sufficiently strong to pierce  defensive perimeter on any selected axis of penetration";Luttwak, ''The Grand Strategy of the Roman Empire'', p. 176 from the third century onwards, both Germanic tribes and Persian armies pierced the frontiers of the Roman Empire.Alfoldi, ''The Crisis of the Empire'', p. 211* Heather, ''The Fall of the Roman Empire'', pp. 58–67 In response, the Roman army underwent a series of changes, more organic and evolutionary than the deliberate military reforms of the Republic and early Empire. A stronger emphasis was placed upon ranged combat ability of all types, such as field artillery, hand-held ''ballistae'', archery and darts. Roman forces also gradually became more mobile, with one cavalryman for every three infantryman, compared to one in forty in the early Empire.Elton, ''Warfare in Roman Europe'', p. 94Santosuosso, ''Storming The Heavens'', p. 190 Additionally, the Emperor Gallienus took the revolutionary step of forming dedicated cavalry regiments, separating them from the mixed cavalry and infantry regiments of the past.Grant, ''A History of Rome'', p. 285* Vogt, ''The Decline of Rome'', p. 74 A diverse range of cavalry regiments existed, including ''catafractarii'' or ''clibanarii'', ''scutarii'', and legionary cavalry known as ''promoti''. Collectively, these regiments were known as ''equites''. Around 275 AD, the proportion of ''catafractarii'' was also increased. There is some disagreement over exactly when the relative proportion of cavalry increased, whether Gallienus' reforms occurred contemporaneously with an increased reliance on cavalry, or whether these are two distinct events. Alfoldi appears to believe that Gallienus' reforms were contemporaneous with an increase in cavalry numbers. He argues that, by 258, Gallienus had made cavalry the predominant troop type in the Roman army in place of heavy infantry, which dominated earlier armies. According to Warren Treadgold, however, the proportion of cavalry did not change between the early 3rd and early 4th centuries.Treadgold, ''Byzantium and its Army, 284–1081'', p. 56.

Larger groups of ''barbari'' began to settle in Rome's territories around this time, and the troops they were contracted to provide to the Roman army were no longer organised as ''numeri'' but rather were the forerunners of the later rented native armies known as federated troops (Latin: ''foederati'').'''''' Alfoldi, ''The Crisis of the Empire'', p. 212 Though they served under Roman officers, the troops of these units were far more barbarised than the ''numeri'', lacked Romanisation of either military structure or personal ideology, and were ineligible for Roman citizenship upon discharge.  These native troops were not permitted to fight in native war bands under their own leaders, unlike the later ''foederati''; instead, these troops were split into small groups attached to other Roman units.Alfoldi, ''The Crisis of the Empire'', p. 219 They existed therefore as a halfway house between ''numeri'', who were encouraged to be Romanised, and the ''foederati'', who raised officers from their own ranks and were almost entirely self-dependent.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="56524a45a237a1bd3dea8645f1e2169a" name="Knight-Iran" sectnum="7#1">../img/56524a45a237a1bd3dea8645f1e2169a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>