<document id="ec871f96492f968f26e2f4c058e55452-5" name="Preity_Zinta" cat="19">
<text>
Zinta is particularly known in the Indian media for her straightforwardness and for honestly expressing her outspoken views and forthright opinions in public, be it about her on-screen or off-screen life or raising a voice against any social injustice. These features were noted during the ''Bharat Shah Case'', when she testified against the underworld; following this incident she was described by journalists as "The only man in Bollywood". Her characteristic dimple has been cited by the media as her trademark. She is often described by the press as having a vivacious personality and a bubbly, outgoing persona, an image she has confessed to disliking.

In 2003, Zinta appeared in the number one spot on Rediff's "Top Bollywood Female Stars". She was ranked second for the following three years. She has been featured frequently on other Rediff lists, including "Bollywood's Most Beautiful Actresses", "Bollywood's Best Dressed Women" and "Woman of Many Faces".
In September 2006, the UK magazine ''Eastern Eye'' ranked her at 41 in the list of "Asia's Sexiest Women".

On July 15, 2005, Zinta filed a defamation suit against leading Mumbai tabloid ''Mid-Day'' after tapes emerged alleging that Salman Khan had made derogatory comments about her. The tabloid published transcripts indicating that she had a sexual relationship with Khan, and she was cross-examined as a chief witness in January 2007. She said about the case, "I felt humiliated as it spoiled my reputation and character in public." She told of disparaging phone calls she received from individuals pretending to be Salman Khan, and that she had been repeatedly questioned in a derogatory fashion by the media. Zinta further stated that the events affected her professionally as well; a planned film with Khan was abandoned. The tape was examined by the Government's Forensic laboratory in Chandigarh which concluded that it was a fake.

Between 2004 and 2007, Zinta made three appearances on the Indian talk show ''Koffee with Karan'', hosted by Karan Johar, appearing with Saif Ali Khan, Abhishek Bachchan and Bobby Deol, respectively. In 2006, she was a guest judge in the singing talent contest ''Indian Idol 2''. She returned briefly to her occupation as a model when she walked the ramp for Manish Malhotra's display ''Fashion Week 2006'', along with actress Kajol. Later that year, Zinta and filmmaker Karan Johar represented Bollywood at the 2006 Cannes Film Festival to promote Johar's forthcoming ''Kabhi Alvida Naa Kehna'', which featured Zinta in a leading role.

In May 2007, Zinta returned to Cannes for the 60th Film Festival to attend the premiere of ''My Blueberry Nights'', which opened the gathering. She co-hosted the 52nd Filmfare Awards ceremony alongside Shahrukh Khan, Juhi Chawla and Karan Johar. She was selected as the first brand ambassador for GoAir, a new airline service owned by Jehangir Wadia from Wadia Group. Speculation arose in the press that she endorsed the brand as a favour to Jeh, who is Ness Wadia's brother, a suggestion that Zinta quickly denied. May 2008 saw Zinta making her third consecutive appearance at Cannes; she attended the 61st Film Festival as the brand ambassador of Chopard, the maker of luxury watches and jewellery.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="10c2ac3860f030d6670131d133ac3a57" name="Zinta_IIFA_04" sectnum="5#1">../img/10c2ac3860f030d6670131d133ac3a57.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>