<document id="ecb575a5bb6c87eb2145295081385e3f-2.3" name="Thierry_Henry" cat="26">
<text>
On 25 June 2007, in an unexpected turn of events, Henry was transferred to Barcelona for €24 million. He signed a four-year deal for a reported €6.8 (£4.6) million per season., nationmultimedia.com, 23 June 2007, accessed 22 July 2007. It was revealed that the contract included a release clause of €125 (£84.9) million., ''The Daily Express'', 25 June 2007, accessed 28 June 2007. Henry cited the departure of Dein and continued uncertainty over Wenger's future as reasons for leaving,, ''The Sun'', 23 June 2007, accessed 28 June 2007., BBC Sport, 23 June 2007, accessed 28 June 2007. and maintained that "I always said that if I ever left Arsenal it would be to play for Barcelona.", soccernet.espn.go.com, 26 June 2007, accessed 15 October 2007. Despite their captain's departure, Arsenal got off to an impressive start for the 2007–08 campaign, and Henry admitted that his presence in the team might have been more of a hindrance than a help. He stated: "Because of my seniority, the fact that I was captain and my habit of screaming for the ball, they would sometimes give it to me even when I was not in the best position. So in that sense it was good for the team that I moved on.", soccernet.espn.go.com, 14 October 2007, accessed 15 October 2007. Henry left Arsenal as the club's leading all-time league goal-scorer with 174 goals and leading all-time goal-scorer in Europe with 42 goals; in July 2008, Arsenal fans voted him as Arsenal's greatest player ever in Arsenal.com's Gunners' Greatest 50 Players poll., arsenal.com, accessed 18 July 2008.

At Barcelona, Henry was given the number 14 jersey, the same as he had worn at Arsenal. He scored his first goal for his new club on 19 September 2007 in a 3–0 Champions League group stage win over Lyon,, ''The Daily Telegraph'', 20 September 2007, accessed 23 September 2007, and he recorded his first hat-trick for Barça in a league match against Levante ten days later., soccernet.espn.gp.com, 29 September 2007, accessed 5 October 2007. However, with Henry mostly deployed on the wing throughout the season, he was unable to reproduce the goal-scoring form he achieved with Arsenal. Henry expressed dissatisfaction with the move to Barcelona in the initial year, amidst widespread speculation of a return to the Premier League. In an interview with Garth Crooks on BBC Football Focus, Henry described missing life "back home" and even "the English press"., youtube.com, accessed 13 April 2009. However, Henry concluded his debut season as the club's top scorer with 19 goals in addition to nine league assists, second behind Lionel Messi's ten. He went on to surpass this tally in a more integrated 2008–09 campaign, winning the first trophy of his Barcelona career on 13 May 2009 when Barcelona defeated Athletic Bilbao in the Copa del Rey final. Barcelona won the league and Champions League soon after, completing a treble for the Frenchman, who had combined with Lionel Messi and Samuel Eto'o to score 100 goals between them that season. The trio was also the most prolific trio in Spanish league history, scoring 72 goals and surpassing the 66 goals of Real Madrid's Ferenc Puskas, Alfredo di Stefano and Luis del Sol of the 1960–61 season.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="de98a3e7642d484e2dc5973b38cc12ba" name="Thierry_Henry_FC_Barcelona_cropped" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/de98a3e7642d484e2dc5973b38cc12ba.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>