<document id="ecb575a5bb6c87eb2145295081385e3f-4" name="Thierry_Henry" cat="26">
<text>
Although Henry played up front as a striker during his youth, he spent his time at Monaco and Juventus playing on the wing. When Henry joined Arsenal in 1999, Wenger immediately changed this, switching Henry to his childhood position, often pairing him with Dutch veteran Dennis Bergkamp. During the 2004–05 season, Wenger switched Arsenal's formation to 4-5-1.Hatherall, Chris, "", ''The Independent'', 30 October 2006, accessed 23 April 2007 This change forced Henry to adapt again to fit into the Arsenal team, and he played many games as a lone striker. Still, Henry remained Arsenal's main offensive threat, on many occasions conjuring spectacular goals. Wenger once said of his fellow Frenchman: "Thierry Henry could take ball in the middle of park and score a goal that no one else in the world could score".Clarke, Richard, "", arsenal.com, accessed 27 July 2007.

One of the reasons cited for Henry's impressive play up front is his ability to calmly score from one-on-ones. This, combined with his exceptional pace, means that he can get in behind defenders regularly enough to score.Hansen, Alan, , BBC Sport, 13 March 2006, accessed 27 March 2007. When up front, Henry is occasionally known to move out wide to the left wing position,Jacob Daniel, ''The Complete Guide to Coaching Soccer Systems and Tactics'', pg 190, (Reedswain Inc., 1 March 2004)., BBC Sport, 12 April 2002, accessed 26 March 2007. something which enables him to contribute heavily in assists: between 2002–03 and 2004–05, the striker managed almost 50 assists in total and this was attributed to his unselfish play and creativity. Henry would also drift offside to fool the defence then run back onside before the ball is played and beat the offside trap,"", Goal.com, 22 September 2008, accessed 22 September 2008. although he never provided Arsenal a distinct aerial threat. Given his versatility in being able to operate as both a winger and a striker, the Frenchman is not a prototypical "out-and-out striker", but he has emerged consistently as one of Europe's most prolific strikers. In set pieces, Henry was the first-choice penalty and free kick taker for Arsenal, having scored regularly from those positions., sportinglife.com, 28 August 2003, accessed 30 October 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="26357e4a074bd2ec631a187435e3a187" name="Van_Persie_free_kick" sectnum="4#1">../img/26357e4a074bd2ec631a187435e3a187.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>