<document id="ecbf1f7afc3cab9308c49ba3449fa9f0-5" name="Ellis_Paul" cat="20">
<text>
On May 1, 2004 Paul was the recipient of the 2nd annual Boston College Arts Council Alumni Award for Artistic Achievement. The award was presented as part of the sixth annual Boston College Arts Festival. His appearances at the festival also included an "Inside the BC Studio" interview with music writer Scott Alarik, a master class on songwriting, and a concert.Estvanik, Nicole. , May 2004. Retrieved February 28, 2007. In 2004 Paul was also awarded his 13th Boston Music Award in the category of Outstanding Singer/Songwriter.  At the time Paul was writing what he called "country tunes" when he teamed up with an Irish musician, producer, and studio expert named Flynn.  This resulted in ''American Jukebox Fables'', released April 5, 2005, a recording produced by Flynn that surprised some fans by melding folk, pop and electronica.  Paul said that his collaboration with Flynn formed a partnership where he brought banjos and accordions and Flynn brought a laptop and keyboard.  Although Paul knew that the end result would fall outside the comfort zone of some fans who expected another acoustic folk album, experimenting with Flynn's musical chemistry set injected excitement and fun into the recording project.Kocher, Chris.  Folkie Paul’s new path takes him to Oxford.  ''Press & Sun-Bulletin'' (Binghamton, NY), May 11, 2006.

For over ten years, Paul has annually played Club Passim on New Year's Eve.  In early 2006 Black Wolf Records released ''Live at Club Passim'', a recording compiled from his 2005 New Year's Eve shows.  In May 2006, Paul toured Europe and England playing to sold-out shows in Paris, France; Twickenham, England; Cheltenham, England and Wasserburg, Germany.  The tour also included two BBC radio interviews and a radio interview in Paris.  Paul was included on the Woody Guthrie Coalition’s DVD ''Woody Sez: a Tribute to Woody Guthrie'' released in 2006.  The tribute show, recorded July 13, 2005 at the Crystal Theater in Okemah, OK, included Paul performing a duet with The Burns Sisters on “God’s Promise”.  Also released in 2006 was Paul's "best of" album, released as ''Ellis Paul Essentials'', on October 10.   The two-disk retrospective of Paul’s 15-year career contained some songs that were absolutes and others that were included based on polls held on his website and discussion board.  In his ''Folkwax'' review of Ellis Paul ''Essentials'', Arthur Wood stated: "If you've never visited "musically" with Mr. Ellis Paul, ''Essentials'' is a stunning place to start."Wood, Arthur.  ''FolkWax E-Zine''. October 26, 2006. (Free with registration.)  In his review for ''The Washington Post'', Mike Joyce said "
''Essentials,'' a career-spanning double CD from veteran singer-songwriter Ellis Paul, has a few newly produced, John Jennings-helmed tracks of previously recorded tunes that help set this compilation apart from most retrospectives."Joyce, Mike. , ''The Washington Post'', June 29, 2007.  Retrieved July 1, 2007. In her review for Sing Out!, Kari Estren said "Paul's ''Essentials'' is just that and a must for your folk collection."Estren, Kari.   Review of Ellis Paul Essentials.  Sing Out!, Vol. 51, #1, p. 161, Spring 2007. 



In January 2008, Paul released a children's and family record entitled ''The Dragonfly Races''.  Inspired after the birth of his second daughter, Paul said that he wanted to teach his children about the world through the use of music. The songs are meant to be enjoyed by both children and adults, and Paul said "I wanted my kids to hear music with social commentary and some fantasy involved."Koenig, Seth.   ''The Times Record'', Oct. 11, 2007.  Retrieved October 24, 2007. Scott Alarik said "Paul sings movingly about what really worries new parents, and turns lazy dragonflies, gentle monsters, and resilient roses into useful metaphors for world peace, the power of faith, and the delights of a sleepy day."Alarik, Scott.  ''The Boston Globe'', Nov. 15, 2007. Retrieved November 16, 2007. In April 2008 the Parents' Choice Foundation awarded ''The Dragonfly Races'' a Silver Medallion.  The Parents' Choice Awards program honors the best material for children in these categories: books, toys, music and storytelling, magazines, software, videogames, television and websites.Parents' Choice Foundation.  Retrieved April 29, 2008.

In 2009, country musician Jack Ingram chose to record a song written by Paul. According to CMT, Paul's "The World Ain't Slowing Down", may be the song that takes Ingram to the "next level".Shelburne, Craig.  CMT Blog, Sept. 29, 2008. Retrieved June 16, 2009. Ingram says "It'll be fun for me to expose people to a fantastic song from an artist who's had a 20-year career of being a very successful folk artist." Mansfield, Brian.  ''USA Today'', December 26, 2008.  Retrieved June 16, 2009. 

Sugarland's first holiday album, ''Gold and Green'' released on October 13, 2009Morran, Chris.  ''Oklahoma Magazine'', August 31, 2009.  Retrieved August 31, 2009. includes "City of Silver Dreams" and "Little Wood Guitar," co-written by Kristian Bush and Paul.Jurek, Thom.  Allmusic.com. Retrieved Oct. 12, 2009.Bjorke, Matt.  Roughtstock.com.  October 12, 2009. Retrieved October 14, 2009. In his review of the album, Matt Bjorke compares "City of Silver Dreams" to Joni Mitchell's "River" saying it could be a "seminal holiday song".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3ad8c7e4571a9a04ded76707fb40a445" name="Ellis%26Jada" sectnum="5#1">../img/3ad8c7e4571a9a04ded76707fb40a445.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>