<document id="ed079ec9a95b0134db9a088c7788df78-4.2" name="Paul_Nobuo_Tatsuguchi" cat="29">
<text>
On May 11, 1943, the American Seventh Infantry Division began landing on Attu to retake the island from the Japanese.  Attu's commander, Yamasaki, positioned his troops – who were outnumbered five to one – in the mountains from where they temporarily delayed the Americans' advance inland.  Tatsuguchi's diary entry on May 12 records the Japanese move into the mountains after the American landings, stating simply "evacuated to the summit.  Air raids carried out frequently.  Heard loud noise, it is naval gunfire.  Prepared battle equipment."Hays, p. 135.


On May 14, American artillery fired phosphorus smoke shells to mark Japanese positions in the mountains.  Many Japanese, and many Americans, believed these were poison gas shells.  Tatsuguchi noted in his diary that, "In the enemy the U.S. Forces used gas but no damage was done on account of strong wind."Garfield, p. 298, Hays, p. 36 & 136.

Tatsuguchi recorded in his diary that he was forced to move his field hospital into a cave to escape American naval and aerial bombardment. He relocated the hospital and patients several times as the Japanese forces were pushed back by the Americans.  His May 17 entry describes one of the moves:



Tatsuguchi refers again and again in his diary to the constant, intense attacks by American aircraft and artillery on his comrades' positions.  On May 21, he noted that he "was strafed when amputating a patient's arm" and on May 23 that "by naval gun fire a hit was scored on the pillar pole of tents for patients and the tents gave in and killed two instantly.  No food for two days."Hays, p. 138–139.  On May 26, Tatsuguchi recorded that "there was a ceremony of granting of the Imperial Edict.  The last line of Umanose  was broken through.  No hope for reinforcements.  We will die for cause of Imperial Edict."Garfield, p. 324, Cloe, p. 289, Hays, p. 140.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e242996355cef5e6cd0dd3f606fe3cfc" name="Attu_Invasion_02" sectnum="4.2#1">../img/e242996355cef5e6cd0dd3f606fe3cfc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>