<document id="ed2a1d6fedc5c7e69ed3f79eabf0b997-3.2" name="Ozzie_Smith" cat="26">
<text>
After more behind-the-scenes contract wrangling, Smith became a St. Louis Cardinal on February 11, 1982.Smith and Rains 1988: 57 Herzog believed Smith could improve his offensive production by hitting more ground balls, and subsequently created a motivational tool designed to help Smith concentrate on that task.Smith and Rains 2002: 28–29 Approaching Smith one day during spring training, Herzog said, "Every time you hit a fly ball, you owe me a buck. Every time you hit a ground ball, I owe you a buck. We'll keep that going all year."Smith and Rains 1988: 61 Smith agreed to the wager, and by the end of the season had won close to $300 from Herzog. As the 1982 season got underway, Herzog's newly assembled team won 12 games in a row during the month of April, and finished the season atop the National League East division.Leach 2008: 37 Herzog would later say of Smith's contributions that, "If he saved two runs a game on defense, which he did many a night, it seemed to me that was just as valuable to the team as a player who drove in two runs a game on offense."Smith and Rains 2002: 6

Smith became a father for the first time during the 1982 season with the birth of his son O.J., today known as Nikko, on April 28.Smith and Rains 1988: 65 Smith also developed a lasting friendship with teammate Willie McGee during the season, and Smith said he likes to think he "helped Willie get over some of the rough spots of adjusting to the major leagues".Smith and Rains 1988: 66 Smith later participated in the postseason for the first time when the Cardinals faced the Atlanta Braves in the best-of-five 1982 National League Championship Series (NLCS). Smith drove in the series' first run by hitting a sacrifice fly that scored McGee in Game 1, ultimately going five for nine in St. Louis' three-game series sweep.

Just as Herzog had predicted when he told Smith the Cardinals would win the pennant with him on the team, Smith found himself as the team's starting shortstop in the best-of-seven 1982 World Series against the Milwaukee Brewers. During the contest Smith scored three runs, had five hits, and did not commit an error in the field.Rains 2003: 105 When St. Louis was trailing 3&ndash;1 with one out in the sixth inning of Game 7, Smith started a rally with a base hit to left field, eventually scoring the first of the team's three runs that inning. After Bruce Sutter struck out Gorman Thomas in the ninth inning, Smith celebrated a World Series championship with his teammates.

After the World Series championship, Smith and the Cardinals agreed on a new contract in January 1983 that paid Smith $1 million per year.Smith and Rains 1988: 81 Smith was voted in as the National League's starting shortstop in the All-Star Game for the first time in 1983, and at season's end won a fourth consecutive Gold Glove Award.Smith and Rains 1988: 87 During July of the 1984 season, Smith went on the disabled list with a broken wrist after being hit by a pitch during a game against the Padres.Smith and Rains 1988: 95 Smith's return to the lineup a month later was not enough to propel the Cardinals to a postseason berth.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2f5cf977b5b06f87e01e608c295b9d5c" name="Ozzie_Smith_statue_part" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/2f5cf977b5b06f87e01e608c295b9d5c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>