<document id="ed2a1d6fedc5c7e69ed3f79eabf0b997-4" name="Ozzie_Smith" cat="26">
<text>
Upon retirement, Smith took over for Mel Allen as the host of the television series ''This Week in Baseball'' (''TWIB'') in 1997. Smith also became color commentator for the local broadcast of Cardinals games on KPLR-TV from 1997 to 1999.Robinson, Tom. "Ozzie Puts Down Glove, Picks Up Mike." ''The Virginian-Pilot''. May 22, 1997: C1. Retrieved on 2007-12-28. When his stint on ''This Week in Baseball'' concluded, Smith then moved on to do work for CNN-SI beginning in 1999.Rains and Reid 2002: 109


On January 8, 2002 Smith received a phone call from Jack O'Connell, the secretary of the Baseball Writer's Association of America, informing him that he had been elected to the Baseball Hall of Fame on his first ballot by receiving 91.7% of the votes cast.Rains and Reid 2002: 107 As it happened, the Olympic torch was passing through St. Louis on its way to Salt Lake City for the 2002 Winter Olympics, and Smith served as a torchbearer in a ceremony with St. Louis Rams' quarterback Kurt Warner that evening.Smith and Rains 2002: 18–19 Smith was inducted into the Hall of Fame during ceremonies on July 28, 2002. During his speech, he compared his baseball experiences with the characters from the novel ''The Wonderful Wizard of Oz'', after which his son Dustin presented his Hall of Fame plaque. Days later on August 11, Smith was back at Busch Memorial Stadium for the unveiling of a statue in his likeness made by sculptor Harry Weber. Weber chose to emphasize Smith's defensive skills by showing Smith stretched horizontal to the ground while fielding a baseball. At the ceremony Weber told Smith, "You spent half of your career up in the air. That makes it difficult for a sculptor to do something with it."

Smith has also been an entrepreneur in a variety of business ventures. Smith opened "Ozzie's" restaurant and sports bar in 1988, started a youth sports academy in 1990, became an investor in a grocery store chain in 1999, and partnered with David Slay to open a restaurant in the early 2000s.Rains and Reid 2002: 113 Of those businesses, the sports bar and youth academy remain in operation as of 2009. Smith has also appeared in numerous radio and television commercials in the St. Louis area since retiring from baseball, and in 2008 pursued a new business venture by releasing a brand of salad dressing.

Smith is father to three children from his marriage to former wife Denise; sons Nikko, Dustin, and daughter Taryn. Smith remains a visible figure around the St. Louis area, making appearances as varied as playing the role of the Wizard in the St. Louis Municipal Opera's summer 2001 production of ''The Wizard of Oz''.Rains and Reid 2002: 114 In 1999 he ranked number 87 on ''The Sporting News''' list of the 100 Greatest Baseball Players, and finished third in voting at shortstop for the Major League Baseball All-Century Team.  Smith has also been honored with induction into the Alabama Sports Hall of Fame and the St. Louis Walk of Fame, and received an honorary Doctor of Humane Letters degree from Cal-Poly. Smith has chosen to limit his association with the Cardinals for as long as La Russa remains manager of the team, still upset with the situation that unfolded in 1996. Besides playing golf as a hobby, Smith cheered on his son Nikko as he cracked the top ten finalists of the 2005 edition of ''American Idol''.Wald, Jaina. "When it's "Idol" time at Ozzie's, folks go crazy for Nikko." ''St. Louis Post-Dispatch''. 2005-04-06. E3. Retrieved on 2008-03-19.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a3aad57874d72f1fb9bcd05a7635cdf5" name="Ozzie_Smith_Doubleday" sectnum="4#1">../img/a3aad57874d72f1fb9bcd05a7635cdf5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>