<document id="ed91d05e7bd45934c7ffeb8a2aa21065-1" name="Daspletosaurus" cat="3">
<text>
While very large by the standard of modern predators, ''Daspletosaurus'' was not the largest tyrannosaurid. Adults could reach a length of 8–9 meters (26–30 ft) from snout to tail. Mass estimates have centered around 2.5 tonnes (2.75 short tons) but have ranged between 1.8 tonnes (2 tons) and 3.8 tonnes (4.1 tons).

''Daspletosaurus'' had a massive skull that could reach more than 1 meter (3.3 ft) in length. The bones were heavily constructed and some, including the nasal bones on top of the snout, were fused for strength. Large fenestrae (openings) in the skull reduced its weight. An adult ''Daspletosaurus'' was armed with about six dozen teeth that were very long but oval in cross section rather than blade-like. Unlike its other teeth, those in the premaxilla at the end of the upper jaw had a ''D''-shaped cross section, an example of heterodonty always seen in tyrannosaurids. Unique skull features included the rough outer surface of the maxilla (upper jaw bone) and the pronounced crests around the eyes on the lacrimal, postorbital, and jugal bones. The orbit (eye socket) was a tall oval, somewhere in between the circular shape seen in ''Gorgosaurus'' and the 'keyhole' shape of ''Tyrannosaurus''.

''Daspletosaurus'' shared the same body form as other tyrannosaurids, with a short, ''S''-shaped neck supporting the massive skull. It walked on its two thick hindlimbs, which ended in four-toed feet, although the first digit (the hallux) did not contact the ground. In contrast, the forelimbs were extremely small and bore only two digits, although ''Daspletosaurus'' had the longest forelimbs in proportion to body size of any tyrannosaurid. A long, heavy tail served as a counterweight to the head and torso, with the center of gravity over the hips.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a26586cc8d2742698061f0cde7bc4691" name="Daspletosaurus_torosus_steveoc" sectnum="1#1">../img/a26586cc8d2742698061f0cde7bc4691.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>