<document id="ed94ea9a4fd2a9b1e9ad5be2bd7b682a-4" name="Tasmanian_Devil" cat="3">
<text>
Tasmanian Devils are widespread and fairly common throughout Tasmania, but are quickly dying from a facial cancer. Found in all habitats on the island, including the outskirts of urban areas, they particularly like dry sclerophyll forests and coastal woodlands. The Tasmanian Devil is a nocturnal and crepuscular hunter, spending the days in dense bush or in a hole. Young devils can climb trees, but this becomes more difficult as they grow larger. Devils can also swim. They are predominantly solitary animals and do not form packs. They occupy territories of 8&ndash;20 km², which can overlap considerably amongst different animals.

A devil eating kangaroo
Tasmanian Devils can take prey up to the size of a small kangaroo, but in practice they are opportunistic, and eat carrion more often than they hunt live prey. Although the devil favours wombats, it will eat all small native mammals, domestic mammals (including sheep), birds, fish, insects, frogs and reptiles. Their diet is largely varied and depends on the food available. On average, they eat about 15% of their body weight each day; however, they can eat up to 40% of their body weight in 30 minutes if the opportunity arises.Pemberton, D. and Renouf, D. 1993. A field-study of communication and social behaviour of Tasmanian Devils at feeding sites. ''Australian Journal of Zoology'', 41:507–526. Tasmanian Devils eliminate all traces of a carcass, devouring the bones and fur in addition to the meat and internal organs. In this respect, the devil has earned the gratitude of Tasmanian farmers, as the speed at which they clean a carcass helps prevent the spread of insects that might otherwise harm livestock.

Although they hunt alone, eating is a social event for the Tasmanian Devil.  Much of the noise attributed to the animal is a result of raucous communal eating, at which up to 12 individuals can gather, and can often be heard several kilometres away. A study of feeding devils identified 20 physical postures, including their characteristic vicious yawn, and the 11 different vocal sounds that devils use to communicate as they feed. They usually establish dominance by sound and physical posturing, although fighting does occur. Adult males are the most aggressive, and scarring is common from fighting over food and mates.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="20b0778d9d2fcb513062e0266e45fc9e" name="Tasmanian_Devil_resting" sectnum="4#1">../img/20b0778d9d2fcb513062e0266e45fc9e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>