<document id="ed94ea9a4fd2a9b1e9ad5be2bd7b682a-2" name="Tasmanian_Devil" cat="3">
<text>
The Tasmanian Devil is the largest surviving carnivorous marsupial in Australia. It has a squat and thick build, with a large head and a tail which is about half its body length. The devil stores body fat in its tail, so unhealthy devils often have thin tails. Unusual for a marsupial, its forelegs are slightly longer than its hind legs. Devils can run up to  per hour for short distances. The fur is usually black, although irregular white patches on the chest and rump are common. Males are usually larger than females, having an average head and body length of , with a  tail, and an average weight of . Females have an average head and body length of , with a  tail, and an average weight of .Guiler, E.R. 1983. Tasmanian Devil in R. Strahan Ed. ''The Australian Museum Complete Book of Australian Mammals''. p 27–28. Angus & Robertson ISBN 0-207-14454-0  The average life expectancy of a Tasmanian Devil in the wild is estimated at six years, although they may live longer in captivity. 

The devil has long whiskers on its face and in clumps on the top of the head. These help the devil locate prey when foraging in the dark, and aid in detecting when other devils are close during feeding. When agitated, the devil can produce a strong odour, its pungency rivalling even the skunk. Hearing is its dominant sense, and it also has an excellent sense of smell. Since devils hunt at night, their vision seems to be strongest in black and white. In these conditions they can detect moving objects readily, but have difficulty seeing stationary objects.Department of Primary Industries, Water and Environment.  An analysis of mammalian bite force relative to the body size shows that the devil has the strongest bite of any living mammal (over ).Wroe, S, McHenry, C, and Thomason, J. 2005. Bite club: comparative bite force in big biting mammals and the prediction of predatory behaviour in fossil taxa. ''Proceedings of the Royal Society B-Biological Sciences'' 272:619–625 PMID 15817436 The power of the jaw is in part due to its comparatively large head. A Tasmanian Devil also has one set of teeth that grows slowly throughout its life.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a905bd7f2c540803d8a774b8853b2c80" name="TasmanianDevil_1888" sectnum="2#1">../img/a905bd7f2c540803d8a774b8853b2c80.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>