<document id="ed98748bf61dd7c57969505bea8369a6-7" name="École_Polytechnique_massacre" cat="14">
<text>
Since 1991, the anniversary of the massacre has been designated the National Day of Remembrance and Action on Violence Against Women, intended as a call to action against discrimination against women.  A White Ribbon Campaign was launched in 1991 by a group of men in London, Ontario, in wake of the massacre, for the purpose of raising awareness about the prevalence of male violence against women, with the ribbon symbolizing "the idea of men giving up their arms." Commemorative demonstrations are held each year on December 6 across the country in memory of the slain women and numerous memorials have been assembled.



The Place du 6-Décembre-1989 in the Côte-des-Neiges/Notre-Dame-de-Grâce borough of Montreal was created as a memorial to the victims of the massacre. Located at the corner of Decelles Avenue and Queen Mary Road, a short distance from the university, it includes the art installation ''Nef pour quatorze reines'' (''Nave for Fourteen Queens'') by Rose-Marie Goulet. It is the site of annual commemorations on December 6.

A memorial erected in Vancouver sparked controversy because it was dedicated to "all women murdered by men", which critics say implies all men are potential murderers. As a result, women involved in the project received death threats and the Vancouver Park Board subsequently banned any future memorials that might "antagonize" other groups.

The event has also been commemorated through references in television, theatre, and popular music. A play about the shootings by Adam Kelly called ''The Anorak'' was named as one of the best plays of 2004 by the ''Montreal Gazette''. A movie entitled ''Polytechnique'', directed by Denis Villeneuve was released in 2009, and sparked controversy over the desirability of reliving the tragedy in a commercial film.

Additionally, several songs have been written about the events in different musical genres, including "Montreal" by rock band The Tragically Hip, "Montreal Massacre" by the death metal band Macabre, and "This Memory" by the folk duo the Wyrd Sisters. "Gunshow", the season ten premiere episode of ''Law & Order'', was based partly on this event and the Columbine shooting.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2e010be640901bca69a8fd705a712d3d" name="nef-detail" sectnum="7#1">../img/2e010be640901bca69a8fd705a712d3d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>