<document id="ee2c0a9a9257c740ea1269d084682ec6-3.6" name="Battle_of_Albuera" cat="29">
<text>
The musketry duel that developed between Colborne's brigade and Girard's left flank was so intense that both sides faltered. The French began to break, and were only kept in place by their officers beating them back with swords as they tried to retreat.  The left of Colborne's brigade, assailed by both musket fire and grapeshot from Girard's supporting guns, tried to force the issue with a bayonet charge but were unsuccessful. On the right Colborne's men continued to trade volleys with the French and, seeing their resolve wavering, also fixed bayonets and charged. and .


As the brigade moved forward a blinding hail- and rain-shower hit the battlefield, rendering both sides' muskets useless. describes the sudden shower, while  explains why muskets are useless in the wet.  Under cover of the reduced visibility Latour-Maubourg launched two Polish cavalry regiments at Colborne's exposed right flank. Ploughing through the unprepared British infantry, the 1st Vistula Uhlans and the 2nd Hussars virtually annihilated Colborne's first three regiments. Only the fourth, the 31st Regiment of Foot, was able to save itself by forming into square.  The cavalry pressed on against Colborne's supporting KGL artillery battery and captured its guns (although all but the howitzer were subsequently recovered)..

Having captured five regimental flags and eight cannon the Uhlans swept past the 31st's square, scattering Beresford and his staff, and attacked the rear of Zayas's line. claims six colours were taken, but then goes on to acknowledge that Lieutenant Latham saved the Buff's King's Colour and that the Uhlans only took the flagstaff.  Zayas met this assault unflinchingly while continuing to direct fire at Girard..  By this time the rainstorm had cleared and Lumley, commanding Beresford's horse, could finally make out the devastation caused by the French and Polish cavalry. He sent two squadrons of the 4th Dragoons to disperse the Uhlans, which they did, but the British troopers were in their turn driven off by a fresh hussar regiment that Latour-Maubourg had sent to cover the lancer's retreat..  Closing on the action, the 29th Regiment of Foot (the lead regiment of Stewart's second brigade) opened fire on the scattered Vistula lancers..  Most of this fusillade actually missed its intended targets and instead struck the rear ranks of Zayas's men. The Spaniards nevertheless stood firm; their actions very likely saved the allied army from destruction.

British sources state that the Polish cavalrymen refused to accept any surrender by the British infantry, and deliberately speared the wounded as they lay. Tradition reports that the British 2nd Division swore to give no quarter to Poles following Albuera. Of the 1,250 men lost by Colborne's first three regiments, 479 were taken prisoner.. This represents a rather low proportion of prisoners to total casualties; in a similar situation where French infantry squares were broken by cavalry, at the Battle of Garcia Hernandez, the French lost 200 killed and wounded, and 1,400 captured..
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="03c8093b6585604239705546c3d3ae76" name="Buffs" sectnum="3.6#1">../img/03c8093b6585604239705546c3d3ae76.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>