<document id="eebbd249f5cb214a731d364786cd3cbd-5" name="Three_Studies_for_Figures_at_the_Base_of_a_Crucifixion" cat="1">
<text>
Bacon often created second versions of his major paintings.Farr, Peppiatt, Yard (1999), 217--> In 1988, he completed a near-copy of the original ''Three Studies''. At 78 × 58 inches (198 × 147 cm), this second version is more than twice the size of the original, and the orange background has been replaced by a blood-red hue. The figures occupy a smaller proportion of the canvas than those of the 1944 version, a device which, according to the Tate Gallery's catalogue, "plung them into a deep void"."". Tate Gallery display caption, November 2005. Retrieved on 14 February, 2007. 

Critical opinion was mixed, and the 1988 triptych drew criticism from those who felt that its more refined painting technique robbed the image of much of its power.Hyman, James. "". James Hyman Fine Art, 2002. Retrieved on 14 February, 2007. Denis Farr suggested that while the second version's larger scale gave it "a majestic quality which is highly effective", its svelte presentation lessened its shock value.Farr, Peppiatt, Yard (1999), 217 Critic Jonathan Meades felt that while the 1988 triptych was a more polished and painterly work, it lacked the rawness of the original. Reflecting on Bacon's tendency to revisit subject matter, Meades observed that "Bacon's auto-plagiarism in areas other than portraiture had less deleterious consequences. Nonetheless the 1988 version (or near copy) of the great 1944 Crucifixion Triptych is the lesser work: it is slicker, more polished and it evinces a greater ease with paint. The backgrounds are now elaborated, defined and bereft of the garish, grating poison orange of 1944."Meades, Jonathan. "Raw, Embarrassing, Nihilistic". ''New Statesman'', 6 February, 1998. The art critic James Demetrion found that despite these differences, the second version still achieves the power and impact of the first.Davies, Yard (1986), 35
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="93512a62c29bf3c88263454ad13205fc" name="Second_Version_of_Triptych_1944" sectnum="5#1">../img/93512a62c29bf3c88263454ad13205fc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>