<document id="eebbd249f5cb214a731d364786cd3cbd-2" name="Three_Studies_for_Figures_at_the_Base_of_a_Crucifixion" cat="1">
<text>
The panels of ''Three Studies for Figures at the Base of a Crucifixion'' are painted on light Sundeala boards, a material Bacon was using at the time as an inexpensive alternative to canvas.Durham, Andrew. "Note on Technique", ''Francis Bacon, exh. cat.'', Tate Gallery, London, 1985. Each bears a single taut sculptural form pitched against a harsh orange background. The orange hue displays inconsistently across the canvasses, due in part to the low level of oil in the paint, which resulted in varying rates of absorption into the board. The pallid flesh tones of the figures were achieved by overlaying grey and white brushstrokes, while the figures' props were coloured using a variety of yellow, green, white, and purple tones.


The art critic Hugh Davies has suggested that of the three figures, that on the left most closely resembles a human form, and that it might represent a mourner at the cross.Davies, Yard (1986), 16 Seated on a table-like structure, this limbless creature has an elongated neck, heavily rounded shoulders, and a thick mop of dark hair. Like its sister objects, the left-hand figure is portrayed with layers of white and grey paint. The central figure's mouth is positioned directly on its neck, rather than on a distinct face.Kieran (2005), 185 It bares its teeth as if in a snarl, and is blindfolded by a drooping cloth bandage—a device likely drawn from Matthias Grünewald's ''Mocking of Christ''.Peppiatt (1996),  87 This creature faces the viewer directly and is centralised by a series of converging lines radiating from the base of the pedestal. 

Situated on an isolated patch of grass, the right-hand figure's toothed mouth is stretched open as if screaming, although David Sylvester has suggested that it may be yawning. Its mouth is open to a degree impossible for a human skull. The orange background of this panel is brighter than the hues rendered in the other frames, and the figure's neck opens up into a row of teeth, while a protruding ear juts out from behind its lower jaw. This panel closely resembles an earlier painting by Bacon, ''Untitled, c. 1943'', which was thought destroyed until it re-emerged in 1997.

Inspection under infrared has revealed that the panels were heavily reworked during a number of revisions.Despite Bacon's claim that they were spontaneously conceived. The legs of the central figure are surrounded by small magenta horseshoe shapes, which infrared shows to have been first drafted as flowers. The area below the head is thickly coated with white and orange paint, while the inspection exposes a series of underlying curved brushstrokes used to compose a landscape, and a small distant reclining figure. When the canvas is unframed, a number of measuring marks are visible on the outer margin of board, indicating that the composition was carefully conceived.

Bacon said in a 1959 letter that the figures in ''Three Studies'' were "intended to  use at the base of a large Crucifixion which I may still do."Sylvester (2000), 19 By this, Bacon implied that the figures were conceived as a predella to a larger altarpiece. The biographer Michael Peppiatt has suggested that the panels may have emerged as single works, and that the idea of combining them as a triptych came later. However, there is little in the themes or styles of the three panels to suggest that they were originally conceived as a whole. Though they share the same orange background, Bacon had already used this colour in two prior pieces; moreover, his ''oeuvre'' can be characterized by periods that are dominated by a single background colour. From the beginning of his career, Bacon preferred to work in series and found that his imagination was stimulated by sequences; as he put it, "images breed other images in me." 

The Crucifixion itself is conspicuously absent, and there is no trace or shadow of its presence in the panels. Writing in 1996, Wieland Schmied noted that the three Furies have replaced Christ and the two thieves crucified on either side of him.Schmied (1996), 76 The form of the Furies is borrowed directly from Picasso's late 1920s and mid-1930s pictures of biomorphs on beaches, in particular from the Spanish artist's ''The Bathers'' (1937).Bürger, Peter. In Zweite (2006), 30 However, the eroticism and comedy of Picasso's figures have been replaced by a sense of menace and terror derived in part from Matthias Grünewald's ''Mocking of Christ''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ad08c130e65e6bdae172b5bad1dd8c1f" name="Grünewald_Christ_Carrying_the_Cross-1" sectnum="2#1">../img/ad08c130e65e6bdae172b5bad1dd8c1f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>