<document id="ef0559d3419c3a5bdfa1467bfcea06bc-2" name="John_W._Johnston" cat="14">
<text>
Johnston served as commonwealth attorney for Tazewell County between 1844 and 1846. In 1846, he was elected to serve the remainder of the 1846–1847 term in the Virginia Senate, representing Tazewell, Wythe, Grayson, Smyth, Carroll, and Pulaski counties.Leonard, ''The General Assembly of Virginia'', 424. He was re-elected for the 1847–1848 session.Leonard, ''The General Assembly of Virginia'', 428.

During the Civil War, he held the position of Confederate States receiver, and was also elected as a councilman for the town of Abingdon in 1861.Summers, ''History of Southwest Virginia'', 648. Not much is known of his activities during the war, but he did send a letter to Brigadier-General John Echols that the Order of Heroes of America, was "growing fearfully" in southwest Virginia.''Official Records'', Series IV, V 3, p. 812, 816 This secret order was composed of Union sympathizers. This information was used in conjunction with other reports to request a suspension of ''habeas corpus'' so that the military could make arrests.

After the war, in 1867, he founded the Villa Maria Academy of the Visitation in Abingdon for the education of girls.Lang, ''Villa Maria Academy of the Visitation'', 1 He was judge of the Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery of Virginia in 1869–1870.Summers, ''History of Southwest Virginia'', 600. Also around 1869, he formed a law partnership with a young local attorney, and his future son-in-law, Daniel Trigg. In 1872, they set up their offices in a small building near the courthouse which became known as the Johnston-Trigg Law Office.King, ''Places in Time, Volume One'', 58

In November 1868, he wrote a letter to his daughter, which revealed that butter was scarce and that he doubted he would get a supply for the winter, but that "when we have spare ribs, sausages & crackilin bread, we can do without butter. The fact is I begin to consider butter a luxury anyhow, that poor people have no business with."John W. Johnston to Lavalette McMullen, November 6, 1868, LS, John W. Johnston Papers, Special Collections, Duke University
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="da3ed2287ef800a56dc00723c8d6b912" name="LewisSummersLawOffice" sectnum="2#1">../img/da3ed2287ef800a56dc00723c8d6b912.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>