<document id="ef0559d3419c3a5bdfa1467bfcea06bc-4.3" name="John_W._Johnston" cat="14">
<text>
On December 13, 1870, Thomas C. McCreery (D) of Kentucky introduced a resolution regarding the Arlington House, the former home of Robert E. Lee, that brought down a firestorm of objections.''Journal of the Senate'', December 13, 1870.; Johnston, ''Reminiscences of Thirteen Years in the Senate'', 14–23 The resolution called for an investigation to establish its ownership and the possibility of returning it to Mrs. Robert E. Lee. In addition, McCreery proposed the government fix up the premises, return any Washington relics discovered, and determine whether a suitable location nearby existed to relocate the dead.''Journal of the Senate'', December 13, 1870. Johnston described the excitement caused as the most pronounced he would see in his thirteen years in the Senate. It put him in "the most painful and embarrassing position of my life". and he was vehemently opposed:



However, in the course of the speeches opposing the resolution, Johnston felt General Lee's memory had been attacked and he felt duty bound to defend him. The Democratic Party, knowing his views and that of his state, approached him and asked him to keep silent for the sake of the party and the relief of Virginia. Johnston correctly predicted that he would be attacked at home.Johnston, ''Reminiscences of Thirteen Years in the Senate'', 24–25 He was up for re-election, and the opposing candidates used his position against him. A delegation from the Virginia General Assembly travelled to Washington to talk with the Democrats and assess the situation and were satisfied by the reports they received.Johnston, ''Reminiscences of Thirteen Years in the Senate'', 26

Later, Johnston made a speech on behalf of Mrs. Lee and her Memorial proposal. His first attempt to speak was objected to and he was denied permission.Johnston, ''Reminiscences of Thirteen Years in the Senate'', 41 Near the end of the session, when an unrelated bill was under discussion, Johnston made a motion related to it and then used the opportunity, which was allowed to Senators, to make his speech; this caused "great indignation and impatience on the floor".Johnston, ''Reminiscences of Thirteen Years in the Senate'', 42 The Lee family and their advisors desired that the "true facts about the sale of Arlington and the nature of her claim to the property, should be placed before the country"Johnston, ''Reminiscences of Thirteen Years in the Senate'', 27 so that, if found in her favor, she could receive compensation and then donate the property to the government.Johnston, ''Reminiscences of Thirteen Years in the Senate'', 30–31 Eventually the Supreme Court of the United States did find in the family's favor in 1882.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b63888c919b3e45531ebf142a35a5db4" name="Arlington_House_pre-1861" sectnum="4.3#1">../img/b63888c919b3e45531ebf142a35a5db4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>