<document id="ef642b1f151ea92c0bbdf03f7f439782-7" name="We_Are_the_World" cat="20">
<text>
Four months after the release of "We Are the World", USA for Africa had taken in almost $10.8 million. The majority of the money came from record sales within the US. Members of the public also donated money—almost $1.3 million within the same time period. In May 1985, USA for Africa officials estimated that they had sold between $45 million and $47 million worth of official merchandise around the world. Organizer Ken Kragen announced that they would not be distributing all of the money at once. Instead, he revealed that the foundation would be looking into finding a long-term solution for Africa's problems. "We could go out and spend it all in one shot. Maybe we'd save some lives in the short term but it would be like putting a Band-Aid over a serious wound." Kragen noted that experts had predicted that it would take at least 10 to 20 years to make a slight difference to Africa's long-term problems.

In June 1985, the first USA for Africa cargo jet carrying food, medicine and clothing departed for Ethiopia and the Sudan. It stopped ''en route'' in New York, where 15,000 T-shirts were added to the cargo. Included in the supplies were high-protein biscuits, high-protein vitamins, medicine, tents, blankets and refrigeration equipment. Harry Belafonte, representing the USA for Africa musicians, visited Sudan in the same month. The trip was his last stop on a four nation tour of Africa. In Africa, Belafonte was greeted and praised by Prime Minister Salim Ahmed Salim. Salim told the musician, "I personally and the people of Tanzania are moved by this tremendous example of human solidarity."

One year after the release of "We Are the World", organizers noted that $44.5 million had been raised for USA for Africa's humanitarian fund. They stated that they were confident that they would reach an initial set target of $50 million. By October 1986, it was revealed that their $50 million target had been met and exceeded; CBS Records gave USA for Africa a cheque for $2.5 million, drawing the total amount of money to $51.2 million. USA for Africa's Hands Across America event had also raised a significant amount of money—approximately $24.5 million for the hungry in the US.

Since its release, "We Are the World" has raised over $63 million for humanitarian causes. Ninety percent of the money was pledged to African relief, both long and short term. The long term initiative included efforts in birth control and food production. The remaining 10 percent of funds was earmarked for domestic hunger and homeless programs in the US. From the African fund, over 70 recovery and development projects were launched in seven African nations. Such projects included aid in agriculture, fishing, water management, manufacturing and reforestation. Training programs were also developed in the African countries of Mozambique, Senegal, Chad, Mauritania, Burkina Faso, Mali and Niger.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9240ac1f98f931a618e055f1c472bc14" name="Opbushel" sectnum="7#1">../img/9240ac1f98f931a618e055f1c472bc14.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>