<document id="ef6758327d43b64e0d1c084fca05028e-6" name="Port_Chicago_disaster" cat="29">
<text>
The Port Chicago Naval Magazine National Memorial was dedicated in 1994 to the lives lost in the explosion. The National Park Service (NPS) was directed to design and maintain the memorial.Department of the Interior. September 27, 2007. "". Retrieved on March 4, 2009. Congressman George Miller pushed for the memorial to be upgraded to national park status in 2002, in the knowledge that such status would help the site "become more competitive for federal funds to upgrade and enhance facilities and education materials".Congressman George Miller. March 11, 2002. "". Retrieved on March 4, 2009. This effort did not result in a change of status. In 2006, a local newspaper article highlighted the precarious position of the disused chapel within the grounds of the Concord Naval Weapons Station, a chapel that had been previously dedicated to the memory of those fallen in the explosion. The 1980 chapel was said by local historian John Keibel to be unsalvageable due to lead paint and its dilapidated condition. Keibel called attention to the stained glass windows which were crafted in 1991 as a tribute to the disaster, noting that they could be dismantled and remounted at the memorial site. In March 2008, NPS was directed by Congress to manage the memorial, after passage of a bill introduced in 2007 by Miller.110th Congress, 1st Session. House of Representatives. "". Retrieved on March 4, 2009. On July 10, 2008, Senator Barbara Boxer introduced legislation that would expand the memorial site by five acres (two hectares), if the land was judged safe for human health and was excess to the Navy's needs. The Port Chicago Naval Magazine National Memorial Enhancement Act of 2008 was not put to a vote.OpenCongress.org. 110th Congress, Second Session. "". Retrieved on March 4, 2009. On February 12, 2009, Miller introduced a similar bill entitled "Port Chicago Naval Magazine National Memorial Enhancement Act of 2009" which, in addition to calling for another five acres, allowed for the City of Concord and the East Bay Regional Park District "to establish and operate a facility for visitor orientation and parking, administrative offices, and curatorial storage for the Memorial."111th Congress, 1st Session. "". Retrieved on March 4, 2009. The bill remains under consideration.

The site is contained within an active military base and requires prior reservation in order to visit. Visitors are asked to allow 90 minutes per visit and are shuttled to the site in NPS vehicles from the Concord Naval Weapons Station Identification Office.National Park Service. Port Chicago Naval Magazine National Memorial. "". Retrieved on March 4, 2009.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8c07648625df6faba1c8ef92d0243e88" name="Port-Chicago-memorial" sectnum="6#1">../img/8c07648625df6faba1c8ef92d0243e88.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>