<document id="f09ad97b6a34bde31eed38267a3266d2-8" name="El_Hatillo_Municipality,_Miranda" cat="11">
<text>
The mountainous terrain and geographic features of El Hatillo have made it difficult to extend the Caracas Metro to southeast Caracas, so the main transportation methods in the municipality are private vehicles and road public transportation. An extension of the Metro—Line 5—has been proposed, but construction has not been initiated as of 2007; phase 2 of Line 4 is still under construction. Urban planning in the municipality has been unorganized; news archives show that at least since 1998, neighbors have been complaining about the dense traffic caused by new residential and commercial construction, yet new or enhanced alternative roads to resolve the traffic problems have not been completed. A south beltway suggested 25 years ago has not been constructed due to its high cost.   However, as of January 2006, a new route that will connect La Lagunita with Macaracuay—a neighborhood in northeast Caracas—is under construction and is planned to be completed in 2010; according to Mayor Catalán, 23% of El Hatillo's inhabitants will eventually use this transit way.  Its cost was estimated in early 2006 as US$19,572,000.   

Local solutions—such as the proposed Metro extension line and the road connecting La Lagunita and Macaracuay—may improve the traffic congestion around El Hatillo, but the traffic issue affects all of Caracas. It is estimated that one million vehicles transit Caracas daily, causing a collapse of the transportation network.    Automobiles travel at an average speed of 15 km/h (9 mph) on the streets and highways of Caracas.  There are numerous factors contributing to the traffic problem in Caracas. According to the Venezuelan Society of Transportation Engineers, a city should allocate 20% of its public area to transportation; in Caracas, less than 12% is allocated. In 2004, fifty thousand new vehicles were sold in Caracas. In 2005, sixty thousand more were sold, and as of November, 2006, seventy thousand more had been sold.  In five years, 250 thousand more cars are circulating in Caracas on roadways that have not increased proportionally to the increase in the number of cars.  Further, public transportation is not fully reliable; an average trip in the city using mass transit takes around ninety minutes.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="641c8b80eba8726aba19b04743125a45" name="Hatillo-street" sectnum="8#1">../img/641c8b80eba8726aba19b04743125a45.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>