<document id="f09ad97b6a34bde31eed38267a3266d2-5" name="El_Hatillo_Municipality,_Miranda" cat="11">
<text>
Venezuelan law specifies that municipal governments have four main functions:  executive, legislative, comptroller, and planning.  The executive function is managed by the mayor, who is in charge of representing the municipality's administration. The legislative branch is represented by the Municipal Council, composed of  seven councillors, charged with the deliberation of new decrees and local laws. The comptroller tasks are managed by the municipal comptroller's office, which oversees accountancy. Finally, planning is represented by the Local Public Planning Council, which manages development projects for the municipality.    

El Hatillo has had four mayors through 2008. Mercedes Hernández de Silva was the first mayor of the municipality, serving from 1993 until 1996. Succeeding her, Flora Aranguen was Mayor from 1996 until 2000. That same year, Alfredo Catalán was elected mayor and reelected in 2004. On November 23 Myriam Do Nascimento was elected mayor.

The 2007 president of the Municipal Council is Leandro Pereira, supported by the political party Justice First.  All but one of the seven councillors belong to political parties opposed to President Hugo Chávez's administration.   There is also a Legislative Commission, presided over by councillor Salvador Pirrone in 2007. The commission's job is to assist the municipality in legal matters, such as the creation of new laws and decrees.

On March 8, 2000—the year after a new constitution was introduced in Venezuela—it was decreed that the Metropolitan District of Caracas would be created, and that some of the powers of El Hatillo Municipality would be delegated to the ''Alcaldía Mayor'', which would also govern the Baruta, Libertador, Sucre and Chacao municipalities. Each of the five municipalities is divided into parishes; El Hatillo has only one, the Santa Rosalía de Palermo Parish, sometimes called Santa Rosalía de El Hatillo Parish or simply El Hatillo Parish.

In December 2006, as a part of a constitutional reform, Chávez proposed a reorganization of the municipal powers. Chávez mentioned his reform plans again in his January 2007 presidential inauguration, suggesting a new form of subdivision&mdash;communal cities&mdash;in which mayors and municipalities would be replaced by communal powers.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3bcd639e5f03c8ef58d1932f8395d4c2" name="El_Hatillo_City_Hall" sectnum="5#1">../img/3bcd639e5f03c8ef58d1932f8395d4c2.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>