<document id="f0a3a2b9f40487c74ff0bce9f820e993-6.5" name="Shaw_and_Crompton" cat="11">
<text>
The main Crompton War Memorial, located on the High Street, consists of a Scottish granite plinth surmounted by a large bronze statue flanked by two Rolls of Honour containing the 346 names of those from Shaw and Crompton who fought and died in World War I. Panels listing the Roll of Honour from World War II were added and unveiled on 12 November 1950 by Councillor H. M. Turner. Commissioned by the Crompton War Memorial Committee, the statue was conceptualised in 1919 by Richard Reginald Goulden, and unveiled on 29 April 1923 by General Sir Ian Hamilton. The original cost for the memorial alone was £4,000, but the total cost, including site and layout, was about £6,067.

The inscription on the memorial reads:

''In memory of the men of Crompton who fought and gave their lives to free mankind from the oppression and brutal tyranny of war. 1914–1919.''

The symbolic memorial depicts a group in which the central figure is a man defending the future generations, represented by young children, against foreign aggression, represented by a beast. The memorial is also a time capsule. Inside it is a lead casket containing coins, a copy of the local newspaper, three cops of spun cotton, and a length of cloth manufactured in the local area.

A second, smaller war memorial is located in Jubilee Gardens. It is dedicated to the soldiers who fought in the Second Boer War. It consists of a plaque built into a stone wall that is located between two large bushes.

Its inscription reads:
''In memory of the Crompton men who lost their lives in the South African war 1899–1902''

It then lists eight men: four who were "killed in action", two who "died of wounds", and two who "died of disease".

In 1995, to mark the 50th anniversary of the ending of the Second World War, a landmark known as The Shaw and Crompton Beacon was erected in Jubilee Gardens. 

The inscription on the plaque below reads:
''The Shaw and Crompton beaconerected by the Parish Council in 1995 tocommemorate the fiftieth anniversary ofthe ending of World War Twothis plaque was presented by members of the British Legion
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d2d6c71f4f72b5fc279d6109190c119d" name="Shaw_and_Crompton_Beacon" sectnum="6.5#1">../img/d2d6c71f4f72b5fc279d6109190c119d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>