<document id="f0daf67dcae9b0f1412e1c985da7ad0b-2.6" name="Anne_of_Denmark" cat="25">
<text>
In London, Anne adopted a cosmopolitan lifestyle, while James preferred to escape the capital, most often at his hunting lodge in Royston.Stewart, 181. Anne's chaplain, Godfrey Goodman, later summed up the royal relationship: "The King himself was a very chaste man, and there was little in the Queen to make him uxorious; yet they did love as well as man and wife could do, not conversing together".Stewart, 182:  'conversing together' in the now obsolete sense of ''living together'' Anne moved into Greenwich Palace and then Somerset House, which she renamed Denmark House. After 1607, she and James rarely lived together,Willson, 403. by which time she had borne seven children and suffered at least three miscarriages. After narrowly surviving the birth and death of her last baby, Sophia, in 1607, Anne’s decision to have no more children may have widened the gulf between her and James.Williams, 112.

The death of Prince Henry in 1612 at the age of eighteen, probably from typhoid, and the departure for Heidelberg of the sixteen-year-old Princess Elizabeth in April 1613, after marrying Elector Frederick V of the Palatine,Anne had originally objected to the match with Frederick, regarding it as beneath her dignity; and she did not attend the wedding at the Banqueting House in Whitehall, absent "as they say, troubled with the gout". Stewart, 247, 250; Williams, 154–156. further weakened the family ties binding Anne and James.Croft, 89. Henry's death hit Anne particularly hard; the Venetian ambassador was advised not to offer condolences to her "because she cannot bear to have it mentioned; nor does she ever recall it without abundant tears and sighs".Barroll, 134; The letter writer John Chamberlain suggested that Anne absented herself from the investiture of Charles as Prince of Wales four years later "lest she renew her grief by the memory of the last Prince". Stewart, 249. From this time forward, Anne’s health deteriorated, and she withdrew from the centre of cultural and political activities, staging her last known masque in 1614 and no longer maintaining a noble court.Croft, 89; Anne's ailments included gout, dropsy, arthritis and swollen feet. Williams, 159. Her influence over James visibly waned as he became openly dependent on powerful favourites.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="89df2141946d0aa8093f3d46f34b76a3" name="Eliz_bohemia_3" sectnum="2.6#1">../img/89df2141946d0aa8093f3d46f34b76a3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>