<document id="f0daf67dcae9b0f1412e1c985da7ad0b-2.5" name="Anne_of_Denmark" cat="25">
<text>
Observers regularly noted incidents of marital discord between Anne and James. The so-called Gowrie conspiracy of 1600, in which the young Earl of Gowrie, John Ruthven, and his brother Alexander Ruthven were killed by James's attendants for a supposed assault on the King, triggered the dismissal of their sisters Beatrix and Barbara Ruthven as ladies-in-waiting to Anne, with whom they were "in chiefest credit".Williams, 61–3; Barroll, 25. The Queen, who was five months pregnant,She gave birth to her second son, Charles, on the evening of 19 November 1600, at the same time as the Ruthven brothers' corpses were being hanged, drawn, and quartered. Williams, 66; Barroll, 26. refused to get out of bed unless they were reinstated and stayed there for two days, also refusing to eat. When James tried to command her, she warned him to take care how he treated her because she was not the Earl of Gowrie.James Melville, who witnessed the scene, wrote in his diary: "Foremost among those refraining to believe in the guilt of the two brothers was the Queen herself. She remained in her apartment and refused to be dressed for two days...Although the King receiving full information of his wife's conduct and of the consequences to be drawn from it, he could not be persuaded to take up the matter right, but sought by all means to cover his folly." Williams, 63. James placated her for the moment by paying a famous acrobat to entertain her,Williams, 63–4. but she never gave up, and her relentless support for the Ruthvens over the next three years was taken seriously enough by the government to be regarded as a security issue.Barroll notes a "politically relentless" streak in Anne. Barroll, 23. Anne, however, always promised she would never take part in any "practice" against James. Barroll, 28. In 1602, after discovering that Anne had smuggled Beatrix Ruthven into Holyrood, James carried out a cross-examination of the entire household;Barroll, 27; Williams, 64–65. in 1603, he finally caved in to Anne's campaign and granted Beatrix Ruthven a pension of £200."Because though her family is hateful on account of the abominable attempt against the King, she has shown no malicious disposition." Williams, 65.

A briefer confrontation occurred in 1613 when Anne shot James's favourite dog dead during a hunting session; after his initial rage, James smoothed things over by giving her a £2000 diamond in memory of the dog, whose name was Jewel.Williams, 164–5. In 1603, James fought with Anne over the proposed composition of her English household, sending her a message that "his Majesty took her continued perversity very heinously".Williams, 76. In turn, Anne took exception to James's drinking: in 1604 she confided to the French envoy, "the King drinks so much, and conducts himself so ill in every respect, that I expect an early and evil result".Croft, 56.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="229a7bc437d7c7a79373c43285142818" name="Anne_of_Denmark-1605" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/229a7bc437d7c7a79373c43285142818.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>