<document id="f0e703d20bd18ec26ceb07a9ab1d986c-3" name="Ernest_Joyce" cat="14">
<text>
When Shackleton was selecting the crew for his Antarctic expedition in ''Nimrod'', Joyce was one of his earliest recruits. The story that Shackleton saw Joyce on a bus that was passing his expedition offices, sent someone out to fetch him, and recruited him on the spot, is frequently told and possibly true.Riffenburgh, p. 125, Fisher, p. 127 and Huntford, p. 194, all tell this story. Fisher cites it to Shackleton biographer H R Mill, Huntford and Riffenbaugh say "so the story goes". To join the expedition, Joyce bought his release from the Navy, and in later years would claim that Shackleton had failed to recompense him for this, despite a promise to do so.Riffenburgh, p126 This was one of several disputes over money which eventually strained his relations with Shackleton.Tyler-Lewis, pp. 253&ndash;58, describes several of Joyce's financial claims He, Shackleton and Frank Wild were the only members of the expedition with previous Antarctic experience; on the basis of his ''Discovery'' exploits, Joyce was put in charge of general stores, sledges and dogs. Before departure in August 1907, he and Wild took a crash course in printing at Sir Joseph Causton's printing firm in Hampshire, as Shackleton intended to publish a book or magazine while in the Antarctic.Fisher, p. 121 

''Nimrod'' left New Zealand on 1 January 1908, and was towed towards the Antarctic pack ice by the tug ''Koonya''.Riffenburgh, pp. 143&ndash;45 On 23 January, now under her own power, she reached the Ross Ice Shelf (then known as the "Great Ice Barrier", or "Barrier"), where Shackleton planned to base his headquarters in an inlet discovered during the ''Discovery'' voyage. This proved impossible,This inlet, where Scott and Shackleton had taken balloon flights in February 1902, had greatly expanded, to become a bay &ndash; the Bay of Whales. This convinced Shackleton that the ice was not secure. Three years later Roald Amundsen would base his South Pole expedition there. and there being no feasible alternative landing site on nearby King Edward VII Land, Shackleton was forced to break an agreement he had made with Scott and take ''Nimrod'' to McMurdo Sound.Riffenburgh, pp. 110&ndash;16 The site finally chosen for a base was Cape Royds, some  north of Scott's old ''Discovery'' headquarters at Hut Point. During the extended, difficult process of unloading the ship Joyce remained ashore, looking after the dogs and ponies, and helping to build the expedition hut.Riffenburgh, p. 166, calls the process of unloading the stores and setting up the shore base "mind-numbingly difficult". This was due to a combination of adverse weather and the alleged over-caution of Nimrod's captain, Rupert England. See Riffenburgh, pp. 157&ndash;67 In March he assisted the party that made the first successful ascent of Mount Erebus, although he did not make the climb himself.Mills, p. 62

During the following winter Joyce, with Wild's help, printed copies of the expedition book ''Aurora Australis'', edited by Shackleton.About 25 or 30 copies of the book were printed, sewn and bound, according to Mills, p. 65 &ndash; some sources say more. Copies still in existence are worth huge sums. In 1988 a facsimile edition was published by SeTo Publishing, New Zealand. Otherwise he was busy preparing equipment and stores for the next season's journey to the Pole in which, in view of his experience, he fully expected to be included. However, various mishaps had reduced the number of ponies to four, so Shackleton cut the southern party to that number. One of those dropped was Joyce, on advice from expedition doctor Eric Marshall, who noted that Joyce had a liver problem and the early stages of heart disease.Riffenburgh, p. 191Wild, who was one of the four who made the southern journey, later wrote in his diary after the party's bid to reach the Pole had failed: "if we only had Joyce and Marston here instead of these two useless grub-scoffing beggars" &ndash; (referring to Marshall and Jameson Adams) &ndash; "we would have done it easily." Wild, p. 96 Joyce showed no particular resentment; he assisted the preparatory work and accompanied the polar party on the southward march for the first seven days.Riffenburgh, p. 201 In the following months he took charge of enhancing the depots, to ensure adequate supplies for the returning southern party. He deposited a special cache of luxuries at Minna Bluff, together with life-saving food and fuel, earning Wild's spontaneous praise.Riffenburgh, pp. 216&ndash;18

Shackleton and his party returned safely, on ''Nimrod's'' last feasible date for sailing home. They had established a new Farthest South at 88°23&prime;S, only 97 geographical miles (112 statute miles, 180 km) from the South Pole. Joyce had been ready to remain at the base with a rearguard, to wait for the party or to establish its fate if it did not return.Riffenburgh, p. 274 ''Nimrod'' finally reached London in September 1909 and was prepared, under Joyce's direction, as a floating exhibition of polar artefacts. Shackleton paid him a salary of £250 a year for this (2008 equivalent approx. £18,000),
a generous amount for the time. Thereafter Joyce, in the absence of regular paid employment, looked for another expedition.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="64d39d8f031312f2d5fa90ec9cca1f6d" name="Bay_of_Whales_broad" sectnum="3#1">../img/64d39d8f031312f2d5fa90ec9cca1f6d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>