<document id="f1214b16dd1c8085ffaeb5fc89780a2e-1" name="Ælle_of_Sussex" cat="25">
<text>
Ælle, if he existed, lived in the middle of the least-documented period in English history of the last two millennia.For example, James Campbell writes: "The natural vice of historians is to claim to know about the past.  Nowhere is this claim more dangerous than when it is staked in Britain between AD 400 and 600" (''The Anglo-Saxons'', p. 20).  By the early fifth century Britain had been Roman for over three hundred and fifty years.  The most troublesome enemies of Roman Britain were the Picts of central and northern Scotland, and the Gaels known as Scoti, who were raiders from Ireland. Also vexatious were the Saxons, the name Roman writers gave to the peoples who lived in the northern part of what is now Germany and the southern part of the Jutland peninsula.  Saxon raids on the southern and eastern shores of England had been sufficiently alarming by the late third century for the Romans to build the Saxon Shore forts, and subsequently to establish the role of the Count of the Saxon Shore to command the defence against these incursions.  Roman control of Britain finally ended in the early part of the fifth century; the date usually given as marking the end of Roman Britain is 410, when the Emperor Honorius sent letters to the British, urging them to look to their own defence.  Britain had been repeatedly stripped of troops to support usurpers' claims to the Roman empire, and after 410 the Roman armies never returned.Hunter Blair, ''An Introduction'', pp. 1–14.Campbell et al., ''The Anglo-Saxons'' pp. 13–16.

Sources for events after this date are extremely scarce, but a tradition, reported as early as the mid sixth century by a British priest named Gildas, records that the British sent for help against the barbarians to Aetius, a Roman consul, probably in the late 440s.  No help came.  Subsequently (and Gildas's information here is supplemented by other, later sources, such as the Anglo-Saxon Chronicle), a British leader named Vortigern is supposed to have invited continental mercenaries to help fight the Picts who were attacking from the north.  The leaders, whose names are recorded as Hengest and Horsa, rebelled, and a long period of warfare ensued.  The invaders&mdash;Angles, Saxons, Jutes, and Frisians&mdash;gained control of parts of England, but lost a major battle at Mons Badonicus (the location of which is not known).  Some authors have speculated that Ælle may have led the Saxon forces at this battle, while others reject the idea out of hand.

The British thus gained a respite, and peace lasted at least until the time Gildas was writing: that is, for perhaps forty or fifty years, from around the end of the fifth century until midway through the sixth.Hunter Blair, ''An Introduction'', pp. 13–16.Campbell et al., ''The Anglo-Saxons'' p. 23. Shortly after Gildas's time the Anglo-Saxon advance was resumed, and by the late sixth century nearly all of southern England was under the control of the continental invaders.Hunter Blair (''Roman Britain'', p. 204) gives the twenty-five years from 550 to 575 as the dates of the final conquest.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="54798737adcdd7187d3961c37da28dac" name="Ella_-_John_Speed" sectnum="1#1">../img/54798737adcdd7187d3961c37da28dac.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>