<document id="f1d8deb2f01716e709aba61388c2e7b7-5.4" name="Velociraptor" cat="3">
<text>
Fossils of dromaeosaurids more primitive than ''Velociraptor'' are known to have had feathers covering their bodies, and fully developed, feathered wings. The fact that the ancestors of ''Velociraptor'' were feathered and possibly capable of flight long suggested to paleontologists that ''Velociraptor'' bore feathers as well, since even flightless birds today retain most of their feathers.

In September 2007, researchers found quill knobs on the forearm of a ''Velociraptor'' found in Mongolia. These bumps on bird wing bones show where feathers anchor, and their presence on ''Velociraptor'' indicate it too had feathers. According to paleontologist Alan Turner, 



Co-author Mark Norell, Curator-in-Charge of fossil reptiles, amphibians and birds at the American Museum of Natural History, also weighed in on the discovery, saying:



According to Turner and co-authors Norell and Peter Makovicky, quill knobs are not found in all prehistoric birds, and their absence does not mean that an animal was not feathered – flamingos, for example, have no quill knobs. However, their presence confirms that ''Velociraptor'' bore modern-style wing feathers, with a rachis and vane formed by barbs. The forearm specimen on which the quill knobs were found (specimen number IGM 100/981) represents an animal 1.5 meters in length (5 ft) and 15 kilograms (33 lbs) in weight. Based on the spacing of the six preserved knobs in this specimen, the authors suggested that ''Velociraptor'' bore 14 secondaries (wing feathers stemming from the forearm), compared with 12 or more in ''Archaeopteryx'', 18 in ''Microraptor'', and 10 in ''Rahonavis''. This type of variation in the number of wing feathers between closely related species, the authors asserted, is to be expected, given similar variation among modern birds.

Turner and colleagues interpreted the presence of feathers on ''Velociraptor'' as evidence against the idea that the larger, flightless maniraptorans lost their feathers secondarily due to larger body size. Furthermore, they noted that quill knobs are almost never found in flightless bird species today, and that their presence in ''Velociraptor'' (presumed to have been flightless due to its relatively large size and short forelimbs) is evidence that the ancestors of dromaeosaurids could fly, making ''Velociraptor'' and other large members of this family secondarily flightless, though it is possible the large wing feathers inferred in the ancestors of ''Velociraptor'' had a purpose other than flight. The feathers of the flightless ''Velociraptor'' may have been used for display, for covering their nests while brooding, or for added speed and thrust when running up inclined slopes.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="11984bacc7f55bbbfdef5f6724376d36" name="Velociraptor_dinoguy2" sectnum="5.4#1">../img/11984bacc7f55bbbfdef5f6724376d36.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>