<document id="f1d8deb2f01716e709aba61388c2e7b7-1" name="Velociraptor" cat="3">
<text>
''Velociraptor'' was a mid-sized dromaeosaurid, with adults measuring up to  long,  high at the hip, and weighing up to . The skull, which grew up to  long, was uniquely up-curved, concave on the upper surface and convex on the lower. The jaws were lined with 26&ndash;28 widely spaced teeth on each side, each more strongly serrated on the back edge than the front—possibly an adaptation that improved its ability to catch and hold fast-moving prey.

''Velociraptor'', like other dromaeosaurids, had a large manus ('hand') with three strongly curved claws, which were similar in construction and flexibility to the wing bones of modern birds. The second digit was the longest of the three digits present, while the first was shortest. The structure of the carpal (wrist) bones prevented pronation of the wrist and forced the 'hands' to be held with the palmar surface facing inwards (medially), not downwards. The first digit of the foot, as in other theropods, was a small dewclaw. However, whereas most theropods had feet with three digits contacting the ground, dromaeosaurids like ''Velociraptor'' walked on only their third and fourth digits.  The second digit, for which ''Velociraptor'' is most famous, was highly modified and held retracted off of the ground. It bore a relatively large, sickle-shaped claw, typical of dromaeosaurid and troodontid dinosaurs. This enlarged claw, which could be over  long around its outer edge, was most likely a predatory device used to tear into prey, possibly delivering a fatal blow.

Long bony projections (prezygapophyses) on the upper surfaces of the vertebrae, as well as ossified tendons underneath, stiffened the tail of ''Velociraptor''. The prezygapophyses began on the tenth tail (caudal) vertebra and extended forward to brace four to ten additional vertebrae, depending on position in the tail. The stiffening forced the entire tail to act as a single rod-like unit, preventing vertical motion between vertebrae. However, at least one specimen preserves a series of intact tail vertebrae curved sideways into an ''S''-shape, suggesting that there was considerably more horizontal flexibility. These adaptations of the tail probably provided balance and stability while turning, especially at high speeds.

In 2007, paleontologists reported the discovery of quill knobs on a well-preserved ''Velociraptor mongoliensis'' forearm from Mongolia, confirming the presence of feathers in this species.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e6741a18b89e00c507da63e591414815" name="Velociraptor_BW" sectnum="1#1">../img/e6741a18b89e00c507da63e591414815.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>