<document id="f1d8deb2f01716e709aba61388c2e7b7-2" name="Velociraptor" cat="3">
<text>
An American Museum of Natural History expedition to the Outer Mongolian Gobi Desert in 1922 recovered the first ''Velociraptor'' fossil known to science: a crushed but complete skull, associated with one of the raptorial second toe claws (AMNH 6515). In 1924, museum president Henry Fairfield Osborn designated the skull and claw (which he assumed to come from the hand) as the type specimen of his new genus, ''Velociraptor''. This name is derived from the Latin words ''velox'' ('swift') and ''raptor'' ('robber' or 'plunderer') and refers to the animal's cursorial nature and carnivorous diet. Osborn named the type species ''V. mongoliensis'' after its country of origin. Earlier that year, Osborn had mentioned the animal in a popular press article, under the name "Ovoraptor djadochtari" (not to be confused with the similarly named ''Oviraptor''). However, because the name "Ovoraptor" was not published in a scientific journal or accompanied by a formal description, it is considered a ''nomen nudum'' ('naked name'), and the name ''Velociraptor'' retains priority.

While North American teams were shut out of communist Mongolia during the Cold War, expeditions by Soviet and Polish scientists, in collaboration with Mongolian colleagues, recovered several more specimens of ''Velociraptor''. The most famous is part of the legendary "Fighting Dinosaurs" specimen (GIN 100/25), discovered by a Polish-Mongolian team in 1971. This fossil preserves a single ''Velociraptor'' in the midst of battle against a lone ''Protoceratops''. This specimen is considered a national treasure of Mongolia, although in 2000 it was loaned to the American Museum of Natural History in New York City for a temporary exhibition.

Between 1988 and 1990, a joint Chinese-Canadian team discovered ''Velociraptor'' remains in northern China.  American scientists returned to Mongolia in 1990, and a joint Mongolian-American expedition to the Gobi, led by the American Museum of Natural History and the Mongolian Academy of Sciences, turned up several well-preserved skeletons. One such specimen, IGM 100/980, was nicknamed "Ichabodcraniosaurus" by Norell's team because the fairly complete specimen was found without its skull (an allusion to the Washington Irving character Ichabod Crane).Novacek, M. (1996). ''Dinosaurs of the Flaming Cliffs'', Anchor Books. This specimen may belong to ''Velociraptor mongoliensis'', but Norell and Makovicky concluded that it was not complete enough to say for sure, and it awaits a formal description.

Maxillae and a lacrimal (the main tooth-bearing bones of the upper jaw, and the bone that forms the anterior margin of the eye socket, respectively) recovered in 1999 by the Sino-Belgian Dinosaur Expeditions were found to pertain to ''Velociraptor'', but not to the type species ''V. mongoliensis''.  Pascal Godefroit and colleagues named these bones ''V. osmolskae'' (for Polish paleontologist Halszka Osmólska) in 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="26733dacc68bcc58926ea783eb0b8954" name="Velociraptor_mongoliensis_type_skull_and_jaws" sectnum="2#1">../img/26733dacc68bcc58926ea783eb0b8954.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>