<document id="f1e7b1e399714181aaa6069cfa545da8-2.1" name="Gwen_Stefani" cat="20">
<text>
Eric introduced Gwen to 2 Tone music by Madness and The Selecter, and in 1986 he invited her to provide vocals for No Doubt, a ska band he was forming. Finally, in 1991, the band was signed to Interscope Records. She also did backup vocals for Sublime on the song "Saw Red", notably before either No Doubt's breakthrough success in 1995 or Sublime's the following year.


The band released its self-titled debut album in 1992, but its ska-pop sound was unsuccessful due to the popularity of grunge.Bush, John. . Allmusic. Retrieved April 14, 2007. Stefani rejected the aggressiveness of female grunge artists and cited Blondie singer Debbie Harry's combination of power and sex appeal as a major influence.Strauss, Neil. . ''Rolling Stone''. January 31, 2002. Retrieved April 17, 2007. No Doubt's third album, ''Tragic Kingdom'' (1995), which followed the self-released ''The Beacon Street Collection'' (1995), took more than three years to make. During this time, the band almost split up because of the failed romantic relationship between Stefani and bandmate Tony Kanal.Ali, Lorraine. . ''Newsweek''. 2004. Retrieved April 17, 2007. Their break-up inspired Stefani lyrically, and many of the album's songs, such as "Don't Speak", "Sunday Morning", and "Hey You", chronicle their relationship and her happiness.. CHUM Limited. July 19, 2005. Retrieved January 25, 2007. Five singles were released from ''Tragic Kingdom'' and "Don't Speak" led 1996's U.S. year-end airplay chart.. Rock on the Net. Retrieved April 17, 2007. Stefani left college for one semester to tour for ''Tragic Kingdom'' but did not return when touring lasted two and a half years. The album sold more than 16 million copies worldwide, and received several Grammy Award nominations.. CNN. January 6, 1998. Retrieved April 30, 2007.

No Doubt released the less popular ''Return of Saturn'' in 2000, which expands upon the New Wave influences of ''Tragic Kingdom''.Erlewine, Stephen Thomas. . Allmusic. Retrieved April 27, 2007. Most of the lyrical content focuses on Stefani's often rocky relationship with then-Bush frontman Gavin Rossdale and her overall insecurities, including indecision on settling down and having a child.Willman, Chris. . ''Entertainment Weekly'', issue 539. May 12, 2000. Retrieved April 27, 2007. The band's 2001 album, ''Rock Steady'', explores more reggae and dancehall sounds while maintaining the band's New Wave influences, generally receiving positive reviews.Cinquemani, Sal. , which was recorded live by Guy Charbonneau (audio recording engineer)'s Le Mobile Remote Recording Studio and later released on CD and DVD formats.Guy Charbonneau="discography..rock steady" . ''Slant Magazine''. 2004. Retrieved April 30, 2007. The album generated career-highest singles chart positions in the United States,. Allmusic. Retrieved April 17, 2007. and "Hey Baby" and "Underneath It All" received Grammy Awards. A greatest hits collection, ''The Singles 1992–2003'', which includes a cover of Talk Talk's "It's My Life", was released in 2003 to moderate sales. 

Outside No Doubt, Stefani has collaborated on the singles "South Side" and "Let Me Blow Ya Mind" with Moby and Eve, respectively. In 2002 Eve and Stefani won a Grammy Award for Best Rap/Sung Collaboration for "Let Me Blow Ya Mind".Armor, Jerry. . Yahoo! Music News. February 28, 2002. Retrieved April 30, 2007. She also collaborated with The Brian Setzer Orchestra on a cover of "You're the Boss", originally performed by Elvis Presley and Ann-Margret, for its 1998 album ''The Dirty Boogie''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f7eaa37f77dc824cc849a9ab39de8834" name="Gwen-Stefani" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/f7eaa37f77dc824cc849a9ab39de8834.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>