<document id="f20a2f9af69ec89480eb94e3b6c9dcba-8" name="Æthelberht_of_Kent" cat="25">
<text>
There is little documentary evidence about the nature of trade in Æthelberht’s Kent.  It is known that the kings of Kent had established royal control of trade in the late seventh century, but it is not known how early this control began.  There is archaeological evidence that suggests that the royal influence predates any of the written sources.  It has been suggested that one of Æthelberht’s achievements was to take control of trade away from the aristocracy and to make it a royal monopoly.  The continental trade provided Kent access to luxury goods which gave Kent an advantage in trading with the other Anglo-Saxon nations and the revenue from trade was important in itself.Yorke, ''Kings and Kingdoms'', p. 40.

Kentish manufacture before 600 included glass beakers and jewelry. Kentish jewellers were highly skilled and before the end of the sixth century they gained access to gold.  Goods from Kent are found in cemeteries across the channel, and as far away as at the mouth of the Loire.  It is not known what Kent traded for all of this wealth, although it seems likely that there was a flourishing slave trade.  It may well be that this wealth was the foundation of Æthelberht’s strength, although his overlordship and the associated right to demand tribute, would have brought wealth in its turn.

It may have been during Æthelberht’s reign that coins first began to be minted in England: none bear his name, but it is thought likely that the first coins predate the end of the sixth century.  These early coins were gold, and probably were the shillings (''scillingas'' in Old English) that are mentioned in Æthelberht’s laws.  The coins are also known to numismatists as "thrymsas".”Coinage”, M.A.S. Blackburn, in Lapidge, ''Encyclopaedia of Anglo-Saxon England''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="885d1855d2b40e0009ceabcf339f3ab8" name="Eadbaldobv.1" sectnum="8#1">../img/885d1855d2b40e0009ceabcf339f3ab8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>