<document id="f265b60b59c83e1f2545925331f4aa9e-2" name="The_Philadelphia_Inquirer" cat="19">
<text>
John Norvell left the ''Aurora & Gazette'' and his job as editor because he disagreed with what he felt was the newspaper's editorial approval of a movement towards a European class system. When Norvell and John Walker founded ''The Inquirer'' they wanted the newspaper to represent all people and not just the higher classes. The newly launched newspaper supported Jeffersonian democracy and President Andrew Jackson, and it declared support for the right of the minority's opinion to be heard. A legend about the founding of ''The Inquirer'' states that Norvell  said, "There could be no better name than ''The Inquirer''. In a free state, there should always be an inquirer asking on behalf of the people: 'Why was this done? Why is that necessary work not done? Why is that man put forward? Why is that law proposed? Why? Why? Why?'"

When Norvell and Walker sold their newspaper to Jesper Harding, Harding kept the paper close to the founder's politics and backed the Democratic Party. However, disagreeing with Andrew Jackson's handling of the Second Bank of the United States he began supporting the anti-Jackson wing of the Democrats. During the 1836 Presidential election Harding supported the Whig party candidate over the Democratic candidate and afterwards ''The Inquirer'' became known for its support of Whig candidates. Before the American Civil War began, ''The Inquirer'' supported the preservation of the Union, and was critical of the antislavery movement which many felt was responsible for the Southern succession crisis. Once the war began ''The Inquirer'' maintained an independent reporting of the war's events. However ''The Inquirer'' firmly supported the Union side. At first ''The Inquirer'''s editors were against emancipation of the slaves, but after setbacks by the Union army ''The Inquirer'' started advocating a more pro-war and pro-Republican stance. In a July 1862 article ''The Inquirer'' wrote "in this war there can be but two parties, patriots and traitors."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ce6f863b1e08c4b3b5d2673108388e37" name="Inquirerbldg_sign" sectnum="2#1">../img/ce6f863b1e08c4b3b5d2673108388e37.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>