<document id="f26503293185bb6fd5bd415e4279b171-1.5" name="John_Frusciante" cat="20">
<text>
Frusciante wrote and recorded a plethora of songs during and after the ''By the Way'' tour. In February 2004, he started a side project with Joe Lally of Fugazi and Josh Klinghoffer, called Ataxia. The group was together for about two weeks, during which they recorded about ninety minutes of material. After two days in the recording studio, they played two shows at the Knitting Factory in Hollywood, and spent two more days in the studio before disbanding. Later that year, five songs provided by Frusciante appeared on ''The Brown Bunny'' soundtrack.''The Brown Bunny soundtrack'' liner notes.

 

Frusciante released his fourth full-length solo album ''Shadows Collide with People'' on February 24, 2004. This featured guest appearances from some of his friends, including Klinghoffer, and Chili Peppers bandmates Smith and Flea.''Shadows Collide with People'' liner notes In June 2004, he announced that he would be releasing six records over six months:Devenish, Colin. (June 29, 2004) "". ''Rolling Stone'', Retrieved on August 27, 2007. ''The Will to Death'', Ataxia's ''Automatic Writing'', ''DC EP'', ''Inside of Emptiness'', ''A Sphere in the Heart of Silence'' and ''Curtains''. With the release of ''Curtains'' Frusciante debuted his only music video of 2004, for the track "The Past Recedes". He wanted to produce these records quickly and inexpensively on analog tape, avoiding modern studio and computer-assisted recording processes.Payne, John. (July 29, 2004) "". ''LA Weekly'', Retrieved on August 27, 2007.

In early 2005, Frusciante entered the studio to work on his fifth studio album with the Chili Peppers, ''Stadium Arcadium''. His guitar playing is dominant throughout the album, and he provides backing vocals on most of the tracks. Although usually following a "less is more" style of guitar playing,Walker, James.  www.purpleradio.co.uk. Retrieved on 2007-06-25 he began using a full twenty-four track mixer for maximum effect.''Stadium Arcadium'' bonus DVD footage In the arrangements, he incorporates a wide array of sounds and playing styles, from the funk-influenced ''Blood Sugar Sex Magik'' to the more melodic ''By the Way''. He also changed his approach to his playing, opting to contribute solos and allow songs to be formed from jam sessions. Several reviews have stressed that the influence of Hendrix is evident in his solos on the album, with Frusciante himself backing this up.  He also expanded the use of guitar effects throughout the album, and used various other instruments such as  the synthesizer and mellotron. He worked continuously with Rubin over-dubbing guitar progressions, changing harmonies and using all his technical resources.

Frusciante began a series of collaborations with friend Omar Rodriguez-Lopez and his band The Mars Volta, by contributing vocals and electronic instrumentation to their album ''De-Loused in the Comatorium''.''De-Loused in the Comatorium'' liner notes He also contributed guitar solos on their 2005 album ''Frances the Mute''.''Frances the Mute'' liner notes In 2006, he helped The Mars Volta complete their third album ''Amputechture'' by playing guitar on seven of its eight tracks.''Amputechture'' liner notes In return, Rodriguez-Lopez has played on several of Frusciante's solo albums, as well as made a guest appearance on ''Stadium Arcadium''.''Curtains'' liner notes''Stadium Arcadium'' liner notes
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f893986ad8857c929532cabc3015bbbf" name="John_Frusciante_2" sectnum="1.5#1">../img/f893986ad8857c929532cabc3015bbbf.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>