<document id="f265b60b59c83e1f2545925331f4aa9e-1.3" name="The_Philadelphia_Inquirer" cat="19">
<text>
In 1969 Annenberg was offered US$55 Million for ''The Inquirer'' by Samuel Newhouse, but having earlier promised John S. Knight the right of first refusal of any sale offer, Annenberg sold it to Knight instead. ''The Inquirer'', along with the ''Philadelphia Daily News'', became part of Knight Newspapers and its new subsidiary, Philadelphia Newspapers Inc. Five years later, Knight Newspapers merged with Ridder Publications to form Knight Ridder.

When ''The Inquirer'' was bought, it was understaffed, its equipment was outdated, many of its employees were underskilled and the paper trailed its chief competitor, the ''Evening Bulletin'', in weekday circulation. However, Eugene L. Roberts Jr., who became ''The Inquirer'''s executive editor in 1972, turned the newspaper around.  Between 1975 and 1990 ''The Inquirer'' won seventeen Pulitzers, six consecutively between 1975 and 1980, and more journalism awards than any other newspaper in the United States. ''Time'' magazine chose ''The Inquirer'' as one of the ten best daily newspapers in the United States, calling Roberts' changes to the paper, "one of the most remarkable turnarounds, in quality and profitability, in the history of American journalism." By July 1980 ''The Inquirer'' had become the most circulated paper in Philadelphia, forcing the ''Evening Bulletin'' to shut down two years later. ''The Inquirer'''s success was not without hardships. Between 1970 and 1985 the newspaper experienced eleven strikes, the longest lasting forty-six days in 1985. ''The Inquirer'' was also criticized for covering "Karachi better than Kensington". This did not stop the paper's growth during the 1980s, and when the ''Evening Bulletin'' shut down, ''The Inquirer'' hired seventeen ''Bulletin'' reporters and doubled its bureaus to attract former ''Bulletin'' readers. By 1989 Philadelphia Newspapers Inc.'s editorial staff reached a peak of 721 employees.

The 1990s saw gradually dropping circulation and advertisement revenue for ''The Inquirer''. The decline was part of a nationwide trend, but the effects were exacerbated by, according to dissatisfied ''Inquirer'' employees, the paper's resisting changes that many other daily newspapers implemented to keep readers and pressure from Knight Ridder to cut costs. During most of Roberts's time as editor, Knight Ridder allowed him a great deal of freedom in running the newspaper. However, in the late 1980s, Knight Ridder had become concerned about ''The Inquirer'''s profitability and took a more active role in its operations. Knight Ridder pressured ''The Inquirer'' to expand into the more profitable suburbs, while at the same time cutting staff and coverage of national and international stories. Staff cuts continued until Knight Ridder was bought in 2006, with some of ''The Inquirer'''s best reporters accepting buyouts and leaving for other newspapers such as ''The New York Times'' and ''The Washington Post''. By the late 1990s, all of the high level editors who had worked with Eugene Roberts in the 1970s and 80s had left, none at normal retirement age. Since the 1980s, the paper has won just one Pulitzer, a 1997 award for "Explanatory Journalism." In 1998 ''Inquirer'' reporter Ralph Cipriano filed a libel suit against Knight Ridder, ''The Philadelphia Inquirer'', and ''Inquirer'' editor Robert Rosenthal over comments Rosenthal made about Cipriano to ''The Washington Post''. Cipriano had claimed that it was difficult reporting negative stories in ''The Inquirer'' about the Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Philadelphia and Rosenthal later claimed that Cipriano had "a very strong personal point of view and an agenda...He could never prove ." The suit was later settled out of court in 2001.

Knight Ridder was bought by rival The McClatchy Company in June 2006. ''The Inquirer'' and the ''Philadelphia Daily News'' were among the twelve less-profitable Knight Ridder newspapers that McClatchy put up for sale when the deal was announced in March. On June 29, 2006, ''The Inquirer'' and ''Daily News'' were sold to Philadelphia Media Holdings LLC, a group of Philadelphian area business people, including Brian P. Tierney, Philadelphia Media's chief executive. The new owners planned to spend US$5 million on advertisements and promotions to increase ''The Inquirer'''s profile and readership. 

In the years following Philadelphia Media Holding's acquisition, ''The Inquirer'' has seen larger than expected revenue losses, mostly from national advertising, and continued loss of circulation. The revenue losses have caused management to cut four hundred jobs at ''The Inquirer'' and ''Daily News'' in the three years since the papers were bought. On August 21, 2007, Philadelphia Media Holdings announced that it was selling The Inquirer Building in a plan to help pay off the debts incurred when buying the newspapers. Despite efforts to cut costs, Philadelphia Newspapers LLC, filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection on February 21, 2009. Philadelphia Media Holdings is about US$390 million in debt due to money borrowed to buy ''The Inquirer'' and ''Daily News''. In May 2009, Brian Tierney suggested that the paper, in conjunction with its sister publication the ''Philadelphia Daily News'' and their shared web site Philly.com, would launch an online paid-content model by the end of the year.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a71ceb832aeb851b7c8d2bca2dc1892e" name="Inquirerbldgfull" sectnum="1.3#1">../img/a71ceb832aeb851b7c8d2bca2dc1892e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>