<document id="f280ed595fef45748ba1ce7a52deae4e-5" name="Stede_Bonnet" cat="14">
<text>
By the end of August, news had reached Charleston that Bonnet's vessels were moored in the Cape Fear River. Robert Johnson, governor of South Carolina, authorized Colonel William Rhett to lead a naval expedition against the pirates, even though the Cape Fear River was in North Carolina's jurisdiction. After a false start due to the appearance of another pirate ship near Charleston, Rhett arrived at the mouth of the Cape Fear River on September 26 with two eight-gun sloops and a force of 130 men.Butler (2000), p65. Bonnet initially mistook Rhett's squadron for merchantmen and sent three canoes to capture them.Seitz (2002), p136–137. Unfortunately for Rhett, his flagship ''Henry'' had run aground in the river mouth, enabling Bonnet's canoe crews to approach, recognize the heavily armed and manned sloops as hostile and return uninjured to warn Bonnet. The sun had set by the time the rising tide lifted the ''Henry'' off the river bottom.Seitz (2002), p137.

The 46 pirates were scattered among the three sloops. During the night, Bonnet brought all of them aboard the ''Royal James'' and planned to fight his way out to sea in the morning rather than risk the Cape Fear River's narrow channels in the dark. Bonnet also wrote a letter to Governor Johnson, threatening to burn all the ships in Charleston harbor. At daybreak, on September 27, 1718, Bonnet set sail toward Rhett's force, and all three sloops opened fire, initiating the Battle of Cape Fear River. The two South Carolinian sloops split up in an effort to bracket the ''Royal James''. Bonnet tried to avoid the trap by steering the ''Royal James'' close to the river's western shore, but ran aground in the process. Rhett's closing sloops also ran aground, leaving only the ''Henry'' in range of the ''Royal James''.Johnson (1724), pp97–99.

The battle was at a stalemate for the next five or six hours, with all the participants immobilized. Bonnet's men had the advantage that their deck was heeled away from their opponents, giving them cover, while the ''Henry'''s deck was tilted toward the pirates, thus exposing Rhett's men to punishing musket volleys. Bonnet's force suffered twelve casualties while killing ten and wounding fourteen of Rhett's 70-man crew. Most of Bonnet's men fought enthusiastically, challenging their enemies to board and fight hand to hand, and tying a knot in their flag as a mock signal to come aboard and render aid. Bonnet himself patrolled the deck with a pistol drawn, threatening to kill any pirate who faltered in the fight. Nevertheless, some of the prisoners who had been forced to join the pirate crew refused to fire on Rhett's men, and one narrowly escaped death at Bonnet's hands in the confusion of the engagement.Tryals (1719), pp18–19.Johnson (1724), p99.Butler (2000), p66.

The battle was ultimately decided when the rising tide lifted Rhett's sloops free while temporarily leaving the ''Royal James'' stranded. Bonnet was left helpless, watching while the enemy vessels repaired their rigging and closed to board his paralyzed vessel. Outnumbered almost three to one, Bonnet's men would have had little hope of winning a boarding action. Bonnet ordered his gunner, George Ross, to blow up the ''Royal James's'' powder magazine. Ross apparently attempted this, but was overruled by the remainder of the crew, who surrendered. Rhett arrested the pirates and returned to Charleston with his prisoners on October 3.Johnson (1724), pp99–100.Tryals (1719), p18.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="16dc451c371ec8c8c4d9a5629583fa2a" name="Stede-Bonnet-Monument_Charleston-SC" sectnum="5#1">../img/16dc451c371ec8c8c4d9a5629583fa2a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>