<document id="f2c2350d0f017ab0074b4e50633af682-11" name="Lethbridge" cat="11">
<text>
Mass transit in Lethbridge consists of 40 buses (with an average age of 10 years) operating on more than a dozen routes. Traditionally, bus routes in the city started and ended downtown. In the early 21st century, however, Lethbridge Transit introduced cross-town and shuttle routes, such as University of Lethbridge to Lethbridge College, University of Lethbridge to the North Lethbridge terminal, and Lethbridge College to the North Lethbridge terminal. Several routes converge near the Chinook Regional Hospital, although it is not officially a terminal.

The Parks and Recreation department maintains the citywide, 30-kilometre (19 mi) pedestrian/cyclist Coal Banks Trail system (). The system was designed to connect the Oldman River valley with other areas of the city, including Pavan Park in the north, Henderson Lake in the east, Highways 4 and 5 in the south and a loop in West Lethbridge (including University Drive and McMaster Blvd).

Four provincial highways (3, 4, 5, and 25) run through or terminate in Lethbridge. This has led to the creation of major arterial roads, including Mayor Magrath Drive, University Drive and Scenic Drive. This infrastructure and its location on the CANAMEX Corridor has helped make Lethbridge and its freight depots a major shipping destination. Lethbridge is 100 kilometres (62 mi) north of the United States border via Highways 4 and 5 and 210 kilometres (130 mi) south of Calgary via Highways 2 and 3. Highways 2, 3 and 4 form part of the CANAMEX trade route between Mexico, the United States, and Canada.

Lethbridge is near the Lethbridge County Airport and the CPR rail yards in Kipp, Alberta. The rail yards were moved to Kipp, just west of the city, from downtown Lethbridge in 1983 to make way for commercial expansion., The Virtual Crowsnest Highway. Accessed December 26, 2006. The county airport provides commercial flights to Calgary and Edmonton, as well as private and charter flights elsewhere. The airport provides customs services for flights arriving from the United States.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8731ddc7f3f8aa054f02163e97060d53" name="Lethbridge_Transit" sectnum="11#1">../img/8731ddc7f3f8aa054f02163e97060d53.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>