<document id="f2cddd116b495c6e31a23cf1340bfc3b-5" name="Early_life_of_Keith_Miller" cat="26">
<text>
At the start of the 1936&ndash;37 season, Miller was selected for the Colts, a state under-21 team that played at district level. At the end of the 1936 school year, Miller completed year 10 by passing five of his eight subjects. Disinclined towards university studies, he left school without finishing his leaving year and began working as a clerk for a car business. Miller felt confident that he could make a career out of sport and therefore felt that further education was unnecessary.Perry, p. 30.

Miller spent the 1937&ndash;38 season with the Colts and won the team's batting trophy for having the best average; he made 340 runs at 42.50. Across the entire competition, Miller had the eighth highest average. He scored three half-centuries and a 102 against Northcote.Perry, p. 32. At this stage, Miller was a solid, slow and steady batsman, who accumulated his runs gradually, but ''The Age'' predicted that his physical growth would open his horizons, opining "Once he fills out&mdash;he is rather tall for his weight&mdash;Miller should become a brilliant, aggressive batsman".Perry, p. 31. In early February 1938, late in the summer, he made his first-class debut for Victoria as an 18-year-old and hit 181 in 289 minutes against Tasmania at the Melbourne Cricket Ground. With his increased power, Miller began to loft the ball over the infield and struck five fours. During the 1938&ndash;39 season, he rejoined South Melbourne and played four first-class matches for Victoria, scoring 125 runs at an average of 25.00. However, Miller was yet to play in the Sheffield Shield competition, only taking to the field in one-off matches against other teams. In the two matches against Tasmania in December 1938, Miller took his first catch, but managed only four, seven not out and three, and he spent a period of time outside the team. Miller was recalled in March 1939&mdash;late in the season&mdash;for two matches against Western Australia in Perth, scoring 111 runs at 37.00, notching his first first-class fifty of the season in the second innings of the first match.

Miller achieved more success as a footballer. In 1937, he followed his brothers Les and Ray and joined the Brighton Football Club in the Victorian Football Association (VFA). The VFA was the second tier of Australian rules football below the Victorian Football League (VFL). A defender, Miller played his first two seasons on the flanks; he was yet to reach his physical peak and lacked the power required to play in central defensive positions until his third season, in 1939. At this stage, he was unable to hip and shoulder his opponents and relied on his running ability and accurate kicking.Perry, p. 33.


During the 1939&ndash;40 season, Miller was selected to make his Sheffield Shield debut in a match against South Australia at Adelaide Oval.Perry, p. 35. Batting at No. 4, Miller came to the crease at 2/9 after a top-order collapse, but managed only four runs before being caught by Richard Whitington&mdash;with whom he later wrote cricket books&mdash;from the bowling of Harold Cotton. When Victoria fielded, Miller ran out his future ''Invincibles'' captain Don Bradman; it was the first time that Bradman had been caught short of his ground in first-class cricket.Perry, p. 36.Whitington, p. 50. Miller also took his first catch at Shield level, that of Mervyn Waite. In the second innings, he managed seven before being bowled by  leg spinner Clarrie Grimmett,Perry, p. 37. one of the leading bowlers in the world in the 1930s. One of Miller's teammates was Percy Beames, who also happened to be his manager at Vacuum Oil, where he had moved from his first job. Miller made 41 and 47 not out in his second match against Queensland, top-scoring in the second innings as his team completed a seven-wicket victory. Miller retained his place for the match against New South Wales, but was out for 14 in both innings. He had difficulties against leg spin, falling to Bill O'Reilly and Cec Pepper.Perry, p. 38. In the return match against South Australia, Miller decided to take the initiative against Grimmett, charging down the wicket to drive the leg spinner. He featured in a 165-run partnership with Hassett, and at times bluffed Grimmett by moving forward before leaning back after the bowler had adjusted his length. Miller reached 108 to complete his first century in Shield competition. He was given out caught by Bradman from Garth Burton, after an appeal for a disputed catch; Miller asked the umpires if Bradman had caught a bump ball.Perry, p. 39. Nevertheless, Bradman praised Miller's innings,Perry, p. 40. and Clem Hill predicted a bright future for the Victorian. Apart from the century, Miller had an average season, making 37, 1 and 24 in his remaining innings to end the campaign with 298 runs at 29.80. He did not bowl during the season.Perry, p. 43.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5dde2b54342bd85a509818f20f7242cf" name="Young_miller_drive" sectnum="5#1">../img/5dde2b54342bd85a509818f20f7242cf.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>