<document id="f2d3c13138758f223fe1c277f56f242d-2" name="Issy_Smith" cat="29">
<text>
The 1st Manchester Regiment, stationed in India, sailed from Karachi for France on 29 August 1914 as the constituent British battalion of the Jullundur Brigade, 3rd (Lahore) Indian Division. The battalion disembarked at Marseilles in late September, but was not deployed to the front until 26 October 1914, when it occupied trenches east of Festubert.James p 96Mileham, p 85

Actively engaged in the battles of Givenchy and Neuve Chapelle, the 1st Manchesters had incurred hundreds of casualties by the beginning of "Second Ypres" on 22 April 1915.Mileham, p 92 Chemical warfare first emerged on the Western Front during the German offensive, and Smith himself would be temporarily incapacitated by gas. The 1st Manchesters were involved in an initially successful counter-attack conducted by the Jullundur and Ferozepore brigades on 26 April 1915, near Wieltje, in conjunction with other  Allied units.Wyrall, p 122 Rudimentary forms of protection against the chlorine gas proved ineffectual, limiting the advance and causing many soldiers to succumb to its effects. 

During the Allied counter-attack, Smith, of his own volition, ventured towards a German position to attend to a severely wounded soldier. He carried him some  to relative safety while exposed to intense German fire. According to the Victoria Cross citation, he brought in "many more wounded men" throughout the day under similarly perilous conditions "regardless of personal risk". Recounting his own rescue by Smith to a Daily Mail correspondent, Sergeant Rooke said of the corporal: "He behaved with wonderful coolness and presence of mind the whole time, and no man deserved a Victoria Cross more thoroughly than he did".


Smith was hospitalised in Dublin, where he recuperated from his gassing. His Victoria Cross was later presented to him at Buckingham Palace by King George V.Jewish Chronicle, 11 February 1916, p 8 Feted by publications such as the Jewish Chronicle, Smith's status as a recipient of the VC was utilised by the British government for the purposes of stimulating further recruitment.Cesarani, p 118 His visits to Jewish communities in the United Kingdom generated much interest, attracting dignitaries and large crowds in the process. On one such occasion, in September 1915, he was invited back to his old school in the East End to receive a gold watch and chain in honour of his Victoria Cross from his former schoolmates.''The Times'', 6 September 1915; pg. 11; Issue 40952; col D Also that month, Smith was received at Mansion House, Dublin by the Under-Secretary for Ireland, Matthew Nathan, who took advantage of the occasion to reaffirm loyalty to both Britain and Ireland.Keogh, p 69 Contemporaries, however, continued to report instances of discrimination against Jewish servicemen, including an incident involving Issy Smith in Leeds.Jewish Chronicle, 22 October 1915, p 5 While documenting his recruitment drive, the Jewish Chronicle reported that the proprietor of the Grand Restaurant had refused to serve Smith during his tour of Yorkshire because he was Jewish, while indicating the staff were prepared to accept his non-Jewish acquaintance.Jewish Chronicle, 22 October 1915, p 13 Smith's tour continued without disruption, taking him to Edinburgh, Scotland. 

Meanwhile, on the Western Front, the demoralised and depleted Indian Corps fought its final European battle at Loos.Omissi, , bbc.co.uk. Accessed 15 August 2007. With the exception of two cavalry divisions, the Indian Corps in Europe redeployed to the Middle East theatre, sailing from Marseilles on 10 December, 1915 and arriving in Basra on 8 January 1916 to be integrated into the Mesopotamian Expeditionary Force. Smith returned to active duty as a sergeant, serving in Mesopotamia and Palestine until the cessation of hostilities with the Ottoman Empire and Germany on 30 October and 11 November respectively. He had been wounded five times.

Demobilised after the war, Smith returned to London. As a war hero, he was intermittently invited to social functions. In June 1920, he attended a garden party at Buckingham Palace, given by the king for all surviving Victoria Cross recipients. They included veterans of the Indian Mutiny, Rorke's Drift, Relief of General Gordon, the First and Second Boer Wars, countless campaigns on the borders of the empire, and dozens from the Great War.''The Times'', 28 June 1920; pg. 19; Issue 42448; col B In October 1921, with  Harry Kenny VC, he unveiled the Hackney War Memorial.''The Times'', 15 September 1921; pg. 5; Issue 42826; col G In 1922, he attended "The Pilgrimage to Ypres", in Belgium, laying a wreath at the Cloth Hall there.''The Times'', 31 July 1922; pg. 12; Issue 43097; col A
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2f90e952fc7926f24b9835de67a92a4b" name="Victoria_Cross_Medal_Ribbon_%26_Bar" sectnum="2#1">../img/2f90e952fc7926f24b9835de67a92a4b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>