<document id="f3128071d6d92c6b28a5d4cb4f8b4630-8" name="Peterborough" cat="11">
<text>
The City of Peterborough (including its outlying villages) is the birthplace of many notable people, including the astronomer George Alcock MBE, one of the most successful visual discoverers of novas and comets; Journal of the British Astronomical Association, vol.111 no.2 (pp.64-66) February 2001. John Clare, from Helpston, now considered to be one of the most important poets of the nineteenth century;Robinson, Eric H.  ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography'' Oxford University Press, 2004 (subscription required , retrieved 10 September 2007). artist, Christopher Perkins;Collins, R. D. J.  ''Dictionary of New Zealand Biography'' vol.4 Auckland University Press, 1998. and Sir Henry Royce, 1st Baronet of Seaton, engineer and co-founder of Rolls-Royce.Jeremy, David J.  ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography'' Oxford University Press, 2004 (subscription required , retrieved 10 September 2007). Physician, actor and author, Sir John Hill, credited with 76 separate works in the Dictionary of National Biography, the most valuable of which dealing with botany, is also said to have been born in Peterborough.O'Connor, Barry  ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography'' Oxford University Press, 2004 (subscription required , retrieved 30 September 2007). The socialist writer and illustrator, Frank Horrabin, who was born in the city, was elected its member of parliament in 1929.Cole, Margaret  (rev. Amanda L. Capern) ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography'' Oxford University Press, 2004 (subscription required , retrieved 06 October 2007).

The utilitarian philosopher, Richard Cumberland, was 14th Lord Bishop of Peterborough from 1691 until his death in 1718;Parkin, Jon  ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography'' Oxford University Press, 2004 (subscription required , retrieved 30 September 2007). and Norfolk-born nurse and humanitarian, Edith Cavell, who received part of her education at Laurel Court in the Minster Precinct, is commemorated by a plaque in the Cathedral and by the name of the hospital.Daunton, Claire  ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography'' Oxford University Press, 2004 (subscription required , retrieved 30 April 2007). Two prominent historical figures were born locally, Hereward the Wake, an outlaw who led resistance to the Norman Conquest and now lends his name to several places and businesses in Peterborough;Mellows, William Thomas (ed.) ''The Peterborough Chronicle of Hugh Candidus'' (p.41) Peterborough Natural History, Scientific and Archæological Society, 1941. and St. John Payne, one of the group of prominent Catholics martyred between 1535 and 1679 and later designated the Forty Martyrs of England and Wales, who was beatified by Pope Leo XIII in 1886 and canonised with the other 39 by Pope Paul VI in 1970. ''Omelia del Santo Padre Paolo VI'' The Holy See, 25 October 1970.

Musicians include Sir Thomas Armstrong, organist, conductor and former principal of the Royal Academy of Music;Stoker, Richard  ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography'' Oxford University Press, 2004 (subscription required , retrieved 24 April 2007). Andy Bell, lead vocalist of the electronic pop duo Erasure;, ''BBC News Online'', 10 February 2003. Barrie Forgie, leader of the BBC Big Band;, Vinyl Vulture (retrieved 24 April 2007). Don Lusher OBE, trombonist and former professor of the Royal College of Music and the Royal Marines School of Music;Voce, Steve  (obituary), ''The Independent'', London, 7 July 2006. Paul Nicholas, actor and singer; Internet Movie Database (retrieved 24 April 2007). Keith Palmer, better known as Maxim Reality, MC with dance act The ProdigyMontalbano, Dan  ''The Independent'', London, 31 August 2006. &mdash; Graham 'Gizz' Butt, who played live guitar with The Prodigy, lives in the area &mdash; Nigel Sixsmith, keytar player and founder member of The Art Of Sound; SoundClick (retrieved 24 April 2007). Skins actor Luke Pasqualino;Reinis, Nick, , ''Peterborough Evening Telegraph'', 22 January 2009.. Jonathan Gill (Arishay) and his fellow bandmate Aston Merrygold, who is lead singer of The X Factor (Series 5) runners-up JLS are also from Peterborough., ''Peterborough Evening Telegraph'', 27 October 2008.

Other living personalities include television presenter, Sarah Cawood, who grew up in Maxey;, ''Liverpool Daily Post'', 3 February 2004. and BBC presenter Jake Humphrey was born in the city., ''Peterborough Evening Telegraph'', 4 August 2009. Adrian Durham, football journalist and radio broadcaster;Kirby, Terry. , ''The Independent'', London, 31 August 2006. and biologist, author and broadcaster, Prof. Brian J. Ford, who attended the King's School and still lives in Eastrea near Whittlesey.Pearson, Mark , ''Peterborough Evening Telegraph'', 7 October 2005 (facsimile of p.23 from the Brian J. Ford Website, retrieved 24 April 2007). Local businessman Peter Boizot MBE OMRI, founder of the Pizza Express restaurant chain, has supported the cultural and sporting life of Peterborough and received its highest accolade, the freedom of the city.Muir, Jonny , ''Peterborough Evening Telegraph'', 4 October 2007. Peterborough City Council, 29 February 2008. Tottenham Hotspur and England footballer, David Bentley, was born in the city;, ESPNsoccernet (retrieved 27 May 2007). and Stoke City midfielder, Matthew Etherington, started his career in the youth academy at Peterborough United;, Football Database (retrieved 24 April 2007). in the same team was Simon Davies, with whom Etherington made a joint transfer to Tottenham Hotspur., Football Database (retrieved 18 August 2008). Former England goalkeeper, David Seaman MBE, also first began to make a name for himself while at the club., ''The Guardian'', London, 14 January 2004. Motorcycle racer, Craig Jones, lived in city until his death after a high-speed crash at Brands Hatch;, ''Peterborough Evening Telegraph'', 4 August 2008. as does Louis Smith, who in 2008 became Great Britain's first gymnast to win an individual Olympic medal in a century. ''BBC News Online'', 17 August 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="db7b4eaa9bff9a699fcd80130882f155" name="Cecilsr" sectnum="8#1">../img/db7b4eaa9bff9a699fcd80130882f155.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>