<document id="f3128071d6d92c6b28a5d4cb4f8b4630-2.4" name="Peterborough" cat="11">
<text>
From 1889 the ancient Soke of Peterborough formed an administrative county in its own right with boundaries similar, although not identical, to the current unitary authority.Under the Local Government Act 1888 (51 & 52 Vict. c.41). The area however remained geographically part of Northamptonshire until 1965, when the Soke of Peterborough was merged with Huntingdonshire to form the county of Huntingdon and Peterborough.The Huntingdon and Peterborough Order 1964 (SI 1964/367), see Local Government Commission for England (1958&ndash;1967), ''Report and Proposals for the East Midlands General Review Area (Report No.3)'', 31 July 1961 and ''Report and Proposals for the Lincolnshire and East Anglia General Review Area (Report No.9)'', 7 May 1965. Following a review of local government in 1974, Huntingdon and Peterborough was abolished and the current district created by the merger of the Municipal Borough of Peterborough with Peterborough Rural District, Barnack Rural District, Thorney Rural District, Old Fletton Urban District and part of the Norman Cross Rural District, which had each existed since 1894.Under the Local Government Act 1894 (56 & 57 Vict. c.73). This became part of the non-metropolitan county of Cambridgeshire.Under the Local Government Act 1972 (1972 cap.70), see  (SI 1972/2039) Part 5: County of Cambridgeshire. Letters patent were granted which continued the style of the city over the greater area.Issued under the Great Seal of the Realm dated 25 June 1974, see the . In 1998 the city became autonomous of Cambridgeshire county council as a unitary authority, but it continues to form part of that county for ceremonial purposes. (SI 1996/1878), see Local Government Commission for England (1992), ''Final Recommendations for the Future Local Government of Cambridgeshire'', October 1994 and ''Final Recommendations on the Future Local Government of Basildon & Thurrock, Blackburn & Blackpool, Broxtowe, Gedling & Rushcliffe, Dartford & Gravesham, Gillingham & Rochester upon Medway, Exeter, Gloucester, Halton & Warrington, Huntingdonshire & Peterborough, Northampton, Norwich, Spelthorne and the Wrekin'', December 1995. The leader and cabinet model of decision-making, first adopted by the city council in 2001, is similar to national government.Under the Local Government Act 2000 (2000 cap.22), see  Department for Environment, Transport and the Regions, February 2001.

Policing in the city remains the responsibility of Cambridgeshire Constabulary; and firefighting, the responsibility of Cambridgeshire Fire and Rescue Service. Nowadays the Peterborough Volunteer Fire Brigade, one of few of its kind, effectively functions as a retained fire station.Walton, Jemma , ''Peterborough Evening Telegraph'', 26 July 2007. The Royal Anglian Regiment serves as the county regiment for Cambridgeshire. Peterborough formed its first territorial army unit, the 6th Northamptonshire Rifle Volunteer Corps, in 1860., ''Peterborough Evening Telegraph'', 3 April 2008.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a4b75fe3a712ef0ecabd389ffee51155" name="PB_TownHall" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/a4b75fe3a712ef0ecabd389ffee51155.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>