<document id="f3128071d6d92c6b28a5d4cb4f8b4630-1.2" name="Peterborough" cat="11">
<text>
Railway lines began operating locally during the 1840s, but it was the 1850 opening of the Great Northern Railway's main line from London to York that transformed Peterborough from a market town to an industrial centre. Lord Exeter had opposed the railway passing through Stamford, so Peterborough, situated between two main terminals at London and Doncaster, increasingly developed as a regional hub.Brooks, John  (p.12) The Welland Partnership and Jarrold Publishing, Norwich, 2004.
 
Coupled with vast local clay deposits, the railway enabled large-scale brick-making and distribution to take place. The area was the UK's leading producer of bricks for much of the twentieth century. Brick-making had been a small seasonal craft since the early nineteenth century, but during the 1890s successful experiments at Fletton using the harder clays from a lower level had resulted in a much more efficient process.Davies (pp.23-24). The dominance of London Brick in the market during this period gave rise to some of the country's most well-known landmarks, all built using the ubiquitous Fletton. Hanson Building Products, 2007. Perkins Engines was established in Peterborough in 1932 by Frank Perkins, creator of the Perkins diesel engine. Thirty years later it employed more than a tenth of the population of Peterborough, mainly at Eastfield.Baker, Anne Pimlott. "Perkins, Francis Arthur (1889–1967)". ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography'', Oxford University Press, 2004.. Baker Perkins had relocated from London to Westwood, now the site of HMP Peterborough, in 1903, followed by Peter Brotherhood to Walton in 1906; both manufacturers of industrial machinery, they too became major employers in the city.Davies (pp.26-27). British Sugar remains headquartered in Woodston, although the beet sugar factory, which opened there in 1926, was closed in 1991., British Sugar (retrieved 5 January 2008).

Designated a New Town in 1967, Peterborough Development Corporation was formed in partnership with the city and county councils to house London's overspill population in new  townships sited around the existing urban area.Under the New Towns Act 1965 (1965 cap.59) cf.  (SI 1988/1410), the designation was made on 21 July 1967, see the . There were to be four townships, one each at Bretton, Orton, Paston/Werrington and Castor. The last of these was never built, but a fourth, called Hampton, is now taking shape south of the city. It was decided that the city should have a major indoor shopping centre at its heart. Planning permission was received in late summer 1976 and Queensgate, containing over 90 stores and including parking for 2,300 cars, was opened by Queen Beatrix of the Netherlands in 1982. 34 miles (55 km) of urban roads were planned and a network of high-speed roads, known as parkways, was constructed.Hancock, Tom ''Greater Peterborough Master Plan'' Peterborough Development Corporation, 1971. 

Peterborough's population grew by 45.4% between 1971 and 1991. New service-sector companies like Thomas Cook and Pearl Assurance were attracted to the city, ending the dominance of the manufacturing industry as employers. An urban regeneration company named Opportunity Peterborough, under the chairmanship of Lord Mawhinney, was set up by the Office of the Deputy Prime Minister in 2005 to oversee Peterborough's future development., ''Peterborough Evening Telegraph'', 2 March 2005. Between 2006 and 2012 a £1 billion redevelopment of the city centre and surrounding areas is planned. The master plan provides guidelines on the physical shaping of the city centre over the next 15–20 years. Proposals are already progressing for the north of Westgate, the south bank and the station quarter, where Network Rail is preparing a major mixed use development., Peterborough City Council, East of England Development Agency and English Partnerships, February 2005. Whilst recognising that the reconfiguration of the relationship between the city and station was critical, English Heritage found the current plans for Westgate unconvincing and felt more thought should be given to the vitality of the historic core., Historic Buildings and Monuments Commission for England and Commission for Architecture and the Built Environment, 16 March 2006.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="71782af66da0ee94c4762c79954e4969" name="Front_of_Burghley_House_2009" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/71782af66da0ee94c4762c79954e4969.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>