<document id="f3128071d6d92c6b28a5d4cb4f8b4630-6.12" name="Peterborough" cat="11">
<text>
Peterborough enjoys a wide range of events including the annual East of England Show, Peterborough Festival and CAMRA beer festival, which takes place on the river embankment in late August. English Tourist Board (retrieved 20 April 2007).

The Key Theatre, built in 1973, is situated on the embankment, next to the River Nene. The theatre aims to provide entertainment, enlightenment and education by reflecting the rich culture Peterborough has to offer. The programme is made up of home-grown productions, national touring shows, local community productions and one-off concerts. There is disabled access, an infrared hearing system for the deaf and hard of hearing and there are also regular signed performances.
''The Key Times'' is the theatre's newspaper, available free of charge from the last Saturday of each month. In 1937 the Odeon Cinema opened on Broadway, where it operated successfully for more than half a century. In 1991 the Odeon showed its last film to the public and was left to fall into a state of disrepair, until 1997, when a local entrepreneur purchased the building as part of a larger project, including a restaurant and art gallery. The Broadway, designed by Tim Foster Architects, was one of the largest theatres in the region and offered a selection of live entertainment, including music, comedy and films., ''Peterborough Evening Telegraph'', 18 April 2001. In January 2009, it was severely damaged by arsonists, resulting in closure when its insurers refused to pay the claim due to faulty fire detection systems.Baker, Marie, , ''Peterborough Evening Telegraph'', 26 January 2009. The Embassy Theatre, now a public house, also opened here in 1937, later becoming a cinema., Cannon Cinema, Peterborough, 1987. The John Clare Theatre within the new central library, again on Broadway, is home to the Peterborough Film Society. One of the region's leading venues, The Cresset in Bretton, provides a wide range of events for the residents of the city and beyond, including theatre, comedy, music and dance. Peterborough has a 13-screen Showcase Cinema, an ice rink and two indoor swimming pools open to the general public. A diverse range of restaurants can be found throughout the city, including Chinese & Cantonese, Indian & Nepalese, Thai and many Italian restaurants. In the closing months of 2006, Polish, Japanese and Mexican restaurants were all opened.

A regional magazine, Art and Soul, encouraging the arts and local music was started in 2007. The magazine covers many aspects of the Peterborough arts and music scene, including organising gigs in the city., Art and Soul Magazine (retrieved 19 January 2009). Peterborough has recently been used as the setting for two popular novels, ''A Short History of Tractors in Ukrainian'' by Marina Lewycka 2005 shortlist title ''A Short History of Tractors in Ukrainian'' by Marina Lewycka (336 pp. Viking, London, 2005) Orange Home UK (retrieved 26 January 2008). and ''A Spot of Bother'' by Mark Haddon.Ness, Patrick  (review of ''A Spot of Bother'' by Mark Haddon, 390 pp. Jonathan Cape, London, 2006), ''The Guardian'', London, 26 August 2006.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5cf1673db0839239bfee6cdd44f51214" name="RAH_frieze,_Peterborough_Cathedral" sectnum="6.12#1">../img/5cf1673db0839239bfee6cdd44f51214.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>