<document id="f3128071d6d92c6b28a5d4cb4f8b4630-5.9" name="Peterborough" cat="11">
<text>
Peterborough is home to one of the largest concentrations of Italian immigrants in the UK. This is mainly as a result of labour recruitment in the 1950s by the London Brick Company in the southern Italian regions of Puglia and Campania. By 1960 approximately 3,000 Italian men were employed by London Brick, mostly at the Fletton works.Colpi, Terry ''The Italian Factor: The Italian Community in Great Britain'' (p.149) Mainstream Publishing, Edinburgh, 1991. In 1962 the Scalabrini Fathers, who first arrived in 1956, purchased an old school and converted it into a church named after the patron saint of workers San Giuseppe. By 1991 over 3,000 christenings of second-generation Italians had been carried out there.Colpi (p.235). The population of Peterborough has grown much faster than the national average over the last few years, mainly as a result of immigration. In the late twentieth century the main source of immigration has been from Commonwealth countries such as India and Pakistan. A more recent issue is that an unknown number of eastern Europeans from accession states have moved to Peterborough since 2004. This may mean that the population figures, based on the 2001 census, are an underestimate. Cambridgeshire County Council, June 2003. The East of England Regional Assembly estimate that 16,000 eastern Europeans are now living in the city, one in ten of the population.Reid, Sue , ''The Mail on Sunday'', London, 24 August 2006. Modern Peterborough is a rapidly developing city and one that continues to change. The change has not been without problems however. In May 2004 groups of Pakistani residents clashed with Afghan and Iraqi asylum seekers. In the "running street battles," houses and cars were set alight and windows were smashed. Some people were hospitalised. The fighting occurred in the multicultural Millfield area of the city., ''BBC News Online'', 20 May 2004. In July of that year, a festival set up by the Indian community to celebrate the city's diversity turned violent. Pakistanis and Iraqis clashed over the weekend, leaving a man in hospital and large gangs fighting., ''BBC News Online'', 26 July 2004. Since then, race relations have improved significantly. 

East Anglia is the leading destination for new migrants and half of the 83,000 who have registered to work in the region have settled in Cambridgeshire. According to a report published by the police in 2007 "the hidden scale of migration into the county is demonstrated by the different number of languages officers and staff deal with, which now exceeds 100. Translation costs linked to dealing with incidents and crime are close to £1 million a year." The report says the migrant communities have led to a change in the nature of crime in the county, with an increase in drink-driving offences, knife crime and an international dimension added to activities such as running cannabis factories and human trafficking. The number of foreign nationals arrested in the north of the county rose from 894 in 2003 to 2,435 in 2006, but the report also says "inappropriately negative" community perceptions about migrant workers often complicate routine incidents, raising tensions and turning them "critical;" the fact that many new migrants are crowded into privately rented accommodation, often in multiple occupation, is a potentially destabilising factor in many communities, raising problems of noise, parking, waste disposal, petty robbery, household disputes and assaults against women in mixed houses., Cambridgeshire Constabulary and Cambridgeshire Police Authority, 19 September 2007. Julie Spence OBE, the Chief Constable, was careful to add there was "little evidence that the increased numbers of migrant workers have caused significant or systematic problems in respect of community safety or cohesion." She also emphasised that the dramatic change in the county's profile &mdash; from a rural county in which four years ago 95% of teenagers were white to one of the country's major ethnically mixed growth points &mdash; has had a positive impact in development and jobs. Cambridgeshire's population is one of the fastest growing in Britain and is projected to rise by a further 12.5% or 94,000 by 2016, mostly fulled by 69,000 eastern European migrants.Travis, Alan , ''The Guardian'', London, 20 September 2007. On 11 March 2008, the BBC broadcast ''The Poles are Coming!'', a controversial documentary by award-winning filmmaker Tim Samuels, as part of its ''White Season''., Is white working class Britain becoming invisible? A season of programmes on ''BBC Two'' (retrieved 19 March 2008).  June 2007 estimates by the Office of National Statistics give the following percentage break down into broad ethnic groups: 86.8% White, 8.2% Asian or Asian British, 2.1% Black or Black British, 1.1% Chinese or Other, and 1.8% Mixed Race.

The number of languages in use is growing and diversity is spreading where previously few languages other than English were spoken. Peterborough now offers classes in Italian, Urdu and Punjabi in its primary schools. (p.6) CILT the National Centre for Languages, 2006. As the city expands the council has introduced a new statutory development plan. Peterborough City Council, July 2005. Its aim is to accommodate an additional 22,000 homes, 18,000 jobs and over 40,000 people living in Peterborough by 2020. The newly developing Hampton township will be completed, there will be a 1,500 home development at Stanground and a further 1,200 home development at Paston.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f687193c40f3d5adaf416130e71b86f8" name="Pbguildhall" sectnum="5.9#1">../img/f687193c40f3d5adaf416130e71b86f8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>