<document id="f3128071d6d92c6b28a5d4cb4f8b4630-5.10" name="Peterborough" cat="11">
<text>
Christianity has the largest following in Peterborough, in particular the Church of England, with a significant number of parish churches and a cathedral.  Recent immigration to the city has also seen the established Roman Catholic population increase substantially.Walton, Jemma. , ''Peterborough Evening Telegraph'', 27 February 2007. Other denominations are also in evidence; the latest church to be constructed is a £7 million "superchurch," KingsGate, formerly Peterborough Community Church, which can seat up to 1,800 worshippers.Sandall, Jonathan , ''Peterborough Evening Telegraph'', 21 September 2006. In comparison with the rest of the country, Peterborough has a lower proportion of Christians, Buddhists, Hindus, Jews and Sikhs. However, the city has a higher percentage of Muslims and people with no religion than the national average. Cambridgeshire County Council, October 2004. The majority of Muslims reside in the Millfield and New England areas of the city, where two large mosques (including the Faidhan-e-Madina Mosque) are based. Peterborough also has both Hindu (Bharat Hindu Samaj) and Sikh (Singh Sabha Gurdwara) temples in these areas.

The Anglican Diocese of Peterborough covers roughly 1,200 square miles (3,100 km²), including the whole of Northamptonshire, Rutland, and the Soke of Peterborough (the area to the north of the River Nene). Historically in Huntingdonshire, the parts of the city south of the river fall within the Diocese of Ely, which covers the remainder of Cambridgeshire and western Norfolk. However, the current Bishop of Peterborough has been appointed Assistant Bishop in the Diocese of Ely, with pastoral care for these parishes delegated to him by the Bishop of Ely., ''Peterborough Evening Telegraph'', 2 August 2004., Diocese of Ely, Ref. 0471, 29 July 2004. The city falls wholly within the Roman Catholic Diocese of East Anglia, which has its seat at the Cathedral Church of Saint John the Baptist, Norwich.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5a5ff3db5eec17269057636c9a8cf855" name="Peterborough_precinct" sectnum="5.10#1">../img/5a5ff3db5eec17269057636c9a8cf855.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>