<document id="f36a03cc474d62b5f3007c7ea33e0b5a-2.6" name="Our_Gang" cat="19">
<text>
Starting in 1928, ''Our Gang'' comedies were distributed with phonographic discs that contained synchronized music-and-sound-effect tracks for the shorts. In spring 1929, the Roach sound stages were converted for sound recording, and ''Our Gang'' made its "all-talking" debut in April 1929 with the three-reel ''Small Talk.'' It took a year for McGowan and the gang to fully adjust to talking pictures, during which time they lost Joe, Jean and Harry, and added Norman "Chubby" Chaney, Dorothy DeBorba, Matthew "Stymie" Beard, Donald Haines and Jackie Cooper. Jackie proved to be the personality the series had been missing since Mickey left, and he was featured in three 1930/1931 ''Our Gang'' shorts, ''Teacher's Pet'', ''School's Out'', and ''Love Business''.These three shorts explored Jackie's crush on the new schoolteacher Miss Crabtree, played by June Marlowe. Jackie soon won the lead role in Paramount's feature film ''Skippy'', and Roach sold Jackie's contract to MGM in 1931. Other ''Our Gang'' members appearing in the early sound shorts included Buddy McDonald, Bobby "Bonedust" Young, and Shirley Jean Rickert.

Beginning with ''When the Wind Blows'', background music scores were added to the soundtracks of most of the ''Our Gang'' films. Initially, the music consisted of orchestral versions of then popular tunes. Marvin Hatley had served as the music director of Hal Roach Studios since 1929, and RCA employee Leroy Shield joined the company as a part-time musical director in mid 1930. Hatley and Shield's jazz-influenced scores, first featured in ''Our Gang'' with 1930's ''Pups is Pups'', became recognizable trademarks of ''Our Gang'', ''Laurel and Hardy'', and the other Roach series and films. Another 1930 short, ''Teacher's Pet'' marked the first use of the ''Our Gang'' theme song, "Good Old Days", composed by Leroy Shield and featuring a notable saxophone solo. Shield and Hatley's scores would support ''Our Gang's'' on-screen action regularly through 1934, after which series entries with background scores became less frequent.

In 1930, Roach began production on ''The Boy Friends'', a short-subject series which was essentially a teenaged version of ''Our Gang''. Featuring ''Our Gang'' alumni Mickey Daniels and Mary Kornman among its cast, ''The Boy Friends'' was produced by Roach for two years, with fifteen installments in total.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1aa2ac6a54482116ab43f0d43185eb24" name="Hi-neighbor-our-gang" sectnum="2.6#1">../img/1aa2ac6a54482116ab43f0d43185eb24.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>