<document id="f36a03cc474d62b5f3007c7ea33e0b5a-2.4" name="Our_Gang" cat="19">
<text>
According to Roach, the idea for ''Our Gang'' came to him in 1921, when he was auditioning a child actress to appear in one of his films. The girl was, in his opinion, overly made up and overly rehearsed, and Roach patiently waited for the audition to be over. After the girl and her mother left the office, Roach looked out of his window to a lumberyard across the street, where he saw a group of children having an argument. The children had all taken sticks from the lumberyard to play with, but the smallest kid had taken the biggest stick, and the others were trying to force him to give it to the biggest kid. After realizing that he had been watching the kids bicker for 15 minutes, Roach thought a short film series about kids just being themselves might be a success. Maltin & Bann. The Little Rascals: ''The Life & Times of Our Gang'', p. 9.

Under the supervision of Charley Chase, work began on the first two-reel shorts in the new "kids-and-pets" series, which was to be called ''Hal Roach's Rascals'', later that year. Director Fred Newmeyer helmed the first version of the pilot film, entitled ''Our Gang,'' but Roach scrapped Newmeyer's work and had former fireman Robert F. McGowan re-shoot the short. Roach tested it at various theaters around Hollywood. The attendees were very receptive, and the press clamored for "lots more of those 'Our Gang' comedies." The colloquial usage of the term ''Our Gang'' led to its becoming the series' second (yet more popular) official title, with the title cards reading "''Our Gang'' Comedies: Hal Roach presents ''His Rascals'' in..." The series was officially called both ''Our Gang'' and ''Hal Roach's Rascals'' until 1932, when ''Our Gang'' became the sole title of the series.

The first cast of ''Our Gang'' kids was recruited primarily from children recommended to Roach by studio employees, including  photographer Gene Kornman's daughter Mary Kornman, their friends' son Mickey Daniels, Roach child actor Ernie "Sunshine Sammy" Morrison and family friends Allen "Farina" Hoskins, Jack Davis, Jackie Condon and Joe Cobb. Most of the early shorts were shot outdoors and on location, and also featured a menagerie of comic animal characters, such as Dinah the Mule.

Roach's distributor Pathé released ''One Terrible Day'', the fourth short to be produced for the series, as the first ''Our Gang'' short on September 10, 1922; the pilot ''Our Gang'' was not released until November 5. The ''Our Gang'' series was a success from the start, with the kids' naturalism, the funny animal actors, and McGowan's direction making a successful combination. The shorts did well at the box office, and by the end of the decade the ''Our Gang'' kids were pictured on numerous product endorsements.

The biggest ''Our Gang'' stars in this period were Sunshine Sammy around whom the series was structured; Mickey Daniels; Mary Kornman; and little Farina who eventually became both the most popular member of the 1920s gang Maltin & Bann. The Little Rascals: ''The Life & Times of Our Gang'', p. 246. and the most popular African-American child star of the 1920s. Bogle, Donald (1973, rev. 2001). Toms, Coons, Mulattoes, Mammies & Bucks: An Interpretive History of Blacks in American Films. New York: Continuum. Pg. 21. ISBN 082-641267-X. Mickey and Mary were also very popular, and were often paired together in both ''Our Gang'' and a later teenaged version of the series called ''The Boy Friends'', which Roach produced from 1930 to 1932. Other early ''Our Gang'' kids were Eugene "Pineapple" Jackson, Scooter Lowry, Andy Samuel, Johnny Downs, and Jay R. Smith.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="bd92f75f32050625ceec9b95d8e2a54a" name="Oldgreyhoss" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/bd92f75f32050625ceec9b95d8e2a54a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>