<document id="f3cfa82072d36a1fff0ee9be3ffbdd9e-3.7" name="Isaac_Brock" cat="14">
<text>
Meanwhile, American general Stephen Van Rensselaer III, a Federalist political appointee, in command of a sizable army near Lewiston, came under presidential pressure to invade. Although Van Rensselaer had severe doubts about the quality of his troops, he had no choice but to attack. Making matters worse, Van Rensselaer was an inexperienced militia general, and thus not trusted by the majority of regular army troops. In the early morning of 13 October 1812, he attempted to cross the Niagara River, leading to the Battle of Queenston Heights. Despite heavy fire from British artillery, the first wave of Americans (under Captain John E. Wool) managed to land, and then follow a fishermen's path up to the heights. From this point, they attacked and routed the British artillery. Brock himself had arrived from nearby Fort George and moved up to the artillery battery to gain a better view only minutes before Wool attacked. He, his aides and the gunners were forced to beat a hasty retreat, leading their horses down the steep slope.

Fearing that the Americans, with the artillery out of the way, would move the rest of their troops across the river, Brock ordered an immediate attack on their position. True to his philosophy of never ordering men where he would not lead them, he personally led the charge on foot. The charge nearly succeeded, but was repelled. An obvious target with his commanding height and in his general's uniform, Brock was wounded in the hand and then shot and killed by American sharpshooters. Brock's last words have been reported as "Push on, brave York Volunteers" (in reference to a group of the militia Brock favoured) or "Push on, don't mind me"Tupper (1847) p.331 footnote or ''Surgite!'' (Latin for "rise" or "push on"—now used as a motto by Brock University), and even "a request that his fall might not be noticed or prevent the advance of his brave troops, adding a wish, which could not be distinctly understood, that some token of remembrance should be transmitted to his sister."Tupper (1847) p.331 These accounts are considered unlikely, as it is also reported that Brock died almost immediately without speaking,Latimer, p.79 and the hole in his uniform suggests that the bullet entered his heart.

Following his death, John Macdonell became the senior officer present. Macdonell led another unsuccessful charge in which both he and, according to some accounts,e.g. Nursey, p.161–162 Brock's own horse which Macdonell was riding were mortally wounded. During the charge, it is reported that the 49th used "Revenge the General" as a battle cry. In the afternoon, Sheaffe arrived on the battlefield with reinforcements and took command of the British forces. In sharp contrast to his predecessors' direct attacks, Sheaffe took a more cautious approach. This ultimately proved successful, leading to a total victory over the Americans.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="19a3550a1f4114e065525ad113e70bcd" name="Rogerhalesheaffe" sectnum="3.7#1">../img/19a3550a1f4114e065525ad113e70bcd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>