<document id="f42b16bb78b927d33a9c278040a8f6a3-5" name="Siege_of_Malakand" cat="29">
<text>
The campaigns of the Malakand Field Force continued beyond the siege of Malakand South, North, and of the Chakdara fort. Immediately after the siege, two brigades of the British garrison were relocated to a new camp a few miles away to relieve the pressure in the overcrowded Malakand South. These received only light fire during 5 August 1897; however, on 8 August, Saidullah rallied his surviving Pashtun forces and attacked the British garrison at Shabkadr fort near Peshawar. These attacks put the continued loyalty of friendly Pashtun levies guarding the British supply lines to Chitral at risk, thus endangering the supply convoys and their small escorts.Elliott–Lockhart p. 80 In response, on 14 August, the British advanced farther into Pashtun territory and engaged a force of "several thousand"Elliott–Lockhart p. 90 Pashtun tribesmen, with General Meiklejohn leading a flanking manoeuvre which split the Pashtun army in two, forcing it to pull back to Landakai.Elliott–Lockhart p. 93 The British continued to engage Pashtun tribesmen throughout the day, suffering two officers and 11 other ranks killed.Elliott–Lockhart p. 100 

The siege of Malakand was Winston Churchill's first experience of actual combat, which he later described in several columns for the ''The Daily Telegraph'', receiving £5 per column; these articles were eventually compiled into his first published book, ''The Story of the Malakand Field Force'', beginning his career as a writer and politician.Jablonsky p. 300 Of the book's publication he remarked, " will certainly be the most noteworthy act of my life. Up to date (of course). By its reception I shall measure the chances of my possible success in the world." Of the siege of Malakand, and of the entire campaign against the Pashtun tribes in northern Pakistan, Churchill remarked that they were a period of significant "transition".Churchill p. 191

The War Office authorized the award of the clasp ''Malakand 1897'' to the India Medal for those of the British and Indian armies who participated in this action.Joslin p. 30 The battleground remained closed to visitors and under military control since the publication of Churchill's memoirs, and is the location of a Pakistani military base.  However in 2006 the Pakistani government began opening the area to foreign visitors.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3f3b55c5f64cb469c13d5dcf32aaeafe" name="ChurchilMalakand" sectnum="5#1">../img/3f3b55c5f64cb469c13d5dcf32aaeafe.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>