<document id="f4396ed3f5b62398eb8d8fb8be2f2416-2.2" name="Rheinmetall_120_mm_gun" cat="29">
<text>
The appearance of new Soviet tanks during the late 1970s and early 1980s, such as the T-80B, demanded the development of new technologies and weapons to counter the threat posed to Western armor.Jerchel (1998), p. 24  Apart from increased firepower,Baryatinskiy (2006), pp. 23–25 the T-80B was protected by a new composite ceramic armor.Baryatinskiy (2006), p. 14  The T-72 also went through a modernization program, in an attempt to bring it up to the standards of the T-80B.  In 1985, a new version entered production, known as the T-72B, showcasing a new laminate armor protection system.  The turret armor of the T-72B surpassed the T-80B's in protection, and was designed primarily to defeat anti-tank missiles.Zaloga (1993), p. 10



The German government began the development of the Leopard 3, although this was canceled after the fall of the Soviet Union.Jerchel (1998), p. 33–34  On 29 October 1991, the governments of Switzerland, Netherlands and Germany agreed to cooperate in the development of a modernization program for the Leopard 2.  Part of this program included the introduction of a longer  tank gun,Jerchel (1998), p. 34 a cheaper alternative to a brand new tank gun,Hilmes (2004), p. 76 increasing the maximum range of the gun by an estimated .  Although the gun is longer, allowing for a higher peak pressure from the propellant, the geometry remains the same, allowing the gun to fire the same ammunition as that fired from the shorter caliber version of the cannon.Jane's Armour & Artillery Upgrades (subscription), '''', accessed 10 November 2008  The longer barrel allows ammunition to attain higher velocities; for example, with new kinetic energy penetrators ammunition can reach velocities of around .Rheinmetall Defence, '', accessed 10 November 2008  The new barrel weighs .

The longer tank gun has been retrofitted into the Leopard 2, into a model known as the Leopard 2A6.  Both the Spanish Leopard 2E and the Greek Leopard 2HEL, as derivatives of the Leopard 2A6, use the 55 caliber long tank gun.Candil (2007), p. 66

Other tanks that use the gun include the South Korean K2 Black Panther and, as part of an upgrade program currently being carried out, the British Challenger 2.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4d4f20d4c8c04926479a267312726d81" name="Leopard_2A6_with_new_smoke_dispenser" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/4d4f20d4c8c04926479a267312726d81.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>