<document id="f4507409bcd05764e54e0a018453c7ec-2.2" name="Diane_Keaton" cat="19">
<text>
After ''Manhattan'' in 1979, Keaton and Woody Allen ended their long working relationship, and the film would be their last major collaboration until 1993. In 1978 Keaton became romantically involved with Warren Beatty, and two years later he cast her to play opposite of him in ''Reds''. In the film she played Louise Bryant, a journalist and feminist, who flees from her husband to work with radical journalist John Reed (Beatty), and later enters Russia to locate him as he chronicles the Russian Civil War. ''The New York Times'' wrote that Keaton was, "nothing less than splendid as Louise Bryant - beautiful, selfish, funny and driven. It's the best work she has done to date."Vincent Canby. . The New York Times. December 4, 1981. Retrieved February 24, 2006. Keaton received her second Academy Award nomination for the film.

Beatty cast Keaton after seeing her in ''Annie Hall'', as he wanted to bring her natural nervousness and insecure attitude to the role. The production of ''Reds'' was delayed several times since its conception in 1977, and Keaton almost left the project when she believed it would never be produced. Filming finally began two years later. In a 2006 ''Vanity Fair'' story, Keaton described her role as "the everyman of that piece, as someone who wanted to be extraordinary but was probably more ordinary ... I knew what it felt like to be extremely insecure." Assistant director Simon Relph later stated that Louise Bryant was one of her most difficult roles, and that " almost got broken.""The Making of ''Reds''". ''Vanity Fair''. March 2006.

1984 brought ''The Little Drummer Girl'', Keaton's first excursion into the thriller and action genre. ''The Little Drummer Girl'' was both a financial and critical failure, with critics claiming that Keaton was miscast for the genre, such as one review from ''The New Republic'' claiming that "the title role, the pivotal role, is played by Diane Keaton, and around her the picture collapses in tatters. She is so feeble, so inappropriate."Stanley Kauffmann. "The Little Drummer Girl." ''The New Republic'' 191. November 5, 1984. However, that same year she received positive reviews for her performance in ''Mrs. Soffel'', a film based on the true story of a repressed prison warden's wife who falls in love with a convicted murderer and arranges for his escape. Two years later she starred with Jessica Lange and Sissy Spacek in ''Crimes of the Heart'', adapted from Beth Henley's Pulitzer Prize-winning play into a moderately successful screen comedy. She starred in her first commercial vehicle with 1987's ''Baby Boom'', her first of four collaborations with writer-producer Nancy Meyers. In ''Baby Boom'' Keaton starred as a Manhattan career woman who is suddenly forced to care for a toddler. That same year she made a cameo in Allen's film ''Radio Days'' as a nightclub singer. 1988's ''The Good Mother'' was a misstep for Keaton. The film was a financial disappointment (according to Keaton, the film was "a Big Failure. Like, BIG failure"Henri Behar. . Film Scouts interviews. December 22, 1996. Retrieved March 26, 2006.), and some critics panned her performance, such was one review from ''The Washington Post'': "her acting degenerates into hype &ndash; as if she's trying to sell an idea she can't fully believe in."Hal Hinson. . ''The Washington Post''. November 4, 1988. Retrieved March 1, 2006.

In 1987, Keaton directed and edited her first feature film, a documentary named ''Heaven'' about the possibility of an afterlife. ''Heaven'' met with mixed critical reaction, with ''The New York Times'' likening it to "a conceit imposed on its subjects."Vincent Canby. . ''The New York Times''. April 17, 1987. Retrieved March 24, 2006. Over the next four years, Keaton went on to direct music videos for artists such as Belinda Carlisle, two television films starring Patricia Arquette, and episodes of the series ''China Beach'' and ''Twin Peaks''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c83ea8ae9168a63e13cd6a0d0a5e8655" name="Nancy_Reagan_with_Warren_Beatty_and_Diane_Keaton_1981" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/c83ea8ae9168a63e13cd6a0d0a5e8655.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>