<document id="f4507409bcd05764e54e0a018453c7ec-2.4" name="Diane_Keaton" cat="19">
<text>
Keaton's first film of 2000 was ''Hanging Up'' with Meg Ryan and Lisa Kudrow. Keaton also directed the film, despite claiming in a 1996 interview that she would never direct herself in a film, saying " you automatically have different goals. I can't think about directing when I'm acting." The film was a drama about three sisters coping with the senility and eventual death of their elderly father. ''Hanging Up'' rated poorly with critics, and grossed a modest US$36 million at the North American box office.. Retrieved March 28, 2006.

In 2001 Keaton co-starred with Warren Beatty once again in ''Town & Country'', a critical and financial fiasco. Budgeted at an estimated US$90 million, the film opened to little notice and grossed only $7 million in its North American theatrical run.. Box Office Mojo. Retrieved March 21, 2006. Peter Travers of ''Rolling Stone'' claimed that ''Town & Country'' was, "less deserving of a review than it is an obituary ... The corpse took with it the reputations of its starry cast, including Warren Beatty  Diane Keaton".Peter Travers. . ''Rolling Stone''. May 9, 2001. Retrieved March 3, 2006.

In 2001 and 2002 Keaton starred in four low-budget television films. She played a fanatical nun in the religious drama ''Sister Mary Explains It All'', an impoverished mother in the drama ''On Thin Ice'', and a bookkeeper in the mob comedy ''Plan B''. In ''Crossed Over'' she played Beverly Lowry, a woman who forms an unusual friendship with the only woman executed while on death row in Texas, Karla Faye Tucker.

Keaton's first major hit since 1996 came in 2003's ''Something's Gotta Give'', directed by Nancy Meyers and co-starring Jack Nicholson. Nicholson and Keaton, aged 63 and 57 respectively, were seen as bold casting choices for leads in a romantic comedy. Twentieth Century Fox, the film's original studio, reportedly declined to produce the film, fearing that the lead characters were too old to be bankable. Keaton commented about the situation in ''Ladies' Home Journal'': "Let's face it, people my age and Jack's age are much deeper, much more soulful, because they've seen a lot of life. They have a great deal of passion and hope- why shouldn't they fall in love? Why shouldn't movies show that?"Merle Ginsberg. "Adopting Was the Smartest Thing I've Ever Done. ''Ladies' Home Journal''. January 2004. Keaton played a middle-aged playwright who falls in love with her daughter's much older boyfriend. The film was a major success at the box office, grossing US$125 million in North America.. Retrieved March 28, 2006. Roger Ebert wrote that " bring so much experience, knowledge and humor to their characters that the film works in ways the screenplay might not have even hoped for."Roger Ebert. . December 12, 2003. Retrieved February 20, 2006. The following year, Keaton received her fourth Academy Award nomination for her role in the film.

Most recently, Keaton starred in the moderately successful 2005 comedy ''The Family Stone'' with Sarah Jessica Parker. Her film, ''Because I Said So'' with Mandy Moore, opened on February 2, 2007 to poor reviews. She has co-starred with Stephen Collins in both ''The First Wives Club'' (1996) and ''Because I Said So''.

Keaton has served as a producer on films and television series. She produced the FOX series ''Pasadena'', which was cancelled after airing only four episodes in 2001 but later completed its run on cable in 2005. In 2003 she produced the Gus Van Sant drama ''Elephant'', about a school shooting. On why she produced the film, she said "It really makes me think about my responsibilities as an adult to try and understand what's going on with young people." - Diane Keaton. Retrieved March 21, 2006.

Outside of the film industry, Keaton has continued to pursue her interest in photography. As a collector, she told ''Vanity Fair'' in 1987: "I have amassed a huge library of images - kissing scenes from movies, pictures I like. Visual things are really key for me."Joan Juliet Buck. "Inside Diane Keaton" ''Vanity Fair''. March 1987. She has published several more collections of her own photographs, and has also served as an editor for collections of vintage photography. Works she has edited in the last decade include a book of photographs by paparazzo Ron Galella, an anthology of reproductions of clown paintings, and a collection of photos of California's Spanish Colonial-style houses.

Keaton has also established herself as a real estate developer. She has resold several mansions in Southern California after renovating and redesigning them. One of her clients is Madonna, who purchased a US$6.5 million Beverly Hills mansion from Keaton in 2003.. Contact Music. May 16, 2003. Retrieved March 21, 2006. She received the Film Society of Lincoln Center's Gala Tribute in 2007.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5fda8c2053f9c16a1fe2ff07a2c856ab" name="HangingUp2000" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/5fda8c2053f9c16a1fe2ff07a2c856ab.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>