<document id="f537b5cfb11d8edb0a981f16642d476c-10" name="Herne_Bay,_Kent" cat="11">
<text>
The town is a popular destination for water sports; it has clubs for sailing, rowing and yachting. The town has hosted the Zapcat powerboat racing championships. Fishing is popular on the pier and Herne Bay Angling Association competes nationally in beach and boat fishing competitions.

Herne Bay Hockey Club, Greenhill Gymnastics Club, Herne Bay Cricket Club and Herne Bay Youth Football Club are located at Herne Bay High School, a specialist sports college. The hockey club runs a ladies' team and five men's team, the highest of which plays in the Kent Sussex Regional 1st XI League. Herne Bay Cricket Club runs two junior teams, a men's Sunday team and two men's Saturday teams; the Saturday teams play in the Kent Cricket Feeder League East. 



Herne Bay Youth Football Club has 22 teams, and over 320 players aged 6 to 18. Four teams play in the Kent Youth League and the remainder in the East Kent Youth Mini Soccer & 11 a Side Leagues.

Herne Bay Tennis Club is situated on the outskirts of town and runs multiple teams in the Kent League, East Kent League and Dover & District League. Their facilities include four all-weather courts (two floodlit), up to six astroturf courts and a purpose built clubhouse. The club offers junior coaching and runs regular club nights for players of all ages and abilities.

Herne Bay Basketball Club runs teams for men, women and juniors in the East Kent Basketball League. Herne Bay Golf Club has an eighteen-hole course on the outskirts of the town. 
The Memorial Park contains a sports field, eight tennis courts and a basketball court which can be used free of charge. Herne Bay Bowling Club is situated next to the Memorial Park and hosts several lawn bowls Open Tournaments each year. 

There is a council owned sports centre on the pier, with a rink used for roller-skating and roller hockey. The centre has table tennis, badminton and squash courts, a solarium, a gymnasium and a crèche. There is another privately owned gymnasium in the town centre. Herne Bay Judo Club is located near the railway station and the same venue also holds clubs for table tennis and badminton. There are also two other table-tennis clubs in the town. Bujinkai karate classes are held at Herne Bay Junior School. 

Herne Bay Football Club, based at Winch's Field, play in the Kent League Premier Division. They were Kent League champions in 1992, 1994, 1997 and 1998.

The town is the founder of the Roller Hockey sport with the "''Herne Bay Roller Hockey club''" being the first to exist in the world. at www.thebayrollerhockey.co.uk (accessed 20 May 2008)
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1ad196546d78a78bd9d48a1c82f7b608" name="Herne_Bay_water_in_December_2007" sectnum="10#1">../img/1ad196546d78a78bd9d48a1c82f7b608.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>