<document id="f558f1c0dfda24d1afa77500bf9c78c0-2.8" name="England_national_football_team_manager" cat="26">
<text>
Robson had announced before the tournament that he would step down from the post after the finals and Graham Taylor was appointed, having been approached in April 1990 by the FA.  Failure to proceed past the qualifying round of UEFA Euro 1992 with a 2&ndash;1 defeat against Sweden led to newspaper headlines such as "Swedes 2 Turnips 1" and Taylor's nickname of "Turnip Head".  Following defeat to Holland in the penultimate qualifying match for the 1994 World Cup, for only the third time in its history, England had failed to qualify for the World Cup. The qualifying campaign was recorded in a television documentary and Taylor's remark "Do I not like that" soon after entered popular culture.  Failure in the qualification resulted in Taylor resigning and Terry Venables took over the helm in 1994.  As England were hosts for Euro 96, he did not manage the team in a competitive match for over two years. In January 1996 he announced that he would resign after the tournament as a result of several court cases, but led England to the semi-finals where they were defeated by Germany on penalties. 

He was replaced by Glenn Hoddle, whose unorthodox off-the-field approach in bringing in faith healer Eileen Drewery to help the team drew significant criticism.  Hoddle suggested she was "more of an agony aunt" but during the 1998 World Cup, the press suggested Drewery had influenced Hoddle in squad selection.  England were knocked out of the tournament in the second round, once again on penalties, this time against Argentina.  Hoddle's much-criticised diary portraying his version of events at the World Cup was subsequently published, drawing further criticism.  However, an interview with Matt Dickinson, a reporter from ''The Times'', suggested that Hoddle had a "controversial belief that the disabled, and others, are being punished for sins in a former life."   Hoddle's comments were criticised by several notable politicians including Sports Minister Tony Banks and Prime Minister Tony Blair.  Hoddle stated that he was not prepared to resign and claimed his words were misinterpreted and pointed out his contributions and commitment to organisations helping the disabled.  The Football Association terminated Hoddle's contract soon afterwards, which was welcomed by representatives of disabled groups.

Howard Wilkinson was caretaker manager for a single game before the appointment of Kevin Keegan in February 1999.  Initially combining the job with a role at Fulham, Keegan was made full-time coach in May. He led England to qualification for the 2000 European Championship following success in a two-legged play-off against Scotland.  Two 3&ndash;2 losses resulted in England leaving the tournament at the group stage.  A loss to Germany in the last international match at the old Wembley Stadium in the first 2002 World Cup qualifying match led to Keegan's resignation.  Keegan resigned in the Wembley toilets, an hour after the team was booed off by the England fans; he told the FA officials that tactically he felt "a little short at this level".

Howard Wilkinson again returned as caretaker for one more match, followed by Peter Taylor who presided over a friendly loss to Italy.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3dcd00813e2b72572c9b44595a3d037e" name="Glenn_Hoddle2" sectnum="2.8#1">../img/3dcd00813e2b72572c9b44595a3d037e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>