<document id="f5fdc33803f448197e795e5cd6de7eab-2.7" name="East_End_of_London" cat="11">
<text>
Many disasters have befallen the residents of the East End, both in war and in peace. In particular, as a maritime port, plague and pestilence have disproportionately fallen on the residents of the East End. The area most afflicted by the Great Plague (1665) was in Spitalfields,Plague deaths measured at more than 3000 deaths per 478 sq yards in Spitalfields in 1665 (source: ''London from the Air'') and cholera epidemics broke out in Limehouse in 1832 and struck again in 1848 and 1854. Typhus and tuberculosis were also common in the crowded 19th century tenements. The  was a passenger steamer crowded with day trippers returning from Gravesend to Woolwich and London Bridge. On the evening of 3 September 1878, she collided with the steam collier ''Bywell Castle'' (named for Bywell Castle) and sank into the Thames in under four minutes. Of the approximately 700 passengers, over 600 were lost. Thames Police Museum accessed 19 September 2007

During World War I, on 19 January 1917 73 people died, including 14 workers, and more than 400 were injured, in a TNT explosion in the Brunner-Mond munitions factory in Silvertown. Much of the area was flattened, and the shock wave was felt throughout the city and much of Essex. This was the largest explosion in London history, and was heard in Southampton and Norwich. Andreas Angel, chief chemist at the plant, was posthumously awarded the Edward Medal for trying to extinguish the fire that caused the blast.''The Silvertown Explosion: London 1917'' Graham Hill and Howard Bloch (Stroud: Tempus Publishing 2003). ISBN 0-7524-3053-X. The same year, on 13 June, a bomb from a German Gotha bomber killed 18 children in their primary school in Upper North Street, Poplar. This event is commemorated by the local war memorial erected in Poplar Recreation Ground,The ''Poplar War Memorial'' is an exclusively civilian memorial, reflecting the pacifism of the Mayor Will Crooks and local MP George Lansbury. (Peace Pledge Union) accessed 2 April 2007 but during the war a total of 120 children and 104 adults were killed in the East End by aerial bombing, with many more injured. East London History Society accessed 14 November 2007

Another tragedy occurred on the morning of 16 May 1968 when Ronan Point, a 23-storey tower block in Newham, suffered a structural collapse due to a natural gas explosion. Four people were killed in the disaster and seventeen were injured, as an entire corner of the building slid away. The collapse caused major changes in UK building regulations and led to the decline of further building of high rise council flats that had characterised 1960s public architecture.''Collapse: Why Buildings Fall Down'' Phil Wearne (Channel 4 books) ISBN 0-7522-1817-4
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="74a346fe7b352930841cb60f2cd130a7" name="Princess_alice_collision_in_thames" sectnum="2.7#1">../img/74a346fe7b352930841cb60f2cd130a7.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>