<document id="f6010d4f548ad8334ad55e20abc3801c-2.2" name="Music_of_Athens,_Georgia" cat="20">
<text>
The rock scene in Athens dates back to the 1970s, when local music was based around house parties, eccentric thrift store fashions and a wild and weird atmosphere. The foundation of the 40 Watt Club nightclub in 1978 helped to establish Athens' nightlife, which had previously suffered due to a lack of resources for community performances. The 40 Watt Club became a well-known regional attraction for music fans, and was followed by the Uptown Lounge; with the local industry's growth in the 1980s, both the 40 Watt Club and the Uptown Lounge moved to larger spaces, the latter taking over the landmark Georgia Theatre. The early 1980s saw a host of new bands and venues appear, while the city's musical subculture became more diversified. LSD, a hallucinogenic drug, was widely used in the college music scene in this era. Many members of Athens's most prominent later bands became locally renowned starting in the 1970s, including The B-52's.Unterberger, pgs. 133–134 Unterberger states that the scene ''was brewing... even before the Sex Pistols made one of their few 1970s American appearances in nearby Atlanta in early 1978.''

''Ort's Oldies'', a used record store on Jackson Street, and its proprietor, William Orten Carlton, commonly known as ''Ort'', were among the institutional figures that made the Athens music scene possible. Ort has an excellent memory for rock trivia, which served him well in running the store. Perhaps more importantly, his off-the-wall sense of humor and warmly iconoclastic personality (and his thrift-sale wardrobe) were regularly on display at parties, gigs and musical venues around town.

A final element in creating and sustaining the Athens musical culture was the University of Georgia Lamar Dodd School of Art. The great majority of Athens' musicians and their fan base were associated with the University's liberal arts curriculum, and the School of Art, rather than the music department, was the area where the creative and musical alliances that later defined the scene began forming in the 1970s. Michael Stipe of R.E.M. was an art major (although he did not graduate), and the Art School incubated other major figures such as Curtis Crowe, founding member and drummer for Pylon. The cinematographer for the documentary film ''Athens GA: Inside/Out'' was Jim Herbert, an art school professor. Herbert went on to direct music videos for a number of Athens bands, including 14 for R.E.M.














The B-52's and R.E.M. became by far the most famous musical products of Athens in the 1980s, when both bands launched a string of hits. Their roots in the city's local scene go back to the 1970s and early 80s. The B-52's formed after a St. Valentine's Day party in 1977. The members had little musical knowledge, but performed New Wave music with a cheeky and humorous image and sound. They were known for their campy thrift store fashion, and their unusual and eye-catching music videos for hits like "Rock Lobster" and "Love Shack".Unterberger, pgs. 133–135 Though the B-52's were the first Athens band to achieve national prominence, their popularity was soon eclipsed by R.E.M.. The future members of the band R.E.M. moved to Athens to work and/or attend the University of Georgia, including bassist Mike Mills and former drummer Bill Berry.  The group began performing as R.E.M. in 1980. They became locally prominent, and released a single, "Radio Free Europe", that was a major college rock hit. Their popularity grew with a series of singles, EPs and albums that made R.E.M. the top underground band in the country, finally breaking into the mainstream with 1987's "The One I Love" and "It's the End of the World as We Know It (And I Feel Fine)". By 1991's ''Out of Time'' album &mdash; which featured vocals by Kate Pierson of The B-52s &mdash; and its acclaimed follow-up ''Automatic for the People'' (named after the motto of, Weaver D's, a local Athens soul-food eatery), R.E.M. had become one of the world's biggest rock bands. The band's style went through many evolutions but originally had a jangle pop sound and harmonies often compared to folk-rock band The Byrds; singer and songwriter Michael Stipe is known for obscure, allusive lyrics delivered in a monotonous drone.Unterberger, pgs. 135–136 "Radio Free Europe" was chosen as the "best independent single of the year" by the major New York magazine ''The Village Voice''. "The One I Love" was R.E.M.s first Top Ten hit in the United States.'' The success of R.E.M. and the B-52's brought attention from major labels and music media to Athens, and many local bands received a career boost.

The band Pylon was a long-standing and influential part of the Athens scene, and became critical darlings in the 1980s, but never achieved significant mainstream success. This was partially because they eschewed several record contracts from the major labels due to a lack of trust in their corporate goodwill. Pylon's dance rock style was not very accessible or commercial, and was accompanied grating, chanting-style vocals, funky guitars and bass-heavy beats. Other 1980s local bands with nationwide alternative followings included Oh-OK, with Michael Stipe's sister Lynda Stipe and future solo performer Matthew Sweet, Dreams So Real and Love Tractor. The members of R.E.M. have remained fixtures in Athens as they have also become international stars, helping out local performers like Vic Chesnutt, the Chickasaw Mudd Puppies and Jack Logan Unterberger, pgs. 134-137. The Elephant 6 Collective, a group of like-minded indie bands, gained limited nationwide exposure starting in the mid-1990s with the rise of Neutral Milk Hotel, Elf Power and Olivia Tremor Control. The same period saw the Kindercore Records roster find critical acclaim, including the bands Sunshine Fix, Masters of the Hemisphere and Japancakes. Candy, a DJ store owned by Michael Lachowski of Pylon, opened in 1998; the store became an important part of the burgeoning dance music scene that produced Danger Mouse, Phungus and DJ 43
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="690e1d6d7ab3c9e9f2116f075f7ded8b" name="New-40-Watt" sectnum="2.2#1">../img/690e1d6d7ab3c9e9f2116f075f7ded8b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>