<document id="f615455cda36f8afe043d888634bb999-2" name="Nine_Inch_Nails" cat="20">
<text>
Allmusic's Steve Huey states that "Nine Inch Nails were the most popular industrial group ever and were largely responsible for bringing the music to a mass audience." Reznor has never referred to his own work as industrial music, but admits to borrowing techniques from such early industrial bands as Throbbing Gristle and Test Dept. Despite the disparity between those artists initially operating under the term "industrial" and Nine Inch Nails, it has become common in journalistic descriptions of Reznor's body of work to describe it as such. Reznor acknowledged in ''Spin'' magazine that "Down in It" was influenced by early Skinny Puppy, particularly their song "Dig It"; other songs from ''Pretty Hate Machine'' were described in the same interview as synth-pop. Reviewing ''The Fragile'', critic Steve Cooper noted that the album juxtaposes widely varied genres, such as solo piano in "The Frail" and drum and bass elements in "Starfuckers, Inc."

Certain techniques and styles can be found throughout NIN's catalog. Songs such as "Wish" (), "The Day the World Went Away" (), and "The Day the World Went Away" () exhibit terraced dynamics. Reznor's singing follows a similar pattern, frequently moving from whispers to screams. The band's music also occasionally features complex time signatures, notably in "The Collector", from ''With Teeth'', and concert favorite "March of the Pigs".  Archived at . Reznor also uses noise and distortion in his song arrangements, and incorporates dissonance with chromatic melody and/or harmony. These techniques are all used in the song "Hurt" (), which features a highly dissonant tritone played on guitar during the verses, a B5#11, emphasized when Reznor sings the eleventh note on the word "I" every time the B/E# dyad is played. "Closer" () concludes with a chromatic piano motif: the same melody that first appears during the chorus of ''Heresy'', and then recurs on the title track of ''The Downward Spiral''. On ''The Fragile'', Reznor revisits this technique of repeating a motif multiple times throughout different songs, either on a different musical instrument, with a transposed harmony, or in an altered tempo.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="1f440edca652b83c525e89487845192e" name="NineInchNails" sectnum="2#1">../img/1f440edca652b83c525e89487845192e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>