<document id="f615455cda36f8afe043d888634bb999-1.4" name="Nine_Inch_Nails" cat="20">
<text>
Nine Inch Nails' second full-length album, ''The Downward Spiral'', entered the ''Billboard'' 200 in 1994 at number two, and remains the highest-selling NIN release in the United States. Influenced by late-1970s rock albums ''Low'' and ''The Wall'', by David Bowie and Pink Floyd respectively, ''The Downward Spiral'' features a wide range of textures and moods to illustrate the mental progress of a central character.  Flood once again co-produced several tracks on the album, though it proved to be his last collaboration with Nine Inch Nails.  Longtime Flood-collaborator Alan Moulder mixed most of ''The Downward Spiral'' and subsequently took on more extensive production duties for future NIN releases. It was recorded at Le Pig Studios, Beverly Hills – built by Reznor in the house where Charles Manson's "family" murdered Sharon Tate, wife of noted film director Roman Polanski, and four of her friends.. 

The album spawned two singles, "March of the Pigs" and "Closer", along with "Hurt" and "Piggy" which were issued to radio without a commercial single release. The music video for "Closer" was directed by Mark Romanek and received frequent rotation on MTV, though the network made extensive edits to the original version, which they perceived to be too graphic.  A radio edit that partially mutes the song's explicit lyrics also received extensive airtime.  The ''Closure'' video documented highlights from NIN's Self Destruct tour, including full live videos of "Eraser", "Hurt" and a one-take "March of the Pigs" clip made for MTV.

Critical response to ''The Downward Spiral'' has generally been favorable: in 2005 the album was ranked 25th in ''Spin'''s list of the "100 Greatest Albums, 1985–2005", and in 2003 ''Rolling Stone'' ranked the album number 200 on their "The 500 Greatest Albums of All Time" list. After ''The Downward Spiral'''s release, Reznor produced an accompanying remix album entitled ''Further Down the Spiral'', the only non-major NIN release to be certified gold in the United States. It featured contributions from electronic musician Aphex Twin, producer Rick Rubin, and Jane's Addiction guitarist Dave Navarro, among others.

The Self Destruct tour in support of the album reached its widest mainstream audience with a mud-drenched performance at Woodstock '94 that was broadcast on Pay-Per-View and seen in as many as 24 million homes. Nine Inch Nails received considerable mainstream success thereafter, performing with significantly higher production values and adding theatrical visual elements to the live show. Around this time, Reznor's studio perfectionism, struggles with addiction, and bouts of writer's block prolonged the production of a follow-up record.

In 1997 Reznor produced the soundtrack to the David Lynch film ''Lost Highway''.  The release spawned the single "The Perfect Drug", the video for which was again directed by Mark Romanek.  A tenth anniversary deluxe reissue of ''The Downward Spiral'' was released in 2004.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="56142cd1da8ae5aaeb1ab5198b59fad1" name="Closer_Monkey" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/56142cd1da8ae5aaeb1ab5198b59fad1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>