<document id="f615455cda36f8afe043d888634bb999-1.8" name="Nine_Inch_Nails" cat="20">
<text>
In February 2008, Reznor posted a news update on the Nine Inch Nails website entitled "2 weeks." On March 2, ''Ghosts I窶的V'', a 36-track instrumental album, became available via the band's official website. ''Ghosts I窶的V'' was made available in a number of different formats and forms, ranging from a free download of the first volume, to a $300 Ultra-Deluxe limited edition package. All 2500 copies of the $300 package sold out in three days.  The album is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Share Alike license.  The album was created improvisationally over a 10-week period and contributors included Atticus Ross, Alan Moulder, Alessandro Cortini, Adrian Belew, and Brian Viglione.

Similar to the announcement that ultimately led to the release of ''Ghosts I窶的V'', a post on the band's website in April 2008 read "2 weeks!" On May 5, Nine Inch Nails released ''The Slip'' via their website without any advertisement or promotion. The album was made available for download free of charge, protected under the same Creative Commons license as ''Ghosts'', and has seen individual downloads surpassing 1.4 million.  ''The Slip'' has since been released on CD as a limited edition set of 250,000.

Since the release of ''Ghosts I窶的V'' and ''The Slip'', a 25-date tour titled ''Lights in the Sky'', was announced in several North American cities, and was later expanded to include several more North American dates as well as dates in South America. Cortini and Freese returned as members from the previous tour, while Robin Finck rejoined the band and Justin Meldal-Johnsen was added on bass guitar.  In late 2008, Freese and Coritini left the live band, and with the addition of Ilan Rubin on drums, the band became a four-piece.  In January, 2009, Reznor uploaded unedited HD-quality footage from three shows as a download of over 400 GB via bitTorrent.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="78ed55322732e4f13ddc87b9a492193e" name="NIN2008" sectnum="1.8#1">../img/78ed55322732e4f13ddc87b9a492193e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>