<document id="f615455cda36f8afe043d888634bb999-1.2" name="Nine_Inch_Nails" cat="20">
<text>
Written, arranged, and performed by Trent Reznor, Nine Inch Nails' first album ''Pretty Hate Machine'' debuted in 1989. It marked Reznor's first collaboration with Adrian Sherwood (who produced the lead single "Down in It" in London, England without having met Reznor face-to-face) and Mark "Flood" Ellis. Flood's production would appear on each major Nine Inch Nails release until 1994, and Sherwood has done remixes for the band as recently as 2000. Reznor and his co-producers expanded upon the Right Track Studio demos by adding singles "Head Like a Hole" and "Sin". ''Rolling Stone'''s Michael Azerrad described the album as "industrial-strength noise over a pop framework" and "harrowing but catchy music"; Reznor proclaimed this combination "a sincere statement" of "what was in  head at the time". After spending 113 weeks on the ''Billboard'' 200, ''Pretty Hate Machine'' became one of the first independently released records to attain platinum certification. MTV aired videos for "Down in It" and "Head Like a Hole", but an explicit video for "Sin" was only released on the 1997 home video ''Closure''.

In 1990, NIN began the Pretty Hate Machine Tour Series, in which they toured North America as an opening act for alternative rock artists such as Peter Murphy and The Jesus and Mary Chain. At some point, Reznor began smashing his equipment while on stage; ''Rockbeat'' interviewer Mike Gitter attributed NIN's early success in front of rock oriented audiences to this aggressive attitude. Nine Inch Nails then embarked on a world tour that continued through the first Lollapalooza festival in 1991. After a poor European reception opening for Guns N' Roses, NIN returned to America amid pressure from TVT to produce a follow-up to ''Pretty Hate Machine''. In response, Reznor secretly began recording under various pseudonyms to avoid record company interference.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="362972424d61b558f8160623edfb63a4" name="Trent_Reznor_Lollapalooza_1991" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/362972424d61b558f8160623edfb63a4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>