<document id="f615455cda36f8afe043d888634bb999-1.6" name="Nine_Inch_Nails" cat="20">
<text>
A further six years elapsed before Nine Inch Nails' fourth full-length album, ''With Teeth'', was released in 2005, though it was leaked prior to its official release date. The album was written and recorded following Reznor's battle with alcoholism and substance abuse.  Like ''The Fragile'', ''With Teeth'' debuted on top of the ''Billboard'' 200. The album's package art lacks typical liner notes; instead it simply lists the names of songs and co-producers, and the URL for an online PDF poster with lyrics and full credits. The entire album was made available in streaming audio on the band's official MySpace page in advance of its release date.  Critical reception of the album was generally favorable: ''Rolling Stone'''s Rob Sheffield described the album as "vintage Nine Inch Nails".

A promotional video for the song "The Hand That Feeds" premiered on NIN's website in March 2005, rather than the traditional music channels.  Reznor also released the source files for the song in GarageBand format a month later, allowing fans to remix the song.  Reznor similarly released files for the album's second single "Only" in a wider range of formats, including Pro Tools and ACID Pro.  David Fincher directed a video for "Only" using primarily computer-generated imagery. The third single, "Every Day Is Exactly the Same", was released in April 2006, but a planned music video was reportedly scrapped in the post-production stage. The song topped ''Billboard'''s Alternative Songs charts.

Nine Inch Nails launched a North American arena tour in autumn 2005, supported by Queens of the Stone Age, Autolux and Death from Above 1979. Another opening act on this tour, hip-hop artist Saul Williams, performed on stage with Nine Inch Nails at the Voodoo Music Experience festival during a headlining appearance in hurricane-stricken New Orleans, Reznor's former home. To conclude the ''With Teeth'' era of the band, NIN completed a tour of North American amphitheaters in the summer of 2006, joined by Bauhaus, TV on the Radio, and Peaches. In late 2006, the official NIN website announced that a tour documentary entitled ''Beside You in Time'' would be released in three formats: DVD, HD DVD and Blu-ray Disc.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a3004bb244e2cfa1d287944ca82077c9" name="Nine_Inch_Nails_Moline_03" sectnum="1.6#1">../img/a3004bb244e2cfa1d287944ca82077c9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>