<document id="f6edb499d71fa9ef08d26469a49e4681-4.4" name="Willie_Wagtail" cat="3">
<text>
Willie Wagtail incubating its eggs
Willie Wagtails usually pair for life. The breeding season lasts from July to December, more often occurring after rain in drier regions. Anywhere up to four broods may be raised during this time. It builds a cup-like nest on a tree branch away from leaves or cover, less than 5 m (16 ft) above the ground. Rafters and eaves may also be used. It has been observed to build its nest in the vicinity of those of the Magpie-lark (''Grallina cyanoleuca''), possibly taking advantage of the latter bird's territoriality and aggression toward intruders. Similarly, it is not afraid to build near human habitation.

The nest consists of grass stems, strips of bark, and other fibrous material which is bound and woven together with spider web. Even hair from pet dogs and cats may be used. The female lays two to four small cream-white eggs with brownish markings measuring 16 x 21 mm, and incubates them for 14 days. Like all passerines, the chicks are altricial and nidicolous; they are born naked and helpless with closed eyes, and remain in the nest.Higgins ''et al.'' p. 241 Both parents take part in feeding the young, and may continue to do so while embarking on another brood.Coates, p. 141 Nestlings remain in the nest for around 14 days before fledging. Upon leaving, the fledglings will remain hidden in cover nearby for one or two days before venturing further afield, up to 20 m (60 ft) away by the third day. Parents will stop feeding their fledglings near the end of the second week, as the young birds increasingly forage for themselves, and soon afterwards drive them out of the territory.Higgins ''et al.'' p. 242 

The female Pallid Cuckoo (''Cuculus pallidus'') will lay eggs in a Willie Wagtail nest, although the hosts often recognise and eject the foreign eggs, so successful brood parasitism is rare. Parasitism by the Fan-tailed (''Cacomantis flabelliformis''), Brush, (''C. variolosus''), Horsfield's Bronze (''Chrysococcyx basalis''), and Shining Bronze-cuckoo (''C. lucidus'') has also been reported.

Although the Willie Wagtail is a successful species, predators do account for many eggs and young. About two thirds of eggs hatch successfully, and a third leave the nest as fledglings. Nestlings may be preyed upon by both Pied Butcherbird, (''Cracticus nigrogularis'') Black Butcherbirds (''C. quoyi''), the Spangled Drongo (''Dicrurus bracteatus''), and the Pied Currawong (''Strepera graculina''), as well as the feral cat (''Felis catus''), and rat species. The proximity of nesting to human habitation has also left nests open to destruction by children.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="73b421ce565560769f73e31df774d430" name="Willy_Wagtail_nest" sectnum="4.4#1">../img/73b421ce565560769f73e31df774d430.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>