<document id="f718b3f868a32280f808dc23652e84f1-3" name="Wormshill" cat="11">
<text>
At , the village is in central Kent, approximately  south-east of London. The nearest town is Sittingbourne,  to the north. Wormshill is surrounded by villages and hamlets of a similar size, including Frinsted, Bicknor, Bedmonton and Hucking.

The village is on a high point of the North Downs. The nearby road intersection of ''Black Post'' is recorded on the Ordnance Survey maps at  above sea level. The landscape is primarily characterised by undulating calcareous grassland and ancient deciduous woodland over chalk downland. The settlement itself (as opposed to the wider parish) is on a downland ridge between two shallow dip slope valleys that separate it from Bicknor to the north-west and Frinsted to the east.


Wormshill's elevated and exposed position on the North Downs means it occasionally experiences extreme weather conditions such as the heavy snowfalls of 11&ndash;14 January 1987, March 2005 and February 2009. Reports indicating snowfall specifically over the Kent Downs Article indicating North Downs received highest snowfall during relevant period (28cm (11 inches)) In the late 1700s Hasted commented: "Being exposed to the northern aspect, it lies very bleak and cold."

Much of the local woodland was devastated by the Great Storm of 1987, which in October swept across south-east England with hurricane-force winds. A significant part of the exposed woodland to the north-east of Wormshill was felled and, after replanting, has only recently shown signs of maturing. An ancient yew tree believed to have stood for several hundred years in the grounds of the house at Norwood Farm was destroyed along with other long-standing trees. However, some 20 years later, the village displays few obvious signs of the damage.

The countryside around the village has been described as "an area where the whole landscape is a piece of history&mdash;a valley where time has stood still and the pattern of woods and
fields is much as it was 500 years ago". A designated ancient woodland lies to the north-west of the village. A website providing detailed map overlays giving landscape information.  Predominantly centred on ''Barrows Wood'' but also including ''High Wood'' and ''Trundle Wood'', this is likely a remnant of the woodland described by Hasted: "…at the northern boundary of the parish there is a considerable quantity of wood, consisting mostly of hazel and oak, with numbers of trees of the latter, interspersed among them, which are but small, never here growing to any size." An ancient track that passes through the remnants of this woodland has been damaged by the use of off-road vehicles leading to attempts by local landowners to block ''Drake Lane'', a byway that runs through ''Drake Lane Wood'' in the south-west of the parish and which may have been used by recruits of Sir Francis Drake's navy. Photograph of barriers to four-wheel drive vehicles at ''Drake Lane''. Deep water-logged ruts in the track have resulted in the partial resurfacing of the route. and  Photographs of tyre ruts and further barriers to access at ''Drake Lane''.

The village stretches primarily along a single carriageway road known as ''The Street''. The north-eastern end of ''The Street'' is a designated Conservation Area. The lack of development stems from its position within the Kent Downs Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty (AONB) and a Site of Nature Conservation Interest, which influences local planning laws and limits permission to build new housing. All development is subject to a high level of scrutiny; any development that would adversely affect the natural beauty of the landscape will automatically be resisted, and large-scale development proposals must be accompanied by an environmental impact assessment. The last major development was that of the residential cul-de-sac ''Draysfield''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="641f81dc218f03a4107424f5c743e98c" name="WinterWormshill" sectnum="3#1">../img/641f81dc218f03a4107424f5c743e98c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>