<document id="f81b65072205c55fb211f3a6a9e06345-1.10" name="Judy_Garland" cat="19">
<text>
With the demise of her television series, Garland returned to the stage. Most notably, she performed at the London Palladium with her then 18-year-old daughter Liza Minnelli in November 1964. The concert, which was also filmed for British television network ITV, was one of Garland's final appearances at the venue. She made guest appearances on the ''The Ed Sullivan Show'', ''The Tonight Show'', ''The Hollywood Palace'', and ''The Merv Griffin Show'', guest-hosting an episode of the last one.DiOrio, p. 202

Garland sued Sid Luft for divorce in 1963, claiming "cruelty" as the grounds. She also asserted that Luft had repeatedly struck her while he was drinking and that he had attempted to take their children from her by force. She had filed for divorce more than once previously, including as early as 1956.

A 1964 tour of Australia was largely disastrous. Garland's first concert in Sydney, held in Sydney Stadium because no concert hall could accommodate the crowds who wanted to see her, went well and received positive reviews. Her second performance, in Melbourne, started an hour late. The crowd of 70,000, angered by her tardiness—and believing Garland to be drunk—booed and heckled her, and she fled the stage after just 45 minutes.Edwards p. 213 She later characterized the Melbourne crowd as "brutish". A second concert in Sydney was uneventful but the Melbourne appearance garnered her significant bad press. Some of that bad press was deflected by the announcement of a near fatal episode of pleurisy, followed by Garland's fourth marriage to tour promoter Mark Herron. They announced that their marriage had taken place aboard a freighter off the coast of Hong Kong; however, Garland was not legally divorced from Luft at the time the ceremony was performed.Edwards p. 214 Her divorce from Luft became final on May 19, 1965, but Herron and Garland did not legally marry until November 14.Frank p. 556

In February 1967, Garland was cast as "Helen Lawson" in ''Valley of the Dolls'' for 20th Century Fox. The character of "Neely O'Hara" in the book by Jacqueline Susann was rumored to have been based on Garland.Seaman, pp. 292&ndash;93 The role of O'Hara in the film was played by Patty Duke. During the filming, Garland missed rehearsals and was fired in April. She was replaced by Susan Hayward.Seaman, p. 343 Garland's prerecording of the song ''I'll Plant My Own Tree'' survives today, along with her wardrobe tests.

Returning to the stage, Garland made her last appearances at New York's Palace Theatre in July, a 16-show tour, performing with her children Lorna and Joey Luft. Garland wore a sequined pantsuit on stage for this tour, which was part of the original wardrobe for her character in ''Valley of the Dolls.''Shipman p. 494

By early 1969, Garland's health had deteriorated. She performed in London at the ''Talk of the Town'' nightclub for a five-week runClarke p. 412 and made her last concert appearance in Copenhagen during March 1969.DiOrio, p. 204 She married her final husband, Mickey Deans, in London on March 17, 1969,Steiger, p. 88 her divorce from Herron having been finalized on February 11 of that year.Edwards p. 275

On June 22, 1969, Garland was found dead by Deans in the bathroom of their rented Chelsea, London house. The coroner, Gavin Thursdon, stated at the inquest that the cause of death was "an incautious self-overdosage" of barbiturates; her blood contained the equivalent of ten  Seconal capsules.Clarke p. 422 Thursdon stressed that the overdose had been unintentional and that there was no evidence to suggest she had committed suicide. Garland's autopsy showed that there was no inflammation of her stomach lining and no drug residue in her stomach, which indicated that the drug had been ingested over a long period of time, rather than in one dose. Her death certificate stated that her death had been "accidental." citing ''United Press International'' article "Judy Took Too Many Pills", and containing a copy of Garland's death certificate. Even so, a British specialist who had attended Garland said she had been living on borrowed time due to cirrhosis of the liver.Times Wire Services, "Judy Garland Believed Killed by Overdose," St. Petersburg Times, June 24, 1969.  Garland had turned 47 just 12 days prior to her death. Her ''Wizard of Oz'' co-star Ray Bolger commented at Garland's funeral, "She just plain wore out." An estimated 20,000 people lined up for hours at the Frank E. Campbell Funeral Chapel to view her body. Garland was interred in Ferncliff Cemetery, in Hartsdale, New York.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="04bbc807749b892130fd48b2f0f3d6fc" name="Judysgrave" sectnum="1.10#1">../img/04bbc807749b892130fd48b2f0f3d6fc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>