<document id="f82c7682b284ffa37fdcd1bc429a35bb-2.1" name="Clem_Hill" cat="26">
<text>
Hill topped the averages for South Australia in the 1895–96 season, scoring 371 runs in seven innings. An Australian team to tour England in 1896 was selected towards the end of the season and Hill was not included. A disappointed Hill responded by scoring 206 against New South Wales, who were captained by an Australian selector, Tom Garrett. Experienced cricket watchers were impressed with Hill's ability at such a young age to control the strike, scoring 154 from his side's last 197 runs.  Following this performance, public demand saw the selectors draft the 19-year-old Hill into the touring squad.

Hill was one of four batsmen touring England for the first time; Joe Darling, Frank Iredale and Harry Donnan were the others. All four scored more than 1,000 runs for the tour with Hill scoring 1,196 runs at an average of 27.81.. CricketArchive. Retrieved on 2008-12-21.  According to ''Wisden Cricketers' Almanack'', Hill "was a brilliant success" and his batting on good wickets during the tour was "first rate".  Hill made his Test début in the First Test at Lord's.  Australia collapsed in the first innings to be all out for 53 with Hill bowled by George Lohmann for one.  England made 292 runs in reply but the second innings saw an Australian fightback.  The captain, Harry Trott (143),  was partnered by Syd Gregory (103) to help Australia to a score of 347, setting England 109 runs to win. Hill failed again scoring only five, bowled this time by Jack Hearne. Rain made England's task a little more difficult but they were able to make the runs for the loss of only four wickets.  Hill played in the remaining two Tests, but managed to score only 30 runs in the series. Australia lost the series and the Ashes by two Tests to one.

The next Ashes series was held in 1897–98 with Stoddart again assembling an English team to tour Australia.  The team included players such as K.S. Ranjitsinhji and George Hirst.  The touring team's first match on arrival was against South Australia and Hill batted well, scoring exactly 200.  The First Test was played in Sydney and a minor controversy ensued when officials abandoned the first day's play due to earlier heavy rain without consulting the two captains.  The delay did not seem to affect the English who batted first and scored 551, including centuries by Ranjitsinhji and Archie MacLaren.  The Australians were forced to follow-on after making 237.  Batting again, Hill scored 96 but England managed to win the match by nine wickets. The Second Test was played in Melbourne and Australia fought back, winning by an innings and 55 runs with Hill scoring 58. Another innings victory in the Third Test in Adelaide saw Australia leading the series two Tests to one.


The teams returned to Melbourne for the Fourth Test.  England started the match brilliantly, reducing Australia to 6/58See scoring (cricket) for an explanation of cricket score formats.  This score and all others in the article follow the Australian format of wickets fallen followed by runs made.  on a pitch that assisted the bowlers.  Hill, aged just 20, was watching at the non-striker's end as the wickets fell.  Hugh Trumble came to join him and together they began to rescue the Australian innings.  When Hill reached his maiden Test century, he had scored all but 42 of his side's runs.  Hill played balls pitched outside leg stump particularly well and drove beautifully throughout the innings.Frith, p. 59.  At the tea interval, Hill, feeling refreshed, mentioned to Trumble that he thought he would "have a go at them now".  The experienced Trumble cautioned Hill, replying "You young devil, you have to stop there.  Go along as you have been doing."  Hill and Trumble made 165 runs batting together, still a record for a seventh wicket partnership in Ashes Tests. Hill was 182 not out at the end of the day's play, the highest first-day innings against England in Australia, and leaving the ground was greeted by a barrage of photographers.  After a rest day, Hill added only six more runs before being dismissed at last by Hearne.  His innings remains the highest in Ashes Tests by a player under 21.  Batting for 294 minutes he gave only the one chance at dismissal. The journalist and former Test player Tom Horan wrote "Hill's innings will be talked of when the smallest boy who saw it will be white with the snows of time."  Australia won the Test by 8 wickets to recover the Ashes. That summer, Hill scored 1,196 runs in 19 innings including five centuries, the first Australian to score 1,000 runs in a home season.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="49f6103ea1f6e18753512c4a6b135946" name="ClementHill" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/49f6103ea1f6e18753512c4a6b135946.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>