<document id="f82c7682b284ffa37fdcd1bc429a35bb-2.3" name="Clem_Hill" cat="26">
<text>
For the first time under the auspices of the Marylebone Cricket Club, an English team travelled to Australia for the 1903–04 season to contest the Ashes. Contrary to expectations before the tour, the English won the series and the Ashes three Tests to two.  Hill trailed Trumper and Noble in the series averages, making 276 runs at 27.60 without ever getting to 100 in an innings.  In the First Test, Hill was at the centre of what ''Wisden'' described as a "very regrettable and indeed disgraceful  demonstration". Batting with Trumper, Hill had run well past the stumps at the bowler's end for a fourth run.  The English return gave the Australian pair an opportunity for an overthrow.  Hill had to run the entire length of the pitch.  Albert Relf at mid-on gathered and threw to the wicket-keeper, Dick Lilley who removed the bails and appealed for the run out.  Umpire Bob Crockett gave Hill out.  Hill could not believe the decision as the ball had passed behind him when he slid his bat to make his ground.  The crowd were also convinced that Hill was not out and began to hoot, chanting "Crock!, Crock!, Crock!"  Bottles were thrown onto the surrounding cycle track and the English captain Plum Warner threatened to take his team from the ground.  At the end of the day, Crockett required a police escort when leaving the ground.  Hill's best performance of the series was at his home town, Adelaide, in the Third Test.  Hill scored 88 before being dismissed by Ted Arnold, caught by the wicket-keeper. Australia won the Test by 216 runs.

Hill toured England for the last time with the 1905 Australian team.  The Test series was dominated by what was seen as uninspired cricket with England retaining the Ashes two Tests to nil.Wynne-Thomas, pp. 237–238.  The Australian batting suffered from a lack of steadiness and Hill was one of the Australians criticised by ''Wisden'' that season; " would certainly have met with more consistent success if he had retained his old self-control. He was somewhat indiscriminate in hitting at the off-ball, and many a time his impatience cost him his wicket."  However ''Wisden'' praised his fielding, saying "Trumper, Hill, and Hopkins did any amount of fine work in the deep field".

The Australians recovered the Ashes from the 1907–08 English team, winning the series four Tests to one.  England were hit by the loss of their captain, Arthur Jones who contracted an illness that threatened to develop into pneumonia, causing him to miss the first three Tests.  Hill, batting with team-mate Roger Hartigan playing his first Test match, set a record in the Third Test in Adelaide.  Suffering from influenza and unable to field in the English first innings, Hill joined Hartigan at the fall of the seventh wicket.  During his innings, Hill vomited beside the pitch and had to quickly leave the field several times.  The pair managed to bat on and take the match into a fourth day.  Hartigan, whose leave from work had expired, was relieved to receive a telegram from his employer: "Stay as long as you are making runs."  When Hartigan was dismissed for 116, the pair had together made 243 for the eighth wicket—still an Australian Test record. With Sammy Carter, Hill continued before finally dismissed by Jack Crawford for 160, after 5 hours and 19 minutes of batting.  At the end of his innings Hill was close to collapse but his efforts assisted his team defeat the English by 245 runs.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b806634f5442291d73e5c66a010542e5" name="HillandDog" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/b806634f5442291d73e5c66a010542e5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>