<document id="f82c7682b284ffa37fdcd1bc429a35bb-2.4" name="Clem_Hill" cat="26">
<text>
Australia were due to tour England to contest the Ashes in 1909.  Hill, along with other senior players, was fighting against a proposal to move the management of international tours away from the players to the new Australian Board of Control for International Cricket Matches. Hill by now was a team selector and strongly opposed the selection in the team of 40-year-old Peter McAlister, who Hill claimed "was past his best" and "not suited to English conditions".Haigh, p. 169.  McAlister was also a member of the selection panel and was able to secure a majority for his selection. Hill accused his fellow selectors of conspiracy and said he had "decided to wash his hands of the affair" and that "he did not consider that the best men had been chosen". Hill's relationship with McAlister would remain fractious.  Hill was also a delegate on the Board of Control, representing the South Australian Cricket Association (SACA).  At the Board meeting in February 1909 to set the terms to be offered to the players selected for the tour, the SACA delegates were outvoted on every point.Haigh, p. 170.  Hill declined to accept the terms offered. Since his marriage in 1905, Hill had spent considerable time away from his wife with his commitments during two Test series against England and this may have also influenced his decision not to tour.


When Hill returned to the Test team it was as captain for a series against the visiting South Africa national cricket team in 1910–11.  The South Africans, led by Aubrey Faulkner, had a novel bowling attack consisting of several googly bowlers, such as Bert Vogler, Reggie Schwarz and Faulkner himself and the chinaman bowler Charlie "Buck" Llewellyn.  The South Africans started the tour well, defeating a South Australian team unable to handle the unusual bowling approach.Pollard (1988), pp. 987–988.  Hill, after consulting with other players, settled on a strategy of hitting the bowlers off their length with aggressive batting.  Hill showed the way in the First Test at Sydney, scoring his first 100 runs in 98 minutes. In a partnership with Warren Bardsley, the pair scored 224 runs in only two hours.   After just 3 hours and 20 minutes at the crease, he was dismissed for 191; his highest Test score. Australia won the Test by an innings and 114 runs.  Australia won the Second Test in Melbourne after bowling the South Africans out for 80 in their second innings, but the South Africans fought back to win the Third Test in Adelaide by 38 runs.
Australia won the Fourth Test by 508 runs after being sent in to bat by South Africa, who hoped to trap them on a rain-affected wicket.  The Australians managed to end the first day's play at 8/317 to avoid the trap and win the Test.  In the second innings, Hill hit another century (100) in only 100 minutes, with ''Wisden'' noting that he "play especially well".  Australia won the final Test and the series four Tests to one.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="56aa3d8db1fc9117eb02d6e9c7ed9058" name="AustralianCricketTeam1911" sectnum="2.4#1">../img/56aa3d8db1fc9117eb02d6e9c7ed9058.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>