<document id="f845969569b72822ace0d51533e8aa7b-5.6" name="Choral_symphony" cat="20">
<text>
While Berlioz allowed the programmatic aspects of his text to shape the symphonic form of ''Roméo'' and to guide its content, he also showed how an orchestra could supplant such a text wordlessly to further illustrate it. He wrote in his preface to ''Roméo'': 
    
  
If, in the famous garden and cemetery scenes the dialogue of the two lovers, Juliet's asides, and Romeo's passionate outbursts are not sung, if the duets of love and despair are given to the orchestra, the reasons are numerous and easy to comprehend. First, and this alone would be sufficient, it is a symphony and not an opera. Second, since duets of this nature have been handled vocally a thousand times by the greatest masters, it was wise as well as unusual to attempt another means of expression. It is also because the very sublimity of this love made its depiction so dangerous for the musician that he had to give his imagination a latitude that the positive sense of the sung words would not have given him, resorting instead to instrumental language, which is richer, more varied, less precise, and by its very indefiniteness incomparably more powerful in such a case.  
    
As a manifesto, this paragraph became significant for the amalgamation of symphonic and dramatic elements in the same musical composition.Holoman, 261. Musicologist Hugh MacDonald writes that as Berlioz kept the idea of symphonic construction closely in mind, he allowed the orchestra to express the majority of the drama in instrumental music and set expository and narrative sections in words.MacDonald, ''New Grove (1980)'', 2:596. Fellow musicologist Nicholas Temperley suggests that, in ''Roméo'', Berlioz created a model for how a dramatic text could guide the structure of a choral symphony without circumventing that work from being recognizably a symphony.Temperley, ''New Grove (1980)'', 18:460. In this sense, musicologist Mark Evans Bonds writes, the symphonies of Liszt and Mahler owe a debt of influence to Berlioz.  

More recently, Alfred Schnittke allowed the programmatic aspects of his texts to dictate the course of both his choral symphonies even when no words were being sung. Schnittke's six-movement Second Symphony, following the Ordinary of the Mass of the Roman Catholic Church, works programmatically on two levels simultaneously. While soloists and chorus briefly perform the mass, set to chorales taken from the Gradual,Ivashkin, notes for Chandos 9519, 5. the orchestra provides an extended running commentary that can continue much longer than the section of the mass being performed. Sometimes the commentary follows a particular chorale but more often is freer and wider ranging in style. Despite the resulting stylistic disparity, biographer Alexander Ivashkin comments, "musically almost all these sections blend the choral  tune and subsequent extensive orchestral 'commentary.'" The work becomes what Schnittke called an "Invisible Mass",As cited in Ivanskin, notes to Chandos 9519, 5. and Ivashkin termed "a symphony against a chorale backdrop".

The program in Schnittke's Fourth Symphony, reflecting the composer's own religious dilemma at the time it was written, is more complex in execution, with the majority of it expressed wordlessly. In the 22 variations that make up the symphony's single movement, The actual number of variations in the Schnittke Fourth Symphony is "a subtle non-synchronicity" of the piece, considering the "3 by 5 scheme" of the Rosary upon which these variations are reportedly based. Weitzman, notes for Chandos 9463, 5. Schnittke enacts the 15 traditional Mysteries of the Rosary, which highlight important moments in the life of Christ.Weitzman, notes for Chandos 9463, 6. As he did in the Second Symphony, Schnittke simultaneously gives a detailed musical commentary on what is being portrayed. Schnittke does this while using church music from the Catholic, Protestant, Jewish and Orthodox faiths, the orchestral texture becoming extremely dense from the many musical strands progressing at the same time.Moody, ''New Grove (2001)'', 22:566.Ivashkin, ''Schnittke'', 161. A tenor and a countertenor also sing wordlessly at two points in the symphony. Words are saved for a finale in which all four types of church music are used contrapuntallyWeitzman, notes for Chandos 9463, 7. as a four-part choir sings the ''Ave Maria''. The choir can choose whether to sing the ''Ave Maria'' in Russian or Latin. The programmatic intent of using these different types of music, Ivashkin writes, is an insistence by the composer "on the idea ... of the unity of humanity, a synthesis and harmony among various manifestations of belief".Ivashkin, ''Schnittke'', 165.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d9837c28b7ed66ce3ae13b73ecf032dd" name="Romeo_and_juliet_brown" sectnum="5.6#1">../img/d9837c28b7ed66ce3ae13b73ecf032dd.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>