<document id="f845969569b72822ace0d51533e8aa7b-3.4" name="Choral_symphony" cat="20">
<text>
A composer may also respond to a text by expanding a choral symphony beyond the normal bounds of the symphonic genre. This is evident in the unusual orchestration and stage directions Berlioz prepared for his ''Roméo et Juliette''. This piece is actually in seven movements, and calls for an intermission after the fourth movement &ndash; the "Queen Mab Scherzo" &ndash; to remove the harps from the stage and bring on the chorus of Capulets for the funeral march which follows.Holoman, 262&ndash;263. Berlioz biographer D. Kern Holoman observed that, "as Berlioz saw it, the work is simply Beethovenian in design, with the narrative elements overlain. Its core approaches a five-movement symphony with the choral finale and, as in the '' Fantastique'', both a scherzo and a march.... The 'extra' movements are thus the introduction with its ''potpourri'' of subsections and the descriptive tomb scene ."Holomon, 263. 


Mahler expanded the Beethovenian model for programmatic as well as symphonic reasons in his Second Symphony, the "Resurrection", the vocal fourth movement, "Urlicht", bridging the childlike faith of the third movement with the ideological tension which Mahler seeks to resolve in the finale.Franklin, ''New Grove (2001)'', 15:618. He then abandoned this pattern for his Third Symphony, as two movements for voices and orchestra follow three purely instrumental ones before the finale returns to instruments alone.Mitchell, ''New Grove'', 11:515. Like Mahler, Havergal Brian expanded the Beethovenian model, but on a much larger scale and with far larger orchestral and choral forces, in his First Symphony. Subtitled "The Gothic" and written between 1919 and 1927, the symphony was inspired by Goethe's ''Faust'' and Gothic cathedral architecture.MacDonald, ''New Grove (2001)'', 4:341. The Brian First is in two parts. The first consists of three instrumental movements; the second, also in three movements and over an hour in length, is a Latin setting of the ''Te Deum''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e5dfef9ce74ff4710971c58377611cfc" name="Gustav-Mahler-Kohut" sectnum="3.4#1">../img/e5dfef9ce74ff4710971c58377611cfc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>