<document id="f845969569b72822ace0d51533e8aa7b-3.2" name="Choral_symphony" cat="20">
<text>
Stravinsky said about the texts of his ''Symphony of Psalms'' that "it is not a symphony in which I have included ''Psalms'' to be sung. On the contrary, it is the singing of the ''Psalms'' that I am symphonizing".White, ''Stravinsky'', 321. This decision was as much musical as it was textual. Stravinsky's counterpoint required several musical voices to function simultaneously, independent melodically and rhythmically, yet interdependent harmonically. They would sound very different when heard separately, yet harmonious when heard together.Sachs and Dahlhaus, ''New Grove (2001)'', 6:564&ndash;569. To facilitate maximum clarity in this interplay of voices, Stravinsky used "a choral and instrumental ensemble in which the two elements should be on an equal footing, neither of them outweighing the other".Stravinsky, ''Chronicles'', as cited in White, ''Stravinsky'', 321. 

 
Mahler's intent in writing his Eighth Symphony for exceptionally large forces was a similar balance between vocal and instrumental forces. It was not simply an attempt at grandiose effect, though the composer's use of such forces earned the work the subtitle "Symphony of a Thousand" from his press agent (a soubriquet which has stuck to the symphony to the present day).Kennedy, ''Mahler'', 100. Like Stravinsky, Mahler makes extensive and extended use of counterpoint, especially in the first part, "Veni Creator Spiritus". Throughout this section, according to music writer  Michael Kennedy, Mahler displays considerable mastery in manipulating multiple independent melodic voices.Kennedy, ''Mahler'', 152. Musicologist Deryck Cooke adds that Mahler handles his huge forces "with extraordinary clarity".Cooke, 93.

Vaughan Williams also insisted on a balance between words and music in ''A Sea Symphony'', writing in his program note for the work, "It is also noticeable that the orchestra has an equal share with the chorus and soloists in carrying out the musical ideas". Music critic Samuel Langford, writing about the premiere of the work for ''The Manchester Guardian'', concurred with the composer, writing, "It is the nearest approach we have to a real choral symphony, one in which the voices are used throughout just as freely as the orchestra."Cited in Kennedy, ''Vaughan Williams'', 99.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="8da458fbd01ff2e0298cde898eace5a9" name="Igor_Stravinsky_LOC_32392u" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/8da458fbd01ff2e0298cde898eace5a9.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>