<document id="f86e362022cb775c9707a239be3a9f71-1.2" name="Michigan_State_Capitol" cat="1">
<text>
The 1835 Michigan Constitution provided that:
:''The seat of government for this state shall be at Detroit, or at such other place or places as may be prescribed by law until the year eighteen hundred and forty-seven, when it shall be permanently located by the legislature.'' 


Prior to 1847, Detroit had fought to maintain the capital within its jurisdiction, but communities in the growing western part of the state had many reasons for moving inland, including the need to increase defensibility by moving the state government away from the Canadian border. Detroit had been occupied during the War of 1812, and the border area of Michigan of less than a mile between Detroit and Windsor, Ontario, at the Detroit River continued to be occupied by British troops on both banks. Proponents of moving the capital also sought to promote settlement and the economy in the interior, as well as making the great government more accessible to the people throughout the state.

Contenders seeking designation as the new capital included Ann Arbor, Jackson, and Grand Rapids. At one point during the debate, Marshall officials were so certain of its selection that they built a governor's mansion. After extensive debate, state senator Joseph H. Kilbourne of Ingham County proposed that the nearly-uninhabited Lansing Township be made the seat of government. The legislature agreed, with the location north of Ann Arbor, west of Detroit, and east of Grand Rapids being deemed a suitable compromise. The legislature renamed it as the Town of Michigan, though by 1848 the original name of Lansing was restored.

Construction began in 1847 on the state capitol building in Lansing, a temporary structure on the block bordered by Washington Avenue and Capitol Avenue. It was a simple two-story wood frame structure, painted white with green wooden shutters and topped by a tin cupola. The total cost for construction was $22,952.01. The building was sold when the permanent capitol building opened in 1879. It was then used as a factory until, like the first capitol, it was destroyed by a fire in 1882.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0f29061f920c54ef7a5664b48a5bf94b" name="Old_capitol_bldg" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/0f29061f920c54ef7a5664b48a5bf94b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>