<document id="f8b863bd0862467214aab9dfd55543ac-7.8" name="Borat:_Cultural_Learnings_of_America_for_Make_Benefit_Glorious_Nation_of_Kazakhstan" cat="19">
<text>
Prior to being considered for appearance in the film, all potential participants were required to sign long release forms agreeing not to take legal action for any defamation of character or fraud carried out during the film's production. The usual disclaimer included at the end of the film's credits, stating that all characters in the film were fictitious, also noted that "No real person depicted or appearing in the film has sponsored or otherwise endorsed its contents."

After the film's release, Dharma Arthur, a news producer for WAPT-TV in Jackson, Mississippi, wrote a letter to ''Newsweek'' saying that Borat's appearance on the station had led to her losing her job: "Because of him, my boss lost faith in my abilities and second-guessed everything I did thereafter … How upsetting that a man who leaves so much harm in his path is lauded as a comedic genius." Although Arthur has said she was fired from the show, she told the AP that she left the station.Carlson, Erin (November 13, 2006), , ''washingtonpost.com'' She claims to have checked a public relations website that Borat's producers gave her before booking him.

In news coverage that aired in January 2005 of the filming of the rodeo scene, Bobby Rowe, producer of the Salem, Virginia, rodeo depicted in the movie, provided background on how he had become the victim of a hoax. He said that "months" prior to the appearance, he had been approached by someone from "One America, a California-based film company that was reportedly doing a documentary on a Russian immigrant"; he agreed to permit the "immigrant" to sing the U.S. national anthem after listening to a tape. After the film's release, Rowe said "Some people come up and say, 'Hey, you made the big time'; I've made the big time, but not in the way I want it." Cindy Streit, Borat's etiquette consultant has subsequently hired high-profile attorney Gloria Allred, who is demanding the California Attorney General investigate fraud allegedly committed by Baron Cohen and the film's producers. The guest whom Borat had described as a "retard" after "misunderstanding" a statement that he was retired (spoken with a drawl), commented that "I have never been more hurt in my life. When I first found out that the footage was going to be used for a film released in North American cinemas I felt confused, embarrassed, and angry. For the rest of my life I will have to live with the fact that I am featured in a film that contains strong language, nudity, and sex. I am floored."

There are conflicting reports regarding the feelings of the participants in the scenes in which Borat and Azamat stay at a guest house owned by a Jewish couple. The British tabloid ''The Sun'' claims that a scene depicting cockroaches running around in their home has hurt Mariam and Joseph Behar's business in Newton, Massachusetts. The couple were quoted as saying, "This is very insulting. They never told us they were going to do this. It is really terrible." However, the ''Salon'' Arts & Entertainment site quotes the Behars as calling the film "outstanding," referring to Baron Cohen as "very lovely and very polite" and a "genius." The ''Boston Globe'' also interviewed the couple, saying they considered the film more anti-Muslim than anti-Semitic and had feared that Baron Cohen and his ensemble might be filming pornography in the house.

The feminists from Veteran Feminists of America (VFA) also felt that they had been duped, having "sensed something odd was going on" before and during the interview with Borat. ''The Guardian'' later reported at least one of the women felt that the film was worth going to see at the cinema.

The ''New York Post'' had reported in November 2006 that Pamela Anderson filed for divorce from her husband Kid Rock after he reacted unfavorably to the movie during a screening. ''The Post'''s article specifically claimed he had said of her role in the film, "You're nothing but a whore! You're a slut! How could you do that movie?" Anderson later confirmed in an interview on ''The Howard Stern Show'' that Rock was upset by her appearance in the film, but did not confirm this was the cause of the separation.

There has been some debate in United Pentecostal circles regarding the camp meeting's depiction in the film. United Pentecostal ministers are barred from attending mainstream movies at all, and the faithful are strongly admonished against it. SpiritalAbuse.org, 2007-04-04. Retrieved on 2007-07-02.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6fb5f5c33ec8e7b5a158b6bc786f5d13" name="Borat_disclaimer" sectnum="7.8#1">../img/6fb5f5c33ec8e7b5a158b6bc786f5d13.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>