<document id="f8d3a31cdd07e6dd89cf77a7583b3a16-3" name="Mother_and_Child_Reunion_(Degrassi:_The_Next_Generation)" cat="19">
<text>
Producers were able to bring back a number of actors from ''Degrassi High'' to guest star as their characters for the reunion storyline. Stefan Brogren, Pat Mastroianni, Stacie Mistysyn and Amanda Stepto agreed early on to return for the episode to play their characters Archie "Snake" Simpson, Joey Jeremiah, Caitlin Ryan and Christine "Spike" Nelson respectively, and appeared at the CTV press conference in June to publicize the new series. Brogren and Stepto signed contracts to appear in the entire season. Dan Woods also returned to the series in a starring role to play Dan Raditch, now principal of Degrassi Community School.Ellis 2005, pp. 42–51 By the time "Mother and Child Reunion" began to shoot, twelve more former ''Degrassi High'' cast members had agreed to appear: Danah Jean Brown (Trish Skye), Darrin Brown (Dwayne Myers), Michael Carry (Simon Dexter), Irene Courakos (Alexa Pappadopoulos), Chrissa Erodotou (Diana Economopoulos), Anais Granofsky (Lucy Fernandez), Rebecca Haines (Kathleen Mead), Sara Holmes (Alison Hunter), Neil Hope (Derek "Wheels" Wheeler), Kyra Levy (Maya Goldberg), Cathy Keenan (Liz O'Rourke), and Siluck Saysanasy (Yick Yu) all reprised their roles.

For the new generation of students, the producers chose from six hundred auditionees, all of whom were children in an attempt to provide a group of characters that the target audience of teenagers could relate to, rather than actors in their twenties pretending to be teenagers, something other shows of the same period and target audience such as ''Buffy the Vampire Slayer'' and ''Dawson's Creek'' were doing.  Miriam McDonald first auditioned in October 2000 to play Emma Nelson, Spike's daughter, and was selected for the role after a callback and three screen tests. Ryan Cooley appeared as J. T. Yorke, Jake Goldsbie as Toby Isaacs, and Cassie Steele as Manny Santos.Ellis 2005, pp. 74–75, 58–59, 66–67, 80–81 All signed their contracts just days before appearing at the CTV press conference. Christina Schmidt appeared briefly as Terri McGreggor, and Melissa McIntyre appeared in just one scene as Ashley Kerwin; she had no lines to speak in this episode.Ellis 2005, pp. 82, 76–77 Cassie Steele's sister, Alex Steele, made her first appearance as Angela Jeremiah, Joey's six-year-old daughter.Ellis 2005, p. 89 She returned with Mastroianni to the series at the beginning of season two to take on more permanent roles. Also appearing in "Mother and Child Reunion" were Jeff Gruich as Mr. Nystrom, and Nigel Hamer as Mr. Isaacs.

Film director Kevin Smith, who had been a fan of Degrassi from the early 1990s when he worked at a convenience store in Leonardo, New Jersey,Ellis 2005, p. 6 has paid homage to Degrassi by making reference to it in several of his films. For example, he named a ''Clerks'' character Caitlin Bree after Caitlin Ryan, his favorite Degrassi character, wrote Shannen Doherty's character Rene wearing a Degrassi jacket throughout his ''Mallrats'' film, and had Jason Lee's character in ''Chasing Amy'' specifically mention ''Degrassi Junior High'' as the television show he would rather be watching, instead of going out. At the press conference for the new series, Schuyler announced that Smith would be appearing in "Mother and Child Reunion" as Caitlin's boyfriend. However, due to scheduling conflicts, Smith was unable to film the role, which was passed on to Don McKellar, who had previously worked with director Bruce McDonald on a number of productions. Smith, and his View Askewniverse collaborators Jason Mewes and Alanis Morissette, did get the chance to appear in ''Degrassi: The Next Generation'' in the final three episodes of season four, and two episodes of season five.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="909cfcfcc5a695630446202fbdedac5d" name="MaCR_press_conference" sectnum="3#1">../img/909cfcfcc5a695630446202fbdedac5d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>