<document id="f8ddff20e5cbbcbe55dbb84555a38bb7-5" name="Charles_II_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
Another political storm which faced Charles was that of succession to the Throne. The prospect of a Catholic monarch was vehemently opposed by Anthony Ashley Cooper, 1st Earl of Shaftesbury (previously Baron Ashley and a member of the Cabal, which had fallen apart in 1673), and his power base was strengthened when the House of Commons of 1679 introduced the Exclusion Bill, which sought to exclude the Duke of York from the line of succession. Some even sought to confer the Crown to the Protestant Duke of Monmouth, the eldest of Charles's illegitimate children. The ''Abhorrers''—those who thought the Exclusion Bill was abhorrent—were named Tories (after a term for dispossessed Irish Catholic bandits), while the ''Petitioners''—those who supported a petitioning campaign in favour of the Exclusion Bill—became called Whigs (after a term for rebellious Scottish Presbyterians).Hutton, pp. 373, 377, 391 and Miller, ''Charles II'' pp.310–320


Fearing that the Exclusion Bill would be passed, and bolstered by some acquittals in the continuing Plot trials, which seemed to him to indicate a more favourable public mood towards Catholicism, Charles dissolved the English Parliament, for a second time that year, in the summer of 1679. Charles's hopes for a more moderate Parliament were not fulfilled, within a few months he had dissolved Parliament yet again, after it sought to pass the Exclusion Bill. When a new Parliament assembled at Oxford in March 1681, Charles dissolved it for a fourth time after just a few days.Hutton, pp.376–401 and Miller ''Charles II'' pp.314–345 During the 1680s, however, popular support for the Exclusion Bill ebbed, and Charles experienced a nationwide surge of loyalty, for many of his subjects felt that Parliament had been too assertive. Lord Shaftesbury was charged with treason and fled to Holland, where he died. For the remainder of his reign, Charles ruled as an absolute monarch.Hutton, pp.430–441

Charles's opposition to the Exclusion Bill angered some Protestants. Protestant conspirators formulated the Rye House Plot, a plan to murder the King and the Duke of York as they returned to London after horse races in Newmarket. A great fire, however, destroyed Charles's lodgings at Newmarket, which forced him to leave the races early thus, inadvertently, avoiding the planned attack. News of the failed plot was leaked.Fraser, p.426 Protestant politicians such as Arthur Capell, 1st Earl of Essex, Algernon Sydney, Lord William Russell and the Duke of Monmouth were implicated in the plot. Lord Essex slit his own throat while imprisoned in the Tower of London; Sydney and Russell were executed for high treason on very flimsy evidence; and the Duke of Monmouth went into exile at the court of William of Orange. Lord Danby and the surviving Catholic lords held in the Tower were released and the King's Catholic brother, James, acquired greater influence at court.Hutton, pp.420–423 and Miller ''Charles II'' pp.366–368 Titus Oates was convicted and imprisoned for defamation.Fraser, p.437

Charles suffered a sudden apoplectic fit on the morning of 2 February 1685, and died at 11:45 a.m. four days later at Whitehall Palace (at the age of 54). The symptoms of his final illness are similar to those of uraemia (a clinical syndrome due to kidney dysfunction).Fraser, p.450 and Hutton, p.443 On his deathbed Charles asked his brother, James, to look after his mistresses: "be well to Portsmouth, and let not poor Nelly starve",Fraser, p.456 and told his courtiers: "I am sorry, gentlemen, for being such a time a-dying."Bryant, Mark (2001). ''Private Lives''. London: Cassell. ISBN 0304357588 p.73 On the last evening of his life he was received into the Roman Catholic Church, though the extent to which he was fully conscious or committed, and with whom the idea originated, is unclear.Hutton, pp.443 and 456 He was buried in Westminster Abbey "without any manner of pomp" on 14 FebruaryFraser, p.459 and was succeeded by his brother who became James II of England and Ireland and James VII of Scotland.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5fae6a7a280474ea97951cefae17510f" name="charles2coin" sectnum="5#1">../img/5fae6a7a280474ea97951cefae17510f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>