<document id="f9318cc6fcecdb20baecfeb2ee6951f8-2" name="Felice_Beato" cat="1">
<text>
Little is certain about Felice Beato's early development as a photographer, though it is said that he bought his first and only lens in Paris in 1851.Clark, Fraser, and Osman, 90. He probably met British photographer James Robertson in Malta in 1850 and accompanied him to Constantinople in 1851. Robertson had been an engraver at the Imperial Ottoman Mint since 1843 and had probably taken up photography in the 1840s.Broecker, 58; Clark, Fraser, and Osman, 89, 90. In 1853 the two began photographing together and they formed a partnership called "Robertson & Beato" either in that year or in 1854 when Robertson opened a photographic studio in Pera, Constantinople. Robertson and Beato were joined by Beato's brother Antonio on photographic expeditions to Malta in 1854 or 1856 and to Greece and Jerusalem in 1857. A number of the firm's photographs produced in the 1850s are signed "Robertson, Beato and Co." and it is believed that the "and Co." refers to Antonio.Oztuncay, 24; Clark, Fraser, and Osman, 90–91.

  

In late 1854 or early 1855 James Robertson married the Beato brothers' sister, Leonilda Maria Matilda Beato. They had three daughters, Catherine Grace (b. 1856), Edith Marcon Vergence (b. 1859) and Helen Beatruc (b. 1861).

In 1855 Felice Beato and Robertson travelled to Balaklava, Crimea where they took over reportage of the Crimean War following Roger Fenton's departure. They photographed the fall of Sebastopol in September 1855, producing about 60 images.Auer and Auer; Broecker, 58.

In February 1858 Felice Beato arrived in Calcutta and began travelling throughout Northern India to document the aftermath of the Indian Rebellion of 1857.Harris, 23; Dehejia, 121; Auer and Auer; Masselos 2000, 1. Gernsheim states that Beato and Robertson ''both'' travelled to India in 1857, but it is now generally accepted that Beato travelled there alone. Gernsheim, 96. During this time he produced possibly the first-ever photographic images of corpses.Turner, 447. It is believed that for at least one of his photographs taken at the palace of Secundra Bagh in Lucknow he had the skeletal remains of Indian rebels disinterred or rearranged to heighten the photograph's dramatic impact (see events at Taku Forts). He was also in the cities of Delhi, Cawnpore, Meerut, Benares, Amritsar, Agra, Simla and Lahore.Harris, 23; Clark, Fraser, and Osman, 91–92. Beato was joined in July 1858 by his brother Antonio, who later left India, probably for health reasons, in December 1859. Antonio ended up in Egypt in 1860, setting up a photographic studio in Thebes in 1862.Clark, Fraser, and Osman, 90, 91.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ddba056554530ee75101666fa0684f41" name="Secundra_Bagh_after_Indian_Mutiny" sectnum="2#1">../img/ddba056554530ee75101666fa0684f41.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>