<document id="f93a256341a109226a74537de9b268d7-5" name="Zanzibar_Revolution" cat="14">
<text>
One of the main impacts of the revolution in Zanzibar was to break the power of the Arab/Asian ruling class, who had held it for around 200 years.  Despite the merger with Tanganyika Zanzibar retained a Revolutionary Council and House of Representatives which was run on a one party system and had power over domestic matters..  The domestic government is led by the President of Zanzibar, Karume being the first holder of this office.  This government used the success of the revolution to implement reforms across the island.  Many of these involved the removal of power from Arabs, for example the Zanzibar civil service became an almost entirely African organisation and land was redistributed from Arabs to Africans.  However the revolutionary government also instituted social reforms such as free healthcare and the opening up of the education system to African students, who had, occupied only 12% of secondary school places prior to the revolution.

The government sought help from the Soviet Union, the German Democratic Republic (GDR) and China for funding for several projects and military advice.  The failure of several GDR-led projects including the New Zanzibar Project, a 1968 urban redevelopment scheme to provide new apartments for all Zanzibaris, led to Zanzibar focussing on Chinese aid.  The post-revolution Zanzibar government was accused of draconian controls on personal freedoms and travel and exercised nepotism in appointments to political and industrial offices, the new Tanzanian government being powerless to intervene.  Dissatisfaction with the government came to a head with the assassination of Karume on 7 April 1972, which was followed by weeks of fighting between pro and anti-government forces..  A multi-party system was eventually established in 1992, but Zanzibar remains dogged by allegations of corruption and vote-rigging.

The revolution itself remains an event of interest for Zanzibari's and academics.  Historians have analysed the revolution as having a racial and a social basis with some stating that the African revolutionaries represent the proletariat rebelling against the ruling and trading classes, represented by the Arabs and South Asians.  Others discount this theory and present it as a racial revolution that was exacerbated by economic disparity between races.  Within Zanzibar the revolution is a key cultural event and it has been marked by the release of 545 prisoners on its tenth anniversary, and by a military parade on its 40th.  Zanzibar Revolution Day is celebrated on 12 January each year and has been designated as a public holiday by the government of Tanzania.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="15885b2e55076e11b88d03ac54a9dcfb" name="Zanzibar_revolution_40_years" sectnum="5#1">../img/15885b2e55076e11b88d03ac54a9dcfb.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>