<document id="f947a9b1e73f31ed2d8d17e0fb6f7b6c-1.2" name="Rob-B-Hood" cat="19">
<text>
The cast of ''Rob-B-Hood'' includes actors ranging from newcomer Gao Yuanyuan to veteran actor Chen Baoguo. Daniel Wu and Nicholas Tse, stars of ''New Police Story'', make cameo appearances as homosexual security van drivers during a car chase in the film.

Octopus, Thong's partner in crime, is played by Louis Koo, an award winning actor with past appearances including the TVB drama series ''Detective Investigation Files IV'' and the films ''Election'' and ''Election 2''. Although Koo co-starred with Jackie Chan, a number of action scenes involving his character were shot with a stunt double. In addition, Koo was the baby's favourite on set—Whenever the baby cried, Koo was always the first to cheer him up. 

The Landlord, the leader of Thongs and Octopus, is played by Michael Hui, a Hong Kong Film Award-winning comedic actor who starred in various box office hits from 1970s to 1990s before emigrating to Canada shortly before the handover of Hong Kong. Hui was chosen for the part because he is the ideal actor to play a character who persuades others to do bad things. The producers had originally intended Hui to fight along with Chan and Koo, however, it was eventually decided that Hui would simply act as the brains of the gang.

''Rob-B-Hood'' features a collaboration between Chan and Yuen Biao. The pair, along with Sammo Hung, were Peking Opera School classmates and co-starred in a number of action comedy films in the 1980s, including ''Project A'', ''Wheels on Meals'', and the ''Lucky Stars'' trilogy. Chan had originally intended to co-star with both Yuen and Hung, reuniting the trio for the first time since 1988's ''Dragons Forever''. However, Hung declined due to scheduling conflicts. Yuen Biao plays the role of Police Inspector Mok, assigned to investigate the baby's disappearance. Some of Yuen's past antics were revisited in ''Rob-B-Hood'', including a fight in which he tried in vain to handcuff Chan's character.

Over 100 auditions were held before the suitable baby was found to star in the film. Benny Chan chose Matthew Medvedev, a one-year old infant of Chinese and Colombian descent. Medvedev, known as Baby Matthew, was literally recruited off the street when an assistant director spotted him with his parents on the MTR. Although his family was simply visiting Hong Kong, they agreed to stay and let Matthew appear in ''Rob-B-Hood''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6e0caf02ef84ce32f6321bc73b808572" name="Rbh_F" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/6e0caf02ef84ce32f6321bc73b808572.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>