<document id="f98a8f5d28b9c13d11a48e424b7af28c-2" name="Battle_of_Barrosa" cat="29">
<text>
Following Soult's appropriation of many of Victor's troops, the Allies sensed an opportunity to both engage Marshal Victor in an open battle and to raise the siege of Cádiz..  To that end, an Anglo-Spanish expedition was sent by sea from Cádiz to Tarifa, with the intention of marching north to engage the French rear.  This force comprised some 8,000 Spanish and 4,000 British troops, with the overall command ceded to the Spanish General Manuel la Peña, a political accommodation since he was widely regarded as incompetent..  To coincide with la Peña's assault, it was arranged that General Zayas would lead a force of 4,000 Spanish troops in a sally from Cádiz, via a pontoon bridge from the Isla de León..

The British contingent&mdash;an Anglo-Portuguese division commanded by Lieutenant-General Sir Thomas Graham&mdash;sailed from Cádiz on 21 February 1811, somewhat later than planned..  Graham's forces were unable to land at Tarifa due to bad weather and were forced to sail on to Algeciras, where they disembarked on 23 February..  Joined by a composite battalion of flank companies under Colonel Browne, the troops marched to Tarifa on 24 February, where they received a further reinforcement from the fortress garrison there..  By 27 February, they were joined by la Peña's Spanish troops, who had left Cádiz three days after Graham and, despite encountering similar weather difficulties, had succeeded in landing at Tarifa.

To further strengthen the Allied ranks, a force of Spanish irregulars under General Beguines had been ordered to come down from the Ronda mountains by 23 February and join the main Anglo-Spanish force. Unaware of the delays in sailing, Beguines had advanced as far as Medina-Sidonia in search of the Allied army; unsupported, and embroiled in skirmishes with Victor's right flank, he returned to the mountains.  General Cassagne, Victor's flank commander, informed the Marshal of the developing threat. Victor responded by sending three infantry battalions and a cavalry regiment to reinforce Cassagne, and ordering the fortification of Medina-Sidonia..

Having concentrated, the combined Allied force began marching north towards Medina-Sidonia on 28 February, and la Peña now ordered Beguines's irregulars to join them at Casas Viejas.  Once there, however, Beguines's scouts reported that Medina-Sidonia was held more strongly than had been anticipated. Rather than engaging the French and forcing Victor to weaken his siege by committing more of his troops to the town's defence, la Peña decided that the Allied army should march across country and join the road that ran from Tarifa, through Vejer and Chiclana, to Cádiz..



This change of plan, combined with further bad weather and la Peña's insistence on marching only at night, meant the Allied force was now two days behind schedule.  La Peña sent a message to Cádiz informing Zayas of the delay, but the dispatch was not received and on 3 March, Zayas launched his sally as arranged.Ironically, the messenger, a Spanish officer sent in a fishing boat, was detained by a Royal Navy brig as a 'suspicious character' .  A pontoon bridge was floated across the Santi Petri creek and a battalion sent across to establish a bridgehead prior to the arrival of the main force.  Victor could not allow the Cádiz garrison, which still numbered about 13,000 men, to make a sortie against his lines while he was threatened from outside, so on the night of 3&ndash;4 March he sent six companies of ''voltigeurs'' to storm the bridgehead entrenchments and prevent a breakout.  Zayas's battalion was ejected from its positions, with 300 Spanish casualties, and Zayas was forced to float the pontoon bridge back to the island for future use..   claims that the bridgehead was actually held, but  agrees that this sortie was repelled.

Marshal Victor had, by now, received intelligence from a squadron of dragoons that had been driven out of Vejer, informing him of the strong Anglo-Spanish force making its way up the western road from Tarifa.  In conjunction with the aggressive action of the Cádiz garrison, this led him to conclude that the approaching troops were heading for Cádiz; their line of march was therefore predictable, so he prepared a trap..  General Villatte's division was sent to block the neck of the peninsular on which the western road ran, preventing access to the Santi Petri creek and the Isla de Léon.  Two other divisions, under the commands of Generals Ruffin and Leval, were ordered to conceal themselves in the thick Chiclana forest in position to attack the flank of the Allies as they engaged Villatte's division..

After another night march, on 5 March the Allies reached a hill to the south east of Barrosa, the Cerro del Puerco (also referred to as the Barrosa Ridge).  Scouts reported the presence of Villatte's force, and la Peña ordered his vanguard division to advance.  With the aid of a fresh sortie of Zayas's troops from Cádiz, and reinforced by a brigade of the Prince of Anglona's division, the Spanish drove Villatte's force across the Almanza Creek..  La Peña refused his vanguard permission to pursue the retreating French, who were consequently able to regroup on the far side of the creek.  Graham's Anglo-Portuguese division had remained behind on the Cerro del Puerco to defend the rear and right flank of la Peña's main force..
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="fcf79955418d284102394d8dfeafc7b6" name="Thomas_Graham_Lord_Lynedoch" sectnum="2#1">../img/fcf79955418d284102394d8dfeafc7b6.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>