<document id="f98a8f5d28b9c13d11a48e424b7af28c-3.3" name="Battle_of_Barrosa" cat="29">
<text>
Advancing up the ridge they had just abandoned, Browne's battalion came under intense fire from Ruffin's emplaced infantry and artillery. Within a few salvoes, half the battalion was gone and, unable to continue, Browne's men scattered amongst the cover provided by the slope and returned fire..  Despite his success, Ruffin could not descend the hill to brush away the remnants of Browne's battalion, as Dilkes's brigade had by now emerged from the wood and was forming up at the base of the slope..

Dilkes, instead of following Browne's route up the slope, advanced to the right where there was more cover and ground not visible to the French.  As a result, the French artillery could not be brought to bear, and Dilkes's brigade managed to get near the top of the ridge without suffering serious loss.  By this time, though, its formation had become disorganised, so Ruffin deployed four battalion columns in an attempt to sweep both Dilkes and the remaining "Flankers" back down the slope. Contrary to French expectations, the crude British line stopped the attacking columns in their tracks, and the two forces exchanged fire.Ruffin later spoke of "''the incredibility of such a rash attack''" .  Marshal Victor, by then himself on the crest of the ridge, brought up his reserve in two battalion columns of grenadiers.  These columns were, as with the previous four, subjected to intense musket fire and were brought to a halt just metres from the British line.  The first four columns had started to give ground, so Victor tried to disengage his reserves and bring them to their support.  However, as the two grenadier columns attempted to move off from their stalled positions, they came under additional fire from the remnants of Browne's battalion, which had renewed its own advance.  Prevented from rallying, the entire French force broke and fled to the valley below.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e5f748c89dc644334cf109092db69e25" name="Viktor" sectnum="3.3#1">../img/e5f748c89dc644334cf109092db69e25.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>