<document id="f9983935d2abf59bc8bb63203f07f25f-1.3.6" name="Byzantine_navy" cat="29">
<text>
The ascension of Emperor Basil I (867–886) heralded this revival, as he embarked on an aggressive foreign policy. Continuing the policies of his predecessor, Michael III (842–867), he showed great care to the fleet, and as a result, successive victories followed. In 867, a fleet under the ''droungarios tou plōïmou'' Niketas Ooryphas relieved Dalmatia from Arab attacks and reestablished Byzantine presence in the area. A few years later, he twice heavily defeated the Cretan pirates, temporarily securing the Aegean. Cyprus also was temporarily recovered and Bari occupied. At the same time, however, the Muslim presence in Cilicia was strengthened, and Tarsos became a major base for land and seaborne attacks against Byzantine territory, especially under the famed emir Yazaman al-Khadim (882–891).

In the West, the Muslims continued to make steady advances, as the local Byzantine forces proved inadequate: the Empire was forced to rely on the aid of their nominal Italian subjects, and had to resort to the transfer of the eastern fleets to Italy to achieve any progress. Following the fall of Enna in 855, the Byzantines were confined to the eastern shore of Sicily, and under increasing pressure. A relief expedition in 868 achieved little. Syracuse was attacked again in 869, and in 870, Malta fell to the Aghlabids. Muslim corsairs raided the Adriatic, and although they were driven out of Apulia, in the early 880s they established bases along the western Italian coast, from where they would not be completely dislodged until 915. In 878, Syracuse, the main Byzantine stronghold in Sicily, was attacked again and fell, largely because the Imperial Fleet was occupied with transporting marble for the construction of the ''Nea Ekklesia'', Basil's new church. In 880, Ooryphas' successor, the ''droungarios'' Nasar, scored a significant victory in a night battle over the Tunisians who were raiding the Ionian Islands. He then proceeded to raid Sicily, carrying off much booty, before defeating another Muslim fleet off Punta Stilo. At the same time, another Byzantine squadron scored a significant victory at Naples. These successes allowed a short-lived Byzantine counteroffensive to develop in the West in the 870s and 880s under Nikephoros Phokas the Elder, expanding the Byzantine foothold in Apulia and Calabria and forming the ''thema'' of Longobardia, which would later evolve into the Catepanate of Italy. A heavy defeat off Milazzo in 888, however, signaled the virtual disappearance of major Byzantine naval activity in the seas around Italy for the next century.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2eba5a598fcbc5cdd75b0a52d9da8613" name="Solidus-Basil_I_with_Constantine_and_Eudoxia-sb1703" sectnum="1.3.6#1">../img/2eba5a598fcbc5cdd75b0a52d9da8613.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>