<document id="f9983935d2abf59bc8bb63203f07f25f-4.12" name="Byzantine_navy" cat="29">
<text>
Unlike the warships of Antiquity, Byzantine and Arab ships did not feature rams, and the primary means of ship-to-ship combat were boarding actions and missile fire, as well as the use of inflammable materials such as Greek fire. Despite the fearsome reputation of the latter, it was only effective under certain circumstances, and not the decisive anti-ship weapon that the ram had been in the hands of experienced crews.

Like their Roman predecessors, Byzantine and Muslim ships were equipped with small catapults (''mangana'') and ballistae (''toxoballistrai'') that launched stones, arrows, javelins, pots of Greek fire or other incendiary liquids, caltrops (''triboloi'') and even containers full of lime to choke the enemy or, as Emperor Leo VI somewhat implausibly suggests, scorpions and snakes.Leo VI the Wise, ''Tactica'', XIX.61–65, transl. in  Marines and the upper-bank oarsmen were heavily armored in preparation for battle (Leo refers to them as "cataphracts") and armed with close-combat arms such as lances and swords, while the other sailors wore padded felt jackets (''neurika'') for protection and fought with bows and crossbows. The importance and volume of missile fire during sea combat can be gauged from the fleet manifests for the Cretan expeditions of the 10th century, which mention 10,000 caltrops, 50 bows and 10,000 arrows, 20 hand-carried ''ballistrai'' with 200 bolts called ''myai'' ("flies") and 100 javelins per dromon.

From the 12th century on, the crossbow (called , ''tzangra'' in Greek) became increasingly important in Mediterranean warfare, remaining the most deadly weapon available until the advent of fully rigged ships with gunpowder artillery. The Byzantines made infrequent use of the weapon, chiefly in sieges, although its use is recorded in some sea battles. Cannons were introduced in the latter half of the 14th century, but they were rarely used by the Byzantines, who only had a few artillery pieces for the defense of the land walls of Constantinople. Unlike the Venetians and Genoese, there is no indication that the Byzantines ever mounted any on ships.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5e6dddde1678030a4dc4000fd89470ec" name="Liquid_fire_granades_Chania" sectnum="4.12#1">../img/5e6dddde1678030a4dc4000fd89470ec.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>