<document id="fa774a3d87df390c60374735a831bd6f-5.4" name="Kid_A" cat="20">
<text>
The cover art, by Donwood and Tchock (an alias for Thom Yorke), is a computer rendering of a mountain range, with pixelated distortion near the bottom. It was a reflection of the war in Kosovo in winter 1999. Donwood was affected by a photograph in ''The Guardian'', saying the war felt like it was happening in his own street. Influenced by Victorian era military art depicting British colonial subjects, Donwood also produced colourful oil paintings, creating a sharp texture with knives and putty. The back cover is a digitally modified depiction of another snowscape with fires raging through fields. ''Kid A'' came with a booklet of Donwood and Tchock artwork, printed on both glossy paper and thick tracing paper. Near the back there is a large triptych-style fold-out drawing.


Some of the artwork was seen to take a more explicitly political stance than the album's lyrics. The red swimming pool on the spine of the CD case and on the disc represents what Donwood termed "a symbol of looming danger and shattered expectations". It came from the graphic novel ''Brought to Light'' by Alan Moore and Bill Sienkiewicz, in which the CIA measures its killings through state-sponsored terrorism by the equivalent number of 50-gallon swimming pools filled with human blood. This image haunted Donwood throughout the ''Kid A'' project. Early pressings of ''Kid A'' came with an extra booklet of artwork hidden under the CD tray. The booklet contained political references, including a demonic portrait of then-British Prime Minister Tony Blair surrounded by warnings of demagoguery.

A special edition of ''Kid A'' was also released, in a thick cardboard package in the style of a children's book with a new cover and different oil paintings of apocalyptic landscapes and bear images.  Although in the same style as the album art, these paintings were without digital distortion. The book included a page with statistics on world glacier melt rates, paralleling the art's themes of environmental degradation. In 2006, Donwood and Tchock exhibited Radiohead album artwork in Barcelona, with a focus on ''Kid A''. An art book documenting the work and Donwood's inspirations, called ''Dead Children Playing'', was also issued.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="3c38a87af792a8983ad306e20bc9c958" name="Glaciers" sectnum="5.4#1">../img/3c38a87af792a8983ad306e20bc9c958.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>