<document id="fa77af39834ba95d16e428f199ac981e-3" name="Jaws_(film)" cat="19">
<text>
Richard D. Zanuck and David Brown, producers at Universal Pictures, heard about Peter Benchley's novel at identical times at different locations. Brown came across it in the fiction department of ''Cosmopolitan'', a lifestyle magazine then edited by his wife, Helen Gurley Brown. A small card gave a detailed description of the plot, concluding with the comment "might make a good movie".Brown, David, "A Look Inside ''Jaws''", produced by Laurent Bouzereau, available as a bonus feature on some laserdisc and DVD releases of ''Jaws'' The producers each read it overnight and agreed the next morning that it was "the most exciting thing that they had ever read" and that, although they were unsure how they would accomplish it, they wanted to produce the film.Zanuck, Richard D., "A Look Inside ''Jaws''", produced by Laurent Bouzereau, available as a bonus feature on some laserdisc and DVD releases of ''Jaws'' Brown says that had they read the book twice they would have never have made the film because of the difficulties in executing some of the sequences. They purchased the film rights to Benchley's novel in 1973 for approximately $175,000.

Zanuck and Brown had originally planned to hire Dick Richards, a filmmaker of considerable experience, to direct the film. However, they grew irritated by Richards' vision of directing "a movie about a whale"; Richards was subsequently dropped from the project, and Zanuck and Brown then signed Spielberg to direct before the release of his first theatrical film, ''The Sugarland Express'' (also a Zanuck/Brown production). Spielberg wanted to take the novel's basic concept, removing Benchley's many subplots. The film makers removed the novel's adulterous affair between Ellen Brody and Matt Hooper because it would compromise the camaraderie between the men when they went out on the ''Orca''.

When they purchased the rights to his novel, the producers guaranteed that the author would write the first draft of the screenplay. Overall, Benchley wrote three drafts before deciding to bow out of the project (although he appeared in the final film, a cameo appearance as a news reporter). Tony and Pulitzer Prize-winning playwright Howard Sackler happened to be in Los Angeles when the filmmakers began looking for another writer and offered to do an uncredited rewrite, and since the producers and Spielberg were unhappy with Benchley's drafts, they quickly accepted his offer. ''Spotlight on Location: The Making of Jaws'', ''Jaws'' 30th Anniversary DVD documentary,   Spielberg sent the script to Carl Gottlieb (who appears in a supporting acting role in the film as Meadows, the politically connected reporter), asking for advice. Gottlieb rewrote most scenes during principal photography, and John Milius contributed dialogue polishes. Spielberg has claimed that he prepared his own draft, although it is unclear if the other screenwriters drew on his material. The authorship of Quint's monologue about the fate of the cruiser USS ''Indianapolis'' has caused substantial controversy as to who deserves the most credit for the speech. Spielberg described it as a collaboration among John Milius, Howard Sackler and actor Robert Shaw. Gottlieb gives primary credit to Shaw, downplaying Milius' contribution.Gottlieb, Carl. (2001) ''The Jaws Log''. ISBN 0-571-20949-1


Three mechanical sharks were made for the production: a full version for underwater shots, one that moved from camera-left to right (with its hidden side completely exposing the internal machinery), and an opposite model with its right flank uncovered. Their construction was supervised by production designer Joe Alves and special effects artist Bob Mattey. After the sharks were completed, they were shipped to the shooting location, but unfortunately had not been tested in water and when placed in the ocean the full model sank to the ocean floor. A team of divers retrieved it.

Location shooting occurred on the island of Martha's Vineyard, Massachusetts, chosen because the ocean had a sandy bottom while  out at sea. This helped the mechanical sharks to operate smoothly and still provide a realistic location. Still, the film had a famously troubled shoot and went considerably over budget. David Brown said that the budget "was $4 million and the picture wound up costing $9 million". Shooting at sea led to many delays: unwanted sailboats drifted into frame, cameras were soaked, and the ''Orca'' once began to sink with the actors onboard. The mechanical shark frequently malfunctioned, due to the hydraulic innards being corroded by salt water. The three mechanical sharks were collectively nicknamed "Bruce" by the production team after Spielberg's lawyer. Disgruntled crew members gave the film the nickname "Flaws".

To some degree, the delays in the production proved serendipitous. The script was refined during production, and the unreliable mechanical sharks forced Spielberg to shoot most of the scenes with the shark only hinted at. For example, for much of the shark hunt its location is represented by the floating yellow barrels. This forced restraint is widely thought to have increased the suspense of these scenes, giving it a Hitchcockian tone.  This suspenseful restraint was also intended from the moment Spielberg was contracted for the movie as one of his conditions was that he didn't have to show the shark for the first hour.Inside the Actor's Studio: Steven Spielberg

The scene where Hooper discovers fisherman Ben Gardner's body in the hull of his wrecked boat was added after an initial screening of the film. Actor Craig Kingsbury had to press his head into a latex mold to make an exact copy, which was then attached to a fake body and placed in the wrecked boat's hull. The team filmed many takes of the scene where the head suddenly appears. After reactions to that screening, Spielberg said he was greedy for "one more scream" and, with $3,000 of his own money, financed the scene after he was denied funding from Universal Pictures.

Footage of real sharks was shot by Ron and Valerie Taylor in the waters off Australia, with a dwarf actor in a miniature shark cage to create the illusion that the shark was enormous. Originally, the script, following the novel, had the shark killing Hooper in the shark cage, but during filming, one of the sharks became trapped in the girdle of the cage, and proceeded to tear the cage apart. The cage contained no one at the time, so the script was changed to allow Matt Hooper to live and the cage to be empty. Despite the rare footage of a great white shark exhibiting violent behavior, only a handful of these shots were used in the finished film.

The role of Quint was originally offered to actors Lee Marvin and Sterling Hayden, both of whom passed. Producers Zanuck and Brown had just finished working with Robert Shaw on ''The Sting'', and suggested him to Spielberg as a possible Quint. Roy Scheider became interested in the project after overhearing a screenwriter and Spielberg at a party talking about having the shark jump up onto a boat. Richard Dreyfuss initially passed on the role of Matt Hooper, but after being disappointed by his own performance in a pre-release screening of ''The Apprenticeship of Duddy Kravitz'', a film he had just completed, he immediately called Spielberg and accepted the role, fearing that no one would want to hire him once ''Kravitz'' was released. The first person actually cast for the film was Lorraine Gary, the wife of then-studio chief, Sid Sheinberg.

Spielberg himself was not present for the shooting of the final scene where the shark explodes. Spielberg believed that the crew were planning to throw him in the water when this scene was complete. It has since become a tradition for Spielberg to be absent when the final scene of a film he directs is being filmed.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e79f538c518e926d25635b54c5769968" name="Mechashark" sectnum="3#1">../img/e79f538c518e926d25635b54c5769968.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>