<document id="fa77af39834ba95d16e428f199ac981e-5" name="Jaws_(film)" cat="19">
<text>
''Jaws'' bears similarities to several literary and artistic works, most notably ''Moby-Dick'' by Herman Melville. The character of Quint strongly resembles Captain Ahab, the obsessed captain of the ''Pequod'' who devotes his life to hunting a sperm whale. Quint's monologue reveals his similar vendetta against sharks, and even his boat, the ''Orca'', is named after the only natural enemy of the white shark. In the novel and original screenplay, Quint dies after being dragged under the ocean by a harpoon tied to his leg, similar to Ahab's death in Melville's novel. A direct reference to these similarities may be found in the original screenplay, which introduced Quint by showing him watching the film version of ''Moby-Dick''. His laughter throughout makes people get up and leave the theater (Wesley Strick's screenplay for ''Cape Fear'' features a similar scene). However, the scene from ''Moby-Dick'' could not be licensed from Gregory Peck, the owner of the rights.

It's widely acknowledged that Peter Benchley modeled Quint on Brooklyn-born fisherman Frank Mundus, nicknamed the "Monster Man," and some accounts claim that the seed from which Jaws later sprang was planted when Benchley read a newspaper article about Mundus hauling in a huge great white shark off the coast of Long Island in the early 1960s.
--> In the novel and original screenplay, when the ''Orca'', like the ''Pequod'' is sunk by the creature, only Brody was to have survived. Some have also noticed the influences of two 1950s horror films, ''The Creature from the Black Lagoon'' and ''The Monster That Challenged the World''.

Similarities to Henrik Ibsen's play ''An Enemy of the People'' have also been noted by critics.  The Ibsen work features a Doctor who discovers that a seaside town's medicinal hot springs, a major tourist attraction and form of revenue, are contaminated, and attempts to convince his fellow townspeople of the danger. This leads to the Doctor losing his job and being disowned by the townspeople. This parallels Brody's conflict with Mayor Vaughn, who refuses to acknowledge the presence of a shark that may dissuade summer beachgoers from coming to Amity.  Of course, this film has Brody's concerns vindicated undeniably when there are more shark attacks at the crowded beach in broad daylight.  The sequel, ''Jaws 2'', would make perhaps more overt references to the Ibsen work, particularly in the town council and business interests who vote to fire Brody.

''Jaws'' was a key film in establishing the benefits of a wide national release backed by heavy media advertising, rather than a progressive release that let a film slowly enter new markets and build support over a period of time. Rather than let the film gain notice by word-of-mouth, Hollywood launched a successful television marketing campaign for the film, which added another $700,000 to the cost. The wide national release pattern would become standard practice for high-profile movies in the late 1970s and afterward.

The film conjured up so many scares that beach attendance was down in the summer of 1975 due to its profound impact. Though a horror classic (its opening sequence was voted the scariest scene ever by a Bravo Halloween TV special), the film is widely recognized as being responsible for fearsome and inaccurate stereotypes about sharks and their behavior. Benchley has said that he would never have written the original novel had he known what sharks are really like in the wild. He later wrote ''Shark Trouble'', a non-fiction book about shark behavior and ''Shark Life'', another non-fiction book describing his dives with sharks. Conservation groups have bemoaned the fact that the film has made it considerably harder to convince the public that sharks should be protected. ''Jaws'' set the template for many future horror films, so much so that the script for Ridley Scott's 1979 science fiction film ''Alien'' was pitched to studio executives with one tag line: "Jaws in space." A line from ''Jaws'' also inspired the name of Bryan Singer's production company ''Bad Hat Harry'', as it is his favorite film. The film has been adapted into two video games, two theme park rides at Universal Studios Florida and Universal Studios Japan,  and two musicals: "JAWS The Musical!", which premiered in the summer of 2004 at the Minnesota Fringe Festival; and "Giant Killer Shark: The Musical," which premiered in the summer of 2006 at the Toronto Fringe Festival. In 2009, Aristocrat acquired the rights from Universal Studios to make a video slot machine based on the motion picture.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5b549175d856c37365e9124705222983" name="UniversalStudiosJawsShark" sectnum="5#1">../img/5b549175d856c37365e9124705222983.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>