<document id="fa8185a85aac7ffa79a7f00a631aa7ae-4" name="Ecclesiastical_heraldry" cat="25">
<text>
Saint Peter was represented holding keys as early as the fifth century. As the Roman Catholic Church considers him the first pope and bishop of Rome, the keys were adopted as a papal emblem; they first appear with papal arms in the 13th century.Noonan, ''The Church Visible'', p.189. Two keys perpendicular were often used on coins, but beginning in the 15th century were used to represent St. Peter's Basilica. Perpendicular keys last appeared in the shield of the papacy in 1555, after which the crossed keys are used exclusively.Galbreath, ''Papal Heraldry'', p.6–7. The keys are gold and silver, with the gold key placed to dexter (viewer's left) on the personal arms of the Pope, although two silver keys or two gold keys were used late into the 16th century.Galbreath, ''Papal Heraldry'', p.12–13. The keys as a symbol of Saint Peter may be found within many coats of arms; the coat of arms of the Prince-Archbishopric of Bremen displayed two argent (silver) crossed keys as Saint Peter is the patron saint of the Bremian archiepiscopal cathedral.

The Papal Tiara or ''triregnum'' is the three-tiered crown used by the Pope as a sovereign power. It is first found as an independent emblem in the 13th century, though at that time with only one coronet.Galbreath, ''Papal Heraldry'', p.22. In the 15th century, the tiara was combined with the keys above the papal shield. The tiara and keys together within a shield form the arms of Vatican City. In heraldry, the white tiara is depicted with a bulbous shape and with two attached red strips called lappets or infulae.Noonan, ''The Church Visible'', p.195. The coat of arms of Pope Benedict XVI sparked controversy by displaying a mitre and pallium instead of the customary tiara.

The red and gold striped ombrellino or pavilion was originally a processional canopy or sunshade and can be found so depicted as early as the 12th century.Galbreath, ''Papal Heraldry'', p.27. The earliest use of the ombrellino in heraldry is in the 1420s when it was placed above the shield of Pope Martin V. It is more commonly used together with the keys, a combination first found under Pope Alexander VI.Galbreath, ''Papal Heraldry'', p.31. This combined badge represents the temporal power of Vatican City between Papal reigns, when the acting head of state is the cardinal Camerlengo. The badge first appeared with a cardinal's personal arms on coins minted by order of the Camerlengo, Cardinal Armellini, during the inter-regnum of 1521. During the 17th and 18th centuries, it appeared on coins minted ''sede vacante'' by papal legates, and on coins minted in 1746 and 1771 while a pope reigned.Galbreath, ''Papal Heraldry'', p.34. The ombrellino appears in the arms of basilicas since the 16th century, with ornamentation for major basilicas. If found in a family's coat of arms, it indicates that a relative had been pope.von Volborth, ''Heraldry of the World'', p.172.


The papal coat of arms is often depicted with angels as supporters.''Vocabolario Araldico Ufficiale della Consulta Araldica'' (1907), images 384 and 420. Other Catholic or Anglican clergy do not use supporters unless they were awarded as a personal honor, or were inherited with family arms.Boutell, ''Boutell's Heraldry'', p.224;  Some cathedral arms use a single chair (cathedra) as a supporter.See .
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="cd4398108e35998e27347e90458afd91" name="Medici_Leo_XI" sectnum="4#1">../img/cd4398108e35998e27347e90458afd91.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>