<document id="fa872286e40d63b9d1850d3f9797034a-7" name="Exmoor" cat="11">
<text>
The attractions of Exmoor include 208 scheduled ancient monuments, 16 conservation areas, and other open access land as designated by the Countryside and Rights of Way Act 2000. Exmoor receives approximately 1.4 million visitor days per year. Many come to walk on the moors or along waymarked paths such as the Coleridge Way. Attractions on the coast include the Lynton and Lynmouth Cliff Railway, which connects Lynton to neighbouring Lynmouth, where the East and West Lyn River meet. Woody Bay, a few miles west of Lynton, is home to the Lynton & Barnstaple Railway, a narrow gauge railway which connected the twin towns of Lynton and Lynmouth to Barnstaple, about 31 km (just over 19 miles) away.''The Lynton & Barnstaple Railway Magazine'' published by The L&BR Trust. Various editions  Further along the coast, Porlock is a quiet coastal town with an adjacent salt marsh nature reserve and a harbour at nearby Porlock Weir. Watchet is a historic harbour town with a marina and is home to a carnival, which is held annually in July. 

Inland, many of the attractions are centred around small towns and villages or linked to the river valleys, such as the ancient clapper bridge at Tarr Steps and the Snowdrop Valley near Wheddon Cross, which is carpeted in snowdrops in February and, later, displays bluebells. Withypool is also in the Barle Valley. The Two Moors Way passes through the village. As well as Dunster Castle, Dunster's other attractions include a priory, dovecote, yarn market, inn, packhorse bridge, mill and a stop on the West Somerset Railway. Exford, lies on the River Exe. Brendon, in the Brendon Valley is noted for the annual Exmoor folk festival.

Exmoor has been the setting for several novels including the 19th-century ''Lorna Doone: A Romance of Exmoor'' by Richard Doddridge Blackmore,  and Margaret Drabble's 1998 novel ''The Witch of Exmoor''. The park was featured on the television programme ''Seven Natural Wonders'' twice, as one of the wonders of the West Country.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0d65004825eaf59522356d69ca3a057b" name="North_Devon_Exmoor" sectnum="7#1">../img/0d65004825eaf59522356d69ca3a057b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>