<document id="fab4b82dcf65dbf68da99e994eecd5ce-4" name="Forest_Park_(Portland,_Oregon)" cat="11">
<text>
Forest Park lies in the Coast Range ecoregion designated by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA). Reverse side  In its natural state, the forest consists mainly of three tree species, Douglas-fir, western hemlock, and western red cedar, and smaller numbers of grand fir, black cottonwood, red alder, bigleaf maple, madrone, and western yew. Much of the forest that existed here before 1850 was gone by 1940. The stage of re-growth in the forest depends on when it was last logged or burned.Houle, pp. 16&ndash;23

In the mid-1990s, about one percent of the total vegetation in the park consisted of grasses, bracken, thistle, and fireweed in sections of the forest cleared two to five years earlier. Another two percent had reached the shrub stage, between three and thirty years old, with small trees dominated by such plants as thimbleberry, salmonberry, and blackberry. Forest areas 10 to 30 years old that contained tall alder and maple trees and smaller conifers accounted for about 20 percent of the park.

Larger areas were occupied by forests in which conifers had grown taller than the alders and maples. About 50 percent of Forest Park consists of these areas, which are between 30 and 80 years old and in which Douglas-firs have begun to dominate. Another 25 percent of the park contains forests dominated by middle-aged conifers, 80 to 250 years old. In these areas, red alders, which live for about 100 years, have begun to die, and the Douglas-firs, which can live for 750 years, attain heights up to about . Under the big trees are shade-tolerant trees such as western red cedar, western hemlock, and grand fir and smaller plants such as Oregon-grape, vine maple, and salal.

The last forest stage, old growth, is reached after 250 years and includes many snags, downed and dead trees, and fallen logs. Timber-cutting and fires reduced old growth in Forest Park to "almost nothing"  by 1940, and most of the forest has not yet attained this stage. Patches exist near Macleay Park and further west near Germantown Road and Newton Road. The largest tree in Forest Park is a Douglas-fir near the Stone House, the remains of a former public restroom near Balch Creek. It is  high, and the trunk is  in circumference.    

Among the prominent wildflowers are Hooker's fairy bells, vanilla leaf, evergreen violet, and trillium.Houle, p. 18 Invasive species include English ivy, European holly, clematis, morning glory, and Himalayan blackberry. Citizen groups such as the No Ivy League and Friends of Forest Park engage in projects to remove ivy, maintain trails, and plant native species.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="5e380246b5215dcbc968f81cc89bac40" name="Forest_park_oregon_grape_flowering_P3932" sectnum="4#1">../img/5e380246b5215dcbc968f81cc89bac40.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>