<document id="fac84533054ac2bc3fc5a679e68a140d-3.2" name="Pride_and_Prejudice_(1995_TV_serial)" cat="19">
<text>
The budget of about £1 million per episode (totalling US$9.6 million) allowed 20 shooting weeks of five days to complete the filming of six 55-minute episodes. Production aimed for 10.5-hour shooting days plus time for costume and make-up.Birtwistle and Conklin 1995, pp. 27&ndash;34. Two weeks before filming began, about 70 of the cast and crew gathered for the script read-through, followed by rehearsing, lessons for dancing, horse-riding, fencing, and other skills that needed to be ready ahead of the actual filming. Filming took place between June 1994 and 1 November 1994 to reflect the changing seasons in the plot, followed by post-production until mid-May 1995. Scenes in the same geographical area were grouped together in the filming schedule.


Twenty-four locations, most of them owned by the National Trust, and eight studio sets were used for filming.Birtwistle and Conklin 1995, pp. 35&ndash;43.Birtwistle and Conklin 1995, pp. 73&ndash;78. Reflecting the wealth differences between the main characters, the filming location for Longbourn showed the comfortable family house of the Bennet family, whereas Darcy's Pemberley needed to look like the "most beautiful place", showcasing good taste and the history of the aristocracy. The first location that the producers agreed on was Lacock in Wiltshire to represent the village of Meryton. Luckington Court, which was in close proximity, served as the interior and exterior of Longbourn during 10 weeks of filming. Lyme Hall in Cheshire was chosen as Pemberley, but management problems forced production to film Pemberley's interiors at Sudbury Hall in Sudbury, Derbyshire.Birtwistle and Conklin 1995, pp. 22&ndash;26. 

The producers found Belton House in Grantham, Lincolnshire to best match Lady Catherine de Bourgh's estate, Rosings, which needed to appear "over-the-top" to reflect the disagreeableness of its fictional owner. Old Rectory at Teigh in Leicestershire was chosen as Hunsford parsonage, Mr Collins's modest home. Edgcote Hall in Banbury, Oxfordshire served as the interior and exterior of Netherfield, Bingley's estate, along with Brocket Hall in Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire as the Netherfield ballroom. The London streets and coaching inn were filmed in Lord Leycester Hospital in Warwick, Warwickshire. Wickham's and Georgiana's planned elopement in Ramsgate was filmed in the English seaside resort Weston-super-Mare in Somerset.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ac6435b7f1499c89465c44a8e3fcd90d" name="Lyme_Park_2" sectnum="3.2#1">../img/ac6435b7f1499c89465c44a8e3fcd90d.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>