<document id="fac8f46f64593fe57e13c4ff49921ac1-2.1" name="Jaguar" cat="3">
<text>
The last taxonomic delineation of the jaguar subspecies was performed by Pocock in 1939. Based on geographic origins and skull morphology, he recognized eight subspecies. However, he did not have access to sufficient specimens to critically evaluate all subspecies, and he expressed doubt about the status of several. Later consideration of his work suggested only three subspecies should be recognized.

Recent studies have also failed to find evidence for well defined subspecies, and are no longer recognized. Larson (1997) studied the morphological variation in the jaguar and showed that there is clinal north–south variation, but also that the differentiation within the supposed subspecies is larger than that between them and thus does not warrant subspecies subdivision. A genetic study by Eizirik and coworkers in 2001 confirmed the absence of a clear geographical subspecies structure, although they found that major geographical barriers such as the Amazon River limited the exchange of genes between the different populations. A subsequent, more detailed, study confirmed the predicted population structure within the Colombian jaguars.

Pocock's subspecies divisions are still regularly listed in general descriptions of the cat.", Taxonomy, pp. 5–7, Jaguar Species Survival Plan Seymore grouped these in three subspecies.

# ''Panthera onca onca'': Venezuela through the Amazon, including
#* ''P. onca peruviana'' ('''Peruvian Jaguar'''): Coastal Peru
# ''P. onca hernandesii'' ('''Mexican Jaguar'''): Western Mexico – including
#* ''P. onca centralis'' ('''Central American Jaguar'''): El Salvador to Colombia
#* ''P. onca arizonensis'' ('''Arizonan Jaguar'''): Southern Arizona to Sonora, Mexico
#* ''P. onca veraecrucis'': Central Texas to Southeastern Mexico
#* ''P. onca goldmani'' ('''Goldman's Jaguar'''): Yucatan Peninsula to Belize and Guatemala
# ''P. onca palustris'' (the largest subspecies, weighing more than 135 kg or 300 lb): The Pantanal regions of Mato Grosso & Mato Grosso do Sul, Brazil, along the Paraguay River into Paraguay and possibly northeastern Argentina.

The ''Mammal Species of the World'' continues to recognize nine subspecies, the eight subspecies above and additionally ''P. o. paraguensis''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a8cf996d87a98f94fc96e0ecbf20ae9a" name="Jaguar_tier_2" sectnum="2.1#1">../img/a8cf996d87a98f94fc96e0ecbf20ae9a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>