<document id="fac84533054ac2bc3fc5a679e68a140d-6.9" name="Pride_and_Prejudice_(1995_TV_serial)" cat="19">
<text>
The serial is often associated with a scene in its fourth episode where a fully-dressed Darcy, having emerged from a swim in a lake, accidentally encounters Elizabeth. While many critics attributed the scene's appeal to Firth's sexual attractiveness and vice versa, Andrew Davies thought that it unwittingly "rerobed, not disrobed, Austen". When he originally wrote the scene (it was not part of Austen's novel), he did not intend to highlight a sexual connection between Elizabeth and Darcy but create "an amusing moment in which Darcy tries to maintain his dignity while improperly dressed and sopping wet". The BBC opposed Davies's initial plan of having Darcy naked, but the producers discarded the proposed alternative of using underpants as anachronistic and silly. Since (according to Davies) Firth also had "a bit of the usual tension about getting  kit off", the scene was filmed with Firth in his character's linen shirt, breeches and boots. A stuntman, who appears in midair in a very brief shot, was hired because of the risk of infection with Weil's disease at Lyme Park. A short underwater segment was filmed separately with Firth in a tank at Ealing Studios in West London.

''The Guardian'' declared the lake scene "one of the most unforgettable moments in British TV history". The sequence also appeared in Channel 4's Top 100 TV Moments in 1999, between the controversial programme ''Death on the Rock'' and the Gulf War. ''The New York Times'' compared the scene's indelibility to Marlon Brando's shouting "Stella!" in his undershirt in ''A Streetcar Named Desire'', and Firth's future projects began alluding to it &ndash; screenwriter/director Richard Curtis added in-joke moments of Firth's characters falling into the water to ''Love Actually'' and ''Bridget Jones: The Edge of Reason'', and Firth's character from the 2007 film ''St Trinian's'' emerges from a fountain in a soaking wet shirt before meeting up with an old love. The creators of the 2008 ITV production ''Lost in Austen'' emulated the lake scene in their ''Pride and Prejudice'' reinterpretation through their modern-day heroine who cajoles Darcy into recreating the iconic moment for her. 

Cheryl L. Nixon suggested in ''Jane Austen in Hollywood'' that Darcy's dive is a "revelation of his emotional capabilities", expressing a "Romantic bond with nature, a celebration of his home where he can 'strip down' to his essential self, a cleansing of social prejudices from his mind, or ... a rebirth of his love for Elizabeth".Nixon 1998, p. 24. Linda Troost and Sayre Greenfield summarised in the same book that the scene "tells us more about our current decade's obsession with physical perfection and acceptance of gratuitous nudity than it does about Austen's Darcy, but the image carves a new facet into the text".Troost and Greenfield 1998, p. 6.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="053f9349b9aa2cb25a8162c18160d54e" name="Pride_and_Prejudice_Colin_Firth_Wet_Shirt" sectnum="6.9#1">../img/053f9349b9aa2cb25a8162c18160d54e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>