<document id="faff1c20fbc964bce00abd863437458e-1.1" name="Chiffchaff" cat="3">
<text>
*''P. c. collybita'', the nominate form, breeds in Europe east to Poland and Bulgaria, and is described below. It mainly winters in the south of its breeding range around the Mediterranean and in North Africa. It has been expanding its range northwards into Scandinavia since 1970 and close to the southern edge of the range of ''P. c. abietinus''.

*''P. c. abietinus'' occurs in Scandinavia and northern Russia, and winters from southeastern Europe and northeastern Africa east to Iraq and western Iran. It is intermediate in appearance between ''P. c. tristis'' and ''P. c. collybita'', being grey-washed olive-green above with a pale yellow supercilium, and underparts whiter than in ''P. c. collybita'', but it has very similar vocalisations to the nominate subspecies. Due to individual variation, it can be difficult to reliably separate ''P. c. abietinus'' and ''P. c. collybita'' outside their main breeding and wintering ranges.

*''P. (c.) tristis'', the '''Siberian Chiffchaff''', breeds in Siberia east of the Pechora River and winters in the lower Himalayas. It is a dull subspecies, grey or brownish above and whitish below, with little yellow in the plumage, and the buff-white supercilium is often longer than in the western subspecies. It has  a higher pitched ''suitsistsuisit'' song and a short high-pitched ''cheet'' call. It is sometimes considered to be a full species due to its distinctive plumage and vocalisations, being similar to ''P. s. sindianus'' in these respects.Helbig, Andreas J.; Martens, Jochen; Seibold, I.; Henning, F.; Schottler, B; Wink, Michael (1996): Phylogeny and species limits in the Palearctic Chiffchaff ''Phylloscopus collybita'' complex: mitochondrial genetic differentiation and bioacoustic evidence. ''Ibis'' 138 (4): 650–666  Nominate ''P. c. collybita'' and ''P. c. tristis'' do not recognize each other's songs. Schubert, M. (1982): Zur Lautgebung mehrerer zentralasiatischer Laubsänger-Arten (''Phylloscopus''; Aves, Sylviidae). ''Mitteilungen aus dem Zoologischen Museum Berlin'' 58: 109–128. Martens, Jochen; Meincke, C. (1989): Der sibirische Zilpzalp (''Phylloscopus collybita tristis''): Gesang und Reaktion einer mitteleuropäischen Population im Freilandversuch. ''Journal für Ornithologie'' 130 (4): 455–473.   Pending resolution of the status of ''P. (c.) fulvescens'', which is found where the ranges of ''P. c. abietinus'' and ''P. c. tristis'' connect and may Marova, I. M. & Leonovich, V. V. (1993)  ''Sbornik Trudov Zoologicheskogo Muzeya, Moskovskogo Gosudarstvennogo Universiteta'' 30: 147–163. or may not be a hybrid between these, ''tristis'' is maintained in ''P. collybita''.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="0241001da4795b3e7d6a00aae34ae8d5" name="Spectrogramcollybita2" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/0241001da4795b3e7d6a00aae34ae8d5.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>