<document id="faff1c20fbc964bce00abd863437458e-1.2" name="Chiffchaff" cat="3">
<text>
* ''P. ibericus'', the '''Iberian Chiffchaff''' is brighter, greener on the rump, and yellower below than ''P. collybita'', and has a ''tit-tit-tit-tswee-tswee'' song. It was initially named ''P. brehmii'', but the type specimen of that taxon is not an Iberian Chiffchaff. This species is found in Portugal and Spain, west of a line stretching roughly from the western Pyrenees Salomon, Marc (1989):  ''Behaviour'' 111 (1–4): 270–290. via the mountains of central Spain to the Mediterranean; the Iberian and Common Chiffchaffs co-occur in a narrow band along this line. Balmori, Alfonso; Cuesta, Miguel Ángel; Caballero, José María (2002):  . ''Ardeola'' 49(1): 19–27. Apart from the northernmost section, the precise course of the contact zone is not well-documented. A long-distance migrant, this species winters in western Africa. It differs from ''P. c. collybita'' in vocalisations,Salomon, Marc; Hemim, Y. (1992): ''Ethology'' 92 (4): 265–282. external morphology,Salomon, Marc; Bried, J.; Helbig, Andreas J.; Riofrio, J. (1997) Morphometric differentiation between male Common Chiffchaffs, ''Phylloscopus  collybita'' Vieillot, 1817, and Iberian Chiffchaffs, ''P.  brehmii'' Homeyer, 1871, in a secondary contact zone (Aves: Sylviidae). ''Zoologischer Anzeiger'' 236: 25–36. and mtDNA sequences. Helbig, Andreas J.; Salomon, Marc; Bensch, S. & Seibold, I. (2001): ''Journal of Evolutionary Biology'' 14: 277–287.  There is  hybridization in the contact zone,, almost always between male ''P. ibericus'' and female ''P. c. collybita'',  and hybrids apparently show much decreased fitness;  hybrid females appear to be sterile according to Haldane's Rule. Helbig, Andreas J.; Salomon, Marc; Wink, Michael; Bried, Joël (1993):  ''C. R. Acad. Sci. III'' 316: 205–210. Regarding the latter aspect, it is interesting to note that the Iberian Chiffchaff apparently is the oldest lineage of chiffchaffs and quite distinct from the Common Chiffchaff.


*''P. canariensis'', the '''Canary Islands Chiffchaff''' is a non-migratory species formerly occurring on the major Canary Islands, which is differentiated from ''P. collybita'' by morphology, vocalisations and genetic characteristics, and, of course, is not sympatric with any other chiffchaffs. The nominate western subspecies ''P. c. canariensis'' of El Hierro, La Palma, La Gomera, Tenerife, and Gran Canaria is smaller than Common Chiffchaff, and has shorter, rounder wings. It is olive-brown above and has a buff breast and flanks; it has a rich deep ''chip-cheep-cheep-chip-chip-cheep'' song, and a call similar to the nominate race. The eastern ''P. c. exsul'' of Lanzarote and possibly Fuerteventura is paler above and less rufous below than its western relative, and had a harsher call; it might have been a distinct species, but it became extinct in 1986 at latest, probably much earlier. The reasons for its extinction are unclear, but it appears always to have been scarce and localised, occurring only in the Haria Valley of Lanzarote.

*''P. sindianus'', the '''Mountain Chiffchaff''', is found in the Caucasus (''P. s. lorenzii'') and Himalayas (''P. s. sindianus''), and is an altitudinal migrant, moving to lower levels in winter. The nominate subspecies is similar to ''P. c. tristis'', but with a finer darker bill, browner upperparts and buff flanks; its song is almost identical to ''P. collybita'', but the call is a weak ''psew''. ''P. s. lorenzii'' is warmer and darker brown than the nominate race; it is sympatric with Common Chiffchaff in a small area in the Western Caucasus, but interbreeding occurs rarely, if ever. The Mountain Chiffchaff differs from ''tristis'' in vocalisations, Martens, Jochen (1982): Ringförmige Arealüberschneidung und Artbildung beim Zilpzalp, ''Phylloscopus collybita''. Das ''lorenzii''-Problem. ''Zeitschrift für Zoologische Systematik und Evolutionsforschung'' 20: 82–100. Martens, Jochen; Hänel, Sabine (1981): Gesangformen und Verwandtschaft der asiatischen Zilpzalpe ''Phylloscopus collybita abietinus'' und ''Ph. c. sindianus''. ''Journal für Ornithologie'' 122 (4): 403–427.   external morphology,Cramp, Stanley. (ed.) (1992): ''The Birds of the Western Palearctic'', Vol. 6. Oxford University Press, Oxford. and mtDNA sequences. Its two subspecies appear to be distinct vocally, and also show some difference in mtDNA sequences; they are maintained at subspecies rank pending further research.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="eb194028a4c9989a96fc67584eea0688" name="Lz10_pano_2" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/eb194028a4c9989a96fc67584eea0688.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>