<document id="fb06f0811bb2933e974471758302c3a9-2.3" name="James_II_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
After Oliver Cromwell's death in 1658 and the subsequent collapse of the Commonwealth in 1660, Charles II was restored to the English throne.  Although James was the heir-presumptive, it seemed unlikely that he would inherit the crown, as Charles was still a young man capable of fathering children.Callow, 89. Upon his brother's restoration, James was created Duke of Albany in Scotland, to go along with his English title, Duke of York. Upon his return to England, James produced an immediate controversy by announcing his engagement to Anne Hyde, the daughter of Charles' chief minister, Edward Hyde.Callow, 90. In 1659, while attempting to seduce her, James promised he would marry Anne.Miller, 44. Anne became pregnant in 1660, but following the Restoration and Charles's return to power, no one at the royal court expected a prince to marry a commoner, no matter what he had pledged beforehand.Miller, 44–5.  Although nearly everyone, including Anne's father, urged the two not to marry, they did so.  The couple was married secretly, then went through an official marriage ceremony on 3 September 1660, in London.  Their first child, Charles, was born less than two months later, but died in infancy, as did five further sons and daughters.  Only two daughters survived: Mary (born 30 April 1662) and Anne (born 6 February 1665).Waller, 49–50  Samuel Pepys wrote that James was fond of his children and his role as a father, writing that he played with them "like an ordinary father", a contrast to the distant parenting common to royals at the time.Miller, 46.  James's wife was devoted to him and influenced many of his decisions.Miller, 45–46.  Even so, he kept a variety of mistresses, including Arabella Churchill and Catherine Sedley, and was reputed to be "the most unguarded ogler of his time."Miller, 46.  Samuel Pepys recorded in his diary that James "did eye my wife mightily". Ibid.  James's taste in women was often maligned, with Gilbert Burnet famously remarking that James's mistresses must have been "given him by his priests as a penance." Miller, 59.  Anne Hyde died in 1671.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ece6d62294ae35b8f4eacaa2335408b4" name="James_II_and_Anne_Hyde_by_Sir_Peter_Lely" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/ece6d62294ae35b8f4eacaa2335408b4.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>