<document id="fb06f0811bb2933e974471758302c3a9-2.6" name="James_II_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
In 1677, James reluctantly consented to his daughter Mary's marriage to the Protestant William of Orange (who was also James's nephew).  James acquiesced after his brother Charles and William had agreed upon the marriage.Miller, 84; Waller, 94–97.  According to Turner, James's reaction to the agreement was "The King shall be obeyed, and I would be glad if all his subjects would learn of me to obey him".  Turner, 132.  Despite the Protestant marriage, fears of a potential Catholic monarch persisted, intensified by the failure of Charles II and his wife, Catherine of Braganza, to produce any children.  A defrocked Anglican clergyman, Titus Oates, spoke of a "Popish Plot" to kill Charles and put the Duke of York on the throne.Miller, 87  The fabricated plot caused a wave of anti-Catholic hysteria to sweep across the nation.



In England, the Earl of Shaftesbury, a former government minister and now a leading opponent of Catholicism, attempted to have James excluded from the line of succession.Miller, 99–105  Some members of Parliament even proposed that the crown go to Charles's illegitimate son, James Scott, 1st Duke of Monmouth.Harris, 74  In 1679, with the Exclusion Bill in danger of passing, Charles II dissolved Parliament.Miller, 93–95  Two further Parliaments were elected in 1680 and 1681, but were dissolved for the same reason.Miller, 103–104  The Exclusion Crisis contributed to the development of the English two-party system:  the Whigs were those who supported the Bill, while the Tories were those who opposed it.  Ultimately, the succession was not altered, but James was convinced to withdraw from all policy-making bodies and to accept a lesser role in his brother's government.Miller, 90

On the orders of the King, James left England for Brussels.Miller, 87–91  In 1680, he was appointed Lord High Commissioner of Scotland and took up residence at the Palace of Holyroodhouse in Edinburgh in order to suppress an uprising and oversee royal government.Miller, 95  James returned to England for a time when Charles was stricken ill and appeared to be near death.Miller, 98–99  The hysteria of the accusations eventually faded, but James's relations with many in the English Parliament, including the Earl of Danby, a former ally, were forever strained and a solid segment turned against him.Miller, 89; Callow, 180–183
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6cf95badb662264aebd9b6b16f7c26a3" name="James_Scott" sectnum="2.6#1">../img/6cf95badb662264aebd9b6b16f7c26a3.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>