<document id="fb06f0811bb2933e974471758302c3a9-2.5" name="James_II_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
James's time in France had exposed him to the beliefs and ceremonies of Catholicism; he and his wife, Anne, became drawn to that faith.Miller, 58–59; Callow, 144–145.  Callow writes that Anne "made the greatest single impact upon his thinking" and that she converted shortly after the Restoration, "almost certainly before her husband". Ibid., 144.  James took Eucharist in the Roman Catholic Church in 1668 or 1669, although his conversion was kept secret for some time and he continued to attend Anglican services until 1676.Callow, 143–144; Waller, 135  In spite of his conversion, James continued to associate primarily with Anglicans, including John Churchill and George Legge, as well as French Protestants, such as Louis de Duras, the Earl of Feversham.Callow, 149

Growing fears of Catholic influence at court led the English Parliament to introduce a new Test Act in 1673.Miller, 69–71  Under this Act, all civil and military officials were required to take an oath (in which they were required not only to disavow the doctrine of transubstantiation, but also denounce certain practices of the Catholic Church as "superstitious and idolatrous") and to receive the Eucharist under the auspices of the Church of England.Kenyon, 385  James refused to perform both actions, instead choosing to relinquish the post of Lord High Admiral.  His conversion to Catholicism was thereby made public.

Charles II opposed the conversion, ordering that James's daughters, Mary and Anne, be raised as Protestants.Waller, 92  Nevertheless, he allowed James to marry the Catholic Mary of Modena, a fifteen-year-old Italian princess.Waller, 16–17  James and Mary were married by proxy in a Catholic ceremony on 20 September 1673.Miller, 73  On 21 November, Mary arrived in England and Nathaniel Crew, Bishop of Oxford, performed a brief Anglican service that did little more than recognise the Catholic marriage.Turner, 110–111  Many of the English, distrustful of Catholicism, regarded the new Duchess of York as an agent of the Pope.Waller, 30–31
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ed44f6bda665ebe13f1bb64dae9afd1a" name="Mary_of_modena_lg" sectnum="2.5#1">../img/ed44f6bda665ebe13f1bb64dae9afd1a.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>