<document id="fb06f0811bb2933e974471758302c3a9-5.12" name="James_II_of_England" cat="25">
<text>
In France, James was allowed to live in the royal château of Saint-Germain-en-Laye.Miller, 235 James's wife and some of his supporters fled with him, including the Earl of Melfort; most, but not all, were Catholic.Miller, 235–236 In 1692, James's last child, Louisa Maria Teresa, was born. online at burkes-peerage.net (accessed 9 February 2008) Some supporters in England attempted to restore James to the throne by assassinating William III in 1696, but the plot failed and the backlash made James's cause less popular.Miller, 238; Waller, 350 Louis XIV's offer to have James elected King of Poland in the same year was rejected, for James feared that acceptance of the Polish crown might (in the minds of the English people) render him incapable of being King of England. After Louis concluded peace with William in 1697, he ceased to offer much in the way of assistance to James.Miller, 239

During his last years, James lived as an austere penitent.Miller, 234–236 He wrote a memorandum for his son advising him on how to govern England, specifying that Catholics should possess one Secretary of State, one Commissioner of the Treasury, the Secretary at War, with the majority of the officers in the army.Macaulay, 445  He died of a brain hemorrhage on 16 September 1701 at Saint-Germain-en-Laye.Miller, 240 His body was laid to rest in a coffin at the Chapel of Saint Edmund in the Church of the English Benedictines in the Rue St. Jacques in Paris, with a funeral oration by Henri-Emmanuel de Roquette. In 1734, the Archbishop of Paris heard evidence to support James's canonization, but nothing came of it. During the French Revolution, James's tomb was raided and his remains scattered.Miller, 240; Waller, 401; MacLeod, 349. MacLeod and Waller say all of James's remains were lost.  says parts of his bowel sent to the parish church of St. Germain-en-Laye were rediscovered in 1824 and are the only known remains left. The ''English Illustrated Magazine''s  on St. Germain from September 1901 concurs.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ef3d19712d732128b15be1584c69c72f" name="Château_de_Saint-Germain-en-Laye01" sectnum="5.12#1">../img/ef3d19712d732128b15be1584c69c72f.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>