<document id="fbdbd8e2ce3c1d124f61203169f91a77-3.19" name="Tang_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
The Chinese of the Tang period employed complex chemical formulas for an array of different purposes, often found through experiments of alchemy. These included a waterproof and dust-repelling cream or varnish for clothes and weapons, fireproof cement for glass and porcelain wares, a waterproof cream applied to silk clothes of underwater divers, a cream designated for polishing bronze mirrors, and many other useful formulas.. The vitrified, translucent ceramic known as porcelain was invented in China during the Tang, although many types of glazed ceramics preceded it..

Ever since the Han Dynasty (202 BC - 220 AD), the Chinese had drilled deep boreholes to transport natural gas from bamboo pipelines to stoves where cast iron evaporation pans boiled brine to extract salt.. During the Tang Dynasty, a gazetteer of Sichuan province stated that at one of these 182 m (600 ft) 'fire wells', men collected natural gas into portable bamboo tubes which could be carried around for dozens of km (mi) and still produce a flame.. These were essentially the first gas cylinders; Robert Temple assumes some sort of tap was used for this device.

The inventor Ding Huan (fl. 180 AD) of the Han Dynasty invented a rotary fan for air conditioning, with seven wheels 3 m (10 ft) in diameter and manually powered.. In 747, Emperor Xuanzong had a "Cool Hall" built in the imperial palace, which the ''Tang Yulin'' (唐語林) describes as having water-powered fan wheels for air conditioning as well as rising jet streams of water from fountains.. During the subsequent Song Dynasty, written sources mentioned the air conditioning rotary fan as even more widely used..

This Tang yellow-glazed pottery horse includes a carefully sculpted saddle, which is decorated with leather straps and ornamental fastenings featuring eight-petalled flowers and apricot leaves.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a039717f49ffb663f7a97380a5661f3c" name="Plat_à_offrandes_Chine_Musée_Guimet_2418_1" sectnum="3.19#1">../img/a039717f49ffb663f7a97380a5661f3c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>