<document id="fbdbd8e2ce3c1d124f61203169f91a77-1.2.2" name="Tang_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
Following the Sui Dynasty's example, the Tang abandoned the nine-rank system in favor of a large civil service system. Students of Confucian studies were potential candidates for the imperial examinations, the graduates of which could be appointed as state bureaucrats in the local, provincial, and central government. There were two types of exams that were given, ''mingjing'' ('illuminating the classics examination') and ''jinshi'' ('presented scholar examination')..  The ''mingjing'' was based upon the Confucian classics, and tested the student's knowledge of a broad variety of texts.  The ''jinshi'' tested a student's literary abilities in writing essay-style responses to questions on matters of governance and politics, as well as their skills in composing poetry..  Candidates were also judged on their skills of deportment, appearance, speech, and level of skill in calligraphy, all of which were subjective criteria that allowed the already wealthy members of society to be chosen over ones of more modest means who were unable to be educated in rhetoric or fanciful writing skills. There was a disproportionate number of civil officials coming from aristocratic as opposed to non-aristocratic families. The exams were open to all male subjects whose fathers were not of the artisan or merchant classes,. although having wealth or noble status was not a prerequisite in receiving a recommendation.. In order to promote widespread Confucian education, the Tang government established state-run schools and issued standard versions of the Five Classics with selected commentaries.

This competitive procedure was designed to draw the best talent into government. But perhaps an even greater consideration for the Tang rulers, aware that imperial dependence on powerful aristocratic families and warlords would have destabilizing consequences, was to create a body of career officials having no autonomous territorial or functional power base. The Tang law code ensured equal division of inherited property amongst legitimate heirs, allowing a bit of social mobility and preventing the families of powerful court officials in becoming landed nobility through primogeniture.. As it turned out, these scholar-officials acquired status in their local communities and in family ties, while they also shared values that connected them to the imperial court. From Tang times until the end of the Qing Dynasty in 1912, scholar-officials functioned often as intermediaries between the grassroots level and the government. Yet the potential of a widespread examination system was not fully realized until the Song Dynasty, where the merit-driven scholar official largely shed his aristocratic habits and defined his social status through the examination system... As historian Patricia Ebrey states of the Song period scholar-officials:



Nevertheless, the Sui and Tang dynasties institutionalized and set the foundations for the civil service system and this new elite class of exam-drafted scholar-officials.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="beb99a0a33a6e63035164f750700527e" name="Tang-xuanzong" sectnum="1.2.2#1">../img/beb99a0a33a6e63035164f750700527e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>