<document id="fbdbd8e2ce3c1d124f61203169f91a77-1.1" name="Tang_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
The Li family belonged to the northwest military aristocracy prevalent during the reign of the Sui emperors.. The mothers of both Emperor Yang of Sui (r. 604-617) and the founding emperor of Tang were sisters, making these two emperors of different dynasties first cousins.. Li Yuan (later to become Emperor Gaozu of Tang, r. 618-626) was the Duke of Tang and former governor of Taiyuan when other government officials were fighting off bandit leaders in the collapse of the Sui Empire, caused in part by a failed Korean campaign... With prestige and military experience, he later rose in rebellion along with his son Li Shimin (later Emperor Taizong, r. 626-649) and his equally militant daughter Princess Pingyang (d. 623) who raised her own troops and commanded them.. In 617, Li Yuan occupied Chang'an and acted as regent over a puppet child emperor of the Sui, relegating Emperor Yang to the position of ''Taishang Huang'', or retired emperor/father of the present emperor. With the news of Emperor Yang's murder by his general Yuwen Huaji (d. 619), on June 18, 618, Li Yuan declared himself the emperor of a new dynasty, the Tang..

Li Yuan ruled until 626 before being forcefully deposed by his son Li Shimin, Prince of Qin. Li Shimin had commanded troops since the age of 18, had prowess with a bow, sword, lance, and was known for his effective cavalry charges.. Fighting a numerically superior army, he defeated Dou Jiande (573-621) at Luoyang in the Battle of Hulao on May 28, 621... In a violent elimination of royal family due to fear of assassination, Li Shimin ambushed and killed two of his brothers, Li Yuanji (b. 603) and Crown Prince Li Jiancheng (b. 589) in the Incident at Xuanwu Gate on July 2, 626. Shortly thereafter, his father abdicated in his favor and Li Shimin ascended the throne. He is conventionally known by his temple name Taizong (唐太宗). Although killing two brothers and deposing his father contradicted the Confucian value of filial piety,. Taizong showed himself to be a capable leader who listened to the advice of the wisest members of his council.  In 628, Emperor Taizong held a Buddhist memorial service for the casualties of war, and in 629 had Buddhist monasteries erected at the sites of major battles so that monks could pray for the fallen on both sides of the fight.. This was during the campaign against Eastern Tujue, a Göktürk khanate that was destroyed after the capture of Jiali Khan Ashini Duobi by the famed Tang military officer Li Jing (571-649), who later became a Chancellor of the Tang Dynasty. With this victory, the Turks accepted Taizong as their Khagan, or Great Khan (天可汗), in addition to his rule as the Son of Heaven...
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="a9deec24037e52e05c8837abc6307219" name="Emperor_Taizong_gives_an_audience_to_the_ambassador_of_Tibet" sectnum="1.1#1">../img/a9deec24037e52e05c8837abc6307219.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>