<document id="fbdbd8e2ce3c1d124f61203169f91a77-1.5.11" name="Tang_Dynasty" cat="14">
<text>
Palace ladies in a garden from a mural of Prince Li Xian's tomb in the Qianling Mausoleum, where Wu Zetian was also buried in 706
Although she entered Emperor Gaozong's court as the lowly consort Wu Zhao, Wu Zetian would rise to the highest seat of power in 690, establishing the short-lived later Zhou Dynasty. Empress Wu's rise to power was achieved through cruel and calculating tactics. For example, she allegedly killed her own baby girl and blamed it on Gaozong's empress so that the empress would be demoted.  Emperor Gaozong suffered a stroke in 655, and Wu began to make many of his court decisions for him, discussing affairs of state with his councilors that would take orders from her while she sat behind a screen.. When Empress Wu's eldest son and crown prince began to assert his authority and announce his support for issues that were opposed to Empress Wu's ideas, he suddenly died in 675. Many suspected he was poisoned by Empress Wu. Although the next heir apparent kept a lower profile, in 680 he was accused by Wu of plotting a rebellion and was banished (and later forced to commit suicide).. After only six weeks on the throne in 683, Emperor Zhongzong was deposed by Empress Wu after his attempt to appoint his wife's father as chancellor.  Because she dominated the court of Emperor Ruizong (r. 684-690), a group of Tang princes and their allies staged a major rebellion against Empress Wu in 684; her armies suppressed their dissent within two months. Becoming China's first female emperor in 690 upon her son's forced abdication, she ruled until shortly before her death in 705, deposed by her own retainers while her designated heir became Emperor Zhongzong again..

In order to legitimize her rule, she circulated a document known as the ''Great Cloud Sutra'', which predicted that a reincarnation of the Maitreya Buddha would be a female monarch who would dispel illness, worry, and disaster from the world... She even introduced numerous revised written characters to the written language, which reverted back to the originals after her death.. Arguably the most important part of her legacy was diminishing the power of the northwest aristocracy, allowing people from other clans and regions of China to become more representative in Chinese politics and government...
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="cdb75bdeff8f74e304a7d7c1572188aa" name="Wild_goose_pagoda_xian_china" sectnum="1.5.11#1">../img/cdb75bdeff8f74e304a7d7c1572188aa.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>