<document id="fc66f418ce7c7855daed259ca643fb0a-4.6" name="Naval_Battle_of_Guadalcanal" cat="29">
<text>
Both ''Kirishima'' and ''Ayanami'' were scuttled and sank by 03:25, November 15.Morison, ''The Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 281; Hammel, ''Guadalcanal:  Decision at Sea'', p. 391. ''Uranami'' rescued survivors from ''Ayanami'' and destroyers ''Asagumo'', ''Teruzuki'', and ''Samidare'' rescued the remaining crew from ''Kirishima''.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 484; ''Atago'', ''Takao'', and ''Nagara'' returned to Japan for repairs, with all three being out of action for about one month.  ''Chōkai'' was repaired at Truk and returned to Rabaul on December 2, 1942. (combinedfleet.com). ''Gwin'' and ''South Dakota'' were repaired and returned to action a few months later: ''Gwin'' in April 1943, and ''South Dakota'' in February 1943.  In the engagement, 242 U.S. and 249 Japanese sailors died.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 486. The engagement was one of only two battleship-against-battleship surface battles in the entire Pacific campaign of World War II, the other being at the Surigao Strait during the Battle of Leyte Gulf.


The four Japanese transports beached themselves at Tassafaronga on Guadalcanal by 04:00, November 15 and Tanaka and the escort destroyers departed and raced back up the Slot towards safer waters. The transports were attacked, beginning at 05:55 by U.S. aircraft from Henderson Field and elsewhere, and field artillery from U.S. ground forces on Guadalcanal. Later, destroyer ''Meade'' approached and opened fire on the beached transports and surrounding area. These attacks set the transports afire and destroyed any equipment on them that the Japanese had not managed to quickly unload. Only 2,000–3,000 of the troops originally embarked actually made it to Guadalcanal, and most of their ammunition and food supplies were lost.Evans, ''Japanese Navy'', p. 195–197; Morison, ''The Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 282–284; Hammel, ''Guadalcanal:  Decision at Sea'', p. 394–395; Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 488–490; Jersey, ''Hell's Islands'', p. 307–308. Morison and Jersey state that 2,000 Japanese soldiers landed with 260 cases of ammunition and 1,500 bags of rice. Lost were provisions for 30,000 men for 20 days, 22,000 artillery shells, thousands of cases of small-arms ammunition, and 76 large and seven small landing craft. Realizing that the transports would not have enough time to unload before daybreak, Tanaka asked permission to run them aground. Mikawa rejected his request, but Kondo accepted it, so Tanaka ordered the transport captains to run their ships aground. The American artillery that shelled the beached transports was from the 244th Coast Artillery Battalion and 3rd Defense Battalion, including two  guns and several 5-inch guns.

Yamamoto's reaction to Kondo's failure to accomplish his mission of neutralizing Henderson Field and ensuring the safe landing of troops and supplies was milder than his earlier reaction to Abe's withdrawal, perhaps because of Imperial Navy culture and politics. Kondo, who also held the position of second in command of the Combined Fleet, was a member of the upper staff and battleship "clique" of the Imperial Navy while Abe was a career destroyer specialist. Admiral Kondo was not reprimanded or reassigned but instead was left in command of one of the large ship fleets based at Truk.Hara, ''Japanese Destroyer Captain'', p. 157, 171.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="4272fb2a5d4fc517cef47fe3a869b970" name="BeachedTransports" sectnum="4.6#1">../img/4272fb2a5d4fc517cef47fe3a869b970.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>