<document id="fc66f418ce7c7855daed259ca643fb0a-4.5" name="Naval_Battle_of_Guadalcanal" cat="29">
<text>
Kondo split his force into several groups, with one group, commanded by Shintaro Hashimoto and consisting of ''Sendai'' and destroyers ''Shikinami'' and ''Uranami''  ("C" on the maps), sweeping along the east side of Savo Island, and destroyer ''Ayanami'' ("B" on the maps) sweeping counterclockwise around the southwest side of Savo Island to check for the presence of Allied ships.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 234, 273–274; Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 473. The Japanese ships spotted Lee's force around 23:00, though Kondo misidentified the battleships as cruisers.  Kondo ordered the ''Sendai'' group of ships, plus ''Nagara'' and four destroyers ("D" on the maps) to engage and destroy the U.S. force before he brought the bombardment force of ''Kirishima'' and heavy cruisers ("E" on the maps) into Ironbottom Sound. The U.S. ships ("A" on the maps) detected the ''Sendai'' force on radar but did not detect the other groups of Japanese ships. Using radar targeting, the two U.S. battleships opened fire on the ''Sendai'' group at 23:17. Admiral Lee ordered a cease fire about five minutes later after the radar returns on the northern group appeared to disappear from his ship's radar scopes. However, ''Sendai'', ''Uranami'', and ''Shikinami'' were undamaged and circled out of the danger area.Kilpatrick, ''Naval Night Battles'', p. 116–117; Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 274; Hammel, ''Guadalcanal:  Decision at Sea'', p. 362–364; Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 475.


Meanwhile, the four U.S. destroyers in the vanguard of the U.S. formation began engaging both ''Ayanami'' and the ''Nagara'' group of ships at 23:22. ''Nagara'' and her escorting destroyers responded effectively with accurate gunfire and torpedoes, and destroyers ''Walke'' and ''Preston'' were hit and sunk within 10 minutes with heavy loss of life. The destroyer ''Benham'' had part of her bow blown off by a torpedo and had to retreat (she sank the next day), and destroyer ''Gwin'' was hit in her engine room and put out of the fight.Kilpatrick, ''Naval Night Battles'', p. 118–121; Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 475–477; Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 274–275; Hammel, ''Guadalcanal:  Decision at Sea'', p. 368–383. However, the U.S. destroyers had completed their mission as screens for the battleships, absorbing the initial impact of contact with the enemy, although at great cost.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 478. Lee ordered the retirement of ''Benham'' and ''Gwin'' at 23:48.

''Washington'' passed through the area still occupied by the damaged and sinking U.S. destroyers and fired on ''Ayanami'' with her secondary batteries, setting her afire. Following close behind, ''South Dakota'' suddenly suffered a series of electrical failures, reportedly during repairs when her chief engineer locked down a circuit breaker in violation of safety procedures, causing her circuits repeatedly to go into series, making her radar, radios, and most of her gun batteries inoperable. However, she continued to follow ''Washington'' towards the western side of Savo Island until 23:35, when ''Washington'' changed course left to pass to the southward behind the burning destroyers. ''South Dakota'' tried to follow but had to turn to right to avoid ''Benham'' which resulted in the ship being silhouetted by the fires of the burning destroyers and made her a closer and easier target for the Japanese.Lippman, ''Second Naval Battle of Guadalcanal'', Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 477–478; Hammel, ''Guadalcanal:  Decision at Sea'', p. 384–385; Morison, ''The Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 275–277.

Receiving reports of the destruction of the U.S. destroyers from ''Ayanami'' and his other ships, Kondo pointed his bombardment force towards Guadalcanal, believing that the U.S. warship force had been defeated. His force and the two U.S. battleships were now heading towards each other.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 479.

Almost blind and unable to effectively fire her main and secondary armament, ''South Dakota'' was illuminated by searchlights and targeted by gunfire and torpedoes by most of the ships of the Japanese force, including ''Kirishima'', beginning about 00:00 on November 15. Although able to score a few hits on ''Kirishima'', ''South Dakota'' took 25 medium and one large-caliber hit, some of which did not explode, that completely knocked out her communications and remaining gunfire control operations, set portions of her upper decks on fire, and forced her to try to steer away from the engagement. All of the Japanese torpedoes missed.Morison, ''The Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 277–279, . The "Gunfire Damage Report" made by the Bureau of Ships showed 26 damaging hits and can be found at , Hammel, ''Guadalcanal:  Decision at Sea'', p. 385–389. Admiral Lee later described the cumulative effect of the gunfire damage to ''South Dakota'' as to, "render one of our new battleships deaf, dumb, blind, and impotent."Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 480. ''South Dakota'''s crew casualties were 39 killed and 59 wounded, and she turned away from the battle at 00:17 without informing Admiral Lee, though observed by Kondo's lookouts.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 482.Lippman, ''Second Naval Battle of Guadalcanal'', p. 9. Lee stated he felt "relief", but Capt. Davis of ''Washington'' said ''South Dakota'' "pulled out" without a word.


The Japanese ships continued to concentrate their fire on ''South Dakota'' and none detected ''Washington'' approaching to within .''Washington'' was tracking a large target (''Kirishima'') for some time but refrained from firing since there was a chance it could be ''South Dakota''. ''Washington'' had not been able to track ''South Dakota''’s movements because she was in a blind spot in the ''Washington''’s radar and Lee could not raise her on the radio to confirm her position. When the Japanese illuminated and fired on ''South Dakota'', all doubts were removed as to which ships were friend or foe. From this close range, ''Washington'' opened fire and quickly hit ''Kirishima'' with at least nine main battery shells and almost forty secondary ones, causing heavy damage and setting her aflame. ''Kirishima'' was hit below the waterline and suffered a jammed rudder, causing her to circle uncontrollably to port.Kilpatrick, ''Naval Night Battles'', p. 123–124; Morison, ''The Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 278; Hammel, ''Guadalcanal:  Decision at Sea'', p. 388–389; Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 481.

At 00:25, Kondo ordered all of his ships that were able to converge and destroy any remaining U.S. ships. However, the Japanese ships still did not know where ''Washington'' was located, and the other surviving U.S. ships had already departed the battle area. ''Washington'' steered a northwesterly course towards the Russell Islands to draw the Japanese force away from Guadalcanal and the presumably damaged ''South Dakota''. The Japanese ships finally sighted ''Washington'' and launched several torpedo attacks, but by adroit maneuvering by her captain, ''Washington'' avoided all of them and also avoided running aground in shallow waters. At length, believing that the way was clear for the transport convoy to proceed to Guadalcanal (but apparently disregarding the threat of air attack in the morning), Kondo ordered his remaining ships to break contact and retire from the area about 01:04, which most of the Japanese warships complied with by 01:30.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 483–484.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="66a1608f8792701cb4824af7c226e5ac" name="NavalGuadalcanalWashington" sectnum="4.5#1">../img/66a1608f8792701cb4824af7c226e5ac.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>