<document id="fc66f418ce7c7855daed259ca643fb0a-2.3" name="Naval_Battle_of_Guadalcanal" cat="29">
<text>
At 03:00 on November 13, Admiral Yamamoto postponed the planned landings of the transports, which returned to the Shortlands to await further orders.  Dawn revealed three crippled Japanese (''Hiei'', ''Yudachi'', and ''Amatsukaze''), and three crippled U.S. ships (''Portland'', ''Atlanta'', and ''Aaron Ward'') in the general vicinity of Savo Island.Hammel, ''Guadalcanal:  Decision at Sea'', p. 270. ''Amatsukaze'' was attacked by U.S. dive-bombers but escaped further damage as she headed to Truk and eventually returned to action several months later. The abandoned hulk of ''Yudachi'' was sunk by ''Portland'', whose guns still worked despite the other damage to the ship.Hammel, ''Guadalcanal:  Decision at Sea'', p. 272. The tugboat ''Bobolink'' motored around Ironbottom Sound throughout the day of November 13, assisting the damaged U.S. ships, rescuing U.S. survivors from the water, and, reportedly, shooting Japanese survivors floating in the water.Kilpatrick, ''Naval Night Battles'', p. 98; Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 454.

''Hiei'' was attacked repeatedly by Marine TBF Avenger torpedo planes from Henderson Field, TBFs and SBD Dauntless dive-bombers from ''Enterprise'', which had departed Nouméa on November 11, and B-17 Flying Fortress bombers of the United States Army Air Forces 11th Heavy Bombardment Group from Espiritu Santo. Abe and his staff transferred to ''Yukikaze'' at 08:15. ''Kirishima'' was ordered by Abe to take ''Hiei'' under tow, escorted by ''Nagara'' and its destroyers, but the attempt was cancelled because of the threat of submarine attack and ''Hiei''’s increasing unseaworthiness.Kilpatrick, ''Naval Night Battles'', p. 79 and 97–100; Hammel, ''Guadalcanal:  Decision at Sea'', p. 298–308. After sustaining more damage from air attacks, ''Hiei'' sank northwest of Savo Island, perhaps after being scuttled by her remaining crew, in the late evening of November 13.Hammel, ''Guadalcanal:  Decision at Sea'', p. 298–308; Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 259–160. ''Enterprise'' and her escorting warships were designated Task Force 16 (TF16) and was commanded by Rear Admiral Thomas C. Kinkaid.  TF16 consisted of ''Enterprise'' plus battleships ''Washington'' and ''South Dakota'', cruisers ''Northampton'' and ''San Diego'', and ten destroyers.

''Portland'', ''San Francisco'', ''Aaron Ward'', ''Sterett'', and ''O'Bannon'' were eventually able to make it back to rear-area ports for repairs. ''Atlanta'', however, sank near Guadalcanal at 20:00 on November 13.Hammel, ''Guadalcanal:  Decision at Sea'', p. 274–275. Departing from the Solomon Islands area with ''San Francisco'', ''Helena'', ''Sterret'', and ''O'Bannon'' later that day, ''Juneau'' was torpedoed and sunk by Japanese submarine ''I-26'' (). ''Juneau''’s 100+ survivors (out of a total complement of 697) were left to fend on their own in the open ocean for eight days before rescue aircraft belatedly arrived. While awaiting rescue, all but ten of ''Juneau''’s crew died from their injuries, the elements, or shark attacks.  The dead included the five Sullivan brothers.Kurzman, ''Left to Die'', Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 456; Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 257; Kilpatrick, ''Naval Night Battles'', p. 101–103.

Because of the confused nature of the battle, the U.S. believed that they had sunk as many as seven Japanese ships.Jameson, ''The Battle of Guadalcanal'', p. 35. This, plus the Japanese retreat, caused the U.S. to believe at the time that they had won a significant victory. It was only after the war that the U.S. learned that they had suffered what most see as a crushing tactical defeat.Hammel, ''Guadalcanal:  Decision at Sea'', p. 399.

Nevertheless, most historians appear to agree that Abe's decision to retreat turned this tactical defeat into a strategic victory for the U.S. Henderson Field remained operational with attack aircraft ready to deter the slow Japanese transports from approaching Guadalcanal with their precious cargoes.Hammel, ''Guadalcanal:  Decision at Sea'', p. 400.Morison, ''Struggle for Guadalcanal'', p. 258. Plus, the Japanese had lost an opportunity to eliminate the U.S. naval forces in the area, a result which would have taken even the comparatively resource-rich U.S. some time to recover from.  Reportedly furious, Admiral Yamamoto relieved Abe of command and later directed his forced retirement from the military. However, it appears that Yamamoto may have been more angry over the loss of one of his battleships (''Hiei'') than he was over the abandonment of the supply mission and failure to completely destroy the U.S. force.  Shortly before noon, Yamamoto ordered Vice Admiral Nobutake Kondo, commanding the Second Fleet at Truk, to form a new bombardment unit around ''Kirishima'' and attack Henderson Field on the night of November 14–15.Hammel, ''Guadalcanal:  Decision at Sea'', p. 401; Hara, ''Japanese Destroyer Captain'', p. 156.

Including the sinking of ''Juneau'', total U.S. losses in the battle were 1,439 dead. The Japanese suffered between 550 to 800 dead.Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 459–460.  Analyzing the impact of this engagement, historian Richard B. Frank states,
This action stands without peer for furious, close-range, and confused fighting during the war.  But the result was not decisive. The self-sacrifice of Callaghan and his task force had purchased one night's respite for Henderson Field. It had postponed, not stopped, the landing of major Japanese reinforcements, nor had the greater portion of the (Japanese) Combined Fleet yet been heard from."Frank, ''Guadalcanal'', p. 461.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="06036321a2c2f161efafa86984f44168" name="portland" sectnum="2.3#1">../img/06036321a2c2f161efafa86984f44168.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>