<document id="fc78e3d39a4109cd572a69872bbd5b8f-3" name="S.H.E" cat="20">
<text>
S.H.E has released twelve studio albums to date, including three compilation album and one which is only digitally released. All of S.H.E's album covers display an oxalis, the symbol for the group. On some covers, the clover is easy to spot on the front (''Girls Dorm'', ''Together'', ''Encore'', ''Forever'', ''Play'') or on the back (''FM S.H.E''); on other covers, its appearance is more subtle (''Super Star'', ''Once Upon a Time''). S.H.E's other contributions include songs in the soundtracks of ''Magical Love'', ''The Rose'', ''Reaching for the Stars'', ''Tokyo Juliet'', ''The Little Fairy'', ''Hanazakarino Kimitachihe'', and ''Bull Fighting''. In 2008, they sang the ending theme for the film ''CJ7''.

All three members have different vocal ranges to complement each other. Ella sings within the alto to mezzo-soprano range, while Hebe and Selina sing within the mezzo-soprano to soprano range. UDN Stars. United Daily News. . September 20, 2003. Retrieved March 2, 2007. 

Most S.H.E songs fall into the category of pop music. Songs from this genre consist of light melodies, Singtao News. . March 24, 2006. Retrieved March 2, 2007. simple drum beats, and the occasional piano or synthesizer accompaniment. In ''Girls Dorm'' and ''Youth Society'', acoustic guitar melody lines were used as well. While some slower songs, particularly those in ''Genesis'', fall into the genre of R&B, high-tempo songs, such as "Beauty Up My Life", focus more on techno. S.H.E has also sung a few pop/rock songs, including "Piquancy" (), "Super Star", and "Star Light" (). As their career progressed, S.H.E began mixing light-hearted pop ballads with elements of hip hop and dance. Attempts to fuse these genres started with songs such as "If You're Happy, Then I'll Be Pleased" (), which contained a short rap segment, and evolved into songs such as "Listen to Yüan Wei-Jen Play Guitar" (), which is composed entirely of rap with the exception of the chorus.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="e9cd5420361bf077eba2ee79706ccf5e" name="SHE_oxalis" sectnum="3#1">../img/e9cd5420361bf077eba2ee79706ccf5e.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>