<document id="fd39f6966d43dd2afcf5b99cd57d72ed-4" name="Jenna_Jameson" cat="19">
<text>
Jameson's autobiography, ''How to Make Love Like a Porn Star: A Cautionary Tale''  was published August 17, 2004. It was co-written with Neil Strauss, a contributor to ''The New York Times'' and ''Rolling Stone'', and published by ReganBooks, a division of HarperCollins. It was an instant bestseller, spending six weeks on ''The New York Times'' Best Seller list. The autobiography also won the 2004 "Mainstream's Adult Media Favorite" XRCO award in a tie with Seymore Butts's ''Family Business'' TV series. It was translated into German as ''Pornostar. Die Autobiographie''  in November 2005, and Spanish as ''Como Hacer El Amor Igual Que Una Estrella Del Porno''  in January 2006.

The book covers her early career from her beginning in show business living with her tattoo artist boyfriend, through receiving the Pornographic Hot d'Or award at Cannes, and wedding pictures from her second marriage. It does not omit sordid details, describing her two rapes, drug addictions, an unhappy first marriage, and numerous affairs with men and women. The first-person narrative is broken up by personal photos, childhood diary entries, family interviews, movie scripts, and comic panels.

The autobiography publisher, Judith Regan, also served as executive producer of a tie-in television news special, ''Jenna Jameson's Confessions'', airing on VH1 on August 16, 2004, one day before the book's launch. In April 2005, ReganBooks and Jameson filed lawsuits against each other. The point of contention was a proposed reality show about Jameson's everyday life, discussed between her then-husband, Jay Grdina, and the A&E Network. ReganBooks maintained that any A&E deal was a breach of Jameson's contract, which indicated that ReganBooks had a stake in the profits generated by both the special based on her memoir and a reality-based series, as well as "any similar projects." Jameson's suit claimed that the A&E deal preceded the ReganBooks contract., by Josh Grossberg, E! Online, April 15, 2005. Retrieved on February 5, 2007 The reality series had still not materialized, and the lawsuit was still being discussed, when HarperCollins fired Judith Regan on December 15, 2006, over an unrelated issue.

In January 2007, Jameson was reported in talks with producers on turning the autobiography into a movie, with Scarlett Johansson to play Jameson. In March 2007, Jameson was reportedly missing meetings with producers, thus endangering the movie, due to problems with a recent vaginoplasty. Also cited by
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="45199f42999c24536ffa16dcf1740e59" name="Jameson_j-howtomakelovelike" sectnum="4#1">../img/45199f42999c24536ffa16dcf1740e59.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>