<document id="fd39f6966d43dd2afcf5b99cd57d72ed-8" name="Jenna_Jameson" cat="19">
<text>
* 1995 The X-Rated Critics Organization XRCO Award for Starlet of the Year (presented in 1996)"", XRCO. Retrieved 2007-10-20.
* 1996 Hot D'Or Best New American Starlet, Best American Actress
* 1996 AVN Best New Starlet Award, AVN Awards for Best Actress (Video) – ''Wicked One'', Best Couples Sex Scene (Film) – ''Blue Movie'' (with T.T. Boy)

* 1996 Fans of X-Rated Entertainment (FOXE) Video Vixen
* 1997 AVN Award for Best Couples Sex Scene (Film) – ''Jenna Loves Rocco'' (with Rocco Siffredi), Best Couples Sex Scene (Video) – ''Conquest'' (with Vince Vouyer)
* 1997 Hot D'Or for Best American Actress
* 1997 FOXE Female Fan Favorite
* 1998 AVN Award for Best All-Girl Sex Scene (Film) – ''Satyr'' (with Missy)
* 1998 Hot D'Or for Best American Actress – ''Sexe de Feu, Coeur de Glace''
* 1998 FOXE Female Fan Favorite
* 1999 Hot D'Or for Best American Movie – ''Flashpoint''
* 2003 AVN Award for Best All-Girl Sex Scene (Video) – ''I Dream of Jenna'' (with Autumn and Nikita Denise)
* 2003 G-Phoria Award for Best Female Voice Performance – ''Grand Theft Auto: Vice City''
* 2003 XRCO Award for Best Girl/Girl scene – ''My Plaything: Jenna Jameson 2'' (with Carmen Luvana) (presented August 19, 2004)"", Dan Miller, ''Adult Video News'', hosted by XRCO. Retrieved 2007-10-20.
* 2004 AVN Award for Best Interactive DVD – ''My Plaything: Jenna Jameson 2'' (Digital Sin)
* 2004 XRCO Hall of Fame, XRCO Award for Mainstream's Adult Media Favorite – for ''How to Make Love Like a Porn Star: A Cautionary Tale'' (tied with Seymore Butts for ''Family Business'') (presented June 2, 2005)"", Heidi Pike-Johnson, ''Adult Video News'', hosted by XRCO. Retrieved 2007-10-20.
* 2005 AVN Award for Best Actress (Film) – ''The Masseuse'', Best All-Girl Sex Scene (Film) – ''The Masseuse'' (with Savanna Samson), Best Couples Sex Scene (Film) – ''The Masseuse'' (with Justin Sterling)
* 2006 AVN Hall of Fame, AVN Awards for Best Supporting Actress (Film) – ''The New Devil in Miss Jones'', Best All-Girl Sex Scene (Film) – ''The New Devil in Miss Jones'' (with Savanna Samson), Crossover Star of the Year
* 2006 F.A.M.E. Awards for Hottest Body, and Favorite Adult Actress
* 2006 Temptation Hall of Fame, Temptation Awards for Best Supporting Actress (Film) – ''The New Devil in Miss Jones'', Best All-Girl Sex Scene (Film) – ''The New Devil in Miss Jones'' (with Savanna Samson), Temptress of the Year
* 2006 Added to Adult Star Path of Fame in Edison, New Jersey.Benn, D. "Jenna Jameson on the Adult Star Path of Fame: 43 Stars Laid in New Jersey". Porno News Network, 2006. Retrieved on February 16, 2007
* 2006 XBIZ Award ''Businesswoman of the Year''
* 2007 AVN Award for Crossover Star of the Year, avnawards.com. Retrieved 2007-10-20.
* 2007 F.A.M.E. Award for Favorite Performer of All Time
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="9bd2124c75a3be2ad62599478073d7c1" name="Jenna_XRCO" sectnum="8#1">../img/9bd2124c75a3be2ad62599478073d7c1.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>