<document id="fd39f6966d43dd2afcf5b99cd57d72ed-9" name="Jenna_Jameson" cat="19">
<text>
While Jameson has stated in the past that she is bisexual, and that she has slept with 100 women and 30 men off-screen in her life, she has also stated she is "totally hetero." She has stated the best relationship she ever had was her lesbian relationship with porn actress Nikki Tyler, which she documents in her autobiography. They lived together at the start of her porn career and again before her second marriage. Famous male boyfriends discussed in her autobiography include Marilyn Manson and Tommy Lee.

On December 20, 1996, Jameson married porn star/Wicked Pictures director Brad Armstrong (real name Rodney Hopkins). The marriage lasted just 10 weeks. Although they informally separated in March 1997, she remained contractually obligated to work on Wicked Pictures projects involving both of them. They legally separated and divorced in March 2001, after Brad discovered her sexual affair with Jorge Araya Montoya (whom she met in a visit to Costa Rica).

In the summer of 1998, Jameson met former pornographic studio owner Jay Grdina (born John G. Grdina), scion of a wealthy cattle-ranching family, who had entered pornographic film production after college. Since 1998, he has been Jameson's only on-screen male sex partner, acting under the name Justin Sterling. They were engaged in December 2000 – well before her divorce from Armstrong/Hopkins – and married June 22, 2003. They unsuccessfully tried to have children from mid-2004 onwards, as Jameson had planned to permanently retire from porn performing upon becoming a mother. The couple resided in Scottsdale, Arizona, in a  Spanish-style mansion, bought for $2 million in 2002.

In November 2004, Jameson was diagnosed with skin cancer. Though surgery successfully removed it, she miscarried shortly after the diagnosis. She was unable to get pregnant again, even with in vitro fertilization. Jameson said the in vitro process "wasn't a good thing for me"; she gained weight and did not get pregnant. According to Jameson, the stresses of the cancer plus infertility led to her marriage's collapse.

In August 2006, ''Star'' magazine and TMZ.com confirmed with Jameson's publicist that she and Grdina had separated, and that Jameson was dating musician Dave Navarro.

In 2006, she began dating mixed martial artist and former UFC champion Tito Ortiz, whom she met on Myspace. Ortiz cancelled a November 12, 2006 appearance as the guest of honor at the United States Marine Corps birthday ball at the Marine Corps Air Station Miramar in San Diego, when the Corps refused to let him bring Jameson as his guest."Miramar ball guest cancels; wants to bring porn-star girlfriend", By John Hoellwarth, ''Marine Corps Times'', October 27, 2006. On November 30, 2006, in an interview on ''The Howard Stern Show'', Ortiz stated that he is in love with Jameson, that she is no longer acting in pornography, and that they are in a monogamous relationship.
On December 12, 2006, Jameson filed for divorce from Grdina.
She introduced Ortiz and talked about their relationship at the 2008 AVN Adult Movie Awards while she was presenting an award. She also made brief appearances on two episodes of ''The Celebrity Apprentice'' to help Ortiz on the tasks assigned in those episodes.

In March 2007 at the AVN Awards, Jameson blamed her appearance on the divorce proceedings.

Jameson announced in August 2008 that she and Ortiz were expecting twins together in April 2009.
On March 16, 2009 Jameson gave birth to twin boys named Jesse Jameson Ortiz and Journey Jette Ortiz. Jesse weighed in at 4 lbs and Journey weighed 4 lbs 11 oz.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="032e18fe9ba476400e0bbbd7d9a3f401" name="Jenna_Jameson_and_Jay_Grdina" sectnum="9#1">../img/032e18fe9ba476400e0bbbd7d9a3f401.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>