<document id="fd39f6966d43dd2afcf5b99cd57d72ed-3" name="Jenna_Jameson" cat="19">
<text>
Jameson says that she started acting in pornographic films to get back at her boyfriend, Jack, for cheating on her. She first appeared in an erotic film in 1993, a non-explicit softcore movie by Andrew Blake, with girlfriend Nikki Tyler, whom she had met modeling for Suze Randall. Her first pornographic movie scenes were filmed by Randy West and appeared in 1994's ''Up and Cummers 10'' and ''Up and Cummers 11''. She quickly achieved notice and appeared in several other pornographic films while still living in Las Vegas.

Jameson got her first breast implants on July 28, 1994, to enhance her stripping and movie careers. By 2004, she had had two different sets of breast implants and a chin implant.

Jameson's first pornographic film appearances were lesbian scenes (a common way that female performers ease into the business). She says: "Girl-on-girl was easy and natural. Then they offered me lots of money to do boy-girl." Her first heterosexual scene was in ''Up and Cummers 11'' (1994). At the beginning of her career, she promised herself that she would never do anal sex or double penetration scenes on film. She has also never done any interracial sex scenes with men (despite that category's runaway popularity during 2000s). When asked about this on ''The Howard Stern Show'' on February 8, 2008, she said that she wasn't necessarily opposed to doing so; rather, "it never really came up", as there were few black men working in porn when she started, and none of them worked  for the same company  she did. Instead, her "signature move" was oral sex, lubricated with saliva.

In 1994, after overcoming her drug addiction by spending several weeks with her father and grandmother, Jameson relocated to Los Angeles to live with Nikki Tyler. She started modeling again, and in 1995 got her father's blessing to make a career out of pornographic films. Her first movie after that was ''Silk Stockings''. Later in 1995, Wicked Pictures, a then small pornographic film production company, signed her to an exclusive contract. She remembers telling Wicked Pictures founder Steve Orenstein:


The contract earned Jameson US$6,000 for each of eight movies in her first year. Her first big-budget production was ''Blue Movie'' (1995), where she played a reporter investigating a porn set; It won multiple AVN Awards. In 1996, Jameson won top awards from three major industry organizations, the XRCO Best New Starlet award, the AVN Best New Starlet Award, and the Fans of X-Rated Entertainment (FOXE) Video Vixen award. She was the first entertainer to win all three awards. A stream of other awards followed.

By 2001, Jameson earned $60,000 for a day and a half of filming a single DVD, and $8,000 per night dancing at strip clubs. She tried to restrict herself to five films per year and two weeks of dancing per month. Her husband Jay Grdina has said that she earned as much as $25,000 per night dancing.

Since November 2005, she has been the host of Playboy TV's ''Jenna's American Sex Star'', where prospective porn stars compete in sexual performances for a contract with her company, ClubJenna. Winners of the contracts for the first two years were Brea Bennett and Roxy Jezel.

In August 2007, Jameson had her breast implants removed, reducing her from a D to a C cup; she also said she was finished with appearing on camera in pornographic films, though she would continue running ClubJenna, which was grossing $30 million per year."", ''Us Weekly'', August 22, 2007. Retrieved 2008-01-15. In January 2008, Jameson confirmed she is retiring from pornographic performances."", by Steven Andrew, January 14, 2008, XFanz. Retrieved 2008-01-15.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="2726277e0a653bc96c7bbdeaac66d11c" name="Jenna_Jameson_Jan12_2007" sectnum="3#1">../img/2726277e0a653bc96c7bbdeaac66d11c.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>