<document id="fe2e3e96a867ea3e21667653f2ee9459-4.2" name="A_Very_Merry_Unauthorized_Children's_Scientology_Pageant" cat="17">
<text>
In late 2006, the musical was performed at New York Theatre Workshop's 4th Street Theatre in New York City, with Alex Timbers reprising his role as director and Gabriel Kahane as musical director.  That same year, the show was also presented at the Boston Center for the Arts in Boston by Boston Theatre Works, and at Dad's Garage Theatre in Atlanta.  The Boston production was directed by Jason Southerland.  When contacted by ''The Boston Globe'' for a statement on the Boston production, Boston Church of Scientology president Gerard Renna stated that the musical: "is not something we're addressing" and that they were instead focused on antidrug education.  

Dad's Garage Theatre presented the musical again in 2007, from November 30 to December 23, 2007.  The entire cast from the 2006 production returned, and director Mary Claire Dunn emphasized that she educated the cast about Scientology on the first day of rehearsal.  Theatre company Brat Productions in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania also put on a 2007 production, with performances from December 13 through December 30, 2007 at St. Stephen's Theater.  The production was directed by Lee Ann Etzold.  Landless Theatre Company in Washington, D.C. also presented the musical from December 20, 2007 through January 13, 2008 at the District of Columbia Arts Center in Adams Morgan.  Andrew Lloyd Baughman was the director and music director.  

Rarely Done Productions in Syracuse, New York put on a production of the play, which ran from October 3 to October 18, 2008. Circle Theatre in Fort Worth, Texas has announced a 2008 production, which ran November 20 to December 20, 2008. Know Theatre of Cincinnati Cincinnati, Ohio planned a 2008 production December 6 through January, 2008. Ron May, artistic director of Stray Cat Theatre in Phoenix, Arizona, also planned a production of the play for the 2008 season, and A Red Orchid Theatre in Chicago, Illinois planned a production to run from November 17 to December 28, 2008. Representatives for the Church of Scientology did not respond to repeated requests for comment from the ''Chicago Tribune'' about the 2008 Chicago production.

A Red Orchid Theatre will again present a production of the play in its 2009-2010 season. The Chicago production will be directed by Steve Wilson, and is planned to run from November 12, 2009 through January 3, 2010. The play's artistic director, Kirsten Fitzgerald spoke positively of rehearsals for the Chicago production: "The energy that explodes into the theatre with the start of each rehearsal is palpable and impossible to deny, even from the office next door. I am ecstatic and so very grateful to bring last year's smash-hit to audiences old and new.  The heart of last year's joyous and hilarious Chicago Premiere returns with plenty of surprises and new fun up our sleeves."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="d06ce4a04112d979dff8136f5211c3dc" name="2007_A_Very_Merry_Unauthorized_Scientology_promo_poster" sectnum="4.2#1">../img/d06ce4a04112d979dff8136f5211c3dc.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>