<document id="fe2e3e96a867ea3e21667653f2ee9459-1" name="A_Very_Merry_Unauthorized_Children's_Scientology_Pageant" cat="17">
<text>
Alex Timbers developed the concept and directed the play, while Kyle Jarrow wrote the accompanying book, music, and lyrics.  Timbers and Jarrow were classmates together at Yale University.  The script for the play is published by Samuel French, Inc.  Jarrow was motivated to write the script by what he saw as a shift in religious teachings - from an old model involving hell and retribution, to a new system of thought promising money or peace.  Jarrow commented on Timbers' idea of using children to tell a story about Scientology: "I did a lot of work on cults in college, and what I learned is that they sort of turn you into a child by appealing to that part of you that wants to be taken care of and given answers.  And so it all began to make sense to me."  He said Scientology would be "an especially interesting topic for a theater piece" because of its criticism of psychiatry, relative newness compared to Buddhism, Islam, Judaism, and Christianity, and practice of requiring "that the follower take courses which cost significant amounts of money."

Jarrow's script was "almost entirely based on Hubbard's own writings and the church's literature", though Jarrow was also influenced by critical journalistic accounts.  He also drew on the "awkward woodenness of Christmas pageants &mdash; the fact that children are often made to say large words that don't sound natural coming out of their mouths."  Timbers said they chose to stick to Church of Scientology primary source material for background on the script because "We thought that the best way to satirize the Church of Scientology was to let the Church speak for itself."  During production, the creative team worked with cast members to educate them about the play's background. "Kids shouldn't just be saying things that they don't understand. That's what we're criticizing...people who just parrot behavior and language. We wanted to have an honest conversation with them," Jarrow said.  The published version of the script says that the musical should not be performed by adults; Jarrow said adults are "too jaded", and would not be able to portray the "unwinking satire" of the piece.


The producers wanted the musical to appear like a "corny and low-rent production".  The ensemble includes 10 actors from ages eight to twelve.  Though professionals, the child actors perform with a "realistic lack of polish", as they are playing non-professional children of Scientologists, performing in a holiday pageant. The chorus portrays Thetans, and the reactive and analytical portions of the mind are depicted by two children who share a conjoined right brain costume.  During the Xenu story, the narrator is outfitted in a cardboard robot suit, and the actor portraying Xenu wears a "tacky headdress".  Staging, costumes and set design are all made to appear to be the "earnest work of schoolteachers and supportive parents trying to provide a colorful and cheery atmosphere on a small budget."  The stage design includes a  "colorful, crayon-colored backdrop of space age-like, semi-circular set pieces."  Costumes include white robes, rainbow-striped socks and tinsel halos.  Props used to denote locations include "a waving cardboard palm frond for Hawaii, a street sign and cell phones for New York."  The musical ends with a tableau vivant, where the audience sees the cast standing at the back of the theater holding candles and singing cheerfully as a door closes and they are blocked from view.

Early in the production of the play, John Carmichael, president of the Church of Scientology in New York, found out that a theatrical production involving Scientology was in the works. After showing up unannounced to a rehearsal, Carmichael sent a letter to the play's New York producer, Aaron Lemon-Strauss, citing his concerns at the possibility of being ridiculed. In the letter, Carmichael also pointed out the church's many past lawsuits. Alex Timbers was quoted as saying:  "We've been told that the letter is a precursor to a lawsuit." Carmichael visited the artistic staff a total of three times to voice his concerns before the play's debut.  After this occurrence, Jarrow and Timbers' attorneys advised them to insert the word "Unauthorized" into the title of the play. This was done to avoid potential litigation from the Church of Scientology.  In an interview with ''The New York Times'', Carmichael later stated: "These folks have a right to write whatever play they want... but they've sunk to clichés."
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b8e5dd5a52ac018552282e3e8a4e5db8" name="2007_A_Very_Merry_Xenu" sectnum="1#1">../img/b8e5dd5a52ac018552282e3e8a4e5db8.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>