<document id="fe895e20f843e10790adcf56e7138235-2.12" name="Shrine_of_Remembrance" cat="1">
<text>
Although the original architects had proposed including four statues of war leaders, Monash rejected this plan. Instead there were to be no statues representing individual members of the Australian Defence Force at the shrine itself, although a number of statues were to be added in the surrounding parklands. The first of these was "The Man With The Donkey" representing John Simpson Kirkpatrick, although he was not named on the statue, and officially the work is said to represent the "valour and compassion of the Australian soldier". Nearby is the Lone Pine (''Pinus brutia''). This tree, planted in 1933, is one of four seedlings planted in Victoria from seeds of a cone brought back by Sgt. Keith Mc Dowell from Gallipoli. The statue, by Wallace Anderson, was installed in 1936 on the initiative of women who had founded a "Mother's Tribute".Inglis (2008), pp. 308&ndash;310.  A statue of Monash was also commissioned and was designed by Leslie Bowles. Casting was due to begin in 1938, but the onset of World War II delayed work, and thus it was not installed until 1950, and, as with Simpson and his donkey, was located away from the shrine. 


The Shrine is set in a large expanse of parkland officially called Kings Domain. Over the years many other war memorials have been built in this area, including the Australian-Hellenic Memorial to Australian and Greek dead in the Battles of Greece and Crete in 1941, and statues of Monash and Blamey. Most of the trees which line the approaches to the Shrine bear plaques commemorating individual Army units, naval vessels or Air Force squadrons, placed there by veterans' groups. An older memorial to Victorians killed in the Second Boer War of 1899–1902 is also located nearby on the corner of St Kilda and Domain Roads.

The Driver and Wipers Memorial, also in the Shrine reserve, commemorates the thousands of Australian lives lost during the fighting at Ypres; "Wipers" is the way servicemen pronounced "Ypres" during World War I. The bronze soldiers are the work of the British sculptor Charles Sargeant Jagger and originally stood outside the Museum and State Library of Victoria in Melbourne. They were transferred to the Shrine in 1998. The Driver is a soldier holding a horse whip and bridles, wearing breeches,a protective legging, spurs, and a steel helmet, and the figure is a recasting of one of the figures from the Royal Artillery Memorial in Hyde Park, London, UK. The other bronze, the "Wipers" figure, is a British infantry soldier standing guard with standard issue .303 rifle, bayonet fixed, a German helmet at his feet. This too is a recasting, taken from the Hoylake and West Kirby War Memorial in Merseyside, UK.

On July 19, 2008 being the 92nd anniversary of the Battle of Fromelles a replica of the 1998 sculpture by Peter Corlett in the ''VC Corner Australian Cemetery and Memorial'', Fromelles was unveiled. This depicts Sergeant Simon Fraser, 57th Battalion, (a farmer from Byaduk, Victoria), rescuing a wounded compatriot from ''no man's land'' after the battle.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="acf71d9ded82d2194a1ee5ea60aab3ec" name="Driver_and_Wipers" sectnum="2.12#1">../img/acf71d9ded82d2194a1ee5ea60aab3ec.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>