<document id="fe895e20f843e10790adcf56e7138235-1.4" name="Shrine_of_Remembrance" cat="1">
<text>
After World War II it was felt necessary to add to the Shrine an element commemorating the Australian war dead of the second great conflict. Once again a competition was run, with A. S. Fall and E. E. Milston as the joint winners.Isaacson (1999) p. 51. Milston's design was eventually chosen as the one to go ahead,Isaacson (1999) p. 52. and the result was the World War II Forecourt, a wide expanse of stone in front of the Shrine's north face; the Eternal Flame, a permanent gas flame set just to the west of the north face; and the World War II Memorial, a 12.5-metre-high (41 ft) cenotaph a little further west.  The Forecourt replaced a reflecting pool that had previously stood in front of the Shrine.  These enlargements were dedicated by Queen Elizabeth II on 28 February 1954. Australia's involvements in later wars, such as the Korean War, the Malayan Emergency, the Vietnam War and the Gulf War, are commemorated by inscriptions.

In 1951 the body of Field Marshal Sir Thomas Blamey, Australia's military commander during World War II, was held at the Shrine for three days for public viewing followed by a State funeral on site. 20,000 people visited the Shrine as he lay in state.Hetherington (1973), p. 399.

During the Vietnam War the Shrine became a centre of conflict when anti-war demonstrators protested during ANZAC Day services against Australia's involvement in the war.Inglis (2008), pp. 359&ndash;360. In 1971 the Shrine was defaced when the word PEACE! was painted in large white letters on the pillars of the north portico.Inglis (2008), p. 360. Despite vigorous cleaning, the porous nature of the stone used in the Shrine's construction meant that the slogan remained faintly visible for over 20 years.

In 1985 the Remembrance Garden was added beneath the western face of the Shrine to honour those who served during post-WWII conflicts.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="b906a5d48476aae6f50755c9c6c2748b" name="Melbourne_war_memorial02" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/b906a5d48476aae6f50755c9c6c2748b.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>