<document id="feefd85c705ba3c2ad4c37fddbe5a366-7" name="Killer_Whale" cat="3">
<text>
In 2008, the IUCN changed its assessment of the killer whale's conservation status from conservation dependent to data deficient, in recognition of the likelihood that one or more killer whale types may be yet-unrecognized species. Should a new killer whale species be determined to exist, it is possible that it is an endangered species. Depletion of prey species, pollution, conflicts with fishing activities, and habitat degradation are currently the most significant threats to killer whales worldwide.  

Like other animals at the highest trophic levels of the food chain, the killer whale is particularly susceptible to poisoning via accumulation of Polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) in the body. A survey of animals off the Washington coast found that PCB levels in killer whales were higher than those in harbour seals in Europe that have been sickened by the chemical. Samples from the blubber of killer whales in the Norwegian Arctic show higher levels of PCBs, pesticides and brominated flame-retardants than in polar bears.

In the Pacific Northwest, stocks of salmon, a main food source for resident killer whales, have declined dramatically in recent years.  On the west coast of Alaska and the Aleutian Islands, populations of seals and sea lions have also undergone a major decline. If food is scarce, killer whales must draw from their blubber for energy, which further magnifies the effects of pollutants. In 2005, the United States government listed the southern resident community of killer whales as an endangered population under the Endangered Species Act. The southern resident community comprises three pods which spend most of the year in the Georgia and Haro Straits and Puget Sound in British Columbia and Washington. These killer whales do not breed outside of their community, which was previously estimated at around 200 animals and had shrunk to around 90.M.L. Lyke, "" ''Seattle Post Intelligencer'' 14 October 2006 In October 2008, the annual survey of resident killer whales revealed that seven killer whales were missing and presumed dead, reducing the known number to 83. This is potentially the largest decline in the population in the past ten years. Ken Balcomb, a senior scientist at the Center for Whale Research on the San Juan Islands, has proclaimed this incident as a "disaster". These deaths can be attributed to declines in chinook salmon.Le Phuong. "Researchers: 7 Orcas Missing from Puget Sound" Associated Press.  25, October 2008.  http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20081025/ap_on_re_us/killer_whales

Noise from shipping, drilling, and other human activities can interfere with the acoustic communication and echolocation of killer whales. In the mid-1990s, loud underwater noises from salmon farms were used to deter seals. Killer whales subsequently avoided the surrounding waters. In addition, high intensity navy sonar has become a new source of distress for killer whales. Killer whales are popular with whale watchers, which may change killer whale behaviour and stress killer whales, particularly if boats approach killer whales too closely or block their line of travel. 

The ''Exxon Valdez'' oil spill had an adverse effect on killer whales in Prince William Sound and the Kenai Fjords region of Alaska. Eleven members (about half) of one  Resident pod disappeared in the following year. The spill reduced the amount of available prey, such as salmon, and has thus been responsible for a local population decline. In December 2004, scientists at the North Gulf Oceanic Society said that the AT1 transient population of killer whales (currently considered part of a larger population of 346 transients), now only numbering 7 individuals, has failed to reproduce at all since the spill. This population is expected to become extinct.http://www.wildwhales.org/newsletter/nov_dec_2004.htm Sightings Newsletter report on AT1 pod
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="6f6daa943dd7904f3ca1ac9b1e240540" name="Orca_mother_calf" sectnum="7#1">../img/6f6daa943dd7904f3ca1ac9b1e240540.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>