<document id="feefd85c705ba3c2ad4c37fddbe5a366-4" name="Killer_Whale" cat="3">
<text>
Killer whales are found in all oceans and most seas, including (unusually for cetaceans) the Mediterranean and Arabian Seas. However, they prefer cooler temperate and polar regions. Although sometimes spotted in deep water, coastal areas are generally preferred to pelagic environments.
The killer whale is particularly highly concentrated in the northeast Pacific Basin, where Canada curves into Alaska as well as the Johnstone Strait area and Washington state. They are making a bigger presence in California too. There are also large populations off the coast of Iceland and off the coast of northern Norway. They are regularly sighted in Argentina and the Antarctic waters right up to the ice pack and are believed to venture under the pack and survive breathing in air pockets like the beluga does. In the Arctic, however, the species is rarely seen in winter, as it does not approach the ice pack. It does visit these waters during summer.

Information for off-shore regions and tropical waters is more scarce, but widespread, if not frequent, sightings indicate that the killer whale can survive in most water temperatures. Sightings are rare in Indonesian and Philippine waters. No estimate for the total worldwide population exists. Local estimates include 70,000–80,000 in the Antarctic, 8,000 in the tropical Pacific (although tropical waters are not the killer whale's preferred environment, the sheer size of this area—19 million square kilometres—means there are thousands of killer whales), up to 2,000 off Japan, 1,500 off the cooler northeast Pacific and 1,500 off Norway. Adding very rough estimates for unsurveyed areas, the total population could be around 100,000.

With the rapid decline of Arctic sea ice in the Hudson Strait, the range of killer whales has now extended into the far northern waters of Canada. Through the 1990s, killer whales were sighted in western Hudson Bay at a rate of 6 per decade; sightings rose to more than 30 between 2001–2006., Reuters, January 22, 2007

White killer whales have been spotted in the northern Bering Sea and around St. Lawrence Island.  Also, there have been sightings along the Russian coast.  In February 2008, a white killer whale was photographed two miles (3 km) off Kanaga Volcano.  The whale was a healthy, adult male about 25 to  long and weighing upward of 10,000 pounds.

The migration patterns of killer whales are poorly understood. Each summer, the same resident killer whales appear off the coasts of British Columbia and Washington State. After decades of research, it is still unknown where these animals go for the rest of the year. Transient pods have been sighted from southern Alaska to central California.

On some occasions, killer whales will swim into freshwater rivers. They have been documented 100 miles (160 km) up the Columbia River in the United States. They have also been found in the Fraser River in Canada and the Horikawa River in Japan.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="91728aad4c54e8a7198ffadb2dbf8010" name="Orca_porpoising" sectnum="4#1">../img/91728aad4c54e8a7198ffadb2dbf8010.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>