<document id="feefd85c705ba3c2ad4c37fddbe5a366-6.5" name="Killer_Whale" cat="3">
<text>
Fish-eating killer whales in the North Pacific have a complex but extremely stable system of social grouping. Unlike any other mammal species whose social structure is known, resident killer whales of both sexes live with their mothers for their entire lives. Therefore, killer whale societies are based around matrilines consisting of a single female (the matriarch) and her descendants. The sons and daughters of the matriarch form part of the line, as do the sons and daughters of those daughters. The average size of a matriline is nine animals.

Because females can live for up to ninety years, it is not uncommon for four or even five generations to travel together. These matrilineal groups are highly stable. Individuals split off from their matrilineal group only for up to a few hours at a time, in order to mate or forage. No permanent casting-out of an individual from a matriline has ever been recorded.

Closely related matrilines form loose aggregations called pods, consisting on average of about 18 animals. All members of a pod use a similar set of calls, known as a dialect. Unlike matrilines, pods may split apart for days or weeks at a time in order to forage.  Killer whales within a pod do not interbreed; mating occurs only between members of different pods.


Resident pods have up to 50 or more members, with an average of 15 in the Northern resident community in the Pacific Northwest. Occasionally, several pods join to form superpods, sometimes with more than 150 animals.
Resident pods often include subpods, which comprises one daughter or cousin that sometimes travels only with her offspring and sometimes joins the rest of the pod.

The next level of grouping is the clan. A clan consists of pods which have a similar dialect. Again, the relationship between pods appears to be genealogical, consisting of fragments of families with a common heritage on the maternal side. Different clans can occupy the same geographical area; pods from different clans are often observed traveling together. When Resident pods come together to travel as a clan, they greet each other by forming two parallel lines akin to a face-off before mingling with each other.

The final layer of association, perhaps more arbitrary and devised by humans rather than the other very natural divisions, is called the community and is loosely defined as a set of clans that are regularly seen mixing with each other. Communities do not follow discernible familial or vocal patterns.In the northeast Pacific, three communities of fish-eating Orcas have been identified:
the southern community (1 clan, 3 pods, 90 Orcas as of 2006), the northern community (3 clans, 16 pods, 214 Orcas as of 2000), and the south Alaskan community (2 clans, 11 pods, 211 Orcas as of 2000)

Transient groups are generally smaller because, although they too are based on matrilines, some male and female offspring eventually disperse from the maternal group. However, transient groups still have a loose connection defined by their dialect.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="418d1399272795a55356fe80659b6b06" name="Orca_2" sectnum="6.5#1">../img/418d1399272795a55356fe80659b6b06.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>