<document id="feefd85c705ba3c2ad4c37fddbe5a366-1" name="Killer_Whale" cat="3">
<text>
'''''Orcinus orca''''' is the sole species in the genus '''''Orcinus''''', one of the many species originally described by Linnaeus in 1758 in ''Systema Naturae''.  It is one of thirty-five species in the dolphin family, which is believed to date back at least five million years. Like the Sperm Whale genus ''Physeter'', ''Orcinus'' is currently classified as a genus with a single, abundant species, which would make the killer whale one of the oldest dolphin species. 

There are at least three to five types of killer whales that are distinct enough to be considered different races, subspecies, or possibly even species. The IUCN reported in 2008, "The taxonomy of this genus is clearly in need of review, and it is likely that O. orca will be split into a number of different species or at least subspecies over the next few years." In the 1970s and 1980s, research off the west coast of Canada and the United States identified the following three types:
* '''Resident''': These are the most commonly sighted of the three populations in the coastal waters of the northeast Pacific. The resident killer whales' diet consists primarily of fish and sometimes squid, and they live in complex and cohesive family groups. Pods possess lifelong family bondshttp://community.oceana.org/creatures/killer-whale, often living in large matrilineal groups and vocalizing in highly variable and complex dialects. Female residents characteristically have a rounded dorsal fin tip that terminates in a sharp corner. They are known to visit the same areas consistently. The resident populations of British Columbia and Washington are amongst the most intensely studied marine mammals ever. Researchers have identified and named over 300 killer whales over the past 30 years.
* '''Transient''': The diet of these killer whales consists almost exclusively of marine mammals; they do not eat fish. Transients in southern Alaska generally travel in small groups, usually of two to six animals. Unlike residents, transients may not always stay together as a family unit. Pods consist of smaller groups with less persistent family bonds and vocalizing in less variable and less complex dialects.  Female transients are characterized by dorsal fins that are more triangular and pointed than those of residents. The gray or white area around the dorsal fin, known as the "saddle patch," often contains some black coloring in residents. However, the saddle patches of transients are solid and uniformly gray. Transients roam widely along the coast—some individuals have been sighted in Southern Alaska and later in California.
* '''Offshore''': These killer whales were discovered in 1988 when humpback whale researcher Jim Darling signaled to killer whale researchers Michael Bigg and Graeme Ellis that he saw killer whales in open water. These killer whales cruise the open oceans and are believed to feed primarily on schooling fish. However, because of the large presence of scarred and nicked dorsal fins resembling that of the mammal-hunting transients, the possibility that they eat mammals and sharks cannot be ruled out. They have mostly been encountered off the west coast of Vancouver Island and near the Queen Charlotte Islands. They have been seen traveling in groups of up to 60 animals. Currently, there is little known about the habits of this population, but they can be distinguished genetically from the residents and transients. Offshores appear to be shorter than the residents and the transients and females are characterized by dorsal fin tips that are continuously rounded.

Killer whale populations in other parts of the world have not been as well studied. However, there appears to be a correlation between a population's diet and its social behaviour. Fish-eating killer whales in Alaska and Norway have also been observed to have resident-like social structures. Mammal-eating killer whales in Argentina and the Crozet Islands have been observed to behave more like transients.
Transient and resident killer whales live in the same areas, but avoid each other. The name ''transient'' originated from the belief that these killer whales were outcasts from larger resident pods. Researchers later discovered that transients are not born into resident pods or vice-versa. The evolutionary split between the two groups is believed to have begun two million years ago. Recent genetic research has found that the types have not interbred for up to 10,000 years.Chadwick, Douglas H. "Investigating A Killer." National Geographic (April 2005) 
Three killer whale types have recently been documented in the Antarctic.
*'''Type A''' looks like a "typical" killer whale, a large, black and white form with a medium-sized white eye patch, living in open water and feeding mostly on minke whales.
*'''Type B''' is smaller than Type A. It has a large white eyepatch and a patch of grey colouring on its back, called a "dorsal cape." It feeds mostly on seals.
*'''Type C''' is the smallest type and lives in larger groups than any other type of killer whale. Its eyepatch is distinctively slanted forwards, rather than parallel to the body axis. Like Type B, it has a dorsal cape. Its only prey observed so far is the Antarctic Cod.
Type B and C killer whales live close to the Antarctic ice pack, and diatoms in these waters may be responsible for the yellowish colouring of both types. Research is ongoing whether Type B and C killer whales are different species.Pitman, Robert L. and Ensor, Paul. "Three forms of killer whales (''Orcinus orca'') in Antarctic waters" ''Journal of Cetacean Research and Management'' 5(2):131–139, 2003 Spring 2004
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="c433733cfdd3590e54d5c5ecb4da2f24" name="Type_C_Orcas" sectnum="1#1">../img/c433733cfdd3590e54d5c5ecb4da2f24.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>