<document id="ff106428f695e8509f1e2a6f047a9516-3.12" name="William_Tecumseh_Sherman" cat="29">
<text>
Like Grant, Sherman was convinced that the Confederacy's strategic, economic, and psychological ability to wage further war needed to be definitively crushed if the fighting were to end. Therefore, he believed that the North had to conduct its campaign as a war of conquest and employ scorched earth tactics to break the backbone of the rebellion, which he called "hard war".

Sherman's advance through Georgia and South Carolina was characterized by widespread destruction of civilian supplies and infrastructure. Although looting was officially forbidden, historians disagree on how well this regulation was enforced.See, for instance, Grimsley, pp. 190–204; McPherson, pp. 712–714, 727–729. The speed and efficiency of the destruction by Sherman's army was remarkable. The practice of bending rails around trees, leaving behind what came to be known as Sherman's neckties, made repairs difficult. Accusations that civilians were targeted and war crimes were committed on the march have made Sherman a controversial figure to this day, particularly in the South.

The damage done by Sherman was almost entirely limited to the destruction of property. Though exact figures are not available, the loss of civilian life appears to have been very small.See, for instance, Grimsley, p. 199 Consuming supplies, wrecking infrastructure, and undermining morale were Sherman's stated goals, and several of his Southern contemporaries noted this and commented on it. For instance, Alabama-born Major Henry Hitchcock, who served in Sherman's staff, declared that "it is a terrible thing to consume and destroy the sustenance of thousands of people", but if the scorched earth strategy served "to paralyze their husbands and fathers who are fighting ... it is mercy in the end."Hitchcock, p. 125

The severity of the destructive acts by Union troops was significantly greater in South Carolina than in Georgia or North Carolina. This appears to have been a consequence of the animosity among both Union soldiers and officers to the state that they regarded as the "cockpit of secession". See, for instance, Grimsley, pp. 200–202. One of the most serious accusations against Sherman was that he allowed his troops to burn the city of Columbia. Sherman himself stated that "f I had made up my mind to burn Columbia I would have burnt it with no more feeling than I would a common prairie dog village; but I did not do it ..."December 11, 1872 deposition, Mixed Commission, XIV, 91, quoted in Marion B. Lucas, ''Sherman and the Burning of Columbia'' (Univ. of S. Car. Press, 2000), p. 154.  However, on April 5, 1865, Sherman wrote to his father-in-law that "I think you will be satisfied with the manner in which I dispose of Charleston, as also of the burning of Columbia."  Simpson and Berlin, ''Sherman's Civil War'', p. 842.  Historian James M. McPherson has concluded that:



Sherman's official report on the burning placed the blame on Lt. Gen. Wade Hampton III, who Sherman said had ordered the burning of cotton in the streets. In his memoirs, Sherman said, "In my official report of this conflagration I distinctly charged it to General Wade Hampton, and confess I did so pointedly to shake the faith of his people in him, for he was in my opinion a braggart and professed to be the special champion of South Carolina."Sherman,'' Memoirs'', p. 767.  In this general connection, it is also noteworthy that Sherman and his subordinates (particularly John A. Logan) took steps to protect Raleigh, North Carolina, from acts of revenge after the assassination of President Lincoln.Sherman,'' Memoirs'', pp. 838–39; Woodworth, ''Nothing but Victory'', p. 636. 

In 1867 a chance meeting of former combatants occurred in Federal Governor Orr's office in Columbia. Gen. Howard, commander of the US 15th Corps of Sherman's army during the burning, was to be introduced to Gen. Hampton in the presence of many dignitaries. Gen. Hampton said, "Before I take your hand General Howard, tell me who burnt Columbia?" Gen. Howard replied, "It is useless to deny that our troops burnt Columbia, for I saw them in the act." (See Edwin J. Scott, Random Recollections of a Long Life. page 185; The Burning of Columbia, Charleston, SC, 1888, page 11.)
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="204c487e5118357b377418af871cc286" name="Sherman_sea_1868" sectnum="3.12#1">../img/204c487e5118357b377418af871cc286.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>