<document id="ff106428f695e8509f1e2a6f047a9516-7" name="William_Tecumseh_Sherman" cat="29">
<text>
Sherman died in New York City on February 14, 1891. On February 19, there was a funeral service held at his home there, followed by a military procession. Sherman's body was then transported to St. Louis, where another service was conducted on February 21, 1891 at a local Catholic church. His son, Thomas Ewing Sherman, a Jesuit priest, presided over his father's funeral mass. General Joseph E. Johnston, the Confederate officer who had commanded the resistance to Sherman's troops in Georgia and the Carolinas, served as a pallbearer in New York City. It was a bitterly cold day and a friend of Johnston, fearing that the general might become ill, asked him to put on his hat. Johnston famously replied: "If I were in  place, and he were standing in mine, he would not put on his hat." Johnston did catch a serious cold and died one month later of pneumonia.See, for instance, Lewis, p. 652; Marszalek, pp. 495–98.  

Sherman is buried in Calvary Cemetery in St. Louis. Major memorials to Sherman include the gilded bronze  by Augustus Saint-Gaudens at the main entrance to Central Park in New York City and  by Carl Rohl-Smith near President's Park in Washington, D.C. Other posthumous tributes include the naming of the World War II M4 Sherman tankThe U.S. M4 tank was first given the service name General Sherman by the British and the "General Sherman" Giant Sequoia tree, the most massive documented single-trunk tree in the world.

Some of the artistic treatments of Sherman's march are the Civil War era song "Marching Through Georgia" by Henry Clay Work; Herman Melville's poem ; Ross McElwee's film ''Sherman's March''; and E. L. Doctorow's novel ''The March''. At the beginning of Margaret Mitchell's novel ''Gone with the Wind'', first published in 1936, the fictional character Rhett Butler warns a group of upper-class secessionists of the folly of war with the North in terms very reminiscent of those Sherman directed to David F. Boyd before leaving Louisiana. Sherman's invasion of Georgia later plays a central role in the plot of the novel. Charles Beaumont in the ''Twilight Zone'' episode "Long Live Walter Jameson" has the lead character (a history professor) comment on the burning of Atlanta that the union soldiers did it unwillingly at the behest of a Sherman described as sullen and brutish.  The presentation of Sherman in popular culture is now discussed at book-length in ''Sherman's March in Myth and Memory'' (Rowman and Littlefield, 2008), by Edward Caudill and Paul Ashdown.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="496450eb6836a0b6820617cdb535aa32" name="He_burned_atlanta" sectnum="7#1">../img/496450eb6836a0b6820617cdb535aa32.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>