<document id="ff106428f695e8509f1e2a6f047a9516-4" name="William_Tecumseh_Sherman" cat="29">
<text>
In May 1865, after the major Confederate armies had surrendered, Sherman wrote in a personal letter:



In July 1865, only three months after Robert E. Lee’s surrender at Appomattox, General W. T. Sherman was put in charge of the Military Division of the Missouri, which included every territory west of the Mississippi.
Sherman's main concern as commanding general was to protect the construction and operation of the railroads from attack by hostile Indians.  In his campaigns against the Indian tribes, Sherman repeated his Civil War strategy by seeking not only to defeat the enemy's soldiers, but also to destroy the resources that allowed the enemy to sustain its warfare. The policies he implemented included the extensive killing of large numbers of buffalo, which were the primary source of food for the Plains Indians.See Isenberg, pp. 128, 156 

Sherman's views on Indian matters were often strongly expressed.  He regarded the railroads "as the most important element now in progress to facilitate the military interests of our Frontier."  Hence, in 1867, he wrote to Grant that "e are not going to let a few thieving, ragged Indians check and stop the progress of ."Sherman to Rawlins, October 23, 1865, quoted in Ahearn, ''Sherman and the Settlement of the West'', 24; Sherman to Grant, May 28, 1867, quoted in Fellman, ''Citizen Sherman'', 264 & 453 n.5 (see also Papers of Ulysses S. Grant, Vol. 17, p. 262).  After the 1866 Fetterman Massacre, Sherman wrote Grant that "e must act with vindictive earnestness against the Sioux, even to their extermination, men, women and children."Sherman to Grant, December 28, 1866, reproduced in ''Wild Life on the Plains and Horrors of Indian Warfare'' (1891), 120.  After George Armstrong Custer's defeat at the Battle of Little Bighorn, Sherman wrote that "hostile savages like Sitting Bull and his band of outlaw Sioux ... must feel the superior power of the Government."Seemingly Sherman to Tappan, July 21, 1876, quoted in Marszalek, ''Sherman: A Soldier's Passion'', 398.  He further wrote that "uring an assault, the soldiers can not pause to distinguish between male and female, or even discriminate as to age."Seemingly Sherman to Herbert A. Preston, April 17, 1873, quoted in Marszalek, ''Sherman: A Soldier's Passion'', 379.  Despite his harsh treatment of the warring tribes, Sherman spoke out against the unfair way speculators and government agents treated the natives within the reservations.See, for instance, Lewis, pp. 597–600.

On July 25, 1866, Congress created the rank of General of the Army for Grant and then promoted Sherman to lieutenant general. When Grant became president in 1869, Sherman was appointed Commanding General of the United States Army. After the death of John A. Rawlins, Sherman also served for one month as interim Secretary of War. His tenure as commanding general was marred by political difficulties, and from 1874 to 1876, he moved his headquarters to St. Louis, Missouri in an attempt to escape from them. One of his significant contributions as head of the Army was the establishment of the Command School (now the Command and General Staff College) at Fort Leavenworth.



In 1875 Sherman published his memoirs in two volumes. According to critic Edmund Wilson, Sherman



On June 19, 1879, Sherman delivered an address to the graduating class of the Michigan Military Academy, in which he may have uttered the famous phrase "War Is Hell".Fred R. Shapiro and Joseph Epstein, eds., ''The Yale Book of Quotations'' (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2006), 708.  On April 11, 1880, he addressed a crowd of more than 10,000 at Columbus, Ohio: "There is many a boy here today who looks on war as all glory, but, boys, it is all hell."From transcript published in the ''Ohio State Journal'', August 12, 1880, reproduced in Lewis, p. 637.  In 1945, President Harry S. Truman would say: "Sherman was wrong.  I'm telling you I find peace is hell."Richard S. Kirkendall, ed., ''Harry's Farewell: Interpreting and Teaching the Truman Presidency'' (Columbia: University of Missouri Press, 1880), 63.

Sherman stepped down as commanding general on November 1, 1883, and retired from the army on February 8, 1884. He lived most of the rest of his life in New York City. He was devoted to the theater and to amateur painting and was much in demand as a colorful speaker at dinners and banquets, in which he indulged a fondness for quoting Shakespeare.See, for instance, Woodward Sherman was proposed as a Republican candidate for the presidential election of 1884, but declined as emphatically as possible, saying, "If drafted, I will not run; if nominated, I will not accept; if elected, I will not serve."Marszalek in ''Encyclopedia of the American Civil War'', p. 1769. Such a categorical rejection of a candidacy is now referred to as a "Shermanesque statement".
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="f6943bb5cdad10cf8f6c7a15b204d008" name="Portrait_Sherman" sectnum="4#1">../img/f6943bb5cdad10cf8f6c7a15b204d008.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>