<document id="ff106428f695e8509f1e2a6f047a9516-2.11" name="William_Tecumseh_Sherman" cat="29">
<text>
Though he came to disapprove of slavery, Sherman was not an abolitionist before the war, and like many of his time and background, he did not believe in "Negro equality".See, for instance, letter by W.T. Sherman to Salmon P. Chase, January 11, 1865, reproduced in ''Sherman's Civil War'', pp. 794–795, and letter by W.T. Sherman to John Sherman, August 1865, quoted in Liddell Hart, p. 406 His military campaigns of 1864 and 1865 freed many slaves, who greeted him "as a second Moses or Aaron"Letter to Chase, cited above and joined his marches through Georgia and the Carolinas by the tens of thousands.

The fate of these refugees became a pressing military and political issue.  Some abolitionists accused Sherman of doing little to alleviate the precarious living conditions of the freed slaves. See, for instance, Sherman, ''Memoirs'', vol. II, p. 247.  To address this issue, on January 12, 1865, Sherman met in Savannah with Secretary of War Stanton and with twenty local black leaders. After Sherman's departure, Garrison Frazier, a Baptist minister, declared in response to an inquiry about the feelings of the black community:



Four days later, Sherman issued his Special Field Orders, No. 15. The orders provided for the settlement of 40,000 freed slaves and black refugees on land expropriated from white landowners in South Carolina, Georgia, and Florida. Sherman appointed Brig. Gen. Rufus Saxton, an abolitionist from Massachusetts who had previously directed the recruitment of black soldiers, to implement that plan., January 16, 1865. See also McPherson, pp. 737–739 Those orders, which became the basis of the claim that the Union government had promised freed slaves "40 acres and a mule", were revoked later that year by President Andrew Johnson.

Although the context is often overlooked, and the quotation usually chopped off, one of Sherman's most famous statements about his hard-war views arose in part from the racial attitudes summarized above. In his ''Memoirs'', Sherman noted political pressures in 1864&ndash;1865 to encourage the escape of slaves, in part to avoid the possibility that "'able-bodied slaves will be called into the military service of the rebels.'"Sherman, ''Memoirs'', pp. 728–29, quoting a December 30, 1864 letter from Henry W. Halleck.  Sherman thought concentration on such policies would have delayed the "successful end" of the war and the "liberat ''all'' slaves."Sherman, ''Memoirs'', p. 729.  He went on to summarize vividly his hard-war philosophy and to add, in effect, that he really did not want the help of liberated slaves in subduing the South:
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ff106428f695e8509f1e2a6f047a9516" name="William_Tecumseh_Sherman" sectnum="2.11#1">../img/ff106428f695e8509f1e2a6f047a9516.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>