<document id="ff106428f695e8509f1e2a6f047a9516-1.4" name="William_Tecumseh_Sherman" cat="29">
<text>
In 1859, Sherman accepted a job as the first superintendent of the Louisiana State Seminary of Learning & Military Academy in Pineville, Louisiana, a position he sought at the suggestion of Major D. C. Buell and secured due to General G. Mason Graham.Sherman, ''Memoirs'', pp. 160–62. He proved an effective and popular leader of that institution, which would later become Louisiana State University (LSU).See . Colonel Joseph P. Taylor, the brother of the late President Zachary Taylor, declared that "if you had hunted the whole army, from one end of it to the other, you could not have found a man in it more admirably suited for the position in every respect than Sherman."Quoted in Hirshson, p. 68.

On hearing of South Carolina's secession from the United States, Sherman observed to a close friend, Professor David F. Boyd of Virginia, an enthusiastic secessionist, almost perfectly describing the four years of war to come:





In January 1861 just before the outbreak of the Civil War, Sherman was required to accept receipt of arms surrendered to the State Militia by the U.S. Arsenal at Baton Rouge, Louisiana. Instead of complying, he resigned his position as superintendent and returned to the North, declaring to the governor of Louisiana, "On no earthly account will I do any act or think any thought hostile ... to the ... United States."Letter by W.T. Sherman to Gov. Thomas O. Moore, January 18, 1861. Quoted in Sherman, ''Memoirs'', p. 156

After the war, General Sherman donated two cannons to the institution.  These cannons had been captured from Confederate forces and had been used to start the war when fired at Fort Sumter, South Carolina.  They are still currently on display in front of LSU's Military Science building.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="cf3071847b83460ca04c4e466db8ee77" name="LSUcannons" sectnum="1.4#1">../img/cf3071847b83460ca04c4e466db8ee77.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>