<document id="ff106428f695e8509f1e2a6f047a9516-1.2" name="William_Tecumseh_Sherman" cat="29">
<text>
Senator Ewing secured an appointment for the 16-year-old Sherman as a cadet in the United States Military Academy at West Point,Sherman, ''Memoirs'', p. 14 where he roomed and became good friends with another important future Civil War General, George H. Thomas. There Sherman excelled academically, but he treated the demerit system with indifference. Fellow cadet William Rosecrans would later remember Sherman at West Point as "one of the brightest and most popular fellows" and "a bright-eyed, red-headed fellow, who was always prepared for a lark of any kind".Quoted in Hirshson, p. 13 About his time at West Point, Sherman says only the following in his ''Memoirs'':



Upon graduation in 1840, Sherman entered the Army as a second lieutenant in the 3rd U.S. Artillery and saw action in Florida in the Second Seminole War against the Seminole tribe. He was later stationed in Georgia and South Carolina. As the foster son of a prominent Whig politician, in Charleston, the popular Lt. Sherman moved within the upper circles of Old South society.See, for instance, Hirshson, p. 21

While many of his colleagues saw action in the Mexican-American War, Sherman performed administrative duties in the captured territory of California. He and fellow officer Lieutenant Edward Ord reached the town of Yerba Buena two days before its name was changed to San Francisco. In 1848, Sherman accompanied the military governor of California, Col. Richard Barnes Mason, in the inspection that officially confirmed the claim that gold had been discovered in the region, thus inaugurating the California Gold Rush. See  and  Sherman, along with the above-mentioned Edward Ord, assisted in surveys for the sub-divisions of the town that would become Sacramento.

Sherman earned a brevet promotion to captain for his "meritorious service", but his lack of a combat assignment discouraged him and may have contributed to his decision to resign his commission. Sherman would become one of the relatively few high-ranking officers in the Civil War who had not fought in Mexico.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="83cdb03238a658503ec538ae40110412" name="sherman_young" sectnum="1.2#1">../img/83cdb03238a658503ec538ae40110412.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>