<document id="ff106428f695e8509f1e2a6f047a9516-2.7" name="William_Tecumseh_Sherman" cat="29">
<text>
Having succeeded Anderson at Louisville, Sherman now had principal military responsibility for a border state (Kentucky) in which Confederate troops held Columbus and Bowling Green and were present near the Cumberland Gap.For more detailed discussion of this overall period, see Marszalek, ''Sherman'', pp. 154–67; Hirshson, ''White Tecumseh'', pp. 95–105; Kennett, ''Sherman'', pp. 127–49.  He became exceedingly pessimistic about the outlook for his command, and he complained frequently to Washington, D.C., about shortages and provided exaggerated estimates of the strength of the rebel forces.  Very critical press reports appeared about him after an October visit to Louisville by the then Secretary of War, Simon Cameron, and in early November Sherman insisted that he be relieved.Sherman to George B. McClellan, November 4, 1861, in Stephen W. Sears, ed., ''The Civil War Papers of George B. McClellan: Selected Correspondence, 1861-1865'' (New York, 1989), p. 127, note 1; Marszalek, ''Sherman'', pp. 161–64.   He was promptly replaced by Don Carlos Buell and transferred to St. Louis, Missouri.  In December, however, he was put on leave by Maj. Gen. Henry W. Halleck, commander of the Department of the Missouri, who considered him unfit for duty.  Sherman went to Lancaster, Ohio, to recuperate.  Some consider that, in Kentucky and Missouri, Sherman was in the midst of what today would be described as a nervous breakdown.  While he was at home, his wife, Ellen, wrote to his brother Senator John Sherman seeking advice and complaining of "that melancholy insanity to which your family is subject."Quoted in Lewis, p. 203.  Sherman himself later wrote that the concerns of command “broke me down," and he admitted contemplating "suicide".Sherman to John Sherman, January 4, 8, 1862, in Simpson and Berlin, ''Sherman’s Civil War'', 174, 176.  His problems were further compounded when the ''Cincinnati Commercial'' described him as "insane".See ''Cincinnati Commercial'', December 11, 1861; Marszalek, ''Sherman'', pp. 162, 164. 

By mid-December, however, Sherman was sufficiently recovered to return to service under Halleck in the Department of the Missouri (in March, Halleck's command was redesignated the Department of the Mississippi and enlarged to unify command in the West). Sherman's initial assignments were rear-echelon commands, first of an instructional barracks near St. Louis and then command of the District of Cairo.At one point, Halleck suggested to General-in-Chief McClellan that Sherman be given command of an expedition on the Cumberland River (on which Fort Donelson was located), but Secretary of War Edwin M. Stanton objected, telling Lincoln that any "expedition ... will prove disastrous under the charge of General Sherman."  Kennett, pp. 155–56, quoting EMS to AL, February 14, 1862.  Operating from Paducah, Kentucky, he provided logistical support for the operations of Brig. Gen. Ulysses S. Grant to capture Fort Donelson.  Grant, the previous commander of the District of Cairo, had recently won a major victory at Fort Henry and been given command of the ill-defined District of West Tennessee.  Although Sherman was technically the senior officer at this time, he wrote to Grant, "I feel anxious about you as I know the great facilities  have of concentration by means of the River and R Road, but  have faith in you — Command me in any way."WTS to USG, February 15, 1862, Papers of Ulysses S. Grant 4:216n; see Smith, pp. 151–52.  

After Grant captured Fort Donelson, Sherman got his wish of serving under Grant when he was assigned on March 1, 1862, to the Army of West Tennessee as commander of the 5th Division.Eicher, p. 485 His first major test under Grant was at the Battle of Shiloh. The massive Confederate attack on the morning of April 6, 1862, took most of the senior Union commanders by surprise. Sherman in particular had dismissed the intelligence reports that he had received from militia officers, refusing to believe that Confederate General Albert Sidney Johnston would leave his base at Corinth. He took no precautions beyond strengthening his picket lines, refusing to entrench, build abatis, or push out reconnaissance patrols. At Shiloh, he may have wished to avoid appearing overly alarmed in order to escape the kind of criticism he had received in Kentucky. He had written to his wife that, if he took more precautions, "they'd call me crazy again".Daniel, p. 138


Despite being caught unprepared by the attack, Sherman rallied his division and conducted an orderly, fighting retreat that helped avert a disastrous Union rout. Finding Grant at the end of the day sitting under an oak tree in the darkness smoking a cigar, he experienced, in his own words "some wise and sudden instinct not to mention retreat". Instead, in what would become one of the most famous conversations of the war, Sherman said simply: "Well, Grant, we've had the devil's own day, haven't we?"  After a puff of his cigar, Grant replied calmly: "Yes. Lick 'em tomorrow, though."Quoted in Walsh, pp. 77–78 Sherman would prove instrumental to the successful Union counterattack of April 7, 1862. At Shiloh, Sherman was wounded twice&mdash;in the hand and shoulder&mdash;and had three horses shot out from under him. His performance was praised by Grant and Halleck and after the battle, he was promoted to major general of volunteers, effective May 1, 1862.

Beginning in late April, a Union force of 100,000 moved slowly against Corinth, under Halleck's command with Grant relegated to a role he found unsatisfactory as second-in-command to Halleck; Sherman commanded the division on the extreme right of the Union's right wing (under George H. Thomas).  Shortly after the Union forces occupied Corinth on May 30, Sherman persuaded Grant not to leave his command, despite the serious difficulties he was having with his commander, General Halleck. Sherman offered Grant an example from his own life, "Before the battle of Shiloh, I was cast down by a mere newspaper assertion of 'crazy', but that single battle gave me new life, and I'm now in high feather." He told Grant that, if he remained in the army, "some happy accident might restore you to favor and your true place."Smith, ''Grant'', p. 212.  In July, Grant's situation improved when Halleck left for the East to become general-in-chief, and Sherman became the military governor of occupied Memphis.Marszalek, ''Sherman'', pp. 188–201.
</text>
<imageset>
<image id="ae38f664ea5d2c299b2dbd8fa0d13e34" name="Solider_at_Sherman_Memorial" sectnum="2.7#1">../img/ae38f664ea5d2c299b2dbd8fa0d13e34.jpg</image>
</imageset>
</document>